<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The Importance of Risk in                                                 SWP-307&#13;
Agricultural Planning Models&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 307&#13;
November 1978&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
Prepared by: P.B.R. Hazell&#13;
R.B. Norton&#13;
M. Parthasarathy&#13;
Development Research Center&#13;
and                                                                               KW-&lt;&#13;
Carlos Pomareda&#13;
Secretaria de Integraci6n&#13;
Ec6nomica de Centroamerica, Guatemala                             '&#13;
Copyright ©) 1978&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
PUB         1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
HG          Vashington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
3881.5                                                                                                  V&#13;
.W57&#13;
W67&#13;
no.307&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations&#13;
or to any individual acting on their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 307&#13;
November 1978&#13;
THE IMPORTANCE OF RISK IN AGRICULTURAL&#13;
PLANNING MODELS&#13;
Agricultural production, particularly in developing countries, is generally&#13;
a risky process, and considerable evidence exists to suggest that farmers&#13;
behave in risk averse ways. Yet risk considerations are rarely incorporated&#13;
into regional or sector planning models; rather farmers are assumed to behave&#13;
in a risk-neutral profit maximizing way. Explicit representations of uncertain&#13;
outcomes and farmers' attitudes toward them have appeared mostly in farm level&#13;
models. At the aggregate level, more indirect approaches have been used which&#13;
amount to specifying "conservative" reactions to changes in the light of&#13;
uncertainty, e.g. the flexibility constraints of recursive programming.&#13;
On theoretical grounds, neglect of risk averse behavior in agricultural&#13;
planning models can be expected to lead to important over-statements of the&#13;
output levels of risky enterprises (often reflected in overly specialized&#13;
cropping patterns), hence also to overestimates of the value of important&#13;
resources (e.g. land and irrigation water). This paper reports results from&#13;
two case studies in Mexico designed to measure the magnitudes of some of these&#13;
biases and, in the process, provides a quantification of risk aversion at&#13;
aggregate farm levels.&#13;
Prepared by:                                              Copyright  3 1978&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
P.B.R. Hazell                                             1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
R. D. Norton                                             Washington, D.C.   20433&#13;
Malathi Parthasarathy, Development Research Center        U. S. A.&#13;
and&#13;
Carlos Pomareda, Secretaria de Integraci6n&#13;
Economica de Centroamerica, Guatemala&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
1.  Introduction                                                          1&#13;
2.  Method of Incorporating Risk                                          2&#13;
3.  Description of the Models                                             7&#13;
A.  The ALPHA Model                                                   7&#13;
B.  The BETA Model                                                   10&#13;
C.  Estimation of Risk Parameters                                    17&#13;
Estimation of  Q Matrices                                      17&#13;
Estimation of  f                                               19&#13;
4.  The Model Results                                                    19&#13;
A.  Quantification of Risk Aversion at the                           19&#13;
Aggregate Level&#13;
B.  Effects on Supply Response Behavior                              26&#13;
C.  Effects on Resource Valuation                                    30&#13;
5.  Conclusions                                                          32&#13;
References                                                               33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THE IMPORTANCE OF RISK IN AGRICULTURAL PLANNING MODELS&#13;
1. Introduction&#13;
Agricultural production, particularly in developing countries,&#13;
is generally a risky process, and considerable evidence exists to suggest&#13;
that farmers behave in risk averse ways.-/ Yet risk considerations are&#13;
rarely incorporated into regional or sector planning models; rather&#13;
farmers are assumed to behave in a risk-neutral profit maximizing way.&#13;
Explicit representations of uncertain outcomes and farmers' attitudes&#13;
toward them have appeared mostly in farm level models.. At the aggregate&#13;
level, more indirect approaches have been used which amount to specifying&#13;
"conservative" reactions to changes in the light of uncertainty, e.g. the&#13;
flexibility constraints of recursive programming [Day, 1963].&#13;
On theoretical grounds, neglect of risk averse behavior in&#13;
agricultural planning models can be expected to lead to important over-&#13;
statements of the output levels of risky enterprises (often reflected in&#13;
overly specialized cropping patterns), hence also to overestimates of the&#13;
value of important resources (e.g. land and irrigation water). This paper&#13;
reports results from two case studies in Mexico designed to measure the&#13;
magnitudes of some of these biases and, in the process,attempts to provide a&#13;
quantification of risk aversion at aggregate farm levels.&#13;
The two models used in this paper are both regional linear&#13;
programming models of the production of annual crops grown under irrigated&#13;
lf   See, in particular, the following case studies:  Cancian [1972],&#13;
Dillion and Anderson [1971], Francisco and Anderson r19721, Lin, Dean and&#13;
Moore 11974], Officer and Halter [1968], and O'Mara [19711.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2.&#13;
conditions. They are static equilibrium models, and through incorpora-&#13;
tion of linear demand functions, simulate competitive market equilibria&#13;
in which both prices and quantities are endogenous. In this respect,&#13;
their structures are identical to CHAC [Duloy and Norton, 1973] but risk&#13;
averse behavior is also incorporated through the methodology described&#13;
in the 1974 article of Hazell and Scandizzo.&#13;
In section 2 we briefly review the risk specification of the&#13;
models, and show why ignoring risk averse behavior in programming models&#13;
can lead to biases in estimated crop outputs and the values of scarce&#13;
resources. In section 3 we present the two models in some detail, and&#13;
discuss the methods used to estimate key risk parameters. Section 4&#13;
contains the results from the two models, and demonstrates the numerical&#13;
importance of incorporating risk averse behavior into agricultural&#13;
planning models. Finally, section 5 contains our brief conclusions.&#13;
2.   Method of Incorporating Risk&#13;
The underlying behavioral assumption in our models is that farmers&#13;
maximize expected net income less its standard deviation -- an (E, a)&#13;
utility function -- rather than expected profits.  This assumption follows&#13;
a tradition begun by Markowitz [1959] and Tobin [1958] regarding choice&#13;
under uncertainty. More precisely, however, our assumption is a variation&#13;
on the approach of Baumol [1963] who used an (E, *a) formulation which&#13;
gives more reasonable answers than the straight (E, a) approach in some&#13;
cases. With Baumol's approach, the decision-maker is assumed to subjectively&#13;
establish a confidence limit and a floor on expected returns, to which the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3.&#13;
limit is applied. In this^paper, parametric programming techniques are&#13;
used to derive values of the subjective parameter    .&#13;
It is well known that a pure (E, a) function, taken over a&#13;
significant range of values, has some rather strange behavioral properties,&#13;
and even the assumption of normally distributed outcomes won't rescue it&#13;
from that fact. Nevertheless, it has been shown that over a limited range&#13;
of values such a function can be viewed as an approximation, via truncated&#13;
Taylor's series, to a polynomial function with all the desirable properties.&#13;
More precisely, the first two terms of a Taylor's series yield an (E, V)&#13;
utility function, and the (E, a) efficiency frontier is a tangency to it&#13;
at the equilibrium point.&#13;
Tsiang 11972, 1974] has provided a careful defense of the (E, a)&#13;
approach as a useful approximation in certain classes of choice situation,&#13;
and it has proven to be helpful in improving predictions of behavior under&#13;
risk at the farm level. Building on that, the purpose of this paper is to&#13;
show one way in which it may be utilized in an aggregate rather than a&#13;
micro model. One of Tsiang's conditions for (E, a) analysis to be useful&#13;
is that the risk be "small" relative to the total wealth of the risk taker.&#13;
while this conditions may be met for the commercial, irrigated farms&#13;
covered in our models, it should be noted that it may not be satisfied&#13;
for the case of rainfed, subsistance farmers confronted with new&#13;
technologies.&#13;
Given the underlying (E, fa) behavioral specification, the&#13;
objective function of an aggregate linear programming model which simulates&#13;
competitive market equilibria can be written as:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.&#13;
(1)       Max U        X'M (A - 0.5 BMX) - C'X - D(X' aX)&#13;
where     X   is a vector of aggregate crop levels;&#13;
M   is a diagonal matrix of average yields;&#13;
C   is a vector of cost coefficients;&#13;
A,B   are the coefficient matrices of the linear demand structure&#13;
EP=A-BMX; EP=expected price and B is assumed to be diagonal.-/&#13;
1   is an appropriate aggregate of individual farm f coefficients;&#13;
and       Q   is an appropriate aggregate of individual farm covariance&#13;
matrices of activity revenues.&#13;
The derivation and justification of this objective function is&#13;
provided by Hazell and Scandizzo [1974].  It is equivalent to the sum of expected&#13;
values of producers' and consumers' surplus over all markets, and it gives the&#13;
asymptotic values of expected -quantities and market clearing prices in&#13;
equilibrium.&#13;
The usual assumption of profit maximizing behavior is of course&#13;
equivalent to setting b equal to zero in (1) . Thus, the effect of&#13;
ignoring1risk averse behavior depends on the properties of the term&#13;
b(X' OX)2  ; at least within the confines of our behavioral assumptions.&#13;
Let the constraint set of the aggregate model be denoted by&#13;
D X &lt; -b&#13;
where D is a matrix of technical coefficients and b is a vector of&#13;
resource supplies.&#13;
2/   Diagonalization is obtained in the models by grouping commodities into&#13;
demand independent groups [Duloy and Norton, 1975].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5.&#13;
The Lagrangian of the model is then:&#13;
(2)       L       V X'M (A - 0.5 BMX) - C'X - D(X'QX)2 + v' (b - DX)&#13;
where  v  is a vector of dual values.&#13;
Now, from the necessary Kuhn-Tucker conditions,&#13;
1&#13;
aL    ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -n &#13;
(3)  ax      m                )-c- b  m  x - c  - b(X  X)  i     Xi  k dkj  &lt;0    (j  ton)&#13;
- b~ rn~ ~            i-i ~ X   k=l~&#13;
where lower case letters denote elements of the corresponding capital matrices,&#13;
n  denotes the number of crops, and  s  denotes the number of constraints.&#13;
Complementary slackness conditions further require that, for all&#13;
non-zero xj in the solution, (3) must hold as a strict equality. Thus&#13;
we can rewrite (3) for any non-zero x. as:&#13;
s~~~~&#13;
(4)      EP    '        c     +                   1  iV dkj2ij xi&#13;
where we have used the fact that since B is diagonal, then&#13;
Ep    -   a  - b  m  xi&#13;
In words, equation (4) states that for each non-zero activity,&#13;
the expected marginal cost per unit of output must be exactly equal to&#13;
expected price. The expected marginal cost comprises expected own marginal&#13;
cost  c4 , plus expected opportunity costs  I vk dkj  as reflected in the&#13;
dual value of the resources used by that activity, plus a marginal risk&#13;
1&#13;
factor  O(X'QX) 2   Xi:ij xi&#13;
Now, had we made the usual assumption of risk neutrality, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6.&#13;
marginal risk term in equation (4) would disappear (because b = 0).&#13;
Consequently, incorporating risk averse behavior leads to different output&#13;
levels in the model solution, and the direction of change from risk&#13;
n&#13;
neutrality depends critically upon the sign of   I  wiXi . Crops which&#13;
have large variances in revenues, and/or positively correlated revenues&#13;
with most other crops, will tend to have a positive marginal risk term,&#13;
and this will lead to a lower output under risk averse behavior. On the&#13;
other hand, crops which have negatively correlated revenues with most other&#13;
crops will tend to have a negative marginal risk term, and hence their&#13;
output will be increased under risk averse behavior.&#13;
In order to show the effect of risk averse behavior on the&#13;
valuation of scarce resources, we can rearrange equation (4) as:&#13;
1s&#13;
--n           s-l&#13;
(5)   v   L   mi E(P)c  - cs (X IQX)    I   X              vd i  vk   / dsj&#13;
where, by suitable rearrangement over k, v  can be the shadow price of any&#13;
S&#13;
selected resource,&#13;
Clearly, the imputed value of the  sth  resource for the  jth&#13;
non-zero activity will be greater or smaller than its value under risk&#13;
neutrality depending upon the sign of I w1x Xi . But the outcome also&#13;
depends on the valuations  vk , k i s   Equation  (5)  must of course&#13;
hold for all non-zero activities, and so we have a simultaneous model in&#13;
the  vk . The overall effect of risk averse behavior on the value of&#13;
Vs is not therefore apparent from (5) . It depends on the total risk&#13;
effect of the complete portfolio of farm crops.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7.&#13;
1&#13;
We do know, however, that since  1'(X'SQX)   &gt;  0  in the model&#13;
objective function (1) , then the value of the objective is smaller&#13;
under risk averse behavior than under risk neutrality. Euler's theorem&#13;
then implies that the total valuation of the scarce resources must be&#13;
smaller. However, this still permits the possibility of some resources&#13;
increasing in value, providing that others are reduced by sufficiently&#13;
large amounts. For those resources whose imputed value is reduced by the&#13;
inclusion of risk (and very likely that means most, if not all, resources),&#13;
how do we interpret the new valuation? To the extent that the model&#13;
structure faithfully reflects individual and market decision processes,&#13;
then it can be said that an adequate treatment of risk normally reduces&#13;
the price which farmers would be willing to pay for their production&#13;
inputs.&#13;
3. Description of the Models&#13;
The two models to be described here both deal with annual crop&#13;
production in selected irrigation districts in Mexico.&#13;
A,   The ALPHA Model&#13;
The first model (hereafter called the ALPHA model) is in actuality&#13;
part of CHAC and comprises eight of the more than one hundred&#13;
administrative districts of the Mexican Ministry of Water Resources.&#13;
These selected districts are not contiguous, but are scattered throughout&#13;
the arid agricultural areas of Mexico; they are among the largest districts.&#13;
The districts and their locations are as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8.&#13;
Area                          District&#13;
Pacific, N.W.          Culiacan, Comisi6n del Fuerte, Guasave,&#13;
Rfo Mayo, Santo Domingo&#13;
North Central          Ciudad Delicias, La Laguna&#13;
Northeast              Bajo RIo San Juan&#13;
Taken together, the  8  districts account for significant shares&#13;
of the national production of cotton, tomatoes, dry alfalfa, rice, soy-&#13;
beans and safflower (see Table 1). They also produce a wide range of&#13;
cereal,crops and vegetables, together with some sugar cane. Some double&#13;
cropping is practiced in all the districts, but particularly in the&#13;
vegetable growing areas. The average district cropping patterns for the&#13;
years 1967/68 to 1969/70 are given in Table 1 , but excluding a small&#13;
percentage of land devoted to crops which are not included in the models.&#13;
Crop production is almost entirely dependent on irrigation in all 8&#13;
districts, and any small areas of rainfed land have been excluded.&#13;
In total, the 8 district models cover 99,000 farms, of&#13;
average size 5.8 hectares - a district breakdown is included in Table&#13;
1 . For modelling purposes each district is treated as a single large&#13;
farm. The farms are presumed to be sufficiently homogeneous that this&#13;
procedure is unlikely to lead to any serious aggregation bias problems.&#13;
The model activities provide for the production, in each district, of crops&#13;
grown by that district in Table 1 , each with a choice of 3 mechanization&#13;
levels and 2 planting dates. A set of labor activities provides flexi-&#13;
bility in selecting seasonal combinations of family and hired day labor.&#13;
Family labor is charged a reservation wage of one-half of the hired day labor rate;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1: AVERAGE DISTRICT CROPPING PATTERNS, 1967/68 TO 1969/70, ALPHA MODEL&#13;
(Harvested Hectares)&#13;
2 of&#13;
Crops        El Fuerte   Culiacan    Rio Mayo   Guasave   Delicias   San Juan   St.  Domingo  Laguna   Aggregate  National&#13;
Production&#13;
Dry Alfalfa       1,988        _           2,144        _        6,510        -             285       5,498      16,425       34&#13;
Cotton           46,364         -         15,535        -        7,903       1,190       17,585      67,964    156,541       25&#13;
Greeu Alfalfa      -             543        _ -                   -           -            -          5,224       5,767        2&#13;
Rice             11,335       23,568        _          3,480      _           _            _           -         38,383       25&#13;
Sugar Cane       12,706       24,172        _-                     -                       -           -         36,878       12&#13;
Safflower         4,790       13,374      10,435       3,737      _           _           1,098        -         33,434       29&#13;
Barley             -            -            112        -         ---                                  -            112        1&#13;
Chillies            386        1,570        -             48      _                                    -          2,004        9&#13;
Beans            16,224       11,024        -            202      _-                                   -         27,450        3&#13;
Chickpeas           561          938        -            271      _-                                   -          1,770        1&#13;
Tomatoes          3,049        9,563        -            581      _                                    -         13,193       37&#13;
Sesame            3,010        2,815       8,390         144      _-                                   -         14,359       4&#13;
Maize            10,792        4,302       4,071       2,420    10,053      54,269         1,038     6,213       93,158        2&#13;
Canteloupe          231          387        -            722      -           -            -           -          1,340        4&#13;
Potatoes          1,320         _-                     -           -           -                       -          1,320        5&#13;
Cucumbers          -            -           -              8      -           -                        -              8        0&#13;
Watermelons          757         325        -             41      -             74          _          -          1,197        5&#13;
Sorghum          24,238       22,795      10,616       1,238     7,719      19,876         _          5,592      92,074      1.&#13;
Soybeans         16,264        4,392      11,886        -         -           -             -          -         32,542       20&#13;
Wheat            23,'61        3,057      29,969       5,742    29,668       1,048       11,738      16,150    120,933        16&#13;
TOTALS         177,576      122,825      93,158      18,634    61,853      76,457       31,744    106,641    688,888&#13;
Number of&#13;
Farms           16,484        6,224       9,185       2,984    10,710      4,480            647     48,341      99,055&#13;
Available Ha's&#13;
per Farm           10          12            8          6          4         16            47          2          5.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10.&#13;
a value derived from CHAC [Duloy and Norton 1973]. Purchasing&#13;
activities provide for the supplies of mules, machinery&#13;
and irrigation water. Seasonal constraints are imposed on land and labor,&#13;
2a/&#13;
and an annual constraint is imposed on water supplies7 Technical coefficients&#13;
and costs are taken at 1967/68 to 1969/70 average levels. The model&#13;
constraints are also based on this period. Average yields are based on&#13;
the 6-year period 1966/67 to 1971/72 , and risk parameters were&#13;
estimated from time series data spanning the period  1961/62  to  1970/71&#13;
The district models are linked in block diagonal form and&#13;
integrated into an aggregate market structure, similar to that in  CHAC&#13;
That is, the market comprises linear domestic demand functions of the&#13;
form EP = A - BMX, and has import and export possibilities at fixed prices.&#13;
For simplicity, to approximate cross-elasticity relationships in demand, the crops&#13;
are classified into demand independent groups, and linear substitution is&#13;
allowed between products within each group as rates fixed by base year&#13;
relative prices.2/ The definition and characteristics of these demand&#13;
groups are summarized in Table 2 . The demand curves for each group&#13;
have the same price elasticities as in CHAC, but are located at mean output&#13;
levels appropriate for the 8 district aggregates. Export and import constraints are&#13;
also taken from CHAC and pro-rated according to the ratio of output from the&#13;
8 districts to national output for each product.&#13;
B.   The BETA Model&#13;
The second model (hereafter called the BETA model) was developed&#13;
by Pomareda and Simmons [19771 and, for the purposes of this study, can be&#13;
2a/ We assume the input costs and the resource constraint values non-stochastic; this&#13;
assumption can be relaxed, using one of several available techniques to handle&#13;
stochastic constraints. See, for example, Charnes and Cooper [1959], Madansky&#13;
[1962], Maruyama [1972].&#13;
3/ For a more detailed description, see the papers by Duloy and Norton. Income&#13;
effects are ignored in this procedure, as this is a partial equilibrium model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
11.&#13;
Table 2:  CHARACTERISTICS OF DEMAND GROUPS, AIPHA MODEL&#13;
Base Period Price&#13;
Demand    Commodity         Commodity       Gro   Inde a/      Own Price&#13;
Group                               (Pesos/ton)                Elasticity&#13;
1      Sugar Cane             70                  70           -0.25&#13;
2      Tomatoes            1150                 1150           -0.4&#13;
3      Chillies             1500                1500           -0.2&#13;
4      Cotton Fibre         5770                5770           -0.5&#13;
5      Dry Alfalfa           400&#13;
Green Alfalfa        100&#13;
Barley               930&#13;
Chickpeas            990                 446           -0.3&#13;
Maize                860&#13;
Sorghum              630&#13;
6      Rice                1220&#13;
Beans               1830&#13;
Chickpeas            990                1285           -0.3&#13;
Potatoes             930&#13;
7      Maize                 860&#13;
}            817           -0.1&#13;
Wheat                800&#13;
8      Cantaloupe            680&#13;
}            741           -2.0&#13;
Watermelons          780&#13;
9      Safflower           1550&#13;
Sesame              2410                1164           -1.2&#13;
Cotton Oil           830&#13;
Soybeans            1600&#13;
10        Cucumbers             590                 590           -0.6&#13;
a/  Group price indices are computed using base year quantity weights.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12.&#13;
viewed as a model of the irrigation districts of Culiacan, Humaya, El Fuerte&#13;
and Guasave.in the state of Sinaloa. Taken together, these four districts&#13;
accounted, in 1973/74, for about 90% of the national exports of tomatoes,&#13;
green peppers and cucumbers, and about 40% of the national exports of melons.&#13;
For modelling purposes, Culiacan and Humaya are grouped as a&#13;
single region, as are El Fuerte and Guasave. This grouping permits&#13;
satisfactory consideration of water transfers between district irrigation&#13;
authorities. The two regions are then treated as single decision making&#13;
umits.&#13;
Although all short cycle crops in each region are included in&#13;
the model, special emphasis was given to the modelling of activities&#13;
representing vegetable production. Each vegetable is allowed several&#13;
planting dates; and the yields for each planting date are disaggregated&#13;
by months (the harvest period of a hectare of tomatoes planted in September&#13;
for example may last as long as three and a half months). Yields are also&#13;
disaggrogated into exportable and non-exportable quality according to U.S.&#13;
Department of Agriculture regulationa on the quality of imports. Non-exportable&#13;
qualities are channelled into domestic Mexican markets.&#13;
The principal resource constraints for each region are monthly&#13;
supplies of land and labor and the annual supply of water. Labor&#13;
requirements are specified by three categories: labor for cultivation,&#13;
harvesting and packing vegetables. Hiring activities provide for&#13;
unlimited supplies of labor for each category of work, but at different&#13;
wage rates. All input costs are at 1973/74 prices.&#13;
The market structure in the BETA model is rather more complicated&#13;
than that in the ALPHA model, though again prices are endogenized through&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13.&#13;
incorporation of linear demand schedules. The complexity arises because&#13;
Mexican vegetable exports (produced mainly in Sinaloa) have significant&#13;
price effects in the U.S. market, and because they compete directly with&#13;
Guatemalan exports. Consequently, in order to adequately model export&#13;
demands, the U.S. and Guatemalan vegetable markets are incorporated directly&#13;
into the model, along with the supply of melons produced competitively in&#13;
the Apatzingan district of Mexico.  A further source of complexity arises&#13;
because U.S. prices are treated endogenously on a monthly basis.&#13;
Mexican domestic demands are treated in CHAC style, with the&#13;
demand schedules and price elasticities given in Table 3 . Prices of&#13;
vegetables other than tomatoes (peppers, cucumbers and cantaloupes) are&#13;
fixed with perfectly elastic demands. The supply of melons from Apatzingan&#13;
is simply incorporated through four seasonal linear programming activities.&#13;
Vegetable supplies from Guatemala (peppers, cucumbers, canta-&#13;
loupes and honeydews) are incorporated through another linear programming&#13;
sub-matrix.  Domestic demands in Guatemala are assumed perfectly elastic&#13;
at fixed prices.&#13;
The U.S. market is incorporated by means of monthly linear supply&#13;
and demand functions (see Tables 4 and 5). It is assumed that supplies and&#13;
demands are both independent through time, and that U.S. prices in other&#13;
periods dre fixed (Mexican exports do not compete in these months).&#13;
The model maximand is a simple generalization of the CHAC type&#13;
objective function in that the producers' and consumers' surplus are summed&#13;
by product, by season and by country.-/  Risk is only introduced in the two&#13;
4/   For a mathematical description, see Pomareda and Simmons 11977].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14.&#13;
Table 3: DEMAND FUNCTIONS FOR TOMATOES AND TRADITIONAL CROPS&#13;
IN MEXICO, l/ BETA MODEL&#13;
Crops               Demand Equation 2/          Direct Price&#13;
Elasticity&#13;
Tomatoes        P = 2,993 - .00008372 Q              -0.5&#13;
Sesame          P = 3.068 - .00011210 Q              -1.2&#13;
Cotton          P = 3.276 - .00000537 Q              -0.5&#13;
Rice            P = 2.960 - .00001536 Q              -0.3&#13;
Safflower       P = 2.069 - .00000531 Q              -1.2&#13;
Beans           P = 5.573 - .00008800 Q              -0.3&#13;
Chickpeas       P = 3.448 - .00007409 Q              -0.3&#13;
Maize            P = 1.126 - .00001938 Q             -0.2&#13;
Sorghum         P = 1.185 - .00000208 Q              -0.3&#13;
Soybeans        P = 2.334 - .00000423 Q              -1.2&#13;
Wheat            P = 0.936 - .00000107 Q             -0.5&#13;
1/  Price elasticities were taken from CHAC. Mean prices and&#13;
quantities were taken from Secretarfa de Recursos Hidrau-&#13;
licos, Estadfstica Agrfcola del Ciclo 1972-73, Mexico,&#13;
D.F., July 1972.&#13;
2/ Quantity in thousand kilos.&#13;
Price in pesos per kilo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15.&#13;
Table 4:  U.S. SUPPLY FUNCTIONS FOR VEGETABLES,I BETA MODEL&#13;
Product                 Month                 Equation  2/&#13;
Tomatoes                    December           P = .0000770 Q&#13;
January           P = .0001052 Q&#13;
February          P = .0001864 Q&#13;
March              P = .0001705 Q&#13;
April              P - .0001278 Q&#13;
May                P = .0000541 Q&#13;
Peppers                     December           P - .0002715 Q&#13;
January           P - .0003822 Q&#13;
February          P = .0007818 Q&#13;
March              P = .0006631 Q&#13;
April             P = .0004780 Q&#13;
Cucumbers                   December           P = .0003792 Q&#13;
January           P = .0007304 Q&#13;
February          P - .0010917 Q&#13;
March              P - .0009442 q&#13;
April              P = .0002798 Q&#13;
Cantaloupes                 January            P = .240380  Q&#13;
February          P - .048850  Q&#13;
March              P = .024020  Q&#13;
April              P = .016450  Q&#13;
May                P = .000110  Q&#13;
1/ Assumed elasticity of supply of 1.00.&#13;
2/ Quantity in thousand kilos.&#13;
Price in pesos per kilo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16.&#13;
Table 5: U.S. DEMAND FUNCTIONS FOR VEGETABLES, BETA MODEL&#13;
Product                    Month                    Equation 1/&#13;
Tomatoes                  December            P - 7.241 - .000043755 Q&#13;
January             P- 6.116 - .000036722 Q&#13;
February            P   4.719 - .000020254 Q&#13;
March               P   7.098 - .000044305 Q&#13;
April               P- 5.398 - .000019006 Q&#13;
May                 P= 8.248 - .000039815 Q&#13;
Peppers                   December            P =10.935 - .00046591  Q&#13;
January             P  1'.041 - .00040690  Q&#13;
February            P= 9.075 - .00026592  Q&#13;
March               P -10.835 - .00035203  Q&#13;
April               P =12.203 - .00042629  Q&#13;
Cucumbers                 December            P   4.046 - .00016589  Q&#13;
January             P   3.905 - .00011539  Q&#13;
February            P = 3.968 - .00009907  Q&#13;
March               P= 4.852 - .00015937  Q&#13;
April               P   3.562 - .00008637  Q&#13;
Cantaloupes               January             P = 5.126 - .0004930   Q&#13;
February            P= 5.126 - .0004930   Q&#13;
March               P = 7.389 - .0001910   Q&#13;
April               P= 5.699 - .0000411   Q&#13;
May                 P = 6.125 - .0000205   Q&#13;
Honeydews                 January             P = 5.110 - .0013200   Q&#13;
February            P = 5.110 - .0013200   Q&#13;
March               P= 2.843 - .0002630   Q&#13;
April               P= 3.170 - .0002240   Q&#13;
1/ Quantity in thousand kilos.&#13;
Price in pesos per kilo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17.&#13;
regional models for Sinaloa, again using an (E, 4a) utility formulation.&#13;
C.   Estimation of Risk Parameters&#13;
In order to incorporate risk averse behavior into the models&#13;
in accordance with equation (1) , it is necessary to have estimates of&#13;
Q  and  n  for each irrigation district.  In principle  D and  2 should&#13;
be suitable weighted averages of the risk aversion parameters and revenue&#13;
covariance matrices of individual farms. Such information is not, of&#13;
course, available, and even if it were, suitable aggregation procedures&#13;
have not yet been developed. Consequently, in formulating the ALPHA and&#13;
BETA models, more approximate and aggregate procedures were used.&#13;
Estimation of 2 Matrices&#13;
The only available data on revenue variations were time series&#13;
data on prices and yields at the irrigation district level. Using these&#13;
data, (13 years in the case of the ALPHA model, but only 6 years for&#13;
the BETA model), covariance matrices of crop revenues were calculated&#13;
for each district modelled, after detrending the original crop revenues&#13;
by linear regressions.&#13;
There are two potential problems with these estimated Q matrices.&#13;
First, the approptiate Q matrices should be aggregates of the covariance&#13;
matrices subjectively perceived by farmers at market equilibrium, and these&#13;
may well differ from observed statistical relationships. The estimated&#13;
matrices are therefore good to the extent that farmers' perceived values&#13;
had converged to the observed statistical relationships, and that the time&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18.&#13;
series data covered an equilibrium period. The latter requirement may not&#13;
be too unrealistic, in that few crops showed statistically significant or&#13;
numerically important trends in their cropping areas during the time periods&#13;
under consideration.&#13;
Second, the i matrices should be direct aggregates of individual&#13;
farm covariance matrices, and should not incorporate any covariance&#13;
relationships that may exist between farms within a district. This is.&#13;
5,&#13;
because it is required that-/&#13;
1                         1&#13;
(x%PXh42         ~        kx~xk)2&#13;
h  Xh  h             keh  k (x Phk  k&#13;
where  h  denotes the  h h  irrigation district, and  k  denotes the  k th&#13;
farm.  The estimated  Q h  matrices are therefore good to the extent that&#13;
the  S   matrices are the same for all farms in the  h h  district, and&#13;
that the covariance between the revenues of any two crops i and j are&#13;
the same between farms as within farms. That is,&#13;
coy (rki   rk)         coy (r  ,  rj)   = co  (r i ' kj)&#13;
where  r  denotes activity revenue and  k , Q  are farms.-/ Unfortunately,&#13;
suitable cross-sectional samples of farm data could not be found to test&#13;
these requirements.&#13;
5/   See Hazell and Scandizzo [1974].&#13;
6/ Under these assumptions, and letting R. denote the average revenue of the&#13;
jth crop observed at the district over ail farms, and K the number of farms&#13;
in the district:&#13;
co(i (R R2  kE(r ki                      2 k   E(rk) E(r i)&#13;
Kki   ki           K k &#13;
2 E I cov (rk., rtj)&#13;
K   k Q&#13;
-1   I X cov (rk, rk&#13;
K2  k kk9k&#13;
1  ;&#13;
K  Lcov (r    r )&#13;
k       ki'  k ,&#13;
=coy (r ki, rkj)      ,all k&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
19.&#13;
Estimation of (&#13;
In the absence of any empirical data from which to estimate the (&#13;
coefficients, the basic procedure followed was to search, through post-optimality&#13;
techniques, values of p which enabled the models to best describe a set of base&#13;
year prices. In both models we make the simplifying assumption that ( is the&#13;
same for all irrigation districts. Various measures of "goodness of fit" were tried,&#13;
but a simple average of the absolute values of the deviations in prices served as&#13;
well as any (hereafter called the mad: mean absolute deviation).&#13;
This method of estimating ( poses the obvious difficulty that it will&#13;
pick up model misspecification and data errors, and that there is no way of knowing&#13;
how serious these errors might be other than by judging the "reasonableness" of&#13;
the estimated parameter.&#13;
4. The Model Results 7/&#13;
A. Quantification of Risk Aversion at the Aggregate Level&#13;
The model P coefficients are a direct representation of risk averse&#13;
behavior at the aggregate farm level. Thus, solving the models tor different values&#13;
of D provides direct information about the effects of different degrees of risk&#13;
aversion on equilibrium prices and quantities, as well as providing a basis for&#13;
quantifying the actual value of 0 .&#13;
Pertinent results from the ALPHA model are presented in Tables 6 and 7.&#13;
Table 6 shows the effect of different ¢ values on the domestic equilibrium prices&#13;
for the commodity groups delineated in Table 2. The prices of groups 2 (tomatoes),&#13;
3 (chillies) and 9 (vegetable oils) all increase with D , indicating corresponding&#13;
reductions in the quantities produced for the domestic market. On the other hand,&#13;
the prices for groups 5 (forage crops), 6 (food crops), 7 (cereals), 8 (melons) and&#13;
10 (cucumbers) decrease as 0 increases, indicating that production of these crops&#13;
for the domestic market increases as producers become more risk averse. The quantity&#13;
7/ The models are solved with a linear programming algorithm using the linearization&#13;
techniques of Duloy and Norton [1975] and Hazell [1971].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20.&#13;
Table 6. PRICE SOLUUTIONS BY COCMMODITY GROTJPSa/ FOR DIFFERENT VALUES&#13;
OF o , ALPHA MODEL&#13;
(Pesos/Ton)&#13;
Base&#13;
Demand Group             Values  of      p                        Period&#13;
0      0.5      1.0      1.5    2.0      2.5     Index&#13;
1            68        70      72       68     68      68        70&#13;
2           321       703     988    1200   1494    1772       1150&#13;
3          1031     1125    1124    1352   1330    1547        1500&#13;
4          5770      5770    5770    5770   5770    5770       5770&#13;
5           499       475     445     449    444      443       446&#13;
6          1373     1316    1241    1233   1227    1217        1285&#13;
7          1o44     1043      992     970    958      989       817&#13;
8          -446       416     420     468    476      416       741&#13;
9          1014      1004    1022    1058   1133    1200       1164&#13;
10          516       436     284     148    148      148       590&#13;
M.A.D.b/     219       175     153     123    146      172&#13;
a/ Prices are reported as group indices, using base year&#13;
quantity weights (these weights are justified by Duloy&#13;
and Norton, 1975)&#13;
b/ The M.A.D. is the mean absolute deviation of the solution&#13;
value from the base period values.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21.&#13;
Table 7. QUANTITIES PRODUCED FOR DOMESTIC MARKET FOR DIFFERENT D VALUES, ALPHA MODEL&#13;
(Tons)&#13;
Crop                                  Values of D                                   Base&#13;
0         0.5       1.0     1.5      2.0         2.5          Year&#13;
Quantities&#13;
Dry Alfalfa        137323    139120    140916   140916   140916   140916   179019&#13;
Cotton             484488    476111    445869   358485   285965   268476   243454&#13;
Green Alfalfa      173445    175714    177983   177983   177983   177983   226109&#13;
Rice               115369    115784    118774   118774   141885   143695   126197&#13;
Sugar Cane        2659859   2659859   2659859  2659859  2659859  2659859  2627020&#13;
Safflower           75777      74467      72752    67437    86449    70914    72490&#13;
Barley                510        517        523      523       523       523      665&#13;
Chillies            15409      15161     15161    14789    14789    14294    14459&#13;
Beans               30278      30278      31060    31060    26428    26765    33001&#13;
Chickpeas            1239       1264      1272      1272      1250     1251      1585&#13;
Tomatoes           223682    202712    185237   171257   153781   136241   174752&#13;
Sesame               9643       9475       9258     8581      8161     7662      9224&#13;
Maize              194989    200993    198093   163852   163851   163406   210801&#13;
Cantaloupe           9966      10589     10589      9967      9966    10589      6935&#13;
Potatoes            45065      45065      46228    46228    21734    22010    27139&#13;
Cucumbers              20         33         35      359      2195     2301        19&#13;
Watermelons         22213      23601      23601    22213    22213    23601    10850&#13;
Sorghum            336856    341263    345670   345669   345670   345669   285818&#13;
Soybeans            59815      58781     63359    75595    63982    68706    57220&#13;
Wheat              326064    320453    328585   369565   369566   367959   343979&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22.&#13;
effects are shown in detail in Table 7 at. the individual commodity level. The prices&#13;
of groups 1 (sugar) and 4 (cotton fibr'-.) show no response to the risk aversion&#13;
parameter.&#13;
These results confirm the ambiguities involved in predicting the effect of&#13;
risk averse behavior on the supplies of individual crops as discussed in section 2.&#13;
They also suggest a usetul definition of riskiness in crop production which takes&#13;
account of inter-crop relationships. High (low) risk crops can be defined as those&#13;
where production decreases (increases) as producers become more risk averse, whereas&#13;
risk neutral crops are those whose production is unaffected by 0 .&#13;
The last columns in Tables 6 and 7 contain the base year values (1967/68 to&#13;
1969/70 averages) of prices and quantities. By comparing the model solutions for&#13;
different 0 values with these base year values, we have a basis for selecting the&#13;
"best-fitting"' value of 0 .&#13;
Clearly the solution corresponding to risk neutrality (4 = 0) is quite&#13;
unsatisfactory. It predicts unrealistically high levels of production of cotton,&#13;
tomatoes, cantaloupes, potatoes, watermelons and sorghum, and particularly low prices&#13;
for groups 2, 3 and 8. There is a definite improvement in both the price and quantity&#13;
fits as 0 increases, but which deteriorates again as 0 approaches 2.5. In the&#13;
latter solution, the quantities produced of tomatoes, maize and potatoes become&#13;
unrealistically low, while those for rice, cucumbers, sorghum and wheat become too&#13;
large.&#13;
In selecting a value of 4 we have chosen to concentrate on the commodity&#13;
group prices because the market structure of the model can only be expected to work&#13;
best at the demand group level. The last row of Table 6 reports the simple mad's&#13;
(mean absolute deviations) of the price fits, and clearly demonstrates the superiority&#13;
of the solution for 0 = 1.5.&#13;
We conclude that introducing risk averse bahavior into the ALPHA model&#13;
significantly improves its predictive power compared to the more usual assumption&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
23.&#13;
of risk neutrality, (the price mad is reduced by 44% when D is increased from&#13;
O to 1.5), and that a reasonable measure of the risk parameter at the aggregate&#13;
farm level may be about 1.5.8/&#13;
Table 8 reports the comparable price solutions from the BETA&#13;
model. It is to be noted that the commodities were not grouped in this&#13;
model (demand independence is assumed), and that since some prices are&#13;
fixed exogenously to the model, these are not reported in Table  8&#13;
Table 9 shows the effect of different D values on the cropping&#13;
patterns in the state of Sinaloa. We reported production in tons for the&#13;
ALPHA model because there are important yield differences between districts&#13;
in that model, but this is not a problem with the BETA model. The&#13;
hectare figures incorporate production for both the export and domestic&#13;
markets, and which is also an essential feature given the importance of&#13;
vegetable exports in the BETA model.&#13;
The model shows considerable flexibility in its response to&#13;
different D values; a feature reflected in the wide range of hectarage&#13;
values for each crop. Tomatoes, peppers, cotton, safflower and soybeans&#13;
exhibit high risk behavior in that their production falls rapidly as risk&#13;
aversion increases, whereas wheat, sesame and maize are clearly low risk&#13;
crops.&#13;
CompaTison of the model solutions with base period values (1973/74&#13;
actuals in this case) again shows that introducing risk averse behavior&#13;
leads to significant improvements in the model's predictive powers as compared&#13;
to risk neutrality. In this case, the best price fit occurs when Q = 0.5&#13;
(the price mad is reduced by 52% as 1 is increased from 0 to 0.5 ).&#13;
8/ Assuming normal distributions, this 0 value corresponds to a 6.7% confidence&#13;
band, which is very close to the sort of risk levels accepted by&#13;
statisticians!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24.&#13;
Table 8. PRICE SOLUTIONS FOR DIFFERENT VALUES OF ~, BETA MODEL&#13;
(Pesos / Kilo)&#13;
Crop                        VALUES OF D                        Base&#13;
Year&#13;
0         0.5       1.0        1.5          Values&#13;
a!&#13;
VEGETABLESa&#13;
Tomatoes         3.493      3.879     4.034      4.226         3.850&#13;
Peppers          4.002      4.747    4.759       4.978         4.852&#13;
Cucumbers        2.824      2.888     2.900      2.676         2.764&#13;
OTHEp /&#13;
Cotton           2.414      2.524     2.560      2.619         2.470&#13;
Safflower        1.371      1.526     1.658      1.839         1.600&#13;
Soybenas         1.485      1.490     1.534      1.622         1.450&#13;
Chickpeas        1.427      1.447     1.449      1.451         2.100&#13;
Rice             1;082      0.987     o.871      o.884         1.075&#13;
Beans            2.001      1.993     1.979      2.026         1.980&#13;
Wheat            0.825      0.775     0.743      0.725         0.800&#13;
Sorghum          0.655      0.637     0.589      0.6i6         0.625&#13;
Sesame           3.055      2.842     2.340      2.286         2.778&#13;
Maize            0.955      0.873     0.745      0.654         o.844&#13;
Mad              0.210      0.101     0.164      0.215&#13;
a/ Export prices, i.e. average U.S.wholesale prices for winter season&#13;
b/ Domestic prices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25.&#13;
Table 9.  CROPPING AREA IN SINALOA FOR DIFFERENT VALUES OF §, BETA MODEL&#13;
(Hectares)&#13;
Crop                             Values of  D                        Base&#13;
0       0.5        1.0      1.5          Year Quantities&#13;
VEGETABLES&#13;
Staked Tomatoes      21713      15117    11996    8595             14200&#13;
Ground Tomatoes       4459        -         -       -               1400&#13;
Green Peppers        11984       3379      3379    2409             2909&#13;
Cucumbers             2107       1869      1697    2531             3643&#13;
OTHER&#13;
Cotton               64232      53409    51904   46210             48075&#13;
Safflower            98976      72983    52751   27187             81471&#13;
Soybeans            104685    103267   102005   89111             117827&#13;
Chickpeas            17115      16646    15396   15396             25844&#13;
Rice                 31308      33047    35576   34733             51505&#13;
Beans                32165      32165    32187   32180             35524&#13;
Wheat                28685      48776    54142   68697             49989&#13;
Sorghum              51376      55266    57005   55717             45798&#13;
Sesame                 218       2597     8558    9155              2584&#13;
Maize                 7087      14875    18769   18889             17740&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26.&#13;
B.   Effects on Supply Response Behavior&#13;
Our results have already shown that the introduction of risk&#13;
averse behavior into the models leads to different levels of production&#13;
for most crops as compared to assuming risk neutrality. These results&#13;
are of course estimates of single points on the product supply functions,&#13;
but they amply demonstrate the biases inherent in ignoring risk averse&#13;
behavior in aggregate linear programming models. We turn now to an explora-&#13;
tion of the broader effects of risk averse behavior on both the slope and&#13;
location of the domestic supply response functions for selected crops.&#13;
Given that most domestic prices are endogenous to our two models,&#13;
it is not possible to derive directly the effects of price changes on&#13;
domestic supplies. Rather, the location of the domestic demand curves&#13;
must be shifted, and the model allowed to determine the new equilibrium&#13;
values of both prices and the quantities supplied. Supply response&#13;
functions derived in this way also allow for price and quantity adjust-&#13;
ments in all other markets; they are not therefore the partial supply&#13;
functions described in economic textbooks, but rather must be considered&#13;
as total supply response relationships.&#13;
To simplify the presentation, we have selected two commodities&#13;
from each model -- commodity groups 2 (tomatoes) and 7 (cereals) from the&#13;
ALPHA model, and sorghum and safflower from the BETA model. In each&#13;
experiment, the demand curve for the relevant group or commodity was&#13;
rotated to the right at discrete intervals of 5% each on the quantity&#13;
axis, while holding all other demand curves at their initial positions.&#13;
The experiments were repeated for both risk neutrality and the best fitting&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27.&#13;
Figure 1 DOMESTIC SUPPLY RESPONSE FOR TOMATOES&#13;
Pesos/Ton                             ALPHA MODEL&#13;
1    2      3     45          6      7    8      9&#13;
'~~~~~~~~~~ 100 _                                             &#13;
500 _~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
V    ~~~* * . * *    *--&#13;
0                                                                                   1 .03 I  |  I.I  I  I  f03Tons&#13;
175          200           225          250           275           300          325&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27a.&#13;
Figure 2 DOMESTIC SUPPLY RESPONSE FOR CEREALS&#13;
ALPHA MODEL&#13;
1500&#13;
1           2                        4             5           6            7&#13;
1000              0&#13;
6       ~~~~7&#13;
i&gt;-1.5&#13;
500 0           4                                                                             Tons&#13;
460  4~~~~~   510         535           560 ~~~~~~585               610&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28.&#13;
Figure 3 DOMESTIC SUPPLY RESPONSE FOR SORGHUM&#13;
BETA MODEL&#13;
Pesos/Kilo.&#13;
0.680 -&#13;
5          6&#13;
4                             =0&#13;
0.660  _&#13;
2&#13;
6&#13;
5&#13;
3         4                          0.5&#13;
0.640&#13;
1,2&#13;
Thousand&#13;
0.620                                                                    I                I  Tons&#13;
220             240              260              280              300              320&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28a.&#13;
Figure 4 DOMESTIC SUPPLY RESPONSE FOR SAFFLOWER&#13;
BETA MODEL&#13;
Pesos/Kilo.&#13;
6&#13;
5           $ =0.5&#13;
1&#13;
2                                                          6   3      &#13;
1.5                                                                                    =0&#13;
5&#13;
1.4 &#13;
1.3                                    1&#13;
Thousand&#13;
1.2                  I                I                 I                I __                 Tons&#13;
100              110              120               130              140               150&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
29.&#13;
values of D . The supply response functions so derived are reported in&#13;
Figures 1 through 4 . The points on these functions depict model&#13;
solutions and these are numbered so that 1 represents the base period&#13;
solution, 2 represents the solution with a 5% quantity shift in the&#13;
relevant demand, 3 represents a 10% shift, etc. Thus points labelled&#13;
with the same numbers in each figure correspond to solutions with different&#13;
I values, but with identical demand structures.&#13;
The two models show markedly different supply response behavior.&#13;
The response relationships obtained from the ALPHA model (Figures 1 and&#13;
2 ) are all highly elastic; supplies to the domestic market increasing by&#13;
about the same percentage as the corresponding shifts in demand. Apparently,&#13;
relative equilibrium prices are such in this model that production of&#13;
tomatoes and cereals is constrained by the volume of domestic demand rather&#13;
than by their marginal profitability. The BETA model on the other hand&#13;
consistently yields more inelastic supply response functions. In this&#13;
case production increases less than proportionally with demand, causing&#13;
prices to increase above their initial equilibrium values. Clearly, there&#13;
is keener competition for resources from other crops in this model.&#13;
Generally, the risk parameter 0 does not have a pronounced or&#13;
consistent effect on the slope of the supply response functions, but it&#13;
does shift their location quite dramatically. Using our earlier definition&#13;
of high risk crops, then tomatoes in the ALPHA model and safflower in&#13;
the BETA model fall into that category, since their production in the&#13;
base solutions (points labelled 1) is smaller with the selected 0 values&#13;
than when  o = 0 . In these cases,  b  shifts the whole supply response&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30.&#13;
function up and to the left (Figures 1 and 4). In contrast, the supply&#13;
response function for a low risk crop (sorghum in the BETA model) is&#13;
shifted down and to the right when risk averse behavior is introduced&#13;
(Figure 3). Cereals (maize and wheat) in the ALPHA model is for all&#13;
practical purposes, a risk neutral group. In this case the location of the&#13;
entire supply response function is barely affected by introducing risk&#13;
averse behavior (Figure 2), though the introduction of risk does give&#13;
some slope to an otherwise perfectly elastic supply function.&#13;
C.   Effects on Resource Valuation&#13;
One of the claimed benefits of constructing aggregate linear pro-&#13;
gramming models is that they may provide shadow prices for scarce resources&#13;
which can be useful in guiding investment decisions. This feature is&#13;
particularly attractive in the Mexican context for valuing irrigation water.9/&#13;
However, few models used for the purpose have been specified with risk&#13;
averse behavior, so that it is pertinant to explore the biases inherent&#13;
in the approach when assuming risk neutral behavior.&#13;
Tables 10 and 11 contain the shadow prices of irrigation&#13;
water at district levels obtained from our models for different values of&#13;
* . These values are taken from annual water constraints, and measure&#13;
the marginal annual return from an additional unit of water when used in&#13;
an optimal seasonal pattern determined by the model.&#13;
Except for the El Fuerte-Guasave region in the BETA model,&#13;
the shadow prices of water consistently decline as  o  increases.  Thus,&#13;
9/  See for example, Bassoco, Norton and Silos [1974].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
31.&#13;
Table 10.  SHADOW PRICES FOR WATER WITH DIFFERENT VALUES OF D  , ALPHA MODEL&#13;
(Pesos/103 Cubic Metres)&#13;
District                        Values of   o&#13;
0       0.5     1.0      1.5       2.0       2.5&#13;
El Fuerte          313      -         -       -         -&#13;
Culiacan            -       -         -       -         -          -&#13;
Rio Mayo          1516    1248      1123   1033        851        845&#13;
Guasave            782     355        -      -         -           -&#13;
Delicias           719     714       523    346        182       115&#13;
San Juan           842     598       172     -         -           -&#13;
St. Domingo       2380    1934      1672   1285        943        656&#13;
La Laguna          816     620       487    478        418        352&#13;
Table 11.  SHADOW PRICES FOR WATER WITH DIFFERENT VALUES OF  X, BETA MODEL&#13;
(Pesos/103 Cubic Metres)&#13;
Region                                  Values of  0&#13;
0          0.5          1.0        1.5&#13;
Culiacan/Humaya                   732         404           -          -&#13;
El Fuerte/Guasave                 523         558          196         42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
. 32.&#13;
assuming risk neutrality in model specification will most likely lead&#13;
to an upward bias in the marginal valuation of irrigation water. However,&#13;
as we argued theoretically in section 2 , and as the El Fuerte-Guasave&#13;
ragion demonstrates, such consistent results need not hold. Assuming&#13;
risk neutrality in the BETA model would actually lead to an underestimation&#13;
of the value of water in the El Fuerte-Guasave region when compared to&#13;
assuming the "best-fitting" value of b . This result occurs because the&#13;
incorporation of risk happens to shift the optimal cropping pattern toward&#13;
the more water-intensive crops.&#13;
5.   Conclusions&#13;
This paper has demonstrated that: a) reasonable estimates of&#13;
risk aversion coefficients can be obtained at aggregate levels through&#13;
programming techniques; b) biases in estimates of stipply response and&#13;
resource valuation may be quite significant in planning models which&#13;
ignore risk averse behavior; and c) the descriptive preformance of&#13;
agricultural planning models can be considerably improved by introducing&#13;
risk averse behavioral assumption, even when based on the theoretically&#13;
problematic (E, a) utility function. The additional data&#13;
requirements for the incorporation of risk are time series observations&#13;
on prices and yields, by crop, for the relevant producing regions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
33.&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Bassoco, L. M., R.D. Norton, and J.S. Silos, "Appraisal of Irrigation Projects&#13;
and Related Policies and Investments," Water Resources Research, 10:&#13;
1071-1079, 1974.&#13;
Baumol, W. J., "An Expected Gain-Confidence Limit Criterion for Portfolio Selection,"&#13;
Management Science, 10: 174-182, 1963.&#13;
Cancian, F., Change and Uncertainty in a Peasant Economy, Stanford University&#13;
Press: Stanford, 1972.&#13;
Charnes, A., and W. W. Cooper, "Chance Constrained Programming," Management&#13;
Science, 6: 70-79, October 1959.&#13;
Day, R.H. Recursive Programming and Production Response, Amsterdam: North-Holland&#13;
Publishing Company, 1963.&#13;
Dillon, J.S. and J.R. Anderson, "Allocative Efficiency, Traditional Agriculture,&#13;
and Risk," American Journal of Agricultural Economics, 53: 26-32, 1971.&#13;
Duloy, J.H., and R.D. Norton, "CHAC: A Programming Model of Mexican Agriculture,"&#13;
ch. IV.1 in L.M. Goreux and A.S. Manne, editors, Multi-Level Plalning:&#13;
Case Studies in Mexico, North-Holland Publishing Company: Amsterdam,&#13;
1973.&#13;
Duloy, J.H. and R.D. Norton, "Prices and Incomes in Linear Programming Models,"&#13;
American Journal of Agricultural Economics, 57: 591-600, 1975.&#13;
Francisco, E.M. and J.R. Anderson, "Choice and Chance West of the Darling,"&#13;
Australian Journal of Agricultural Economics, 16: 82-93, 1972.&#13;
Hazell, P.B.R., "A Linear Alternative to Quadrat:ic and Semi-Variance Programming&#13;
for Farm Planning under Uncertainty," American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, 53: 53-62, 1971.&#13;
Hazell, P.B.R. and P.L. Scandizzo, "Competitive Demand Structures under Risk&#13;
in Agricultural Linear Programming Models," American Journal&#13;
Economics, 56: 235-244, 1974.&#13;
Linn, W., G.W. Dean, and C.V. Moore, "An Empirical Test of Utility vs. Profit&#13;
Maximization in Agricultural Production," American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, 56: 497-508, 1974.&#13;
Madansky, A., "Methods of Solution of Linear Programming under Uncertainty,"&#13;
Operations Research, 10:  463-471, 1962.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
34.&#13;
Markowitz, Harry M., Portfolio Selection, (Cowles Foundation monograph No. 16),&#13;
Wiley: New York, 1959.&#13;
Maruyama, Yoshihiro, "A Truncated Maximum Approach to Farm Planning under&#13;
Uncertainty with Discrete Probability Distributions," American Journal&#13;
of Agricultural Economics, 54: 192-200, May, 1972.&#13;
Officer, R.R. and A.N. Halter, "Utility Analysis in a Practical Setting," American&#13;
Journal of Agricultural Economics, 50: 257-277, 1968.&#13;
O'Mara, G.T., A Decision-Theoretic View of the Microeconomics of Technique Diffusion&#13;
in a Developing Country, Ph.D. Thesis, Stanford University, August 1971.&#13;
Pomareda, C. and R.L. Simmons, "A Programming Model with Risk to Evaluate&#13;
Mexican Rural Wage Policies," Operational Research Quarterly, 28:&#13;
997-1011, 1977.&#13;
Tobin, J., "Liquidity Preference as Behavior Towards Risk," Review of&#13;
Economic Studies, 25: 65-85, 1958.&#13;
Tsiang, S.C., "The Rationale of the Mean-Standard Deviation Analysis, Skewness&#13;
Preference and the DemanI for Money,"  American Economic Review, 62:&#13;
354-371, 1972.&#13;
Tsiang, S.C., "The Rationale of the Mean-Standard Deviation Analysis: Reply&#13;
and Errata for Original Article," American Economic Review, 64:&#13;
442-450, 1974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                       TITLE OF PAPER                              AUTHOR&#13;
279      India - Occasional Papers                            M. Ahluwalia, J. Wall&#13;
S. Reutlinger, M. Wolf&#13;
R. Cassen (consultant)&#13;
280      Educational Effects of Class Size                    W.D. Haddad&#13;
281      Relieving Traffic Congestion:  The Singapore          P.L. Watson&#13;
Area License Scheme                                  E.P. Holland&#13;
282      World Trade and the International Economy:            B. Balassa&#13;
Trends, Prospects and Policies&#13;
283      Urban Land Policy Issues and Opportunities            H. Dunkerley, A. Walters,&#13;
J. Courtney.&#13;
W. Doebele, D. Shoup,&#13;
M.D. Rivkin (consultants)&#13;
284      Pakistan:  Forestry Sector Survey                     S.A. Draper, A.J. Ewing.&#13;
J. Burley, G. Grayum&#13;
(consultants)&#13;
285      The Leisure Cost of Electric Power Failures           M. Munasinghe&#13;
286      Shadow Pricing and Power Tariff Policy                M. Munasinghe, J. Warford&#13;
287      Wages Capital Rental Values and Relative              S. Guisinger (consultant)&#13;
Factor Prices in Pakistan&#13;
288      Educational Reform in the Soviet Union:               I. Blumenthal,&#13;
Implications for Developing Countries                C. Benson (consultants)&#13;
289      Petroleum and Gas in Non-OPEC Developing              R. Vedavalli&#13;
Countries: 1976-1985&#13;
290      Major Reforms of the Swedish Education System         A. Heidenheimer&#13;
(consultant)&#13;
291      Industrialization, Technology and Employment -        T.G. Rawski (consultant)&#13;
China&#13;
292      Development and Income Distribution - Zambia          C. Blitzer&#13;
293      World Potash Survey                                   W. Sheldrick, H. Stier&#13;
294      The Economic Dimensions of Malnutrition in            M. Selowsky&#13;
Young Children&#13;
295      The Technology of Rural Development                   J.P. McInerney&#13;
(consultant)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
No.                       TITLE OF PAPER                              AUTHOR&#13;
296      The Financial Cost of Agricultural Credit:            C.D. Datey (consultant)&#13;
A Case Study of Indian Experience&#13;
297      Agricultural Sector Planning Models:                  A.C. Egbert&#13;
A Selected Summary and Critique&#13;
298      Textbooks and Achievement:  What We Know              S.P. Heyneman.&#13;
J.P. Farrell,&#13;
A. Sepulveda-Stuardo&#13;
(consultants)&#13;
299      An Economic and Social Analysis of the Chao Phya   C. Bruce&#13;
Chao Phya Irrigation Improvement Project II          Y. Kimaro&#13;
300      Two Studies of Development in Sub-Saharan             S. Acharya&#13;
Africa                                               B. Johnston (consultant)&#13;
301      The Intermediate Sector, Unemployment, and            W.F. Steel&#13;
The Employment-Output Conflict:  A Multi-Sector    Y. Takagi (consultant)&#13;
Model&#13;
302      The Economic Theory of the Household and Impact    D. Chernichovsky&#13;
Measurement of Nutrition and Related Health&#13;
Programs&#13;
303      Trade Restrictions and International Price            M. Bale&#13;
Instability,                                         E. Lutz&#13;
304      Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations in                 R. Bird (consultant)&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
305      A Programming Approach to Fertilizer Sector           A. Chqksi&#13;
Planning                                             A. Meeraus&#13;
306      The Foreign Exchange Gap, Growth and Industrial    K. Dervis&#13;
Strategy in Turkey:  1973-1983                       S. Robinson&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PUB HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.307&#13;
Hazell, P. B. R.&#13;
The importance of risk in&#13;
agricultural planning models&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="437477">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1978/11/437477/importance-risk-agricultural-planning-models
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1978/11/437477/importance-risk-agricultural-planning-models</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1978/11/437477/importance-risk-agricultural-planning-models</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/06/27/000178830_98101903401758/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/06/27/000178830_98101903401758/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2000-06-27T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1978-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The importance of risk in agricultural
            planning models
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Agricultural production, particularly in
            developing countries, is generally a risky process, and
            considerable evidence exists to suggest that farmers behave
            in risk averse ways. Yet risk considerations are rarely
            incorporated into regional or sector planning models; rather
            farmers are assumed to behave in a risk-neutral profit
            maximizing way. Explicit representations of uncertain
            outcomes and farmers' attitudes toward them have
            appeared mostly in farm level models. At the aggregate
            level, more indirect approaches have been used which amount
            to specifying "conservative" reactions to changes
            in the light of uncertainty, e.g. the flexibility
            constraints of recursive programming. On theoretical
            grounds, neglect of risk averse behavior in agricultural
            planning models can be expected to lead to important
            over-statements of the output levels of risky enterprises
            (often reflected in overly specialized cropping patterns),
            hence also to overestimates of the value of important
            resources (e.g. land and irrigation water). This paper
            reports results from two case studies in Mexico designed to
            measure the magnitudes of some of these biases and, in the
            process, provides a quantification of risk aversion at
            aggregate farm levels.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The importance of risk in agricultural
            planning models
        </docna>
        <display_title>The importance of risk in
            agricultural planning models</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1978/11/437477/importance-risk-agricultural-planning-models</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Agricultural Research,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Markets and Market Access,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Agriculture</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Hazell, Peter</author>
            <author>Norton, R.</author>
            <author>Parthasarathy, M.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903401758</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Agriculture</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 307</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Agriculture</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural production; Crop yields;
            General equilibrium models; Risk; Risk aversion
            agricultural planning,Agricultural
            production,Agriculture,alfalfa,annual crops,average
            yields,Barley,base
            year,beans,cereal,cereals,Chickpeas,commodities,Commodity,consumers,crop,crop
            production,cropping,cropping
            patterns,crops,Cucumbers,cultivation,decision making,demand
            curve,demand curves,demand functions,Development
            Research,domestic market,domestic markets,double
            cropping,elasticity,elasticity of
            supply,equilibrium,equilibrium prices,expected
            returns,expected values,exports,farm,farm
            crops,farmers,farms,fixed prices,food crops,forage
            crops,harvesting,imports,income,Income
            effects,irrigation,Maize,marginal cost,market clearing
            prices,market equilibrium,market structure,melons,national
            output,Oil,opportunity costs,peppers,planting,planting
            dates,Potatoes,price changes,price elasticities,Price
            Elasticity,price indices,produce,producers,production
            increases,production inputs,production of
            cotton,Purchasing,rice,risk averse,risk aversion,risk
            neutral,Sesame,Sorghum,Soybeans,static
            equilibrium,substitution,sugar,sugar cane,SUPPLY
            FUNCTIONS,surplus,time series,tomatoes,utility
            function,Valuation,vegetable oils,vegetables,wage
            rates,Water Resources,wealth,Wheat
        </keywd>
        <owner>Development Economics and Chief Economist</owner>
        <repnb>SWP307</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textbooks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization and Subnational Regional Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Equalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Federalism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inter-Governmental Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning Materials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Social Impact Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Supply and Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inter-governmental Fiscal Relations</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>