<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. T-7028-BII&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA&#13;
SECOND EMERGENCY EDUCATION RECONSTRUCTION PROJECT&#13;
June 6, 1997&#13;
Human Resources Sector Operations Division&#13;
Central and Southern Europe Departments&#13;
Europe and Central Asia Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
(as of June 5, 1997)&#13;
Currency Unit: Bosnia and Herzegovina Dinars (BHD)&#13;
US$1.00 =        BHD170.00&#13;
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES&#13;
Metric System&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
BH               Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
CY               Calendar Year&#13;
DC               Direct Contracting&#13;
Federation       Federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
EC               European Community&#13;
ECHO             European Community Humanitarian Organization&#13;
EU               European Union&#13;
FY               Fiscal Year of the World Bank&#13;
GPN              General Procurement Notice&#13;
IBD              International Book Development&#13;
ICB              International Competitive Bidding&#13;
IDA-ITF          Development Association-Interim Trust Fund&#13;
IMG              International Management Group&#13;
IS               International Shopping&#13;
LIB              Limited International Bidding&#13;
MOE              Ministry of Education, Science, Culture, and Sports&#13;
NCB              National Competitive Bidding&#13;
NS               National Shopping&#13;
PIU              Project Implementation Unit&#13;
RS               Republika Srpska (Serbian Republic)&#13;
SFOR             NATO Peace Stabilization Force&#13;
SNCB             Simplified National Competitive Bidding&#13;
SOE              Statement of Expenditures&#13;
TFBH             Trust Fund for Reconstruction of Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
UNDP             United Nations Development Program&#13;
UNICEF           United Nations Children's Fund&#13;
USAID            United States Agency for International Development&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January I - December 31&#13;
Vice President:  Johannes Linn (ECAVP)&#13;
Country Director:  Christine Wallich (EC2DR)&#13;
Division Chief:  Ralph W. Harbison (ECI/2HR)&#13;
Responsible Staff:  Jim Stevens, Task Manager (EC1/2HR)&#13;
Ilona Szemzo, Social Sectors Operations Officer (EC2BA)&#13;
Zorica Lesic, Project Officer (EC2BA)&#13;
Michael Mertaugh, Principal Education Officer (ECIi2HR)&#13;
Edith Santos, Sr. Staff Assistant (ECI/2HR)&#13;
Peer Reviewes:  Bo Matsen, Education Specialist (EU ECHO, Sarajevo)&#13;
Sarah Forster, Economist (EC2BA)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA&#13;
SECOND EMERGENCY EDUCATION RECONSTRUCTION PROJECT&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
A. RECONSTRUCTION PROGRESS TO DATE ............................................................. 1&#13;
Primary  School Reconstruction  Program   Update ........................................................ 1&#13;
Books and  Educational Materials Support .............................................................                                            1&#13;
Support for Project Implementation  and  Capacity  Building  ..................                                      .......................... 2&#13;
B. BANK RESPONSE AND RECOVERY STRATEGY FOR EDUCATION ........................... 2&#13;
Emergency  Reconstruction  Program   for 1997  ............................................................ 2&#13;
Project Sustainability   ............................................................. 4&#13;
IBRD/IDA  Assistance  Strategy   ....................                                  ......................................... 5&#13;
C. DETAILED PROJECT DESCRIPTION .............................................................                                                                 6&#13;
School Rehabilitation  and  Furnishing   .........................................                                    .................... 7&#13;
Books and  Educational Materials  .......................                                   ...................................... 7&#13;
Education Finance and Administration .............................................................. 8&#13;
Project Implementation  ............................................................. 8&#13;
Project Costs and  Financing  Plan   .........................                                 .................................... 9&#13;
Environmental Aspects  .............................................................  10&#13;
D. INSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTS AND IMPLEMENTATION ..........                                                                             .................... 10&#13;
Project Implementation  .............................................................  10&#13;
Procurement .............................................................                                                                      11&#13;
Disbursements   .............................................................  13&#13;
Project Audits, Accounting  and Reporting   .............................................................  14&#13;
Supervision  Plan  .............................................................  15&#13;
Agreements to be Reached  .............................................................  15&#13;
E. BENEFITS AND RISKS ............................................................. 16&#13;
TABLES&#13;
Table  1:  Primary  School Reconstruction  Program   in the Federation  .............                                         ................... 3&#13;
Table 2:  Project Cost and  Financing  by  Expenditure Category   .................                                       ..................... 9&#13;
Table  3:  Project Cost by  Component by  Year  ......................................................    9&#13;
Table 4:  Procurement Arrangements  ......................                                        ................................  13&#13;
Table  5:  Disbursement Categories and  Schedule  ......................................................  14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page No.&#13;
APPENDICES&#13;
Appendix 1: Estimated Cost and Disbursement Schedule ............................................. 17&#13;
Appendix 2: Project Implementation Schedule ....................................................   20&#13;
Appendix 3: Summary of Objectives and Key Performance Indicators ............................. 23&#13;
Appendix 4: Project Procurement Plan .....................        ............................... 24&#13;
MAP IBRD No. 28377&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA&#13;
SECOND EMERGENCY EDUCATION RECONSTRUCTION PROJECT&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
A. Reconstruction Progress to Date&#13;
Primary School Reconstruction Program Update&#13;
1.           In December, 1995, The Federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina established a priority&#13;
reconstruction program, which called for repair or reconstruction of damaged facilities at all levels of&#13;
the education system. The total costs of this program were estimated at US$180 million. This original&#13;
program did not include school reconstruction needs for the Republika Srpska (RS) because there was,&#13;
at that time, no agreed primary school reconstruction program for the RS. The priority program has&#13;
since been expanded to include priority reconstruction needs in the Republika Srpska. The total costs&#13;
of this expanded priority program are estimated at US$275 million. This priority program includes 91&#13;
primary schools which the Federation Government aimed to reconstruct as the first phase of&#13;
reconstruction, prior to the start of the 1996-97 school year. Actual primary school reconstruction&#13;
under the priority program has fallen short of that goal, due principally to the lack of donor financing.&#13;
Financing has already been provided for 52 of the 91 primary schools in the Federation's priority&#13;
program. A total of US$10 million has been provided by the World Bank under the first Emergency&#13;
Education Reconstruction Project 1 for reconstruction of 28 primary schools throughout the Federation.&#13;
Reconstruction of these schools is nearly complete. An additional US$10.5 million has been committed&#13;
to reconstruct 24 primary schools and provide school furniture and equipment by the Governments of&#13;
Holland, Greece, and Malaysia, USAID, EU/ECHO and various NGOs. A financing gap of&#13;
approximately US$13 million remains to reconstruct the remaining 39 primary schools in this priority&#13;
program.&#13;
Books and Educational Materials Support&#13;
2.           The Government's priority program also includes provision of textbooks and&#13;
supplementary readers to primary and secondary schools in the Bosniac-majority areas of the&#13;
Federation 2 The program calls for the provision to schools in these areas of 72 textbook titles and 40&#13;
supplementary reader titles, and various other educational materials. This goal has been only partially&#13;
achieved due to a lack of external financing. To date, approximately US$1.5 million in World Bank&#13;
financing and US$0.2 million in Dutch Trust Fund financing has been committed to publishing and&#13;
printing 20 textbooks and various educational materials which are in the process of being delivered to&#13;
Bosnian classrooms. The Soros Foundation has agreed to finance US$0.8 million in supplementary&#13;
readers and five English language training books, and several other donors have expressed interest in&#13;
providing support for training books in other foreign languages. This leaves unfunded approximately&#13;
40 textbook titles, 30 supplementary reader titles, and various other educational materials under the&#13;
Federation's priority program. In addition to funds devoted to the emergency delivery of educational&#13;
I Memorandum and Recommendation of the President, dated April 22, 1996; Report No. P-6856-BIH&#13;
2 Needs for textbooks and supplementary readers in the Republika Srpska and in the Croat-majority areas of the&#13;
Federation are currently being met by the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia and Croatia, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2 -&#13;
materials into Bosnian classrooms, Dutch Trust Funds have been used to provide technical assistance to&#13;
help the Federation MOE begin to redefine its strategy for textbook production and financing. The&#13;
MOE is in the process of formulating new procurement techniques which will shift the responsibility&#13;
for publishing textbooks to the private sector.&#13;
Support for Project Implementation and Capacity Building&#13;
3.           Althougth financing of the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project is&#13;
incomplete, implementation of the financed portions of the Project has been highly satisfactory. With&#13;
support from various sources -- including the International Management Group (IMG), the Project&#13;
Implementation Unit (PIU) of the Emergency Recovery Project, a consultant project management and&#13;
procurement advisor, and Bank staff from the Bosnia Resident Mission -- the Education PIU has&#13;
committed over 90 percent of project funds within three months of the effectiveness date of grant&#13;
financing.3 Approximately 70 percent of World Bank funding was disbursed by the end of CY 1996.&#13;
Government-managed trust funds provided by the Government of the Netherlands have been used to&#13;
finance textbook pre-printing costs, PIU operating costs and works supervision, as well as limited&#13;
office equipment and vehicles. Additional office equipment and vehicles have been procured for the&#13;
PIU and local pedagogical institutes using World Bank Grant and IDA, Credit financing. PIU staff have&#13;
developed project management skills to prepare and implement future investment projects financed by&#13;
the Bank and other donors. UNDP will contract both PIUs shortly, to implement the reconstruction of&#13;
10 schools (seven in the Federation and three in RS), for US$2.0 million being provided by the&#13;
Government of Japan.&#13;
4.           In addition to building capacity for project management, World Bank-managed trust&#13;
funds are being used to promote further analysis and policy reform in several important sub-sectors. In&#13;
the field of teacher training, the Bank is supporting a joint initiative with UNICEF/USAID, the United&#13;
States Information Agency and the Soros Foundation to expose local experts to teacher training&#13;
innovations outside BH and to develop proposals for reform of the teacher training system. The Bank&#13;
and the EU's European Training Foundation are jointly financing a review of the secondary technical&#13;
and vocational education system. This initiative will help develop needed reforms as BH makes the&#13;
transition from emergency reconstruction assistance to long term development of the education system.&#13;
Trust Funds provided by the Government of the Netherlands are also being used to review the textbook&#13;
production and financing system, and to finance study tours designed to expose local experts to&#13;
innovations in the textbook field in other transition economies throughout Eastern and Central Europe.&#13;
B. Bank Response and Recovery Strategy for Education&#13;
Emergency Reconstruction Program for 1997&#13;
5.           The Federation has recently completed preparation of a US$35.0 million primary&#13;
school reconstruction program for 1997 which focuses education reconstruction efforts on about 100&#13;
severely damaged primary schools; the list includes both central school buildings, as well as smaller&#13;
nuclear/satellite schools which report administratively to the central schools. The 1997 also program&#13;
includes the unfinanced portion of the 1996 program (39 schools and about US$13 million) and&#13;
3 The US$500,000 in financing allocated under the IDA credit for pilot projects in RS has already been&#13;
committed. PIU activities were initiated in late 1996. Three pilot schools are presently being reconstructed. All&#13;
funds have been committed as of May 1997.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
represents about 30 percent of overall primary school reconstruction needs. The Republika Srpska's&#13;
1997 primary school reconstruction program of US$17.0 million represents about 30 percent of overall&#13;
primary school reconstruction needs in RS, and includes about 40 primary schools. Criteria for school&#13;
selection under both the Federation and RS components has broadened from the initial focus on lightly&#13;
damaged schools which could be repaired quickly, to include some more severely damaged schools&#13;
which will require more intensive reconstruction. As shown in Table 1, below, the 1997 priority&#13;
primary school reconstruction list for the Federation includes the 39 lightly damaged schools from the&#13;
1996 priority program which were not financed in 1996, plus 140 additional schools which either&#13;
suffered serious war or war-related damage (such as damage due to housing refugees), or are located in&#13;
UNHCR priority areas for return of refugees. Both the Federation and RS programs have been&#13;
prepared in consultation with cantonal (Federation) and regional/municipal authorities.&#13;
Table 1: PRIMARY SCHOOL RECONSTRUCTION PROGRAM IN THE FEDERATION&#13;
(Number of Primary Schools)&#13;
1996 Program      1997 Program&#13;
World Bank financed                  28                 18&#13;
Financed by Other Donors             24                30&#13;
Unfinanced                           39                131&#13;
Total                    91                179&#13;
6.           In addition to the primary school reconstruction programs, both the Federation and the&#13;
RS have prepared priority secondary and higher education reconstruction programs for 1997. Needs&#13;
estimates in 1997 for these levels are about US$40 million for the Federation and about US$20 million&#13;
for the RS, each estimated to represent about 50 percent of highest priority reconstruction needs in&#13;
those subsectors. While emergency financing is needed for secondary and higher education, donors&#13;
have been cautioned in various fora, including the Education Task Force and the Brussels donor&#13;
conferences, that significant investment at these levels should be linked to needed reforms to improve&#13;
the responsiveness of secondary and higher education to the needs of an emerging market economy.&#13;
This is particularly necessary in the case of specialized secondary technical and vocational schools,&#13;
which need significant changes to respond to employment needs in new sectors and new markets.&#13;
7.           Concurrent with emergency physical infrastructure rehabilitation programs, efforts are&#13;
ongoing at all levels to upgrade education management and governance and improve the quality of&#13;
education delivered in Bosnian schools. Education governance in Bosnia-Herzegovina remains in a&#13;
state of flux as the roles and responsibilities of the various levels of government -- Entities, cantons (in&#13;
the Federation) and regions/municipalities (in RS) -- continue to evolve. Preparation and&#13;
implementation of the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project has helped to facilitate&#13;
contacts between the Federation MOE and the cantons/municipalities, but there is an urgent need to&#13;
clarify the roles of various levels of government in providing education, as well as the appropriate&#13;
sources of financing for education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
8.            The Federal and RS MOEs are committed to increasing their capacity to coordinate&#13;
investments in the sector and to focus donor support, where feasible, on priority programs in primary&#13;
education. The preparation of the 1997 reconstruction programs, described above, reflect that&#13;
commitment. The broad goals of the reconstruction program in both the Federation and RS remain the&#13;
same as under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project: to make fully functional those&#13;
classrooms which were damaged by the war, to restore effective teaching capacity by providing&#13;
minimal supplies of textbooks, supplementary readers, and educational materials, and to support the&#13;
resumption of minimal salaries for teachers. At the same time, both the Federation and RS MOEs are&#13;
continuing their efforts to build institutional capacity to manage and coordinate the reconstruction effort&#13;
and to deal with longer-term policy issues.&#13;
9.            Although the emphasis in the Federation and RS continues to be on emergency&#13;
reconstruction needs, government authorities in the Federation are beginning to address a number of&#13;
key long term policy issues.4 Technical assistance, study tours and training are being provided through&#13;
Bank-managed Dutch Trust Fund financing in the following areas: (1) a review of secondary technical&#13;
and vocational education and adult training was recently completed by the European Training&#13;
Foundation and presented to the Government and donors in April 1997, and should provide the&#13;
background for policy dialogue on secondary VET issues during 1997; (2) a multi-donor supported&#13;
Teacher Training Reform Initiative, implemented by the University of Pittsburgh, has successfully&#13;
brought together authorities from all Federation cantons to begin to address structure and content&#13;
reforms in pre-service and in-service teacher training, and will be presented to the Government and the&#13;
donors at the end of June 1997; and (c) pilot textbook production and cost recovery programs have&#13;
been developed by International Book Development (IBD), implementation of which will be financed&#13;
under this proposed project. In addition, key sector policy issues are being pursued under various&#13;
actions carried out under the Education Sector Reconstruction Task Force, which comprises the&#13;
Government and the main donor agencies active in the education sector (including the EU, ECHO,&#13;
UNDP, USAID, UNHCR, UNICEF, UNESCO, IMG and the Soros Foundation, and the Bank). It is&#13;
expected that future investments in the education sector will focus on rebuilding and refocusing&#13;
secondary school facilities in the context of a broader secondary education reform, as well as&#13;
reorienting teacher training and reforming textbook financing and production.&#13;
Project Sustainability&#13;
10.          The key question of sustainability for the investments which the Project will support is&#13;
whether the responsible authorities will have the resources necessary to operate the project schools&#13;
effectively in the future. This means, in particular, whether they will be able to attract and retain&#13;
qualified teachers, and whether they will have the budgets necessary to pay for utilities, replenishment&#13;
of educational materials, and school maintenance. In the course of appraising this Project, data were&#13;
collected from all of the Federation cantons and from the Republika Srpska concerning the availability&#13;
of teachers and local capacities to pay teachers and to provide for other recurrent needs. These data&#13;
reveal that, in general, schools are adequately supplied with teachers; three-quarters of the teachers&#13;
currently in place are fully qualified under prevailing teacher training requirements. Although teachers&#13;
4Until after the September elections, the RS MOE had been reluctant to cooperate with the World Bank and&#13;
other education donors on emergency reconstruction needs and implementation arrangements, as well as long term&#13;
education development issues.; But cooperation has improved recently, resulting in preparation of the 1997 school&#13;
reconstruction program and the development of implementation arrangements for World Bank financing. RS&#13;
MOE authorities have participated in several recent long-term development initiatives ongoing in the Federation,&#13;
and it is hopeful that this cooperation and communication will improve throughout 1997.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-  -&#13;
were generally not paid during the war and throughout the 1995/1996 school year, the situation has&#13;
improved significantly during the current school year. Throughout the Federation, primary-school&#13;
teachers are being paid by the cantons an average of DM 250 per month; secondary school teachers are&#13;
being paid an average of DM 300 per month. A few cantons are already paying for utilities and other&#13;
recurrent costs; others plan to do so. In the Republika Srpska, teachers are also being paid, but they&#13;
receive, on average, only a third as much as teachers in the Federation.&#13;
11.          Contrary to expectations, these recent figures confirm that teachers are being paid&#13;
throughout the country at this early stage in the recovery process. This is encouraging evidence that&#13;
local revenue bases are beginning to recover, and that local budget authorities consistently give a high&#13;
priority to the most urgent recurrent financing needs of schools. For the medium term, however, there&#13;
is a clear need to develop secure financing for utilities and other recurrent costs of schools which are&#13;
not now being met. In the current rapidly evolving budget situation, an important question is whether&#13;
local revenues will be adequate to finance these needs and continue to provide adequately for teachers'&#13;
salaries. Several activities are planned in the coming year to help ensure that there are adequate&#13;
resources for education and other key public services in the future. The Public Expenditure Review&#13;
which the Bank carried out with counterparts in both Entities in early May 1997 examines revenues and&#13;
expenditures of central and cantonal governments, and recommend measures for increasing tax yields&#13;
and improving the efficiency of the budgetary process. Implementation of these measures would be&#13;
supported under a planned investment operation and a planned policy-based operation later in 1997. In&#13;
addition, the proposed Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project would address the needs&#13;
for financial sustainability of education by supporting several actions to strengthen education finance&#13;
and administration: a) carrying out of a study of options for education finance and administration,&#13;
looking at the experiences of other decentralized education systems in relation to the decentralization&#13;
experience under the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, b) dissemination of findings of the study&#13;
through preparation of a report and presentation of a national seminar, and c) supporting consensus-&#13;
building for the recommended measures through local seminars, study visits, etc. Conduct of the study&#13;
under agreed terms of reference and an agreed time schedule, and implementation of the&#13;
recommendations of the study would be conditions of the proposed Second Emergency Education&#13;
Reconstruction Project. Continued implementation of the recommendations of the Education Finance&#13;
and Administration Study would also be supported through conditionality in a planned policy-based&#13;
project in support of public expenditure reform.&#13;
12.          Other education policy issues are being addressed by ongoing initiatives of the&#13;
Education Reconstruction Task Force, with Bank participation. Bank-executed trust fund financing&#13;
provided by the Government of the Netherlands is being used to support policy development in the&#13;
areas of secondary technical and vocational education, teacher training, and textbooks, with the aim of&#13;
improving educational quality and making the delivery of education more efficient and cost-effective.&#13;
It is expected that investments to implement these policies will be supported under subsequent Bank-&#13;
financed operations, as well as by other donors.&#13;
IBRD/IDA Assistance Strategy&#13;
13.          Experience gained from the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project has&#13;
confirmed the importance of working closely with central education authorities to prepare a&#13;
consolidated investment program for each of Bosnia's two Entities. This approach has served to build&#13;
institutional capacity for central authorities to assume a coordination role, and has facilitated regular&#13;
communications between the central level and cantons and municipalities. It has also served to begin&#13;
the process of re-orienting aid flows for education away from uncoordinated activities driven by donor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
preferences toward adoption of a priority reconstruction program established by the Government and&#13;
endorsed by the donor community. This process has had the additional positive impact of helping to&#13;
bring together the two partners of the Federation to participate in investment programming and&#13;
implementation. It is expected that this proposed second project will have a similar influence in&#13;
facilitating cooperation between the Federation and the RS.&#13;
14.          In light of the limited IDA-ITF resources allocated to the education sector in Bosnia&#13;
(US$11.0 million) and the under-funding of the school reconstruction program, the Bank has decided,&#13;
in consultation with the Government and key education donors, to proceed immediately with the&#13;
Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project (FY97), aimed largely at filling the financing gap&#13;
for the first project, and supporting school reconstruction in the Republika Srpska. The commitment of&#13;
Bank funding to the 1997 program (which includes the financing gap from the first project) is expected&#13;
to have a catalytic influence in encouraging other donors to commit to the Government's priority&#13;
education reconstruction program, first for the remaining US$6.0 million needed to rehabilitate schools&#13;
on the Federation's original list, and then to address the additional requirements of the next group of&#13;
140 severely damaged primary schools. Concurrently, the Bank will begin preparation of a third&#13;
education project which would, in addition to continuing support for reconstruction, address longer-&#13;
term sectoral issues such as improved financing and administration, and structural changes to improve&#13;
the relevance of secondary education. IDA-ITF funding under the Second Emergency Education&#13;
Reconstruction Project was expected to be made available by the beginning of the construction season&#13;
in March 1997. However, macro-economic conditionality has delayecl Board presentation until June&#13;
1997, and a good portion of the construction season has been lost. Therefore, the Project will have to&#13;
complete construction activities to be initiated during this construction season, during Spring/Summer&#13;
1998. Funding for the third project will depend on the availability of IDA-ITF funding in 1997/98.&#13;
Significant cofinancing is needed for both projects, as well as for the first Emergency Education&#13;
Reconstruction Project.&#13;
C. Detailed Project Description&#13;
15.          The objective of the proposed Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project is&#13;
to improve primary education access and quality by reconstructing primary schools throughout Bosnia&#13;
and Herzegovina, including schools which are ready for tendering but for which financing was not&#13;
available under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project, and damaged schools in the&#13;
Republika Srpska. This financing will help achieve the first project's objective of helping to restore the&#13;
delivery of primary education of acceptable quality to the children of BH. The proposed project would&#13;
support the reconstruction of 18 primary schools from the unfinanced portion of the Federation's 1996&#13;
priority program; other donors are expected to finance the other schools on the 1997 priority list. It&#13;
would also finance the reconstruction of about 7 heavily damaged primary schools in the Republika&#13;
Srpska. The financing provided under the Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project would&#13;
meet only about 13 percent of estimated total school reconstruction needs at all levels in the Federation&#13;
and in RS during 1997. Project resources have been allocated throughout the Federation and RS on the&#13;
basis of population. Within cantons and municipalities, project resources are allocated on the basis of&#13;
local priorities for education reconstruction.&#13;
16.          A detailed cost table for the proposed project is provided in Appendix 1.&#13;
Implementation and institutional responsibilities are described in Section D. The Project would&#13;
provide: (a) financing for reconstruction of about 25 primary schools in the Federation and RS&#13;
(estimated cost, US$8.1 million); (b) the provision of furniture for classrooms in these schools&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
(estimated cost, US$1.0 million); (c) the provision of textbooks and other educational materials for&#13;
Federation schools (estimated cost, US$0.8 million); (d) technical assistance in Education Finance and&#13;
Administration (US$0.5 million); and (e) incremental costs of project management (US$0.4 million).&#13;
The proposed project would meet about US$7 million of the US$13 million financing gap for the&#13;
reconstruction of Federation schools under the First Emergency Education Reconstruction Project,&#13;
leaving a financing gap of about US$6 million to be met from foreign sources.&#13;
School Rehabilitation and Furnishing&#13;
17.          Construction will be carried out by local construction contractors to be selected on a&#13;
competitive basis. Architectural designs and specifications are being developed through IMG, using&#13;
UNDP financing. Estimated reconstruction costs under the proposed project reflect recent experience&#13;
under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project, in which reconstruction costs have been&#13;
about US$400 per square meter on average. According to a study conducted by the Bank's Resident&#13;
Mission in Sarajevo, these costs are lower than the average costs of school reconstruction financed by&#13;
NGOs during the project period in BH. The cost of school furniture, financed under the first project&#13;
by the EU, was about US$4,000 per classroom, based on a classroom size to accommodate 32 students.&#13;
18.          War-damaged schools to be reconstructed under the proposed project in the Federation&#13;
were selected and agreed with the Bank during preparation of the first Emergency Education&#13;
Reconstruction Project, based on the criteria of: a) light-to-medium war-related damage which could be&#13;
repaired quickly, and b) the absence of other facilities which could accomodate the school-age children&#13;
in the catchment area. (A list of the specific schools selected for rehabilitation and reconstruction&#13;
under the project is available upon request.) Schools have been selected for this second project using&#13;
criteria which have been modified to include more severely damaged schools, as well as schools in&#13;
UNHCR priority areas for the return of refugees and displaced people. As the agency responsible for&#13;
overseeing the school reconstruction process at the Federation level, the MOE took the lead in defining&#13;
criteria for selecting schools and reaching agreement on the criteria with the Bank, as well as for&#13;
working with canton-level education ministries and other education authorities (in those areas where&#13;
canton-level ministries of education were not yet formed) to apply the criteria to the needs of the&#13;
various municipalities. Selection of primary schools for reconstruction in the RS has been carried out&#13;
by the RS MOE, in cooperation with RS regions/municipalities and the Urban Institute of Banja Luka,&#13;
using the same selection criteria and procedures as agreed with the Federation.&#13;
Books and Educational Materials&#13;
19.          This component (estimated cost US$0.8 million) will help fill the financing gap (about&#13;
US$5.0 million) under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project for printing of textbooks,&#13;
as well as a small pilot for textbook production and financing. Financing is limited to the Bosniac-&#13;
majority portions of the Federation, as the RS is obtaining adequate supplies of textbooks from the&#13;
Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, and the Croat-majority portions of the Federation from Croatia. Out&#13;
of the originally agreed 72 titles for printing under the first project, 20 textbook titles were printed&#13;
using IDA project funds (as well as some educational materials) and another five language training&#13;
textbooks were printed by the Soros Foundation. The proposed second project will finance&#13;
approximately 20 more of the previously agreed textbook titles. This material is expected to be&#13;
delivered to schools by the beginning of the 1997-98 school year. Titles selected for production and&#13;
delivery were agreed during preparation of the first project; they are principally in science, math, and&#13;
literature. The average unit cost for textbooks procured under the first project was less than US$3,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
which was slightly below appraisal estimates. Funding for supplementary readers and educational&#13;
materials agreed under the first project has, for the most part, not been forthcoming by donors.&#13;
20.          The Federation MOE has agreed to procure textbooks to be financed under the second&#13;
project through pilot schemes aimed at competitive selection of published manuscripts. Pilots will also&#13;
be conducted to test limited cost recovery through rental of textbooks to students, and to promote&#13;
competitition in preparation of educational manuscripts. These pilots are currently being developed&#13;
with the support of International Book Development (IBD) under Dutch Trust Fund financing. IBD&#13;
will be providing hands-on training to Federation MOE staff as well as representatives of cantons and&#13;
municipalities and private sector publishers in the Federation. The pilots will represent a first step&#13;
towards an overall textbook reform which emphasizes private-sector textbook production and cost&#13;
recovery under a standard-setting and quality assurance role provided by government authorities.&#13;
Education Finance and Administration&#13;
21.           The March, 1994 Washington Agreement which estalblished the Federation of Bosnia&#13;
and Herzegovina, and the November, 1995 Dayton Accord which established the State of Bosnia and&#13;
Herzegovina stipulate that education in the Federation is the responsibility of the ten cantons&#13;
comprising the Federation. But these documents explicitly provide for the delegation of particular&#13;
educational responsibilities upwards to the Federation or downwards to individual municipalities, upon&#13;
agreement by the cantons. There has been little systematic discussion of the need for delegating other&#13;
particular functions to the Federation or to municipalities. This need could arise for several reasons,&#13;
including the need to ensure the quality and consistency of education programs, to capture economies&#13;
of scale, to ensure the consistency of education quality by region, and to promote nationbuilding.&#13;
Although the Republika Srpska has a unitary government and does not face the same questions as the&#13;
Federation concerning the role of regional governments, there is, nonetheless, a need to clarify the role&#13;
of the RS Ministry of Education in establishing education policy and ensuring the necessary financing&#13;
for education programs.&#13;
22.           This component will address the need to clarify the roles of the various levels of&#13;
government -- Entities, the Federation cantons, and RS regions/municipalities -- in providing and&#13;
financing education. It will do so by supporting local and foreign consultant services (estimated cost,&#13;
US$0.5 million) to: (a) carry out a study of options for education finance and administration, looking at&#13;
the experiences of other decentralized education systems in relation to the decentralization experience&#13;
under the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia; (b) disseminate study findings through preparation&#13;
of a report and presentation of a national seminar; and (c) support corsensus-building for the&#13;
recommended measures through local seminars, study visits, etc. Carrying out of the study and&#13;
subsequently implementing its recommendations is to be a condition of project implementation&#13;
(paragraph 47).&#13;
Project Implementation&#13;
23.           This component would finance incremental project recurrent costs (estimated US$0.4&#13;
million) to support the PIU of the Federation MOE, as well as the PIU of the RS MOE. The Project&#13;
would continue to finance salaries and limited operating costs, such as office supplies and gasoline, that&#13;
were initiated under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project. A small amount has been&#13;
set aside for technical assistance, where necessary, and for office equipment to support the RS PIU.&#13;
The role of each PIU is described in Section D below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9 -&#13;
Project Costs and Financing Plan&#13;
24.          Project Costs. The total cost of the second Emergency Education Reconstruction&#13;
Project is US$11.0 million. No price or physical contingencies have been included, given the expected&#13;
short disbursement period and modular nature of this emergency project. The Project is expected to&#13;
disburse over a 24 month implementation period. Project costs are presented in Appendix 1.&#13;
25.          Financing Plan. The proposed project would be financed through a proposed IDA-&#13;
ITF Credit of US$11.0 million. Although there is no formal cofinancing, the Project would finance a&#13;
slice of the overall 1997 education reconstruction program for BH for which donor financing is being&#13;
sought, including for the remaining gap of about US$6.0 million under the original Emergency&#13;
Education Reconstruction Project. Contracts for this work are ready for tendering.&#13;
Table 2: COST AND FINANCING PLAN BY EXPENDITURE CATEGORY&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
IDA-            Total&#13;
ITF&#13;
Amount   %       Amount   %&#13;
1. Civil Works                      8,100.0  100.0   8,100.0   73.6&#13;
Federation                      4,700.0&#13;
RS                              3,400.0&#13;
2. Furniture and Equipment          1,000.0  100.0   1,000.0   9.1&#13;
Federation                        650.0&#13;
RS                                350.0&#13;
3. Books and Educational Materials   800.0  100.0    800.0   7.3&#13;
(Fed. Only)&#13;
4. Technical Assistance and Training  700.0  100.0    700.0    6.4&#13;
Federation                        500.0&#13;
RS                                200.0&#13;
5. Recurrent Costs                   400.0  100.0    400.0    3.6&#13;
Federation                        268.0        _&#13;
RS                                132.0&#13;
Total                                11,000.0  100.0  11,000.0  100.0&#13;
Table 3: COST BY COMPONENT BY YEAR&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
1997     1998       Total&#13;
1. School Reconstruction            6,400.0   2,900.0    9,300.0&#13;
2. Books and Educational Materials    600.0    200.0       800.0&#13;
3.Education Finance and Administration  500.0      -       500.0&#13;
4. Project Implementation             240.0    160.0       400.0&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                   7,740.0   3,260.0    11,000.0&#13;
26.          Taxes. IDA/ITF funds will be used to procure specified project inputs, net of taxes.&#13;
There are no taxes on civil works, and the Government has waived import taxes and duties on goods&#13;
through December 1997. The Government is expected to extend this exemption through the&#13;
implementation period for the Project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10-&#13;
Environmental Aspects&#13;
27.           Because the Project is not expected to have any adverse environmental impact, the&#13;
Project has been assigned to Environmental Category C. Hazardous materials such as asbestos will not&#13;
be used in school construction or rehabilitation under the Project.&#13;
D. Institutional Arrangements and Implemrentation&#13;
Project lImplementation&#13;
28.          Implementation arrangements will be the same as those used for the successful&#13;
implementation of the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project.5 A Project Implementation&#13;
Unit (PIU) located in the Federation MOE is responsible for managing the on-going program in the&#13;
Federation. The PIU has successfully managed US$9.2 million in civil works and educational materials&#13;
contracting under the first project, and will continue to manage the supplementary funding for activities&#13;
in the Federation provided under this project, including maintaining appropriate records as the basis for&#13;
periodic project audits. The PIU will continue to be supported by the professional project management&#13;
and procurement advisor who provided implementation support under the first project. Technical staff&#13;
of the PIU will continue to be responsible for overseeing and coordinating the reconstruction programs&#13;
with canton and municipality level officials. They will also continue to work closely with other&#13;
agencies providing implementation assistance.&#13;
29.           A PIU is established under similar organization and procedures in the Republika Srpska&#13;
MOE to manage implementation of those funds allocated to the primary school reconstruction effort in&#13;
RS. The project management and procurement advisor will also support this unit. Every effort will be&#13;
made to share experiences and documentation between the two Entities. A detailed implementation&#13;
schedule for all components is provided in Appendix 2.&#13;
30.           Primary School Reconstruction Component. The primary school reconstruction&#13;
component will be managed by the Federation PIU's reconstruction unit, which has managed US$8.0&#13;
million in civil works contracting under the first project. A similar unit is being established under the&#13;
RS PIU. The Federation PIU's reconstruction unit is made up of three architect/engineers. It has&#13;
already verified school rehabilitation priorities for project funding with the cantons and managed the&#13;
preparation of architectural assessments, designs and cost estimates with the support of the&#13;
International Management Group, under UNDP funding. Once supplementary funding is approved&#13;
under the Project for the priority schools already selected, this unit will a) formulate bid packages and&#13;
prepare bidding documents (largely completed); b) evaluate bids, recomnmend bid awards, and negotiate&#13;
contracts, and c) manage the supervision of civil works. As with the first project, the unit will continue&#13;
to receive support for managing works supervision from civil engineers provided by the NATO Peace&#13;
Stabilization Force (SFOR). The actual supervision will be carried out by local contractors selected&#13;
competitively by the PIU and paid for under the credit. The reconstruction unit will also take&#13;
responsibility for furniture procurement including defining specifications and coordinating procurement&#13;
and delivery of furniture in cooperation with canton-level educational authorities. The RS PIU will be&#13;
5 The implementation mechanisms actually used to implement the first Emergency Education Reconstruction&#13;
Project have evolved slightly from those described in the Technical Annex for that project. The direct role of&#13;
IMG has been reduced, and the PIU has received support from the PCU of the Economic Recovery Credit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
similarly staffed and undertake the same responsibilities. It will have access to a punctual project&#13;
impiementation technical assistance, funded under the Project, as needed.&#13;
31.          Textbooks. Implementation of this component is to be managed by the Federation&#13;
PIU's educational materials unit, which successfully managed about US$1.5 million in textbook and&#13;
educational materials procurement under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project.&#13;
MOE's Chief Editor will act as the principal counterpart to consultants supporting the design and&#13;
implementation of textbook production and financing pilots based on competitive selection of private&#13;
sector publishers and limited cost recovery over the short term. Working with consultants provided by&#13;
IBD in London (financed by the Government of the Netherlands), the Editor will be responsible for&#13;
assuring content, quality and acceptability of textbooks and educational materials proposed by private&#13;
sector publishers. The Editor will organize the competitive selection of published books and supplies,&#13;
as well as their delivery to canton-level warehouses.&#13;
Procurement&#13;
32.          Procurement arrangements are summarized in the table below and a procurement plan&#13;
is attached in Appendix 3. Project procurement is to be made mainly through National Competitive&#13;
Bidding (NCB), Simplified National Competitive Bidding (SNCB), and National Shopping (NS).&#13;
33.          Advertising. A General Procurement Notice (GPN) was published in Development&#13;
Business in June 1996 for the first project; it will be repeated for the proposed project. The notice will&#13;
include information about the nature of the goods, works and services to be procured under the primary&#13;
school reconstruction program and invite interested and eligible suppliers, contractors and consultants&#13;
to send their expression of interest to the Federation and RS PIUs. The GPN will also be re-published&#13;
in the local press and distributed to embassies. The GPN will be followed by specific advertisements,&#13;
in the local press and distributed to embassies, for individual contracts where necessary. Bidding&#13;
documents will be sent to suppliers who respond to the GPN and the specific advertisements.&#13;
34.          Goods. Local suppliers of school furniture, books and educational materials proved&#13;
responsive and competitive under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project, which relied&#13;
heavily on National Shopping. Goods procurement under this proposed project will rely more heavily&#13;
on National Competitive Bidding procedures, as follows:&#13;
a.    National Competitive Bidding (NCB). NCB procedures, requiring local&#13;
advertisement, will be used for school furniture, equipment, books and materials estimated to cost&#13;
between US$100,000 and US$1.0 million per contract, in accordance with Bank guidelines, up to an&#13;
aggregate limit of US$300,000 for the Federation and US$200,000 for the RS.&#13;
b.    National Shopping (NS). NS will be used for contracts for goods available in Bosnia&#13;
Herzegovina up to an estimated cost of US$100,000 per contract, with at least three quotations, and up&#13;
to an aggregate limit of US$300,000 for the Federation and US$200,000 for the RS&#13;
c.    Direct Contracting (DC). DC will be used for proprietary items, for reasons of&#13;
compatibility and standardization, and in any other justified case. Any direct contracting to be financed&#13;
by the IDA credit will need prior Bank approval.&#13;
35.          Recurrent Costs/Incremental Operating Costs. Recurrent Costs and Incremental&#13;
Operating Costs are currently being financed under a Dutch Trust Fund and under the first Emergency&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Education Reconstruction Project. A small amount of funds -- US$400,000 -- has been set aside under&#13;
the proposed project to finance these activities at rates of remuneration established by the&#13;
Reconstruction Board as recurrent cost financing is exhausted from these other sources.&#13;
36.          Works. Given the nature of civil works under the Project, mainly rehabilitation of&#13;
existing facilities, Simplified National Competitive Bidding (SNCB) will be used for contracts&#13;
estimated to cost up to US$0.2 million per contract up to an aggregate limit of US$2.4 million for the&#13;
Federation and US$1.8 million for the RS. These works will be procured under lump-sum, fixed-price&#13;
contracts awarded on the basis of quotations obtained from at least three qualified contractors in&#13;
response to a written invitation. The invitation shall include a detailed description of works, including&#13;
basic specifications, the required completion period, a basic form of agreement acceptable to IDA, and&#13;
relevant drawings, where applicable. The award shall be made to the contractor who offers the lowest&#13;
price quotation for the required work, and who has the experience and resources to successfully&#13;
complete the contract within the specified time period. Any school construction contracts estimated to&#13;
cost more than US$0.2 million but less than US$2.0 million up to an aggregate limit of US$2.3 million&#13;
for the Federation and US$1.6 million for the RS would be awarded on the basis of advertised&#13;
National Competitive Bidding. The contracting industry was well established throughout BH prior to&#13;
the war. The experience under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project demonstrates that&#13;
much of this capacity still exists. Thus, the civil works for school rehabilitation and reconstruction&#13;
under the Project will be carried out in the customary manner -- through contracts with commercial&#13;
construction enterprises.&#13;
37.          Services. Services under the Project -- mainly for the supervision of works -- will be&#13;
procured through a request for proposals from a short list of qualified firms/individuals. Qualified&#13;
firms will be invited to submit proposals for comprehensive packages of consultant services and&#13;
management of fellowships and training in accordance with the "Guidelines for the Use of Consultants&#13;
by World Bank Borrowers and by The World Bank as Executing Agency" (August 1981). To keep the&#13;
evaluation process manageable, no more than six (but at least three) proposals will be invited following&#13;
a short listing acceptable to the Bank.&#13;
38.          Procurement Implementation Capacity. Procurement performance has been&#13;
satisfactory under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project. The need for hands-on&#13;
assistance provided by the World Bank Resident Mission in Sarajevo, SFOR, and the project&#13;
management and procurement advisor is expected to decline during, implementation of the proposed&#13;
second project. However, this assistance, with the exception of the ERP support, will continue to be&#13;
available to the Federation PIU, as well as to the PIU in the Republika Srpska, which is likely to need&#13;
more hands-on support initially.&#13;
39.          Prior and Post Bank Review of Procurement Documents. Prior review will be&#13;
required for the first three contracts awarded through National Shopping (NS), Simplified National&#13;
Competitive Bidding (SNCB), or National Competitive Bidding (NCB) for both the Federation and for&#13;
RS. Prior review will also continue to be required for all contracts procured through Direct&#13;
Contracting (DC).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Table 4: PROCUREMENT ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
(US$ Million)&#13;
Procurement methods (US$m) a/&#13;
Category of Expenditures    NCB bi    SNCB b/         NS          Other           Total&#13;
Civil works                  3.9         4.2                                       8.1&#13;
(3.9)       (4.2)                                    (8.1)&#13;
Furniture &amp; Equipment        0.5                     0.5 c/                        1.0&#13;
(0.5)                  (0.5) c/                      (1.0)&#13;
Textbooks                    0.8                                                   0.8&#13;
(0.8)                                                (0.8)&#13;
Technical Assistance                                                0.7            0.7&#13;
(0.7)          (0.7)&#13;
Recurrent Costs                                                     0.4            0.4&#13;
(0.4)          (0.4)&#13;
Total Financing              5.2          4.2         0.5           1.1            11.0&#13;
(5.2)       (4.2)       (0.5)         (1. 1)        (1 1.0)&#13;
NCB   - National Competitive Bidding&#13;
SBCB  - Simplified National Competitive Bidding&#13;
NS     - National Shopping&#13;
a/     Figures in parentheses represent IDA-ITF financing.&#13;
b/     All civil works will be procured using national competitive bidding and simplified national competitive&#13;
bidding procedures&#13;
c/     All school furniture and equipment will be procured using NCB and NS.&#13;
Disbursements&#13;
40.           Disbursement categories and projected disbursements under the Credit are shown in&#13;
Table 5, below. The Project is expected to be disbursed over a period of 24 months from the date of&#13;
effectiveness, scheduled for July 1997. The closing date will be October 30, 1999.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Table 5: DISBURSEMENT CATEGORIES AND SCHEDULE&#13;
(US$ million)&#13;
IDA-ITFCategory    Federation    RS    Total         % of Expenditures to be Financed&#13;
1. Civil works          4.6      3.3   7.9    100% (net of taxes)&#13;
2. Goods                 1.5      0.3   1.8    100% of foreign expenditures&#13;
100% of local expenditures (ex-factory cost) and 85% of&#13;
local expenditures for other items procured locally&#13;
3. Tecnical Assistance  0.5       0.2  0.7    100%&#13;
4. Recurrent Costs      0.3       0.1   0.4    100%&#13;
5. Unallocated          0.1       0.1   0.2&#13;
TOTAL             7.0      4.0   11.0&#13;
41.           Special Accounts. To facilitate timely project implementation, payments for agreed&#13;
project actions are to be made from two Special Accounts: one for the Federation and the other for&#13;
RS. The currency of the Special Accounts will be US dollars. Resporisibility for making payments&#13;
from the Special Accounts will continue to be delegated by the State. The authorized allocation of the&#13;
Special Account for the Federation would be US$3.0 million, representing about four months of&#13;
estimated average expenditures expected to be paid from the Special Account. This is consistent with&#13;
the disbursement performance under the first Emergency Education Reconstruction Project. The&#13;
authorized allocation of the Special Account for the RS would be US$1].75 million, also representing&#13;
about four months of average expenditures to be paid from the account. Replenishment applications&#13;
would continue to be forwarded to the Bank monthly and will include reconciled bank statements as&#13;
well as other appropriate documents. For large contracts, the Bank would make direct payments to&#13;
suppliers.&#13;
42.           Statement of Expenditures. With the exception of direct contracting and the first&#13;
three contracts awarding through National Shopping (NS), Simplified National Competitive Bidding&#13;
(SNCB), or National Competitive Bidding (NCB), disbursements would be made against Statements of&#13;
Expenditures (SOEs) for goods and civil works contracts of up to US$ 1.0 million. Disbursement&#13;
against all recurrent expenditures under the Project will be made by Statement of Expenditures, as&#13;
would all expenditures for consultant services amounting to less than US$100,000 for firms and&#13;
US$50,000 for individuals. Detailed documents evidencing expenditures would be maintained in a&#13;
central location by the PIUs for review by the required audit as well as Bank supervision missions.&#13;
Disbursement for contracts requiring the Bank's prior review would be made against presentation to the&#13;
Bank of full contract documentation.&#13;
Project Audits, Accounting and Reporting&#13;
43.           Accounts. Separate and auditable accounts would be established and maintained by the&#13;
two PIUs for the Project. For each Entity, these accounts would include: (i) a record of withdrawals&#13;
with copies of all disbursement requests and underlying documentation; and (ii) a record of transactions&#13;
under the Special Account and copies of the bank statements pertaining to the account.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
44.           Audits. The project accounts would be audited annually by independent auditors who&#13;
shall be employed by November 30, 1997 under terms of reference acceptable to the Bank. Separate&#13;
audit statements would be prepared for the Special Account and for Statements of Expenditures. All&#13;
audit reports would be made available to the Bank within six months after the end of each fiscal year.&#13;
Project accounts would be maintained for one year after they have been audited.&#13;
45.           Reporting. The project PIUs will prepare and furnish to the Bank quarterly: a)&#13;
progress reports showing the status of implementation of the Project, and b) financial reports in a&#13;
format acceptable to the Bank.&#13;
Supervision Plan&#13;
46.           Project implementation will continue to require a large degree of flexibility in view of&#13;
the rapidly changing circumstances in the country. In particular, procurement and disbursement issues&#13;
will continue to require intensive supervision, particularly for the RS PIU, which has less experience&#13;
with World Bank guidelines and procedures. Given the straightforward nature of the Project and the&#13;
short implementation period, no midterm review will be required. To facilitate flexibility and rapid&#13;
decision-making, the social sectors Bank staff located in the World Bank Resident Mission in Sarajevo&#13;
and in the Human Resources Hub in Budapest, as well as headquarters-based staff, will continue to&#13;
provide intensive supervision of initial project implementation, and will provide prompt feedback on&#13;
matters requiring a decision by the Bank.&#13;
Agreements Reached&#13;
47.           Agreement was reached at Negotiations on the following points:&#13;
a)    that the Federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina and the Republika Srpska would: i)&#13;
carry out by September 30, 1997 an Education Finance and Administration Study under&#13;
terms of reference satisfactory to the Association; ii) provide to the Association for&#13;
comment by October 31, 1997 the findings and recommendations of the Education&#13;
Finance and Administration Study; and iii) subsequently implement the&#13;
recommendations of the Study, as discussed and agreed with the Association;&#13;
b)    that the State, the Federation and RS shall employ independent auditors by November&#13;
30, 1997;&#13;
c)    that the Federation and RS shall coordinate with the Procurement Monitoring and Audit&#13;
Unit for purposes of procurement monitoring and audit for their respective parts of the&#13;
Project;&#13;
d)    that the Federation and RS shall by February 28 of each year prepare a report on the&#13;
progress achieved in carrying out their respective parts of the Project and review such&#13;
report, together with the Association, by March 31, 1998; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
e)    that the execution of a Project Agreement between IDA and at least one of the Entities&#13;
and the corresponding Subsidiary Credit Agreement between Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
and such Entity would be a condition of effectiveness for the proposed ITF Credit.&#13;
Execution of the Project Agreement between IDA and the other Entity and the&#13;
corresponding Subsidiary Credit Agreement between Bosnia and Herzegovina and such&#13;
Entity would be a condition of disbursement for that portion of the Credit allocated to&#13;
that Entity.&#13;
E. Benefits and Risks&#13;
48.          Benefits. The proposed Second-Phase Implementation of the Emergency Education&#13;
Reconstruction Project would help to restore the provision of education of acceptable quality&#13;
throughout the Federation and RS, thereby improving the educational qualifications and future&#13;
produptive potential of their school-age population. The Project would also improve the Government's&#13;
capacity to manage education programs, and would continue to provide a framework for cooperation&#13;
between the two partners of the Federation, and encourage similar cooperation between the Federation&#13;
and the Republika Srpska.&#13;
49.          Risks. The risk remains that a renewal of hostilities among the various partners of the&#13;
new State and Federation could undermine implementation of the Project, and prevent (or severely&#13;
delay) achievement of the Project's objectives. However, the reconstruction program itself is helping&#13;
to reduce this risk by creating incentives for cooperation by all parties.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
APPENDIX 1&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project&#13;
Estimated Cost and Disbursement Schedule&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
Project Cost Sununary&#13;
Books and&#13;
School       Educational    Education Finance       Project&#13;
Reconstruction    Materials    and Administration   Implementation      Total&#13;
1. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Civil Works                        8,100.0               -                  -                 -       8,100.0&#13;
B. Furniture and Equipment            1,000.0               -                  -              50.0       1,050.0&#13;
C. Educational Materials                   -            800.0                  -                 -        800.0&#13;
D. Technical Assistance and             150.0               -              500.0            50.0 a!       700.0&#13;
Training&#13;
Total Investment Costs                  9,300.0           800.0              500.0              50.0      10,650.0&#13;
II. Recurrent Costs&#13;
A. Incremental Operating Costs              -               -                  -             350.0        350.0&#13;
Total Recurrent Costs                        -                -                  -             350.0        350.0&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                     9,300.0           800.0              500.0             400.0      11,000.0&#13;
Taxes&#13;
Foreign Exchange                      9,300.0           800.0              500.0             400.0      11,000.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
APPENDIX 1&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project&#13;
Estimated Costs&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
School Reconstruction&#13;
Total&#13;
Cost&#13;
(US$)&#13;
1997      1998      Total&#13;
L. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Civil Works&#13;
Federation: Primary School Reconstruction      3,710.0   1,020.0    4,730.0&#13;
RS: Primary School Reconstruction              1,370.0   2,050.0    3,420.0&#13;
Subtotal Civil Works                             5,080.0   :3,070.0    8,150.0&#13;
B. Primary School Furniture&#13;
Federation: School Furniture                     603.0      67.0      670.0&#13;
RS: School Furniture                             330.0         -      330.0&#13;
Subtotal Primary School Furniture                  933.0      67.0    1,000.0&#13;
C. Design &amp; Management Assistance&#13;
Federation: Construction Supervision              60.0      40.0      100.0&#13;
RS: Construction Supervision                      50.0         -       50.0&#13;
Subtotal Design &amp; Management Assistance            110.0      40.0      150.0&#13;
Total                                          6,123.0   3,177.0    9,300.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
APPENDIX 1&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project&#13;
Estimated Costs&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
Textbooks&#13;
Total&#13;
Cost&#13;
(US$)&#13;
1997   1998   Total&#13;
1. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Books and Educational Materials (Federation Only)&#13;
Textbooks                                          280.0  120.0  400.0&#13;
B. Production and Financing Pilot Schemes (Fed. Only)&#13;
Pilot Development and Implementation               320.0   80.0  400.0&#13;
Total                                              600.0  200.0  800.0&#13;
Education Finance and Administration&#13;
Base Cost (US$)&#13;
1997        Total&#13;
I. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Technical Assistance            350.0        350.0&#13;
B. Training                        150.0        150.0&#13;
Total                                 500.0        500.0&#13;
Operating Costs&#13;
Total Cost (US$)&#13;
1997      1998          Total&#13;
I. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Project Implementation&#13;
1. Equipment Support (RS Only)&#13;
Office Equipment                          24.0        6.0               30.0&#13;
Vehicles                                  20.0          -               20.0&#13;
Total Investment Costs                            44.0       6.0               50.0&#13;
II. Recurrent Costs&#13;
A. Federation: Incremental Operating Costs    140.0     140.0              280.0&#13;
B. Federation: Annual Audits                   10.0      10.0               20.0&#13;
C. RS: Incremental Operating Costs             45.0      45.0               90.0&#13;
D. RS: Annual Audits                            5.0       5.0               10.0&#13;
Total Recurrent Costs                            200.0     200.0              400.0&#13;
Total                               244.0      206.0              450.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
APPENDIX 2&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project&#13;
Project hnplementation Schedule&#13;
Activity                 Description              Start Date    End Date    Responsible&#13;
Agency&#13;
School Reconstruction Component&#13;
Selection of     Develop 1997 priority school&#13;
schools          reconstruction program&#13;
Federation:                      09/96        complete      Fed-PIU&#13;
RS:                               10/ 96      03/97         RS-PIU&#13;
Select schools from program to&#13;
reconstruct with IDA funding&#13;
Federation:                      01/97        complete      Fed-PIU&#13;
RS:                              01/97        06/97         RS-PIU&#13;
Design phase     Prepare assessments/architectural designs&#13;
for schools&#13;
Federation:                      06/96        06/97         PIU/IMG&#13;
RS:                              06/97        07/97         PIU/Urban&#13;
Institute&#13;
Prepare specifications for school&#13;
reconstruction and furniture&#13;
Federation:                      05/96        complete      Fed-PIU&#13;
RS:                              06/97        08/97         PIU/Urban&#13;
Institute&#13;
Prepare procurement documents for   04/97        07/97         PIUs&#13;
Procure          school reconstruction and furniture&#13;
contractors for&#13;
reconstruction   Choose at least three qualified contractors  07/97  07/97       PIUs&#13;
works, school    per school and invite for bidding for&#13;
furniture and    schools estimated below US$1.0 million&#13;
supervision (same&#13;
for Federation and  Advertise works for works estimated  07/97     07/97         PIUs&#13;
RS)              above US$1.0 million&#13;
Prepare bids                        07/97        07/97         Contractors&#13;
Evaluate bids                       07/97-08/97   07/97-08/97   PIUs&#13;
Award and negotiate contracts       07/97-08/97   07/97-08/97   PIUs&#13;
Sign contracts once WB credit effective    07/97-08/97   07/97-08/97   PIUs&#13;
Select supervision contractors using  07/97      07/97         PIUs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Activity                  Description              Start Date    End Date     Responsible&#13;
Agency&#13;
competitive selection&#13;
Reconstruct      Implement reconstruction program      08/97         07/98         Contractors&#13;
schools                                                                            with PlUs &amp;&#13;
and deliver                                                                        Canton/&#13;
furniture                                                                          municipality&#13;
(same for&#13;
Federation and    Supervise reconstruction works and   08/97         07/98         Contractors&#13;
RS)               furniture delivery                                               with PIUs &amp;&#13;
Canton/&#13;
municipality&#13;
Books and Educational Materials Component&#13;
Select books and    Review list of previously agreed   03/97         04/97         PIU/&#13;
materials to be   textbooks and readers and agree with WB                          consultant&#13;
financed          on books to be fnanced&#13;
(Federation only)&#13;
Procure and      Invite printing proposals for agreed  07/97         08/97         PIU&#13;
distribute books    textbooks and readers from a minimum of&#13;
and materials     three local printers/book suppliers&#13;
Evaluate printing/supply proposals from    08/97   09/97         PIU&#13;
printers/book suppliers&#13;
Negotiate printing and supply contracts    09/97   09/97         PIU&#13;
Sign contracts once WB credit is effective  09/97  10/97         PIU&#13;
Distribute books    Take delivery of textbooks readers and  01/98    02/98         PIU&#13;
and materials to    arrange for distribution to canton level&#13;
cantons&#13;
Develop &amp;         Develop pilot activities              12/96        06/97         PIU/ cons.&#13;
implement pilot&#13;
schemes for       Train participants                   07/97         09/97         PIU/cons.&#13;
production and&#13;
financing         Implement pilot activities            10/97        08/98         PIU/ cons.&#13;
Project Implementation Component&#13;
Select key        Establish a Project Implementation Unit&#13;
personnel to         Federation:                        04/96        complete      Fed-MOE&#13;
manage               RS:                                11/96        complete      RS-MOE&#13;
implementation&#13;
Procure support    Define specifications for support    03/97        06/97         PIU&#13;
equipment (RS     equipment (computers, copiers, vehicles,&#13;
only; Federation    etc.) to be provided for PIU&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Activity                  Description               Start Date    End Date     Responsible&#13;
Agency&#13;
PIU equipped&#13;
under first project  Organize separate procurement for office  06/97  07/97         PIU&#13;
equipment and vehicles on the basis of&#13;
three price quotations&#13;
Sign contracts for equipment and vehicles  07/97   07/97         PIU&#13;
once WB credit is effective&#13;
Organize payment  Disburse operating funds for project  08197         11/98         PlUs&#13;
of project related   related operating costs including salaries,&#13;
operating costs   office supplies, and vehicle operation and&#13;
maintenance (Federation and RS)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
APPENDIX 3&#13;
Page 1 of 1&#13;
Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project&#13;
Summary of Objectives and Key Performance Indicators&#13;
INPUTS              OUTPUTS             RISKS AND           OUTCOMES AND&#13;
(Resources          (Goods and          CRITICAL            IMPACTS&#13;
provided for        Services Produced    ASSUMPTIONS        (of project&#13;
OBJECTIVES          program activities)   by the Program)   (The outcome is     activities)&#13;
dependent on...)&#13;
Reconstruction and   - IDA Credit ($10    - About 25 war    - continued peace in  - About 30% of BH&#13;
furnish 25 war      million)            damaged primary     BH                  needs in primary&#13;
damaged primary                         schools             - continued         school&#13;
schools             About US$8.8        reconstructed and    cooperation with   reconstruction met&#13;
million in funds    furnished in BH     RS authorities      - continued&#13;
will be used to:                        - continued (from   improvement in&#13;
- Reconstruct and                       first project)      cooperation&#13;
furniture about 24                      efficient           between Federation&#13;
war damaged                             management of       partners&#13;
primary schools in                      procurement for     - improved aid&#13;
the Government's                        reconstruction and    coordination in&#13;
1997 reconstruction                     furniture contracts   education&#13;
program                                                     - improved&#13;
cooperation&#13;
between Federation&#13;
and RS in&#13;
Education&#13;
Delivery of         -.IDA Credit        - 12 textbooks      - continued peace in  - progress towards&#13;
essential textbooks   (US$10 million)   delivered to schools  BH                meeting emergency&#13;
to Federation       - Dutch Trust Fund   - textbook         - continued (from   educational&#13;
schools and        (US$70,000)          production and cost  first project)     materials needs&#13;
implementation of                       recovery pilots     efficient           - development and&#13;
successful textbook   About US$0.8      successfully        management of       testing of textbook&#13;
pilots              million in IDA      implemented         procurement for     production and cost&#13;
funds will be used                      textbooks and       recovery&#13;
to:                                     education materials   mechanisms that&#13;
- cooperation of    will ensure private&#13;
- procure about 12                      Canton level        sector involvement&#13;
essential textbooks                     officials in textbook  in textbook&#13;
and delivery them                       pilots              provision and help&#13;
to schools                                                  ensure the&#13;
- prepare and                                               sustainability of&#13;
implement textbook                                          public education&#13;
production and cost                                         delivery&#13;
recovery pilots in&#13;
several Federation&#13;
Cantons&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
APPENDIX 4&#13;
Page 1 of 1&#13;
Bosnia and Herzegovina&#13;
Second Emergency Education Reconstruction Project&#13;
Project Procurement Plan&#13;
Expenditure Category          Total Cost         Likely      Invitation    Contract    Work/Delivery     All Work/&#13;
US$Miflion      Procurement    to Bid        Awards          Begins         Delivery&#13;
Methods                                                   Complete&#13;
CIVIL WORKS&#13;
Refurbishment of Schools              8.1           NCB/NS           7/97        7/97         7/97-8/97          8/98&#13;
(estimated 24 contracts)&#13;
GOODS AND EQUIPMENT&#13;
Supply of School Furniture            1.0           NCB/NS           7197        8/97            9/97            12/97&#13;
(estimated 6 contracts)&#13;
Textbook printing                     0.8             NCB            7/97        9197            1/98            2/98&#13;
(estimated 12 contracts)&#13;
TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE&#13;
Works Design         }                0.2              SL            6/97        7/97            7/97            8/97&#13;
Supervision          }                                 SL            7/97      7/97-8/97         7/97         7/97-12/98&#13;
Audits               }                                 SL            8/97        10/97           12/97           4/99&#13;
Education Finance and                 0.5              SL           07/97        9/97            9/97            4/98&#13;
Administration&#13;
OPERATING COSTS&#13;
Salaries/supplies/vehicle operation   0.4             N/A            N/A         N/A             N/A             N/A&#13;
and maintenance&#13;
TOTAL                                 11.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IBRD 28377&#13;
16                           o Tozagreb                      180         ToOsijekI&#13;
TC) Zogre''      To Zagrebs&#13;
To Zogreb&gt;&gt;) +&gt;agreb                C R O  A T I A                To vinkovcc&#13;
""' ,"o.            *,  ,,                  To Osijek&#13;
ski movi                  ns                                                   45'-~~~~~jp'rv&#13;
Nj Boeonslci NoM  Bosnskc&amp;                                                 '   - To Belgrad&#13;
45@                 pet       G rdk                       Bouon-ki&#13;
rniwaor    /a&#13;
~~~~ b A &lt;&lt;tGot9  KFDrssa                                               RPBLICI'n&#13;
43~~~~~~~~~~~~ r' &gt;2                                           %tsj  - -~      -      szz    -         b XgYUnGcOSLAIA&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
A~~~~~~~~~~~~caj dr~ ia*                                                  ar i~ cBeealgrade 2    5    7&#13;
yS  a -                         Proaar                                 R&amp;iIn V;es}Tismapwasrducdytea&#13;
RECONSTRUCTWON  PRO-J ECT                                       .~~~~~~~~Ne~~s  Konv1    bouraemntaceTaeofs&#13;
--:.--. FDERTIN-C NTOLLD  REA  -            ,      ks0tgA     (FEDERAL HIGREPUBLIC &#13;
.0~~~~~3&#13;
69 ~ ~ ~     ~      ~      ~     ~     ~    Reo (AlOA CAISERBTLYX'O&lt;IA E B/MONTENEBUGARIA )EE&#13;
---IN6TrebNI'                                               KILnOMETQ E&#13;
This mopf wasr prouce by the Map&#13;
D     k                         Dsin Unit The Wld X B0 ThKE&#13;
endorsement or acetac   96s&#13;
CROATIA~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ZC n" OAD&#13;
g'as   RIERi2'ai-u                                                                  enjc RMAQA   t&#13;
42,                                                                                                   -65ko &#13;
0   SELECTED CITIES                                "''~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'-k    K.~~~~T&#13;
K t'~~~~~ eltgr -de&#13;
N ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~c&#13;
0~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~14&#13;
TO~ ~~COER19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IMAGING&#13;
Report No.: lP  T  7028   BIH&#13;
Type:     MO       A N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="438578">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/06/438578/bosnia-herzegovina-second-emergency-education-reconstruction-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/06/438578/bosnia-herzegovina-second-emergency-education-reconstruction-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/06/438578/bosnia-herzegovina-second-emergency-education-reconstruction-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/02/24/000009265_3971104184944/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/02/24/000009265_3971104184944/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>N035</credit_no>
        <datestored>2001-05-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1997-06-06T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Bosnia and Herzegovina - Second Emergency
            Education Reconstruction Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The primary objective of the Second
            Emergency Education Reconstruction Project for Bosnia and
            Herzegovina (the Federation) is to continue the work begun
            under the first project similarly named, which aimed to
            restore adequate teaching and learning conditions in the
            country's primary schools. Secondary objectives are to
            help develop an appropriate process of education finance and
            administration, to build government implementation capacity
            to plan and deliver education programs at different
            government levels, and to facilitate communication and
            cooperation on education issues within the Federation, and
            between the Federation and the Serb Republic. The project
            will support: 1) reconstruction of primary schools in the
            Federation and of about seven primary schools in the Serb
            Republic; 2) provision of classroom furniture and equipment;
            3) provision of textbooks and educational materials for
            Federation schools; 4) support for incremental recurrent
            costs for the two project implementation units; and 5)
            technical assistance to improve education finance and administration.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Bosnia and Herzegovina - Second Emergency
            Education Reconstruction Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Bosnia and Herzegovina - Second
            Emergency Education Reconstruction Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1997/06/438578/bosnia-herzegovina-second-emergency-education-reconstruction-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>BA-Education Reconstruction 2 Project -- P045313</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Curriculum &amp; Instruction,Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Gender and Education,Primary Education,Teaching and Learning</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Gender</teratopic>
        <count>Bosnia and Herzegovina</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3971104184944</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Primary education,Central government administration</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1997-2</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Gender</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Education</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Civil works; Communication; Educational
            administration; Educational equipment; Educational
            facilities; Educational financing; Educational furniture;
            Investments; Political cooperation; Primary schools;
            Recurrent costs; Teaching aids; Technical assistance; Textbooks
            addition,Advertising,asbestos,classroom
            size,classrooms,decentralization,Development Program,donor
            agencies,Education Finance,Education governance,education
            policy,education programs,education quality,education
            reform,Education Sector,education system,education
            systems,Educational Materials,educational
            quality,educational responsibilities,effective
            teaching,employment,housing,language
            training,languages,literature,ministries of
            education,Performance Indicators,policy development,policy
            reform,positive impact,primary education,Primary
            School,primary schools,printing,private sector,Public
            Expenditure,qualified teachers,quality assurance,quality of
            education,refugees,school buildings,school
            construction,school facilities,school furniture,School
            Rehabilitation,secondary education,secondary school
            teachers,secondary schools,Sports,study
            tours,teacher,teacher training,teachers,teaching,textbook
            production,textbooks,total costs,vocational education
        </keywd>
        <owner>Human Development Sector Unit (ECSHD)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF021083-ITALY - BHZ-EDUCATION
            RECONSTRUCTION PROJECT II,TF020873-RECONSTRUCTION PROGRAM
            PREPARATION (BANK EX.)</trustfund>
        <repnb>T7028</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Reform and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textbooks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Research and Surveys for Public Contracts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Higher Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education  Enhancing Access, Equity and Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuous Vocational Training (CVT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Technical Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical Vocational Education and Training Policies and Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical and Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Education and Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education/HD Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Expenditures in Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance of Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Curriculum &amp; Instruction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning Materials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplementary</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Bosnia and Herzegovina</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>