<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>16952&#13;
At a Glance&#13;
The World Bank        FPD Note No. 8                                             May 1994&#13;
Mass Privatization in Ukraine&#13;
Bernard Drum&#13;
Ukraine has sofar been unable to activate and monetary policies, following the&#13;
its mass privatization program. Howev- collapse of the Soviet Union. At the&#13;
er, in early March 1994, a multidonor  same time the government has been&#13;
mission to Ukraine signed a memoran-  slow to relax its grip on the economy&#13;
dum of understanding (MOU) on mass  or to allow market forces and the pri-&#13;
privatization with the government. If   vate sector to lead the way out of de-&#13;
this MOU and the 1994 State Privatiza-  cline. Although there have been many&#13;
tion Program approved by Parliament  pronouncements on the need to move&#13;
in early 1994 are both implemented,   to a market economy there are, as yet,&#13;
the Ukraine mass privatization pro-    few tangible signs of a coherent ap-&#13;
gram could become one of the largest   proach to economic policy.&#13;
in the world. This Note reviews the de-&#13;
velopments since Ukraine's indepen-    Details on the total size of the enter-&#13;
dence, including the main provisions   prise sector in Ukraine are hard to&#13;
of the 1994 State Privatization Pro-  come by but the state sector is estimat-&#13;
gram and the MOU.                  ed to be in excess of 10,000 medium&#13;
and large enterprises and well over&#13;
Background                         100,000 small enterprises. Much of the&#13;
The challenge facing the designers and  Soviet Union's diverse heavy and light&#13;
implementers of a mass privatization   industry, including some of its largest&#13;
program in Ukraine is enormous by  monopolies, was located in Ukraine.&#13;
any standards. The Ukrainian econo-&#13;
my has been in continual crisis for the  Privatization in Ukraine, as with other&#13;
last few years. GDP is thought to have  aspects of economic reform, has been&#13;
fallen by about 40 percent since 1989,  paralyzed by a lack of consensus&#13;
and by 15 percent in 1993 alone. Infla-  among policymakers, an absence of&#13;
tion during 1993 was estimated to be   leadership, an ambiguous legal and&#13;
5,000 percent, reaching as high as 75   institutional framework, and weak&#13;
percent per month for a time during    implementation capacity. While in&#13;
the second half of the year. This infla-  neighboring Russia, the spontaneous&#13;
tion was a direct result of government  privatization which had been gather-&#13;
efforts to support existing production   ing momentum in early 1992 was ef-&#13;
patterns through expansionary fiscal   fectively captured and institutionalized&#13;
_:  =P3   Private Sector Development Department&#13;
0F-P        Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
Af @         27&lt;.   .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
by the Russian Mass Privatization Program, the ab-   increased in 1993 to Krb 1,000,050. Hyperinflation&#13;
sence of a similar program in Ukraine has encour-   has made a precise determination of the US$ face&#13;
aged spontaneous privatization to accelerate. Enter-  value equivalent difficult but at today's market rate&#13;
prise employees in Ukraine, and particularly the   the value of a certificate is approximately US$30.&#13;
workers' collectives, perceive that they have own-   (The certificate face value is in any case related to&#13;
ership rights to the enterprises where they work.    the book value of the enterprise assets rather than to&#13;
Their perceptions of ownership rights have been     their market value.) Each enterprise has to submit a&#13;
reinforced by a series of laws and decrees that     privatization application to its parent privatization&#13;
have given workers the right to lease enterprises   body and create a privatization committee to pre-&#13;
with exclusive buyout options at the very low book   pare a plan and oversee the corporatization and&#13;
value.                                              privatization process. For small enterprises (i.e.,&#13;
those with a 1992 book value of Krb 1.5 million or&#13;
The legal and institutional framework               less) the law provides for employee buyout or for&#13;
The basic statutes governing privatization in Ukraine  competitive sale by auction or tender.&#13;
are the laws on (i) Privatization of Property of State&#13;
Enterprises, (ii) Small Privatization, and (iii) Privatiza-   A distinguishing feature of Ukrainian privatization&#13;
tion Certificates. These laws were passed by Parlia-   is the widespread leasing of enterprises of all sizes&#13;
ment in 1992. They have since been supplemented    and the special privileges and priorities given to&#13;
by many other laws, decrees, and regulations which   leaseholders in the privatization process. Lease-&#13;
have further defined the process. In 1992 Parliament  holders were well represented in the outgoing Par-&#13;
approved the 1992 State Privatization Program which  liament. Their influence on the legislation has been&#13;
gave concrete targets for the period 1992-1994, and    significant, despite attempts by some reformers in&#13;
earlier this year the 1994 State Privatization Program   the government to limit leaseholder privileges by&#13;
set new targets for 1994.                          issuing decrees which have sometimes contradicted&#13;
the law. The Privatization Law allows lease buyouts&#13;
All state-owned enterprises now come under the      and the Leasing Law, also passed in 1992, gives&#13;
authority either of the State Property Fund (SPF) or   lessees the exclusive right of buyout for a period of&#13;
the regional or city property funds, which have full  three years. Leaseholders are also allowed to apply&#13;
responsibility for privatization of the enterprises  retained earnings during the lease period to the&#13;
within their portfolios.                            purchase price of the enterprise. In general the&#13;
leaseholders have been winning the battle against&#13;
A first important principle underlying the privatiza-   those favoring more open forms of privatization.&#13;
tion laws for medium and large enterprises is that all  This also reflects the extent to which leasing has&#13;
citizens of Ukraine are entitled to a share of the en-   spread.&#13;
terprise assets. This entitlement is exercised by&#13;
means of privatization certificates which are to be  Foreign investors can participate in medium- and&#13;
distributed to the population free of charge. A sec-   large-scale privatization on the same basis as Ukrai-&#13;
ond important principle is that workers in the enter-  nian nationals, except, of course, that they will not&#13;
prises have first priority and the balance of shares  have privatization certificates to redeem, nor can&#13;
can be distributed and sold by a mix of methods     they benefit from employee privileges. In small-scale&#13;
including auctions, tenders, or public offering.    privatization, Ukrainian investors are given the right&#13;
of first refusal but if no local buyer emerges then&#13;
Privatization certificates are nontradable and take  foreign investors can take part. Foreign investors do,&#13;
the form of privatization accounts opened for each    however, have to convert their foreign currency at a&#13;
citizen in the Savings Bank. The original value of  less advantageous rate than the market rate of ex-&#13;
each citizen's certificate was Krb 30,000. This was  change.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Privatization results to date                     cities on small-scale privatization. The European&#13;
The 1992 State Privatization Program sought to    Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD)&#13;
privatize 15 to 30 percent of assets in retail trade  initially provided assistance with European Union&#13;
and consumer services and several hundred medium   (EU) finance to the SPF in Kiev, but then focused its&#13;
and large enterprises during 1992, and to complete   effort on pilot privatization transactions. The EU' has&#13;
small-scale privatization during the following two  worked directly on medium-scale pilot transactions.&#13;
years. The program also included a plan to privatize  All of these initiatives have produced and continue&#13;
80 to 90 percent of industry and 100 percent of   to produce concrete results. They are being extend-&#13;
trade over the period to the end of 1994. But no  ed but have yet to lead to the widespread replica-&#13;
serious attempt was made to realize these targets.    tion that was originally hoped for.&#13;
Satisfactory progress in meeting them could only&#13;
have been made by designing and initiating a mass   The 1994 State Privatization Program&#13;
privatization program and through a program of    The 1994 State Privatization Program provides for&#13;
very rapid small-scale privatization. Neither of these   mass privatization of medium and large enterprises&#13;
things happened. In 1993 individual privatization  and for a computerized communications network&#13;
transactions did take place and small-scale privatiza-  and data base to support implementation. The pro-&#13;
tion had started. By October 1993, according to in-    gram also proposes rapid and widespread small-&#13;
formation from the SPF, several hundred medium-    scale enterprise privatization. Privatization targets for&#13;
scale enterprises belonging to both SPF and       1994 are 24,000 small-scale enterprises, 1,680 units&#13;
Regional Property Funds and 200 small-scale enter-   of unfinished construction, and 8,000 medium and&#13;
prises had been privatized. The total book value of   large enterprises. Transfer to citizens via certificates&#13;
these enterprises was Krb 130 billion. But the ab-  will account for not less than 70 percent of the total&#13;
sence of a mass privatization program and the in-  value of assets privatized. Foreign investors will have&#13;
ability to replicate small-scale enterprise auctions  to convert their currency at the rate of Krb 420 per&#13;
have prevented the process from building up the   US$, compared with the current market rate of&#13;
same level of momentum that has existed in Russia   around Krb 37,000.&#13;
since 1992.&#13;
In preparing the pipeline of enterprises for privatiza-&#13;
This lack of progress at the center prompted the  tion, priority will be given to retail outlets and con-&#13;
international donors during 1993 to support local-    sumer services and those medium and large enter-&#13;
level programs in an attempt to jump-start the pro-    prises that have the greatest impact on the consumer&#13;
cess. The World Bank, with grant finance from the    market, as well as loss making enterprises. Cabinet&#13;
Dutch and Swiss governments, provided assistance    of Ministers' approval is required for privatization of&#13;
to the privatization bodies in the city and oblast of    monopolies and of enterprises such as those involved&#13;
Kharkiv. The Bank also worked using a Swiss grant  in fuel, energy, transport, medical equipment and&#13;
and the proceeds of the World Bank Institution    pharmaceuticals, certain media, paper, and bread.&#13;
Building Loan in the city of Kiev. The Kharkiv pro-   No privatization is planned this year for 'strategic&#13;
gram included assistance with small- and medium-    activities" such as ports, pipelines, military equip-&#13;
scale privatization and private sector development    ment, public utilities, publishing, education, and the&#13;
and the Kiev program gave assistance in preparing    space complex.&#13;
for small-scale privatization. International Finance&#13;
Corporation (IFC), with grant finance from USAID,    Memorandum of Understanding&#13;
worked on small-scale privatization in L'viv, Zapor-   In February 1994, a joint mission including the World&#13;
izhe, and several other cities and carried out a num-  Bank, EBRD, USAID, and the EU worked in Ukraine&#13;
ber of successful medium-scale pilot transactions.  with privatization and other government officials.&#13;
USAID has worked directly in Odessa and other     This was a highly collaborative initiative driven by a&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
realization on all sides that the time for implement-    Bank's case these funds would be provided from the&#13;
ing mass privatization in Ukraine was long overdue    Institution Building Loan supplemented as far as&#13;
and that the donors were ready to finance the im-      possible by Trust Fund grants, (i.e., grant funds from&#13;
plementation of a program if agreement could be        bilateral donors administered by the Bank). The ex-&#13;
reached with the government on the program con-    temal support will include financing of the design&#13;
tent. A first premise on which the agreement was       and printing of the certificates, implementation of&#13;
negotiated was that there should be no major chang-  the independent bidding network including comput-&#13;
es to the existing legal framework for privatization.    ers and telecommunications equipment, training and&#13;
Refinements would be made where necessary but          equipment for the privatization agencies, a large&#13;
the time required to get Parliament to make changes   public information campaign, support for the devel-&#13;
would not be worth the wait and the uncertainty.       opment of investment funds, secondary securities&#13;
The objective was to get the program up and run-       markets, and postprivatization support for enterprises.&#13;
ning as soon as possible.&#13;
There are no specific agreements to deal with the&#13;
The main commitment agreed to by the government  leaseholder problem but the donors are committed&#13;
in the Memorandum of Understanding is that it will   to provide advisers on incentives to promote rapid&#13;
begin implementing a mass privatization program in   privatization of leased enterprises.&#13;
accordance with the 1994 State Privatization Program.&#13;
Innovations agreed to by the government in the         Next steps&#13;
Memorandum include (0 the use of paper vouchers   Recent parliamentary elections have temporarily&#13;
or certificates instead of the previous plan to use    diverted the attention of some decisionmakers.&#13;
non-paper privatization accounts in the Savings        However consultants are now in the field making&#13;
Bank; (ii) the creation of a network of private bid-   progress with the program design details. Issues still&#13;
ding and processing centers to exchange the certifi-  to be resolved include hiow certificates will be ex-&#13;
cates for shares, thus removing the need for the al-    changed for shares and how the enterprise prepara-&#13;
ready overburdened Savings Bank to play this role;   tion process can be streamlined without major&#13;
and (iii) streamlining the process for preparing enter-   changes to the legislation. Incentives also need to be&#13;
prises for sale. By law, the certificates will not be  developed to encourage leaseholders to go through&#13;
transferable between individuals but will be tradable  the privatization process as soon as possible. As&#13;
for shares in enterprises through the bidding centers   soon as agreement with the government on the de-&#13;
or for units in private investment funds. These funds  tails of the program is reached and implementation&#13;
will be actively promoted and they will be allowed    begins, the government and donors will be carefully&#13;
to use the certificates they receive to buy shares     monitoring the need for further assistance. If the&#13;
through the auction process. These innovations         ambitious plans at last show signs of being realized&#13;
should allow very rapid implementation.                there should be no shortage of further financial sup-&#13;
port from the donors.&#13;
In return the donors who participated in the mission&#13;
agreed to provide USS30 million to suppolt the pro-   Bernard Drum, Senior Enterprise Reform and Privatization Specialist,&#13;
gram over the first four to six months. In the World    Europe and Central Asia Region.&#13;
This series is published to share ideas and invite discussion. It covers financial and private sector development as well as&#13;
industry and energy. The views expressed are those of the author(s) and are not intended to represent an official statement of&#13;
Bank policy or strategy.&#13;
Comments are welcome. Please call the FPD Note line to leave a message: 202-458-1111, or contact Suzanne Smith, editor, Room&#13;
G8105, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC 20043, or Internet address ssmith@worldbank.org.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="438996">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/05/438996/mass-privatization-ukraine
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/05/438996/mass-privatization-ukraine</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1994/05/438996/mass-privatization-ukraine</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/02/11/000009265_3980624164839/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/02/11/000009265_3980624164839/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1994-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2000-02-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Mass privatization in Ukraine
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Ukraine has so far been unable to
            activate ita mass privatization program. However, in early
            March 1994, a multidonor mission to Ukraine signed a
            memorandum of understanding (MOU) on mass privatization with
            the government. If this MOU and the 1994 State Privatization
            Program approved by Parliament in early 1994 are both
            implemented, the Ukraine mass privatization program could
            become one of the largest in the world. The author reviews
            the developments since Ukraine's independence,
            including the main provisions of the 1994 State
            Privatization Program and the MOU.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Mass privatization in Ukraine
        </docna>
        <display_title>Mass privatization in Ukraine</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1994/05/438996/mass-privatization-ukraine</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Judicial System Reform,Legal Institutions of the Market Economy,Municipal Financial Management,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Legal Products</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Drum, Bernard</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980624164839</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Public Sector Management</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>At a glance ; FPD note no. 8,Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 8</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Denationalization; Deregulation; Economic
            crisis; Gross domestic product; Private sector; Government
            ownership; Multilateral aid; Small &amp; medium scale
            enterprises; International financial institutions
            assets,auctions,authority,book
            value,Cabinet,cities,corporatization,economic
            reform,elections,Enterprise Reform,European Union,face
            value,Institution Building,laws,legal
            framework,legislation,market value,monetary
            policies,privatization,public utilities,retained
            earnings,Savings,State Enterprises,State Property,state sector,transport,USAID
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>16952</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Medical Supplies, Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceutical Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Medical Devices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial System Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceuticals</ml:concept><ml:concept>Medical Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>