<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Aggregate Demand and Macroeconomic&#13;
Imbalances in Thailand: Simulations with the&#13;
Siam1 Model&#13;
SWP-448&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 448&#13;
April 1981&#13;
Prepared by: Wafik Grais&#13;
Development Research Center&#13;
Copyright @ 1981&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
IQ-l W &lt;treet, N.W.                                                                        .5L9 ?% &#13;
on, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
PUB&#13;
HG                                                                                             . &#13;
3881.5  's and interpretations in this document are those of the authors&#13;
W57      ild not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
W67       ions, or to any individual acting in their behalf.             i                      i- Aw&#13;
no. 448&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 448&#13;
April 1981&#13;
AGGREGATE DEMAND AND MACROECONOMIC IMBALANCES IN THAILAND:&#13;
SIMULATIONS WITH THE SIAM1 MODEL&#13;
In the latter half of the seventies, Thailand was able to maintain&#13;
high GDP rates of growth. These were, however, associated with growing depen-&#13;
dence on foreign borrowing and chronic budgetary deficits. The average growth&#13;
rate between 1974 and 1979 was close to 8%. But the current account deficit&#13;
reached in 1979 8% of GDP, while the central government deficit was close to&#13;
4% of GDP and inflation was around 15%. These macroeconomic imbalances were&#13;
further exacerbated with the oil price increase of 1979-80, and future growth&#13;
is endangered by the exhaustion of new agricultural land. This paper focusses&#13;
on the demand side adjustments of the Thai economy to lower agricultural growth&#13;
and to higher energy prices. It draws the implications of the demand responses&#13;
on the time path of the resource gap, the current account deficit and on the&#13;
public sector savings gap.&#13;
The analysis uses an economy-wide model built around a social accoun-&#13;
ting matrix. It is a fix-price (prices do not respond to excess demand but are&#13;
cost determined) model which is demand driven for industry, energy and services&#13;
and is supply driven for agriculture.  It is closed at the macroeconomic level&#13;
by assuming exogenous real investment. The model is used to generatie two types&#13;
of results: (1) time paths for the endogenous variables under different assump-&#13;
tions on the paths of exogenous variables, policy parameters and structural&#13;
parameters and (2) elasticities at one point in time of the endogenous variables&#13;
with respect to all predetermined parameters and variables. These elasticities&#13;
measure the direct and indirect effects of, say, variations in energy prices on&#13;
the consumer price index.&#13;
Results of two simu'lations are reported in the paper. The first one&#13;
shows that in the absence of any major policy response to higher energy prices&#13;
and to lower agricultural growth, the resource gap would still be about 5% of&#13;
GDP by 1984, and would only vanish by 1990. The current account deficit, how-&#13;
ever, would remain as high as 6.5% of CDP by 1984 and would be reduced to 3.2%&#13;
by 1990. The public sector savings gap,on the contrary, would gradually increase&#13;
reaching 6.2% of GDP by 1990. In the second simulation, a set of policy measures&#13;
are assumed to be implemented. They are aimed at (i) increasing government&#13;
revenues, (ii) discouraging energy imports and consumption, (iii) encouraging&#13;
exports, (iv) increasing government savings, Under these assumptions, the resource&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- ii-&#13;
gap diminishes more rapidly becoming a surplus (2% of GDP) by 1990, while&#13;
the current account deficit vanishes towards the end of the decade. The&#13;
public sector savings gap di:minishes to 4.5% of GDP by 1985, reaching 3.3%&#13;
by 1990.&#13;
These results show that in both simulations improvement in the&#13;
nmacroeconomic imbalances takes place. It is, however, less pronounced and&#13;
occurs later in the decade in the first simulation.&#13;
Prepared by:                                               Copyright,-c 1981&#13;
Wafik Grais, Development Research Center                   The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iii -&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.   INTRODUCTION ..........................................             1&#13;
II.   THE TOOLS OF ANALYSIS .................................             4&#13;
The Social Accounting Matrix ........................            6&#13;
Economics of the Model ..............................            8&#13;
Relations of SIAM1 ..................................    11&#13;
III.   SIMULATION EXPERIMENTS WITH SIAM1 .....................    23&#13;
"Laisser-aller" versus Policy Intervention .... ......    25&#13;
Direct and Indirect Effects of Marginal Changes in&#13;
Parameters and Exogenous Variables ....         ............    33&#13;
IV.   CONCLUSION  ...........................................    37&#13;
APPENDIX 1: A Base-Year SAM for the SIAM1 Model&#13;
APPENDIX 2: Data Base of the Reference Simulation&#13;
LIST OF TABLES IN MAIN TEXT&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Table 1:  A Social Accounting Matrix of the Thai Economy 1975  ...              7&#13;
Table 2:  The Savings and Investment Ratios ......................    39&#13;
Table 3:  Rates of Growth of Imports and of Exports of Goods and&#13;
Nonfactor Services  ....................................    40&#13;
Table 4:  Trade Balance and Current Account  .....................    41&#13;
Table 5:  Public Finances  .......................................    42&#13;
Table 6:  Selected Elasticities with Respect to&#13;
Exogenous Variables and Parameters  ....................    43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. Introduction&#13;
During the past five years (1975-79), the Thai economy has experienced&#13;
an impressive average annual GDP growth rate of 8.7% at constant market prices.&#13;
Given the downward trend in the rate of population growth, this implies that&#13;
GDP (constant market prices) per capita grew at an annual rate of 6.3% during&#13;
the same period. If maintained, these rates imply a doubling of real income&#13;
per capita approximately every 11 years.&#13;
This impressive growth, however, did not take place in an economy where&#13;
the basic macroeconomic equilibria were holding. Looking at the Investments&#13;
Savings balance, the gap has increased between 1976 and 1979. The ratio of&#13;
investment to GDP grew from 23.23% to 27.85% between these two years, whereas&#13;
the ratio of gross national savings to GDP was stable at 20%-21%. At the end&#13;
of the seventies, the gap between gross national savings and gross investment&#13;
was thus around 7% of GDP. On the average, the deficit in the capital account&#13;
of the government has been larger than the deficit for the private sector. The&#13;
average gap for the government has been around 2.75% of GDP, compared to 2.05%&#13;
for the private sector. It follows that the growth performance of the Thai&#13;
economy was associated with an insufficient generation of savings, the situation&#13;
being worse for the government than for the private sector.&#13;
Looking at the external balance, the current account deficit was&#13;
slightly over 8% of GDP in 1979, reaching 2.25 billion dollars which is double&#13;
the 1978 figure. The bulk of this deficit is in the goods trade balance.&#13;
However, this is not due to soaring imports and lagging exports. The performance&#13;
of Thai exports has, in fact, been impressive; they increased in constant price,&#13;
at an annual rate of 15.2%, while imports increased at 11.6% durirLg the same&#13;
period (1975-79). Basically, the gap is due to the deterioration of the terms&#13;
of trade experienced by Thailand in the past five years.  From 100 in 1975, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2&#13;
terms of trade have shifted to 87.8 in 1979. This decline has since been&#13;
exacerbated by the recent increases in oil prices.-/ In constant 1972 prices,&#13;
the average share of exports in GDP was 19.7% between 1975 and 1979, whereas&#13;
the share of imports- /was 17.3% which would normally indicate a rather healthy&#13;
situation. The same ratios in current prices, however, are 20.9 and 25.5 for&#13;
exports and imports respectively. Given the degree of openness of the economy,&#13;
adverse movements in world prices can clearly be crucial for the external&#13;
balance. Another point worth noting is that although the service balance is&#13;
positive, the factor service balance is negative and has been increasingly so.&#13;
Tha main negative item is the balance of investment income.&#13;
Together with the above mentioned domestic and external imbalances,&#13;
two other phenomena which will have deep effects on the Thai economy are emer-&#13;
ging. The first of these is higher energy costs (mentioned above). The 1979-80&#13;
increases are, of course, not the first experience of this shock: just as&#13;
Thailand appeared to be recovering from the 1973-74 shock, the present one is&#13;
at hand. It is more or less probable that oil prices will continue to rise.&#13;
For a country which is the fifth largest oil importer of the nonproducing deve-&#13;
loping countries, this situation must be taken seriously. Given the present&#13;
external and government deficits, it is hard to see a lengthy postponement of&#13;
domestic oil price increases. However, passing on the increases in world prices&#13;
means higher costs to the economy which could reduce growth and make Thai exports&#13;
less competitive in world markets. It could also lead to social unrest.&#13;
The second phenomenon which will presumably have a profound effect&#13;
on the Thai economy is the exhaustion of new agricultural land. In the past,&#13;
1/ Oil imports in 1979 were 22.7% of total imports.&#13;
2/ For exports and imports: goods and nonfactor services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3&#13;
new land has allowed a high growth in agriculture generated agricultural exports&#13;
and helped alleviate rural poverty, all in the context of extensive agriculture.&#13;
Unless changes occur in agricultural techniques, the exhaustion of new land&#13;
resources will mean lower rates of growth in that sector. This will add to&#13;
the other problems of the Thai economy.&#13;
If not dealth with, present macroeconomic disequilibria, higher energy&#13;
costs, and the land constraint can have strong adverse effects on the growth of&#13;
the economy and on future development. The natural question arises as to what&#13;
would be the macroeconomic picture in the medium term if present trends remain.&#13;
This leads to the question of what kind of adjustment is needed to allow the&#13;
economy to overcome the present disequilibria, the adverse effect of oil prices&#13;
and the land constraint. The latter question has, in fact, two parts. The&#13;
first concerns what policy measures can help alleviate the disequilibria given&#13;
the present structure-/of the economy. The second is what kind of structural&#13;
change would allow the economy to overcome present and emerging problems-/ in the&#13;
long run.&#13;
The analysis presented below deals with the macroeconomic outcome of&#13;
present trends and of different policy measures given the present structure of&#13;
the economy. The policy measures considered are essentially fiscal measures.&#13;
The question of structural change itself is not dealt with, but directions and&#13;
quantification of the impact of marginal structural change are considered.&#13;
The analysis is based on a macroeconomic model,SIAM1, which is built&#13;
around a social accounting matrix (SAM). Given this accounting framework, the&#13;
1/  A structure is defined here as the set of values taken by the technological&#13;
and behavioral parameters governing the eocnomy. Thus, the values taken by&#13;
the input-output coefficients, by the marginal propensities to spend, by the&#13;
different import and export elasticities define the structure of the economy.&#13;
Consequently a change in these parameters is considered to be a structurax&#13;
change.&#13;
'I  This leads naturally to the question of the policy measures which would induce&#13;
these structural znanges.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4&#13;
model traces the flows of incomes from activities to factors of production,&#13;
from these to institutions, and from institutions back to activities.&#13;
The paper is divided into two parts. In Section II the tools: the&#13;
SAM and the model, are presented. In Section III an analysis of the outcome&#13;
of present trends is given, then a set of possible policy measures is defined&#13;
and their implications drawn. Finally, calculations of the direction and&#13;
magnitude of impact of selected marginal changes in exogenous variables, policy&#13;
and structural parameters are presented. Some conclusions follow.&#13;
II. The Tools of Analysis&#13;
SIAM1 is a macro-model built to analyze the performance of the Thai&#13;
economy in the medium run. It takes into account two main features: (1) a&#13;
small open economy (2) still dominated by agriculture.&#13;
Given these features and the emerging problems facing the Thai economy,&#13;
the model is designed mainly to address the following questions:&#13;
(1)  What would be the impact of trends in world prices on the&#13;
performance of exports, on imports and on the current account&#13;
deficit?&#13;
(2)  What would be the outcome of specific fiscal and trade policies&#13;
on the balance of payments and on the public sector savings gap?&#13;
(3) What are the impacts of different investment programs on the&#13;
current account deficit and on the rates of growth of the&#13;
economy?&#13;
(4) How does the performance of the agricultural sector spill over&#13;
on the rest oi the economy?&#13;
To address the above questions without entering into too many details,&#13;
SIAMl is kept at a fairly aggregated level. It assumes an economy with one factor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5&#13;
of production, three institutions, four activities, three commodities and the&#13;
rest of the world. Institutions--households, companies and government--have&#13;
separate current accounts. TRheir capital accounts are, however, consolidated&#13;
into one account. The four activities are agriculture, manufacturing, energy&#13;
and services, which produce domestic goods. These are either mixed with imports,&#13;
resulting in a composite good traded on the domestic market, or they are exported.&#13;
No exports of energy are assumed to take place. The rest of the world accounts&#13;
for international trade and financial transfers.&#13;
In the rest of this section we present first, the SAM and the accounting&#13;
framework of the model economy; second, we describe the economics of the model;&#13;
and third, its relations are presented.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6&#13;
A. The Social Accounting Matrix&#13;
The accounting of a model economy is best understood with the use&#13;
of a social accounting matrix.-/ First, a SAM gives a clear and synthetic&#13;
picture of the flows in the economy at a point in time. Second, it gives&#13;
a consistent accounting framework basic to any modeling effort. Table 1&#13;
shows a SAM for the Thai aconomy in the year 1975, consistent with the sim-&#13;
plified description of the economy outlined above.&#13;
Table 1, like any SAM, is such that a figure in a cell is a payment&#13;
from the column to the rolw account. For example, the intersection of column 4&#13;
and row 5 is a payment of government to the consolidated capital account and&#13;
is thus government savings (6,877 million bahts). Another feature of accoun-&#13;
ting, also intrinsic to SAMs,is that all accounts must balance, hence each&#13;
row sum has to be equal to the corresponding column sum. For example, the&#13;
sum of row 2 gives total receipt of households and the sum of column 2 is the&#13;
split of this receipt onto different items.&#13;
In rows/columns 6 to 21, the SAM gives the production activities&#13;
(rows/columns 6 to 9) and the commodities (rows/columns 10 to 21). The sum&#13;
of column 6 is the total cost of the agricultural sector which is equal to its&#13;
total production given as the sum of row 6. This total production (148,625)&#13;
is either delivered to the domestic market (118,900) or exported (29,725). The&#13;
deliveries to the domestic market are then combined with imports of agricul-&#13;
tural product (1,495), to which are added indirect taxes (852), forming the&#13;
total supply of the composite agricultural good on the domestic market (121,247).&#13;
1/ For a detailed account of the SAM approach, see Pyatt, Roe and associates&#13;
(1977), Social Accounting for Development Planning, with Special Reference&#13;
to Sri Lanka, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1&#13;
A SOCIAI, ACCOUNTING MArRIX OF TIIE TI AJ ECiINOMY 1975&#13;
(in lNillloes nf loA,t)&#13;
_~~                   ~       ~~~ ~                                                                                  ~       ~~~~~~~ _use it- Otg   liea                                           _            _ &#13;
instituttolonf_&#13;
Current Acco nt           C-nsolidated             Production Activities                    Agriculture               Ma-ufacturing                    Bnergy                      S-reR-es&#13;
F-ctno-   lsuss-  conpsniun  Gv  ern-       Aepitl       Aurc     1  rt- n    Energy  Servieea  Comps-  rnporto  iapsttD  Comps-  Expor. Ispets    _p-  ur                            r     Coops-  E-pore   Inports .    dire    o  the    T5r&#13;
Asid.                 mon--I-t   Accoun t        Cus      Itories                           sits                         sIte                          it.                          ite                         Ta         nId&#13;
1       2          3          4                          65  _        7         8     _9            10      t1         12       I3       14        i5         16       17       If        19       20        21         22         23       2&#13;
F.otorn              1                                                            93,628      54,292      6.5f6   1l3,191                                                                                                                                    -219   267,478&#13;
no.unni ds     2 239,124                 1,472       ?10                                                                                                                                                                                               i,323   242,129&#13;
t  u o   Cerp-nita      3  25,852      i,972               1,452                                                                                                                                                                                                         31,276&#13;
a       O 2  Government    4   2,502    3,639    3,629                                                                                                                                                                                             31,119        647    41,536&#13;
Capi t    iAced n                  37,815   26,175      6,877                                                                                                                                                                                              12,253    83,120&#13;
AygricItu.re    6                                                                                                      118,900 29,725                                                                                                                          148,625&#13;
M ... a.tn-ino                                                                                                                                     168,289   13,668                                                                                            181.727&#13;
Pvargy         9                                                                                                                                                                27.895                                                                           272995&#13;
9                                                                                                                                                                                            1 Energy   d  27,895174, 345 11,516               185,861&#13;
i_   Composite     10        70,783                            18,?54       11,875      22,105      -O-        6,230                                                                                                                                           121,247&#13;
1   Egpor-t       11                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     31,59      31,359&#13;
isportt       12                                                                                                         1,495                                                                                                                                    1,495&#13;
Csepesite     13             70,6001               2,720       70,296       13,149      67,751        648     12,749                                                                                                                                           2537 912&#13;
l1,putt       14                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      14,139    14,139&#13;
IsPsnret      15                                                                                                                                    57,551                                                                                                       57,551&#13;
8      Coonpocite    16               6,416                  831        2,570        3,227       6,541    16,812       6,255                                                                                                                                            42,652&#13;
E. YpOrt-         17                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         -O-      -O-&#13;
146445                                                                         14,445&#13;
a    C-rp-ait.    19               50,715               27,412                    26,746      31,268    3,849    47,436                                                                                                       -O-                                    187.427&#13;
11,516    11,516&#13;
Tapoeta       21                                                                                                                                                                                                5,574 65,574&#13;
indirect loses    22                                                                                                             852   1,634        394| 12,072 |     471   7,502        312      -0-       374      7,508   -0-       -O-                            31,119&#13;
Ret  f World        23                189                    34                                  _                                       _        1,101                     50,049                       14,0711                       5,574  1                       71,018&#13;
ota 'l        264 267,478  242,129   31,276    41,536          83,820      248,625    182 957    27,895   180,861  12             1,359    l.495 237,912   146.139   7,551   42,652          -O-  16,445 187,427 11,516    5,574    3 ยง I       19 |71 018&#13;
Note: Investment figures include the statistical discrepancy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
In turn, this sum of column 10 is equal to the sum of row 10 which is the&#13;
aggregate demand for the composite agricultural good. The other activities&#13;
and commodities are organized similarly except that no account is taken of&#13;
energy exports.&#13;
In row/column 2.2 indirect taxes are accounted for. In row 22/&#13;
coluvn 10 to 21, the different sources of indirect taxes are given. They&#13;
are levied either on domestically traded goods, or on internationally traded&#13;
goods. In the latter case they are tariffs on imports or taxes on exports.&#13;
Finally, row 23 gives flows out of the country in the form of trans-&#13;
fers (columns 2 and 4), or imports (columns 12, 15, 18, 21). In column 23&#13;
accounts for flows from abroad into the country. They are, in row 1 net factor&#13;
income;-/in rows 2 and 4, the transfers to households and government respec-&#13;
tively; and in rows 11, 14 and 20, exports. The figure in row 5/column 23 is&#13;
the current account deficit which is also equal to the savings gap.&#13;
B. Economics of the Model&#13;
Given the accounting framework defined above, a full model is obtained&#13;
by specifying agents' behavior and market adjustments. This is done here.&#13;
Generally, a model can rely on either behavioral assumptions or on accounting-&#13;
type relations. SIAM1, in. fact, has very few behavioral assumptions built&#13;
into it.&#13;
Households, companies and government are assumed to allocate their&#13;
total receipts on their different outlays according to some utility maximiza-&#13;
tion- /assuming unchanged relative prices.  Thus, Engel-curve-type relations&#13;
1/ The factor income balance is in deficit while net factor income is actually&#13;
a flow out of the country. It is therefore entered with a negative sign.&#13;
2/ For companies and government this is more a convenient allocation rule than&#13;
a truly behavioral assumption.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9&#13;
ar'e used to allocate total receipts of each of these institutions' current account.&#13;
Given these total receipts, the postulated assumptions allow the determination of&#13;
transfers between institutions, savings and government and private consumption.&#13;
Firms are assumed to determine intermediate demands through input-output&#13;
coefficients. Given firms' intermediate demands, household and government con-&#13;
sumption, and exogenously given investment, total aggregate demands are thus deter-&#13;
mined. These demands are for conposites composed of both imports amd domestically&#13;
produced goods.&#13;
Given aggregate demands for the composite goods, the question is then&#13;
the determination of their composition between imports and domestically produced&#13;
goods. The assumption introduced here is that given a level of aggregate demand&#13;
for a composite good, the share of imports to domestically produced goods is&#13;
obtained through cost minimization.-/&#13;
Agricultural exports are assumed to be the excess of agricultural pro-&#13;
duction over the domestic demand for the domestic agricultural products. Exports&#13;
of manufactures and services are assumed to be sensitive to the ratio of the world&#13;
price of exports to the supply price of the Thai exports. These aLre, in fact,&#13;
demand functions of the rest of the world for Thai manufactures and services.&#13;
We now turn to the assumptions on market adjustments. First, factor&#13;
markets are not modeled. Net prices or value-added coefficients in current prices&#13;
in manufacturing, energy, and services are assumed exogenous. On the product&#13;
markets production is demand-determined for the sectors mentioned above. Agri-&#13;
cultural production is assumed exogenous and, for this sector, the model is&#13;
supply-determined. However, the agricultural net price is assumed endogenous.&#13;
1/ This is again a convenient allocation rule and not a behavioral assumption.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10&#13;
SIAM1 is a fixed-price model. Given import prices, tariffs and&#13;
net prices in manufacturing, energy and services, domestic prices and prices&#13;
of the composite goods are determined on a cost basis. The fixity of prices&#13;
does not mean they are constant. It simply means they do not react to excess&#13;
demand, they are purely cost-determined.&#13;
Once the composite goods prices and domestic prices are determined,&#13;
they jointly determine the net price of agriculture.  The domestic prices of&#13;
manufactures and services, with export taxes,  give   the supply price of&#13;
exports of manufactures and services. Subsequently, the ratio of the world&#13;
price to the corresponding Thai supply price determines exports for manufactures&#13;
and services.&#13;
At this stage, prices, investment, exports of manufactures and services&#13;
and agricultural production are given. The rest of the model is then a quasi-&#13;
standard multisectoral Keynesian model. All the remaining variables are deter-&#13;
mined simultaneously in order to find the level of activity which equalizes&#13;
injections and leakages.&#13;
The main features distinguishing STAM1 from a standard Keynesian&#13;
model are the way agriculture is treated and the way imports are modeled.&#13;
As mentioned, agriculture is the only supply-determined sector,&#13;
hence it contradicts the usual assumption of demand driven production.&#13;
Thus,   agricultural exports are not true injections since they do not con-&#13;
tribute to increase aggregate demand and do not increase levels of activity.&#13;
They simply adjust to equalize supply and demand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
11&#13;
The main difference on the import side- /is that these are not consi-&#13;
dered to be purely competitive. Rather they are more or less substitutable to&#13;
domestic supply according to whether an elasticity of substitution is close to&#13;
infinity or to zero. Furthermore, this specification allows the existence of&#13;
a wedge between world and domestic prices for traded goods. The resulting rela-&#13;
tive autonomy of movements of domestic prices vis-a-vis world prices. This is&#13;
dependent, however, on the value of the elasticity of substitution.&#13;
To summarize, SIAM1 could be described as a quasi-orthodox, standard&#13;
Keynesian model. It is thus a fixed-price demand model. It assumes, however,&#13;
a supply-determined agriculture and imports which are neither pure complements&#13;
or purely competitive.&#13;
C.  Relations of SIAM1&#13;
The above points give a general feeling of the model and of its&#13;
working. In the following a description of the variables and the relations&#13;
is given. All variables with a bar are exogenous variables, and t is the&#13;
time subscript.&#13;
Let PD.t, i=1,2,3,4 be the prices of domestic goods; Vjt, j=1,2,3,4&#13;
are the net prices with Vit endogenous and the others exogenous; Pit, i=1,2,3,4&#13;
are the prices of the composite goods; with ai., i,j=1,2,3,4 denoting the intput-&#13;
output coefficients, the prices of domestic goods are given by&#13;
1/ For an account of this approach, see DeMelo and Robinson (1978), "Tradability&#13;
in Trade Tneory," World Bank; and Dervis, DeMelo -and Robinson  Planning&#13;
)Models ari'a &gt;elopmnet Polica, Chapter 7, (forthc,Dming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12&#13;
4&#13;
PDt   Vt +         il  it&#13;
4                                           (1)&#13;
PD.  =V.  +       -oij. P,t    j=34&#13;
j2 it   i-l&#13;
Let Trit,  i=1,2,3,4 be the rates of indirect taxation on domestic&#13;
goods traded domestically, hence the market prices of these goods PDit,&#13;
i=1,2,3,4 are given by&#13;
it   PDit (1 + Tit),   i=1,2,3,4                         (2)&#13;
Landed prices of imports denoted by PMit,  i=1,2,3,4 are obtained via&#13;
-M&#13;
world prices s it, i=1,2,3,4 and         tariff rates Tmit I i=1,2,3,4&#13;
=-m&#13;
Pmit   (1 + TM it  ritn   i=1,2,3,4                         (3)&#13;
This specification assumes that the supply of imports is perfectly elastic at&#13;
the given prices.&#13;
The prices of the composite goods, Pit , i=1,2,3,4 are obtained&#13;
using the cost function of the cost minimization rule used to allocate aggregrate&#13;
demand between imports and domestic goods.-I  Assuming a constant elasticity of&#13;
substitution (CES) aggregation of imports and domestic goods, the specification&#13;
of the cost function is&#13;
1  Ifai   (1-a )          ai 0nr  (l-;i)|&#13;
1/t       1.  PMit  i  + (-lao      PD.it                    i=1,2,3,4    (4)&#13;
Yi &#13;
1/ See relations (15) and (16).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13&#13;
where 5i is a distribution parameter, yi is a scale parameter and ai is the&#13;
elasticity of substitution. A a i close to zero means that there is not much&#13;
scope for substitution between imports and domestic goods regardless of their&#13;
relative prices. This is a case close to purely complementary imports.&#13;
When ai goes to infinity imports and domestic goods become pure substitutes&#13;
and their ratio is highly sensitive to their relative prices.&#13;
In SIAM1, the domestic price of agricultural goods PD.it   is deter-&#13;
mined by the exogenous world price of exports of these goods, with anl allowance&#13;
for export taxes. However, because of lack of market information, it is assumed&#13;
that the current domestic price of agriculture PDit adjusts to both the current&#13;
it ~ ~ -&#13;
world price and the world price of last period.  Hence, with i t , the world&#13;
price of agricultural exports and TeIt , the export tax on these goods:&#13;
PD   =   f-   +            / r   'et(5&#13;
it   2 ( It +  l(t-1)) / 1+ Tlt)                          5&#13;
This specification assumes that Thai exporters of agricultural goods are price&#13;
takers, so that they bear the burden of any export taxes. One might argue that&#13;
Thailand is a large rice exporter and, hence, can influence its world price.&#13;
However, considering agricultural exports as a whole, the price taking assump-&#13;
tion seems reasonable.l/&#13;
Exports of manufactures and services are assumed to be sensitive to&#13;
relative world and Thai prices.  The former are exogenous and the latter or&#13;
supplier's prices, PD2t and PE4t, respectively, are linked to the ccorresponding&#13;
domestic prices PD2t and PD4t with an allowance for export taxes:&#13;
1/  This seems also to be the relevant assumption in "Thailand:  Towards a&#13;
Development Strategy of Full Participation," IBRD (1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14&#13;
PE2  = (1 + 're2t) PD 2t ,     PE4t = (1 + Te4t) PD 4t               (6)&#13;
where Te2t and Te4t are the export tax rates.&#13;
All the preceding relations determine prices without any reference&#13;
to quantities; this is the fix-price nature of the model. However, prices&#13;
intervene in the determination of quantities and incomes. In the following&#13;
the relations determining these variables are described.&#13;
Let Z  be GNP at factor cost. '/  is allocated between the different&#13;
t&#13;
recipients of incomes assuming their shares vary with the level of GNP.&#13;
Let       Rit   compensation of employees,&#13;
R2t   income from unincorporated enterprise,&#13;
Rot   income from property excluding dividends,&#13;
R4t = operating surplus of companies including the provision&#13;
for fixed capital consumption,&#13;
R5t = government income from property and entrepreneurship,&#13;
then&#13;
Rit     ( + Pi '' r/Z t    ,    i=1,2, ...5                          (7)&#13;
-o     -I&#13;
with pi and p. X i=1,2,.,.5 being parameters satisfying&#13;
Epi = I   and       Pi =   .&#13;
i=l                 i=l &#13;
These constraints ensure that the adding up property IR,t = Zt is always fulfilled.&#13;
The allocation of the total of households' resources TRH  2/is treated&#13;
in the same way as above.&#13;
1/ For the determination of Zt, see relation (24).&#13;
2/  For the determination of TRHt, see relation (20).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15&#13;
Let       Ht = interest on consumers' debt,&#13;
H2t = personal taxes and other current transfers to government,&#13;
H3t   households' savings,&#13;
H4t = consumption of the agriculture composite good,&#13;
H5t   consumption of manufactures,&#13;
H6t = consumption of energy,&#13;
H7t   consumption of services,&#13;
H   = current transfers to the rest of the world,&#13;
8t&#13;
then the allocation relations are&#13;
Hat = (hi    + hi e Sh/THt TRH,    i=1,2,...8              (8)&#13;
8&#13;
with,again,JhR  = 1 and jhl = 0 in order to ensure that  E H.t = TRH  always holds.&#13;
The same type of relations are used to allocate the total :income of&#13;
companies-/ TIC&#13;
t&#13;
Let       Cit = dividends,&#13;
C2t = corporate taxes,&#13;
C3t = corporate savings,&#13;
then&#13;
c   =     + C  e c/  ttTICt,    i=l,2,3                               (9)&#13;
with Xc. = 1   and   Ecl = O  so that  Gc = TIC.&#13;
1           ~~~1 it                    t&#13;
Finally, total government revenue,-/GREV  , is allocated again in&#13;
the same way:&#13;
1/  For the determination of TIC   see relation (21).&#13;
2/  For the determination of GREV t, see relation (22).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16&#13;
Let       Glt   transfers to households,&#13;
G2t   interest on public debt,&#13;
G3t = government savings,&#13;
G4t = government consumption of manufactures,&#13;
G5t = government consumption of energy,&#13;
G6t   government consumption of services,&#13;
G7t =government transfers to the rest of the world,&#13;
then&#13;
Git       +  i e g/GREV tGREVt ,    i=1,2,...7                       (10)&#13;
7  0               71                         7&#13;
with  E gi   1   and    2 gi = 0  ensuring that  I         = GREVt&#13;
t=l                i=l                        i=1&#13;
These allocation rules with the above constraints on the parameters do not&#13;
imply that the government budget is balanced. In fact, GREV is allocated&#13;
between current outlays and savings. Government capital expenditure is not included.&#13;
Thus, depending on the relative value of government savings and government&#13;
investment, there may be either a deficit or a surplus.&#13;
Some comment on the postulated allocation relations is in order here.&#13;
First, it is easily seen 'that the expression between brackets is a budget share&#13;
-o -o&#13;
and that it is dependent on total income (or expenditure). Second, g., ci'&#13;
0      -.0&#13;
h., and p. have the interpretation of budget shares for total expenditures&#13;
1 1&#13;
tending   to zero. Hence, for very low levels of total expenditures the budget&#13;
shares will tend to be very close to the value of these parameters. Third, for&#13;
total expenditures becoming very large, the expressions between brackets will&#13;
tend  towards           0 +      El Ci t  h  + El  and P0 +  -    Hence, these sums can be&#13;
ted  owrd  g   1  1i, i1- i1i    1         1i    2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17&#13;
interpreted as limit budget shares for very high levels of total expenditures.&#13;
-1  -l  -1       -lI&#13;
Implicit to this, is the idea that gi, ci, hi, and Pi, give the maximum pos-&#13;
sible variation of the budget shares.  Fourth, the latter parameters can be&#13;
either positive or negative which allows us to feature declining budget&#13;
shares.  Finally, the parameters 3 indicate-/ the level of total expenditures&#13;
where budget shares are the most sensitive to variations of total expenditures.&#13;
Near that level, they either increase or decrease more steeply, and beyond&#13;
that level they start tapering off.&#13;
Let X t,  j=1,2,3,4 be production in constant prices;  X d   is&#13;
exogenous  agricultural production, and Xdt,  i=2,3,4 are endogenous production levels&#13;
of manufacturing, energy, and services respectively.&#13;
Then the value of the aggregate de-mand for the agricultural composite&#13;
good P tUit, is the sum of households  consumption H4t, investment demand&#13;
Plt a tIt and total intermediate demand  I aljPitXjt, hence&#13;
1                ~~~~~~4d&#13;
it&#13;
lt   Pltt4t    ltlt t   jljl lt it]                   (11)&#13;
where It is total investment demand in constant prices, and elt is the share of&#13;
it which has to be supplied by agriculture. For manufacturing it is&#13;
u2t   P -    5t +G4t +2t 2tit   jl 2j 2t Xt1                    (12)&#13;
where H5t is household consumption of manufactures, G4t is government consumption,&#13;
P   e2It is investment demand, and    a  P   Xd  is intermediate demand.  Similarly,&#13;
1/ There is an inflexion point when total expenditure is equal to f3/2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18&#13;
aggregate demand for the energy composite good is&#13;
3t         H L6 + G5  +            +  4       xi.P             (13)&#13;
3t   PtT   | 6t    5t    3t 3t t   j-l3j 3t it                 (3&#13;
The notations are the same as before, but investment demand here covers only&#13;
changes in stocks. Finally, the aggregate demand for services will be&#13;
Ur=         H   + G   +    O       d Xj                         (14)&#13;
4t ~ -~l 7t +   6t4j jt it&#13;
with obviously no investment demand.&#13;
Note that It is gross investment in constant prices,&#13;
3                                3&#13;
0 e  I  = I  holds, and hence    e&#13;
also, the relation    -itit t      t                      it&#13;
The question which arises at this stage is that of the composition Uof&#13;
these aggregate demands and their relative import intensity.&#13;
The following allocation rule is assumed:  given prices and aggregate demand,&#13;
the import intensity is determined by minimizing costs.-/ The problem is then&#13;
the followingS&#13;
Min (PM.M + PD.D)&#13;
{M,D}&#13;
subject to                            1&#13;
yI5M14  + (I-E)D P   P _ U = O&#13;
where D is domestic goods, M is imports and a CES function is assumed for the&#13;
aggregation of the two. There is in this function a distribution parameter 5,&#13;
1/ See Dervis, DeMelo and Robinson, Chapter 7, (forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
19&#13;
a scale parameter y and a substitution one p. The elasticity of substitution,&#13;
a is defined as l/(l+p).&#13;
The above problem leads to the following allocation relations which&#13;
determine for each vector of prices and each level of aggregate demand the&#13;
amount of imports and domestic demand required:&#13;
D     Y.   (1-6.)  (P./PD.)   U.                              (15)&#13;
it    11             1 1       1&#13;
Mit   Yi    6  (Pi/PMi) i U  ,    i=1,2,3,4                   (16)&#13;
Relation (4) determining the prices of the composite goods is obtained as the&#13;
dual of the cost minimization problem considered here. For this reason the&#13;
parameters used here and there are the same.&#13;
Exports of agricultural products are obtained as the excess of produc-&#13;
tion over domestic demand for the domestic goods&#13;
-d&#13;
E     xd    D                                       (17)&#13;
where the three variables are in constant prices.&#13;
Exports of manufactures and services are assumed to be sensitive to&#13;
the ratio of the world price to the domestic suppliers?price:&#13;
--e&#13;
E   = EB. (rri /PEi )        i=2,4                            (18)&#13;
where weit is the world price (exogenous), ni is a constant elasticilty and&#13;
-e&#13;
EBit is a parameter giving the value of exports where Tit = PE.  . EBit may&#13;
vary with time in order to catch the movements in the world GDP growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20&#13;
As mentioned, production is demand-determined in manufacturing,&#13;
energy and services:&#13;
d&#13;
X   = E   + D       i=2,4&#13;
it    it    it                1(9&#13;
l                 ~~~~~~(19)&#13;
3t  D3t&#13;
These relations equalize supply to demand&#13;
The remaining relations of the model are accounting relations.&#13;
Total households' resources  TRH , are defined as&#13;
3&#13;
t       1Rt   it    lt    1  2t                       (20)&#13;
where F   are current transfers from the rest of the world to households and&#13;
2t&#13;
are exogenous.  This relation states that TRHt is equal to factor incomes paid&#13;
3&#13;
to households  i_Rit, plus dividends C%,, plus transfers from government Git,&#13;
i=&#13;
plus transfers from abroad.&#13;
Total income  of  companies TIC, is obtained as the sum of their gross&#13;
operating surplus R4t' the interest on consumers' debt Hlt and the interest on&#13;
public debt G2t&#13;
TICt = R4t + Ht +G2t                                     (21)&#13;
Government receives a factor income R5t (which is government income&#13;
from property and entrepreneurship), direct taxes from households H2t' corporate&#13;
taxes C2t, net indirect taxes NIT  and transfers from abroad F4t.  Total govern-&#13;
ment revenue is thus&#13;
t   R5t + H2t + C2t + NITt +  4t                     (22)&#13;
F4t is exogenous.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21&#13;
Net indirect taxes are given as the sum of taxes on domestic goods&#13;
4                                  3&#13;
Tit PDitDit, duties on imports  E T-it TritM.t, and taxes on exports&#13;
2&#13;
t PDt,e,tE it, thus&#13;
4                3                2&#13;
NIT       T1tPDttDt +  J-tm. Irm N   +    PD  Te.E              (23)&#13;
t ilit  it it   ilit it it   ilit  it it                 (3&#13;
i=l               i=1      itiPD .&#13;
GNP at current factor cost Zt, is obtained as the sum of value added&#13;
at factor cost in the four sectors and the net factor income from abroad Fit:&#13;
t   vlt    + lt    i2 itlt    lt                    (24)&#13;
another obvious feature of the model is that the sum of leakages must&#13;
be equal to that of injection at an equilibrium level of activity. The economy&#13;
considered being an open economy, this can be put another way: equilibrium&#13;
implies that the "savings gap" is equal to the current account defic:it. This&#13;
is indeed the case here where the preceding relations imply&#13;
SG  = TG&#13;
where SGt is the savings gap defined as&#13;
3&#13;
S   i-l it it it   (H3t + G3t + c3t)                       (25)&#13;
and TGt. the current account deficit:&#13;
4             f,M- 7e&#13;
TGt =      + G 7t +     r tmit              Fi  + -riEi  + PE 2E2  + Pi,Ft        (26)&#13;
(H8~~  +  I=1             i=l,3,4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22&#13;
Gross national savings-fare equal to the sum of households savings H3tI government&#13;
savings G3t and savings of corporations C 3t. Finally, H8t are transfers&#13;
from households to the rest of the world and G7t are transfers from govern-&#13;
ment to the rest of the world.&#13;
1/ Gross domestic savings (GDS) are defined as gross national savings (GNS)&#13;
plus public and private transfers to abroad minus the sum of net factor income&#13;
and public and private transfers from abroad:  GNS = H   + G   + C   and&#13;
GDS = GNS + H8t +G7t -Fit -F   -F                       3t    3t    3t&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
23&#13;
III. Simulation Experiments with SIAMI&#13;
This section describes some simulation experiments with the SIAM1&#13;
model. In evaluating those, it should be emphasized that they are outcomes of&#13;
simulations and not forecasts of the future development of the Thai economy.&#13;
In this context, it is important to keep in mind the limitations of the model&#13;
in its present form.&#13;
One of the major limitations is the assumed exogeneity of investment&#13;
in constant prices. This assumption has been made for lack of an acceptable&#13;
framework to endogenize investment at the present stage. The implic;ation is&#13;
that the investment-savings balance cannot be affected through endogienous&#13;
changes in investment. Other features of the SIAMI model are the fix-price&#13;
assumption, the absence of factor markets and of money.&#13;
In stressing these limitations, two points are in order. First&#13;
there is no, and there cannot be in the foreseeable future, a general multi-&#13;
purpose economy-wide model. Hence, one has to select a few questions and&#13;
devise a model which may give some insights on them, having some crude, but&#13;
hopefully as neutral as possible, assumptions on what is left outside the&#13;
model. This was the stand taken when starting the SIAM1 model which as a&#13;
macroeconomic tool is primarily designed to shed light on the foreign trade&#13;
side2 and on resource mobilization. The second point to make, which is corol-&#13;
lary of the first one, is that the questions addressed in SIAM1 are not the&#13;
only ones the Thai economy is facing. Shifting the attention to other ques-&#13;
tions like employment, income distribution, and industrial structure, there is&#13;
1. By fix-price is meant the nonresponsiveness of prices to excess demand;&#13;
prices are cost determined.&#13;
2. The simulated effects on foreign trade are conditional on the assumption&#13;
about the behavior of investment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24&#13;
a need to complement, extend or change the SIAM1 model. This would also mean&#13;
providing some treatment to endogenize investment, introduce capacity limita-&#13;
tion, determine net prices, and according to the problem at hand, bring money&#13;
or other aspects in the model.&#13;
Apart from the modeling aspects, there is the implementation ques-&#13;
tion which involves the quantification of parameters, the choice of a base&#13;
year, the calibration of the model, and the assumptions on future paths of&#13;
exogenous variables. This is always a difficult matter. However, it should&#13;
be noted that, at the time the simulations presented here were produced, the&#13;
model did not track well the high growth rates of the economy in the late&#13;
1970s. This implies that while the simulation results reported in the follow-&#13;
ing can be compared to each other, comparisons between simulated growth rates,&#13;
etc., in the future with actual rates in the past have to be made with great&#13;
caution.&#13;
Given these caveats and the type of framework presently available,&#13;
we now ask whether the Thai economy can maintain its high rate of growth given&#13;
the present disequilibrium, higher oil prices and the exhaustion of new agri-&#13;
cultural land. The question is whether given the present structure of the&#13;
economy, high rates of growth will generate unsustainable domestic and exter-&#13;
nal macroeconomic imbalances.&#13;
The question is treated here by simulating the working of the Thai&#13;
economy with STAM1 over the period 1980-90. This is done by looking at the&#13;
growth performance, savings and investment ratios, and external disequili-&#13;
brium, as well as government finances. These macroeconomic aspects are consi-&#13;
dered under two alternative assumptions. Under the first, it is assumed that&#13;
present trends in policy variables, and exogenous domestic and world variables&#13;
will remain the same or what they are expected to be. Under the second alter-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25&#13;
native, it is assumed that the government will implement fiscal and trade&#13;
policy measures in order to correct the present disequilibrium. However, in&#13;
both cases, the trends in world prices are assumed to be the same and no&#13;
structural change takes place. This last assumption of no structural change&#13;
is rather restrictive and furthermore, in an uncertain world, future world&#13;
prices may well be different. Therefore, one would like to know how changes&#13;
in world variables1 and structural parameters would modify the macroeconomic&#13;
picture of the economy derived in the simulation experiments considered. Some&#13;
indication of the amount and direction of these modifications is gained by&#13;
looking at the elasticities of relevant endogenous variables with respect to&#13;
exogenous variables as well as with respect to the parameters.&#13;
In this section, we first define the two simulation experiments and&#13;
discuss the outcomes. Next, we describe the derivation of the elasticities of&#13;
endogenous variables with respect to parameters and to exogenous variables.&#13;
Then we present how, in one of the simulations, changes in these can modify&#13;
the derived path of the economy.&#13;
A. "Laisser-aller" versus Policy Intervention&#13;
The "laisser-aller"2 case is taken to be the reference simulation.&#13;
A complete description of its underlying assumptions is given in Appendix 2.&#13;
Basically, it is assumed that gross investment3 in constant prices grows&#13;
exponentially at 5% a year and that gross agricultural production grows at&#13;
4.5% a year. During the first half of the seventies, gross capital formation&#13;
1. Changes relative to basic predictions.&#13;
2. By "laisser-aller" we do not mean "laisser-faire."&#13;
3. Including the statistical discrepancy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26&#13;
in constant 1962 prices actually grew at slightly more than 5% a year, while&#13;
between 1975 and 1979, and in constant 1972 prices, this rate almost reached&#13;
12%. Given the present imbalances, higher energy costs and a less buoyant&#13;
world economy, we have arbitrarily assumed' a growth rate of 5%. This assump-&#13;
tion is contrary to what one would expect according to the accelerator prin-&#13;
ciple. Indeed, in this latter case a lower growth rate of the economy would&#13;
be associated with a lower level of investment. However, if one believes that&#13;
investment is purely autonomous, there would be no reason to expect a decrease&#13;
in its rate of growth. In assuming a growth rate of 5% we somehow stand in&#13;
between the two positions of purely autonomous or purely induced investment.&#13;
According to the index of agriculture production given by the Bank of Thai-&#13;
land,2 the rate of growth of gross agricultural production was 5.3% between&#13;
1970 and 1979, and 4.8% between 1975 and 1979. Given the exhaustion of new&#13;
agricultural land, the assumed rate of 4.5% is in line with expected trends.&#13;
Tables A2.2 and A2.3 in Appendix 2 give the assumed indirect tax&#13;
rates and pattern of government outlays in the reference simulation. It&#13;
amounts to maintaining indirect tax rates at their 1979 value except for&#13;
energy where the rate of duties on imports and the rate of indirect taxation&#13;
on domestic demand are assumed to drop in 1979 and 1980 and go back up to 1978&#13;
values by 1984. This is to take account of the lags in passing on increases&#13;
in oil prices. The shares of government outlays on the different items are&#13;
assumed to follow the trend3 of the period 1960-79, which means a rapidly&#13;
declining share of savings and a high and increasing share of expenditure on&#13;
1. This implies a gradual reduction in the investment/GDP ratio.&#13;
2. Statistical Bulletin, Dec. 1979.&#13;
3. The trend mentioned here is not a time trend," rather the variation in&#13;
shares resulting from variations in government revenue.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27&#13;
services. For convenience, this reference simulation will be referred to&#13;
below as LA ("laisser-aller").&#13;
In the second simulation, government is assumed to implement fiscal&#13;
and trade policy measures, aimed at (a) increasing its revenue through indi-&#13;
rect taxation, (b) discouraging energy imports and consumption through higher&#13;
prices, (c) encouraging exports through reductions in taxes on exports, and&#13;
(d) correcting the imbalance in the government savings gap by increasing the&#13;
share of savings in its total current outlays. More specifically, it is&#13;
assumed that indirect tax rates on domestic demand for domestic goods and&#13;
services increase at 4% per annum, except for energy where the increase is&#13;
6%. This is also the assumed growth rate for the rates of duty on iimports of&#13;
energy, otherwise the rates of duty on imports remain the same as for 1979.&#13;
Furthermore, the rate of duty on imports of energy and the indirect tax rate&#13;
on domestic demand of domestic energy are not assumed to drop in 1979-80 and&#13;
catch up later; in 1979 they remain at 1978 values and increase afterwards at&#13;
the 6% rate mentioned above. Tax rates on exports are assumed to decrease at&#13;
an annual rate of 6%. The pattern of government outlays is also assumed to&#13;
change. Instead of having a lower share of savings with higher government&#13;
revenues, this share is assumed to increase, the shares of all other items&#13;
except the "interest on public debt" decreasing. Apart from the above mea-&#13;
sures, it is also assumed that agricultural production will be able to grow at&#13;
5% instead of the 4.5% of the reference simulation. Another assumption is that&#13;
the world demand for Thai exports of manufactures and services will be pushed&#13;
up by the expansion of world GDP more than in LA. This is expressed by having&#13;
the parameters EB2 and EB4 of relations 18 grow at 15% and 14% respectively,&#13;
instead of 13%. With these last two assumptions, one would expect a higher&#13;
rate of growth of investment. However because of higher taxes, there would&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28&#13;
also be some disincentive to invest. Therefore it was assumed that the growth&#13;
rate of gross investment, in constant prices, remains the same as in LA,&#13;
namely 5%. Again for convenience, this second simulation will be referred to&#13;
in the following as PI (policy intervention).&#13;
We now turn to the macroeconomic picture generated by the two simu-&#13;
lations. With GDP at constant market prices as an indicator of growth, the&#13;
economy grows between 1980 and 1990 at an average rate of 6.7% per annum under&#13;
the assumptions of LA and of 7.1% per annum under PI. Per capita these per-&#13;
centages are 4.5 and 4.9 respectively. As indicated on page 2 above, these&#13;
growth rates can only wit:h great caution be compared to those of the past, but&#13;
probably they do imply a slowdown in the rate of growth of the economy, at&#13;
least in the early eighties. As between LA and PI, the growth performance can&#13;
be compared; the higher rates obtained under PI being due to the assumptions&#13;
of a higher rate of growth of agricultural production, of a more buoyant world&#13;
demand for Thai manufactures, and, of lower export taxes leading to more&#13;
competitive Thai exports of manufactures. These assumptions on exports and&#13;
agriculture appear to be more important than the conservative measures of&#13;
higher domestic taxation, higher tariffs on imports of energy and lower&#13;
government spending.&#13;
The differences between the two simulations with regard to the&#13;
savings and investment ratios are indicated in Table 2. As indicated before,&#13;
the assumption on the ratio of growth of real investment is arbitrary, and is&#13;
the same in the two alternatives. The difference between the two investment&#13;
ratios is therefore mainly due to the higher GDP growth rate under PI. With&#13;
regard to savings, domestic savings are higher than national savings, which&#13;
means that the balance of transfers and factor-income services with the rest&#13;
of the world is in deficit. As pointed out in the introduction, this is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
29&#13;
mainly due to the increasingly negative balance of investment income. The&#13;
different pattern of government outlays between LA and PI results in a higher&#13;
share of government savings in PI. This change in government behavior&#13;
explains also the higher savings generated in PI. With regard to movements in&#13;
the savings-investment balance, it is tempting to draw conclusions from Table&#13;
2, but they would be conditional on the assumed rate for investment growth and&#13;
it is preferable not to elaborate on this point.&#13;
Looking at foreign trade (Table 3), and keeping in mind the depen-&#13;
dence of imports on investment through aggregate demand , the general trend is&#13;
a high but decreasing rate of growth of exports and a lower but increasing&#13;
rate of growth of imports. In PI, both these rates are higher than in LA. On&#13;
the export side, manufactures and services continue to perform well, but this&#13;
is mainly due to the assumption on world demand through the parameters EB2 and&#13;
EB4 of relations 18. Agricultural exports are still growing in constant&#13;
prices between 1981 and 1984, but they decrease between 1984 and 1987 in LA&#13;
and in 1987-90 in PI. The difference between the two simulations is due to&#13;
the higher growth of agricultural production in PI. Agricultural exports are&#13;
determind residually in SIAM1, as the excess of agricultural production over&#13;
domestic agricultural demand. Higher rates of growth of the sectors other&#13;
than agriculture lead to a growth of intermediate demand for agricultural&#13;
goods higher than that of production. This results naturally, after a while,&#13;
in having a smaller surplus available for exports, hence decreasing rates of&#13;
agricultural exports.  On the import side,l imports of manufactures and ser-&#13;
1. Total sectoral domestic aggregate demands are allocated bet een demand for&#13;
imports and demand for domestically-produced goods. This procedure assumes a&#13;
relative stability in the composition of final demand and in the import&#13;
intensity of each component.  Tnvestment having a higher import content tha7i&#13;
cfhe other comonln-s, the import imp icaricns of large variationc in the share&#13;
o` investment will not be adequate&gt;,z -zimulaced,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30&#13;
vices increase faster than other imports. They are, like agricultural&#13;
imports, higher in PI than in LA, because of the higher rate of growth of the&#13;
economy in PI. Imports of energy after slowing down between 1981 and 1987,&#13;
accelerate again after 1987. The slowdown is partially due to the coming on&#13;
stream of gas2 from the Gulf of Thailand by 1982. Although the economy grows&#13;
faster in PI than in LA, the rate of growth of imports of energy in 1987-1990&#13;
is lower in PI, due to the increases in duties on imports of energy and the&#13;
rate of domestic indirect taxes on energy.&#13;
Table 4 shows how the trade balance looks in LA and PI for 1981,&#13;
1984, 1987 and 1990 and gives information on the current account deficit and&#13;
the terms of trade. On the average for the whole decaade these deteriorate&#13;
slightly, but they are essentially stable.3 The trade balance improves faster&#13;
than the current account deficit, again due to the deficit of the factor-&#13;
income balance. Another aspect worth noting is that although agricultural&#13;
exports in constant prices decrease their current price value still increases&#13;
until 1990, pointing to the fact that the rate of increase in world agricultu-&#13;
ral prices still more than compensates for the drop in quantities.&#13;
As can be expected from the assumptions underlying the two simula-&#13;
tions, the share of government revenue in GDP is higher and increases faster&#13;
in PI than in LA (see Table 5). The increase in LA is due to the fact that&#13;
the fastest growing sectors, manufacturing and services, are also relatively&#13;
the most heavily taxed. In PI, the higher rates of taxation and rate of&#13;
1. The implied average elasticity of imports with respect to GDP is .87 in LA&#13;
and .96 in PI.&#13;
2. This is taken into acount by modifying the share parameter of the demand&#13;
relation for imports (relations 16).&#13;
3. In comparison to the drop between 1975 and 1978 where they moved from 100&#13;
to 87.83.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
31&#13;
growth of the economy accentuates the increase in the share of government&#13;
revenue. The increase in the share of government revenue leads to a higher&#13;
share of government expenditure, but this is associated with a decreasing&#13;
share of government savings in LA and an increasing share in PI. This is due&#13;
to the assumption introduced in PI of a share of government savings in govern-&#13;
ment revenue increasing with the latter. These trends in the revenue, savings&#13;
and curent expenditure shares lead to a decreasing share of the public sector&#13;
savings gap in GDP in PI, whereas it increases in LA. Finally, in Table 5 the&#13;
structure of government revenues and expenditures are given. On the revenue&#13;
side, the predominance of indirect taxes is without challenge although the&#13;
share of corporate taxes is increasing. On the expenditure side, services are&#13;
naturally the predominant item.&#13;
From both simulations it appears that the macroeconmic disequilibria&#13;
which are presently plaguing the Thai economy can be dramatically reduced&#13;
towards the end of the decade.I  The major difference between the two alterna-&#13;
tives is that the improvement in LA is less pronounced than in PT and it also&#13;
takes place later. Hence one would expect a less sustainable financial situ-&#13;
ation under LA than under PT.&#13;
However, this means that exports of manufactures and services will&#13;
keep growing fast and the rates of growth of imports will be modest. At any&#13;
rate the trade balance will have to bear the bulk of the adjustment in the&#13;
current account deficit as factor payments in the form of investment income&#13;
will continue to grow. A worrying aspect is the acceleration of the rates of&#13;
growth of imports and the deceleration of those of exports towards the end of&#13;
the decade (see Table 4). On the savings side, the behavior of government&#13;
1. This statement is conditional on the assumption on investment behavior.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
32&#13;
savings appears to be a crucial factor in the speed of adjustment. Increasing&#13;
government revenues wou:Ld probably not be sufficient to reduce the public&#13;
sector savings gap share in GDP because of the present declining trend in the&#13;
share of government savings in GDP. Actions to increase this share would help&#13;
in accelerating the process of adjustment.&#13;
Although on these assumptions some improvement in the current&#13;
account situation as well as in the savings-investment balance occur in the&#13;
late 1980s, Thailand will experience severe external and savings-investment&#13;
disequilibria during the first part of the decade. Whether these and the&#13;
associated rates of growth are sustainable depends largely on the availability&#13;
of foreign savings, of the acceptable accumulation of foreign debt and of&#13;
realistic levels for the debt service ratio. The main question is then whe-&#13;
ther Thailand would be able to emerge from the first part of the eighties&#13;
without sacrificing its financial stability.&#13;
At the end of these simulations we would like to stress once more&#13;
that the results presented here are simulation results and not forecasts.&#13;
They represent, within the framework of the model, the likely outcome of the&#13;
assumptions envisaged and they depend on them. To narrow down the model to a&#13;
forecasting tool one would need a less open model and hence a higher degree of&#13;
closure. A particular example in that respect is the determination of invest-&#13;
ment. Presently in SIAM1, investment is exogenous and no feedback is assumed&#13;
to exist from the rest of the model t6 investment. Introducing such feedback&#13;
with an investment demand function would make the model more closed and proba-&#13;
bly more suited for forecasting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
33&#13;
B. Direct and Indirect Effects of Marginal Changes in Exogenous Variables,&#13;
Policy Parametersj and Structural Parameters&#13;
The preceding analysis focusses on the possible adjust-&#13;
ments of the economy given its structure, and some predictions on world prices,&#13;
growth of investment and of agricultural production. It is hard, however,to&#13;
assume that no structural change at all would take place or that exogenous&#13;
variables will be exactly predicted.&#13;
One way to gain some insight on the possible effects of chamges in&#13;
these variables and parameters is to consider how and by how much their marginal&#13;
change can affect the paths derived in the simulations considered Dreviously.&#13;
Any change in these parameters would have direct and indirect effects.&#13;
We first present how elasticities measuring these direct and indirect effects&#13;
are derived and then illustrate their use with a few examples.&#13;
Basically, any non-optimization model could in principle be written as&#13;
a set of n equations in n endogenous variables, yi, m exogenous variables, xi,&#13;
p policy parameters, Ti' and s structural parameters, ai. Let hi( ) be an equation&#13;
of the model, then the whole model is:&#13;
h. (yy2,        n   1',2''''..,X ;T1'T 2... ,T ;al,a c,   a) = O        (27)&#13;
i=1,2,.. .,m.&#13;
Using implicit derivation and assuming a non-singular Jacobian at each solution&#13;
point then one can compute the following elasticities:&#13;
ay.   x,                                  ay.   T.&#13;
ax j                                      a     y    I   i=1,2,...,n; j=1,2,...,p&#13;
and  a *      1     i=1,2 .... In; j=1,2, .... s                             (28)&#13;
~act Y.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
34&#13;
These elasticities measure the direct and indirect effects of a change in the&#13;
exogenous variables, the policy parameters and the structural parameters on&#13;
endogenous parameters. However, these elasticities are not constant.&#13;
We turn now to a. more general specification for these elasticities.&#13;
Let h( ) =    hi( ) II, i=1,2,...,n be the vector of functions in (27) and&#13;
Y =     Yi    X X =    x|i, t =    Ij | and a =    al | the vectors of endo-&#13;
genous and exogenous variables, and, policy and structural parameters respectively.&#13;
Then by implicit derivation&#13;
ah. a    ay   ay )    a      h 9h &#13;
_    :1x  L      + (ah     1l, 1.  &#13;
aylt w   ar' ~'XIrTI a a'+ (cX T     j&#13;
Assuming Dh  the Jacobian matrix, to be non-singular, then&#13;
fa= I'Dy      (ah J-(ah h'Th'h 'h&#13;
(axt I' aT IaaJ =   tyJ    (aFx 'aTt I aa&#13;
It is then straightforward to serive the matrices of elasticities we are&#13;
looking for.&#13;
One may also be interested in the elasticities of derived variables&#13;
with respect to all independent variables and parameters. For example, changes&#13;
may be sought of in theterms of trade, the consumer's price index or any other&#13;
derived variable. Let V = || vi 11, i=1,2,...,d be the vector of these variables,&#13;
their most general specification would be:&#13;
V = F(y(x,T,),X,T ,),&#13;
where F( ) is a vector of order d, of functions and where y(x,T,a) is also a&#13;
vector of functions but of order n. By derivation of the system of functions&#13;
F( ), it is straightforward to derive the elasticities of V with respect to any&#13;
independent variable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
35&#13;
Table 6 presents some selected elasticities, for 1984 and for the&#13;
simulation of PI (policy intervention). The first three columns are elasticities&#13;
with respect to three exogenous variables: the world price of energy (r3), the&#13;
world price of agriculture (1T), and the gross production of agriculture (X1).&#13;
The next four columns are elasticities with respect to the input-output coeffi-&#13;
cients describing the intermediate demand of the different sectors for energy.&#13;
These elasticities measure the impact of marginal structural&#13;
changes. Finally, the last three columns give elasticities with respect to three&#13;
policy parameters, namely the rates of import duties on agricultural goods,&#13;
manufactures and energy.&#13;
An interesting figure in the table is cell (1,1). It measures the&#13;
elasticity of the consumers price index (CPI) with respect to the world price&#13;
of energy (Tr3).  A one percent increase in f3generates a .263% increase in CPI.&#13;
As a rough approximation,-/ a 10% increase in energy prices would add 2.63% to&#13;
the CPI. This is probably a conservative figure as the model does not: produce&#13;
any demand-pull inflation. Columns 2 and 3 show how dependent the economy is&#13;
on agricultural variables. A one percent increase in the world price of agricul-&#13;
tur   improves the trade balance by more than 3.7% (cell (3,2)); likewise, a&#13;
one percent increase in gross agricultural production could improve the trade&#13;
balance by more than 8.4%. These effects work partially through the impacts of&#13;
agricultural production and the world price of agriculture on agricultural exports,&#13;
shown in cells (12,2) and (12,3). Another elasticity worth noting is that of the&#13;
trade balance with respect to the world price of energy. It is negative, meaning&#13;
-M&#13;
that an increase in 13 would improve the trade balance. This works in three ways:&#13;
l/  Because the elasticity measures marginal changes and depends on the level of&#13;
the variables.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
36&#13;
(1) higher energy prices mean less imports of energy (cell (10,1)); (2) it also&#13;
means higher domestic prices and higher costs to the economy which leads to a&#13;
slowing down of aggregate demand and hence of imports; and (3) the slowing down&#13;
of aggregate demand means, in particular, a slowing down in domestic aggregate&#13;
demand for agricultural goods and consequently more agricultural surplus for&#13;
exports, (cell (12,1)).&#13;
Consider now a marginal change in the input-output coefficients of&#13;
intermediate deliveries of the energy sector. Lowering these coefficients&#13;
would induce a significant improvement in the trade balance (row 3/columns 4,5,6,7).&#13;
The predominant impact of lower coefficients is lower demand for imports (rows 8-11/&#13;
columns 4-7) and higher exports of manufactures and services (rows 13-14/columns 4-7).&#13;
The higher exports result from lower domestic prices due to lower energy costs.&#13;
Finally, columns 8-10 show how a marginal change in rates of import&#13;
duties affect the endogenous variables considered. It appears that changes in&#13;
these policy parameters have little influence. However, imports of agricultural&#13;
goods appear to be relatively sensitive to the tariff rate on agricultural imports.-/&#13;
Government revenues and net indirect taxes are also relatively responsive to the&#13;
tariff rate on imports of manufactures. This is partially due to the importance&#13;
of imports of manufactures and the level of the tariff rate (15%). Finally, a&#13;
one percent increase in the rate of duties on imports of manufactures generates&#13;
a .177% increase in government savings. This obviously works through an increase&#13;
in government revenues and the pattern of government outlays.&#13;
1/ The level of the tariff rate on agricultural imports is 35.8%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
IV. Conclusion&#13;
In this paper we have been concerned with the trade-offs between&#13;
macroeconomic imbalances and growth in the context of the Thai economy in the&#13;
1980s. For this purpose a macroeconomic model was built and used to simulate&#13;
two possible paths of the Thai economy.&#13;
The macroeconomic model SIAM1, based on a SAM, was the tool used for&#13;
the analysis. Hence, the model covers the main flows of incomes from activities&#13;
to factors, factors to institutions and back to activities. SIAM1 is mainly a&#13;
Keynesian model which is demand driven in manufacturing, energy and services,&#13;
although agriculture output is given and the agricultural sector is supply&#13;
determined. This is not only a convenient way of modeling the agricultural&#13;
sector, it also allows us to put a global constraint on the supply side of the&#13;
economy, thus checking any unreasonable growth in demand and the economy. In&#13;
fact, high rates of growth are obtained here at the cost of lower agricultural&#13;
exports as well as,more obviously, of more imports.&#13;
A model such as SIAM1 is essentially macroeconomic, but it is also&#13;
semiaggregate as it assumes more than two sectors. Two questions underlie these&#13;
models concerning (1) their closure, whether at the macro or micro level, and&#13;
(2) the speed of adjustments.  SIAM1 is closed at the macroeconomic level by&#13;
assuming that it is investment driven.  It could easily be transformed into a&#13;
savings-driven model if the current account deficit is exogenized and investnent&#13;
is endogenized. But clearly the implications of the closure rule adopted here&#13;
requires further analysis.   This is also the case for the microeconomic closures&#13;
adopted. Product markets are closed by assuming that production adjusts to demand&#13;
and factor markets are dealt with by postulating exogenous net prices and&#13;
1 The analysis of the elasticities in Section III would be a good starting point.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
agricultural prices determined via world prices. These microeconomic closures&#13;
are certainly two directions in which the model could be Improved. Finally,&#13;
all adjustments are assumed to take place in the year; savings adjust to invest-&#13;
ment, proouction to demand and demand to prices in the "elementary" period to&#13;
solve the model, that is, the year. This is clearly a convenient but neverthe-&#13;
less awkward assumption. As a matter of fact, it is not easy to introduce&#13;
different adjustment periods in a model, to know the length of these periods,&#13;
or to identify them. These micro and macroeconomic closures of models, as well&#13;
as the question of adjustment periods, require further analysis in order to&#13;
improve modeling capacity.&#13;
We have yet to reach an ideal applied model. Despite their numerous&#13;
drawbacks, the applied models are useful as long as they provide insight to&#13;
the problems at hand. And as Kornai put it, "We cannot expect our model to give&#13;
final, decisive answers; it can be considered an accomplishment if it only&#13;
inspires interesting thought:s, if it furnishes additional points of view for&#13;
a decision'.' The first simulation reported here assumes that no specific policy&#13;
measures are implemented in order to adjust to the disequilibria; the second&#13;
assumes the implementation of specific fiscal and trade measures. It appears&#13;
that the economy will under both paths gradually correct the disequilibria which&#13;
presently prevail. The main question is how far the imbalances can go without&#13;
endangering the financial stability of Thailand. Indeed under the first simu-&#13;
lation, the resource gap would still be about 5% of GDP by 1984 and would vanish&#13;
by 1990. The current account deficit, however, would remain as high as 6.5% of&#13;
GDP by 1984 and would be reduced to 3.2% by 1990. The public sector savings&#13;
gap on the contrary would gradually increase reaching 6.2% of GDP by 1990. Under&#13;
1. Kornai, J., "Models and Policy: The Dialogue Between Model Builder and&#13;
Planner," in Blitzer, C.R., P.B. Clark and L. Taylor (eds.), Economy-Wide Models&#13;
and Development Planning. Oxford University Press, 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
the second&amp;simulation the resource gap diminishes more rapidly becoming a&#13;
surplus (2% of GDP) by 1990, while the current account deficit vanishes&#13;
towards the end of the decade. The public sector savings gap diminishes&#13;
to 4.5% of GDP by 1985 reaching 3.3% by 1990.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
40&#13;
Table 2&#13;
The Savings and Investment Ratios&#13;
1981         1984         1987    1   1990&#13;
LA  IPI    LA    PI    LA    PI    LA    PI&#13;
Share of  3ross           a       3.9  3353 32.0  31.25 30.40 29.44 28.80 27.83&#13;
Share of national savings        24.20 24.23 24.6  24.75 25.1  25.84 25.6  27.53&#13;
i) share of households       12.56 12.15 12.35 11.82 12.22 11.56 12,16 11.37&#13;
ii) share of corporations    9.17  9.10  9.76  9.66 10.56 10.46 11.61111.44&#13;
iii) share of government        2.47  2.98  2.4   3.27  2.32  3.82  1.83  4.72&#13;
Share of domestic savings        25.50 25.43 27.40 27.35 28.60 28.74 28.9  29.93&#13;
in GDP&#13;
a/ Investment figures include any statistical discrepancy.&#13;
b/ GDP at current market prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
41&#13;
Table 3&#13;
Rates of Growth of Imports and of Exports of Goods and Nonfactor Services&#13;
(at constant prices)&#13;
1981-1984          1984-1987          1987-1990&#13;
LA      PI.        LA       PI        LA       PI&#13;
Exports               10.87   12.38        9.50   10.90       9.36   10.78&#13;
Agriculture          5.56    7.58       -1.67    1.16      -8.52   -2.49&#13;
Manufacturing       13.44   15.12       13.94   15.30      13.46   14.63&#13;
Services            14.11   14.87       14.02   14.62      13.70   14.25&#13;
Imports                5.57    6.53        5.60    6.60       6.38    7.33&#13;
Agriculture          2.80    3.20        5.16    5.47       5.87    6.07&#13;
Manufacturing        5.99    7.04        5.92    7.07       6.50    7.64&#13;
Energy               3.95    4.35        3.92    4.07       5.63    5.52&#13;
Services             5.79    7.06        6.07    7.37       6.93    7.95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4&#13;
Trade Balance and Current Account&#13;
(million bahts)&#13;
1981                      1984                      1987                      1990&#13;
LA          PI            LA           PI           LA           PI           LA           PI&#13;
Exports             146,296.0   149,686.7    252,772.9   269,920.8   402,398.5   448,565.5   629,296.6   734,293.3&#13;
Agriculture        45,666.1    46,619.8      71,773.9    77,565.1    83,983.1    98,750.9    79,950.1   111,562.9&#13;
Manufacturing      56,699.6    58,421.7    101,648.2   109,821.8   178,962.8   201,663.1   308,496.6   361,597.1&#13;
Services           43,930.3    44,645.2      79,350.8    82,532.9   139,452.6   148,151.5   240,849.9   261,133.3&#13;
Imports             201,108.3   205,025.8    297,547.5   310,978.0   428,558.0   459,126.7   627,155.4   686,013.8&#13;
Agriculture         2,464.8     2,100.8       3,616.2      3,116.2      5,100.6      4,434.7      7,242.5      6,332.1&#13;
Manufacturing    131,211.9   133,782.2    192,664.0   202,335.2   275,188.6   298,555.1   394,379.8   441,721.9&#13;
Energy             54,401.8    54,951.4      82,238.6    84,047.4   120,975.6   124,180.2   185,941.1   190,271.7&#13;
Services           13,029.8    14,191.4      19,028.7    21,479.2    27,293.2    31,956.7    39,592.0    47,688.1&#13;
Trade Balancea/      54,812.3    55,339.1      44,774.6    41,057.2    26,159.5    10,561.2    -2,141.2   -48,279.5&#13;
Tr ide Balance as       8.4          8.1           4.6          3.9         1.8            .7         -.1         -2.1&#13;
percentage of GDP-&#13;
Current Account      62,936.4    63,366.5      72,264.7    68,232.3    74,820.8    56,199.7    65,475.5          5,936.3&#13;
Current Account as      9.7          9.3           7.4         6.5          5.3          3.6          3.2            .30&#13;
percentage of GDP&#13;
Terms of Trade-        78.9   j    79.5           79.60  i    80.5         78.90        80.4         77.60        80.1&#13;
a/  Negative signs denote surplus.&#13;
b/ 1975 = 100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
43&#13;
Table 5&#13;
Public Finances&#13;
1981              1984             1987             1990&#13;
LA      PI        LA       PI      LA       PI       LA      PI&#13;
in GDP  o/                     14.9    18.0       15.40   19.21   15.60   20.63   16.00   22.26&#13;
Indirect Taxes (domestic)       7.86   10.23       7.82   11.20    7.78   12.35    7.76   13.63&#13;
Duties on Imports               2.50    3.36       2.64    3.38    2.59    3.43    2.57    3.53&#13;
Taxes on Exports                 .52      .42       .58      .38     .60      .33      .61     .28&#13;
Personal Taxes                  1.38    1.36       1.45    1.38    1.48    1.41    1.52    1.43&#13;
Corporate Taxes                 1.70    1.71       2.01    2.01    2.31    2.31    2.65    2.63&#13;
Government Income from Pro-    .80        .77       .75      .72     .71      .67      .68     .63&#13;
perty and Entrepreneurship&#13;
Transfers from Abroad            .14      .15       .15      .14     .15      .13      .15     .13&#13;
Share of Government Expen-       12.43   15.00    12.91   15.93   13.28   16.80   14.17   17.53&#13;
diture in GDP&#13;
Transfers to Households          .08      .09       .08      .09     .08      .09      .07      .08&#13;
Interest on Public Debt         1.23    1.50       1.30    1.62    1.37    1.81    1.59    2.11&#13;
Manufacturing                     .97    1.18      1.02    1.23    1.04    1.25    1.10    1.20&#13;
Energy                           .30      .36       .32      .38     .32      .37      .36     .34&#13;
Services                        9.84   11.86    10.18   12.60   10.46   13.27   11.03   13.79&#13;
Transfers Abroad                  .01     .01       .01      .01     .01      .01      .01      .01&#13;
Share of Government Savings       2.47    3.00       2.49    3.28    2.32    3.83    1.84    4.73&#13;
in CUP&#13;
Share of Public Investment        8.00    8.00       8.00    8.00    8.00    8.00    8.00    8.00&#13;
in GDP&#13;
Share of Public Sector            5.53    5.00       5.51    4.72    5.68    4.17    6.16    3.27&#13;
Savings Gap in GDP&#13;
a/  GDP is atcurrent market prices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 6&#13;
Selected Elasticities with Respect to Exogenous Variables and Parameters&#13;
1984 PI/Simulation&#13;
(1)       (2)        (3)        (4)        (5)         (6)       (7)          (8)       (9)      (10)&#13;
-M        -e--                                                   ----&#13;
In3        r1        X1         a31        a32         a33         34         Tm         TM2       TM3&#13;
_                                      t                          '3                  _   _  _  _  _   _&#13;
(1) CPI            .262       .040       .002     -.0006       .0008     -.0647   -.0473        -.0002    -.0033   -.0027&#13;
TT            -.14       -.005      -.178      -.0026    -.0102        .0814   -.0092       -.0002      .0080     .0060&#13;
(3) TB            -.708    -3.745    -8.412         .1232      .3246       .2571    .2959       -.0140      .0240   -.0290&#13;
(4) GDPCFC        -.059      -.0330      .334      -.0003      .0011      -.0536    .0009       -.0000    -.0003   -.0023&#13;
(5) TRH           -.071       .297       .258      -.0006      .0008      -.0658    .0007       -.0002    -.0033   -.0027&#13;
(6) GREV           .041       .198       .136       .0039      .0089       .0459    .0082        .0048      .1602     .0214&#13;
(7) NIT            .075       .152       .086       .0052      .0110       .0797    .0101        .0061      .2036     .0280&#13;
(8) M1            -.034       .089       .210      -.0003      .0004      -.0311    .0003       -.1940    -.0020   -.0010&#13;
(9) M2             .003       .013       .008       .0001      .0003       .0029    .0002        .0000    -.0140      .0001&#13;
(10) M3            -.539       .005       .079       .0505      .1402      -.0796    .1274        .0000      .0010   -.0240&#13;
(11) M4             .058       .081       .056       .0024      .0042       .0606    .0039        .0004      .0108    .0036&#13;
(12) E1             .161      2.545      4.754       .0014    -.0019        .1479   -.0015        .0020      .0080    .0060&#13;
(13) E2            -.139      -.026       .000      -.0052    -.0086       -.1440   -.0080       -.0010    -.0470   -.0060&#13;
(14) E4            -.408      -.364      .000       -.0153    -.0252       -.4235   -.0236       -.0015    -.0224   -.0185&#13;
(15) H3            -.074       .308       .267      -.0006      .0009      -.0681    .0007       -.0003    -.0034   -.0029&#13;
(16) C3            -.075       .361       .309      -.0002      .0021      -.0682    .0018        .0003      .0173   -.0003&#13;
(17) G3             .045       .219       .150       .0043      .0099       .0507    .0090        .0052      .1772    .0237&#13;
(18) I              .069       .102       .000       .00258    .0043        .0715    .0040        .0004      .0418    .0031&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
45&#13;
Table 6 (cont'd)&#13;
CPI         Consumers Price Index&#13;
TT          Terms of Trade&#13;
TB          Trade Balance&#13;
GDPCFC      Gross Domestic Product at Constant Factor Cost&#13;
TRH         Total Resources of Households&#13;
GREV        Government Revenue&#13;
NIT         Net Indirect Taxes&#13;
N1          Imports of Agricultural Goods in Constant Prices&#13;
M2          Imports of Manufactures in Constant Prices&#13;
M3          Imports of Energy in Constant Prices&#13;
M4          Imports of Services in Constant Prices&#13;
E1          Exports of Agricultural Goods in Constant Prices&#13;
E2          Exports of Manufactures in Constant Prices&#13;
E4          Exports of Services in Constant Prices&#13;
H3          Households' Savings&#13;
C3          Corporate Savings&#13;
G3          Government Savings&#13;
I           Gross Investment in Current Prices&#13;
-M&#13;
Tr3         World Price of Energy&#13;
-e&#13;
T1          World Price of Agricultural Goods&#13;
XI          Gross Agricultural Production&#13;
*31         Intermediate Delivery of Energy to Agriculture (I-O coefficient)&#13;
a32         Intermediate Delivery of Energy to Manufacturing (I-0  coefficient)&#13;
a33         Intermediate Delivery of Energy to Energy (I-n  coefficient)&#13;
a34         Intermediate Delivery of Energy to Services (I-0  coefficient)&#13;
TM1     :  Tariff Rates on Imports of Agricultural Goods&#13;
Tm2         Tariff Rates on Imports of Manufactures&#13;
Tm3         Tariff Rates on Imports of Energy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
46&#13;
Appendix 1: A Base Year SAM for the SIAMi Model&#13;
1.        The purpose of this note is to give a brief presentation of a&#13;
small Social Accounting Matrix of the Thai economy for the year 1975.&#13;
2.        The distinctive features of this particular SAM are:&#13;
i) it is consistent with the national accounts figures of 1975;&#13;
ii) it distinguishes four activities-/(sectors of production):&#13;
- agriculture,&#13;
- manufacturing,&#13;
- energy,&#13;
- services;&#13;
ii) it distinguishes three commodities for each activity:&#13;
- composite goods and services traded on the domestic market,&#13;
- imported goods,&#13;
- exported goods.&#13;
3.        The three main sources of data used to build the SAM are:&#13;
(1) the national accounts figures for 1975 as revised in the 1979 issue of&#13;
the National Accounts of Thailand;&#13;
2/&#13;
(2) The input-output matrix for 1975 published by NESDBAwhich assumes competitive&#13;
imports and is at purchasers' prices and;&#13;
(3) the statistical bulletin (monthly) of the Bank of Thailand (BOT).&#13;
In the following, the main assumptions used to get a balanced SAM consistent&#13;
with the National Accounts are described.&#13;
1/ Agriculture includes: crops, livestock, forestry and fisheries. Manufac-&#13;
turing includes all manufacturing (mining and quarrying and construction&#13;
included'; it excludes petroleum products. Energy includes petroleum pro-&#13;
ducts and electricity and water supply. Services include wholesale and&#13;
retail trade, transportation and communication, banking, insurance and real&#13;
estate services, public administration and defense.&#13;
2/ NESDB: National Economic and Social Development Board.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
47&#13;
4.      There is only one factor of production which receives the value-&#13;
added created by the four activities (row 1, columns 6, 7, 8 and 9).  This&#13;
is gross value-added at factor cost as it includes depreciation and excludes&#13;
indirect taxes.&#13;
The figures for agriculture and services are those of the national&#13;
accounts. The split between manufacturing and energy is based on the decom-&#13;
position of GDP at factor cost given in the input-output table. (National&#13;
accounts do not provide separate GDP at factor cost for manufacturing and ser-&#13;
vices.)&#13;
5.        Three types of institutions are considered:  Households (including&#13;
private non-profit institutions); Companies and; Government. Their current&#13;
accounts are distinguished while their capital accounts are consolidated.&#13;
The three current accounts and the consolidated capital account are given&#13;
in rows and columns 2, 3, 4 and 5.&#13;
5.1.      Row 2 gives the receipts of households from the different sources.&#13;
The figures in all the cells of this row are consistent with the national&#13;
accounts figures. The dividends, however, have been taken out of property&#13;
income and put as transfer from companies to households (row 2, column 3).&#13;
5.2.      Row 3 gives the receipts of companies.  In cell (3,1) the&#13;
operating surplus (including provision for the consumption of fixed capital)&#13;
appears.  It is derived residually.  Cells (3,2) and (3,4) give respectively&#13;
the interest on consumers' debt and the interest on the public debt.,&#13;
5,3.      In row 4, all receipts of government appear:&#13;
i) (4,1) is government income from property and entrepreneurship;&#13;
ii) cell(4,2) is the sum of direct taxes on households and other&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
48&#13;
current transfers from households;&#13;
iii) cell (4,3) is direct taxes on corporations and;&#13;
iv) cell (4,22) is net indirect taxes.&#13;
5.4.      The consolidated capital account is in row 5.  It receives:&#13;
i) the savings of Households and private non-profit institutions&#13;
(cell (5,2));&#13;
ii) the savings of Corporations, including the provision for the&#13;
consumption of fixed capital (cell (5,3));&#13;
iii) the savings of Government (cell (5,4)) and;&#13;
iv)"foreign savings"(cell (5,23)).&#13;
All figures in the row 5 are from the National Accounts.&#13;
6.        Rows 10, 13, 16 and 19 give the aggregate demand respectively for:&#13;
- agricultural commodities&#13;
- manufacturing&#13;
- energy&#13;
- services.&#13;
6.1.      Column 2 in rows 10, 13, 16 and 19 gives the split of private con-&#13;
sumption expenditure between the four sectors considered. We have taken the&#13;
average propensities to consume out of total private consumption expenditure&#13;
given in the I-0 table and applied them to the figure of total private con-&#13;
sumption expenditure given in the National Accounts. The first assumption&#13;
is that purchasers' prices and market prices used in the National Accounts&#13;
are the same. The second assumption is that on the interval considered,&#13;
average and marginal propensities are equal.&#13;
6.2.      Column 4 in rows 10, 13, 16 and 19 gives the split of government&#13;
consumption expenditure between the different sectors. The assumptions made&#13;
are the same as for private consumption expenditure, except where government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
49&#13;
consumption of agricultural products has been put to zero. In fact, according&#13;
to the I-0 table it appears to be negligible.&#13;
6.3.       Column 5 in rows 10, 13, 16 and 19 gives the split of total gross&#13;
investment between sectors of origin. The same procedure was used as for&#13;
private and government consumption. It was, however, performed separately&#13;
for increases in stocks and for fixed capital formation. Quite obviously,&#13;
no fixed investment uses energy or services production and there is no accumu-&#13;
lation of stocks in services.&#13;
6.4       The last elements in final demand are exports.  It is reasonably&#13;
assumed that there are no exports of energy.-/ Thus, exports consists of&#13;
agricultural, manufacturing, and service exports. Total exports of goods and&#13;
services (nonfactor) are given in the National Accounts as 57,014 million bahts.-&#13;
From     Thailand:  Towards a Development Strategy of Full Participation (1980),&#13;
it is possible to compute the value of agricultural exports (Tables 3.2 and 3.3&#13;
of the Appendix) which amount to 31,359 million bahts. Manufacturing exports&#13;
are also obtained from the same source and their value is 14,139 million bahts.&#13;
Exports of nonfactor services are computed as the difference between total exports&#13;
of goods and services, and agricultural and manufacturing exports. Their value&#13;
is 11,516 million bahts.&#13;
6.5        These three figures of exports appear in cells (11,23), (14,23) and&#13;
(20,23). They include export taxes paid by the Rest of the World to exports&#13;
which repay them to the account of indirect taxes.&#13;
6.6        The export taxes on agricultural and manufacturing exports are assumed&#13;
to be respectively 1,634 million bahts and 471 million bahts (cells (22,11) and&#13;
(22,14)). (See para. 7)&#13;
I Tn fact. in 1975, 230 mill i3on bahts of petroleum products have been exported,&#13;
t~f -,ure F  .  98 mi           D ยฝah'ts in' 1976 -  nd ne-3gible aftww~-:1'rds.  (See&#13;
a^ 'i .)n _;      'ahts to be e=c~&amp;_ '      anulacc:Ureo.&#13;
2/  Th-ese exp3 - -  i-ide eport ta-es.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
50&#13;
6.7       The value of exports coming out of the agricultural sector is thus&#13;
31,359 - 1,634 = 29,725 million bahts and this figure enters cell (6,11).&#13;
Likewise, the value of manufacturing exports to the manufacturing sector is&#13;
25,655 - 471 = 25,184 million bahts and this figure enters cell (7,14). It&#13;
is assumed that no export taxes are levied on exports of services. Hence, the&#13;
figure in cell (9,20) is identical with that in cell (20,23).&#13;
7.        To get the aggregate demand for the composite good in the four sec-&#13;
tors one must add intermediate demand to the nonexport final demand determined&#13;
above in paras. 6.1, 6.2 and 6.3. This implies the use of the interindustrial&#13;
flows. This was done in several steps which are described below . However,&#13;
for this, information on indirect taxes and on imports is needed. Here indirect&#13;
taxes are considered.&#13;
7.        Net indirect taxes as given in the National Accounts are 31,119 mil-&#13;
lion bahts. For FY'75 imtport duties are 8,270 and export taxes are 2,105 mil-&#13;
lion bahts (source: Thailand: Towards a Development Strategy of Ftll Partici--&#13;
pation (1980), Table 5.6 of Appendix). Using these three tigures indirect taxes&#13;
on domestic trade would be 20,744 million bahts. Now there is the problem of&#13;
splitting domestic and international trade indirect taxes on the different items.&#13;
7.        For FY'75 import duties are split according to Table 7.1.  To bring&#13;
consistency with the SAM classification, it is assumed that duties on food-&#13;
stuffs and on agricultural imports are the same. Likewise, petroleim products&#13;
are assumed to cover energy imports. The remaining duties are assumed to fall&#13;
on imports of manufacturing products.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
51&#13;
Table   7.1&#13;
Import Duties&#13;
Petroleum products           374&#13;
Foodstuffs                   394&#13;
Machinery                  3,488&#13;
Textiles                     443&#13;
Other                      3,571&#13;
Total                      8,270&#13;
In millions of bahts.&#13;
(Source: Thailand: Towards a Development Strategy of Full Participation (1980),&#13;
I.B.R.D.)&#13;
In the SAM import duties on agricultural imports (394) appear in cell (22,12),&#13;
those on manufacturing imports (7,502) in cell (22,15) and finally import duties&#13;
on energy imports (374) are put in cell (22,18).&#13;
Figures for export taxes for the fiscal year 1975 are given in&#13;
Table 7.2.&#13;
Table   7.2&#13;
Export Taxes&#13;
Rice premium                 795&#13;
Rice duty                    514&#13;
Rubber                       325&#13;
Other                        471&#13;
Total                      2,105&#13;
In millions of bahts&#13;
(Source: Thailand: Towards a Development Strategy of Full Participation (1980),&#13;
I.B.R.D.)&#13;
For consistency with the SAM classification, t.ne rice premium and the rice duty&#13;
as well as taxes on rubber are considered as taxes on agricultural exports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
52&#13;
With this approximation, indirect taxes paid on the agricultural&#13;
composite good are 852 (cell (22,10)); on the composite manufacturing good,&#13;
12,072 (cell (22,13)); on energy, indirect taxes are given in cell (22,16)&#13;
with a value of 312; and finally, on services, indirect taxes are given in&#13;
cell (22,19) with a value of 7,508 (all figures being in millions of bahts).&#13;
8.        If "unallocated" imports given by the I-0 table are dropped, total&#13;
imports from this source (98,554 million bahts) are still higher than the&#13;
figure given in the National accounts which is 70,795 million bahts.-/&#13;
Furthermore, according to the I-0 table, no imports of nonfactor services are&#13;
supposed to take place. A first disaggregation of imports (Table 8.1) is&#13;
obtained by applying the shares implicit in the I-0 table to total imports&#13;
given in the National Accounts.&#13;
Table   8.1&#13;
Imports excluding tariffs&#13;
First evaluation&#13;
Agriculture                 1,101&#13;
Manufacturing              55,623&#13;
Energy                    14,071&#13;
Services                    -0-&#13;
In millions of bahts.&#13;
1/ Does not include import duties.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
53&#13;
8. 1      The figures for agriculture and energy in Table 8.1 are close&#13;
to corresponding figures given by the BOT (Statistical Bulletin, Dec. 1979,&#13;
pgs. 46-49). Therefore it is assumed that imports of "manufacturing" or the&#13;
figure 55,623 includes imports of services. Using the balance of total ser-&#13;
vices:  6,160.8(BOT, Statistical Bulletin, Dec. 1979, p. 76) and the balance&#13;
of net factor services: -219, the figure for the balance of nonfactor ser-&#13;
vices is obtained: 5,941.8. Given that exports of services are 11,516&#13;
(para. 6.3) imports of services are derived 5,574.2 and from this figure and&#13;
the previous figure of "imports of manufactures" in Table 8.1, a final figure&#13;
for imports of manufactures is obtained: 50,048.8 (Table 8.2).&#13;
Table 8.2&#13;
Imports excluding Tariffs&#13;
Final Evaluation&#13;
Agriculture                           1,101&#13;
Manufacturing                        50,049&#13;
Energy                               14,071&#13;
Services                              5,574&#13;
In millions of bahts.&#13;
The figures of Table 8.2 are in cells (23,12), (23,15), (23,18) andl (23,21) of&#13;
the SAM.&#13;
8.2       Consider now imports as an addition to supply.  Their value in that&#13;
respect has to include import duties. So by adding import duties to the value&#13;
of imports before duties, the value of the supply of imported goods is obtained.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
54&#13;
In cell (12,10) the value of imported agricultural goods including duties is&#13;
given. For manufacturing imports the figure is given in cell (15,13), for&#13;
energy imports it is pu' in cell (18,16) and for services it is in cell (21,19).&#13;
9.        Now we return to the derivation of interindustrial flows, aggregate&#13;
demand, intermediate demand and gross production. The approach followed is to&#13;
get,in a first step, good estimates of total intermediate sectoral demands and&#13;
total intermediate sectoral costs. A second step is to use these marginals and&#13;
estimate a new matrix of interindustrial flows consistent with them by applying&#13;
the RAS method.-/In fact the procedure involves more than two stages because&#13;
of the need to adjust some figures and ratios to information from different&#13;
sources.&#13;
9.1       The first step was the aggregation of the (33 x 33) interindustrial&#13;
matrix-/ into a (4 x 4) matrix.  In fact only the (32 x 32) first sectors were&#13;
aggregated and the last sector:  "Unallocated" was dropped.  The matrix obtained&#13;
in this way and the implied intermediate demand are given in Table 9.1.&#13;
Table   9.1&#13;
Intermediate&#13;
Agriculture  Manufacturing       Energy      Services       Demand&#13;
Agriculture        17,762        52,595            -0-         5,790       76,147&#13;
Manufacturing      28,782        77,176            762        17,341      124,061&#13;
Energy              6,306         6,417         17,890         7,594       38,207&#13;
Services           15,544         9,456          1,202        17,131       43,333&#13;
All figures are in millions of bahts.&#13;
1/ See Bacharach, M. (1970), Biproportional Matrices and Input-Ouput Change,&#13;
Cambridge University Press.&#13;
2/ NESDB, Input-Ouput Table, Competitive Imports 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
55&#13;
Table 9.1 gives a first estimate of total intermediate demand. However, the&#13;
fourth column includes the intermediate demand of the wholesale and retail&#13;
trade sector, whereas the fourth row does not include any delivery of that&#13;
sector to other sectors. In fact, total deliveries of wholesale and retail&#13;
trade are lumped together in the published input-output table. Thai value is&#13;
71,908 million bahts. This figure should be added to the intermediate demand&#13;
of services. The figure in the last row and last column of Table 9.1, which&#13;
is total intermediate demand of services becomes: 115,241 (43,333 d- 71,980).&#13;
9.2       Using the above estimate of total intermediate demand and total non-&#13;
export final demand, total aggregate demand for the composite goods are calcu-&#13;
lated. The aggregate demands have to be equal to aggregate supplies, hence,&#13;
given imports and taxes, one can compute the domestic supply of domestic goods.&#13;
With the figures of exports, this allows for computation of the gross production&#13;
of each sector. Having determined previously the vector of value added(s),&#13;
it is then easy to compute the vector of total intermediate costs (Table 9.2).&#13;
Table 9.2&#13;
Total Intermediate Costs&#13;
First estimate&#13;
Agriculture                90,934&#13;
Manufacturing             157,430&#13;
Energy                     26,681&#13;
Services                   78,611&#13;
In millions of bahts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9.3       The intermediate costs of Table 9.2 are consistent with the other&#13;
figures of the SAM, howevTer, they are not equal to the intermediate costs&#13;
obtained by adding up the different colums of Table 9.1. An obvious, next&#13;
step would be to take the figures of Table 9.2, the intermediate demand from&#13;
Table 9.1 (with 115,241 for services) and to apply the RAS method on the&#13;
interindustrial flows of Table 9.1. This would give a complete, balanced&#13;
SAM.&#13;
This, however, would give a distorted view of some basic ratios in&#13;
the Tai economy essentially in two respects.&#13;
(1) The figure used for agricultural exports before taxes (cell&#13;
(6,11)) corresponds to the trade classification used by the Bank of Thailand.&#13;
However, the classification underlying the input-output table is the industrial&#13;
classification. For the latter classification any processing of an agricultural&#13;
product is an activity of the manufacturing sector. Hence, when an exportable&#13;
agriculture good is even slightly processed and then exported, it becomes,&#13;
according to the industrial classification, manufactured export. Thus, the&#13;
figure in row 1, column 2 of Table 9.1: 52,595 contains deliveries of essen-&#13;
tially agricultural goods, which are slightly processed by the manufacturing&#13;
sector and then exported. But, in fact, these goods are already included in&#13;
the figure in cell (6.11) of the SAM, which gives agricultural exports. Conse-&#13;
quently, the intermediate demand of agricultural goods as given in Table 9.1&#13;
is an overestimation of actual domestic intermediate demand.&#13;
(2) Imports of energy, as given in cell (18,16) of the SAM are equal&#13;
to 14,445 million bahts. The figure given by the Bank of Thailand (Statistical&#13;
Bulletin, Dec. 1979, p. 49, "Fuel and Lubricants") for imports of fuel and lubri-&#13;
cants is 14,233 million bahts. However, imports of energy as given in the input-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
57&#13;
output table are 19,588   million bahts.  Given the aggregate demand for&#13;
energy (obtained by adding total final demand for energy, to total (inter-&#13;
mediate demand)), the equality between aggregate demand and aggregate supply&#13;
and the chosen figure of imports: 14,445, this would lead to an overestima-&#13;
tion of domestic demand for domestic energy. Subsequently we would overesti-&#13;
mate domestic production of energy.&#13;
In order to take account of the above distortions a reestimation&#13;
of the vectors of total intermediate demand and of total intermediate costs&#13;
was undertaken. The flows of intermediate demand of manufacturing from agri-&#13;
culture and of energy from energy have also been revised. With the two new&#13;
marginal vectors, the RAS method was applied on the modified interindustrial&#13;
matrix in order to get a final matrix of interindustrial flows. In that way&#13;
the whole SAM is balanced.&#13;
The new vectors of intermediate demand and of intermediate costs&#13;
are given in Table 9.3. The basic assumptions underlying them are:&#13;
i) Agricultural exports are 20% of gross agricultural production;&#13;
this implies a gross production of 148,625 million bahts and a domestic demand&#13;
for domestic goods of 118,900. Consequantly aggregate supply and aggregate&#13;
demand are 121,247 million bahts and total intermediate demand of agricultural&#13;
goods if then 40,210 million bahts.&#13;
ii)  The first row of Table 9.1 is modified to take account of the&#13;
new figure for total intermediate demand. Intermediate demands of agricultural&#13;
goods are assumed to be 17,191; 17,473; 5,546 for agriculture, manufacturing and&#13;
energy,and service, respectively.&#13;
iii) Taking account of the difference between the figure of- imports&#13;
of energy given in the input-output table (19,588) and the figure chosen in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
58&#13;
the SAM (14,445)-/, gross production of energy is estimated to be 27,895&#13;
million bahts.&#13;
Table 9.4 gives the matrix of interindustrial flows obtained after&#13;
application of the RAS method. This matrix is consistent with the rest of the&#13;
SAM, which is thus balanced.&#13;
Table 9.3&#13;
Total Intermediate Demand    Total Intermediate Costs&#13;
Agriculture                    40,210                         54,997&#13;
Manufacturing                  94,296                        127,665&#13;
Energy                         32,835                         21,309&#13;
Services                      109,300                         72,670&#13;
Figures are expressed in millions of bahts.&#13;
Table 9.4&#13;
Matrix of Interindustrial Flows&#13;
Agriculture      Manufacturing      Energy      Services&#13;
Agriculture         11,875            22,105           -0-         6,230&#13;
Manufacturing       13,:L49           67,751             648      12,749&#13;
Energy               3,227             6,541         16,812        6,255&#13;
Services            26,746            31,268          3,849       47,436&#13;
Figures are expressed in millions of bahts.&#13;
1/ The 230 million bahts of exports of petroleum products are also taken&#13;
into account. See footnote 1, p. 4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
59&#13;
Appendix 2: Data Base of the Reference Simulation&#13;
In order to define a reference simulation on the period 1980-1990,&#13;
one has to make assumptions on four sets of variables and parameters. These&#13;
are: (1) the structural parameters; (2) the policy parameters; (3) the rest&#13;
of the world variables; and (4) the domestic variables.&#13;
The Structural Parameters&#13;
They are mainly behavioral and technical parameters and could be&#13;
classified into three groups:&#13;
(1) The parameters of the allocation relations 7, 8 and 9&#13;
To get an idea about their order of magnitude, the relations are estimated&#13;
on time series from national account data.  Then keeping the ss, the pi,&#13;
...5, the c., i=l, 2, 3 and the h., i=1,...8 to their estimated values,&#13;
-0            -~~~0  .                0&#13;
the h., i=1,...8, the c , i=l, 2, 3 and the pi, i=l,...5 are adjusted (using&#13;
the appropriate entries in the SAM of 1975) in order to reproduce the data of&#13;
that year (see Table A2.1).&#13;
(2)  The input-output coefficients aij, i,j=l, 2, 3, 4 in relations&#13;
1 and 11 to 14 are obtained from the SAM of 1975 using their definition. The&#13;
parameters allocating gross investment demand over sectors are also obtained&#13;
from the SAM.  They are 61' 62' and 63 of the aggregate demand relations 11 to&#13;
14.&#13;
(3) The parameters of the import demand functions (relations 15&#13;
and 16) and of the related price functions (relation 4) are the elasticities&#13;
of substitution al, c2, a3 '    the share parameters 61' 62' 63' 64 and the scale&#13;
parameters y1, Y2, Y3, y4.  The elasticities of substitution for the base&#13;
scenario were assumed to be .8, 2.0, .15, 2.0 for agriculture, manufacturing,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
60&#13;
energy and services respectively. Using 1975 as the base year for prices,&#13;
and the imports ratios implicit in the SAM, the elasticities of substitu-&#13;
tion determine the share and scale parameters.&#13;
However, the share parameter for energy is independently changed&#13;
in 1982 and onward to take account of the coming on stream of domestic gas&#13;
production.&#13;
The parameters of the export-demand relations 18 are the elastici-&#13;
ties ni and the scale parameters EBi.  Using relative price movements on the&#13;
period 1975-1979 an estimate for n2 is obtained, 2.57. EB is determined&#13;
2                        2&#13;
subsequently using the SAM figure for exports and the ratio of the ratio&#13;
of the world price and the Thai price of exports of manufactures, as observed&#13;
in 1975.  The same procedure is followed to estimate EBA, but with n 4=2.0.&#13;
The Policy Parameters&#13;
The second set of assumptions is on the policy parameters. These&#13;
are, on the one side, the indirect tax rates on domestically and internationally&#13;
traded goods and, on the other side, they are the parameters allocating govern-&#13;
ment revenue.&#13;
(1) Implicit in the SAM of 1975 are all indirect tax rates for&#13;
that year. These base year values are either maintained or lowered to take&#13;
account of recent trends (see Table A2.2).&#13;
(2) A first va:Lue of the parameters allocating government revenue&#13;
(relation 10) is obtained by estimating the set of relations using a time series&#13;
(1970-1979) and nonlinear least squares. The result is a rapidly declining&#13;
share of government savings, of transfers to households and of transfers abroad.&#13;
For the base scenario the same trend in the shares is maintained but at a much&#13;
slower rate and the drop is dampened (see Table A2.3). The adopted assumption&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
61&#13;
here leads to a somewhat optimistic view on the savings gap and hence on the&#13;
current account deficit.&#13;
The Rest of the World Variables&#13;
Linkages between the domestic economy and the rest of the world are&#13;
caught through export and import prices, parameters reflecting the performance&#13;
of Thai exports of manufactures and services and net factor income and other&#13;
transfers.&#13;
(1) The import price of agricultural products Ori) is obtained in&#13;
the following way. For 1980-1982, 1985 and 1990 it is assumed to follow the&#13;
same trend as a Laspeyres index of projected prices of cereals, fruits and&#13;
vegetables and coffee, cocoa and tea.-L/ Between 1982 and 1985 a linear trend&#13;
with 10.1% growth is used to complete the series. In summary, the import price&#13;
of agricultural products is assumed to grow at a rate between 10% and 11% after&#13;
1982 (see Table 2.4).&#13;
(2)  The import prices of manufactures and services (ir2, iT4) are&#13;
assumed to increase at the same rate as the projected trend in the International&#13;
Price Index (IPI).  This is a decreasing rate-/ from 10.5% between 1979-1980,&#13;
to 5.7% between 1989-1990 (see Table A2.4).&#13;
(3) The import price of energy (1T3) is obtained by following the&#13;
projected trend in oil prices. These are assumed to be $28 a barrel in 1980,&#13;
$47.3 in 1985, and $73.6 in 1990, or an increase of 63% in the decade-/(see&#13;
Table A2.4).&#13;
1/ See Report No. 814/80 Price Prospects for Major Primary Commodities, Jan. 1980,&#13;
p. 14, Table 5.&#13;
2/ See Projections of IBRD, Table 16.&#13;
3/  See Report No. 814/80, p. 19, Table 10.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
62&#13;
(4)  The export price of agricultural products (7r) is assumed to&#13;
follow the same trend as a Laspeyres index of projected prices of rice, rubber,&#13;
maize, jute and other agricultural productsL/(see Table 2.5).&#13;
(5)  The world prices of exports of manufactures and services (72,&#13;
-e                                                                    2/&#13;
Tr4) are assumed to increase at the same rate as the projected IPI- (see Table&#13;
A2.5).&#13;
(6) In relation 18 the world demand for Thai exports of manufactures&#13;
and services are dependent only on relative prices. However, one may think&#13;
that they also depend on the overall world activity and on the success of Thai&#13;
exporters over and above price changes. In order to catch these two aspects,&#13;
the parameters EB. are assumed to grow at an exponential rate:&#13;
EB it =EB (to) (1 + ri) t       i=2,4&#13;
The growth rates in the base scenario are assumed to be 13%.&#13;
(7) Net factor income outflow is obtained via a debt model&#13;
It is based on assumptions on (a) investment income receipts; (b) interest&#13;
payments on medium- and long-term debt; and (c) interest payments on short-&#13;
term debt and profit.&#13;
(8) Inflow of private transfers are assumed to remain at a nominal&#13;
value of 300 million bahts.&#13;
(9) Finally, public transfer nominal inflows are assumed to grow at&#13;
13% annually.3-&#13;
l1 See Report No. 814/80, p. 19, Table 10; p. 14, Table 6.&#13;
2/ See Projections of IBRD, Table 16.&#13;
3/ This seems to be the relevant rate for aid increases from donor countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
63&#13;
The Domestic Variables&#13;
The last set of assumptions is on some domestic trends within the&#13;
Thai economy. The relevant variables here are gross investment demand in&#13;
constant prices, It, gross agricultural production in constant prices, -Xd&#13;
and the net prices of manufacturing, energy and services V2t, V3t, V4t res-&#13;
pectively.&#13;
(1)  Gross investment demand in constant prices I  is assumLed to grow&#13;
t&#13;
exponentially at an annual rate of 5%.&#13;
-d&#13;
(2)  Gross agricultural production in constant prices xit is also&#13;
assumed to grow exponentially but at the lower rate, 4.5%.&#13;
(3) Net prices are defined as the ratio of sectoral GDP at current&#13;
factor cost over gross production in constant prices.  If Lj is employment,&#13;
K. is capital, Wi is nominal average wage, and r. is the nominal users cost of&#13;
capital, then: _ d&#13;
i.X=  W.L. + r.K.L+,&#13;
j,     d        I d      -          +x~   r x J   j=2, 3, 3&#13;
This means that net prices are determined by the mix of labor-output,, the capital-&#13;
output, wage, and the cost of capital.  A refined assumption on the trends of&#13;
the Vj, j=2, 3, 4 would require some predictions on all of the mentioned variables.&#13;
In the base scenario a crude but reasonable assumption is adopted:&#13;
(a)  V2 and V4 or net prices of manufacturing and services are assumed&#13;
to have a 0% real growth and a nominal growth parallel to the GDP deflator for&#13;
OECD North countries (see Table A2.6).&#13;
(b)  V3, net price of energy is assumed to have a 3% real growth and&#13;
the same nominal growth as the GDP deflator for OECD North countries. The assump-&#13;
tion of a 3% real growth is there to catch the growing production of gas (Table A2.6).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
64&#13;
Table A2. 1.1&#13;
Parameters of the Allocation Relations&#13;
Households:  U. = (h. + hi        h e  (POPt  ) TRH&#13;
$h = 2769.10&#13;
h..h.                        -O   -&#13;
Interest on               .004         .013               .017&#13;
consumers' debt:&#13;
Taxes                     .012         .012               .024&#13;
Savings                   .150         .02                .17&#13;
Consumption               .833        -.044               .789&#13;
a)Agriculture          (.324)       (-.109)             (.215)&#13;
b)Manufacturing         (.266        (.086)             (.352)&#13;
c)Energy               (.032)       (-.019)             (.013)&#13;
d)Services             (.211)       (-.002)             (.209)&#13;
Transfers Abroad          .001        -.001               .000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
65&#13;
Table A2.1.2&#13;
Parameters of the Allocation Relations&#13;
o   -1   -F /TIC-&#13;
Companies:  Ci   (ci + Ci  e             ) TIC&#13;
6 = 28240&#13;
c&#13;
c ยฐc                            c i+ c.&#13;
__~~~~~~    1&#13;
Dividends                .042            .013                .055&#13;
Corporate taxes          .068            .118                .186&#13;
Corporate savings        .890          - .131                .759&#13;
Table A2.1.3&#13;
Parameters of the Allocation Relations&#13;
-0   -1   -7r/z&#13;
Factors:  R  = (Pi+ Pi  e              Z&#13;
Bz= 1294410&#13;
-0              -1              p.+p.&#13;
.        pO,   ~~~~~p.   1p&#13;
Compensation of          .265            .133                .398&#13;
employees&#13;
Income from un-          .532           -.200                .332&#13;
incorporated&#13;
enterprise&#13;
Income from              .097           -.033                .064&#13;
property&#13;
Operating surplus        .096            .103                .199&#13;
of companies&#13;
Government income        .010           - .003               .007&#13;
from property and&#13;
entrepreneurship&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
66&#13;
Table A2. 2&#13;
% Rates of Indirect Taxes&#13;
M1   Tm2   TM3   TM4   Te1   Te2         4    1    2    3    4&#13;
1980        1.0   1.2    .03  0.0   3.5   3.4   0.0   .7  1.0   .03 4.3&#13;
1981                      .5                                         .5&#13;
1982                     1.0                                        1.0&#13;
1983                     2.0                                        1.0&#13;
1984                     2.7                                        1.0&#13;
1985 - 1990                  2.7                                        1.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
67&#13;
Table A2.3&#13;
Parameters of the Allocation Relations&#13;
-.1 -_ IGREV&#13;
Government:  G. = (g. + g  e  g       ) GREV&#13;
ag = 750,000&#13;
-0           -l-0   -1&#13;
go           gi            g,+-gil&#13;
Transfers to            .005         -.005             .000&#13;
Households&#13;
Interest on Public      .083          .155             .238&#13;
Debt&#13;
Government Savings      .166         -.500             .334&#13;
Consumption:&#13;
Manufacturing          .065          .030             .095&#13;
Energy                 .020          .020             .040&#13;
Services               .660          .301             .961&#13;
Transfers Abroad        .001         -.001             .000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
68&#13;
Table A2.4&#13;
.~~~&#13;
Import Prices       1975 = 1&#13;
-m                -m  -m                      -m&#13;
If1              7T2' 04   -                   3&#13;
Year            Agriculture          Manufacturing,              Energy&#13;
Services&#13;
1980         1.377                   1.281                2.935&#13;
1981         1.417      (2.90)       1.690    (9.00)    3.275  (14.25)&#13;
1982         1.654    (16.72         1.825    (8.00)    3.597  (11.58)&#13;
1983         1.779      (7.55)       1.953    (7.00)    3.950   (9.83)&#13;
1984         1.913       (7.55)      2.084    (6.75)    4.338   (9.83)&#13;
1985         2.057      (7.55)       2.220    (6.50)    4.740   (9.83)&#13;
1986         2.185      (6.72)       2.360    (6.30)    5.178   (9.23)&#13;
1987         2.321       (6.22)      2.505    (6.15)    5.656   (9.23)&#13;
1988         2.463       (6.22)      2.655    (6.00)    6.180   (9.23)&#13;
1989         2.615      (6.22)       2.810    (5.85)    6.752   (9.23)&#13;
1990         2.777      (6.22)       2.971    (5.70)    7.376   (9.23)&#13;
avg. growth rate         7,27                   6,72                9,65&#13;
a! Figures between brackets are rates of growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
69&#13;
Table A2. &#13;
Export Prices al    1975 = 1&#13;
[Year                 _ _                      e        -e&#13;
Agriculture                 2        4&#13;
Agri'c'ultureManuf acturinpgkl&amp; Servic es&#13;
,.~ ~~~~~~2&#13;
1980         15208                           2.9550&#13;
1 9 8-       .'- u27T7   t              j    Xoin9      9 ยฐ SQ)&#13;
-g. gro#t.6o h  i R/    i 4 rate  __                    87 2C)&#13;
; ^iues  e  en  r  ie ia 7             es 0  of grow_to&#13;
.~~~~  . 0  * ,, 7u   b   ,f,'               ,o     -t&#13;
1j 990        25 57      ;       4 -2'3 2.970   &lt; 570)j&#13;
a vg. giro4th rate .  i  ,72&#13;
a/Fwigures 'betweenl7rcieX  aze -rates of growth.            &#13;
a2 nd iTe are world -prces, n ot supply prices, of Th,ai&#13;
4expo-rts;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
70&#13;
Table A2.6&#13;
Net Prices       1975 = 1&#13;
Year              V2              v3                  v4&#13;
Manufacturing        Energy             Services&#13;
1980       1.417             1.627              1.417&#13;
1981       1.513  (6.77)   1.785  (9.71)    1.513  (6.77)&#13;
1982       1.603  (5.95)   1.946  (9.02)    1.603  (5.95)&#13;
1983       1.687  (5.25)   2.106  (8.22)        1.687  (5.25)&#13;
1984       1.773  (5.10)   2.276  (8.07)    1.773  (5.10)&#13;
1985       1.859  (4.85)   2.456  (7.90)    1.859  (4.85)&#13;
1986       1.947  (4.73)   2.645  (7.70)    1.947  (4.73)&#13;
1987       2.037  (4.62)   2.847  (7.64)    2.037  (4.62)&#13;
1988       2.129  (4.52)   3.060  (7.48)    2.129  (4.52)&#13;
1989       2.222  (4.37)   3.286  (7.39)    2.222  (4.37)&#13;
1990       2.317  (4.28)   3.525  (7.27)    2.317  (4.28)&#13;
Figures between brackets are rates of growth (x).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                       TITLE OF PAPER                             AUTHOR&#13;
423       Rethinking Artisanal Fisheries Development:             D. Emmerson (consultant)&#13;
Western Concepts, Asian Experience&#13;
424       Transition toward More Rapid and Labor-                 B. de Vries&#13;
Intensive Industrial Development: The Case&#13;
of the Philippines&#13;
425       Britaints Pattern of Specialization in                  V. Cable&#13;
Manufactured Goods with Developing Countries           I. Rebelo&#13;
and Trade Protection&#13;
426       Worker Adjustment to Liberalized Trade:  Costs          G. Glenday&#13;
and Assistance Policies                                G. Jenkins&#13;
J. Evans&#13;
427       On the Political Economy of Protection in               H. Glismann&#13;
Germany                                                F. Weiss&#13;
428       Italian Commercial Policies in the 1970s                E. Grilli&#13;
429       Effects of Non-Tariff Barriers to Trade on              C. Hamilton&#13;
Prices, Employment, and Imports:  The Case of&#13;
the Swedish Textile and Clothing Industry&#13;
430       Output and Employment Changes in a "Trade               J. Mutti&#13;
Sensitive" Sector:  Adjustment in the U.S.             M. Bale&#13;
Footwear Industry&#13;
431       The Political Economy of Protection in Belgium          P. Tharakan&#13;
432       European Community Protection Against Manufactured  E. Verrydt&#13;
Imports from Developing Countries:  A Case Study    J. Waelbroeck&#13;
in the Political Economy of Protection&#13;
433       Agrarian Reforms in Developing Rural Economies          A. Braverman&#13;
Characterized by Interlinked Credit and Tenancy        T.N. Srinivasan&#13;
Markets                                                (consultant)&#13;
434       How Segmented is the Bogota Labour Market?              G. Fields (consultant)&#13;
435       Pirate Subdivisions and the Market for                  A. Carroll&#13;
Residential Lots in Bogota&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
No.                       TITLE OF PAPER                             AUTHOR&#13;
436       Exchange Rate Adjustments under Generalized            R.M. Bautista&#13;
Currency Floating: Comparative Analysis&#13;
among Developing Countries&#13;
437       The Newly-Industrializing Developing Countries         B. Balassa&#13;
after the Oil Crisis&#13;
438       The Process of Industrial Development and              B. Balassa&#13;
Alternative Development Strategies&#13;
439       Monitoring Rural Development in East Asia              G. Deboeck&#13;
R. Ng&#13;
440       Higher Education in Developing Countries:              G. Psacharopoulos&#13;
A Cost-Benefit Analysis                                (consultant)&#13;
441       Policy Interventions for Technological                 C. Cooper (consultant)&#13;
Innovation in Developing Countries&#13;
442       An Economic and Political Analysis of Alternative   J. de Melo&#13;
Trade Adjustment Policies in Three Archetype           S. Robinson&#13;
Developing Economies&#13;
443       A General Equilibrium Analysis of Foreign              K. Dervis&#13;
Exchange Shortages in a Developing Economy             J. de Melo&#13;
S. Robinson&#13;
444       Adoption of Agricultural Innovations in                G. Feder&#13;
Developing Countries:  A Survey                        R. Just, D. Silberman&#13;
(consultants)&#13;
445       Empirical Justification for Infant Industry            L. Westphal&#13;
Protection&#13;
446       The Political Economy of Specialised Farm              J. Von Pischke&#13;
Credit Institutions                                    P. Heffernan, D. Adams&#13;
(consultants)&#13;
447       Measuring Urban Malnutrition and Poverty:              R. Mohan, M. Wagner&#13;
A Case Study of Bogota and Cali, Colombia              J. Garcia (consultant)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PUB HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.448&#13;
Grais, Wafik.&#13;
Aggregate demand and&#13;
macroeconomic imbalances in&#13;
Thailand : simulations with&#13;
PUB HG3881.5.W57 W67 no.448&#13;
Grais, Wafik.&#13;
Aggregate demand and&#13;
macroeconomic imbalances in&#13;
Thailand :&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="439924">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/04/439924/aggregate-demand-macroeconomic-imbalances-thailand-simulations-siam-1-model
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/04/439924/aggregate-demand-macroeconomic-imbalances-thailand-simulations-siam-1-model</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1981/04/439924/aggregate-demand-macroeconomic-imbalances-thailand-simulations-siam-1-model</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/11/04/000178830_9810190341033/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/11/04/000178830_9810190341033/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-05-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1981-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Aggregate demand and macroeconomic
            imbalances in Thailand : simulations with the SIAM 1 model.
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In the latter half of the seventies,
            Thailand was able to maintain high GDP rates of growth.
            These were, however, associated with growing dependence on
            foreign borrowing and chronic budgetary deficits. This paper
            focuses on the demand side adjustments of the Thai economy
            to lower agricultural growth and to higher energy prices. It
            draws the implications of the demand responses on the time
            path of the resource gap, the current account deficit and on
            the public sector savings gap. The analysis uses an
            economy-wide model built around a social accounting matrix.
            It is a fix-price model and is closed at the macroeconomic
            level by assuming exogenous real investment. The model is
            used to generate two types of results: (1) time paths for
            the endogenous variables under different assumptions on the
            paths of exogenous variables, policy parameters and
            structural parameters; and (2) elasticities at one point in
            time of the endogenous variables with respect to all
            predetermined parameters and variables. These elasticities
            measure the direct and indirect effects of, say, variations
            in energy prices on the consumer price index.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Aggregate demand and macroeconomic
            imbalances in Thailand : simulations with the SIAM 1 model.
        </docna>
        <display_title>Aggregate demand and
            macroeconomic imbalances in Thailand : simulations with the
            SIAM 1 model.</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1981/04/439924/aggregate-demand-macroeconomic-imbalances-thailand-simulations-siam-1-model</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Markets and Market Access,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Consumption</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <count>Thailand</count>
        <authors>
            <author>GRAIS, W.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_9810190341033</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Macro/Non-Trade</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 448</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Elasticity (economic); Energy prices;
            Models; Social accounting matrices; Structural adjustment;
            Time factor
            adverse effects,Aggregate
            demand,agricultural production,agriculture,balance of
            payments,base year,consumer price index,consumers,corporate
            taxes,cost minimization,debt,demand functions,Development
            Strategy,disequilibrium,dividends,domestic demand,domestic
            market,elasticities,elasticity,elasticity of
            substitution,employment,endogenous variables,energy
            prices,excess demand,exogenous
            variables,expenditures,exports,financial
            transfers,forecasts,GDP,GNP,government consumption,gross
            national savings,growth rate,household
            consumption,imports,income
            distribution,inflation,international trade,land
            resources,market information,market prices,oil,oil
            prices,population growth,price increases,price
            takers,private consumption,product markets,real
            income,relative value,savings,stocks,structural
            change,substitutes,suppliers,surplus,tax
            rates,taxation,terms of trade,Trade Balance,trade
            policies,value added,world markets
        </keywd>
        <owner>East Asia &amp; Pacific Country Units</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP448</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Balance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Thailand</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>