<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>At a Glance&#13;
The World Bank               FPD Note No. 15                                                          July 1994&#13;
Options for Private Power&#13;
A framework for decisionmaking&#13;
Denni-s Anderson'&#13;
m      77Te s52ft to private power means coun-&#13;
tries have to choose from among sever-&#13;
al ins-t utional models, ranging from         impetus for change&#13;
the prf.ately owned, vertically integrat-&#13;
ed uti;tity to theffully "unbuindled" or      There are several reasons why countries&#13;
are seeking to move from state to private&#13;
'pure  model in which power stations,         ownershio:&#13;
transviission grids, and regional distri-&#13;
-  butior. networks are all privately and         - Thefinzancial requtirements of meeting&#13;
*  separately owned. There is often in-             new demnands. Demand is doubling&#13;
tense debate over which model to select         every - to 10 years in most developing&#13;
and wh1at criterion to use. There are           regions. Prices averaged less than half&#13;
_  g  some ,-oncerns that choices are too       the supply costs in developing coun-&#13;
some ''oncerns that cho^ces are tootries in 1991, owing to the political&#13;
.Fw ^ &lt; 4  - ,X.  n         frequently driven by market ideology             regulation of prices. Revenue shortfalls&#13;
rather than objective analysis of the           amounted to over S100 billion per&#13;
alternatives. To avoid or address these         year, and coincidentally were about&#13;
situat;ons, standard indicators of eco-         the same as is required for new invest-&#13;
nomi perfornance, based on cost-               ments. Privatization is seen as a means&#13;
and price-efficiency and quality of             of achwevng price-efficpency where&#13;
servicc. willprovide some reliable and         * Cost atd manragerial efficiency. Large&#13;
nonideological answers about what               electric:il losses. brown-outs, black-&#13;
best s-,its a particular country-and            outs, and poor plant availability are&#13;
will a.-.so indicate when and where             common experiences with state-owned&#13;
refor7m. is merited at all. 7his Vote out-      utilities. and have similarly caused&#13;
lines i;e reform. options, provides the         manaygers and pvate capital to iat-&#13;
standard indicators which may give              prove the efficiency and reliability of&#13;
some -ciddance on choice, and briefly           supphl.&#13;
review s some of the risks policymakers        . M1acroeconomics. The drain on public&#13;
revenues caused by subsidizing a&#13;
face i ! any tra nsition period.                 state-owned utility has also led many&#13;
countries to look for an alternative&#13;
Four Models                                     model.&#13;
There are, broadly, four institutional&#13;
mode's for a country to choose from.&#13;
All co: trast distinctly with the most&#13;
Industry and Energy Department&#13;
11- - V-ice P-esidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
commion existing approach based on state-owned    prices to reflect costs, and this would simultaneously&#13;
and -controlled enterprises with no private share  (i) greatly improve internal caih generation in most&#13;
ownership-the point of departure for the majority   countries and (ii) lay the basis for private capital to&#13;
of developing countries. The alternatives are:    be raised in stock and bond markets, and through&#13;
direct investment.&#13;
.llodel 1. The traditional model of the vertically inte-&#13;
grated state-owned public utility, operated as a qua-  Mlodel I would thus lead to financial self-sufficiency&#13;
si-independent public corporation on commercial    in the industry and eliminate the budgetary distress-&#13;
principles. Regulation is independent of-arm's    es that the poor pricing policies of the public utili-&#13;
length from-government, the utilities, and special   ties have caused in many countries. But it remains,&#13;
interests. This is the model followed by rnost Euro-   nevertheless, a "regulated monopoly," and lacks the&#13;
pean utilities, including the U.K. until 1989. Korea,    element of competition and the incentive for mana-&#13;
and Thailand. It is not, of course, strictly a private  gerial and cost-efficiency in the provision of sup-&#13;
model, though what has differentiated it from the  plies. Second, regulated moncoolies are often wed-&#13;
models followed by most developing countries is   ded to existing approaches and inhibit investment in&#13;
independent regulation and that it has attempted to   newly emerging electricity supply technologies.&#13;
"simulate" the results of market competition, e.g.,&#13;
through the adoption of commercial pricing policies   Model 1I overcomes these problems by admitting&#13;
(ideally marginal cost pricing).                  independent generation on the supply system. The&#13;
model introduces competition in new generation,&#13;
Model II. Like MIodel I, but with financial resources    and attracts the additional financial and managerial&#13;
being raised through private share ownership,     resources associated with direct investment. In addi-&#13;
bonds, and private borrowing, and with competition  tion. it is associated with greater accountability be-&#13;
being introduced by private power producers (the  cause of the requirements of independent audits and&#13;
U.S.).                                            the public scrutiny that comes with share owner-&#13;
ship. The increased accountability extends not only&#13;
Model III. Like Model I, with competitive procure-   to cost-efficiency in operations and investment, but&#13;
ment of new generation plus a contract or com-    also to public issues such as compliance with taxa-&#13;
mon carriage for transmission. Countries in the   tion and environmental laws and the provision of&#13;
process of moving to complete vertical separation   universal service.&#13;
may pass through this phase (the U.S. since 1992,&#13;
Mexico).                                          MVodels III and IVare institutionally complex, and&#13;
will not always be the most aopropriate starting&#13;
Model IV Complete vertical separation of genera-  point for many countries. Moziel III opens plant dis-&#13;
tion, transmission, and distribution, with fLill priva-    patching schedules to compet-'ion and this is clearly&#13;
tization of each (the U.K., Argentina, Chile. Peru).  a force for cost-efficiency. In addition, it should lead&#13;
to improved tariff structures: prices would, in theory,&#13;
Benefits of change                                be bid down to marginal fuel rnd operating costs at&#13;
The choice of one model should not preclude evo-   off-peak, and up to marginal c.pital plus fuel and&#13;
lution into another. A country can begin to reform  operating costs at peak. Seasonial pricing would be&#13;
its utility using Model I or II, and evolve to Model III  encouraged on predominantly hydro svstems, and&#13;
or IV None of the models can work without a rea-   contracts between supplier and consumer woLld&#13;
sonable degree of price-efficiency, or thus without    lead to prices correctly reflecting costs according to&#13;
solving the financial problem, and for this reason  voltage level. If prices did nor reflect such cost lev-&#13;
alone all have their merits. Moving from the state-    els and structures, this would he an unmistakable&#13;
owned enterprise to Model I, for instance. requires    sign that competition was lackling.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Model IV has two advantages over Mfodel III. First, it   table indicates where possible the standards that are&#13;
allows for the franchising of dlistribution services.        typically achievecl in best practice situations.&#13;
Hence, companies that believe they could provide&#13;
these services more efficiently are able to contest          Managing risks in transition&#13;
current arrangements. Second. distributors will be          Table 1 concentrates on  static' measures at a point&#13;
better placed than others in the industry to judge the   in time only. But for most countries the path for&#13;
commercial merits of decentralized electricity pro-&#13;
duction, such as cogeneration or smaller-scale gen-&#13;
eration owned by the distribution companv itself or            Table 1. Measures of Efficiency*&#13;
by private investors. NModularity in fossil-fired plants&#13;
and in renewable energy supplies is opening up                 Cost-efficiency&#13;
manv possibilities in this direction.                           1. Reserve plant margins (20%)&#13;
2. Plant availability factors (85 to 90%)&#13;
The biggest economic and financial gains might well            3. Total systems losses (6 to 10%)&#13;
be realized by going from the state-owned enter-                  * coal (2.300-2-800)&#13;
prise to MVIodel II. Some countries might prefer this             * oil (2,300-2.700)&#13;
course if only because they could use the public                  * gas turbines (2,500-2,000)&#13;
utility to take the lead in extending regional and                * combined cvcle (1,700-2,000)&#13;
rural services. Another option might be to combine&#13;
iVodel II with elements of Model IV (such as fran-             Priceelfficilency&#13;
chising) in order to encourage managerial and price-           2. Self-financing ratio (&gt;25%)&#13;
efficiency in supply and investment in decentralized           3. Billing efficiency: thefts (&lt;2%), collection period (&lt;30 to&#13;
generation.                                                      40 days)&#13;
4. Percent share, equity, and bond finance&#13;
Objective basis for choice                                     5. Demand management:&#13;
-_bictiv  b* load factor improvement policies&#13;
The success or failure of any institutional model can             * power factor improvement&#13;
be objectively determined by measuring its economic               * peak load pricing&#13;
efficiency. The advantage of the efficiency criterion             v pricing by voltage level&#13;
is that it immediatelv suggests a range of indicators&#13;
by wvhich the success of a policy can be meeasuredl.           Provision of ser-vice&#13;
p    Y                  ~~~~~~~~1. Loss of loaid probabilitN, i- hours per year)&#13;
Some indicators are shown in Table 1. They are                 2. Percent of public served (rises with per capita income&#13;
neutral among institutional models. ancl are not in-             level and costs and benefits of electrification: long-term&#13;
fluenced by ideological factors. If an electricity in-           gooal is universal provision)&#13;
dustrn scores well on all of them, there might be no           3. compliance wvith environmental policies (varies and&#13;
reason to reform it. no matter wh1ich modlel it con-             evolves vith policics. hut high levels of abatement can&#13;
.if it is a pulic enterprise.                   he achieved through control technologies for PM. NOx.&#13;
forms to-even If It Is a publlc entet-prise.                     wand S02 or use of- clean fuels Sucl as gas)&#13;
The indicators have been divided into three (groups&#13;
to reflect different aspects of economic efficiency:             manCe dr.d)d1`1 'tCC hebv   . WorldI 13ank enurgv staff. Februare&#13;
whether the investment and operating costs are be-                ') 4&#13;
ing, minimized bh  the new moldel (cost-efficiencv)            -TeSC rItes Ot lrtLirn arc loe titan tlhe r-tLlirns of 20 percent&#13;
otten q(ioted by private coinpanies. \vhich incluCle allowoances&#13;
whethler the level and structure of prices reflect the           io- cost cscalation andci slippagc&gt;e and aklo for Countrv risk in&#13;
level and structure of costs (price-efficiency); and             the case of foreign investors. The expected or average real&#13;
whether service is being provided in wavs satisfacto-            financial returns are very likely muech lo\ver. comparable to the&#13;
ry to the public-a criterion which includes environ-             average real financial return of 8 to 12 percent.&#13;
mental factors as well as the provision of kWh. The    I&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
moving from one model to another may be as im-           * rising demancds for new capacity. The amount of&#13;
portant as the choice of the mociel itself. ancd will      new investment required in the clecacle after&#13;
varv with the situation. Some Countries might initial-     privatization will probably exceecl the size of the&#13;
lV prefer Model II (the traditional utility operating on   existing system. New investors may he more at-&#13;
commercial principles. with competitive procure-           tracted to supplying new capacity than to acquir-&#13;
ment of new generation), and shift to Models III or        ing and rehabilitating the existing system. If so, it&#13;
IVat a later time. Others might be concemed with           would be at least a decade before the majority of&#13;
rigidities setting in once a decision has been made        the system could be privately owned, even in&#13;
to set up a competitive arrangement between the            theory.&#13;
public utility and private producers under Model II.    * the large numbers of people and small commer-&#13;
and therefore might prefer to go clirectly to Model III    cial consumers without service. Roughly 2 billion&#13;
or IVI                                                     people do not have access to electricity in devel-&#13;
oping countries, and with population growth and&#13;
The path chosen will depend on the capacity and            urbanization the demand for new connections will&#13;
willingness of the capital markets to support the          be high.&#13;
reforms. In developing countries, the stock markets    * the need to raise prices by 50 to 100 percent or&#13;
presently have a capitalized value of about S800           more in many countries.&#13;
billion and are raising an additional S65 billion each    * fears of nationalist backlashes against foreign&#13;
year-only about half the electricity industry's annu-      ownership. Local capital markets will not be able&#13;
al new investment requirements of $120 billion, and        to absorb the industry fully, and finance will be&#13;
of course there are the financial demands of other         forthcoming from foreign buyers only if political&#13;
sectors to be met. Even when aggressive policies are       and economic risks are low.&#13;
put in place to change the legal framework and cor-&#13;
poratize the industry, the transition to full private    The danger is that if these problems are not ad-&#13;
ownership cannot proceed faster than the private         dressed privatization may not be sustainable, and&#13;
sector's ability to finance it.                          there may be calls for renationalization-a possibili-&#13;
ty that the investors will doubtless have in mind. As&#13;
In turn, availability of finance will be affected by the   one private producer has put it, their fear is that&#13;
following:                                               'nationalization will not be an intermediate step&#13;
between privatization and privatization. but that&#13;
* the inheritance, in most countries, of capacity        privatization will be an intermediate step between&#13;
shortages, overloaded distribution systems. large     nationalization and nationalization. All the more&#13;
losses. thefts of supplies often amounting to over    reason, therefore, to choose the model and the path&#13;
20 percent of electricity prodluced, much generat-   of reform carefullv.&#13;
ing capacity in disrepair. and numerous manageri-&#13;
al problems-including overmanning and lealing    Thi.s \otc has cspeciallv henclitcd tlrnT maturiais and curmments pro-&#13;
with redlundlancies-to be sorted o&gt;ut. This w,ill      idi.d ih) 1Ocrn;:rd1 rcnncnhiirn. lohn iB.lni-Kones. and Peoter Cordutikes.&#13;
leter private acquisition of the existing assets un-&#13;
less their prices are bid clown to a low level.       Dennis Anderson Senior Advisor. tndeustrLr and Energy Dcpartrnnt.&#13;
'I'his series is published to share ideas and invite discussion. It covers financial and private sector development as well as&#13;
industry and energy. The views expressecd are those of the author(s) ancd are not intendecl to represent an official statement of&#13;
Bank policy or strategy.&#13;
Comments are welcome. Please call the FPD Note line to leave a message: 202-458-1111: or contact Suzanne Smith, editor, Room&#13;
G8105. The World Bank. 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC 20433, or Internet address ssmith@worldbank.org.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441124">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/07/441124/options-private-power-framework-decisionmaking
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/07/441124/options-private-power-framework-decisionmaking</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1994/07/441124/options-private-power-framework-decisionmaking</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/10/000009265_3971229181311/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/10/000009265_3971229181311/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1994-07-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>1999-09-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Options for private power : a framework for decisionmaking
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The shift to private power means
            countries have to choose from among several institutional
            models, ranging from the privately owned, vertically
            integrated utility to the fully "unbundled" or
            "pure" model in which power stations, transmission
            grids, and regional distribution networks are all privately
            and separately owned. There is often intense debate over
            which model to select and what criterion to use. There are
            some concerns that choices are too frequently driven by
            market ideology rather than objective analysis of the
            alternatives. To avoid or address these situations, standard
            indicators of economic performance, based on cost and price
            efficiency and quality of service, will provide some
            reliable and nonidealogical answers about what best suits a
            particular country, and will also indicate when and where
            reform is merited at all. This Note outlines the reform
            options, provides the standard indicators which may give
            some guidance on choice, and briefly reviews some of the
            risks policymakers face in any transition period.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Options for private power : a framework for decisionmaking
        </docna>
        <display_title>Options for private power : a
            framework for decisionmaking</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1994/07/441124/options-private-power-framework-decisionmaking</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Access to Markets,Public Sector Economics,Pharmaceuticals &amp; Pharmacoeconomics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Environment,Public Sector Development,International Economics and Trade,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Anderson, Dennis</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3971229181311</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Power &amp; Energy Conversion</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>FPD Note no.15,Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 15</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Environment,Public Sector Development,International Economics and Trade,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Denationalization; Energy industries; Public
            services; Government ownership; Costs; Efficiency; Private
            ownership; Bonds; Stocks; Prices; Capital markets; Market
            competition; Renationalization
            abatement,accountability,audits,bond
            markets,bonds,borrowing,capital markets,clean
            fuels,coal,Demand management,distribution systems,economic
            efficiency,electricity,environmental policies,financial
            resources,income,laws,legal framework,Local capital
            markets,marginal cost,marginal cost pricing,market
            competition,oil,operating costs,peak load pricing,population
            growth,pricing policies,Private
            Sector,Privatization,producers,public revenues,supply costs,urbanization,utilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>ECA/MNA Regions Technical Department</owner>
        <repnb>16959</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Renewable Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>