<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 129                                                                                October 1997&#13;
Utility Regulators-Decisionmaking&#13;
Structures, Resources, and Start-up Strategy&#13;
Warick Smith      Governments creating specialized regulatory    Number of decisionmakers&#13;
agencies must make decisions on a wide range&#13;
of issues. Questions relating to the indepen-   Many countries entrust decisionmaking author-&#13;
dence and responsibilities of such agencies are   ity to a commission or board of three to five&#13;
considered in two companion Notes.' This Note   members; others prefer a single individual. Each&#13;
focuses on a third set of issues, relating to   approach has its strengths and weaknesses, and&#13;
decisionmaking structures, resources, and start-  the choice often depends on a country's tradi-&#13;
up strategy. Like the other two Notes, it em-   tions and conditions (table 1). Agencies respon-&#13;
phasizes the situation of developing countries.   sible for several industries usually choose a&#13;
commission.&#13;
Decisionmaking structure&#13;
Selection of regulators&#13;
The design of an agency's decisionmaking&#13;
structure encompasses issues relating to the   When agencies are to be independent, the goal&#13;
number of decisionmakers. the basis for select-  should be to select regulators with the personal&#13;
ing them, the roles accorded to stakeholders,   qualities needed to exercise independent judg-&#13;
and the regulatory and appeals processes.    ment and resist improper pressures or induce-&#13;
ments. The selection is critical, particularly for&#13;
new agencies that have yet to establish a repu-&#13;
TABLE 1   DECISIONMAKING STRUCTURES-INDIVIDUAL             tation for competence and reliability.&#13;
VERSUS COMMISSION&#13;
Strengths and weakniesses                        Qualifications and disqualifications for appoint-&#13;
ment are usually set out in the law establish-&#13;
ing the agency. Disqualifying factors generally&#13;
Characteristic                 Individual Commission       include having a financial interest in regulated&#13;
firms, which creates a conflict of interest and,&#13;
Speed of decisionmaking           El         El            in some countries, being related to the presi-&#13;
Accountabilityfordecisions        El         Cl            dent or ministers. A common qualification re-&#13;
Resource demands                  El         E             quired is significant experience or training in&#13;
Predictability of decisions       El         El            economics, finance, law, public administration,&#13;
Inulnerability to individual preoccupations  E ]           or industry.&#13;
Invulnerability to improper invfluences  El  ElIt is sometimes suggested that some or all ap-&#13;
Potential to reflect multiple perspectives  Cl  E          pointees should have industry-specific techni-&#13;
Potential to stagger ternsto enhance                       cal expertise or long experience in the regulated&#13;
stability and weaken links with particular                industry. But this requirement is unnecessary&#13;
govemments                         l        El            and in some cases undesirable. It is unnecessary&#13;
because such technical expertise will be avail-&#13;
Note: The I indicates which structure is stronger on each characteristic.  able from agency staff or consultants. It is un-&#13;
desirable if it ends up excluding professionals&#13;
WN               The World Bank Group . Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WN                 Utility Regulators-Decisionmaking Structures, Resources, and Start-up Strategy&#13;
with broader perspectives relevant to economic   legislature often also has a role, such as in con-&#13;
regulation or if it unduly restricts the pool of   firming appointments. Involving both branches&#13;
candidates. It is particularly inappropriate for   of government is especially important in sys-&#13;
multi-industry regulators, because requiring ex-   tems in which the executive does not neces-&#13;
pertise in each industry be represented on the    sarily control the legislature; it provides a check&#13;
commission could crowd out appointees with   against partisan appointments and helps to le-&#13;
broader perspectives. It could also result in the    gitimize regulators' authority.&#13;
expert for each industry becoming the de facto&#13;
regulator for that industry and thus the loss of   Stakeholders' roles&#13;
the potential benefits of a commission approach.&#13;
To ensure that a regulatory agency makes de-&#13;
Another view is that the decisionmaking body    cisions that are well informed and accepted as&#13;
should be composed of representatives of   fair and legitimate, consumers, regulated firms&#13;
consumers and regulated firms rather than tech-   and other stakeholders must have the oppor-&#13;
nical experts. Although it is important for stake-   tunity to present their views. For the reasons&#13;
holders to participate in the regulatory process,   noted above, their participation in the decision-&#13;
there are several reasons why including them    making body is inadvisable. But there are sev-&#13;
on the decisionmaking body is inadvisable:     eral other options.&#13;
* In most industries, attempting to identify&#13;
single representatives of consumers and the    Open regulatory processes. Those with a sig-&#13;
industry is not feasible. Residential, indus-   nificant interest in a regulatory decision are usu-&#13;
trial, and rural consumers all have different   ally permitted to present their views to the&#13;
and sometimes conflicting interests, and in-   agency before the decision is made. In the&#13;
terests are likely to vary within these groups   United States, the process for doing so is usu-&#13;
across regions or income classes. Regulated    ally formal hearings, often criticized for being&#13;
firms can also have different and sometimes   too legalistic, costly, and slow. Regulators in the&#13;
conflicting interests in regulatory decisions.   United Kingdom initially adopted much more&#13;
So, a representative approach can result in   informal processes, but the trend now is toward&#13;
pressures to create very large decisionmaking    greater formality. Countries such as Argentina&#13;
bodies, which would increase delays and    and Bolivia are experimenting with open pro-&#13;
reduce individual accountability.             cesses that more closely reflect local traditions.&#13;
* Decisions of representative bodies hinge on&#13;
their composition and voting rules. if the    Consultative or advisory bodies. Some countries&#13;
composition and voting rules favor one in-   have created special consultative or advisory&#13;
terest over another, decisions can be expected    bodies, usually organized on an industry-specific&#13;
to be biased accordingly. If the interests of   basis, to advise the regulator and other public&#13;
consumers and utilities are equally balanced,   authorities. These bodies are usually part-time&#13;
and the casting vote is left to a representa-   and composed of representatives of consum-&#13;
tive of the government, short-term political   ers, utilities, and industry experts. Special con-&#13;
considerations can be expected to dominate   sumer councils can be especially important in&#13;
regulatory decisionmaking.                    countries that lack effective advocacy of con-&#13;
* Representative bodies internalize bargaining    sumer interests.&#13;
and the exchange of concessions between&#13;
interests, at the expense of a more open and    Regulatory process&#13;
transparent evaluation of competing social&#13;
interests.                                    Decisionmaking processes range from formal&#13;
hearings, as in the United States, to more in-&#13;
The executive branch usually plays the domi-   formal processes, such as those in the United&#13;
nant role in the appointment process, but the    Kingdom. Wherever the balance is struck, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
focus should be on transparency in decision-   law, and engineering, and the character and&#13;
making, which reduces opportunities for im-   integrity to resist improper pressures and in-&#13;
proper influences and underscores the fairness   ducements. People with these attributes are&#13;
and legitimacy of decisions.                   scarce in many reforming countries, and those&#13;
who do have them will often receive attractive&#13;
The regulatory process usually involves three   job offers from privatized utilities. So, to at-&#13;
main steps: providing people with an interest   tract and retain well-qualified staff often re-&#13;
in a decision opportunity to present their views,   quires exempting agency staff from restrictive&#13;
publishing the decision and the detailed rea-   civil service salary rules.&#13;
sons for reaching that decision, and providing&#13;
stakeholders an opportunity to challenge the   There is no magic formula for determining the&#13;
decision through an appeals process.           number of staff required by an agency. It all&#13;
depends on the responsibilities of the agency,&#13;
The appeals process is important to ensure that   the climate in which it must discharge those re-&#13;
the regulator does not stray from its mandate   sponsibilities, and its strategies for performing&#13;
and that it remains accountable. Two closely   those tasks. In the United States, staff size ranges&#13;
related issues need to be considered in design-   from less than 40 in the public utilities commis-&#13;
ing an appeals process.                         sions responsible for multiple industries in the&#13;
smaller states to more than 1,000 in the Federal&#13;
Appellate body. If the regulatory agency is to    Energy Regulatory Commission. As a general&#13;
be independent, the appellate body should also    proposition, "small is beautiful." Overstaffing can&#13;
be independent. In most countries, appeals of   dilute an agency's professional focus and in-&#13;
regulatory decisions go straight to the courts.   crease the direct costs of regulation. It can also&#13;
But, in some countries, there is an intermediate   increase the indirect costs of regulation if staff&#13;
step in which appeals go to a body that is ex-   make unnecessary demands on utilities to jus-&#13;
pected to have more technical expertise than the   tify their jobs. For these reasons, a sound gen-&#13;
courts and that may also be able to respond more   eral principle is to keep the permanent agency&#13;
quickly. In the United Kingdom, for example,   staff as small as possible, engaging consultants&#13;
the antitrust agency hears appeals relating to   to assist with specialized tasks.&#13;
license amendments. In Bolivia, a special super-&#13;
intendency hears appeals from sector regulators.   Regulatory agencies increasingly contract out&#13;
tasks to private firms or consultants, such as&#13;
Grounds of appeal. The grounds of appeal are   the analytical work underpinning tariff adjust-&#13;
usually limited to errors of fact or of law, in-   ment and similar decisions and the compliance&#13;
cluding failure to follow a required process.   audits of regulated firms. But the agency must&#13;
Appellate bodies are generally not permitted    retain-and be seen to retain-responsibility&#13;
to reconsider the merits of the decision and    for its decisions, to avoid undermining the legit-&#13;
substitute their own judgment.                 imacy of its actions. It must also ensure that&#13;
the contractor is not subject to improper influ-&#13;
Resources                                      ences or inducements from regulated firms or&#13;
other sources.&#13;
An agency's effectiveness is determined largely&#13;
by the adequacy of its resources, both human    Funding&#13;
and financial.&#13;
Regulatory tasks, like other government func-&#13;
Human resources                                tions, were traditionally funded from general tax&#13;
revenues. Now, most regulatory agencies ob-&#13;
Utility regulation requires personnel with a mix   tain their income from levies on consumers.&#13;
of skills in such fields as economics, finance,   These levies may be charged to consumers di-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Utility Regulators-Decisionmaking Structures, Resources, and Start-up Strategy&#13;
rectly, but are more often collected indirectly    with political authorities, regulated firms, con-&#13;
by imposing a levy or license fee on regulated    sumers, and other stakeholders. In countries&#13;
firms and allowing them to pass the cost on to    in which the requisite skills are scarce, regula-&#13;
consumers through tariffs. In OECD countries,   tory experience is limited, and there is little&#13;
this approach is usually seen as part of a cost-   tradition of independent public institutions, the&#13;
recovery strategy: it reduces demands on gen-    challenges can be daunting. And life is not&#13;
eral tax revenue and imposes the financial costs    made easier for a regulator if privatization re-&#13;
of regulation on the primarv beneficiaries (con-    mains politically contentious and if the first pub-&#13;
sumers). In many developing and transition    lic evidence of its effects is a price increase&#13;
economies, by contrast, earmarked funding is    allowed by the regulator.&#13;
often viewed primarily as a means of ensuring&#13;
that agencies have a reliable source of income    To meet these challenges, regulators must have&#13;
and thus as a safeguard of agency independence.    adequate training-not only in such traditional&#13;
disciplines as law, finance, and economics, but&#13;
To prevent levies from becoming too burden-    also in negotiation analysis, media relations,&#13;
some, the law establishing the agency usually    and the like. Regulators may also need techni-&#13;
sets a cap on levies, often defined by reference    cal support during the first months in office.&#13;
to industry turnover or some other indicator.    Such support is often provided by consultants&#13;
The cap is 0.5 percent for telecomnmunications    acting to some degree as "shadow" regulators.&#13;
regulators in Argentina, Peru, and Venezuela;&#13;
VieWpoint iS an open 1&#13;
forum intended to     1.0 percent for the energy regulator in Colom-    No less important, newly appointed regulators&#13;
encourage dissemina-  bia; and 2.0 percent for the water regulator in    benefit from contacts and exchanges with more&#13;
tion of and debate on  Peru. The cap establishes the maximum  levy,    experienced regulators from  other countries.&#13;
ideas, innovations, and&#13;
best practices forex-  and actual levies are set each year to cover a    Some of these contacts occur on an ad hoc&#13;
panding the private  budget approved by the legislature. When an    basis, through visits and participation in con-&#13;
sector. The views pub-  agency is responsible for more than one    ferences. But there is also an encouraging trend&#13;
lished are those of the&#13;
authors and should not    industry, a different levy is usually set for each    toward systematizing such contacts, for ex-&#13;
be attributed to the  industry that covers the costs of its own regu-    ample, through a "twinning" arrangement be-&#13;
World Bank or any of  lation and contributes to costs shared across    tween a new regulator and a more experienced&#13;
its affiliated organiza-&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the    industries,                                    foreign regulator. These arrangements can pro-&#13;
conclusions represent                                                     vide a basis for exchanging staff and materials&#13;
official policy of the  Start-up strategy                                  or providing other forms of support and ad-&#13;
World Bank or of its&#13;
Executive Directors                                                        vice. There has also been a recent trend to-&#13;
or the countries they  Utility regulators should be established as long    ward creating "networks" of regulators, such&#13;
represent.           before privatization as possible, even if their    as the International Forum  for Utility Regula-&#13;
To order additional  formal powers do not come into effect imme-    tion sponsored by the World Bank.&#13;
copies please call   diately. This allows regulators time to familiar-&#13;
202-458-1111 or contact   ize themselves with their new responsibilities,    'arick Smith, Utility Regulators-The Independence Debate'&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,&#13;
Room FP-1188,        to establish their offices, and to undertake any        (Viewpoint # 127, October 1997) and "Utility Regulators-Rotes&#13;
The World Bank,      necessary training. It also provides assurance          and Responsibilities" (Viewpoint # 128, October 1997).&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,   to consumers that their interests will be pro-&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
or Internet address  tected after privatization and gives potential in-    Warrick Smith (Wsmito3worldbank.org),&#13;
ssmiihl@worldbank.org.   vestors an opportunity to assess the regulatory    Private Participation in Infrastructure Group&#13;
The series is also   system before formulating proposals.&#13;
available on-line&#13;
(www.worldbank.org/&#13;
html/fpd/notes/      Most new  regulatory agencies can expect a&#13;
notelist.html).      challenging infancy. Besides mastering com-&#13;
8 Printed on recycled  plex technical issues, regulators must define&#13;
paper.               new, and often difficult working relationships&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441283">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/10/441283/utility-regulators-decisionmaking-structures-resources-start-up-strategy
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/10/441283/utility-regulators-decisionmaking-structures-resources-start-up-strategy</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/10/441283/utility-regulators-decisionmaking-structures-resources-start-up-strategy</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/17/000009265_3980319100204/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/17/000009265_3980319100204/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>1999-08-17T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1997-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Utility regulators : decisionmaking
            structures, resources, and start-up strategy
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The design of a regulatory agency's
            decisionmaking structure encompasses issues relating to the
            number of decisionmakers, the basis for selecting them, the
            role played by stakeholders, and the regulatory and appeals
            processes. The selection of the regulator is
            critical--especially in countries that have yet to establish
            a reputation for competence and reliability. When agencies
            are to be independent, the goal should be to select
            regulators with the personal qualities needed to exercise
            independent judgement and resist improper pressures. An
            appeals process is also important to ensure that the
            regulator does not stray from its mandate and that it
            remains accountable. The author outlines good practice.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Utility regulators : decisionmaking
            structures, resources, and start-up strategy
        </docna>
        <display_title>Utility regulators :
            decisionmaking structures, resources, and start-up strategy</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1997/10/441283/utility-regulators-decisionmaking-structures-resources-start-up-strategy</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation,Administrative &amp; Regulatory Law,Community Development and Empowerment,National Governance,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Water Resources,Law and Development,Governance,Social Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Smith, Warrick</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980319100204</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Institutional Development</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 129</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Water Resources,Law and Development,Governance,Social Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Institution building; Developing countries;
            Stockholders; Decision making; Human resources; Financial
            resources; Training; Recruitment; Regulatory agency
            accountability,antitrust,assurance,authority,beneficiaries,cap,consumers,councils,decisionmaking,Human
            resources,integrity,legislature,legitimacy,ministers,private
            firms,public administration,public
            institutions,regulator,regulators,Regulatory
            agencies,regulatory agency,regulatory
            process,representatives,tax revenues,transparency,Utility regulation,voting
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>17421</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Energy and Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Telecommunications and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships in Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Participation in Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>