<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank                                                                      December 1995&#13;
Note No.63   End of the Line for the Local Loop&#13;
Monopoly?&#13;
Technology, competition, and investment in telecom networks&#13;
Peter Smith      Local telephone service is the last bastion of a still frequently asserted public policy preference&#13;
for monopoly provision of telecommunications. This Note challenges the rationale for that prefer-&#13;
ence, addressing four issues: First, is local network competition feasible from a technical and cost&#13;
point of view? Second, is telecommunications competition accepted by major investors? Third,&#13;
how important is competition from a public policy point of view? And fourth, briefly, how can it&#13;
be made to work?&#13;
A traditional and now outdated view in the tele-   Thus, the cellular operators installed about 35&#13;
communications sector is that competition   percent of all new lines last year, a surpris-&#13;
is suitable for terminal equipment, for value-  ingly high percentage. These cellular opera-&#13;
added services, and possibly for long-distance  tors contributed significantly to the expansion&#13;
telephone service after universal service is  of telephone service in Sri Lanka-and dem-&#13;
achieved-but not for local telephone service.   onstrated the transition of cellular service from&#13;
This position is usually accompanied by the   a small, specialized, premium part of the mar-&#13;
view that cellular mobile telephony is not local   ket to a substitute for conventional service.&#13;
telephone service (which it clearly is) but a&#13;
separate "mobile" market segment.         Feasibility and viability&#13;
A modified traditional view is that local service   To assess the feasibility and viability of local&#13;
competition is appropriate only for large mar-  network competition, we need to review two&#13;
kets (such as the United Kingdom) and in rich   groups of factors: first, technology and the cost&#13;
countries that have already achieved universal   characteristics of different technologies; and&#13;
service (for example, Finland, New Zealand,  second, the views of investors, since it is no&#13;
and the United Kingdom). This is wrong. Even   good being right about the technology if in-&#13;
in a relatively small market such as Sri Lanka,  vestors don't believe in it.&#13;
local network competition is beneficial. Sri&#13;
Lanka has four cellular operators and some of   The choice of technologies for the provision&#13;
the lowest cellular telephone service prices in   of local telephone service is now broader than&#13;
the world. In 1994, the number of telephone   ever. There are several wireless options: ana-&#13;
lines in the country increased by about 47,000.  log and digital cellular radio, digital cordless&#13;
Of these, about 30,000 were conventional lines  telephony (for example, Digital European&#13;
provided by state-owned Sri Lanka Telecom-   Cordless Telecommunications, or DECT), pro-&#13;
a record increase. The remaining 17,000 lines   prietary (noncellular) wireless local loop sys-&#13;
came from the provision of cellular service.  tems such as lonica (being installed in Finland),&#13;
Industry and Energy Department . Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
End of the Line for the Local Loop Monopoly?&#13;
and mobile satellite. There are also fiber-optic    many of these transactions, a policy decision&#13;
cable TV options, and hybrid solutions com-   has been made to continue monopoly rights,&#13;
bining, for example, cable TV and DECT.         sometimes on the basis of an investment bank's&#13;
recommendations. In Mexico, Argentina, and&#13;
Figure 1 compares lifetime costs for two ge-   Venezuela, for example, exclusivity periods of&#13;
neric technologies: traditional underground    six, seven, and nine years were granted. In&#13;
copper cable and wireless. The figure is, of   these and other cases, privatization advisers&#13;
course, simplified and generalized, showing just   have made recommendations that do not nec-&#13;
one cost line for each technology. (The wire-   essarily lead to the best public policy for the&#13;
less cost curve is for Global System Mobile, or   development of the telecommunications sec-&#13;
tor as a whole.&#13;
But do investors think that network competi-&#13;
FIGURE 1                                ----    ~~~~~~~~~tion poses unacceptable risks? Apparently not.&#13;
wmaE$SLVEHSISBWIRtUNE -----  ---In New Zealand, Telecom NZ was successfully&#13;
privatized in a policy environment of open en-&#13;
try in all market segments. In the Philippines,&#13;
foreign investors such as NYNEX, Cable &amp; Wire-&#13;
less, and Telstra have entered-or are prepar-&#13;
ing to enter-the market as competitors or&#13;
Goat                                         ~~~~~~~~~~~~~partners of competitors. In Mexico, a large&#13;
domestic cellular operator with support from&#13;
..J~$!!'~" ~    Bell Atlantic has proposed installing a fixed&#13;
Uftdegrnho~pprabIawireless network to serve 1.5 million custom-&#13;
ers. In southern Tndia, US West has proposed a&#13;
"'=-'.'==-''='--r9- '=i:= 'telecom build-own-operate scheme and has not&#13;
tscrionsity{sbhsc$b''erscj333e*ita                 3'te6  asked for an exclusive franchise. Other ex-&#13;
amples show that investors have accepted com-&#13;
f  , -  z -  -r    petition in Australia, Malaysia, Sweden, the&#13;
United Kingdom, and the United States and in&#13;
the cellular market of almost every country.&#13;
GSM, cellular.) Actual cost structures vary ac-   Why competition is so important&#13;
cording to the technology, market, topography,&#13;
network configuration, and grade of service.   Many of the benefits of telecommunications&#13;
Nevertheless, the figure shows that in areas of   competition are well known-lower costs,&#13;
low subscriber density (fewer than 250 to 300   lower prices, greater innovation. Less recog-&#13;
subscribers per square kilometer), wireless sys-   nized and more important benefits, however,&#13;
tems have lower costs. Furthermore, because    particularly for developing countries with sig-&#13;
wireless costs are falling relative to the costs   nificant underinvestment in the sector, are in-&#13;
of cable systems, the crossover point is mov-   creased investment and better service.&#13;
ing to the right. Thus, wireless systems are be-&#13;
coming more competitive, in larger parts of the    By way of comparison, the alleged benefits of&#13;
market, every year.                             exclusive franchises are short-term stability in&#13;
a difficult privatization environment (as in Ar-&#13;
What do investors think?                        gentina in 1990), higher profits, and more in-&#13;
vestment ("no one will invest unless you grant&#13;
The issue of exclusivity often arises in the con-   them a monopoly"). In some cases, it is true&#13;
text of telecommunications privatizations. In   that a very short period of exclusivity (say, one&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
year) can contribute to stability in a difficult  tant in many countries. Finland has authorized&#13;
environment. But the second alleged benefit,   duopolistic competition in the provision of both&#13;
higher profits, is not, of course, a customer   local and long-distance service, and Indonesia's&#13;
benefit. Thus, the question of whether compe-   government has authorized Ratelindo to pro-&#13;
tition or monopoly is tlle better public policy   vide fixed wireless local loop service in the&#13;
in an environment of underinvestment hinges   Jakarta and Bandung areas of West Java. Local&#13;
on which leads to more investment. This is   network competition is also pending in India,&#13;
really an empirical question. But it seems likely   Mexico, and Sri Lanka and could become very&#13;
that competition will stimulate more investment,  important in China.&#13;
because it opens more channels for investment,&#13;
and it creates incentives to invest to meet de-&#13;
mand-companies that do not invest will risk&#13;
losing market share. This stimulus is exactly      - ;      t &#13;
iFIGUFt 2 ANiNUAL INESTMENT BY, PLOT. i99G-94:&#13;
what is needed in countries with chronic under-&#13;
investment in telecommunications-such as             Milion of constant US dollars&#13;
Bangladesh, India, the Philippines, and Sri&#13;
Lanka. Two examples from Ghana and the Phil-&#13;
ippines confirm the expectation that competi-&#13;
tion will stimulate investment in the sector.&#13;
4si&#13;
Ghana, a small West African country with less&#13;
than 20 million people and low per capita in-&#13;
come, is regarded as a relatively high-risk loca-&#13;
tion by some foreign investors. In 1992, a small,      30.&#13;
mainly foreign-owned cellular operator, Mobitel,&#13;
began operations in the capital, Accra. Mobitel's&#13;
business plan called for it to extend service to  :___2__ ;_._.___._                     i_L___-_-_-&#13;
Kumasi, the second main city, only when the                ;        1S9          Z "a     1993       1994&#13;
required investment could be financed out of&#13;
retained earnings. This decision changed in 1994.    SoIWe:AuterscaIcuaIonsAased onPT annual rts.&#13;
Mobitel rushed to provide service in Kumasi af-&#13;
ter a new operator, Celltel, announced plans to&#13;
provide service in both Accra and Kumasi within&#13;
a few months. Furthermore, Mobitel has halved    How to make it work&#13;
its connection charges since Celltel began op-&#13;
erations earlier this year.                    For competition to work, new entrants need&#13;
reasonable interconnection, reasonable prices,&#13;
In the Philippines, the threat of competition   telephone numbers, and, often, radio licenses-&#13;
similarly prompted a quick response from the   in a sense, all technical issues with technical&#13;
main telephone service provider, PLDT. Only   solutions. But even more important is that the&#13;
in 1993-after PLDT came to believe that the   government must have the will to enforce rea-&#13;
government was serious about authorizing new    sonable rules of competition in the sector. This&#13;
entrants to provide local telephone service on   is particularly clear in the case of interconnec-&#13;
a large scale-did it announce its "zero back-   tion, where, in the absence of effective regula-&#13;
log program." PLDT's investment program    tion, "strategic" conduct by the incumbent&#13;
turned sharply upward after 1993 (figure 2).    telephone company can hinder or prevent new&#13;
entry. For a new entrant to interconnect its net-&#13;
These are not isolated examples. The issue of   work with that of the incumbent, it needs in-&#13;
local network competition is becoming impor-   formation on the type of equipment that exists&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
End of the Line for the Local Loop Monopoly?&#13;
at different interconnection points. The incum-&#13;
bent can impede interconnection by providing&#13;
no information, wrong information, or changed&#13;
information. It can make only a limited num-&#13;
ber of interconnection points available, forc-&#13;
ing the new entrant to send traffic along&#13;
unnecessarily long routes. The incumbent may&#13;
lease lines to new entrants that are incorrectly&#13;
dimensioned and unreliable. And it may pro-&#13;
vide revenue settlement arrangements that are&#13;
unsatisfactory, and make payments late. In&#13;
short, without effective regulation, an incum-&#13;
bent can keep new entrants out of the busi-&#13;
ness-and put them out of business.&#13;
Conclusion&#13;
This Note has made the case that local net-&#13;
work competition is increasingly feasible from&#13;
a technical and cost point of view, that it is&#13;
increasingly accepted by investors, and that it&#13;
offers important benefits from a public policy&#13;
The Note series is an      point of view-particularly  its potential to&#13;
open forum intended to     stimulate investment. But in order to work, it&#13;
encourage dissemina-       must be  supported  by  effective  regulation.&#13;
tion of and debate on      Much work remains to be done in many coun-&#13;
ideas, innovations, and&#13;
best practices for         tries to  move toward  a competitive telecom-&#13;
expanding the private      munications  sector. Policymakers  should  be&#13;
sector. The views          encouraged to address the critical issues of this&#13;
published are those of                     to a           t      r       i&#13;
the authors and should     transition-and  discouraged  from  losing time&#13;
not be attributed to the   on counterproductive efforts to maintain mo-&#13;
World Bank or any of its   nopolies in this dynamic sector.&#13;
affiliated organizations.&#13;
Nor do any of the con-&#13;
clusions represent         References&#13;
official policy of the     Gareth Evans, Steve Carter, Stuart Macintosh, and others. 1995. "Key&#13;
World Bank or of its         Technological and Policy Options for the Telecommunications&#13;
Executive Directors          Sector in Central and Eastem Europe and the Former Soviet Union.&#13;
or the countries they        Paper prepared for the European Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
represent.                   Development. Coopers and Lybrand, London.&#13;
Peter Smith and Gregory Staple. 1994. Telecommunications Sector&#13;
Comments are welcome.        Reform in Asia-Toward a New Pragmatism. World Bank Discus-&#13;
Please call the FPD          sion Paper 232. Washington, D.C.&#13;
Note line to leave a       OECD. 1995. Telecommunications Infrastructure-The Benefits of&#13;
message (202-458-1111)       Competition. Paris.&#13;
or contact Suzanne&#13;
Smith, editor, Room&#13;
G8105, The World Bank,     Peter Smith, Senior Telecommunications Policy&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,         Specialist, Industry and Energy Department&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
or Internet address&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.&#13;
$Printed on recycled&#13;
paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441235">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/12/441235/end-line-local-loop-monopoly-technology-competition-investment-telecom-networks
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/12/441235/end-line-local-loop-monopoly-technology-competition-investment-telecom-networks</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/12/441235/end-line-local-loop-monopoly-technology-competition-investment-telecom-networks</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/10/000009265_3980420172824/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/10/000009265_3980420172824/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>1999-09-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1995-12-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            End of the line for the local loop
            monopoly? technology, competition, and investment in telecom networks
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Local telephone service is the last
            bastion of a still frequently asserted public policy
            preference for monopoly provision of telecommunications.
            This Note challenges the rationale for that preference,
            addressing four issues: First, is local network competition
            feasible from a technical and cost point of view? Second, is
            telecommunications competition accepted by major investors?
            Third, how important is competition from a public policy
            point of view? And fourth, how can it be made to work? This
            Note makes the case that local network competition is
            increasingly feasible from a technical and cost point of
            view, that it is increasingly accepted by investors, and
            that it offers important benefits from a public policy point
            of view. But in order to work, it must be supported by
            effective regulation. Policymakers should be encouraged to
            address the critical issues of this transition toward a
            competitive telecommunications sector.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            End of the line for the local loop monopoly?
            technology, competition, and investment in telecom networks
        </docna>
        <display_title>End of the line for the local
            loop monopoly? technology, competition, and investment in
            telecom networks</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1995/12/441235/end-line-local-loop-monopoly-technology-competition-investment-telecom-networks</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Telecommunications Infrastructure,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,ICT Policy and Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Information and Communication Technologies,Conflict and Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Smith, Peter</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980420172824</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Telecommunications &amp; Informatics</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 63</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Information and Communication Technologies,Conflict and Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Information and communications</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Telephone networks; Costs; Technology;
            Investments; Denationalization; Government policy;
            Monopolies; Market competition; Local telephone networks; Telecommunications
            affiliated organizations,ber,cellular
            operators,cellular radio,foreign
            investors,innovations,monopoly,mov,policy
            environment,radio,retained
            earnings,telecom,telecommunications,Telecommunications
            Infrastructure,Telecommunications Policy,Telecommunications
            Sector,telephone,telephone numbers,telephone
            service,telephony,text,universal service
        </keywd>
        <owner>ECA/MNA Regions Technical Department</owner>
        <repnb>16922</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications Competition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Backbone Telecommunications Infrastructure Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications Sector Competition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>