<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank Group                                                                  February 1997&#13;
Note No. 105  Extending Telecommunications Service&#13;
to Rural Areas-The Chilean Experience&#13;
Awarding subsidies through competitive bidding&#13;
Bjdrn Wellenius    Private sector-led, competitive markets are re-   Nonetheless, about 1.5 million people-10 per-&#13;
placing traditional public telecommunications   cent of all Chileans-live in localities that do&#13;
monopolies in emerging and mature econo-   not even have a public telephone. Some 500,000&#13;
mies alike. As operators focus on the most prof-   households-a sixth of the total-will not be&#13;
itable market segments, some policymakers   able to afford telephone connections in the fore-&#13;
worry that the government will be left to shoul-  seeable future. To increase access to public tele-&#13;
der the burden of providing service to rural   phones in rural and low-income urban areas,&#13;
areas. But there is growing evidence that un-  the Chilean government set up a special fund&#13;
der liberal entry, investment, and pricing poli-  in 1994. The fund, with a limited life and due to&#13;
cies, rural telecommunications can be good   expire in 1998, is financed by the national bud-&#13;
business. New technologies are making it easier   get and administered by a council chaired by&#13;
to reach low-density and remote localities. Still,  the telecommunications minister. The council&#13;
pockets of population may remain without ser-  decides on the annual program of projects eli-&#13;
vice because of the exceptionally high cost and   gible for subsidy and awards the projects and&#13;
low revenue potential of providing service to  subsidies through competitive bidding.&#13;
them. How large is this gap, how can it be&#13;
bridged, and who pays? Recent experience in   Eligible projects&#13;
Chile suggests some answers.&#13;
The council's secretariat, the sector regulator&#13;
Chile's Telecommunications                Subsecretaria de Telecomunicaciones (SUBTEL),&#13;
Development Fund                          compiled a first roster of about 2,300 rural lo-&#13;
calities needing public telephones based on a&#13;
Chile's telecommunications market is one of  survey of provincial and local authorities, neigh-&#13;
the most open and competitive in the world.   borhood associations, telephone companies,&#13;
Following privatization of the main telecom-   and the general public. SUBTEL then grouped&#13;
munications companies in the late 1980s, the   these localities into projects according to geo-&#13;
number of telephone lines quadrupled to more   graphical proximity and technical solutions&#13;
than 2 million today. Competition introduced   likely to be cost-effective and did a cost-ben-&#13;
in the late 1980s in data, value added, and cable  efit analysis to estimate the subsidy needed, if&#13;
TV services and private networks, and since   any, to install one public telephone in each&#13;
1994 in domestic and international long-dis-  locality.' Projects that looked commercially&#13;
tance telephony, has brought about rapid net-  viable without subsidy were brought to the at-&#13;
work modernization, new services, and prices  tention of telecommunications operating com-&#13;
that are among the world's lowest. Competi-  panies and the business community; existing&#13;
tion in local services is intensifying, mainly from    and new operators can apply for licenses to&#13;
long-distance carriers starting wireline and wire-  serve these localities. Projects that had a posi-&#13;
less local service and from combined voice and   tive social net present value (NPV) but were&#13;
cable television offerings.               not commercially viable were ranked by social&#13;
Industry and Energy Department. Finance, Private Sector, and infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Extending Telecommunications Service to Rural Areas-The Chilean Experience&#13;
NPV per unit of subsidy needed to make them    minute calls. The maximums are tied through a&#13;
viable and by other factors.                 formula to published indices (wholesale prices,&#13;
cost of labor, and foreign exchange) and the&#13;
The fund's first round, initiated in 1995, con-   corporate tax rate for the full ten years of ser-&#13;
sisted of the forty-six highest-ranked projects,   vice. Licensees must post the call charges in each&#13;
whose estimated subsidy requirements added   telephone and inform SUBTEL of any changes.&#13;
up to the fund's 1995 budget of US$4.3 mil-&#13;
lion. These projects covered 1,285 localities   The maximum subsidy available from the fund&#13;
throughout the country. The localities typically   for each project ranged from  US$300 to&#13;
have fewer than 1,000 inhabitants-the aver-   US$26,000 per locality and averaged US$3,340.&#13;
age is 360-and are located within roughly 50   The subsidy, in current pesos with no adjust-&#13;
kilometers (30 miles) of existing telecommuni-   ment for inflation, is paid in a lump sum once&#13;
cations facilities. Once complete, these projects  the facilities have been built and have been&#13;
will provide access to basic telecommunica-   inspected by SUBTEL. Thus, the licensee has&#13;
tions services for about 460,000 people, a third   both a contractual obligation and an incentive&#13;
of the population now without access.        to initiate service quickly. Projects are not eli-&#13;
gible for any further subsidies.&#13;
Terms&#13;
The bidding process and its results&#13;
The bidding documents set the terms and con-&#13;
ditions for all projects: the service obligations,   Public invitations to bid for each of the forty-six&#13;
tariffs, interconnection principles, requirements   projects were issued in October 1995. Each&#13;
for bidders, bidding procedures, and rules for   project would be awarded to the bidder asking&#13;
awarding bids. The documents also listed the   for the lowest subsidy. Bids could propose ad-&#13;
projects, giving for each one the location, the   ditional services, in the project locations or else-&#13;
number of public telephones required, and the   where, but these proposals would not be taken&#13;
maximum subsidy available.2 The winning bid-   into account in the evaluation. Existing telecom-&#13;
der for each project is granted a nonexclusive   munications companies as well as prospective&#13;
operating license within sixty days and must   new providers meeting minimum legal require-&#13;
provide at least one public telephone in each   ments could bid. Thirty companies purchased&#13;
locality for ten years, available to the public  the bidding documents. Bids were opened in&#13;
every day, twenty-four hours a day. Service   public in December 1995, and the results an-&#13;
must begin six to twenty months after the li-   nounced in March 1996. Bidders made sixty-&#13;
cense has been granted.                      two offers for forty-two of the forty-six projects,&#13;
covering most localities. The fund committed&#13;
The choice of technology, network structure,   only 48 percent of its 1995 budget to achieve&#13;
and location of the public telephones is left to   about 90 percent of its program, largely because&#13;
the licensee. SUBTEL processes applications for   bids for zero subsidy were made for sixteen&#13;
any radio frequencies required concurrently with   projects (accounting for 51 percent of localities&#13;
the operating license. The installations must   and 59 percent of the population). Most of the&#13;
comply with the technical and interconnection   other projects were bid at or near the maximum&#13;
standards applicable to all telecommunications   available subsidy (table 1). About 75 percent of&#13;
networks. The licensee is free to set the call  localities were in projects bid at US$5,000 or&#13;
charges subject to a maximum (specified in the   less per locality (table 2).&#13;
bidding documents) equivalent to US$0.07 per&#13;
minute for a five-minute call to any telephone   Competitive entry was the main factor driving&#13;
within the same primary service area.3 This com-   down the subsidy. Chilesat, a long-distance car-&#13;
pares with about us$0.05 per minute for five-   rier seeking to develop local networks, bid zero&#13;
minute local calls from urban coin-operated   subsidy for each of those sixteen projects.&#13;
telephones. Higher charges are allowed for   Chilesat outbid Companiia de Telecomunica-&#13;
shorter calls, up to US$0.13 per minute for one-   ciones de Chile (CTC), the largest local telephone&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 1  LOWEST Big1$ RECEIVED FOR THE 1995 RURAL PROGRAM&#13;
Projects               Lclte                    naiat&#13;
Level ol lowest bid            Nmr        PeetNumber    errcent                  umbr    Percent&#13;
At niaximum substidy             1            9493.1780                                      2&#13;
Below Maximnunsubsit*             8          17            43         3           9,3W        2&#13;
Alosubsiy                        '16         35           659        51         25905&#13;
NoI~~~~~~id            4 ~~~~~9                180       144.0)                   I&#13;
Total                    49         100          145        10(1        402,000     101&#13;
Saurnce:SIJBEL&#13;
operator, in eight of those projects. And it tied&#13;
with CTC in the other eight. Because the bid-&#13;
TABLE 2  AVERAGE SUBgSIDY PER LOCALITY tN Th4E LOWES&#13;
ding documents contained no provisions for&#13;
resolving ties, these projects were not awarded.                BlDS FOR TE1995 RURAL PROGRAM&#13;
By mid-1996, CTC applied to extend its current&#13;
license to include all eight unawarded projects.Avresusd&#13;
(US$)                  Projecft           Locallities&#13;
Besides entry and defensive strategies, observ-&#13;
ers cite other factors that motivated CTC and          0                        19656&#13;
Chilesat and that may explain why these com-                                     3        ON103&#13;
panies had not already moved into markets for          ZM-5AKJ                  !5                214&#13;
which they were prepared to bid zero subsidy.&#13;
The bidding process documented the existence                                     99&#13;
of demand and willingness to pay in m-any small,                                                   365&#13;
scattered localities that had not yet caught the       NO bid                    4                180&#13;
operators' attention. Call charges exceeding           TOta                     46               1,285&#13;
those authorized in cities made the projects vi-&#13;
able with limited subsidies. Once a public tele-        oe:UTL&#13;
phone in one locality is made viable by a&#13;
subsidy, other services can be provided in that&#13;
locality and others at low marginal cost and for   foothold in CNT's territory. Empresa Nacional&#13;
significantly higher returns. And the sixty-day    de Telecomunicaciones (ENTEL), the country's&#13;
turnaround for processing new operating and    main long-distance carrier and already exten-&#13;
radio licenses compared very favorably with one    sively involved in rural areas, also did not&#13;
year or more for extending existing licenses,     participate. And the program did not create new&#13;
players. A small company established to enter&#13;
Parts of the program, however, did not benefit   the rural mark-et bid for one project but lost to&#13;
much from  competition. CTC bid at or near   the incumbent operator.&#13;
the maximum available subsidy for twenty-three&#13;
projects in provinces where it faced no chal-   Lessons&#13;
lengers. And it won three other projects by a&#13;
slight margin against a small local operator, with    The Chilean experience suggests a number of&#13;
both companies bidding close to the maximum.   lessons that may be broadly applicable in other&#13;
Some operators that were expected to bid did    emerging economies:&#13;
not participate. Compafiia Nacional de Tel-        The key to accelerating rural telecommuni-&#13;
fonos (CNT), a regional operator, did not bid      cations development is competition. An en-&#13;
for any projects, even in its own region, which    vironment that encourages new entry and&#13;
opened the way for CTC and Chilesat to gain a      competition can go a long way toward meet-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Extending Telecommunications Service to Rural Areas-The Chilean Experience&#13;
ing basic telecommunications needs in rural    inhabitants. The US$2.2 million savings from&#13;
areas on commercial terms.                              1995 have been rolled over, resulting in a total&#13;
- Given the right policy environment, limited             budget for 1996 of about US$8.8 million. But&#13;
government subsidies suffice to close gaps    the amount of subsidy for each location is likely&#13;
between the commercial and social objec-    to increase. The four projects for which no bids&#13;
tives of rural telecommunications develop-    were received in 1995 need a higher subsidy to&#13;
ment. The fund's 1995 commitment was less    attract offers. Project locations are likely to be&#13;
than 0.5 percent of telecommunications rev-    farther away from  existing facilities, increasing&#13;
enues countrywide.                                      the cost and possibly generating lower revenues.&#13;
* Market forces can determine which projects    And while a one-time subsidy to offset part of&#13;
really need subsidy and how much. Competi-    the initial investment cost appeared to suffice&#13;
tive bidding following established administra-    in the first round, in the future some projects&#13;
tive procedures and subject to independent    may need a subsidy for annual operating costs.&#13;
judicial review  can keep political pressures           In such cases, SUBTEL would probably prefer&#13;
largely at bay. The Chilean bidding process    to lump the present value of all recurrent subsi-&#13;
left little room  for discretion in the awards.    dies into a single initial payment.&#13;
Cost-benefit analysis was used only for the&#13;
initial screening  of projects, to determine            With successful completion of the 1996 round,&#13;
roughly how  much subsidy the government    more than 97 percent of Chileans will likely&#13;
should be prepared to pay and which projects            have access to basic telecommunications by&#13;
should go first. But limited competition for    1998, and the fund may well have a surplus.&#13;
the projects meant that in many cases the sub-    Given Chile's strong market orientation, it is&#13;
open forum intended to    sidy awarded was the maximum  available-                unlikely that the government would use the&#13;
encourage dissemina-      set by the study, not the market.                       fund to subsidize regular business or residen-&#13;
tion of and debate on  - In a competitive environment, small subsi-    tial telephone connections or use. But the fund&#13;
ideas, innovations, and&#13;
best practices for        dies can  give tremendous leverage. The                 and its market-oriented approach could be used&#13;
expanding the private     fund's US$2.1 million commitment of public    to stimulate the provision of lifeline telephone&#13;
sector.The views          money for the 1995 program  triggered pri-    service to low-income households, improve&#13;
published are those of&#13;
the authors and should    vate  telecommunications investments of    telephone access for disabled people, and ex-&#13;
not be attributed to the  about US$40 million. These investments in-    tend Internet connectivity to public schools,&#13;
World Bank or any of its  clude additional facilities offered by the bid-    health centers, and libraries.&#13;
affiliated organizations.&#13;
Nor do any of the con-    ders, more than twice what was required by&#13;
clusions represent       the projects. The US$2.1 million will result    The auhor gratefully acknowledges the help of Gregorio San Marti,&#13;
official policy of the    in 1,285 rural public telephones, averaging             Oscar Cabello, and Claudio Gambardella in documenting and dis-&#13;
World Bank or of its&#13;
Executive Directors       US$1,634 per telephone. By contrast, in the             cussing material used in this Note.&#13;
or the countries they     1980s, the government paid the incumbent                  The planning inirstry's standard method for social and private evalu-&#13;
ation of prujects was adapted for use with clusters of localities.&#13;
represent.                operators US$6 million to install only 300                Simple assumptions were made. For example, operating revenue&#13;
To order additional       rural public telephones, averaging US$20,000.             was forecast as a percentage of average income. The results, while&#13;
copies please call 202-  * Errors of analysis in the worst case lead only           subjcat to error, are helieved to he good enough for initial classifi-&#13;
canion of projects and rough determination of maximum suhsidies.&#13;
458-1111 or contact      to errors of timing. The four projects that had          2 In all cases, the maximum subsidy was less than the estimated&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,&#13;
Room G8105, The Worid     no bidders, presumably because the maximum                initial cost.&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street,      subsidy wa    o    o,will be included agi                 Chile is divided into tiwenry-four primary service areas. The call&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street,   subsldy was too low, wllbe  ncldedagain  charge for the subsidized rural telephones allows users to call&#13;
NW, Washington, D.C.      next year with higher subsidy limits. Projects            anywhere within their primary service area, including the provin-&#13;
20433, or Internet&#13;
address ssmith7e          deemed viable but that eventually fail to be              cial capital and several municipal centers. Calls beyond this area&#13;
worldbank.org.            undertaken on a commercial basis may be re-               are charged as long distance.&#13;
The series is also        considered for subsidy in following years.&#13;
available on-line                                                                 Bj6rn Wellenius, Telecommunications Adviser,&#13;
(www.worldbank.InutyadEegDeamet(wlnis&#13;
org/html/fpd/notes/    The next rounds-1996 and beyond                            IndustandEnergyDepartment(bwellenius@&#13;
notelist.html).                                                                   worldbank.org)&#13;
&amp;Printed on recycled   The fund's second round, begun in August 1996,&#13;
paper.                 covers almost 2,500 localities with about 500,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441230">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/02/441230/extending-telecommunications-service-rural-areas-chilean-experience-awarding-subsidies-through-competitive-bidding
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/02/441230/extending-telecommunications-service-rural-areas-chilean-experience-awarding-subsidies-through-competitive-bidding</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/02/441230/extending-telecommunications-service-rural-areas-chilean-experience-awarding-subsidies-through-competitive-bidding</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/10/000009265_3980420172730/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/10/000009265_3980420172730/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>1999-09-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1997-02-28T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Extending telecommunications service to
            rural areas - the Chilean experience : awarding subsidies
            through competitive bidding
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Chile's telecommunications market
            is one of the most open and competitive in the world.
            Nevertheless, about 10 percent of all Chileans that live in
            localities do not even have a public telephone. To increase
            access to public telephones in rural and low-income urban
            areas, the Chilean government set up a special fund in 1994.
            The fund, due to expire in 1998, is financed by the national
            budget and administered by a council chaired by the
            telecommunications minister. The council decides on the
            annual program of projects eligible for subsidy and awards
            the projects and subsidies through competitive bidding. The
            fund's second round began in August 1996. With
            successful completion of the 1996 round, more than 97
            percent of Chileans will likely have access to basic
            telecommunications by 1998, and the fund may well have a
            surplus. This Note describes the Chilean experience and the
            lessons that may be broadly applicable in other emerging economies.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Extending telecommunications service to
            rural areas - the Chilean experience : awarding subsidies
            through competitive bidding
        </docna>
        <display_title>Extending telecommunications
            service to rural areas - the Chilean experience : awarding
            subsidies through competitive bidding</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1997/02/441230/extending-telecommunications-service-rural-areas-chilean-experience-awarding-subsidies-through-competitive-bidding</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,ICT Policy and Strategies,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Public Sector Economics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Communities and Human Settlements,Information and Communication Technologies,Public Sector Development,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Chile</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Wellenius, Bjorn</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980420172730</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Telecommunications &amp; Informatics</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 105</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Communities and Human Settlements,Information and Communication Technologies,Public Sector Development,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Information and communications</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Subsidies; Telephone services; Development
            finance; Rural areas; Procurement; Rural telecommunication
            systems; Emerging economies; Licenscee; Telecommunications; Localities
            accounting,cities,competitive
            bidding,competitive environment,competitive markets,foreign
            exchange,households,income,inflation,inhabitants,innovations,libraries,licenses,limited
            competition,marginal cost,operating costs,operating
            revenue,phones,present value,Private
            sector,privatization,provisions,radio,rural areas,rural
            telecommunications,rural
            telephones,savings,tax,telecommunications,telecommunications
            investments,telephone access,telephone companies,telephone
            connections,telephone lines,telephones,television,urban areas
        </keywd>
        <owner>ECA/MNA Regions Technical Department</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>16895</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Connectivity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lagging Regions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Connectivity and Lagging Regions</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Chile</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>