<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>1T a 8z&#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank Group                                                                     October 1996&#13;
Note No.96   Competition in Telecoms-Implications&#13;
for Universal Service and Employment&#13;
Ben A. Petrazzini  Despite the huge opportunities opening up   vided by a monopoly carrier, and this basic&#13;
from new technology, competitive markets, and   telephony is still out of reach for most of the&#13;
the globalization of production and trade, gov-   population. The reluctance to open monopoly&#13;
erninents in many emerging economies have   markets to competition arises from fears about&#13;
been reluctant to introduce much competition   what it means for universal service, employ-&#13;
in their domestic telecommunications markets.   ment, and the viability of the incumbent na-&#13;
Services are largely restricted to basic voice pro-   tional carrier. This Note argues that these&#13;
concerns are misplaced. The arrival of new&#13;
technologies and new services means that the&#13;
real issue for government is not whether to&#13;
FIGURE 1  CELLULAR TELEDENSITY IN DEVELOPING            liberalize but when and how.&#13;
COUNTRIES OF ASIA AND LATIN AMERICA&#13;
Main lines per lO0 inhabitants                          Universal service&#13;
In practice, there is little evidence that compe-&#13;
0.8         .             .Competitive markets         tition puts universal service at risk. Most of the&#13;
0.6                          +                            _ available data point to an increase in network&#13;
0.4                                                     penetration and service availability with&#13;
~ Monopoly m a       rkets }   competition.&#13;
0.2                              Moopl markt&#13;
o                         |   .               l        Competition in cellular services, which has been&#13;
1991          1992           1993           1994       introduced more widely and for longer than&#13;
Source: Petrazzini and Clark 1996.                      competition in wireline services in developing&#13;
countries, clearly has led to much greater net-&#13;
work penetration than monopolies. In Asia and&#13;
FIGURE 2  TELECOM EMPLOYMENT IN DEVELOPING              Latin America, for example, teledensity-the&#13;
COUNTRIES OF ASIA AND LATIN AMERICA            number of main lines per 100 inhabitants-has&#13;
Employment Jnormalizedi                                 risen more rapidly in competitive markets (fig-&#13;
(inidex: 1990=100J                                      ure 1). In the OECD countries competitive cel-&#13;
120                                 }                   lular markets have achieved a teledensitv three&#13;
times higher than monopoly markets and cellu-&#13;
________                      Competitivemre          lar teledensitv in markets with competition in&#13;
both cellular service and the public switched&#13;
1000 - Monopoly markets  telephone network (PSTN) is twice that in those&#13;
with competition only in cellular services (OECD&#13;
I________________ _________________  j1996b). The indirect competition from cellular&#13;
199w      1991        1992       1993       1994       service has had a positive side effect on wire-&#13;
Soutrce.ITU 1995.                                       line teledensity, promoting greater wireline net-&#13;
work penetration than in countries with no&#13;
cellular competition (Petrazzini and Clark 1996).&#13;
industry and Energy Department . Vice Presidency for Finanice and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Competition in Telecoms-Implications for Universal Service and Employment&#13;
Even the threat of competition in developing   privatization. In Africa and the Pacific Basin&#13;
countries has an impact on monopoly carriers.  too, the evidence shows that privatized sys-&#13;
Several countries have set a precise date for  tems have achieved much faster teledensity&#13;
the end of the licensed public operators' mar-   growth than their state-owned counterparts.&#13;
ket exclusivity. Where that date is less than&#13;
three years in the future, there is a strong sta-   Employment&#13;
tistical correlation between the threat of com-&#13;
petition and the increasing rates of teledensity   There is a widespread belief that competition&#13;
growth (Petrazzini and Clark 1996).       triggers significant labor cuts, but the evidence&#13;
suggests that this is not the case in developing&#13;
Among developing countries, there are numer-  countries. A comparative analysis of twenty-&#13;
ous examples showing the positive effect of   six countries in Asia and Latin America shows&#13;
competition on universal service. In China, the   that during 1990-94 employment in markets&#13;
entry of a second carrier into the market has   with varying degrees of competition increased&#13;
dramatically improved the rate of network and   by 20.73 percent, while in monopoly markets&#13;
service deployment. In 1990, the network   employment grew by only 3.13 percent (figure&#13;
growth rate was 25.7 percent. In 1993, after   2). A more detailed analysis of the sample&#13;
the announcement of competition, the network   shows that while employment grew in all com-&#13;
growth rate skyrocketed to 58.9 percent. In the   petitive markets, monopoly markets had an un-&#13;
same year, ten national fiber-optic backbones   even performance: in traditional public&#13;
were completed and a new high-speed com-   operators, employment grew by 5.6 percent,&#13;
munications system (ChinaDDN) was launched.   while in privatized monopolies it dropped by&#13;
In mobile telephony services, prices dropped   9 percent. But among the public operators,&#13;
by 30 percent and customer subscription grew    employment rose in only 40 percent of the com-&#13;
by 261 percent. And the waiting period for new    panies, and declined in 60 percent (Petrazzini&#13;
wireline connections dropped for both busi-  and Clark 1996).&#13;
ness and residential customers, by as much as&#13;
50 percent. In the Philippines, the announce-  It turns out that network modernization ac-&#13;
ment of competition in 1993 led to a 1,530 per-   counted for only 29 percent of all telecommu-&#13;
cent increase in the annual installation of main   nications investments in developing countries&#13;
lines. A similar pattern occurs in new technolo-   in the mid-1990s, while the installation of new&#13;
gies such as the Internet. In OECD countries,  lines-a task that boosts employment oppor-&#13;
for example, growth in the number of Internet  tunities-accounted for alnmost 71 percent. In&#13;
hosts is five times faster in competitive mar-   developing countries, where teledensity was&#13;
kets than in monopoly markets (ITU 1995 and   as low as 5.2 in 1994, network expansion cre-&#13;
OECD 1996a). There is nothing to indicate that   ates a demand for labor that outweighs the&#13;
the same pattern would not occur in develop-  trends toward workforce reduction that network&#13;
ing countries.                             modernization has generated in industrial coun-&#13;
tries, where teledensity was 52.3.&#13;
Privatization has also enhanced the prospects&#13;
for universal service. Developing countries that  Incumbent public operators&#13;
have privatized their telecommunications sys-&#13;
tems have experienced much faster growth in   After decades of unchallenged exclusive rights&#13;
their networks than those that have retained a   that have allowed employees to build up im-&#13;
state monopoly. This is particularly true in Asia   portant welfare benefits, many public telecom-&#13;
and Latin America, where teledensity growth   munications operators strongly resist the opening&#13;
in countries with privatized telecommunications   up of domestic markets. But recent experiences&#13;
has been twice the rate in nonprivatized mar-  in competitive markets suggest that former mo-&#13;
kets during each of the five years following   nopoly operators are not as vulnerable to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
entry of competing service providers as initially   vation means that, increasingly, competition will&#13;
expected. In most cases, new entrants have had   come from international sources.&#13;
difficulties in taking any significant share of the&#13;
market, let alone growing large enough to gain   Until quite recently, governments and public&#13;
market power and become a serious threat to   operators were fairly effective at blocking in-&#13;
the former public operator.                  ternational competition out of their domestic&#13;
telecommunications markets. But by the mid-&#13;
In Malaysia, for example, which introduced    1990s, new and difficult-to-control sources of&#13;
competition in long-distance and international   competition had emerged, and they are spread-&#13;
services in 1993. none of the new entrants had   ing rapidly. Although these new technologies&#13;
chipped away any significant share of the mar-   and services operate on different platforms and&#13;
ket from Telekom Malaysia Berhad, the former   through different media, they have one thing&#13;
monopoly operator, by early 1996. In China,  in common: they can all bypass incumbent op-&#13;
the licensing of China United Telecommunica-   erators or regulators, providing services that&#13;
tions (China Unicom, or Lian Tong) in late 1993   are difficult to shut down. Callback services,&#13;
as a second operator raised concerns for the   Internet phone, low-earth-orbit satellites, and&#13;
incumbent carrier, the Ministry of Posts and   global operators are among the most signifi-&#13;
Telecommunications. But three years later,   cant challenges to domestic public teleconimu-&#13;
China Unicom still faces an uphill battle to es-   nications operators in developing countries.&#13;
tablish a significant market presence. In the&#13;
United Kingdom, after more than ten years of   Callback operators, which have thrived because&#13;
long-distance competition, British Telecom    of the differences in tariffs between industrial&#13;
continues to hold more than 90 percent of the   and developing countries, have quickly&#13;
market.                                      grabbed a big chunk of the market in many&#13;
developing countries. In Argentina, there were&#13;
There are some cases, however, as in Chile,   until recently twenty-three callback providers&#13;
where the interconnection requirements along   offering tariffs as low as a quarter of the public&#13;
with competition can have significantly detri-   operator's prices. Teleintar, the international&#13;
mental effects on the incumbent's market share.   service operator, estimates that it has lost more&#13;
Chile's multicarrier system in the long-distance   than 30 percent of its market share to callback&#13;
and international telecommunications market,   operators. Public operators in developing coun-&#13;
allows users to access any carrier at any time   tries have attempted to limit competition from&#13;
by simply dialing a code before the desired   callback providers through court decisions (the&#13;
number. The ease of this system enabled one   Philippines), government orders (China), and&#13;
of the new service providers to claim 16 per-  tariff reductions (Argentina), but there is no&#13;
cent of the Chilean international service mar-   clear-cut way for them to block callback ser-&#13;
ket after only seven months of operation. In   vices without hurting their own business.&#13;
such cases, the absence of costs associated with&#13;
switching operators makes the price of service   Internet phone has just joined callback services&#13;
the major and probably the only factor guid-   as a significant potential threat to established&#13;
ing customers' choice of operator. Market share   public operators. Until recently, Internet ser-&#13;
under these conditions can decrease or expand   vices had been limited to data transmission.&#13;
rapidly.                                     But in 1994, software was developed that al-&#13;
lows voice communication among computers&#13;
New technology                               connected to the Internet. It is expected that&#13;
new developments in Internet phone software&#13;
Much of the debate about the effects of compe-   will allow computers connected to the Inter-&#13;
tition has focused on the entry of new operators   net to call telephones in the public switched&#13;
in the domestic market. But technological inno-   telephone network by early 1997, and that later&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Competition in Telecoms-Implications for Universal Service and Employment&#13;
in the year these services will be extended to                To make the best of the situation, governments&#13;
phone-to-phone communication based on new                     could consider two proactive reform  strategies.&#13;
Internet gateways. This will allow  telephone                 If a government believes that its national carrier&#13;
users to communicate over the PSTN  at Inter-                 can withstand the challenges of competition, it&#13;
net prices-a prospect that will no doubt put    should consider corporatizing the state-owned&#13;
considerable pressure on the tariff structure for             operator and gradually lowering entry barriers&#13;
long-distance and international services.                     in both value added and basic services. Several&#13;
developing countries (including China, India,&#13;
Mobile satellite serv ices provided over low-earth-           Malaysia, the Philippines, and Vietnam) have&#13;
orbit satellites present both opportunities and               chosen this approach in an effort to strengthen&#13;
challenges to public operators in developing                  the entrepreneurial capabilities of their public&#13;
countries. Mobile satellite services can offer ser-           operators. But since the organizational and cul-&#13;
vices that complement the national PSTN, but    tural transition from  a public utility operation to&#13;
they can also bypass the public network by pro-               a commercial venture takes time, governments&#13;
viding direct global services to large customers              should begin early to expose their telecommu-&#13;
at very low  cost. With large customers generally             nications operators to competition.&#13;
accounting for only 3 to 5 percent of a public&#13;
operator's customer base, but more than 50 per-               if a government believes that its national car-&#13;
The Note series is an    cent of its revenues, the migration of even a                 rier will not be able to stand up to competition&#13;
open forum istended to&#13;
encourage dissemina-     small number of these customers to mobile sat-                or if fiscal considerations are a priority, privati-&#13;
tion of and debate on    ellite services could significantly erode the public           zation may be a good  alternative. Just as in&#13;
ideas, innovations, and  operator's profits.                                           introducing  competition, timing is important,&#13;
best practices for&#13;
expanding the private                                                                  not so much because the company has to be&#13;
sector. The views        This rapid expansion of global services creates               prepared for privatization but because the de-&#13;
published are those of   serious pressures for small public operators in                clining value of monopolv markets over time&#13;
the authors and should&#13;
not be attributed to the  developing countries. Sooner or later, on their              can erode the price that would be paid for the&#13;
World Bank or any of its    own initiative or forced by events, they will    company.&#13;
affiliated organizations.  have to compete with large public operators&#13;
Nor do any of the con-   bae    inlrefrinmrkt.O     ore   e&#13;
clusions represent       based in large foreign markets. Of course, de-                This Note is based on previous work by the author. See Petrazzini&#13;
official policy of the   veloping  countries could  attempt to  contain                 1996&#13;
World Bank or of its     these pressures through regulatory mechanisms.&#13;
Executive Directora&#13;
or the countries they    But there  are no  technological or economic                  References&#13;
represent.               constraints on the expansion  of these global&#13;
frce   int   loa   makt  in  th   developing                   T (International Telecommunications tJnion). 199S. lPhr/d Telecom-&#13;
To order additional                                     .n                .    n           mnicattons Detvelopment Report: JOrformarion I frastructurets.&#13;
copies please call the   world. Unprepared public operators will find                     Geneva.&#13;
FPD Note line to leave a    it hard to compete against the commercial and               OECD (Organization for Economic Cooperation and Developnment).&#13;
message (202-458-1111)    technological sophistication and dvnamism  of                   1996a. li/ormationInfrastlructure Convergence and Pricing: The&#13;
or contact Suzanne       .                         .                                      Interzet. Paris.&#13;
Smith, editor, Room      international operators.                                          .   1996b Reflections onr the Bee,feits of lobile Cellular- 7ele-&#13;
G8105, The World Bank,                                                                    communication Infrasrructire CotGbpetiton. Paris.&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,       Challenges and                                                Petrazzini, Ben A. 1996. Global Telecom Talks. A Trillion DollarDeal.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,                        Wopportunities                               ashington. D.C: InstitLite for International Economics.&#13;
or Internet address                                                                    Petrazzini, Ben A., and Theodore K. Clark. 1996. Cost and Benefits of&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.    There is little doubt that new  information tech-               Telecomnmunications Liberalization in Developing Counties. Paper&#13;
Previous issues are also    nologies and  services will progressively  and                presented at the conference Liberalizing Telecommunications, In-&#13;
available on-line lhttp://                                                                sotutLe for international Economics, Washington, D.C,, Jantuary 29.&#13;
www.worldbank.org/       irreversibly erode the market position of tele-&#13;
html/fpd/notes/          communications monopolies and  their high                      Ben A. Petrazzini, Hong Kong University&#13;
notelist.html).          profit margins. As a result, the financial value               of Science and Technology, (bpetrazz@&#13;
@Printed on recycled     of these  companies will deteriorate, making                   usthk.ust.bk)&#13;
paper.                   them  less attractive to future investors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441228">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/10/441228/competition-telecoms-implications-universal-service-employment
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/10/441228/competition-telecoms-implications-universal-service-employment</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1996/10/441228/competition-telecoms-implications-universal-service-employment</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/10/000009265_3980420172705/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/10/000009265_3980420172705/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1996-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2000-10-24T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Competition in telecoms - implications for
            universal service and employment
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The author argues that competition in
            domestic telecommunications markets promotes both universal
            service and employment in developing countries. Thus,
            incumbent monopoly operators should be reformed. And since
            incumbents are subject to increasingly fierce international
            competition from callback services, Internet phone services,
            mobile satellite services, and global operators, this reform
            should happen sooner rather than later.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Competition in telecoms - implications for
            universal service and employment
        </docna>
        <display_title>Competition in telecoms -
            implications for universal service and employment</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1996/10/441228/competition-telecoms-implications-universal-service-employment</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Knowledge Economy,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Education for the Knowledge Economy,ICT Policy and Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Information and Communication Technologies,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Education</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Petrazzini, Ben A.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980420172705</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Telecommunications &amp; Informatics</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 96</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Information and Communication Technologies,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Education</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Information and communications</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Telecommunication networks; Employment;
            Denationalization; Monopolies; Communication technology;
            Satellites; Market competition; Callback services;
            Telecommunications; Internet phone services
            comparative analysis,competitive
            markets,data transmission,Economic
            Cooperation,employment,exclusive rights,growth
            rate,innovations,licensing,market
            power,media,monopolies,monopoly,networks,profit
            margins,regulatory
            mechanisms,satellites,telecommunications,telecommunications
            markets,telecoms,TELEDENSITY,telephones,telephony,telephony
            services,universal service,value added
        </keywd>
        <owner>ECA/MNA Regions Technical Department</owner>
        <repnb>16885</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>