<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The World Bank                                                                       September 1995&#13;
Note No.51   Bankruptcy Reform-Breaking the Court&#13;
Logjam in Colombia&#13;
Izak Atiyas      Ideally, bankruptcy policy should encourage the   solution to these problems: it shifted the bank-&#13;
reorganization of companies whose liquidation   ruptcy procedures from the traditional judicial&#13;
value is smaller than their value as a going con-   system to a credible administrative agency with&#13;
cern, and the liquidation of companies for which   more expertise in handling workouts.2 The re-&#13;
the opposite is true. In addition, it should en-   sult was a process with more authority, more&#13;
courage a speedy resolution of financial distress.  flexibility, and more speed. Colombia's reform&#13;
The longer a company stays in bankruptcy, the   provides a workable model for other countries&#13;
greater the loss of value and the more difficult it  suffering from congested courts.&#13;
becomes to rehabilitate the company and to pay&#13;
off its creditors. The crucial issue in bankruptcy   Prereform: Two judicial forums,&#13;
is designing a process that will distribute   confusion, and high cost&#13;
i,¢---    ~decisionmaking authority among the debtor, the&#13;
creditors, and the oversight agency in a way that  In common with other countries, Colombia had&#13;
achieves these objectives. When that process  two insolvency procedures. The first, the con-&#13;
gives the debtors too much power, they can sim-   cordato, was basically a financial reorganization&#13;
ply delay in order to force concessions from    procedure, designed to reach a conciliatory&#13;
creditors, with the result that firms that should   agreement between a company experiencing fi-&#13;
Z    be liquidated may end up being reorganized.   nancial difficulties and its creditors, with the pur-&#13;
And when it gives creditors too much power,   pose of rehabilitating the debtor's business. The&#13;
too many liquidations may occur, leading to the   second, the quiebra, was a liquidation proce-&#13;
loss of going concern values.              dure. Once a company entered quiebra, its as-&#13;
sets were sold and the proceeds distributed to&#13;
i           ~~~~~Recently, Ramachandran (1995) has suggested   creditors. However, and in contrast to most othcr&#13;
Aa,4          that the allocation of decisionmaking power in   countries, Colombia had two institutions deal-&#13;
bankruptcy law affects only the tactics of the   ing with bankruptcy-the court system and the&#13;
parties involved and not the eventual outcomes.'  Superintendency of Companies. The Superin-&#13;
The view taken here is that if changes in the   tendency was mainly a watchdog agency that&#13;
bankruptcy law, procedures, and institutional   monitored companies' compliance with com-&#13;
structure can help speed the pace at which com-   pany law. It had oversight of firms with more&#13;
panies move out of bankruptcy, outcomes are  than 100 workers, firms with foreign liabilities&#13;
likely to improve. As Colombia's experience   exceeding a third of their assets, and firms that&#13;
shows, that pace can be determined by the rules   were more than 50 percent government owned.&#13;
governing the process. Before undertaking re-&#13;
form in 1989, Colombia provided a good ex-   Reorganization procedures were of two types.&#13;
ample of the kinds of problems and inefficiencies   The first was optional. It was used mainly by&#13;
that arise when debtors are granted excessive   small and medium-size companies, and the&#13;
power, there are multiple forums for dealing with   competent authority was the district judge. By&#13;
bankruptcy, and the judicial system suffers from    contrast, the larger firms under the supervision&#13;
a lack of skills and limited processing capacity.   of the Superintendency of Companies had to&#13;
The reform introduced an innovative institutional   go through a mandatory concordato if they&#13;
Private Sector Development Department . Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Bankruptcy Reform-Breaking the Court Logjam in Colombia&#13;
were unable to repay their debts. These firms   There were other ways to delay bankruptcy&#13;
could not be liquidated until after a reorgani-   procedures. To cause a hearing to be post-&#13;
zation had been attempted, overseen by the   poned, debtors could simply fail to show up,&#13;
Superintendency.                             behavior against which the creditors had no&#13;
remedies. The parties could appeal almost ev-&#13;
Delays easy and disruptive                   ery decision of the judge or the superinten-&#13;
dent. Objections could also be raised by&#13;
In mandatory concordatos, the debtor retained   creditors who were free-riding, that is, black-&#13;
the management of the company unless fraud   mailing other creditors to gain favorable treat-&#13;
was established. Following admission to the   ment in the negotiations. The limited processing&#13;
process, the first step was to validate the list of   capacity of the court system contributed to the&#13;
claims. Any objections raised by the parties in-   delays. It could take judges a long time to con-&#13;
volved had to be resolved at this time. Once   firm a plan already agreed to by the creditors&#13;
disagreements were resolved, the parties were   and the debtor. In May 1989, of the sixteen&#13;
convened in a hearing in which they voted on   cases in which an agreement had been reached&#13;
a proposal to reorganize the liabilities (and, in   and needed only to be confirmed by the judge,&#13;
principle, the assets) of the company. If an   nine had been awaiting confirmation for more&#13;
agreement was reached, it went to the district  than a year.&#13;
judge for confirmation. If there was no agree-&#13;
ment, the procedure was declared failed and a   High cost&#13;
quiebra was initiated.&#13;
As a result of these delays, bankruptcy proce-&#13;
The concordatos were typically plagued by de-   dures often failed to yield efficient outcomes.&#13;
lays. From a sample of 190 firms that had en-   Firms that needed to be liquidated often ended&#13;
tered bankruptcy between 1982 and 1989, there   up being reorganized. And firms that were liq-&#13;
were 82 cases in which no agreement had been   uidated often ended up with all their assets&#13;
reached by May 1989. Of these, 54 had been   stripped, so that there was nothing left to re-&#13;
going on for more than two years, 36 for more   pay creditors.&#13;
than three years, and 16 for more than five&#13;
years.3 Most delays occurred during the vali-   After a financial crisis in the early 1980s, man-&#13;
dation of claims, a part of the process vulner-   datory reorganizations reached an economically&#13;
able to opportunistic behavior. Although the   significant scale in Colombia. In 1986 and 1987,&#13;
validation of claims was overseen by the Su-   for example, about 60 of the 1,000 or so manu-&#13;
perintendency, objections had to be resolved   facturing companies supervised by the Super-&#13;
by the district court. As a result, the resolution   intendency were under reorganization. These&#13;
of bankruptcy procedures often depended on   companies held assets valued at about 12 per-&#13;
the lengthy resolution of several additional, par-   cent of the country's total manufacturing as-&#13;
allel cases in different courts. Debtors wanting   sets, and as much as 20 percent of the assets in&#13;
to delay procedures, in order to extract con-   some sectors, such as textiles. Thus, the per-&#13;
cessions from creditors or to strip the assets of   formance of the companies in bankruptcy&#13;
the firm, could easily find excuses for filing   weighed heavily in the performance of their&#13;
objections. For example, the law required from    industries.&#13;
the creditors "at least summary proof' of their&#13;
loans; the fact that many loan documents, es-   Reform of the concordato:&#13;
pecially for smaller creditors, were inadequately   One forum and no delay tactics&#13;
prepared helped the debtors in that respect.&#13;
There were no measures in the law to penal-  In the 1989 reform of the mandatory reorgani-&#13;
ize debtors or creditors for filing objections sim-   zation procedures, the most significant change&#13;
ply to gain time or to disrupt the process.  was the designation of the Superintendency as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the sole competent authority. The Superinten-&#13;
dency was thus endowed with the authority to&#13;
decide on matters that had previously gone to           TABLE 1 DURATION OF REORGANIZATlON PROGEURES&#13;
the district judge. Most important, it was given        ;&#13;
the authority to resolve disputes arising from          Duration         Proceduresinitiated   Proceduresinitiated&#13;
objections raised during the validation of              (months)          beforethereform        afterthereform&#13;
claims. It was also authorized to confirm any&#13;
agreements reached between the parties. Grant-&#13;
ing these judicial powers to an administrative          13 to 24              1  (34)               7  (28)&#13;
authority created a constitutional controversy,         25 to48               44  (29)               2   (8)&#13;
resolved only when a new constitution was in-           49 or more            17  (11}&#13;
troduced that permitted an administrative au-           Unfinished            12  (8)                8  (32)&#13;
thority to assume the functions of a judge.             Total                152 (100)              25 (100)&#13;
The reform also introduced time limits for the&#13;
different stages of reorganization. For example,        Note:Figuresin parentheses are percentage shares of the totaL Preretorn figures&#13;
cover the decadle priorto reform. To make ttte results mote comparable, the second&#13;
as soon as the Superintendency approves an              aolucneaentatesonthosecasesiaitiatedbetweenMaVyl9Sandtheendofl99l.&#13;
application for a concordato, all evidence of             withetthecutoff morerecentcaseswouldnaohavehadenougbdmimetocometo&#13;
clostre and s.the ratio of unfinished cases underthe new cods would have beet&#13;
claims on the firm  must be provided within             biased upwards.&#13;
twenty days. The parties then have five days            SourcetCatombia Superintendency of Companies.&#13;
to object to the claims and must attend a pre-&#13;
liminary hearing within the next fifteen days.&#13;
The rules governing the final hearing are also&#13;
quite strict. If the debtor does not show  up    Impact and lessons&#13;
and cannot justify his absence within three days,&#13;
a new hearing is convened during which an    With the reform still relatively new, it is hard&#13;
agreement may be approved by vote of only   to evaluate its overall impact. But it seems that&#13;
the creditors. If the creditors do not show up    bankruptcy cases are being resolved more&#13;
or an agreement is not reached, the hearing    quickly. The proportion of cases in which an&#13;
can be convened only once or twice more, af-   agreement is reached within a year has in-&#13;
ter which the concordato is declared failed.       creased from  18 percent to 32 percent (table&#13;
1). Before the reform, only 52 percent of cases&#13;
In another move to expedite the process, the    resulted in an agreement within two years; this&#13;
reform  ruled out appeals for many decisions    ratio has now increased to 60 percent. These&#13;
of the competent authority. Where appeals are    percentages probably underestimate the real&#13;
possible, they do not suspend the process. The    benefits of the reform. Since parties dissatis-&#13;
reform  also allows the creditors to establish    fied with the way the Superintendency handles&#13;
mechanisms for control and monitoring dur-   the procedures have some room to appeal,4 in&#13;
ing the procedure. It requires the formation of   principle, the gains described above should be&#13;
a creditors committee of representatives of dif-   contrasted with any additional delays caused&#13;
ferent classes of creditors (including workers,   by appeals. But data on appeals are not avail-&#13;
public agencies, and financial and nonfinancial   able. However, the business community, includ-&#13;
creditors). It also requires the appointment of   ing both creditor banks and debtors, have&#13;
an examiner of the property, credits, and af-   generally welcomed the reform, suggesting that&#13;
fairs of the debtor. Both the committee and the    improvements are real and substantial.5&#13;
examiner have extensive functions. In particu-&#13;
lar, both can request that the competent au-    No comparable data exist for the optional cases&#13;
thority remove the debtor from the management   that still take place in the traditional court sys-&#13;
of the firm.                                       tem. But there is a general consensus among&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Bankruptcy Reform-Breaking the Court Logjam  in Colombia&#13;
professionals, lawyers, and the business com-    ing the traditional courts into any step of the&#13;
munity that, even though these cases are gov-    process would slow  the entire process. Not&#13;
erned  by similar legislation, it takes much               every country has an entity like the Superin-&#13;
longer to reach agreements in the optional con-    tendency ready to step into the breach. An&#13;
cordatos under the court system  than in the               important-and  sometimes rare-attribute  of&#13;
mandatory concordatos under the Superinten-    the Superintendency is its reputation in both&#13;
dency. There are several reasons for this dif-    the banking system  and the business commu-&#13;
nity as an impartial and competent institution&#13;
free from politics. When there are entities that,&#13;
Giving the Superintendency the sole                                                with a bit of nurturing, could assume a role&#13;
-C:)                                                                   like that of the Superintendency, deciding&#13;
legal authority to handle the entire                                               whether to improve the traditional court sys-&#13;
tem  or to switch to the alternatives by giving&#13;
bankrtptcyprocess effectivelyrprevents                                            them the necessary legal powers is a matter of&#13;
judgment. The greatest danger lies in creating&#13;
delays due to frivolous but time-                                                  parallel courts with overlapping jurisdictions.&#13;
consumning  appe ls.                                                               Illustration by Ruth Sofair Ketler.&#13;
a  Ramachandran (1995) concentrated mainly on the transition econo-&#13;
mies of Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union,&#13;
2 This approach is an example of the out-of-court institutional solu-&#13;
tions mentioned by Fleisig (1995).&#13;
ference. First, giving the Superintendency the                In the United States, where bankruptcy reorganizations are also&#13;
sole legal authority to handle the entire bank-               considered lengthy, the process is estimated to take an average of&#13;
r-uptcy process effectively prevents delays due              one and a half to two years between filing and resolution. In France&#13;
and the United Kingdom, the period is shorter.&#13;
to frivolous but time-consuming appeals. Sec-                Ramachand.ran (1995) points out that one result of moving proce-&#13;
This series is published  ond, the Superintendency staff are competent                dures out of the court system may be an increase in appeals.&#13;
to share ideas and invite   in analyzing the financial situation of compa-            Since in the new system most appeals cannot delay negotiations,&#13;
discussion. It covers      anlzn                                       op-            objections cannot be used as a tactic. Thus, under the new system,&#13;
financial and private   nies, they are more likely than the courts to                 frivolous objections intended to delay the process are less likely.&#13;
sector development as   rule on the merits of the claims, and they are&#13;
well as industry and    better mediators. Third, setting time limits for    References&#13;
energy. The viewvs&#13;
expressed are those of  each  step in the process, together with the&#13;
the authors and are not    elimination  of several judicial forums, has               glamcHa 1995. "The Power of Cates Role in Enterprise Restructur&#13;
intended to represent   speeded the entire bankruptcy process.                       ing: A Hammer to Turn a Screw?" FPD Note 38.&#13;
an official statement of&#13;
Bank policy or strategy.&#13;
Colombia's experience could teach other coun-    IzakAtiyas, Private Sector Development&#13;
Comments are wvelcome.   tries some useful lessons. First, setting time lim-    Department&#13;
Please call the FPD&#13;
Note line to leave a    its for the steps in the bankruptcy process has&#13;
message I202-45B-1111)    advantages-although, of course, unrealistic&#13;
or contact Suzanne      deadlines should be avoided. They are likely&#13;
Smith, editor, Room&#13;
G8105, The Worid Bank,    to be violated often, allowing appeals on pro-&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,      cedural grounds. Second, when traditional court&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,    procedures for bankruptcy  are  difficult to&#13;
or Internet address&#13;
ssmith7Mworldhank.org.    change, an attractive alternative is to legally&#13;
empower another entity to handle the entire&#13;
@Printed on recycled    process. In doing so, governments should guard&#13;
paper.                  against implicitly allowing multiple legal forums&#13;
by permitting interim steps to be appealed in&#13;
the traditional courts. The strength of a chain&#13;
is determined by its weakest link, and allow-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441468">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/09/441468/bankruptcy-reform-breaking-court-logjam-colombia
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/09/441468/bankruptcy-reform-breaking-court-logjam-colombia</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/09/441468/bankruptcy-reform-breaking-court-logjam-colombia</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980312102702/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980312102702/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1995-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2000-10-24T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Bankruptcy reform : breaking the court
            logjam in Colombia
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Many developing countries suffer from
            logjam in the courts, a condition that tends to reduce the
            effectiveness of bankruptcy law in relieving financial
            distress. Colombia's bankruptcy reform provides some
            useful lessons for these countries. In particular, it shows
            that when traditional court procedures are hard to change,
            an alternative is to legally empower another entity to
            handle the entire process. The author explains how it was
            done in Colombia.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Bankruptcy reform : breaking the court
            logjam in Colombia
        </docna>
        <display_title>Bankruptcy reform : breaking the
            court logjam in Colombia</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1995/09/441468/bankruptcy-reform-breaking-court-logjam-colombia</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Judicial System Reform,Legal Institutions of the Market Economy,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Strategic Debt Management,Legal Products</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Colombia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Atiyas, Izak</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980312102702</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Non-Sector Specific</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 51</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Multisector</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Bankruptcy; Courts; Judicial process;
            Financial planning; Debt rescheduling; Court rules
            authority,banking
            system,Bankruptcy,bankruptcy law,bankruptcy
            procedures,Bankruptcy reform,bankruptcy
            reorganizations,courts,creditor,creditors,debtors,debts,fraud,insolvency,judges,judicial
            powers,judicial system,lawyers,legal
            authority,legislation,liquidation,mediators,professionals,public agencies,reorganization
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>16910</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Debt Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Closing of Business</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Servers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Switches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bankruptcy Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insolvency and creditor/debtor regimes</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secured Transactions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial System Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bankruptcy and Liquidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Network Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insolvency and Creditor Rights</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Colombia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>