<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank Group                                                                        September 1996&#13;
Note No.89   Portfolio Investment Funds  Assessing the&#13;
Impact on Emerging Markets&#13;
Teresa Barger,    The portfolio funds industry in emerging markets is roughly ten years old. By 1995, the industry had&#13;
Laurend e Craner    grown to more than US$100 billion managed through 1,300 funds, and represented about half the for-&#13;
and Irlving&#13;
Kuczynski          eign capital flows to emerging markets. Although portfolio funds account for only about 5 percent of&#13;
the capitalization of emerging stock markets, they have been responsible for kick starting the develop-&#13;
ment of many of these markets. And contrary to common perceptions, the main beneficiaries of this&#13;
growth have been the local firms and investors who hold about 90 percent of emerging market stocks.&#13;
Where developing country stock markets existed   stocks, low turnover, a weak regulatory and in-&#13;
ten years ago, they were characterized by small  stitutional environment for investors (poor ac-&#13;
capitalization relative to GDP, relatively few listed   counting standards, little research, weak investor&#13;
protection, few brokers), and restrictions on for-&#13;
eign entry and on capital and dividend repatria-&#13;
TABLEI IFC INVESTMENTS-OPENING MARKETS TO FOREIGN            tion. Much has changed. The number of stock&#13;
PORTFOLIO INVEST-MEhT                                 markets, the number of listed firms, market capi-&#13;
POaTFOLIO INVatTMENT  talization, and turnover have all grown dramati-&#13;
CapitalizatioV .  cally over the past decade, particularly since 1990.&#13;
(US$n illions)    Emerging market capitalization increased more&#13;
IFC     Country                                   Dec.       than tenfold between 1985 and 1994, from US$170&#13;
approval or region  Fund                   Initial  1995     billion to nearly US$2 trillion. Such countries as&#13;
Bangladesh, Ecuador, Namibia, Swaziland, and&#13;
1984    Korea, Rep. of Korea Fund            60   747         Zambia and many transition economies have set&#13;
1986    Global      Emerging Markets Growth Fund 50  5,571    up stock markets during the past five years. By&#13;
1986    Thailand    Thailand Fund            3               the end of 1994, there were 17,000 firms listed&#13;
on emerging stock markets-almost as many as&#13;
1987    Malaysia    Malaysia Fund Inc.       84   181        on markets in industrial countries.&#13;
1989    Latin Amenrica New World nvestment Fund   62   233&#13;
1989    Philippines   Manila Fund Inc.       50    51         Birth of an industry&#13;
1989    Turkey      Turkish Investment Fund Inc.  24    32&#13;
1990    Chile       Five Arrows Chile Fund   75   347        The development of foreign portfolio investment&#13;
1996    Portugal    Portuguese Investment Fund   30    24    funds has been a prime mover in this explosion&#13;
1992  Mauritius    Mautitius Fund  1 7  28  in stock market growth. The International Fi-&#13;
1992    Mauritius    Mauritius Fund          17     2        nance Corporation (IFC) has played a key role&#13;
1993    Africa      Africa Emerging Markets Fund  30    64   in creating the portfolio funds industry in emerg-&#13;
1994    Middle East  Emerging Middle East Fund    40    36    ing markets (see table 1 for countries or regions&#13;
where IFC cosponsored the first foreign invest-&#13;
Somee:lFC.                                                   ment vehicles; also see box 1). Its involvement&#13;
goes back to the late 1970s, when, after identi-&#13;
International Finance Corporation - Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Portfolio Investment Funds-Assessing the Impact on Emerging Markets&#13;
The Korea and Mexico Funds, started in the early&#13;
govrnmnt efoa iititivs~ nd nvetorintres hameattht  980s, marked the beginning of the portfolio&#13;
IFO' fud prmoton ffors hve eoke diferetlyin dffeentequity industry in emerging markets. Interest was&#13;
countries. Often, lEC will develop aluniYs concept'structure1befmdquickly kindled in other countries, and initial&#13;
efecit its nrnnagers,dfine-itspoliiesan4inves-'m-nifiocui -ndfunds quickly drew in others. For example, two&#13;
mohiizeaworld-class rmdenivriting group. And eftenit will move in  years after the Malaysia Fund's launch in 1987,&#13;
advnceof riateiniiatve, bcaue  arkts arey xis orrethe country had attracted eight other funds,&#13;
which raised US$600 million. At the end of 1991,&#13;
hestan o beaus tereis o oca plye tointodce ew rouct,lust seven years after the launch of the Korea&#13;
IFCsfistnvetinntaste  ore Fud n 154 ByJun ISSSFCFund, there were nearly 300 funds-managing&#13;
bad committed lJS0i8 mllliontathirty-one funds, whoetal su8 at    US$20 billion-targeting emerging markets.&#13;
ineto wa US21 iu 3 blion Aitpmoe fud  in oe cun-t &#13;
tresFlG hsbetrgtoaradragoinetrshuhtsBefore long, most policymakers in emerging&#13;
underwriting and placement effors. IE also uses itsunderwritingmarkets had relaxed their attitudes and were&#13;
0.andplacemt capacity to generate                                 keen to move beyond the closed-end vehicles&#13;
demonstrtion effcts  useand attract a variety of portfolio funds. As inter-&#13;
value exceeds the mo-eyraisedfatthefuhd.                          national investment banks and asset managers&#13;
A sampl of .EG's portfolio-covering a reasonable investmentbecame willing to enter the emerging market&#13;
volume jea-nd numbof fundsuan several years of experience-        funds business, IFC scaled back its activities,&#13;
suggst~ hat he aeragz43prcen nomnal ate f reurnshifting to the promotion of funds targeting stock&#13;
e  n G i                 n p                                      markets untouched by foreign portfolio invest-&#13;
of this assetclns..s.....    ment-especially in Africa and the Middle East.&#13;
i-- iiiiiconsistently -g'ood-performanc3eii-of*:'l's-ja-"e,  ''IFC's board approved investments in the Africa&#13;
E-0,                             ~~~~~~~~Fund and the Mauritius Fund in 1993. And in&#13;
fying regulatory barriers as the key constraint to    October 1994, it approved an investment in the&#13;
stock market growth, IFC began working with a    Emerging Middle East Fund, the first publicly&#13;
few  interested governments to amend these    offered New York-listed investment fund cov-&#13;
regulations and identify potential investors and    ering markets in the region. The US$40 million&#13;
fund managers. IFC's Emerging Markets Data   fund, the first in the region to be listed on a&#13;
Base, set up around this time, was an important   major international market, is initially focusing&#13;
lubricant in the process. For the first time, in-    on Egypt, Israel, Jordan, Morocco, Oman, and&#13;
vestors could get a comparative picture of the    Tunisia.&#13;
investment environment and stock market re-&#13;
turns in different countries.                      While all this was a revolution waiting to hap-&#13;
pen, the speed with which it happened caught&#13;
But the birth of the early funds was not easy. For    most observers by surprise. Several currents hap-&#13;
example, IFC started work in 1977 on the con-    pened to coincide. Privatization increased the&#13;
cept of the Emerging Markets Growth Fund, the    supply of assets for investors to buy. A few gov-&#13;
first global fund targeting developing countries.    ernments started to promote private pension&#13;
This fund had a nine-year gestation, not coming    funds and domestic mutual funds to raise na-&#13;
to closure until mid-1986. Initially, some govern-   tional savings rates. In transition economies, the&#13;
ments were persuaded to open up to closed-end    combination of many new  private firms, dis-&#13;
country funds, because these funds seemed to   tressed banking sectors, and voucher privatiza-&#13;
overcome the two main concerns of host gov-   tion led to big opportunities for portfolio funds.&#13;
ernments: foreign control of domestic firms and    improved telecommunications and financial in-&#13;
destabilizing, "hot" money flows. Closed-end    novation made it easier to invest. And now, as&#13;
funds raise a fixed sum and then close the share-   the industry has become more competitive, the&#13;
holder group. Structured as finite pools owned    market's response to the introduction of suc-&#13;
by multiple investors and aiming for diverse port-   cessful new fund vehicles has accelerated-as&#13;
folios, these closed-end portfolio country funds    illustrated by the growth of the passively man-&#13;
seemed to pose little threat.                      aged "index" fund industry in emerging mar-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 1 FUND MANAGERS DRIVE INSTITUTIONAL&#13;
DEVELOPMENT&#13;
kets. By late 1995, less than two years after the                                            mnavestors and fund&#13;
inception of the first index fund, the indexed                                               managers demand:&#13;
emerging market funds had surged to more than                                                Entorcement      Regulatory&#13;
US$4 billion, a twentyfold increase over 1994.                                                                agency is&#13;
(Roughly 75 percent of emerging market index                                                                  strengthened&#13;
funds are now  using IFC's Emerging Markets                                                  Custody and      Custodians&#13;
Funds Data Base indexes.)                                                                   transfer agents    spring up&#13;
Beter          o Accounting&#13;
The catalytic effect                                                 ~~~~~~~~~~ ~ ~~~~~~~~disclosure  standards&#13;
The catalytic effect                                              |                                             | i | g i improve&#13;
Better           Research&#13;
In many markets, relatively small amounts of                                                information       improves&#13;
foreign capital have been enough to act as a                                                 Lower      i      Brokers&#13;
catalyst (box 2). For example, although the first                                            transaction      become more&#13;
country funds in Malaysia, the Republic of Ko-                                               costs            competitive&#13;
rea, and Thailand each raised less than 1 per-                                               Better price     Market&#13;
cent of the host market's capitalization at the                                              disnovery        transactions&#13;
time, they had a big effect on the financial and&#13;
institutional development of these markets. A&#13;
recent review of size, liquidity, pricing, and in-         Market attracts small           Trust in market increases, and&#13;
receutiont l eview                                          investors and savers         market functions more efficiently&#13;
stitutional development measures in eleven de-&#13;
veloping economies where country funds&#13;
opened the market found significant increases&#13;
in most of these measures.'                                 BOX 2  THLE MAURITIUS FUND&#13;
How have relatively small infusions of foreign              The closed-end Mauritius Fund, launed in 19S3, offered the first&#13;
capital through funds so successfully stimulated&#13;
the development of emerging markets? Foreign                opportunityforinternationalportfolioinvestorstobuyMauritian&#13;
entry typically has set off two parallel virtuous           securities. This fund played a pivotal role in a wider government&#13;
cycles. First, an institutional development cycle          strategy to promote securities markets and open capital markets to&#13;
(figure 1). International investors-and, by                 foreign investors.&#13;
proxy, the managers of their funds--demand                    FC took a 17 percent stake in the fund, helped refine the structure,&#13;
high standards in regulation and information. &#13;
Spurred by the prospect of new  investment,                 an  laced part oftheund with otherinvestors.ilnvestorsinthefund&#13;
market regulators often undertake reforms as                were given a year's exclusive access. Institutional investors&#13;
part of the opening-up process. In addition, fund           subscribed US$17.3 milion. The funds impact together with the&#13;
managers require local services, such as brokers,           government's liberalization strategy, has led to dramatic growth in&#13;
custody and transfer agents, and information on             the size, liquidity, and breadth of the market (see table).&#13;
local companies. In response to this demand,&#13;
local providers spring up, competition increases,           MAURITIUS-STOCK MARKET INDICATORS&#13;
and standards improve. Although these changes               Iatr                            DICATORS&#13;
are driven initially by foreign investment, the             Indicator                      December1992  December1994&#13;
benefits of more market intermediaries and a                Number of companies                  22              35&#13;
more transparent, efficient market accrue to all            Market capitalization (US$ millions)    416        1,514&#13;
players. As trust in the market improves, more&#13;
local investors and firms enter the market-&#13;
attracting more funds and encouraging the de-               Turnover ratio (percent)             2.9              7&#13;
velopment of local fund managers.                           Market index                         183            474&#13;
Price-eamings ratio                 11.6           1BA&#13;
Second, a cycle of financial broadening and&#13;
deepening. Although the inflows of foreign funds            Source: IFC.&#13;
may be small relative to the market, they often&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Portfolio Investment Funds-Assessing the Impact on Emerging Markets&#13;
have a significant effect on trading activity. Stock        or new equity issues) than do enterprises in in-&#13;
prices rise in response to the extra demand.    dustrial economies.2 Stock markets remain places&#13;
Higher price-earnings ratios reduce firms' cost    where local firms raise equity overwhelmingly&#13;
of raising  equity, with  dramatic effects. The             from  local investors. Adding in other foreign&#13;
higher ratios encourage listed firms to raise more          capital (for example, direct equity holdings)&#13;
capital from the market, and new  firms to enter    brings the estimated foreign portfolio capital in-&#13;
the market through initial public offerings. The            vested in emerging markets at the end of 1994&#13;
larger, more liquid market attracts more foreign            to  about US$200 billion-still only about 10&#13;
and domestic investors. New                                                        percent of their total capi-&#13;
investors emerge-domestic    T                                  -- -----           talization. Thus, with about&#13;
insurance companies, pen-               F       E                                  90 percent of emerging mar-&#13;
sion funds, mutual funds,                                                          ket capitalization, local in-&#13;
LOAINVEST      _OR OWNl--&#13;
and individuals. More inter-                                                       vestors have been the main&#13;
mediaries-brokers, under-                 0 P C         OF E                       beneficiaries of the recent&#13;
writers, custodians-enter               Eme   w'-k 'ca 't"liati'.'  growth (figure 2).&#13;
the market to meet the de-                         M     I         ... Fl&#13;
mand from  the larger num-    -,, ,ill                                             The  benefits  of  more,&#13;
ber of investors and firms.             2                                          deeper, and broader stock&#13;
As market liquidity and effi-                                                      markets in developing coun-&#13;
ciency increase, more firms              1                                         tries reach many more firms&#13;
issue stock, including "sec-                                                       than those that tap the mar-&#13;
The Note series is an   ond-tier" companies that                 1                                          kets directly. Liquid stock&#13;
open forum intended is&#13;
openfourage dissemina   previously would not have                                                           markets drawing on large&#13;
tion of and debate on   considered a public listing.                  2-      0                             numbers of savers and in-&#13;
ideas, innvaions,and    The key element in this vir-                                                        vestors improve exit oppor-&#13;
best practices far&#13;
expanding the private   tuous cycle is liquidlity: im-                     FrTn         Lcltnte    o    nrpeer&#13;
sector. The views       proved market liquidity for              Sonw- - .                                  and investors. Initial public&#13;
published are those of  existing securities (the sec-                                                       offerings  provide  firms&#13;
the suthors and shouldmakt&#13;
not be attributed to the  ondary market) encourages                                                         owners and private equity&#13;
World Bank or any of its    more new stock issues by listed firms and initial    investors the opportunity to realize high returns.&#13;
affiliated organizations.    public offerings by firms new to the market (the       That encourages more entrepreneurs to start&#13;
Nor do any of the con-&#13;
clusions represent      primary market).                                             firms and more investors to provide funds for&#13;
official policy of the                                                               investment through venture capital funds and&#13;
World Bank or of its    Conclusion                                                   larger private equity vehicles. The greater avail-&#13;
Executive Directors&#13;
or the countries they                                                                ability of private equity improves access to such&#13;
represent.              While foreign portfolio funds were not the only              finance for growing, investing firms.&#13;
factor in jump-starting the growth in emerging&#13;
To order additional&#13;
copies please call the  stock markets over the past decade, they clearly             This Note and the data in it are drawn from the InternationaL Finance&#13;
FPD Note line to leave a    have catalytic effects far beyond the money they         Corporation, Investment Funds in Emerging Mnarkets (Washington,&#13;
message (202-458-tlll)    mobilize. They help to put countries "on the               D.C., 1996).&#13;
or contact Suzanne                                                                   I Ross Levine and Sara Zervos, '¶lntern-ational CapitaltFlow Lbheraliza-&#13;
Smith, editor, Room     map" for emerging market investors, and in-                  Xon and stock Market Development" (World Bank, Policy Research&#13;
G8105, The World Bank,    crease the amount and quality of research on                 Department, Washington, D.C., 1994). The economies reviewed&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,      these markets. And by improving the price-earn-                wvere Brazil, Chile, India, Malaysia, Mexico, the Philippines, Portu-&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,        r       l          a     p         e           of       gal, the Republic of Korea, Thailand, Turkey, and Taiwan (China).&#13;
Or Internet address     ings ratios, liquidity, and pricng efficiency of               Ajit Singh, 'Corporate Financial Patterns in Industrializing Econo-&#13;
ssmith7tfworldbank.org.    domestic markets, they improve firms' access                mies: A Comparative International Study" (IFC Technical Paper 2,&#13;
Previous issues are also    to all equity capital in emerging markets-criti-           Intemational Finance Corporation, Washington, D.C., 1995).&#13;
available on-line lhttp://&#13;
www.worldbank.org/      cal for busmess growth in developing econo-&#13;
html/fpd/notes/         mies. IFC  research  shows that, contrary  to                Teresa Barger, Capital Markets, Laurence&#13;
notelist.html).         common perceptions, large firms in developing                Carter, Corporate Planning Department (email:&#13;
®Printed on recycled    countries finance more investment from  exter-    Icarter@ifc.org), and Irving Kuczynski, Finan-&#13;
paper.                  nal sources (through borrowing, private equity,    cial Sector Issues, IFC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441457">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/09/441457/portfolio-investment-funds-assessing-impact-emerging-markets
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/09/441457/portfolio-investment-funds-assessing-impact-emerging-markets</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1996/09/441457/portfolio-investment-funds-assessing-impact-emerging-markets</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980420172646/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980420172646/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1996-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2000-10-24T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Portfolio investment funds : assessing the
            impact on emerging markets
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Although portfolio funds account for
            only about 5 percent of the capitalization of emerging stock
            markets, these small infusions of capital, particularly
            foreign portfolio investment funds, have been responsible
            for jump starting the development of many of these markets.
            The main beneficiaries of this growth have been the local
            firms and investors who hold about 90 percent of emerging
            market stocks. This Note examines the key role played by the
            International Finance Corporation (IFC) in creating the
            portfolio funds industry and helping to put countries on the
            map for emerging market investors. By improving the
            price-earnings ratio, liquidity, and pricing efficiency of
            domestic markets, portfolio funds improve firms access to
            all equity capital in emerging markets, a factor critical
            for business growth in developing countries. The Note also
            outlines the benefits that flow to developing country
            entrepreneurs and investors as a result of this increased
            liquidity the stock market provides.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Portfolio investment funds : assessing the
            impact on emerging markets
        </docna>
        <display_title>Portfolio investment funds :
            assessing the impact on emerging markets</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1996/09/441457/portfolio-investment-funds-assessing-impact-emerging-markets</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Markets and Market Access,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Financial Intermediation,Access to Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,International Economics and Trade,Conflict and Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Barger, Teresa</author>
            <author>Carter, Laurence</author>
            <author>Kuczynski, Irving</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980420172646</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Capital Markets Development</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 89</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,International Economics and Trade,Conflict and Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Finance</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Stock markets; Investment promotion; Foreign
            capital; Foreign investments; Capital markets; Equity
            investments; Private enterprises; Institutional investors;
            Capital markets; Portfolio investment funds
            Accounting,affiliated
            organizations,borrowing,brokers,capital flows,capital
            markets,capitalization,disclosure,domestic markets,emerging
            markets,equity capital,foreign capital,foreign
            investment,foreign investors,Growth Fund,initial public
            offerings,INSTITUTIONAL DEVELOPMENT,insurance,investment
            banks,liquidity,mutual
            funds,Portfolio,Privatization,savings,savings
            rates,securities,securities markets,stock
            markets,stocks,transition economies,turnover,venture capital
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>16878</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Markets and Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Placement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Securities Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mutual Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>