<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>169 S3&#13;
Technical Note&#13;
The World Bank         FPD Note No. 9                                           June 1994&#13;
Reality Checks for Power Forecasts&#13;
Two Simple Checks Relating Power Sector Demand Forecasts&#13;
to the Macroeconomy&#13;
Robert Bacon&#13;
Power demandforecasts are an integral instead. The difficulty with this ap-&#13;
part ofpowerproject appraisal. The  proach is that it can lead to very high&#13;
costs of getting these forecasts wrong    growth rates projected to continue&#13;
can be very high. An overoptimistic  over a long period. These may well be&#13;
demandforecast can lead to projects   inconsistent with macroeconomic de-&#13;
which are unnecessarily large at the    velopments (e.g., very large real price&#13;
countr's current state of economic    rises in electricity as the government&#13;
development, diverting resourcesfrom   removes subsidies in order to comply&#13;
better uses. Too low a demandforecast  with loan agreements), and with typi-&#13;
will lead to underprovision ofpower    cal patterns of power demand viewed&#13;
and to shortages later on. This Note sets  over the longer term.&#13;
out two simple reality checks which&#13;
can help to prevent such mistakes  When these data gaps exist, interna-&#13;
tional experience can be a very impor-&#13;
The approach                       tant comparator to check the plausibil-&#13;
These forecasts are usually expressed   ity of the trend projections. This Note&#13;
as an average growth rate over a cer-  suggests two simple methods of&#13;
tain time horizon, e.g., 10 percent per  checking projections against the expe-&#13;
annum for twenty years. They are of-  rience of other countries.' The first&#13;
ten based on trend projections of the    check calculates implicit price and&#13;
power sector and when this is the case, income elasticities for the demand&#13;
it is important to check that they are   scenario, so that they can be compared&#13;
consistent with likely movements of    with international values based on&#13;
the principal macroeconomic determi-  more intensive investigations The sec-&#13;
nants of demand. However, in some    ond check, which is a simplification of&#13;
of the poorest countries, which are    this first approach, calculates a coun-&#13;
now starting to look at large power    try's projected power-to-income ratio.&#13;
projects, there is often insufficient in-   Again this ratio can be compared to&#13;
formation on historic demand patterns  actual levels for other countries which&#13;
to make a reliable forecast. Frequently, are at similar stages of development.&#13;
in this situation, a simple extrapolation  l A more detailed version of this Note will be pro-&#13;
of demand growth rates has been used   duced in the IEN Occasional Papers senes&#13;
Industry and Energy Department&#13;
--~   D    Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The calculation of implicit price and income      Test case&#13;
elasticities of power demand                      Assume in the forecast that the power demand&#13;
growth will be at a steady 10 percent per annum for&#13;
Formula                                            a thirty-year period (1995 to 2025), which implies&#13;
The starting point is a relationship which is assumed  that demand will reach 1745 percent of its initial&#13;
to link demand growth with real income and real    level by the end of the period. Real income is fore-&#13;
electricity price growth rates. Based on a "constant    cast to grow at an average of 5 percent per annum&#13;
elasticity" demand equation this long-term relation-   for the whole period. However, it is assumed that&#13;
ship can be expressed as:                         the total real price rise, equivalent to 3 percent per&#13;
year for thirty years (243 percent total increase), will&#13;
The rate of growth of demand is equal to the rate   be concentrated in the first ten-year period, and that&#13;
of growth of prices times the price elasticity, plus   the last twenty years will see no further real price&#13;
the rate of growth of income times the income     increase. The annual rate of increase of real prices is&#13;
elasticity                                        therefore 9.3 percent between 1995 and 2005.&#13;
This is expressed formally as:                    The basic formula (1) can now be applied period by&#13;
period. For the period 1995 to 2005 the equation&#13;
d = p x b + g x a                   (1)    becomes:&#13;
where: d = annual average rate of growth of de-           0.1 = 0.093 b + 0.05 a              (2)&#13;
mand;&#13;
a = income elasticity (positive);          Table 1 gives some combinations of price and in-&#13;
g = annual average rate of growth of real   come elasticities consistent with the macroeconomic&#13;
income;                                data of (2). A complete set of feasible combinations&#13;
b = price elasticity of demand (negative);  can be obtained by plotting price and income elas-&#13;
p = average annual rate of change of real   ticities on a graph. Since the relationship is a straight&#13;
power prices.                          line, plotting any two points and passing a line&#13;
through them will describe all the possible solutions.&#13;
This relation can be used to show which values of  Because price elasticities are always negative, and&#13;
income and price elasticities would make the      income elasticities for power are always positive,&#13;
macro variables consistent with the demand for    attention can immediately be focused on just one&#13;
power growth assumed. These possible combina-   subset of all solutions to (2).&#13;
tions of elasticities can then be compared to inter-&#13;
national experience for other developing countries&#13;
to check whether the total scenario appears plau-&#13;
sible, or whether the demand forecast would be&#13;
sible, or whether th  demad f t wTABLE 1 Combinations of Price and Income Elasticites&#13;
consistent with the macro variables only if the     that Satisfy the Forecast of Power Demand Growth and&#13;
income and price elasticities in the country were    the Macroeconomic Scenario (1995-2005)&#13;
very atypical of international experience. In the            Price Elasticity   Income Elasticity&#13;
latter case it would be necessary to conduct an in-              +0.00           +2.00&#13;
depth review to ensure that the demand forecast                  -0.50           +2.93&#13;
was well founded, i.e., that the country would                   -100            +3 86&#13;
indeed follow a growth path out of line with ex-&#13;
perience elsewhere.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
For the period 2005 to 2025 the equation becomes:   and the sample of Latin American countries. The&#13;
price elasticities appear to be higher for industrial-&#13;
0.1 = 0.00 b + 0.05 a                (3)    ized countries, but are still substantial for the Latin&#13;
American countries.&#13;
When the rate of change of prices is zero, the value&#13;
of the price elasticity is immaterial. Thus the only  There have been some suggestions that income elas-&#13;
value of the income elasticity that is compatible with  ticities tend to fall as the level of income rises, but&#13;
the data is 2.0.                                    again little systematic testing of this hypothesis has&#13;
been carried out. The econometric evidence that&#13;
International benchmarks                            does exist supports a view that the long-run price&#13;
The key to using this approach is that the implicit    elasticity could well center around -0.5, but might be&#13;
values of the elasticities can be compared with those  higher. The long-run income elasticity is likely to be&#13;
established by more detailed investigation for other   greater than unity. Values larger than 2 have been&#13;
countries at a similar level of development. If the  reported for relatively short periods for some rapidly&#13;
sets of values are fairly close then this supports the    industrializing countries, but values greater than 3&#13;
reliability of the forecast power demand for the    are very rare.&#13;
country in question. On the other hand, if the values&#13;
are very different then the power demand forecast    In many projections the total growth of real income&#13;
should be viewed more critically.                   over the period is likely to be much larger than the&#13;
total movement in real electricity prices, so that the&#13;
Systematic evidence on international values of price   key to demand forecasting would be the value of&#13;
and income elasticities for electricity demand comes  the income elasticity. However, in periods where&#13;
from econometric studies which have correlated      prices are allowed to change very rapidly (typically&#13;
year-by-year power demand changes with income       in order to catch up to costs), price elasticities can&#13;
and price changes, as well as with other variables,    be just as important as income elasticities in deter-&#13;
when appropriate. There is a very large body of     mining overall power demand.&#13;
such work for industrialized countries, but relatively&#13;
little work of this nature has been done for develop-  Results&#13;
ing countries, especially for the poorest countries.  This simple test shows that a scenario of 10 percent&#13;
Westley (New Directions in Econometric Modeling of  demand growth, while income grows at 5 percent and&#13;
Energy Demand: With Applications to Latin America,  real prices grow at 9.3 percent for the first decade of&#13;
Inter-American Development Bank, 1992) surveys a   the forecast, is at the very edge of credibility. With a&#13;
wide range of studies for electricity demand. For a    price elasticity of -0.5, the income elasticity would&#13;
group of Latin American countries (Costa Rica, Para-  have to be almost 3 for the period in order for this&#13;
guay, Colombia, Dominican Republic, and Mexico)   forecast to be consistent with the macro scenario. A&#13;
the mean price elasticity is -0.48, and the mean in-    value of 3 for the income elasticity is outside the&#13;
come elasticity is 0.47 for residential and commercial  range of experience reported from other countries.&#13;
demand and 1.18 for industrial demand. For a sam-&#13;
ple of twenty-six studies of industrialized countries    For the period 2005 to 2025, where the income elas-&#13;
the mean long-run price elasticity is -1.15 and the  ticity would have to be 2.0, the scenario is consistent&#13;
income elasticity is 1.10. The two sets of income   with international evidence, but again such a value&#13;
elasticities are fairly similar, despite the very large  holding over a long period, while income levels&#13;
differences in per capita income between the coun-   grow very substantially, is certainly at the higher end&#13;
tries analyzed in the industrialized countries group,   of experience.&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The calculation of electricity-to-income ratios&#13;
TABLE 2: Electricity Intensity and GNP at Various Dates&#13;
The second check is simply to calculate the electricity    Date    GW'b        GNP       GWh/GNP   GNP/per&#13;
(energy) intensity ratio of the country over the project                   (US$mm1ion)  (US$milhon)   capita&#13;
life and relate this to projected per capita income.       1995      800      5,000        0.160       200&#13;
Projections which have demand running too far out          2000    1,288      6,381        0.202       226&#13;
of line with anticipated income growth, will imply         2005    2,075      8,144        0 255       256&#13;
2015    5,381     13,266        0.406      327&#13;
an energy intensity that does not equate with the          2025   13,960     21,610        o.646       420&#13;
experience of other countries with similar economic&#13;
living standards and similar economic conditions.&#13;
This check in effect ignores price effects, but it is&#13;
easier to obtain energy intensities for a wide range    Table 3 gives actual data for a sample of countries in&#13;
of countries than it is to obtain econometric models   1990. The countries selected have income per capita&#13;
for demand in low income countries.                      similar to the hypothetical case.&#13;
The starting values for demand and income need to&#13;
be known in order to calculate changes in energy           TABLE 3: Electricity Demand and GNP in Various Coun-&#13;
intensity over the period. This is illustrated for a       TriE 31990u&#13;
hypothetical country. In 1995 GNP is projected to be       tries (1990)&#13;
US$200 (1990 real) per capita, derived from a total                          (US$milhon) (US$millhon)  capita&#13;
GNP of US$5,000 million and a population of 25             Bangladesh 8,057    22,738       0 354      210&#13;
million. The population is projected to increase at        Malawi      587      1,701       0 345      200&#13;
2.5 percent per annum, so that real income per capi-       Rwanda      195      2,215       0 088      320&#13;
ta will grow at 2.5 percent for the whole period if        Kenya      3,215     8,939       0 360      370&#13;
GNP grows at the projected rate of 5.0 percent. The&#13;
number of GWh used in 1995 is projected to be 800.&#13;
From 1995 onwards, power demand and GNP are&#13;
assumed to grow as in the scenario used for the         These tables suggest that the energy intensities im-&#13;
previous elasticity analysis.                           plied in the demand projections for the hypothetical&#13;
country are again at the limits of experience com-&#13;
Table 2 gives the calculations for total GWh, real      pared to other developing countries. The projection&#13;
GNP, GWh per unit of real GNP, and GNP per capi-   of energy intensity for 2015 is well above that for&#13;
ta at various dates. The energy intensity more than     countries such as Kenya, which at present has a&#13;
quadruples over the thirty-year period. This is not     substantially higher per capita real income than the&#13;
surprising given that the growth of power demand is  hypothetical country will have after twenty years.&#13;
projected to rise 5 percent per annum more rapidly&#13;
than income over a twenty-year period.                  Robert Bacon, Industry and Energy Department&#13;
This se4es is published to share Ideas and invite discussion. It covers financial and pnvate sector development as well as&#13;
industry and energy The views expressed are those of the author(s) and are not intended to represent an official statement of&#13;
Bank policy or strategy&#13;
Comiments are welcome Please call the FPD Note line to leave a message. 202-458-1 11 1, or contact Suzanne Smith, editor, Room&#13;
G8105, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC 20043, or Internet address ssmithElworldbank.org.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441493">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/06/441493/reality-checks-power-forecasts-two-simple-checks-relating-power-sector-demand-forecasts-macroeconomy
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/06/441493/reality-checks-power-forecasts-two-simple-checks-relating-power-sector-demand-forecasts-macroeconomy</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1994/06/441493/reality-checks-power-forecasts-two-simple-checks-relating-power-sector-demand-forecasts-macroeconomy</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2000-10-24T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2000-10-24T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980218124215/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980218124215/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2000-10-24T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1994-06-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Reality checks for power forecasts : two
            simple checks relating power sector demand forecasts to the macroeconomy
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In some of the poorer countries now
            starting to look at large power projects, the information on
            past power demand patterns is not good enough to make
            reliable demand forecasts. Forecasters often end up simply
            projecting current growth rates. But this can produce
            forecasts that are inconsistent with macroeconomic
            developments such as the real price rises that occur when
            governments remove subsidies. The author outlines two simple
            reality checks to help prevent forecast error.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Reality checks for power forecasts : two
            simple checks relating power sector demand forecasts to the macroeconomy
        </docna>
        <display_title>Reality checks for power
            forecasts : two simple checks relating power sector demand
            forecasts to the macroeconomy</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1994/06/441493/reality-checks-power-forecasts-two-simple-checks-relating-power-sector-demand-forecasts-macroeconomy</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Energy and Environment,Inequality,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Energy,Poverty Reduction,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Bacon, Robert</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980218124215</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Power &amp; Energy Conversion</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 9,FPD note no. 9</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Energy,Poverty Reduction,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Energy demand; Power generation; Electric
            power rates; Macroeconomic planning; Project appraisal;
            Gross national product
            annual rate,average annual,average
            growth,average growth rate,average rate,benchmarks,demand
            forecasting,demand growth,developing countries,Econometric
            Modeling,econometric models,economic
            conditions,elasticities,elasticity,electricity,electricity
            demand,electricity prices,Energy Demand,energy
            intensity,forecasts,GNP,growth rate,growth
            rates,income,income elasticity,income increase,income
            levels,living standards,low income,per capita income,price
            changes,price elasticities,price elasticity,price elasticity
            of demand,Private Sector,real GNP,real income,real level
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>16953</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Demand</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>