<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank Group                                                                        May 1997&#13;
Note No. 111   Ownership and Corporate Governance-&#13;
Evidence from the Czech Republic&#13;
Stijn Claessens,    The Czech voucher privatization scheme, which started in 1991, was one of the earliest, most&#13;
Simeon Djankov   comprehensive, and most rapidly implemented of all the mass privatization schemes in Eastern&#13;
and Gerhard&#13;
Pohl             Europe and the former Soviet Union. The scheme has resulted in relatively concentrated owner-&#13;
ship: of the shares offered, two-thirds ended up with investment funds, most of them with a&#13;
small number of bank-sponsored funds. How have these changes in ownership affected enter-&#13;
prise governance and restructuring? There is some evidence to suggest that Czech firms are per-&#13;
forming better than firms in other Central and Eastern European countries. But so far there has&#13;
been only limited anecdotal evidence about the impact of the Czech ownership changes on gov-&#13;
ernance. This Note reports on a new study that assesses whether concentrated ownership leads&#13;
to better oversight of firm managers in the Czech Republic.&#13;
The best approach to enterprise             much each of these reforms has contributed to&#13;
restructuring?                              improved performance has not been empirically&#13;
established. But it is clear that better manage-&#13;
Large-scale enterprise restructuring in transi-   ment is vital for restructuring-and better man-&#13;
tion economies is a wide-ranging process of   agement will come about only through changes&#13;
moving from a highly distorted economy with  in firms' ownership structure.&#13;
many loss-making firms to a normal market&#13;
economy in which most firms are profitable.   There is much debate, too, over which method&#13;
For government policy, it implies making losses   of privatization is best. Some countries have&#13;
transparent by liberalizing prices and adopt-  stressed the importance of attracting good&#13;
ing new accounting standards and practices.   owners in the form of strategic-usually for-&#13;
For firms, it usually means shedding labor and   eign-investors. But the number of enterprises&#13;
concentrating on activities in which they have   privatized and restructured through direct sales&#13;
a competitive advantage.                    to foreign investors has been small. In Hungary,&#13;
for example, the sale of firms to foreign inves-&#13;
How to bring about enterprise restructuring most  tors has received much publicity, but only a&#13;
efficiently is a matter of lively debate. Different  few large firms with significant market power&#13;
countries have used different strategies over the   have in fact been privatized this way. Foreign&#13;
past seven years: depoliticizing management by   investors have been uninterested in the aver-&#13;
giving managers more autonomy, increasing   age-size industrial firm.&#13;
competition, improving financial discipline (in-&#13;
cluding through bankruptcy and liquidation of   Countries such as the Czech Republic and Rus-&#13;
loss-making firms), revamping state asset man-   sia have developed mass privatization programs&#13;
agement systems, and privatizing firms. How    where the emphasis has been on speed. The&#13;
Private Sector Development Department . Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Ownership and Corporate Governance-Evidence from the Czech Republic&#13;
phases. The first phase, offering nearly 1,000&#13;
firms, started in late 1991 and ended in mid-&#13;
t- -- ~~~~1993. The second, offering more than 850 firms,&#13;
started in January 1994 and ended in October&#13;
of that year. The share auctions, organized in&#13;
five sequential rounds of bidding, were designed&#13;
to reveal as much information and analysis of&#13;
firm vatuation as possible, to improve price dis-&#13;
were exchanged for shares and secondary trad-&#13;
ing started on the Prague stock exchange.&#13;
Czech mass privatization program, imple-   All citizens aged eighteen and over could buy&#13;
mented first and covering the largest share of   vouchers for a nominal fee to use in bidding at&#13;
the enterprise sector, moved about 70 percent   these auctions-directly or through financial&#13;
of the Czech economy from the state to pri-  intermediaries called investment funds. In es-&#13;
vate hands within a short period. The Czech   sence, these investment funds involved a spon-&#13;
program is thus a good test case of the effect   sor first setting up a management company,&#13;
of this predominant approach to changing the   which then set up a fund to own the shares.&#13;
ownership of firms--an approach that has prob-   The management company manages the fund&#13;
ably contributed to the Czech Republic's bet-  for a fee under contract and the shareholders&#13;
ter record in enterprise restructuring compared   of the fund are the former voucher holders and&#13;
with other transition economies.             any new investors who buy fund shares in sec-&#13;
ondary markets. (See figure 1 for the structure&#13;
The Czech mass privatization                  of these funds.)&#13;
In preparation for privatization, firms were   When initiated, the program elicited much&#13;
corporatized but only very limited restructuring   skepticism. Mass privatization would lead to&#13;
was carried out. Privatization occurred in two   ownership by outside investors, but many ex-&#13;
pected that it would also lead to diffuse own-&#13;
ership and poor oversight of management. As&#13;
FUgUE2  O$ERSIIPI~ONE ~   ND-  =things turned out, many investment funds&#13;
PROFLTABILITY                                    emerged and, through aggressive marketing,&#13;
collected 75 percent of the vouchers held by&#13;
1      m     _    _   d  _ i _    _g.8=g_8             citizens. Bank-sponsored funds acquired the&#13;
most, with the ten largest holding nearly 70&#13;
percent of the vouchers acquired by the in-&#13;
vestment funds. This outcome held out the&#13;
promise of better oversight by owners: con-&#13;
&gt;OM                                         ~~~~~~~~~~~~~centrated ownership gives the owners better&#13;
incentives to monitor firms and make neces-&#13;
sary changes in management. By contrast, in&#13;
firms with diffuse ownership, no single owner&#13;
has an incentive to "mind the store,' so man-&#13;
&lt;3D    3H1    40-50 ~50-~OD   00-40   ~  agement is not disciplined for had performance&#13;
~ percntageo~otaI hares utst~nlii~g~or rewarded for good performance.&#13;
~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~~In 1992-95 the Czech Republic had a good&#13;
record in enterprise restructuring. A separate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 3  OWNERSHIP CONCENTRATION AND MARKET&#13;
VALUATlON&#13;
Alt firms&#13;
Ratio of ma*ket value&#13;
study comparing enterprise performance in all      to bookvalue&#13;
Central and East European countries (Bulgaria,      1.2&#13;
the Czech Republic, Hungary, Poland, Roma-&#13;
nia, the Slovak Republic, and Slovenia) shows&#13;
that Czech firms had the highest growth rates&#13;
in labor and total factor productivity, followed&#13;
by Polish and Slovak firms.' To shed more light     8.9&#13;
on this result and to see how changes in own-&#13;
ership affect the way Czech firms are managed,&#13;
the study that is the subject of this Note looks    0.7&#13;
at whether firms with more concentrated own-&#13;
ership are indeed better managed. If that were                                   0-6 _- =.&#13;
the case, these firms would have higher profit-       Topiviow shares apercetqeofoalsh s&#13;
ability and their shares would trade for higher&#13;
prices in the stock market. After all, if more     Firm=s in which iank-spo6s.red funds are the- maorit-&#13;
concentrated ownership leads to better over-       owners&#13;
sight of managers, profitability should corre-     Ratoofmaietaloe&#13;
late positively with the degree of ownership&#13;
concentration. And market prices, which in-   1-    2&#13;
corporate the effect of better oversight on fu-&#13;
ture firm performance, should be higher for&#13;
firms with more concentrated ownership. In&#13;
market economies, where this is a much-stud-&#13;
ied topic, these relationships are quite strong.&#13;
0.3&#13;
Analysis&#13;
Using data for all the more than 700 Czech        -0.6&#13;
firms that were consistently listed on the Prague   .     30= - 3-4    4040             - 00-0  &gt;7.:&#13;
Stock Exchange over the period 1992-95, the           Toiveeslses apercet              an&#13;
study finds that there are indeed strong posi-       r - n -i .   . k-      r .u: s - . te -aj i=&#13;
FIrms In whchba afnnsefed, fus -ar-h meaiiil- y 1&#13;
tive relationships between ownership concen-              a      i       s&#13;
tration and profitability (figure 2).2 It also finds   E   owars n vaine&#13;
that the more concentrated the ownership of a            vtohoo. i -  &#13;
firm, the higher its market value (figure 3, top   1.2i-&#13;
panel).3 (This correlation sometimes breaks   -u&#13;
down when a single investor holds more than&#13;
50 percent of all shares, since the shares of&#13;
minority shareholders are then valued less.)   -    ..&#13;
Together, the two results suggest that the Czech         -                       -&#13;
privatization program was effective in improv-&#13;
ing firms' management because of the concen-       0i&#13;
trated ownership structure that resulted.      X&#13;
Much of the ownership is concentrated in turn&#13;
among funds sponsored by commercial banks,            Teptiwo a sa-ga         *-ret&#13;
which themselves are large creditors of the firms&#13;
in which the funds hold equity stakes. What&#13;
does this mean for the quality of corporate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Ownership and Corporate Governance-Evidence from the Czech Republic&#13;
governance? Many analysts have argued that    stake. Any negative effects of conflicts of in-&#13;
the investment funds face conflicts of interest    terest-due to banks' controlling equity-thus&#13;
because they have to serve multiple objectives:    appear to be outweighed by the positive ef-&#13;
when deciding in which company to invest and             fects of banks' close monitoring of firms in&#13;
how to value firms, a bank-sponsored fund has    which they have an (indirect) equity stake.&#13;
to balance the interests of the bank with the&#13;
interests of the fund shareholders. Under pres-    Conclusion&#13;
sure from the sponsor, for example, the fund&#13;
managers could encourage firms to borrow                 The Czech Republic's mass privatization pro-&#13;
from the sponsor bank at higher interest rates,    gram  has spurred enterprise restructuring and&#13;
thus treating fund shareholders unfairly in fa-    led to better monitoring of firms. The invest-&#13;
vor of the bank. But it can also be argued that    ment funds, which supervise and manage firms&#13;
a bank that has an (indirect) equity stake in a    on behalf of their investors, have played a key&#13;
firm  can better monitor the firm  and its man-    part in this. The Czech model offers useful les-&#13;
agement. Through its representation on the               sons for other transition economies: the speed&#13;
board of directors, the bank has access to more          of privatization matters, and both more con-&#13;
information and is more willing to monitor the           centrated ownership and indirect ownership by&#13;
firm. The better corporate governance that can           banks lead to faster restructuring.&#13;
result makes it more likely that the firm will&#13;
restructure, leading to higher market value and&#13;
forum intended to      profitability. The firm  may also have easier    This Note is based on a paper of the same title (Policy Research Work-&#13;
encourage dissemina-   access to bank financing, which again makes    ing Paper 1737, World Bank, Washington, DC, April 1997).&#13;
Stijo Claessens, Simeon Djankov, and Gerhard Pohl, 'Determninants&#13;
tion of and debate on  restructuring more likely.                                  of Performance of Manufacturing Firms in Seven European Transi-&#13;
ideas, innovations, and                                                            ton Economnies" (World Bank, Europe and Central Asia, and Middle&#13;
best practices for                                                                 East and North Africa Technical Department, Washington, DC, March&#13;
expanding the private  Since ownership by bank-sponsored funds                     1997).&#13;
sector. The views      potentially has two opposite effects on the               2 The definition of profitability is&#13;
published are these of                                                                               Gross operating profit&#13;
the authors and should  value and profitability of firms, the net effect               Profitability = Nfess o     it&#13;
not be attributed to the  is an empirical matter. But it is clear that banks       T  dnNet fnxed assets + inventory&#13;
3The definition of market value is&#13;
World Bank or any of its    have dual incentives to help firms restructure.                         Stock market valuation + total debt&#13;
affiliated organizations.                                                              Market vaLue =&#13;
Nor do any of the con-  First, improvements in firms' performance will                                 Net fixed assets + inventory&#13;
clusions represent     increase their market value and thus the re-&#13;
official policy of the  turn on the assets of bank-sponsored funds.    Stijn Claessens, Principal Economist, East Asia&#13;
World Bank or of its&#13;
Executive Directors    Second, firms with improved profitability are             and the Pacific Vice Presidency (claessens@&#13;
or the countries they  likely to borrow  to finance new  investments.            worldbank.org), and Simeon Djankov, EMTPS&#13;
represent.                                                                       Financial Economist (sdjankov@worldbank.&#13;
To order additional    The empirical analysis shows that concentrated            org), and Gerhard Pohl, Manager (gpohl@&#13;
copies please call 202-  ownership  by bank-sponsored  investment    worldbank.org), Private Sector Development&#13;
458-1111 or contact    funds is beneficial in improving firm  manage-    and Finance Group, Europe and Central Asia,&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,&#13;
Room G8105, The World  ment (figure 3, middle panel). And it finds no            and Middle East and North Africa, Technical&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street,   evidence that market value and profitability are          Department&#13;
NW, Washington, D.C.   lower for firms in which investment funds spon-&#13;
20433, or Internet&#13;
address ssmith7@       sored by the firm's main bank have a large&#13;
worldbank.org.         ownership stake, which would be the case if&#13;
The series is also     conflicts of interest dominated. On the con-&#13;
available on-line&#13;
(www.worldbank.        trary, it finds that (indirect) ownership control&#13;
org/html/fpd/notes/    by the main bank has a positive effect (figure&#13;
notelist.html).        3, bottom  panel). This suggests that, on bal-&#13;
SPrinted on recycled   ance, banks play a positive role in supervising&#13;
paper                  firms when they also hold an (indirect) equity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441453">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/05/441453/ownership-corporate-governance-evidence-czech-republic
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/05/441453/ownership-corporate-governance-evidence-czech-republic</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/05/441453/ownership-corporate-governance-evidence-czech-republic</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980313101846/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980313101846/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-05-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1997-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Ownership and corporate governance :
            evidence from the Czech Republic
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The authors argue that mass
            privatization in the Czech Republic has spurred enterprise
            restructuring and that investment funds have played a key
            part in this outcome. Using 1992-95 data for more than 700
            Czech firms, the authors find strong positive relationships
            between ownership concentration and profitability. And the
            higher the ownership concentration, the higher the
            firm's market value. They argue that these two results
            suggest that the Czech privatization program was effective
            in improving firms' management because of the
            concentrated ownership that resulted.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Ownership and corporate governance :
            evidence from the Czech Republic
        </docna>
        <display_title>Ownership and corporate
            governance : evidence from the Czech Republic</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1997/05/441453/ownership-corporate-governance-evidence-czech-republic</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Small Scale Enterprise,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Financial Crisis Management &amp; Restructuring,Private Participation in Infrastructure</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Industry,Conflict and Development</teratopic>
        <count>Czech Republic</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Claesens, Stijn</author>
            <author>Djankov, Simeon</author>
            <author>Pohl, Gerhard</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980313101846</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Privatization-DV</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 111</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Industry,Conflict and Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Private Sector Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Denationalization; Investment trusts;
            Ownership; Private enterprises
            accounting,accounting standards,affiliated
            organizations,auctions,autonomy,bankruptcy,bidding,commercial
            banks,company,corporate governance,corporate
            Ownership,debt,empirical analysis,enterprise
            restructuring,firms,fixed assets,foreign investors,interest
            rates,inventory,liquidation,market valuation,market
            value,privatization,productivity,profitability,shareholders,transition
            economies,voucher privatization
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>16869</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Debt Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Closing of Business</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civic Participation and Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Small Scale Enterprise</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bankruptcy and Liquidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Resolution and Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Corporate Law</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Czech Republic</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>