<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank                                                                            May 1996&#13;
Note No.79   Mitigating Project Risks  World Bank&#13;
Support for Government Guarantees&#13;
PhilrppeBenoit    Project risks and risk mitigation         as an offshore bank, issue the guarantee (for&#13;
example, a letter of credit). Under this struc-&#13;
Private investors try to mitigate the risks facing   ture, often used to provide coverage to for-&#13;
a proposed project before they invest Foreign   eign investors concerned about timely payment&#13;
investors in developing countries are often con-  from a host government guarantor, the inves-&#13;
cerned about two kinds of risk in particular.  tors look to the third-party guarantor for pay-&#13;
The first is political risk-risk relating to politi-   ment, and the third party relies on the host&#13;
cal acts of government and to the general coun-   government for reimbursement.&#13;
try context, including war, expropriation, and&#13;
restrictions on repatriation of earnings The sec-   World Bank support for guarantees&#13;
ond kind of risk, referred to here as 'parastatal&#13;
risk," relates to the performance of parastatal   The World Bank has employed two distinct&#13;
companies and includes such risks as failure  financial vehicles to support developing coun-&#13;
of the government-owned power company to  try governments that decide to provide guar-&#13;
supply electricity to a project           antees to attract private investment issuing&#13;
guarantees to investors and making loans to&#13;
To mitigate project risks, investors generally   host governments to fund guarantees&#13;
require guarantees from the project sponsors&#13;
For protection specifically against political risks,   World Bank guarantees&#13;
investors often procure insurance or guaran-&#13;
tees from specialized institutions, such as ex-   The International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
port credit agencies or private political risk   Development (IBRD), one of the World Bank's&#13;
insurers. Another source of political risk insur-  two constituent organizations, has established&#13;
ance for foreign investment in developing coun-   a guarantee program to issue guarantees to&#13;
tries is the Multilateral Investment Guarantee   lenders covering either all or a part of their&#13;
Agency (MIGA), a specialized organization in  loan against certain specified risks (partial risk&#13;
the World Bank Group                      guarantees), or certain specified payments un-&#13;
der their loan against all risks (partial credit&#13;
In addition, foreign investors in developing   guarantees) The Bank's other constituent or-&#13;
countries often approach host governments for   ganization, the International Development As-&#13;
guarantees, particularly for political and   sociation (IDA). which lends at concessional&#13;
parastatal risks. Host governments structure  rates, has never issued guarantees and has no&#13;
these guarantees in a variety of ways They   guarantee program in place.&#13;
may issue guarantees directly to investors. Or&#13;
they may establish a special facility to do so,   When the IBRD issues its guarantee, it receives&#13;
such as a facility to issue guarantees for export   a counterguarantee from the host country, un-&#13;
financing. In both these approaches, investors   der which the country remains financially re-&#13;
rely on the host government to finance pay-   sponsible for any payments that the IBRD&#13;
ments under the guarantee. But in some   makes to lenders (figure 1). The IBRD has is-&#13;
projects, governments have a third party, such   sued guarantees for several large infrastructure&#13;
ku              Private Sector Development Department . Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
L&amp;W                 Mitigating Pmject Risks-World Bank Support for Government Guarantees&#13;
FIGURE 1 - IBRD GUARANTEE&#13;
Ceirnie,-                   ~~~~~projects For example, in the 1994 Pakistan Hub&#13;
- , = -e                                River Power Project, the IBRD issued a partial&#13;
iGuaratntee                             risk guarantee protecting lenders against debt&#13;
service defaults resulting from a breach by the&#13;
Pakistan government of its undertakings to the&#13;
project company These undertakings relate to&#13;
-~ - - ---- ~ ~ -~ l Loan1- -  -          ~ parastatal performance and certain political&#13;
risks (such as currency transfer). Projects in-&#13;
votving the partial credit guarantee include the&#13;
1994 China Yangzhou Thermal Power Project&#13;
and the 1994 Philippines Leyte-Luzon Geother-&#13;
mal Project; in both cases, the IBRD guarantee&#13;
-IURE Z  WORLD BANK-FINANCED T'HIRiJIPRY                                                     &#13;
GUARANTEE                       ~~ covered long-term maturities.'&#13;
World Bank financing of government&#13;
guarantees&#13;
ReinE bnrementwgreenieni     E - r     --         The World Bank can also support host govern-&#13;
ment guarantees by providing loans to finance&#13;
them  The host country provides investors with&#13;
Guarantee                   ~~~~a guarantee, the World Bank provides a loan&#13;
-     -            ~~~~~~~Guarantee        ---==-    ----&#13;
to the country, and the country draws down&#13;
the loan if and as required to finance payments&#13;
due to the investors under the guarantee. Such&#13;
World Bank loans could be provided to finance&#13;
- - - -- - Yesi0nt-- -                   - -a wide range of government guarantee struc-&#13;
tures, ncluding the third-party guarantee struc-&#13;
ture (figure 2).&#13;
The World Bank has provided loans to fund guar-&#13;
antees and other forms of coverage in only a&#13;
Fi&amp;URE 3 -WORLD BANK(FINANCED AND                               few projects to date. One such project, the 1995&#13;
-- MIGA-ADMINISTEBEI GUARANTEE=-                8    Moldova Pre-Export Guarantee Facility Project,&#13;
_                            i~~~~~~~~nvolves both a government guarantee facility&#13;
-ean                 ff   -and a third-party guarantor. Moldova established&#13;
a guarantee facility to cover foreign supplier&#13;
-   ~   ~ Admtnistrat,opagree,ment4g |-------- - ~-      =- credit provided to its exporters against speci-&#13;
fied political risks In parallel, an offshore bank&#13;
(the agent bank), acting as a third-party guaran-&#13;
tor on behalf of Moldova, issued standby letters&#13;
- -- -~ Gnaaantea      -; ~ ~~= ~ of credit to the foreign creditors, backstopping&#13;
bank could draw down the IBRD loan to fund&#13;
payments to be made under its letters of credit&#13;
-    -   --lfvetuoe[ - 7- - - --=---------------   to the foreign creditors. In a second project, the&#13;
1994 Argentina Capital Market Development&#13;
Project, the government created a backstop fa-&#13;
cility to purchase eligible commercial bank&#13;
bonds from banks otherwise unable to place&#13;
them because of specified market disruptions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The IBRD provided a loan to Argentina to fund  First, the World Bank has greater leverage than&#13;
eventual payments from the facility.           most commercial banks and other private in-&#13;
vestors over developing country govern-&#13;
Integrating Bank and MIGA support              ments-in large part because of its financial,&#13;
contractual, and cooperative relationships with&#13;
The World Bank and MIGA are exploring an       these countries, as well as its multilateral char-&#13;
integrated approach to supporting host gov-    acter. It can use this leverage to discourage&#13;
ernments of developing countries in providing  unreasonable government actions that would&#13;
political risk coverage for foreign investments    threaten the success of a project. Second, a&#13;
where insurers are unwilling to issue insurance  payment by the World Bank always entails a&#13;
funded from their own resources (figure 3)     corresponding obligation from the host gov-&#13;
Under this approach                            ernment-under the counterguarantee for an&#13;
* The World Bank would provide a loan to the   IBRD guarantee, and under the loan itself for&#13;
host country.                                a loan financing a guarantee This obligation&#13;
X The country would use the loan to provide    creates a financial disincentive for a govern-&#13;
designated investors with coverage against   ment to take actions that would trigger pay-&#13;
specified political risks                    ments to the investors&#13;
* The country would have MIGA administer   * Guarantees and loans to finance guarantees&#13;
the coverage.                                allow host governments to shed project rnsks&#13;
* Both the investors and the country would    that they would assume under a traditional&#13;
rely on MIGA to evaluate and process any     World Bank loan Under traditional debt fi-&#13;
investor claims                              nancing, the country must repay the World&#13;
* As administrator, MIGA would pay investors'  Bank loan even if the project fails, regard-&#13;
claims, using the proceeds from the country's    less of the reason Under guarantees, the&#13;
Bank loan                                    Bank makes payments, which trnggers the&#13;
* The country would be obligated to repay to   government's financial liability, only for speci-&#13;
the Bank all amounts withdrawn under the     fied risks These instruments thus provide&#13;
loan-but the loan would be drawn down        governments with a straightforward mecha-&#13;
only if and as required to pay valid claims.  nism for shedding project risks, particularly&#13;
commercial ones, by leaving the exposure&#13;
This approach is being considered for a power  for them with private investors.&#13;
project whose foreign sponsors are concerned   Guarantees also provide a mechanism for gov-&#13;
about their ability to convert local currency  ernments in transnational projects, such as the&#13;
earnings into foreign exchange The host gov-   construction of a pipeline between two coun-&#13;
ernment has requested an IDA loan to finance   tnes, to allocate political risks between the&#13;
currency transfer coverage for these investors,  host countries. In such a project, each host&#13;
to be administered by MIGA.                    government could provide lenders with a guar-&#13;
antee covering the political risks relating to&#13;
The implications of Bank support               its country The lenders would be covered&#13;
against all political risks, while each gov-&#13;
World Bank support for guarantees presents     emient's liability to the lenders would be lim-&#13;
several advantages'                            ited to the political risks its country poses&#13;
* The IBRD, under its guarantee program,   * The World Bank can provide developing&#13;
serves as an independent offshore guarantor  countrnes with the financial resources (typi-&#13;
with strong financial standing-to which      cally in foreign exchange) to fund payments&#13;
lenders can turn to for payment regardless    to investors or to a third-party guarantor.&#13;
of the host government's actions or financial   * Guarantees often allow a project to obtain&#13;
weaknesses.                                  lending on relatively favorable terms by pro-&#13;
* The World Bank's involvement in a transac-    tecting lenders and mitigating political and&#13;
tion can mitigate political risks in two ways  parastatal risks This can lead to a lower&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Mitigating Pmject Risks-World Bank Support for Government Guarantees&#13;
interest rate or extend the maturity of the    tory reforms-which reduce the cost to gov-&#13;
loans, as has been the case with the IBRD           ernments of attracting private investment and&#13;
partial credit guarantees. But guarantees can    eventually obviate the need for host govern-&#13;
also add to the transaction costs. there typi-    ment guarantees.&#13;
cally are guarantee fees, and legal expenses&#13;
may be higher if the guarantee makes the    Use of guarantees&#13;
transaction much more complex.&#13;
Obtaining the services of a third-party guar-    Whether the World Bank should provide an&#13;
antor can be costly for governments of de-    IBRD guarantee or a loan financing a govern-&#13;
veloping countries that do not enjoy a strong    ment guarantee for a proposed project depends&#13;
credit rating  Commercial institutions may    on the assessment of the project and the costs&#13;
require the government to provide escrow             and benefits of such Bank support. The Bank&#13;
accounts and other costly security arrange-    assesses the project's development impact, the&#13;
ments to back the government's reimburse-    investor's need for the guarantee, the nature&#13;
ment obligation. But the World Bank, because    of the risks to be covered, the government's&#13;
of its development character and leverage in    actions to mitigate those risks, the cost of such&#13;
securing reimbursement by member country    coverage to the government, and the benefits&#13;
governments, can fulfill the role of third-    to the country from the investor's involvement&#13;
party guarantor at a relatively low  cost to    in the project. Another factor considered by&#13;
the government                                      the Bank is the ability of the government and&#13;
the investors to obtain alternatives to Bank sup-&#13;
An integrated World Bank-MIGA  approach    port. These include MIGA insurance and risk&#13;
would present several additional advantages            mitigation provided by the International Fi-&#13;
open forum intended to    It would permit a developing country govern-    nance Corporation (IFC), another member of&#13;
encourage dissemina-  ment to finance political risk coverage for in-    the World Bank Group.3&#13;
tion of and debate on  vestors in order to secure their participation in&#13;
ideas, innovations, and&#13;
beas practices for    priority development projects  It would give    To date, the World Bank has issued few IBRD&#13;
expanding the private  these governments access to MIGA's expertise    guarantees and loans to finance government&#13;
sector The views      in designing and administering political risk    guarantees. Their use has been hampered in part&#13;
published are those of&#13;
the authors and should    insurance And it would provide investors with    by their newness As government officials, the&#13;
not be attributed to the  an offshore, independent third party to admin-    private sector, and Bank staff become more com-&#13;
World Bank or any of its   ister the coverage  The result of this integra-    fortable with these instruments, and as the em-&#13;
affiliated organizations&#13;
Nor do any of the con-    tion of the Bank and MIGA would be a structure    phasis on prnvate sector investment in projects&#13;
clusions represent    that makes the most of the comparative ad-    increases, the number of projects in which these&#13;
official policy of the  vantages of each institution                         instruments play a part wtll likely grow&#13;
World Bank or of its&#13;
Executive Directors&#13;
or the countries they  But World Bank support for government guar-    l For a fuller discussion, see Philippe Benoit, Project Finance at the&#13;
represent             antees can raise concerns in certain circum-             World Bank, World Bank Techmcal Paper 312 (Washington, Dc,&#13;
Comments are welcome    stances  Guarantees are generally inefficient          1996)&#13;
Pleas cal theFPD  istruentswhere there is a strong likelihood    2For a fuller descnption of IBRDf guarantees, see the Wodld Bank's&#13;
Please call the FPDJ  instruments where there 1S a strong llkellhod            Guarantees and the Project Finance and Guarantees sernes, pub-&#13;
Note line to leave a  that the risks guaranteed against will occur In          lished by the World Bank's Cofinancing and Project Finance&#13;
messonage S202458-111    these cases, efforts should focus on reducing         Department&#13;
or contact Suzanne    the risks toreasould                  Fu rermore,        For example, the IFC offeis a loan svndication program that pro-&#13;
Smith, editor, Room  the risks to a reasonable level Furthermore,              vides commercial lenders with the protection of its lender-of-record&#13;
G8105, The World Bank,   the availability of guarantees might encourage        umbrella For a fuller descnption of MIGA and the IFC, see their&#13;
1 818 H Street, NW, &#13;
Washington, D C 20433,   investors to seek broader protection from host        1995 annual reports&#13;
or Internet address   governments than they would otherwise re-&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank org    quire  And while guarantees provide protec-    Philippe Benoit, Senior Prvate Sector Develop-&#13;
@Printed on recycled  hon to specific investors in specific transactions,    ment Specialist, Private Sector Development&#13;
paper                 they are no substitute for substantive regula-    Department (email pbenoit@worldbank org)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441483">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/05/441483/mitigating-project-risks-world-bank-support-government-guarantees
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/05/441483/mitigating-project-risks-world-bank-support-government-guarantees</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1996/05/441483/mitigating-project-risks-world-bank-support-government-guarantees</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980218124209/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980218124209/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1996-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2000-10-24T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Mitigating project risks : World Bank
            support for government guarantees
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The World Bank has two distinct
            financial vehicles to support developing country governments
            wanting to provide guarantees to attract private investors:
            issuing guarantees to investors and making loans to host
            governments to fund guarantees. The author explains how
            these vehicles work and reviews some of their advantages and disadvantages.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Mitigating project risks : World Bank
            support for government guarantees
        </docna>
        <display_title>Mitigating project risks : World
            Bank support for government guarantees</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1996/05/441483/mitigating-project-risks-world-bank-support-government-guarantees</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Public Sector Economics,Financial Crisis Management &amp; Restructuring,Economic Adjustment and Lending</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Public Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Benoit, Philippe</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980218124209</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Public Sector Management</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 79</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Public Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Project risks; Risk management; Government
            ownership; Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency; Foreign
            investments; Political stability; Risk assessment; Private
            investments; Investment risks; Government guarantees
            Bank accounts,Bank
            guarantees,bonds,commercial banks,coverage,debt,debt
            service,electricity,financial resources,foreign
            exchange,foreign sponsors,government
            guarantees,guarantor,insurance,insurers,lender,lenders,loan,loan
            financing,maturities,maturity,Private Sector,project
            sponsors,rates,risk mitigation,transaction costs,World Bank
            financing,World Bank loans
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>16938</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agent Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Resolution and Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>