<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 157                                                                         November 1998&#13;
World Bank Guarantees for Oil&#13;
and Gas Projects&#13;
Scott Sinclair   Private investors are considering several large-scale oil and gas production, pipeline, and cross-&#13;
border pipeline projects in developing countries, including in West Africa and in the Caspian Sea&#13;
region. While the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund are well known for their work in&#13;
helping to create enabling environments for foreign investment in large infrastructure projects, by&#13;
supporting reform in such areas as taxation and energy legislation, this Note focuses on a different&#13;
role for the World Bank-encouraging private sector involvement in large-scale oil and gas projects&#13;
by providing guarantees in direct support of the government contractual undertakings that may be&#13;
needed to induce foreign direct investment in these projects. World Bank guarantees offer a unique&#13;
type of risk mitigation that may prove to be a catalyst in raising finance for these projects.&#13;
In developing countries hydrocarbon resources   Government undertakings&#13;
have traditionally been owned and developed&#13;
by the state. But as recovering these resources   The concession agreement between a govern-&#13;
has become increasingly difficult and costly,   ment and the project entity is the document&#13;
governments have begun inviting foreign in-  that defines the government's obligations to the&#13;
vestors to become involved in the sector. The   project. This Note uses the term concession&#13;
role offered to private sector participants var-  agreement broadly, to include production shar-&#13;
ies from country to country, but in all cases  ing agreements, transport and transit agree-&#13;
the government continues to play a significant   ments, and government offtake agreements.&#13;
role, sometimes as a regulator, sometimes as&#13;
an investor, sometimes as an offtake purchaser,  In a typical oil and gas concession agreement&#13;
and sometimes as all three.               the government grants to the project entity the&#13;
right to develop the project in exchange for a&#13;
Because of the large capital requirements for  stream of payments or payments-in-kind. This&#13;
many oil and gas projects, and the growing re-   government revenue stream may take several&#13;
luctance of many oil and gas companies to use  forms, but typically includes one or more of&#13;
their balance sheets to fund these projects, many   the following:&#13;
private sector sponsors are pursuing project fi-   * Fixed rents.&#13;
nancing. A successful project financing depends   * Royalties (based on sales).&#13;
in large part on the strength of the contractual   * Profit overrides (effectively reducing the&#13;
commitments of the various project participants,    upside potential to sponsors).&#13;
which, taken together, ensure lenders that there   * Taxes (income orotherwise).&#13;
will be a reliable source of cash flow for repay-&#13;
ment of the debt. Among the most important  In some concessions the government, or a state-&#13;
commitments are the contractual undertakings   owned enterprise such as the state gas com-&#13;
of the host government or governments.    pany, will contract to purchase the oil or gas&#13;
The World Bank Group * Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2                   World Bank Guarantees for Oil and Gas Projects&#13;
produced by the project. If the state enterprise    might otherwise hinder a project financing.&#13;
contracts for a significant share of the through-    Such risks include political force majeure events&#13;
put, the creditworthiness of this offtake obli-   (such as civil unrest and general strikes), cur-&#13;
gation  becomes  key  to  the  project's   rency availability and convertibility, and per-&#13;
financeability.                                    mitting (box 1).&#13;
A comprehensive concession agreement for a    What are the consequences if a government fails&#13;
large oil and gas project should address the    to meet its obligations under a concession agree-&#13;
government's obligations to establish a frame-    ment? Clearly, a simple right to terminate the&#13;
work for dealing with a variety of risks that   concession agreement offers no real remedy to&#13;
the project sponsors and no comfort to their&#13;
lenders. Instead, a concession agreement needs&#13;
to provide for financial compensation to the&#13;
project sponsor, through a compensatory reduc-&#13;
'1  *  m                  htion of the government's revenue stream  or&#13;
through contingent payment obligations.&#13;
Maintainthesameschemeoffents.roykes taxs. duties,.and           A government's willingness to bear such a con-&#13;
accounting procedures.                                          tingent liability is in theory a function of its re-&#13;
Grant rights of way, easements, permits, and licenses without   ward for doing it. The desirability of the project&#13;
delay.                                                          to the country will guide the government's pro-&#13;
. Grant import and exporrights and visas.        ..pensity to take risk in general. In other words,&#13;
&#149; Grant import and export rights and visas.              if the government views the benefits as high, it&#13;
&#149; Provide physical security of assets and personnel.              will be willing to stand for a large contingent&#13;
* Adjust rents and royalties or make financial compensation to    obligation to the project. But if the government&#13;
sponsors to maintain economic equilibrium in the event of political  views the benefits as modest, it will be willing&#13;
force majeure such as:                                          to stand for only modest undertakings.&#13;
a Civil unrest, war, terrorism, blockade.&#13;
Whatever the scope of government undertak-&#13;
Neational or general strikes.                                  ings, and regardless of the methodology tised&#13;
i Expropriation and withdrawal of authorization.                to calculate adjustments or compensation, the&#13;
* Diversion or interruption of the commodity flow (including at the  ability of a government to meet its obligations,&#13;
wellhead).                                                    financial and nonfinancial, may well be the&#13;
* Change in relevant law.                                       factor that determines a project's financeability.&#13;
* Pemiitforeigncurrencytransactions,banking,and bank accounts.    Supplementing the government obligations&#13;
with a World Bank guarantee covering part of&#13;
* Guarante cleanup of preexistiig contaminiation,               the project debt may add the element that will&#13;
* Use intemational dispute resolution procedures.                 make successful financing and implementation&#13;
* Guarantee paymients by govemmeent entities, such as             possible.&#13;
* Dernand charges (for example, from the state enterprise fuel&#13;
purchaser).                                                   Cross-border complications&#13;
* Specified damages.&#13;
Cross-border projects pose additional structur-&#13;
* Economic equilibrium (a mechanism for making compensatoriy    ing challenges. Because some level of agree-&#13;
payments or adjustments when there is a divergence from the   ment is needed between the two governments&#13;
economictransaction negotiated between the contractual        on the desirability of the project, cross-border&#13;
parties).                                                     projects should include an intergovernmental&#13;
agreement. Such an agreement would consti-&#13;
tute an international treaty. These are typically&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                     3&#13;
less detailed than private sponsors might like.   In the complex negotiations for a cross-border&#13;
It is perhaps wishful thinking by project spon-    project the principals will need to reach a mu-&#13;
sors to expect that intergovernmental agree-   tually beneficial agreement on the appropriate&#13;
ments would address with any detail financial   compensation if a breach should occur. While&#13;
compensation and risk allocation, although    a government might agree to a contingent li-&#13;
cross-border technical issues, such as facilitat-   ability exceeding the investment in its country,&#13;
ing continuous maintenance services on a    the World Bank's Articles of Agreement limit&#13;
transnational pipeline could be included. But   its ability to guarantee loans to the investment&#13;
the existence of an agreement should provide    project that is in the member country.&#13;
significant comfort to project sponsors and their&#13;
lenders.                                          World Bank guarantees&#13;
The structuring of financial compensation for   A government's financial obligations that flow&#13;
which a government might become liable also   to commercial lenders to a project (through,&#13;
gets complicated in cross-border projects. In   say, bank loans, Eurobonds, or 144A bonds),&#13;
addition to reparations for costs directly caused    may be credit-enhanced by the World Bank&#13;
by a breach of undertaking or a political risk    using a partial risk guarantee. World Bank guar-&#13;
event, private sponsors might ask for financial   antees are "partial" in that they cover the mini-&#13;
compensation to cover consequential losses,   mum number of risks and the smallest amount&#13;
such as:                                          of debt consistent with successful implemen-&#13;
* Carrying costs of an entire chain of projects   tation of a project. In general, if project debt&#13;
(for example, debt seivicing and other fixed    service is interrupted by failure of the govern-&#13;
costs, or equity return in all countries).      ment to make payment as required by the con-&#13;
T The inventory carrying cost of interrupted    cession agreement, guaranteed lenders may call&#13;
throughput throughout a pipeline.               on the World Bank for payment (exceptions&#13;
FIGURE 1 CROSS-BORDER SALES TO MARKET&#13;
wovernment A)             Intergovernmental agreement           Government B&#13;
(weak credit) -                                               (adequate credit)&#13;
A~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
Indemnity A  Production sharing  Transit&#13;
(guarantee A)    agreement   agreement&#13;
Pipeline&#13;
-_  &lt;  (unaffiliated}&#13;
Loan&#13;
Guarantee A&#13;
(production sharing and transit agreements)&#13;
World Bank&#13;
International border&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4                  World Bank Guarantees for Oil and Gas Projects&#13;
include payment failures resulting from events    Structuring&#13;
agreed to be commercial risks or events of&#13;
natural force majeure, since the Bank does not   To use World Bank guarantees, two require-&#13;
underwrite such risks as a matter of policy).   ments have to be met: the government in whose&#13;
The World Bank would promptly pay undis-   territory the project is located must indemnify&#13;
puted amounts, a commitment that raises the   the Bank, and the government whose obliga-&#13;
credit rating of the government's payment ob-   tions are being supported by the guarantee&#13;
ligation to AAA in the eyes of the project lend-   must indemnify the Bank. In most project struc-&#13;
ers. The World Bank would then demand    tures, these two requirements would be met&#13;
reimbursement from the government under the    by the same government, but in cross-border&#13;
terms of an indemnity agreement (World Bank    projects the structures can be problematic.&#13;
guarantees are not insurance policies).         Some simple examples illustrate the issues.&#13;
In most countries the World Bank considers its   Figure 1 shows a relatively simple structure in&#13;
guarantees to be additional to its annual lend-   which a joint venture develops an oil or gas&#13;
ing program. The provisions of the guarantees   project in one country and delivers the prod-&#13;
do not create new obligations but merely back-   uct to the international border. Government A,&#13;
stop the obligations that a government has al-   which the project lenders perceive as a weak&#13;
ready made to a project in the concession    financial credit, enters into concession agree-&#13;
agreement. Bank regulators in most major econo-   ments with the joint venture. The project lend-&#13;
mies have exempted loans covered by Bank    ers agree to make a term  loan to the joint&#13;
guarantees from certain provisioning require-   venture on the condition that the World Bank&#13;
ments, lowering the cost of the loans and in-   guarantee that loan against the risk of govern-&#13;
creasing the appetite of lenders to make them.   ment A breaching either of its concession agree-&#13;
FIGURE 2 CROSS-BORDER SALES TO A STATE ENTERPRISE&#13;
_=_ *                   Intergovernmental agreement&#13;
A  +             | Guarantee of state&#13;
Indemnity A  Production sharing  Transit       enterprise payments                Indemnity B&#13;
(guara tee B)   agreement   agreement                                             (guarantee B)&#13;
Loan&#13;
Guarantee B&#13;
'(   {state enterprise payments)&#13;
International border&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                     5&#13;
ments and causing an interruption in debt ser-   cated) and government B (whose obligations&#13;
vicing. The downstream  part of the project is   are being backed) will have to indemnify the&#13;
creditworthy, so from the World Bank's per-    Bank for the amount of the loan. Depending&#13;
spective the "project" is entirely within coun-   on the economic benefits accruing to country&#13;
trv A, the obligations being backed are those    A, the requirement for an indemnity from gov-&#13;
of government A, and [hus the indemnity of   ernment A could prove to be difficult to ar-&#13;
govemment A covers the Bank's requirements.   range without some clever structuring.&#13;
The example in figure 2 reverses the credit sce-   Figure 3 shows a simple cross-border joint ven-&#13;
nario. Government A has sufficient credit stand-   ture where a single joint venture holds the con-&#13;
ing so that its concession agreements need no    cessions for a production facility and pipeline&#13;
further support. But because the product is to   in country A and for a pipeline in country B.&#13;
be sold at the border to a state enterprise in    Both governments are perceived as weak finan-&#13;
country B that lacks independent creditwor-   cial credits by the project lenders, which will&#13;
thiness, government B will have to guarantee    lend to the joint venture only if the Bank guar-&#13;
the payment obligations of the state enterprise.   antees the governments' payment obligations.&#13;
The project lenders, perceiving government B    The World Bank views the initiative as two&#13;
as a weak financial credit, agree to make a    "projects" divided by the international border.&#13;
term loan to the project on the condition that   To maintain transparency, the Bank prefers that&#13;
the World Bank back the guarantee obligations   the project lenders provide two separate loans,&#13;
of government B. Again, in the World Bank's    with the proceeds of each loan to be used&#13;
view the "project" is entirely in country A. To    exclusively for expenditures in one country.&#13;
meet the Bank's requirements, both govern-   The Bank's indemnity requirements can easily&#13;
ment A (in whose territory the project is lo-   be met in this structure, with government A&#13;
FIGURE 3 SINGLE CROSS-BORDER PROJECT&#13;
GovernmentA              Intergovernmental agreement           Government B&#13;
(weak credit)                                                  (weak credit)&#13;
Indemnity A  Production sharing  Transit                     Transit                  Indemnity B&#13;
(guarantee A)    agreement   agreement A                   agreement B                (guarantee B)&#13;
Joint venture&#13;
L.oan A                                 Loan B&#13;
*                      Project lenders&#13;
Guarantee A                             Guarantee B&#13;
V   (production sharing and transit agreements)  B  (transit agreement B)             I&#13;
World Bank&#13;
International border&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6                    World Bank Guarantees for Oil and Gas Projects&#13;
indemnifying the Bank for claims under guar-    The variations on the theme are endless.&#13;
antee A (which covers loan A for the "project"    These four examples are meant only to illus-&#13;
in country A), and government B doing the    trate the possibilities for using World 13ank&#13;
same for the "project" in its country.              guarantees.&#13;
Figure 4 merely pulls the pieces together in    The process&#13;
what is perhaps a more likely scenario. In this&#13;
example the functions are split among sepa-    For the World Bank the process of issuing a&#13;
rate joint ventures, each constituting a "project"    guarantee begins with requests to the Bank&#13;
from the Bank's perspective. (There are often    from a host government and the private spon-&#13;
business reasons for separate joint ventures,    sors to provide a partial risk guarantee to the&#13;
such as to accommodate local ownership and    project lenders. Bank procedures require ap-&#13;
local financing.) The Bank considers joint op-    proval of each guarantee by its board of ex-&#13;
erations agreements between these joint ven-    ecutive directors. Each project must meet the&#13;
tures (including cross-default provisions in loan    Bank's standard technical, environmental, eco-&#13;
agreements) as commercial risks outside the    nomic, and financial criteria and be in a coun-&#13;
scope of its guarantees. If each guarantee backs    try that is reforming to the Bank's satisfaction.&#13;
a term loan for expenditures only in the coun-    The Bank must determine that the project is in&#13;
try of the "project," each government's expo-    the best interest of the country and that allo-&#13;
sure under its indemnity to the World Bank is   cating guarantee coverage to the project is in&#13;
limited to the amount invested in its territory    the Bank's and the country's best interest. At&#13;
and the Bank's indemnity requirements are    its discretion, the Bank may incorporate in its&#13;
clearly met.                                        own appraisal the results of technical, finan-&#13;
FIGURE 4 MULTIPLE PROJECTS, MULTIPLE GUARANTEES&#13;
II&#13;
Intergovernmental agreement&#13;
I  +         +                t            .~~~~~~~~~~~~~/1 Guarantee of&#13;
Indemnity A  Production sharing  Transit                 Transit  tate enterprise         Indemnity B&#13;
(guarantees    agreement    agreement A                agreement B   payments             (guarantee 3)&#13;
l and 2)        vA4&#13;
A                      &#13;
Upstream loan      Pipeline loan A           Pipeline loan B&#13;
t                                                 +&#13;
Guarantee I         Guarantee 2               Guarantee 3&#13;
Iproduction sharing    (transit agreement A)  (transit agreement B&#13;
agreement)                                and state enterprise)&#13;
International border&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                                   7&#13;
cial, and other assessments undertaken by ad-&#13;
visers to the project lenders.&#13;
For an oil or gas project World Bank policy&#13;
generally requires public disclosure of an en-&#13;
vironmental assessment in final and agreed&#13;
form at least sixty days before board approval&#13;
of the project. Preparation of the environmen-&#13;
tal assessment is chiefly the responsibility of&#13;
the sponsors.&#13;
The sponsors are also responsible for arrang-&#13;
ing their own financing. With the permission&#13;
of the appropriate central bank, loans guaran-&#13;
teed by the World Bank can be in any freely&#13;
convertible currency or the local currency of&#13;
the country in which the project is located.1&#13;
Conclusion&#13;
In  the  financial struci:uring  of oil and  gas                                                                                        Viewpoint is an open&#13;
projects World  Bank  guarantees can  comple-                                                                                           forum intended to&#13;
ment loans from  the International Finance Cor-                                                                                         encourage dissemina-&#13;
tion of and debate on&#13;
poration and the Bank and insurance from  the                                                                                           ideas, innovations, and&#13;
Multilateral Investment Guarantee  Agency.                                                                                              best practices for ex-&#13;
Guaranteed  debt is often  arranged  at lower                                                                                           panding the private&#13;
costs and longer maturities than would other-                                                                                           lished are those of the&#13;
wise  be  possible; the  pass-through  of these                                                                                         authors and should not&#13;
savings to  the governrment can be  an  impor-                                                                                          be attributed to the&#13;
World Bank or any of&#13;
tant part of the Bank's value added in a project.                                                                                       its affiliated organi2a-&#13;
But the  World  Bank's  presence  in  a project                                                                                         tions. Nor do any of the&#13;
reaches  beyond  the  guaranteed  debt, often                                                                                           conclusions represent&#13;
official policy of the&#13;
bringing  comfort to  other parties not directly                                                                                        World Bank or of its&#13;
benefiting from  the guarantee.                                                                                                         Executive Directors&#13;
or the countries they&#13;
represent.&#13;
For more information see 77e World Baoik Goarm tree Catalystfol-&#13;
Prioate capita/Flozs or the Guarantees Handbook ax-aiLable from                                                                      To order additional&#13;
the Project Finonce and Guararitees Department, (202) 473-1650.                                                                      copies please call&#13;
202-458-1111 or contact&#13;
Scott Sinclair  *~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~Susanne Smith, editor,&#13;
Scott Sinclair (ssinclair@worldbank.org), Senior                                                                                        Room FLP-188,&#13;
Financial Officer, Project Finance and                                                                                                  The World Bank,&#13;
Guarantees Department                                                                                                                   1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
or Internet address&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.&#13;
The series is also&#13;
available on-line&#13;
(www.worldbank.org/&#13;
html/fpd/notes/).&#13;
QPrinted on recycled&#13;
paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441578">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/11/441578/world-bank-guarantees-oil-gas-projects
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/11/441578/world-bank-guarantees-oil-gas-projects</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1998/11/441578/world-bank-guarantees-oil-gas-projects</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_9903191055357/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_9903191055357/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1998-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>1999-08-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            World Bank guarantees for oil and gas projects
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Private investors are considering
            several large-scale oil and gas production, pipeline, and
            cross-border pipeline projects in developing countries,
            including in West Africa and in the Caspian Sea region.
            While the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund are
            well known for their work in helping to create enabling
            environments for foreign investment in large infrastructure
            projects, by supporting reform in such areas as taxation and
            energy legislation, this Note focuses on a different role
            for the World Bank -- encouraging private sector involvement
            in large-scale oil and gas projects by providing guarantees
            in direct support of the government contractual undertakings
            that may be needed to induce foreign direct investment in
            these projects. World Bank guarantees offer a unique type of
            risk mitigation that may prove to be a catalyst in raising
            finance for these projects.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            World Bank guarantees for oil and gas projects
        </docna>
        <display_title>World Bank guarantees for oil and
            gas projects</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1998/11/441578/world-bank-guarantees-oil-gas-projects</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,National Governance,Financial Crisis Management &amp; Restructuring,Economic Adjustment and Lending</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Governance,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Environment</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Sinclair, Scott</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_9903191055357</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Oil &amp; Gas Adjustment</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Governance,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Environment</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Oil &amp; Gas</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <src_cit>Viewpoint. -- Note no. 157 (November 1998)</src_cit>
        <keywd>
            Privatization; Bank guarantees; Developing
            countries; Private sector participation; Oil &amp; gas
            exploration; Risks; Concessions; Government commitments;
            Project finance; Risk insurance; Private sponsors; Project finance
            accounting,accounting
            procedures,authorization,balance sheets,Bank,bank
            accounts,Bank guarantees,Bank procedures,capital
            requirements,central
            bank,commitment,commitments,concession,concessions,debt,disclosure,eco,economic
            equilibrium,enabling environments,expenditures,foreign
            direct investment,foreign investment,government
            revenue,Guarantees,income,insurance,inventory,legislation,lenders,Loan,local
            financing,maturities,Multilateral Investment Guarantee
            Agency,oil,partial risk guarantee,political risk,private
            costs,private sector involvement,private sector
            sponsors,project sponsors,savings,sponsor,state enterprise,tal,taxation,transparency,transport
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>18717</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipal Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reparations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Resolution and Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>