<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 171                                                                                 January 1999&#13;
International Power Trade-&#13;
The Nordic Power Pool&#13;
Lenlnart CGrJSsOs    Scandinavia, wlhere countries have traded power   Differences in generation mix largely explain the&#13;
for decades, has the world's most developed   establishment of interconnections in Scandinavia.&#13;
international market for electric power. Recently   Norway relies entirely on hydro, while Denmark&#13;
the trading systeni has changed dramatically,   generates all power in thermal plants, mainly from&#13;
moving from the old model of cooperation   imported coal. SwZeden has a mix of about half&#13;
among the lcading vertically integrated utilities  lhydro and half nuclear generation, and Finland&#13;
in each country, under the Nordel agreement,   a mix of hydro (25 percent), conventional ther-&#13;
to competitive market rules. A common power   mal (45 percent), and nuclear (30 percent) plants.&#13;
market for Norway and Swecden, Nord Pool, was   The power nmarket is fairly large: together. the&#13;
established in 1996, and Finland joined in June   four countries consume about 360 terawatt-hours&#13;
1998 (figure 1). This Note examines why Nord   (TWh) a year, surpassing the U.K. rmarket. The&#13;
Pool came into being, what conditions facili-   differences in generation structure have made it&#13;
tated its development. and what lessons it pro-   economically attractive to trade power, allowing&#13;
vides for Norld Bank client countries.       the countries to optimnize production (figure 2).&#13;
FIGURE 1      THE NORD POOL POWER            FIGURE 2       POWER GENERATION&#13;
MARKET                                       STRUCTURE IN THE&#13;
NORDIC COUNTRIES&#13;
Gas turbines&#13;
Production&#13;
e4_D~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~cs&#13;
Condensing, oil&#13;
Condensing, coal&#13;
Industrial back pressure&#13;
Combined heat and&#13;
power productionL&#13;
Nuclear power&#13;
V                     ~~~~~~~~~Hydropower&#13;
(average)&#13;
100      200      300 ,' 400 TWh&#13;
*Finnish, Norwegian. and Swedish players trade on equal terms.     Consumption&#13;
Ndote.-The figure rLilects three ditferent cost structurestfor nuclear&#13;
*   From otutside the tree trade area Danish participants trade on   power generation.&#13;
special terms.                             Source: Nord Pool.&#13;
The World Bank Group . Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
International Power Trade-The Nordic Power Pool&#13;
The old structure                           Trading of electricity between the countries was&#13;
enabled through Nordel, an organization set up&#13;
Before the move to the international pool the   in the 1960s to promote cooperation among the&#13;
power sectors of Norway, Sweden, and Finland   largest electricity producers in each country.&#13;
all had an oligopoly structure, with dominant   Nordel was based on the principle that each&#13;
state-owned enterprises that also controlled the   country would build enough generating capac-&#13;
national grids, though there were differences in  ity to be self-sufficient. Trading was meant to&#13;
structure, ownership, and regulation.       achieve optimal dispatch of a larger system-and&#13;
investment in interconnection was generally&#13;
Norway's power sector was dominated by the   based not on net exports but on expected sav-&#13;
government-owned integrated utility Statkraft,  ings from pooling available generating capacity.&#13;
which also operated the national grid. There   The countries exchanged information about their&#13;
were also many small local and regional utili-   marginal cost of production. When there was a&#13;
ties. Between fifty and sixty companies, many   difference, trading took place, at a price that&#13;
owned by local or regional authorities, were   was the average of the two marginal costs.&#13;
involved in the transmission of electricity at&#13;
the regional level. The local and regional utili-   The cost-plus structure in the Nordic power sec-&#13;
ties had gained access to the national grid in  tor led to overinvestment in the power sector&#13;
1969 and could buy and sell power through a   and poor return on equity. But because the sys-&#13;
spot market. Electricity was distributed locally  tem retained a degree of competition, there were&#13;
by about 200 companies, many of which were   no significant operating efficiency problems in&#13;
owned by municipalities.                    the utilities.&#13;
In Sweden about half the generation was   The shift to a market-based structure&#13;
government-owned through Vattenfall, which&#13;
also operated the national grid and provided   The shift to an international pool was triggered&#13;
distribution services in parts of the country.   by power sector reforms in Norway starting in&#13;
About ten other integrated utilities of various   the early 1990s. Norway introduced competition&#13;
sizes also used the national grid, but a rela-  in electricity supply in 1991 through reforms&#13;
tively high network fee made it uneconomical   aimed at reducing regional differences in the cost&#13;
for smaller utilities to use it. Like Norway, Swe-   of power, promoting operational efficiency in&#13;
den had a large number of distribution com-   generation and distribution, and achieving more&#13;
panies (presently about 250), many owned by   efficient development of the power sector.&#13;
municipalities.                              Statkraft's transmission activities were spun off&#13;
to a new national grid company, Statnett SF. In&#13;
In Finland the state-owned Imatran Voima Oy   addition, all transmission networks were opened&#13;
(IVO) was the largest utility. IVO also oper-  to third-party access, and vertically integrated&#13;
ated the national grid. Much of the power gen-   companies had to adopt separate accounting for&#13;
eration was owned by Finnish industries,   generation, distribution, and supply activities.&#13;
however, which formed a transmission com-&#13;
pany, TVS, to interconnect their generation and   In Sweden reform was fueled by discontent&#13;
supply areas.                               among the private power companies stemming&#13;
from Vattenfall's control of the national grid, and&#13;
In Denmark, for geographical reasons, the grid   dissatisfaction among the smaller power com-&#13;
is divided into two main parts: one on the Jutland   panies and among customers over their lack of&#13;
peninsula and the other on the island of   access to the market for occasional power. The&#13;
Sjaelland. In each of these two areas the gener-  first major step, taken in 1991, was to corporatize&#13;
ation and distribution utilities, mostly owned by   Vattenfall's generation and distribution activities.&#13;
municipalities, formed special-purpose organi-   Vattenfall remains government-owned, however.&#13;
zations to manage the extra-high-voltage grids   The national grid was retained as a government-&#13;
and the coordinated operation.              owned institution, Svenska Kraftnat, which also&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
serves as the system operator. The networks   hour during the next day. About 44 TWh were&#13;
were gradually opened to new players, and a   traded on the spot market in 1997. The price of&#13;
new electricity act allowing a competitivc mar-  the power to balance the system is also deter-&#13;
ket finally took effect in January 1996.    mined through bidding. Statnett, Svenska&#13;
Kraftnat, and Fingrid are each responsible for&#13;
Finland introduced new energy legislation in   balancing the system in their country. Although&#13;
1995. IVO had already separated its grid activity  they follow the same principles, the rules differ&#13;
into a separate company, IVS. But with the pri-  and work is under way to harmonize them.&#13;
vately owned grid company TVS, Finland had&#13;
two overlapping grid companies for several  In addition to the spot market, Nord Pool offers&#13;
years. Since September 1997 Finland has had a   futures contracts, which are traded a.s weekly&#13;
single, merged grid company, Fingrid, which also   contracts four to seven weeks ahead, as blocks&#13;
acts as the system operator.                of four weeks up to fifty-two weeks ahead, or as&#13;
seasons up to three years ahead. The futures are&#13;
In Denmark reform moved more slowly because   purely financial contracts used for price hedg-&#13;
of the power sector's different structure, with  ing. About fifteen brokering companies offer ser-&#13;
two nonconnected groups owned by munici-   vices to the electricity market. The bulk of the&#13;
palities or cooperatives, each with a monopoly   volume traded is in standardized financial con-&#13;
in its area. New legislation opening the grids to  tracts, often referred to as over-the-counter (OTC)&#13;
negotiated third-party access and allowing com-   contracts. The liquidity of the OTC market is quite&#13;
petition for large consumers, distributors, and   high, particularly for the nearest season. Con-&#13;
generators was introduced in 1996.          tracts can be resold, or a position netted out by&#13;
making an opposite contract. In 1997 the con-&#13;
The creation of a pool                      tracted volume in Nord Pool ftitures and the OTC&#13;
market was estimated at more than 310 TWh.&#13;
Norway led the way in reform, opening up a&#13;
spot market in 1992. A similar power market in  In addition to the spot and futures markets there&#13;
Sweden would have been difficult to manage,  is direct trading between parties in bilateral for-&#13;
as Vattenfall and Sydkraft, the two largest gen-   wards. These bilateral contracts are normally&#13;
erating companies, together control about 75   for physical deliveries and are often tailor-made&#13;
percent of generating capacity. But the Norwe-  to particular requirements. Despite the diver-&#13;
gian market also experienced problems. Because   sity in trading instruments, most of the trading&#13;
all the power in Norway is produced by hydro-   between players still takes place under bilat-&#13;
electric plants, the spot market price was very   eral contracts for physical delivery that were&#13;
volatile. A combined Norwegian-Swedish mar-   signed before the reform.&#13;
ket would address the problems of both coun-&#13;
tries. A decision was therefore made to establish   Impact and lessons&#13;
a joint electricity trading exchange in January&#13;
1996. with a design based on the Norwegian   The smooth transition to the world's first inter-&#13;
experience. The grid operators own the com-   national power market has been thanks in large&#13;
pany, Nord Pool, that organizes the market. Fin-   part to the long tradition of cross-border bilat-&#13;
land joined the power exchange in June 1998,   eral energy trade and cooperation and the&#13;
existence of cross-border transmission structurcs.&#13;
The spot market organized by Nord Pool tradcs&#13;
in hourly contracts for the following day. It is   Ownership and structure&#13;
open to all companies that have signed the nec&#13;
essary agreements with Nord Pool, and pres-   Setting up the pool did not require privatizing&#13;
entlv about 200 trade on the exchange. Bids are   government-owned companies. A mix of&#13;
submitted each morning, and supply and de-   companies continues to operate in the Nordic&#13;
mand curves are then constructed to provide   power sectors-from large government-owned&#13;
the system price and the traded quantity for each   utilities to privately and municipally owned&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
International Power Trade-The Nordic Power Pool&#13;
companies of varying size-running generation,    to keep business from going elsewhere, the pool&#13;
regional networks, and distribution systems and    must ensure that it is an attractive marketplace.&#13;
supplying power to consumers. But ownership&#13;
of the international interconnections that existed    The main initial problem  for competition has&#13;
in the Nordel area when the sectors were re-    been that the cost of installing hourly metering&#13;
structured in Finland, Norway, and Sweden has    has prevented small consumers from changing&#13;
been transferred to the grid company in each    suppliers. Norway has solved this problem  by&#13;
country. That has opened trading to all the play-    adopting a system of predefined customer con-&#13;
ers in the wholesale markets-generators, dis-    sumption profiles. Sweden will probably also&#13;
tributors, and large consumers.                     adopt the consumption profile solution.&#13;
Competitive pressures in the electricity market    Expansion of the pool may lead to a need to&#13;
have resulted in several ownership and struc-    increase transmission capacity between the&#13;
tural changes in the sector, including some    countries. When a free market opens up, the&#13;
cross-ownership between countries and the    cross-border power flow tends to increase if the&#13;
entry of some foreign power companies. In   international power exchange had previously&#13;
addition to the traditional power companies,    been limited to optimizing marginal production.&#13;
other players can trade on the market, includ-    The capacity between Norway and Sweden has&#13;
ing brokers, oil companies, foreign power com-    already fallen short at times, resulting in a clif-&#13;
panies, and  power trading  companies    ference in system price between the two coun-&#13;
representing consumer groups.                       tries. A shortcoming in the Nordic market (as in&#13;
Viewpoint is an open                                                     most other power markets) is that there are no&#13;
forum intended to    The Nordic market has demonstrated that it is   clearly defined rules prescribing when network&#13;
encourage dissemina-  unnecessary to have a single system operator.    expansions have to be built by the grid compa-&#13;
tion of anid debate on&#13;
ideas, innovations, and    Statnett, Svenska Kraftnat, and Fingrid each    nies and how  they should be financed. Such&#13;
best practices for ex-  have the responsibility for managing and bal-    matters probably will have to be resolved case&#13;
panding the private  ancing the national system  in their country.    by case in the Nordic market, possiblv with some&#13;
sector. The views pub- N&#13;
lished are those of the  National tax, environmental, and other laws still   political involvement.&#13;
authors and should not    need to be harmonized, but the system  has&#13;
be attributed to the  nevertheless functioned quite well.                Conclusion&#13;
World Bank or any of&#13;
its affiliated organiza-&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the    Competition and regulation                   An advanced system  requiring sophisticated&#13;
conclusions represent                                                    players, the Nordic power market probably is&#13;
official policy of the&#13;
World Bank or of its  Strict regulation of the network service ensures    not a suitable model for developing countries&#13;
Executive Directors  that third-party access works. But the market is   just beginning to move from  a traditional&#13;
or the countries they  largely assumed to be able to take care of itself   goverinment-owned monopoly utility to a more&#13;
represent.           under the supervision of national competition    market-oriented structure. But Nord Pool dem-&#13;
To order additional  authorities. This approach differs from  that    onstrates the possibilities of an international&#13;
copies please call   adopted in England and Wales, where the pool    power market, an attractive option for devel-&#13;
202-458-1111 or contact&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,    is heavily regulated. Because the Nordic coun-    oping countries with small power systems.&#13;
Room Fl1K-208,       tries already had a large number of players, re-&#13;
The World Bank,      form was easier to implement.                        Reference&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
or Internet address  The spot market operated by Nord Pool is work-    Randan. Hans, Jan Andersen, ancd tSve Poser 1xchange acrorss Na&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.   ing well so far. In contrast to the English and    tional Borders." Nord Pool, Oslo.&#13;
availaTle on line    Welsh pool, where only the producers can par-&#13;
lwww.worldbank.org/  ticipate in the bidding, the Nordic pool is a mar-    Lennart Carlsson, Energy Markets&#13;
html/fpd/notes/).    ket for both sellers and buyers. Another difference    and Reform, Thematic Group&#13;
$ Printed on recycled    is that the generators in the Nordic system are                                         U&#13;
paper.               not obligated to offer their power to the pool. So&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441513">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/01/441513/international-power-trade-nordic-power-pool
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/01/441513/international-power-trade-nordic-power-pool</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/01/441513/international-power-trade-nordic-power-pool</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_99040905052180/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_99040905052180/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-06-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            International power trade : the Nordic
            Power Pool
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Scandinavia, where countries have traded
            power for decades, has the world's most developed
            international market for electricity. Recently the trading
            system has changed dramatically, moving from the old model
            of cooperation among the leading vertically integrated
            utilities in each country, under the Nordel agreement, to
            competitive market rules. Norway and Sweden established a
            common power market, Nord Pool, in 1996, and Finland joined
            in June 1998. This Note examines why Nord Pool came into
            being, what conditions facilitated its development, and what
            lessons it provides for World Bank client countries.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            International power trade : the Nordic Power Pool
        </docna>
        <display_title>International power trade : the
            Nordic Power Pool</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1999/01/441513/international-power-trade-nordic-power-pool</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Windpower,Energy Technology &amp; Transmission,Gender and Social Development,Power &amp; Energy Conversion,Energy Trade</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Energy,Gender</teratopic>
        <count>Finland,Norway,Denmark,Sweden,Europe and Central Asia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Carlsson, Lennart</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_99040905052180</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Power &amp; Energy Conversion</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 171</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Energy,Gender</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Electricity trade; International markets;
            Oligopolies; Grids; Market based mechanisms; Regional
            cooperation; Pool; Spot market; Futures markets; Electric
            utilities; Economic competition
            bilateral contracts,border power
            flow,distribution activities,distribution
            systems,distribution utilities,electric
            power,electricity,electricity producers,electricity
            supply,energy legislation,Energy Markets,energy
            trade,establishment of
            interconnections,exports,Gas,GENERATION
            MARKET,generators,grid,grid activity,grid companies,grid
            company,grid operators,grids,heat,international power
            exchange,International power trade,monopoly utility,Nuclear
            power,oil companies,power,power companies,POWER
            GENERATION,power markets,Power Pool,power sector,power
            systems,power trading,power trading companies,spot
            market,transmission,transmission activities,transmission
            capacity,transmission networks,transmission of electricity,voltage
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>19063</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems Technologies and Operations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Thermal Power Generation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydro Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydroelectric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydropower</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>