<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 173                                                                                      January 1999&#13;
Developing Countries and Accounting&#13;
Rates Reform-A Technological and&#13;
Regulatory El Nifio?&#13;
Carlos A.          New technology and the liberalization of tele-   sidize network development and public services.&#13;
Primo Braga,       communications markets are putting increasing    Several of the most vulnerable countries derive&#13;
Emmanuel           stress on the accounting rates regime-the sys-   up to 50 percent of their telecommunications rev-&#13;
Forestier, and     tem used by telecommunications carriers to settle   enues from international settlements (figure 1).&#13;
Peter A. Stern     their international traffic accounts. While opera-   And for about thirty countries changes to the&#13;
tors in most countries acknowledge that the cur-   settlement regime will have a significant effect&#13;
rent system is unsustainable, many developing    on current account and fiscal balances. In sev-&#13;
countries have resisted the pressures for radical   eral of these countries the telecommunications&#13;
change, arguing that it will cause an unbearably   sector is characterized by distorted pricing struc-&#13;
large drop in their operators' profitability. Many   tures, ineffective policies, and a monopoly ser-&#13;
depend heavily on international revenues to sub-   vice provider.&#13;
FIGURE 1      THE MOST VULNERABLE COUNTRIES&#13;
U.S. settlement payments as a percentage of foreign exchange reserves, 1995&#13;
(log scale)&#13;
100&#13;
Cameroon&#13;
Honduras&#13;
Belize *                      Guyana&#13;
Nicaragua *&#13;
* Jamaica&#13;
10                                                       Trinidad and Tobago   Sierra Leonen  * Tonga&#13;
' 0                 El Salvador&#13;
Pakistan             Guatemala&#13;
Barbados *   4 0ex g       Liberia         * Ecuador&#13;
Senegal *Pananma&#13;
The Gambia&#13;
Costa Rica,  *     Philippines&#13;
*Lao PDR           0 Bolivia&#13;
,olombiae 0 Georgia&#13;
Togo ~~~   Ethiopia&#13;
1______________________________________________Tog__    9 " Bangladesh&#13;
1~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
1                                               10                                              100&#13;
U.S. settlement payments as a percentage of telecommunications revenue, 1995&#13;
(log scale)&#13;
Source: World Bank staff estimates based on U.S. Federal Communications Commission data.&#13;
The World Bank Group * Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2                      Developing Countries and Accounting Rates Reform&#13;
The international accounting rates regime can be    ment rate. The country that receives more traffic&#13;
traced back to the establishment of the Inter-     earns a net settlement payment, usually&#13;
national Telecommunication Union in 1865 and      denominated in U.S. dollars or special drawing&#13;
the need to develop a simple mechanism for         rights (SDRs), at the end of the period (box figure&#13;
compensating international operators for           1). The system also provides simple means to&#13;
delivering international calls from their point of  compensate operators serving as points of transit&#13;
origin to their destination. Under this arrange-   between the two terminal points.&#13;
ment, for the traific flowing between two             In the example in box figure 1 the negotiated&#13;
countries, the operators at each end negotiate a  accounting rate is US$1.40, the settlement rate is&#13;
multiplication factor known as an accounting       US$0.70, and the collection charge, the amount&#13;
rate. In most cases the two operators take the net    charged to the customer, is US$3.49 a minute in&#13;
traffic flowing between them in a given period,    the United States and US$6.41 a minute in&#13;
say a quarter, and multiply this by half of the    Colombia. The net settlement payment is (284.8&#13;
accounting rate, a factor known as the settle-     million - 61.5 million) x 0.70 = US$156.3 million.&#13;
BOX FIGURE 1   WHAT IS AN ACCOUNTING RATE?&#13;
An example based on U.S.-Colombia transactions in 1996&#13;
United States&#13;
Inbound traffic       Outbond traffic t d;Collection charge&#13;
; f 5 n+et s0 _ ~~~~~~~~~Accountigrt&#13;
Accountg Xg rate   * X   X VSettlement rate&#13;
Colombia                 X:         &#13;
Price charged to customers&#13;
between PTOs       Settlement rate&#13;
171           PaymentbetweenPTOs&#13;
Note: PTO is public telephone operator.&#13;
Source: U.S. Federal Communications Commission data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                  3&#13;
Developing countries' ability to resist changes   ing the conventional accounting rates regime.&#13;
in the system will be limited, however, because   In the 1990s, for example. as an initial step to-&#13;
the economic incentives and technological   ward competition in international telecommu-&#13;
opportunities for bypassing the system  are   nications, regulators in some countries permitted&#13;
strong. As a result, and in response to account-  the resale of international services over capac-&#13;
ing rate reforms already being discussed, devel-  ity leased from facilities-based operators, such&#13;
oping countries have about a four-year window    as international operators of submarine cable&#13;
to develop new mechanisms for financing net-   systems and satellite networks. This rapidly&#13;
work expansion (with increased reliance on   growing traffic is not subject to settlement un-&#13;
sources of funding external to the telecommu-   der the accounting rates system, as the new&#13;
nications company), adopt more transparent   entrant pays only a monthly or annual fee for&#13;
practices for supporting universal service (local  the facilities leased at both ends of a relationship.&#13;
access, traditionally subsidized by international&#13;
revenues, will have to be provided at prices   Technological progress is opening new ways&#13;
closer to true costs), and build modern regula-   for operators to deliver traffic, undermining the&#13;
tory structures capable of addressing intercon-   accounting rates regime and increasing the com-&#13;
nection issues in a cost-based manner. The   petitive pressure for traditional telephone ser-&#13;
critical issues for these economies: how to pre-   vices. Internet telephony, for example, bypasses&#13;
pare for the new era in international telecom-   the accounting rates regime and allows proxvid-&#13;
munications relationships, and how to finance   ers to undercut operators of conventional net-&#13;
the transition.                               works. India's recent decision to fully liberalize&#13;
the licensing of Internet senvice providers is likely&#13;
This Note briefly reviews the growing pressures   to cause significant competitive pressure for do-&#13;
on the current arrangements, analyzes the coun-   mestic and international telecommunications op-&#13;
tries most affected, discusses the future of inter-   erators in that country. The emergence of new&#13;
national telephony pricing, and outlines new    global mobile personal communications by sat-&#13;
sources of assistance to help developing coun-   ellite (GMPCS)-such as Globalstar, ICO, and&#13;
tries make the transition.                    Iridium-will add to the stress on the account-&#13;
ing rates regime. GMPCS business plans typi-&#13;
Forces for change                             cally assume that gateway earth stations will be&#13;
able to interconnect with the public switched&#13;
The accounting rates system worked relatively   telephone network at rates substantially lower&#13;
well when international services were jointly   than those used in conventional relationships&#13;
provided by the traditional monopoly service   involving developing countries. So these new&#13;
providers and there were no significant traffic   entrants can be expected to add their voices to&#13;
imbalances between countries. Even with thou-   those pushing for a reform of the regime or for&#13;
sands of bilateral relationships, the system was   substantial cuts in the accounting rates.&#13;
straightforward and inexpensive to administer,&#13;
and its basic principles were codified in an   Several other practices also distort traffic flows,&#13;
agreed framework developed within the Inter-   although they do not bypass the accounting&#13;
national Telecommunication Union (ITU). But   rates system. The most common of these is the&#13;
simplicity came at a price. The rates not only   use of calling or 'home direct" cards and call-&#13;
were disconnected from  costs-depending    back. This practice turns calls around, increas-&#13;
more on the partners' negotiating abilities-   ing the net flow of traffic in the direction&#13;
but also imposed artificially high prices on   opposite to normal and thus skewing traffic&#13;
consumers.                                    settlements in favor of the country where the&#13;
call was originated-often at the expense of&#13;
Today regulatory and technological changes   countries with more competitive and efficient&#13;
have created many more possibilities for bypass-   services. The growing distortion in traffic flows&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4                     Developing Countries and Accounting Rates Reform&#13;
and in settlement payments caused by calling    communications Agreement, which became&#13;
cards and callback has been an important driver    effective in February 1998. Under this agree-&#13;
of the demands for change in the regime.              ment many countries have made a commitment&#13;
to allow foreign operators to set up operations&#13;
A more systemic impetus for change is the    in their territory in the near future. As these&#13;
World Trade Organization (WTO) Basic Tele-    transnational networks multiply, accounting&#13;
FIGURE 2         ACCELERATING IMBALANCES&#13;
Incoming, outgoing, and balance of traffic in Senegal, 1990-96&#13;
Millions of minutes&#13;
60&#13;
*  Incoming&#13;
50  *  Outgoing&#13;
40  El Balance&#13;
30&#13;
20&#13;
10&#13;
0&#13;
-10 &#13;
-20&#13;
-30&#13;
1990          1991          1992           1993          1994           1995          1996&#13;
Incoming, outgoing, and balance of traffic in Mexico, 1991-97&#13;
Billions of minutes&#13;
3&#13;
*  Incoming&#13;
*  Outgoing&#13;
El Balance&#13;
2&#13;
°       -                                              &#13;
-2&#13;
1991          1992           1993           1994          1995           1996           1997&#13;
Source:World Bank staff estimates based on International Telecommunication Union data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                 5&#13;
rates will become even more irrelevant because   result, U.S. international operators have been&#13;
a subsidiary of a foreign operator can typically   looking for other ways to reduce accounting&#13;
exchange international telecommunications   rates. The most recent development was the&#13;
traffic with its home base or other subsidiaries   1997 unilateral decision by the U.S. Federal&#13;
without having to worry about accounting or   Communications Commission (FCC) directing&#13;
settlement rates.                            U.S.-licensed international operators to agree&#13;
on benchmark settlement rates with their inter-&#13;
Together these changes siphon traffic out of the   national partners over the next four years. Most&#13;
accounting rates regime and foster growing traf-   of the proposed benchmarks imply reductions&#13;
fic imbalances. In the United States, for example,   of more than 60 percent. The premise of the&#13;
outgoing traffic exceeded incoming traffic by   FCC decision is that high settlement rates are&#13;
51 million minutes in 1975. By 1996 this imbal-   equivalent to a subsidy from U.S. consumers&#13;
ance had grown to more than 11 billion minutes,  to foreign operators and that with the growing&#13;
translating into net settlements to the rest of the   liberalization of telecommunications markets-&#13;
world approaching US$6 billion a year. In the   particularly in the wake of the WTO Basic Tele-&#13;
cases of Senegal and Mexico net settlements have   communications Agreement-such distortions&#13;
been growing steadily since 1990 (figure 2).  need to be corrected swiftly. The European&#13;
Union, which liberalized its basic telecommu-&#13;
Operators paying net settlements have been   nications infrastructure on January 1, 1998, is&#13;
renegotiating accounting rates. These negotia-   also allowing alternatives to accounting rates&#13;
tions have not kept pace with the growth in   for international telephone traffic among its fif-&#13;
traffic, however, and outpayments have con-   teen members. Indeed. the European Union&#13;
tinued to rise, especially for U.S. carriers. As a   has recommended a system whereby foreign&#13;
FIGURE 3      TOP TEN NET PAYERS AND NET RECIPIENTS OF INTERNATIONAL ACCOUNTING RATES SETTLEMENTS,&#13;
1995&#13;
Millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
4,500&#13;
PAYERS                                           RECIPIENTS&#13;
1,000                                              &gt;   &lt;&#13;
800&#13;
600&#13;
400&#13;
200 U&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
C3  :10'                                                               ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-200&#13;
-400&#13;
-600&#13;
Source; U.S. Federal Communications Commission data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6                 Developing Countries and Accounting Rates Reform&#13;
operators can interconnect at any level of a   Among the countries receiving large net settle-&#13;
member country's network hierarchy and pay   ment flows from the United States, those whose&#13;
only an amount corresponding to the cost of   carriers and economies are most vulnerable to&#13;
interconnection. The European Commission   the effects of the transition are, not surpris-&#13;
estimates of the effects of these changes sug-   ingly, typically small countries with monopo-&#13;
gest that net settlement payments will be orders  listic carriers. This picture is incomplete, of&#13;
of magnitude smaller than under the current   course, since it focuses on correspondent rela-&#13;
accounting rates.                           tionships between the United States and the&#13;
rest of the world. African countries with im-&#13;
Potential effects of reform                 portant relationships with Europe also depend&#13;
on accounting rates revenues from countries&#13;
From the United States, for which the most com-   other than the United States.&#13;
plete data on international settlements are avail-&#13;
able, almost 70 percent of the nearly US$6   Toward a new regime&#13;
billion in settlement payments goes to devel-&#13;
oping countries. The flow is highly skewed:   What role international organizations, particu-&#13;
the top four net receivers (Mexico, China, India,  larly the ITU, will play with respect to the inter-&#13;
and the Philippines) accounted for almost 30   national accounting rates regime is an important&#13;
percent of the U.S. deficit in 1995, while the   issue. Many organizations, including the FCC,&#13;
fifty or so countries of Sub-Saharan Africa ac-   have stated that they would prefer to achieve a&#13;
counted for only 2.5 percent (USS125 million).   multilateral solution to the accounting rates prob-&#13;
The top ten payers and recipients on a global  lem. Whether this is possible, given the grow-&#13;
basis are shown in figure 3.                ing ease of bypassing the system, is an open&#13;
question. The role of national regulatory bodies,&#13;
In the countries receiving large net flows,   many of which are only now being established,&#13;
changes in the settlement regime will have   also needs to be determined. National regula-&#13;
significant effects on operators' revenue-   tors will need to understand and predict the&#13;
generating capability and profits. For the ten   direction of change so that they can continue to&#13;
economies most dependent on settlement pay-   meet their obligations to the public. And once&#13;
ments, these account for up to 50 percent of   new systems emerge, international operators and&#13;
telecommunications revenues. Moreover, for   national regulators alike will have to face the&#13;
many developing countries U.S. settlement pay-   challenge of operating under a regime of mul-&#13;
ments are a major source of hard currency, an   tiple settlement arrangements. Where there are&#13;
important consideration since most equipment   multiple international operators on both sides,&#13;
used to build out the network is imported and   several different settlement schemes could be&#13;
must be paid for in hard currency. The effects  in effect at the same time. Competition among&#13;
will depend not only on the size and pace of  these operators will ensure that the least costly&#13;
cuts in the accounting rates, but also on the   and most innovative system will win out.&#13;
operators' willingness to pass on the benefits&#13;
of lower accounting rates to their customers.   Proposals to reform the international account-&#13;
(Detailed analyses of the costs of providing in-  ing rates system have generally fallen into two&#13;
ternational telecommunications services, the   broad categories:&#13;
potential changes in the international settle-   * Instituting reform within the current account-&#13;
ments regime, and the effects of the changes    ing rates system.&#13;
on operators in developing countries are be-   * Replacing the accounting rates system.&#13;
ing conducted by the ITU and the European&#13;
Commission, for example, with support from    A review of these options indicates the direc-&#13;
the World Bank's Information for Development,  tion in which international settlement arrange-&#13;
or infoDev, Program.)                       ments are likely to evolve.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                   7&#13;
Within the current system the simplest and most   from the point of interconnection to terminate&#13;
obvious reforms are to reduce the accounting    the call. It can establish a gateway or point of&#13;
rates, to change the split of the accounting rate   presence in the country of destination or sim-&#13;
from 50/50 to one that reflects the difference    ply deliver the traffic through leased circuits to&#13;
in the cost of delivering a call between the   the point of interconnection with the destina-&#13;
two ends of the relationship; and to abandon    tion operator. The charge for interconnection&#13;
the requirement by some national regulators   could, of course, be subject to abuse, especially&#13;
that all international operators in the country    where the destination operator is a monopoly.&#13;
have the same accounting rate with correspond-&#13;
ing international operators in another country,   A variant of interconnection arrangements is end-&#13;
or receive the same proportion of return traffic   to-end service provision. As liberalization pro-&#13;
as they send out.' The ITU is proposing cost-   ceeds. it increases the possibilities for an&#13;
based reforms within the current system.        operator to be present at both ends of a rela-&#13;
tionship. An operator could conceivably pro-&#13;
Among proposals for settling international pay-   vide the sernice from originating to destination&#13;
ments outside the accounting rates system, one    subscriber using only its own facilities, and there&#13;
of the most popular is the concept of transpar-   would no longer be a need for special account-&#13;
ent, cost-based. nondiscriminatory call termiina-   ing and settlement arrangements between op-&#13;
tion charges. Under this scheme an operator   erators. Global alliances of operators-such as&#13;
would fix the charge for terminating an incom-   Worldcom. Global One, and Unisource-are al-&#13;
ing international call received at its international   ready providing end-to-end selvices, mainly to&#13;
gateway at the subscriber's premises. Since this   corporate customers outside the conventional&#13;
charge would be applied on a nondiscrimina-   system.&#13;
tory basis, it would be the same for all interna-&#13;
tional operators. It would be transparent becausc    The sender-keeps-all system, in which the origi-&#13;
it would be published. The size of this charge    nating operator keeps all the revenue it col-&#13;
remains to be resolved. It might be set arbi-  lects and exchanges no traffic information or&#13;
trarily by the international operator, or it could   accounts with the destination operator, will&#13;
be based on cost studies. If set by the operator,   continue to be used as an alternative to the&#13;
chances are that the charge would be well above    accounting rates system. It is simple to imple-&#13;
cost where there is still a monopoly. If the charge    ment and involves virtually no transaction costs.&#13;
is based on the cost of providing the termina-   But the system  is often criticized because it&#13;
tion service, it would have to be established    produces no financial flows to compensate for&#13;
according to some mutually agreed costing meth-   the cost of building and maintaining the net-&#13;
odology. The ITU, which is adopting the termi-   work at the terminating end and thus does not&#13;
nation charge method along with two other new    promote network development at the periph-&#13;
methods, is also trying to establish agreed cost   ery. Sender-keeps-all is the system most com-&#13;
models and methodologies. This task will not   monly used between Internet service providers.&#13;
be easy. Most countries have different account-&#13;
ing practices and define costs differently.     Conclusion&#13;
Another possible method is an interconnection    The pressures for reform of the accounting rates&#13;
arrangement like the one the European Union    system pose a short-term threat to the revenues&#13;
is implementing to create a single market. Un    of telecommunications operators, but they also&#13;
der an interconnection arrangement a foreign    offer potential benefits. The introduction of&#13;
international operator is free to interconnect with   cost-based interconnection charges should cut&#13;
a national operator's domestic network at virtu-   the price of international telephony significantly&#13;
ally any point in that network. The foreign op-   for all users, accelerating their inclusion in the&#13;
erator pays for the cost of the facilities used    global information society. Public pressure for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8                        Developing Countries and Accounting Rates Reform&#13;
reform  will increase as the cost of transmitting              World Bank will continue to support-in  co-&#13;
voice data and  images continues to  fall and                  operation with the ITU  and other partners-&#13;
depends less and less on distance. U.S. con-                   efforts to  raise awareness about the  coming&#13;
sumers, for example, will demand to know why                   changes in the accounting rates regime. In ad-&#13;
they should have to pay 88 cents for some in-                  dition, infoDev will provide assistance to de-&#13;
ternational calls when the price for domestic                  veloping  country  regulatory  authorities  in&#13;
long-distance  calls averages only  13  cents-                 developing cost-based pricing policies as part&#13;
even though the cost to the operator is almost                 of a long-term  tariff rebalancing strategy.&#13;
the same. Indian consumers will ask why they&#13;
have to pay ten times as much to call a relative                 Regulators in several countries implemented un:form accoonting&#13;
in a neighboring country as to call another rela-                rates to protect their competing international operators, especially&#13;
tive living a similar distance away in India. And                in relationships with Countries that still have monopolies. Uniform&#13;
rates prevent competing ioteroatiooal operators fcom unfairly un-&#13;
L atin1 Aml1er ican1 con1sumzzers wvill question why             dercutting their competitors in conjonction with the monopohv at&#13;
it costs two to three times as much to call Chile                the other end. The policy of proportionate return traffic requires&#13;
from  Argentina, Brazil, and Mexico as it does                   that the international operattor or operators in the corresponding&#13;
the other way around.                                            country retutm the same proportion of international traffic to an&#13;
oliginating international operator as it sends to an opertator in that&#13;
cottntty. This practice has been criticized as impeding compezition&#13;
International institutions such as the ITU, the                  by disadvantaging small entrants to the international telectmmoni-&#13;
World Bank, and the WTO  have an important                       cations market.&#13;
role to plav in promoting  dialogue about the                  GarlosA. Pirmo Braga (cbragaBworldbank.&#13;
Vievvpointisn open     reform   of the  accounting  rates regime. The                 orglo P rogra   Manager. infoDeq Eimanuel&#13;
forupn intended to      \World Bank could also help finance the cost of                  org),       (efbre1Verzwor1dbnLo rg), Em1nager&#13;
encourage dissemina-     the transition. In 1998 it announced that it will                         (Pforeshen;u'orldbank org, Manager&#13;
teon of and debate on    poietcncladfn calsitneto                                        Telecommutnication-s and Informatics Unit, and&#13;
ideas, innovations, and                          and  financial assistance  to          PeterA. Stern (pstern@tiw.ca), Consultant&#13;
best practices for ex-   developing  countries willing  to  reform  their&#13;
panding the private      telecommunications sector as the traditional ac-&#13;
sector. The views pub-   counting rat&#13;
lished are those of the                 es regime is phased out.&#13;
authors and should not&#13;
be attributed to the     The Bank's support will take three forms. First,&#13;
World Bank or any of&#13;
its affiliated organiza-  when the reduction of accounting rates has a&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the  fiscal and balance of payments impact, the Bank&#13;
conclusions represent    can provide sectoral adjustmeint loans to coun-&#13;
official policy of the&#13;
World Bank or of its     tries committed to openng their telecommun-&#13;
ExecLotive Directors     cations  sector to  competition  and  private&#13;
or the countries they    participation. These loans will finance the tem-&#13;
represent.               porary loss of fiscal revenues. After a transi-&#13;
To order additional      tion period of a few  years, this loss is expected&#13;
copies please call       to be more than offset by higher traffic volume&#13;
202-458-1l i  edor contact  and efficiency gains generated by new  entrants.&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,&#13;
Room Ft I K-208,         Second, when the self-financing capacity of the&#13;
The World Bank,          state operator is significantly affected and the&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,    government agrees to limit its involvement in&#13;
or Internet address      the ownership  and  management of telecom-&#13;
ssmith7@worldbankotrg.    munications operations, the Bank could finance&#13;
The series is also       a time slice of the sector investment program&#13;
(www.worldbank.org/      through sector investment loans. These loans&#13;
html/fpd/notes/).        could also finance the cost of redundancies as-&#13;
® Printed on recycled    sociated  with  restructuring  state  operators.&#13;
paper.                   Third, through the infoDev grants program, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441522">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/01/441522/developing-countries-accounting-rates-reform-technological-regulatory-el-nino
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/01/441522/developing-countries-accounting-rates-reform-technological-regulatory-el-nino</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/01/441522/developing-countries-accounting-rates-reform-technological-regulatory-el-nino</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_99033105561861/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_99033105561861/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>1999-08-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Developing countries and accounting rates
            reform : a technological and regulatory El Nino?
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            New technology and the liberalization of
            telecommunications markets are putting increasing stress on
            the accounting rates regime -- the system used by
            telecommunications carriers to settle their international
            traffic accounts. While operators in most countries
            acknowledge that the current system is unsustainable, many
            developing countries have resisted the pressures for radical
            change, arguing that it will cause an unbearably large drop
            in their operations' profitability. Many depend heavily
            on international revenues to subsidize network development
            and public services. Several of the most vulnerable
            countries derive up to 50 percent of their
            telecommunications revenues from international settlements.
            And for about thirty countries changes to the settlement
            regime will have a significant effect on current account and
            fiscal balances. In several of these countries the
            telecommunications sector is characterized by distorted
            pricing structures, ineffective policies, and a monopoly
            service provider. This Note briefly reviews the growing
            pressures on the current arrangements, analyzes the
            countries most affected, discusses the future of
            international telephony pricing, and outlines new sources of
            assistance to help developing countries make the transition.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Developing countries and accounting rates
            reform : a technological and regulatory El Nino?
        </docna>
        <display_title>Developing countries and
            accounting rates reform : a technological and regulatory El Nino?</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1999/01/441522/developing-countries-accounting-rates-reform-technological-regulatory-el-nino</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Payment Systems &amp; Infrastructure,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Business in Development,Public Sector Economics,Pharmaceuticals &amp; Pharmacoeconomics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Public Sector Development,Health, Nutrition and Population,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Braga, Carlos A. Primo</author>
            <author>Forestier, Emmanuel</author>
            <author>Stern, Peter A.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_99033105561861</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Telecommunications &amp; Informatics</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 173</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Public Sector Development,Health, Nutrition and Population,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Information and communications</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Telecommunications; International
            Telecommunication Union; Developing countries;
            Telecommunication networks; Interconnection; Telephone
            services; Callback services; Telephone networks; European
            Union; Telephone rates; Grants; Pricing policy reofrms
            account,accounting,accounts,benchmarks,business
            plans,cost studies,current account,foreign exchange,foreign
            exchange reserves,hard currency,net settlement,new
            entrants,Private Sector,profitability,public
            services,regulatory
            authorities,subsidiaries,subsidiary,telecommunications,transaction costs
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>19059</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Instruments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems &amp; Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Securities Settlement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Settlement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>World Trade Organization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Balance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>