<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>\9V_2,&#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 177                                                                               April 1999&#13;
Management Contracts in Water and&#13;
Sanitation-Gaza's Experience&#13;
Jamal Saghir     In 1995, as the interim agreements between the   Finally, tariffs were too low-between USS0.30&#13;
Elisabeth        Palestine Liberation Organization and the gov-   and US$0.40 a cubic meter'-for a contract&#13;
Sherwood, and    ernment of Israel were being finalized and   based on revenues to succeed.&#13;
AndreuM 7facoun   signed. water and sanitation services in the Gaza&#13;
Strip were in crisis. Gaza has an extremelyv dense   Under these circumstances a management con-&#13;
population of about 2,500 people per square  tract offered several advantages: it was highly&#13;
kilometer (the population is around 900,000).  flexible, of limited duration, and ensured that&#13;
The thin strip of land's primary sourcc of watcr,   a range of options would be available at the&#13;
a shallow aquifer, was being mined at more than   end of the contract. In addition, the contract&#13;
twice its estimated annual recharge rate, result-   would allow both the Palestinian Authority and&#13;
ing in an increasing deterioration in quality,  the general public to judge the advantages of&#13;
private sector management without committing&#13;
Responsibility for water services was frag-  to a long-term relationship. The contract would&#13;
mented among four municipal water depart-  also allow the private sector to judge the Pal-&#13;
ments, twelve village councils, and the United   estinian Authority's commitment, particularly&#13;
Nations Relief and Works Agency. There was  to cost recovery through tariffs. Finally, the&#13;
no accurate accounting of water production or  terms of the contract included a number of tasks&#13;
consumption, though estimates put daily per   necessary to establishing a sound commercial&#13;
capita consumption at less than 70 liters, well  approach (such as implementing a computer-&#13;
below levels in countries with similar incomes.  ized administrative system, network mapping,&#13;
About half of the water supplied was unac-   and hydraulic modeling). By the time the con-&#13;
counted for-the result of systemn losses, ille-  tract ends the Palestinian Water Authority will&#13;
gal connections, and nonfunctioning meters.    be able to make an informed decision on future&#13;
private participation in infrastructure and regu-&#13;
A stepwise approach to reform              latory arrangements. At that point an alterna-&#13;
tive means of private sector involvement-such&#13;
All stakeholders recognized that private sector   as a lease or a full performance management&#13;
involvement was the only way to rapidly im-   contract-is expected to be implemented.&#13;
prove the water supply system. But long-term&#13;
arrangements posed significant risks to both   So in mid-1996 Lyonnaise des Eaux/Khatib and&#13;
the Palestinian Authority and potential private   Alami (LEKA) was awarded a four-year water&#13;
contractors. First among these was the risk re-   services management contract to help local gov-&#13;
sulting from the political and security situation   ernment service providers and the Palestinian&#13;
in Gaza. Secornd, the Palestinian authorities had   Water Authority improve water service. The con-&#13;
only just been empowered to manage water  tract is the first of its kind in a World Bank-&#13;
resources; it was unlikely that they would agree   funded project in the Middle East.&#13;
to divestment. Third, so little information was&#13;
available on the existing system that there was   Since the contract became active, water quality&#13;
almost no basis for establishing the terms or   has improved, water losses have fallen, and con-&#13;
expectations of a concession contract or lease.   sumption and revenues have increased. Despite&#13;
The World Bank Group * Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Management Contracts in Water and Sanitation-Gaza's Experience&#13;
the improved performance, the management   nual ceilings for incentive payments were set at&#13;
contract has illustrated some of the limitations   one-quarter of the total, or US$750,000.&#13;
of this approach. The contract leaves the imple-&#13;
mentation of management decisions in the hands   The performance payment is calculated accord-&#13;
of the local authorities, limiting the benefits of   ing to thirty-one performance targets grouped&#13;
improved management. For example, although   under the four contract objectives. Each of the&#13;
LEKA has identified nearly 11,000 illegal con-   performance targets-ranging from the number&#13;
nections, resolution is left to municipalities and   of meters repaired or replaced, to reductions in&#13;
the Palestinian Water Authority-and to date,   unaccounted-for water, to the completion of&#13;
action has been limited. And although LEKA has   tasks such as the development and implemen-&#13;
provided training to well operators on chlorine   tation of maintenance and materials manage-&#13;
dosing and routine maintenance procedures,   ment systems-was given indicator values that&#13;
most failures in the dosing units are due to the   quantify the annual achievement of the target.&#13;
reluctance or inability of municipal employees&#13;
to carry out basic procedures.               In addition, all performance targets were&#13;
weighted to reflect the priority of the target. Criti-&#13;
The contract design                          cal targets were given much higher weightings-&#13;
for example, reducing unaccounted-for water is&#13;
The contract fee is split between a fixed an-   weighted the highest of any target. The indica-&#13;
nual payment and an additional performance   tor weightings emphasize the importance placed&#13;
payment based on the achievement of perfor-   on increasing the quantity of available water. A&#13;
mance targets.                               composite performance score determines the in-&#13;
centive payment. If the composite score does&#13;
The fixed-fee portion of the contract, which   not meet a threshold level the operator is dis-&#13;
formed the basis for international competitive   qualified from any incentive payment.&#13;
bidding for the contract, is about US$6 million&#13;
over four years. In return, the operator pro-   The rating system provides for exclusion of&#13;
vides full-time expatriate managers, full-time   work performed by contractors hired by other&#13;
local technicians, administrative support, and   agencies or authorities.2 In addition, LEKA and&#13;
short-term expatriate specialists to undertake   the Palestinian Water Authority are allowed to&#13;
specific tasks. The scope of work for the con-   invoke a force majeure clause of the contract&#13;
tract focuses on four objectives:            for any event beyond their control that makes&#13;
* Increasing the quantity of available water by   it impossible to fulfill their obligations. Such&#13;
improving the efficiency of the water supply   events include strikes, lockouts, and other in-&#13;
distribution system and operating equipment.   dustrial actions (except where such events can&#13;
* Improving the quality of the water supply   be prevented by the party invoking force ma-&#13;
and of wastewater effluent.                jeure) as well as confiscation or any other ac-&#13;
* Improving management of water and waste-   tion by government agencies. Many such events&#13;
water systems through better operations, rev-   have occurred over the life of the contract be-&#13;
enue collections, and customer service.     cause of border closures and other disruptions.&#13;
* Strengthening water and wastewater institu-   As a result a one-time agreement was negoti-&#13;
tions through long-term system planning and   ated to carry over to the second year the bal-&#13;
training.                                   ance of the first year's performance payment,&#13;
less a 10 percent penalty, in return for with-&#13;
An incentive payment was added to the contract   drawing all force majeure claims.&#13;
to encourage the achievement of the contract's&#13;
objectives. The total incentive payment for the   No significant changes have been made to the&#13;
four years is US$3 million, or an additional 50   performance targets. Though some criteria were&#13;
percent of the fixed contract payment. The an-   not sufficiently challenging (metering, system&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
disinfection), on the whole targets have been   This approach has worked well. At the end of&#13;
challen,ging but achievable. At the same time,   the first year of the contract, LEKA's assessment&#13;
performance targets for institutional and proce-   of its performance yielded an incentive fee pay-&#13;
dural development objectives have generally not   ment of US$498,000 (64 percent of the total pos-&#13;
been met-either because of different interpre-   sible payment). The auditor downgraded four&#13;
tations of actions taken or the operator's   of the performance indicators-in three cases&#13;
prioritization of other benchmarks. Different   LEKA claimed full compliance whereas the au-&#13;
weightings in the original contract, or some other   ditor founld that compliance was poor. The&#13;
mechanism for ensuring equal aittention to in-   auditor's score was ultimately used to calculate&#13;
stitutional development, might have addressed   the incentive payment of US$444,000. Perfor-&#13;
this issue from the start. In more recent perfor-   mance in the second year was assessed close to&#13;
mance-based management contracts for Amman,   US$800,000 (due to the carryover frorom the first&#13;
Jorclan, and for the Bethlehem and Ilebron ar-   year).&#13;
eas of the West Bank fewer and better-defined&#13;
indicators have been used.                    Funding&#13;
Contracting out regulation                    The Gaza management contract is not funded&#13;
bv revenue from water and sanitation services.&#13;
Some tension between a private operator and an   Rather, it is funded entirely by a US$25 million&#13;
oversight body is to be expected. In Gaza no    credit from the World Bank to the Palestine&#13;
regulatory capacity existed before the manage-   Liberation Organization for the benefit of the&#13;
ment contract went into effect, and the Palestin-   Palestinian Authority. In most cases it should&#13;
ian Authority, with no experience with a private   not. however, be necessary to guarantee an&#13;
operator, feared being taken advantage of.    external source of funds. Sector reforms should&#13;
raise revenues enough to cover all or most of&#13;
The solution agreed on was to hire a reputable   the costs of a management contract. thereby&#13;
auditing firm (Deloitte and Touche, Norway)   increasing private sector interest in such ar-&#13;
to perform an annual audit of the operator's  rangements. In Gaza, however, political and&#13;
technical and financial performance.3 At the end    secturity concerns would likely have dissuaded&#13;
of each six-month period of the contract, the   operators from taking on such a large assigyn-&#13;
operator prepares a perfornmance report detail-   ment without the support of the Bank credit.&#13;
iog its progress against the perforiiance indi-&#13;
cators, including evidence necessary for   The Bank also contributed to another crucial&#13;
substantiation. As part of this exercise the   aspect of sector improvement, establishing a&#13;
operator calculates its own performance score.   USS12 million fund to invest in the operational&#13;
The operator also reports its activities in each    capacity of water and sanitation infrastructure.&#13;
of Gaza's sixteen municipalities and villages.   The fundl gives the operator the means to make&#13;
In addition, the Palestinian Water Authority   improvements in the system in much the same&#13;
prepares progress reports.                    wvay a lessee would, based on needs identified&#13;
by management. The operator has consider-&#13;
At the end of each contract year the auditor   able flexibility in deternining immediate in-&#13;
reviews the performance reports, confirms their   vestment needs and can procure (using World&#13;
accuracy by visiting sites and examining records   Bank guidelines) goods ancl servxices as needed.&#13;
and inventories, and verifies the performance&#13;
score. The incentive payment is then calculated    Lessons&#13;
on the basis of the performance score. The&#13;
auditor also reports to the Palestinian Water   More than two years after the award of the&#13;
Authority on the operator's financial statements   contract the water supply system  is much&#13;
and any issues arising from them.             improved. In the first half of 1998 unaccounted-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Management Contracts in Water and Sanitation-Gaza's Experience&#13;
for water was around 35 percent lower than in    ties. It financed the operating investment fund,&#13;
1995. Water consumption for the same period             without which the operator could not commit&#13;
was almost 16 million cubic meters, nearly 50    to meeting service targets. And it provided as-&#13;
percent more than in 1995. Total revenue col-    surances on the policy reforms supported by&#13;
lected in 1997 was almost twice that in 1996.    the donors.&#13;
In addition, water delivered in the Gaza Strip&#13;
is now  reliably chlorinated, more than 11,000          Overall, the Gaza experience suggests that man-&#13;
illegal connections have been identified, more    agement contracts are most likely to work un-&#13;
than 2,000 leaks have been repaired, a com-    der four conditions:&#13;
plete database of service connections has been    * The primary objective is to rapidly enhance&#13;
prepared (with almost 10,000 connections re-              the technical capacity and efficiency of services.&#13;
placed), 80 percent of the system  has been    * Government faces obstacles to committing&#13;
mapped, and more than 7,000 meters have been              to a long-term  arrangement for private par-&#13;
repaired and 8,000 replaced.                              ticipation in infrastructure or to inducing the&#13;
private sector to undertake capital investment&#13;
Experience with the management contract in                or take on commercial or political risk.&#13;
Gaza suggests that conferring higher degrees    - Tariffs are too low  to support a long-term&#13;
of management responsibility to an operator               arrangement for private participation in infra-&#13;
could expedite improvements. As successful as             structure.&#13;
the operator has been in meeting the require-    * Government faces difficulties in securing agree-&#13;
Viewpoint is an open  ments under its direct authority, local authori-           ments to allow  the long-term  involvement of&#13;
forum intended to     ties have not been consistent in supporting                the private sector or the regulatory framework&#13;
encourage dissemina-  those improvements. This remains the weak-                 is incompatible with a long-term arrangement&#13;
tion of and debate on&#13;
ideas, innovations, and  est link of the contract.                               for private participation in infrastructure.&#13;
best practices for&#13;
expanding the private  One essential feature of the contract was its use    Where the above conditions apply (as in Gaza),&#13;
sector. The views pub-&#13;
lished are those of the  of independent technical and financial auditors    a management contract provides a window of&#13;
authors and should not    to audit the achievement of the annual perfor-    opportunity in which trust can be developed&#13;
be attributed to the  mance targets, calculate the incentive fee, and          between the public and private sectors. Such&#13;
World Bank or any of&#13;
its affiliated organiza-  provide a comfort letter for payment of the in-    contracts also allow  the authorities to devote&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the  centive fee. But although the contract established   attention to creating an appropriate regulatory&#13;
conclusions represent  clear benchmarks and a performance rating sys-    framework, adjusting tariffs and subsidies, and&#13;
official policy of the&#13;
World Bank or of its  tem, it allowed the operator to focus on bench-    creating an environment more conducive to&#13;
Executive Directors   marks that would generate a higher performance           private risk taking.&#13;
or the countries they  payment. As a result less attention was given to&#13;
represent.&#13;
benchmarks that were perceived as being harder    ' While within the range of many other tariffs in the region, this rate&#13;
To order additional   to achieve or worth too little in terms of their           could not begin to cover realistic provisioning for the miajor capital&#13;
copies p4ease call    weighted worth (for example, training and public           investments that are needed. In contrast, water supplied hyjeruss-&#13;
202 458 l                             c         t    or contact  .              lem Water Undertaking costs between U'SS1 and USSI.50 a cubic&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,    relations). Structurng the contract so that some       meter.&#13;
Room Fl 1 K-208,      objectives are simple contractual requirements,    2 Many donors are helping the Palestinian Authority rehabilitate and&#13;
The World Bank,       within either the base fee or the incentive fee            extend infrastructure and services. The rating system discounts these&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,     w l  o         m   t                                      cotrribtions to the operator's achievement of performance targets.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,    would overcome tms problem.                         3The sditor's oork is fonded by a bilateral donor.&#13;
or Internet address&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.    For several reasons multilateral financing was    Janal Saghir (saghir@worldbank.org),&#13;
The series is also                            hih-is&#13;
available tn-line     essential in such a high-risk environment as    Elisabeth Sherwood (esherwood@worldbank.&#13;
(wwvv.wrldbank.org/  Gaza. This financing covered the fixed fees of    org), and Andrew Macoun, Middle East and&#13;
html/fpd/notes/).     the operator, easing concerns that low revenue    Nortbh Africa Region&#13;
@ Printed on recycled  and other risks would prevent payment by the&#13;
paper.                Palestinian Water Authority or the municipali-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441506">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/04/441506/management-contracts-water-sanitation-gazas-experience
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/04/441506/management-contracts-water-sanitation-gazas-experience</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/04/441506/management-contracts-water-sanitation-gazas-experience</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_99042805372959/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_99042805372959/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-06-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Management contracts in water and
            sanitation - Gaza's experience
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In 1995, as the interim agreements
            between the Palestine Liberation Organization and Israel
            were signed, water and sanitation services in the Gaza Strip
            were in crisis. In mid-1996 Lyonnaise des Eaux/Khatib and
            Alami (LEKA) was awarded a four-year water services
            management contract to help local government service
            providers and the Palestinian Water Authority improve water
            service. Since the contract became active, water quality has
            improved, water losses have fallen, and consumption and
            revenues have increased. Despite the improved performance,
            the management contract has illustrated some limitations.
            Overall, the Gaza experience suggests that management
            contracts are most likely to work under four conditions: 1)
            The primary objective is to rapidly enhance the technical
            capacity and efficiency of services. 2) Government faces
            obstacles to committing to a long-term arrangement for
            private participation in infrastructure or to inducing the
            private sector to undertake capital investment or take on
            commercial or political risk. 3) Tariffs are too low to
            support a long-term arrangement for private participation in
            infrastructure. 4) Government faces difficulties in securing
            agreements to allow the long-term involvement of the private
            sector or the regulatory framework is incompatible with a
            long-term arrangement for private participation in infrastructure.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Management contracts in water and sanitation
            - Gaza's experience
        </docna>
        <display_title>Management contracts in water and
            sanitation - Gaza's experience</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1999/04/441506/management-contracts-water-sanitation-gazas-experience</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Conservation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>West Bank and Gaza</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Saghir, Jamal</author>
            <author>Sherwood, Elizabeth</author>
            <author>Macoun, Andrew</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Middle East!$!80463</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_99042805372959</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Water Supply &amp; Sanitation</subsc>
        <admreg>Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 177</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Management contracts; Water supply &amp;
            sanitation; Water supply systems; Water distribution; Award
            of contracts; Audits; Private sector participation;
            Infrastructure privatization; Infrastructure regulation;
            Regulatory framework; Public-private partnerships
            administrative support,available
            water,concession contract,contract design,contract
            objectives,cost recovery,cubic meter,cubic
            meters,distribution system,effluent,local
            authorities,management of water,municipal
            employees,municipal water,municipalities,performance
            indicators,private operator,private participation,private
            sector,recharge,regulatory capacity,regulatory
            framework,Responsibility for water,sanitation
            infrastructure,sanitation services,service
            connections,service providers,wastewater,Water
            Authority,Water consumption,water production,water
            quality,water service,water services,water supply,water
            supply system,water systems
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Middle East</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>19172</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Energy and Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Telecommunications and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP in Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships in Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arms Length Agencies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Mapping</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting Out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Chains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Delivery Arrangements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Standards, Service Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing for Results</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outcomes Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Drivers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Results Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outsourcing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Participation in Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>