<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>*178 15'&#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 155                                                                               October 1998&#13;
Corporate Finance Lessons from the East&#13;
Asian Crisis&#13;
Michael           This Note examines the corporate roots of the   of a rapid and unsustainable buildup of invest-&#13;
Pornerleanio     financial crisis in East Asia. It summarizes the   ment in fixed assets financed by excessive bor-&#13;
findings of a study of corporate financial per-  rowing. This investment spending spree resulted&#13;
formance in East Asian economies-Hong Kong,  in poor profitability, reflected in low and declin-&#13;
Indonesia, the Republic of Korea, MIalaysia, the   ing returns on equity and on capital employed.&#13;
Philippines. Taiwan (China), and Thailand.' To   The study concluded that at the core of the cor-&#13;
allow a consistent cross-border analysis of fi-   porate crisis were financial excesses that inevi-&#13;
nancial risk and performance, the study used as   tably led to financial distress. The findings&#13;
benchmarks key financial performance ratios for   support the view advanced by Paul Krugman&#13;
corporations in France, Germany, Japan, the   (1998) that crony capitalism-and the associ-&#13;
United States, and Latin America.            ated policies of implicit guarantees-and poor&#13;
banking supervision led to poor credit decisions&#13;
For some Asian economies, especially Indone-   in the banking system and thus the misalloca-&#13;
sia, Korea, and Thailand, clear evidence emerged   tion of resources.&#13;
FIGURE 1 AVERAGE CORPORATE LEVERAGE, 1996&#13;
Debt-equity ratio&#13;
160&#13;
140&#13;
120&#13;
100&#13;
80&#13;
60&#13;
40&#13;
20&#13;
Thailand Japan Republic France Indonesia United  Philip- Taiwan Malaysia Singa- Germany Hong  Latin&#13;
of Korea           States  pines (China)      pore        Kong America&#13;
Note: Data are for December 31.&#13;
Source:World Bank staff calculations based on the Financial Times Information's Extel database.&#13;
LW                The World Bank Group * Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2                  Corporate Finance Lessons from the East Asian Crisis&#13;
Financial indicators                            Growth and financing of tangible fixed assets&#13;
The study assessed corporate financial practices   The study's results point to a rapid buildup oif&#13;
and performance using standard ratio analysis   fixed assets in Asia (figure 2). The average&#13;
focusing on leverage, the growth and financing    change in tangible fixed assets during 1992-96&#13;
of tangible fixed assets, and debt sustainability.   was 33 percent in Indonesia, 29 percent in Thai-&#13;
It captured corporate performance and profit-   land, and 20 percent in Malaysia. This rapid&#13;
ability through ratios measuring return on capital   growth is in stark contrast with the more mod-&#13;
employed and economic value added. It supple-   erate pattern in Hong Kong (17 percent) and&#13;
mented the ratio analysis with an indicator of   in the industrial countries in the sample (1 to 5&#13;
corporate financial fragility-Altman's Z-score.    percent). These findings evidence the unten-&#13;
able business growth in Asian economies. No&#13;
Leverage                                        well-managed company (with the possible&#13;
exception of software companies) can pru-&#13;
The debt-equity ratio-a company's debt divided    dently absorb annual growth of 30 to 40 per-&#13;
by shareholder equity-indicates a company's   cent. Such rapid growth would overwhelm&#13;
leverage-how much borrowed money the com-   managerial capacity and distribution and mar-&#13;
pany is using relative to its equity. The study    keting channels.&#13;
found wide variation in debt-equity ratios in Asia&#13;
and in the sample overall (figure 1). Data for   Debt sustainability&#13;
December 31, 1996, show that Korean and Thai&#13;
companies generally had high debt-equity ra-   To analyze debt sustainability, the study calcu-&#13;
tios (around 150 percent), while those in Hong    lated the ratio of companies' operating cash&#13;
Kong, the Philippines, and Taiwan (China) had   flows (operating income before interest, taxes,&#13;
moderate ratios. Latin American, German, and    and depreciation) to their annual interest pay-&#13;
U.S. companies had modest debt-equity ratios   ments on loans or their debt service (principal&#13;
(90 percent in the United States).               plus interest payments). This ratio indicates&#13;
FIGURE 2 AVERAGE CHANGE IN TANGIBLE FIXED ASSETS, 1992-96&#13;
Percent&#13;
35&#13;
30&#13;
25&#13;
20&#13;
is&#13;
10&#13;
5&#13;
0&#13;
Indonesia Thailand Singa- Malaysia Hong Republic Philip- Taiwan  Latin  Japan  United Germany France&#13;
pore         Kong  of Korea  pines  (China) America    States&#13;
Source:.World Bank staff calculations based on the Financial Times Information's Extel database.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                        3&#13;
TABLE 1   STANDARD &amp; POOR'S RATING REQUIREMENTS&#13;
FOR FINANCIAL RATIOS, BY RATING LEVEL&#13;
Percent&#13;
companies' ability to cover interest payments&#13;
or debt service on their outstanding loans.                Ratio                     AAA               BBB   BB    B&#13;
The findings indicate big differences across               lert.cowageratio          2013 14.94  851  6.03  363  227&#13;
countries (figure 3). The interest coverage ra-            undsrnoperaion/&#13;
tio in Thailand declined from  4.6 in 1992 to               toal debt               116.4  72.3  47.5  34.7  1&amp;4  10.9&#13;
1.92 in 1996 as an increasing debt-equity ratio&#13;
led to a rise in interest expense. The ratios in&#13;
other vulnerable Asian countries were similar:             Opmrting income/sales     24.0  19.2  16.1  15.4  15.1  12.6&#13;
2.44 in Indonesia in 1996 and 1.07 in Korea in             Long-tenn debt/capital    13.4  21.9  32.7  43.4  53.9  65.9&#13;
1995. Corporations in Hong Kong, Malaysia,                 Total debt/capitalization  23.6  29.7  38.7  46.8  5r.8  68.9&#13;
and Taiwan (China) are more robust. Also quite&#13;
, .  ,        ~~~~Net.aUItos are clculated as theeyear (19-96) 9medians.&#13;
robust are those in Latin America (25.36 in 1996)          SouStadrd&amp;Pes bffn   Smice1997.&#13;
and in some industrial countries-the United&#13;
States (7.62), Germany (7.09), France (4.75),&#13;
and Japan (4.31). Standard &amp; Poor's credit rat-&#13;
ing policies put these findings in context (table    ing strategies, because the operating profit is&#13;
1). To earn an A-rating, U.S. companies must    viewed in relation to the total funds employed.&#13;
have a ratio of operating cash flows to interest&#13;
of more than 8.                                      The study's results show a solid 20 percent av-&#13;
erage return on capital employed in Hong Kong&#13;
Return on capital employed                           in 1992-96 (figure 4). The ratio for Indonesia,&#13;
at 11 percent, is good in absolute terms (though&#13;
Return on capital employed or on assets (be-    overshadowed by domestic interest rates of 15&#13;
fore taxes) captures the efficiency with which    to 18 percent). The results for Korea, Malaysia,&#13;
a company uses all its capital resources. Analy-    the Philippines, Taiwan (China), Latin America,&#13;
sis of this ratio permits comparison of busi-    and the industrial countries (France, Germany,&#13;
nesses regardless of differences in accounting    Japan, and the United States) reflect large dif-&#13;
conventions (for example, with regard to de-    ferences in average return on capital during&#13;
preciation) or capital mobilization and financ-    1992-96. While the average return in the United&#13;
FIGURE 3 AVERAGE INTEREST COVERAGE RATIO, 1996&#13;
30&#13;
25&#13;
20&#13;
15&#13;
10&#13;
5&#13;
0&#13;
Latin   Hong   Singa-  United Germany Malaysia France  Japan  Taiwan  Philip- IndonesiaThailand Republic&#13;
America  Kong    pore   States                                (China)  pines                 of Korea&#13;
Note: Ratio of operating cash flows (operating income before interest, taxes, and depreciation) to interest payable on loans.&#13;
Source: World Bank staff calculations based on the Financial Times Information's Extel database.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4                   Corporate Finance Lessons from the East Asian Crisis&#13;
States was 11 percent, in Korea it was 8 percent.   did the return on capital employed consistently&#13;
Latin America's reasonable return on capital of   exceed the cost of capital during 1992-96-and&#13;
16 percent masks high inflation rates. The average    except for Hong Kong, not by a significant mar-&#13;
return in some industrial countries-such as the    gin. But there are significant intertemporal dif-&#13;
5 percent in France and Japan and the 4 percent   ferences for countries: declining trends in&#13;
in Germany-was surprisingly paltry.              economic value added in Thailand highlight the&#13;
economy's deterioration. Japan's positive eco-&#13;
The study's analysis of the return on capital   nomic value added is attributable largely to the&#13;
employed in Thailand, supplemented by the    country's low prevailing interest rates rather than&#13;
debt-equity ratio, suggests that it was no acci-    a high return on capital employed. By contrast,&#13;
dent that the East Asian crisis first erupted in   the analysis suggests that the negative economic&#13;
Thailand. Measures of financial risk show that   value added in Indonesia is explained by the&#13;
Thailand was an outlier in every regard. The    high prevailing domestic interest rates.&#13;
performance of Thai companies progressively&#13;
deteriorated during 1992-96: credit ratios    Financial fragility&#13;
declined, margins were squeezed, and return&#13;
on equity declined significantly, from 13 per-   Estimating Altman's Z-score, the indicator of&#13;
cent in 1992 to 5 percent in 1996.               financial fragility, involves calculating five ratios&#13;
found in a company's financial statements:&#13;
Economic value added                             return on total assets, sales to total assets, equity&#13;
to debt (the inverse of the debt-equity ratio),&#13;
To examine opportunity costs of capital the study    working capital to total assets, and retained&#13;
applied the concept of shareholder economic    earnings to total assets. These ratios are then&#13;
value added. This indicator compares the re-   adjusted by predetermined weights and added&#13;
ported profitability of a corporation-the mea-   together to yield the Z-score, which ranges from&#13;
sured return on capital employed-with the cost   -4 to +8. Companies with Z-scores above 2.99&#13;
of capital, defined as the interest rate (figure 5).   are considered financially sound, while those&#13;
scoring below 1.81 are financially distressed&#13;
The study's results show that only for Hong Kong,   and face possible bankruptcy. Scores between&#13;
Japan, Malaysia, Singapore, and the United States    1.81 and 2.99 indicate vulnerability.&#13;
FIGURE 4 AVERAGE RETURN ON CAPITAL EMPLOYED, BEFORE TAXES, 1992-96&#13;
Percent&#13;
20&#13;
15&#13;
'a&#13;
5&#13;
0&#13;
Hong   Latin  Malaysia Indonesia United  Singa-  Taiwan Republic Thailand Philip- France  Japan Germany&#13;
Kong  America               States   pore  (China) of Korea     pines&#13;
Source: World Bank staff calculations based on the Financial Times Information's Extel database.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                         5&#13;
FIGURE 5 AVERAGE ECONOMIC VALUE ADDED, 1992-96&#13;
Philippines&#13;
Indonesia&#13;
The study's Z-score results suggest considerable                                          Thailand&#13;
fragility of the corporate sector in some Asian                                           Germany&#13;
economies and in France, confirming results for                                           France&#13;
other ratios (figure 6). By 1996 Z-scores for Asia                                        Republic of Korea&#13;
evidenced severe financial distress in Thailand                                     Japan&#13;
(1.5) and Korea (1.6). Indonesia's Z-score (2.7)                                Singapore&#13;
was marginally below the financially sound level                                 Malaysia&#13;
of 2.99. By contrast, cor,jorate sectors were ro-                             United States&#13;
bust in Hong Kong (6.9), Malaysia (3.9), the Phil-                              Hong Kong&#13;
ippines (3.4), and Taiwan, China (3.2). Among           -10    -     -      4    -2      0     2      4     6     8     10    12&#13;
industrial countries the 7-scores suggested vul-                                      Percent&#13;
nerability in France (1.8) and Japan (2.1).&#13;
Note: Calculated as return on capital employed minus the lending rate.&#13;
Source:World Bank staff calculations based on the Financial Times Information's Extel database.&#13;
Implications&#13;
What are the implicationis of these financial in-    The fiindings of this study lead to several con-&#13;
dicator levels for recent Asian corporate perfor-    clusions. First, corporations in Indonesia, Ko-&#13;
mance? A partial picture emerges from research         rea, and Thailand tried to defy financial "laws&#13;
papers now  coming out of investment banks.    of gravity" that can be ignored only at the risk&#13;
This research shows that corporations suffered    of financial distress. Business practices in some&#13;
significant damage as a result of high debt-eq-    Asian countries reflect a lack of financial disci-&#13;
uity ratios in a context of rising interest rates    pline and, to a lesser extent, of operational&#13;
and  a worsening  economic environment,    discipline. The investment spending spree con-&#13;
coupled with exposure to unhedged foreign              tributed to the erosion of profit margins and to&#13;
currency loans. A large number of Asian corpo-    poor financial performance, reflected in declin-&#13;
rations have become insolvent and will have to    ing and low  returns on equity and on capital&#13;
be recapitalized.                                      employed. By contrast, corporations in Hong&#13;
FIGURE 6 AVERAGE CORPORATE FINANCIAL FRAGILITY, 1996&#13;
Altman's Z-score&#13;
8&#13;
7&#13;
6&#13;
5&#13;
4&#13;
3&#13;
2&#13;
O - _&#13;
Hong  MalaVsia United Germany Philip-  Taiwan  Singa- Indonesia Japan   Latin  France Thailand Republic&#13;
Kong           States           pines  (China)   pore                  America                  of Korea&#13;
Source:World Bank staff calculations based on the Financial Times Information's Extel database.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6                   Corporate Finance Lessons from the East Asian Crisis&#13;
Kong, Malaysia, and Taiwan (China) pursued    financing. A restructuring process must also&#13;
prudent financial practices.                      recognize that some corporations might not be&#13;
salvageable.&#13;
Second, the large differences in economic value&#13;
added among the study countries lead to the    In addition, the study supports findings from&#13;
conclusion that Asian corporations have not   other research about the efficiency of financial&#13;
adopted global standards on creating share-   intermediation in Asia. In this region, where&#13;
holder value. In an era of increasing capital   household savings amount to about a third of&#13;
mobility, when capital can rapidly arbitrage dif-   gross domestic product (GDP), the high sav-&#13;
ferences in rates of return, disparities in un-   ings have been largely channeled by banks to&#13;
derlying returns on equity and on capital   businesses. The pursuit of rapid economic&#13;
employed probably are not sustainable in the    growth in the region limited the capacity of&#13;
long run. To ensure availability of equity capi-   internal earnings generation to buffer accumu-&#13;
tal and improved equity market performance,   lation of debt, resulting in high corporate le-&#13;
corporations need to demonstrate to investors    verage. Indeed, Asia's high-debt, high-risk&#13;
that they can sustain solid performance in eco-    model of economic development is a direct&#13;
nomic value added.                                result of the savings intermediation process in&#13;
the region's economies. Asia's high corporate&#13;
Third, the poor operating and financial perfor-   leverage contrasts with that in countries with&#13;
mance in the crisis countries relative to that in   slower growth and more balanced financial&#13;
other countries suggests a need for systemic   systems, including well-developed equity and&#13;
corporate restructuring. A restructuring process    bond markets.&#13;
needs to reflect a readiness to address insol-&#13;
vent corporations through court-supervised re-   Most of the study countries with poor return&#13;
organization or bankruptcy, promotion of   on capital employed have underdeveloped&#13;
voluntary restructuring of distressed and illiq-    capital markets. Asia's bond markets, for ex-&#13;
ulid-but operationally viable-corporations    ample, are less than 20 percent of regional GDP,&#13;
through debt-equity swaps, and assurance of   small in comparison with developed bond mar-&#13;
the liquidity needed during the workout pro-    kets such as that in the United States, which is&#13;
cess through provision for debtor-in-possession    more than 100 percent of GDP. Comparative&#13;
FIGURE 7 COMPOSITION OF CORPORATE FINANCIAL ASSETS, BY TYPE, 1995&#13;
Percent&#13;
100                              ~-5                                             mH: &#13;
80&#13;
Long-term debt&#13;
60                                                                                                      (bonds)&#13;
40    *        *         *        *         *        *         *        t         t          t       -  Bank assets&#13;
20&#13;
0&#13;
China    Hong   Indonesia  Republic  Malaysia Philippines Singapore  Thailand   East Asia Germany, Japan&#13;
Kong             of Korea                                                United Kingdom,&#13;
United States&#13;
Source: World Bank staff calcalations based on the Financial Times Information's Extel database.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                                 7&#13;
statistics on financial sector development sug-                 mild interest rate suppression that subsidized&#13;
gest that, in general, Asian economies have ex-                 corporations at the expense of savers. In addi-&#13;
hibited overdependence on the banking sector                    tion, established, long-term  relationships be-&#13;
and underreliance on  capital markets (figure                   tween companies and banks turned debt into&#13;
7). The key ingredients for successful capital                  quasi-equity  (the  proverbial Asian  "ever-&#13;
markets-transparency, corporatc accountabil-                    grcens"). But such  relationships allowcd  lax&#13;
ity  and  governance, and  proper risk  pricing                 credit approval processes, often without refer-&#13;
through the transmission  of market signals-                    ence to projects' viability and possibly based&#13;
have been  lacking. These Limitations underlie                  on political connections.&#13;
the deficiencies in the performance of Asian&#13;
corporations. And they may have amplified the                   The study's findings suggest that the lack  of&#13;
effects of the  corporate  excesses, leading  to                financial and institutional discipline-coupled&#13;
the crisis. A  more open, balanced, and  com-                   with the recent financial sector liberalization&#13;
petitive financial system  is needed in Asia, one               in some countries and the imposition of mar-&#13;
in which capital is allocated more transparently                ket discipline (including the lifting of interest&#13;
and  with  appropriate  consideration  of risk.                 rate controls) in  an  environment without an&#13;
Increased reliance on capital markcts-and the                   adequate prudential framework-is a plausible&#13;
attendant benefits in transparency, risk assess-                explanation of the mix of currency, corporate,&#13;
ment, risk pricing, and risk dispersion-would                   and banking crises confronting the region. The&#13;
enhance corporate discipline and performance                    implications for regulation and supervision of&#13;
in Asia.                                                        the financial system  are unmistakable.&#13;
The main study also suipports the findings of                   This Note is based on a longer article bt the author: "The East Asia&#13;
recent research on the role of portfolio capital                Crisis and Corporate Finances-The Untold Micro Story," Emerging&#13;
inflows in stock market valuations. The rapid                   Markets Quarterly (forthcoming).&#13;
increase  in  foreign  pa:rticipation  in the  early               The analysis compared the financial profiLe and performance of&#13;
Asian corporations with those of corporations in the other coun-&#13;
1990s occurred in the context of large, closely                   tries The study used financial information on companies for&#13;
held  share  positions  and  limited  public                       1992-96 from the Financial Times tnformation's Extel database,&#13;
shareholding. Foreign inivestors now  have a sig-                  which contains basic data on more than 13,000 companies world-&#13;
wide. The companies selected for the analysis w,ere general manu-&#13;
nificant ownership presence and account for a                      facturing firms, extractive industries, and utilities for which there&#13;
significant share of tranisactions in Asian capi-                  were financial statements for five consecutive years ending in&#13;
tal markets. The "exuberant valuations in East                     1996. The number of companies in the sample and the size of&#13;
their sales relative to GDP suggest that the sample is robust.&#13;
Asia may have been associated with large port-                  2 Bekart and Harvey (1997) find that the cost of capital always falls&#13;
folio equity inflows in an illiquid market, a situ-                after capital market liberalization and that there is litte impact on&#13;
ation in which margina.l flows might have had                      volatility. Other evidence on the effect of capital flows on domestic&#13;
markets comes from a recent study on foreign participation in the&#13;
a disproportionate  effect on  valuations. But                     Korean equiity market. Choe, Kho, and Stultz (1998) examine the&#13;
portfolio flows ranged between  1 and 6 per-                       impact of foreign investors on stock returns in the Republic of&#13;
cent of free-float market capitalization, and al-                  Korea from Novenaber 30, 1996, to the end of 1997 using trade&#13;
cent of free-float  data. They find no evidence that trades by foreign investors had a&#13;
though  additional research  on  this issue  is                    destabilizing effect on Korea's stock market over the sarnple pe-&#13;
needed, preliminary  research  suggests that it                    riod; instead, they find that the Korean market adjusted to large&#13;
is unlikely  that portfolio  equity  flows had  a                  sales by foreign investors. Post and Millar (1998), examining U.S.&#13;
emerging market equity funds during 1996 and 1997, find that share-&#13;
marked impact on valuations.2                                      holders in U.S funds invested in Asia started to withdraw modest&#13;
shares of their investments in late 1996 and stepped tup the pace of&#13;
Finally, it is interesting  to  note  that these                   withdrawals somewhat in 1997.&#13;
microeconomic excesses occurred in a region&#13;
known for macroeconomic discipline. Several                     References&#13;
supposed safety mechanisms had been built&#13;
Aupposedsianfinanmcial  nismshby  poeinymakers            Bekart, Geert, and Campbell Harvey. 1997. "Foreign Speculators and&#13;
into Assan financial systems by policymakers                       Emerging Equity Markets." NBER Working Paper 6312. National&#13;
to manage the microeconomic risks, including                       Bureau of Economic Research, Cambridge, Atass.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Corporate Finance Lessons from the East Asian Crisis&#13;
Choe, Hyuk, Bong-Chan Kho, and Rene Stultz. 1998. "Do Foreign&#13;
investors Destabilize Stock Mankets? The Ktotean Epseenence in 1937 ."&#13;
Social Science Research Network. Available at http://papers.ssrn.coni.&#13;
Krugman, Paul. 1998. "What Happened to Asia?" Available at http://&#13;
vwww.mit.edu/people/krugman.&#13;
Post, Mlitchell A., and Kimberlee Millar. 1998. "U.S. Emerging Mlarket&#13;
Equity Funds and the 1997 Crisis in Asian Financial Markets." invest-&#13;
ment Company Institute Perspective 4(2).&#13;
Standaid &amp; Poor's Ratings Service. 1997. Cozporaie Ratings Criteria.&#13;
New York.&#13;
iliichael Pomerleano (mpomerleano@&#13;
worldbank.org) Senior Capital Market&#13;
Specialist, Capital3Markets Development&#13;
Department&#13;
Viewpoint is an open&#13;
forum itntended to&#13;
encourage dissemina-&#13;
lion of and debate on&#13;
ideas, innovations, and&#13;
best pructices for ex-&#13;
panding the private&#13;
sector. The views pub-&#13;
lished are those of the&#13;
authors and should not&#13;
be attributed to the&#13;
World Bank or any of&#13;
its affiliated organiza-&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the&#13;
conclusions represent&#13;
official policy of the&#13;
World Bank or of its&#13;
Executive Directors&#13;
or the countries they&#13;
represent.&#13;
To order additional&#13;
copies please call&#13;
202-458-1111 or contact&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,&#13;
Room F6P-188,&#13;
The WoTld Bank,&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
or Internet address&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.&#13;
The series is also&#13;
available on-line&#13;
(www.worldbank.org/&#13;
html/fpd/notes/&#13;
notelist.html).&#13;
@) Printed on recycled&#13;
paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441591">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/10/441591/corporate-finance-lessons-east-asian-crisis
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/10/441591/corporate-finance-lessons-east-asian-crisis</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1998/10/441591/corporate-finance-lessons-east-asian-crisis</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_99031910500664/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000094946_99031910500664/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1998-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>1999-08-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Corporate finance lessons from the East
            Asian crisis
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This Note examines the corporate roots
            of the financial crisis in East Asia. It summarizes the
            findings of a study of corporate financial performance in
            East Asian economies - Hong Kong, Indonesia, the Republic of
            Korea, Malaysia, the Philippines, Taiwan (China), and
            Thailand. To allow a consistent cross-border analysis of
            financial risk and performance, the study used as benchmarks
            key financial performance ratios for corporations in France,
            Germany, Japan, the United States, and Latin America.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Corporate finance lessons from the East
            Asian crisis
        </docna>
        <display_title>Corporate finance lessons from
            the East Asian crisis</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1998/10/441591/corporate-finance-lessons-east-asian-crisis</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Financial Intermediation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Conflict and Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Environment</teratopic>
        <count>East Asia and Pacific</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pomerleano, Michael</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_99031910500664</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Finance</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 155</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Conflict and Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Environment</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Finance</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Corporate finance; Financial crises; Cross
            country analysis; Debt-equity ratio; Investment; Corporate
            debt; Financial indicators; Profitability; Financial
            leverage; Debt sustainabilty; Financial stability; Financial regulation
            accounting,arbitrage,assets,banking
            crises,banking sector,banking supervision,banking
            system,bankruptcy,benchmarks,bonds,capital employed,capital
            flows,capital markets,capitalization,Corporate
            finance,corporate restructuring,cost of capital,credit
            approval,crony capitalism,Debt,economic development,Economic
            Research,economic value,economic value added,Equity
            Markets,FINANCIAL ASSETS,financial crisis,financial
            information,Financial Markets,financial
            performance,financial performance ratios,FINANCIAL
            RATIOS,financial risk,financial sector,financial
            systems,fixed assets,foreign investors,GDP,gross domestic
            product,implicit guarantees,inflation,inflation
            rates,INTEREST COVERAGE RATIO,interest expense,interest
            rate,interest rates,investment banks,investment
            spending,laws,liquidity,market liberalization,operating
            income,opportunity costs,portfolio,profit
            margins,profitability,return on
            equity,savings,Speculators,statements,swaps,transparency,value
            added,working capital
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>17815</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Carreer Guidance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Job Fairs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Volatility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prudential Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Equity Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>