<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Note No.47    Competitive Contracting for Privately&#13;
Generated Power&#13;
What to do in the absence of competition in the market&#13;
Robern Bacon     The importance of competition               the most efficient plant in the merit order and&#13;
should indeed run on base load as specified in&#13;
Independent power procducers (IPPs) are an   the typical contract. But circumstances can&#13;
increasingly inportant type of power genera-   change, and after a few years. running the IPP&#13;
tion project in developing countries. In manv   as baseload might no longer be optimal. When&#13;
of these countries. power sector reform involves   a contract does not allow for such a contin-&#13;
unbundling generation from transmission and   gencv, the operational efficiencv of the svstem&#13;
introducing private capital. Rather than pri-  tends to decline. And contracts that provide&#13;
vatizing existing generators. some governments  for guaranteed sales to reduce private inves-&#13;
prefer to create an enabling environment for  tors' risk reduce the competitive pressure on&#13;
IPPs. They have two objectives in doing so.  them to operate their plants efficiently.&#13;
First, by using truly competitive bidding to pro-&#13;
cure new generation capacity, governments   There is inevitably a tension between design-&#13;
seek to minimize the costs of expanding power  ing contracts to reduce uncertainty for the pri-&#13;
supply. And second. by introducing the profit  vate investor and running the power system as&#13;
motive and competition in the power and en-   efficiently as possible. The characteristics of&#13;
ergy sector, they seek gains in operational effi-  power sales agreements are pivotal in resolv-&#13;
ciency that lead to lower prices for electricity  ing this tension. This Note surveys a range of&#13;
users than would otherwise have been pos-  selling agreements-from the most rigid to the&#13;
sible without subsidies.                   most flexible-and highlights their risks and&#13;
benefits for operational efficiency.&#13;
The second result is especiailly hard to achieve.&#13;
and when achieved. it can be even harder to   Some of the most common contractual arrange-&#13;
sustain. Governments in most developing coun-   ments for [PPs place no competitive pressure&#13;
tries lack the proven track record of transpar-   on existing suppliers. These arrangements will&#13;
ent regulation of their power sectors that is  not help improve the efficiencv of the sector.&#13;
needed to attract private investment. Thus,   They will only increase supply capacitv-&#13;
long-term contracts (power purchase agree-  though that can he valuable in a svstem facing&#13;
ments) are required both to encourage entrv   public financing constraints. When the entry&#13;
hy potential investors and to safeguard their  of IPPs fails to put competitive pressure on&#13;
interests. Such contracts attempt to share the   other suppliers. governments need to design&#13;
risks between the parties in a predictable fash-   other efficiency-enhancing reforms, such as per-&#13;
ion. But heCause it is difficult to write legal  formance contracts for the nonprivate genera-&#13;
clauses that cover uncertainties about fLuture  tors. And if the contract does not lead to&#13;
marketing concditions. they cannot he fullv con-   head-to-hiead competition between new IPPs&#13;
tingent. so inefficiencies arise in system op-   and the other suppliers, it should include per-&#13;
eration. For example, at the time of signing a   formance incentives to ensure that the IPP re-&#13;
power purchase agreement, the IPP may be   miains an efficient supplier.&#13;
Industrv and Energy Department * Vice Presidencv for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Competitive Contracting for Privately Generated Power&#13;
Methods of contracting for the sale of         cases. penalties and bonuses are an important&#13;
IPP power and energy                           part of the incentive scheme.&#13;
There are three principal dimensions to power   The price of energy usuallv is tied to an initial&#13;
sales agreements: the selling prices for power   cost estimate and a series of cost indexation fac-&#13;
and energy, the amount of power and energy   tors. An initial heat rate and initial fuel and oper-&#13;
sold, and incentives to improve performance and    ating and maintenance (O&amp;M) costs are assessed&#13;
disincentives to ensure that performance does   for the plant, together with the appropriate in-&#13;
not fall below a basic standard. Sales agreements   dexes (for example, the consumer price index&#13;
generally are based on a two-part pricing struc-   for O&amp;M costs and the average fuel price index&#13;
ture-with separate pavments for capacity and    of the sector for fuel costs). These determine the&#13;
energy. But there are substantial differences in   energy price. Often. the price is set to just cover&#13;
the wav they deal with quantities-ranging from    such costs. and as long as the indexes track the&#13;
must-run" or take-or-pay' contracts on the    actual costs exactly, there will be no change in&#13;
plant's entire output to competitive dispatch. The   the net revenue per unit of energy supplied. The&#13;
stronger a sales agreement's guarantee of a mar-   energy price is then designed. as in certain U.S.&#13;
ket for the IPP's output. the more attractive the    power pools, so that the IPP is indifferent to&#13;
IPP becomes for the IPP sponsor and financiers.   whether or not it is dispatched. The capacity price&#13;
but the less pressure is created to generate that   is collected because the plant was declared avail-&#13;
output efficiently and the less competitive pres-   able, not because it actuallv ran, and since it eams&#13;
sure is applied to other generators. The choice    no net revenue per unit of energy, there is no&#13;
of contract structure must therefore take into   gain from being dispatched. If strong enough,&#13;
account the two-sometimes conflicting-aims   the profit motive can encourage the firm to try to&#13;
of attracting private finance and improving sec-   "beat the index" in fuel purchases or O&amp;M costs&#13;
tor efficiency.                                so that the firm's actual costs rise less than its&#13;
allowed costs. (The firmn is allowed to keep the&#13;
The price of capacity in the power sales agree-   difference-it is not passed on to the consumer.)&#13;
ment usually is related to the capacity declared&#13;
available, rather than to the actual capacity run.   The contractual arrangements for determining&#13;
it is likely to be set so that. at a given level of   how much energy and power are sold can varv&#13;
operation. the discounted revenue from capac-   greatlv. The rest of the Note examines their&#13;
ity payments will cover capital costs over the   importance for the sector.&#13;
life of che project. Contracts tend to set a target&#13;
level for availability (sav, 80 percent) over the   Must-run or take-or-pay contracts&#13;
year. plus a bonus zone above this availability&#13;
and a penaltv zone below it. Setting the target   The least riskv form of contract for IPPs guar-&#13;
well below the feasible availability under good    antees the sale of a stipulated amount of power&#13;
operating practices reduces the financing risk   and energy for the life of the contract. W'hen&#13;
of the IPP and thus the incentive for the op-   this guarantee covers the entire projected out-&#13;
erators to be efficient. If the IPP is one of the    put of the plant. the 11'1' has an assLired market&#13;
lowest-cost generators. it should be used as   that it cannot lose without compensation. but&#13;
much as possible. A honus pavment for avail-  it also cannot increase its market share. Under&#13;
abilitv a;bove the target can be used aIS an in-   this must-run contract. there is no issue of eco-&#13;
centive for higher production. Similarly, if the    nomic dispatc h for the plant even when other&#13;
price for capacitv allows an IPP to earn an eco-   plants have lower costs. The subsequent entrv&#13;
nomic return on capital at a capacity utiliza-   of additional IPPs, each with a long-term con-&#13;
tion below the target, penalties are needed to   tract, can compound this problem. The pur-&#13;
ensure that the IPP remains efficient. Recent   chaser must pay for any contracted output that&#13;
U.S. experience with IPPs shows that, in most   it does not take from the [PP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
This arrangement has three separate effects on    a true merit order. andc svstemwicle generation&#13;
the performance of the sector. First. there is no   costs co&lt;uld be Lunnecessarily high.&#13;
competitive pressiure for the IPP to lower costs.&#13;
so that efficient operation depends solely ont t/e   The use of bonuses and penalties for capacitv&#13;
profit motive. For costs that are indexed, the    availabilitv can lead to some competitive pres-&#13;
incentives to improve performance center on    sure between plants. If the IPP tries to increase&#13;
"beating the index" to benefit from the differ-   its market share by bidding a higher availabil-&#13;
ence. Second, dispatch can occur out of merit  ity (under the incentive of a bonus payment),&#13;
order, leading to the loss of a svstem's produc-   other generators may lose market share and&#13;
tive efficiencv. And third, the lack of competi-   respond by trving to reduce their capacity costs&#13;
tion for market share between the IPP andc other   so as to improve their availability. Dispatch&#13;
generators means that, even if operated effi-   based on economic costs, however, provides&#13;
cientlv, the IPP poses no threat to other genera-   no competitive incentives for the supply of en-&#13;
tors because it has no spare capacitv to capture   ergy. Because generators cannot bid market&#13;
their market share. In the United States. early   prices, but instead offer cost-related prices&#13;
PURPA' projects were of this kind, and the re-   determined at the outset of contracts. there is&#13;
sult was such problems as excess production of   no way for IPPs or for other generators to in-&#13;
off-peak energy, which the buying utility was   crease market share through price competition.&#13;
obligated to purchase. The IPP projects in the    Contracts that guarantee a "minimum take" be-&#13;
Philippines are on a take-or-pay basis, as is a   low normal capacity availability combine as-&#13;
project in Belize and another in Colombia.     pects of the must-run contract with those of an&#13;
economic dispatch contract. Economic dispatch&#13;
Economic dispatch                              is used in IPP contracts in Jamaica and the Do-&#13;
minican Republic, and a second project in the&#13;
The natural development from must-run contracts   Dominican Republic has take-or-pay for up to&#13;
has been to introduce economic dispatch. In these   130 megawatts (MW) of its 185-MW capacity.&#13;
contracts, capacity price is again related to avail-&#13;
ability, and the energy price is paid only for the   Generator trading&#13;
energy dispatched according to costs. The IPP&#13;
can declare its available capacity and thus can    Another step to improve efficiency is to allow&#13;
cover its capital costs, but it is not guaranteed    generators to trade in a market hasecd on eco-&#13;
energy sales. Under this form of contract. the    nomic dispatch. The contract prices for energy-&#13;
plants are dispatched according to their economic   are predeterminecd for all generators. but the&#13;
ranking. That is the main benefit of the arrange-   generators bid availability for the next period&#13;
ment. but it requires establishing an entity to de-   (typically the next day). The dispatch agency or&#13;
termine dispatch on a cost-related basis. Energy    power purchaser determines least-cost dtispatch&#13;
prices linked to a cost index, however, do not   on the basis of tie contract prices and announces&#13;
allow cost savings to be passed on to consumers   the schedule. Generators can then trade energy&#13;
or reflected in the prices that influence dispatch    among themselves. buying from lower-cost gen-&#13;
decisions. That is because this arrangement bases   erators not fully committed in dispatch to mceet&#13;
dispatch on the contractual energy costs, which   some of their contractual commitments.&#13;
relate to the initial settlement level and the xal-&#13;
ues of the indexes since the start of the contract.   Opportlnities for trade emerge when actual costs&#13;
If the initial costs (for example. the beat rate)   for energy are below the contract prices. The&#13;
were incorrectly estimatecd or if the ftuel prices   power purchaser is informed of such trades and&#13;
obtained by the IPP diverge from the index, the   adjusts the dispatch schedule while paying in&#13;
actual cost of generation can be quite different   accord with the original schedule. This system&#13;
from the cost taken into account for dispatch. In   lowers the total costs of generation, but once&#13;
this case, dispatch might not occur according to   again these benefits are not passed on to con-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
a                    Competitive Contracting for Privatelv Generated Power&#13;
suniers. because generator prices ire tiecd to the    Take-or-pay contracts. although attractive to pro-&#13;
cost index. The svstem can lead to competitive    ducers because thev remove demand risk.&#13;
pressure for generators to improve efficiency    achieve none of these benefits. Economic dis-&#13;
once actual costs start to diverge ftrom  the in-    patch contracts. possiblv coupled with mini-&#13;
dex. But it is complicated to operate because    mum-take provisions. can be designed to&#13;
the power purchaser must determine dispatch    provide incentives for the IPP to generate effi-&#13;
in advance and keep records of transactions be-    ciently and can ensure merit order dispatch on&#13;
tween companies. and generators need to have    indexed costs. Where dispatch is related to a&#13;
sophisticated svstems. Generator trading is usecd    predetermined cost index, however, there is no&#13;
in the reformed power sector in Chile.              competition between generators to sell energy.&#13;
But inc:luding a bonus in the capacity price struc-&#13;
Competitive pool                                    ture can create limited competition for the sale&#13;
of capacitv declaredl available. Generator trad-&#13;
The distinctive feature of competitive pools (as    ing can ensure that dispatch occurs on the basis&#13;
they exist in England and W'ales. Argentina. the    of actual costs. Where these costs are likely to&#13;
ELEX pool in New South Wales, and, to a limited    diverge substantiallv from the cost indexes used&#13;
extent. Norwav) is that pricesfor energD  are bid   in the IPP contract. generator trading can be an&#13;
rather than related to costs hv ia jbrmzlda. That    attractive option if there are enough generators&#13;
allows prices to be lowered when there is real   to create a true market and a pool of suitably&#13;
competition, as generators struggle to increase    qualified managers to operate the system.&#13;
or to hold onto their market shares. Generators&#13;
bid their capacity availability and their offered    Full competition through an open pool is suit-&#13;
energy price. The pool operator then determines    able only for large, mature systems with spare&#13;
economic dispatch and pays for energy on the    capacity. Even in the system  in England and&#13;
basis of marginal bid prices and for capacity on    Wales, generators have taken several years to&#13;
This series is published    the basis of declared availability and a formula   learn how to benefit fully from the complexi-&#13;
to share ideas and invite  that gives signals for long-term  investment. In    ties caused by rapid changes in prices. These&#13;
discussion. It covers&#13;
finncuiaand prIvatcer  pinnciple, this system can be highly efficient in    prices sometimes have been too high because&#13;
sector development as    producing the lower consumer prices associated    the two dominant generators have taken ad-&#13;
well as industry and  with competition. But experience in the svstem    vantage of their market power. restricting the&#13;
energy. The views         cmeiin             xeine            sse&#13;
expressed are those of   in England ancd Wales suggests that there are manv    capacity offerecd to the market to drive Up the&#13;
the authors and are not    problems associated with setting up and rinning    price of available capacity.&#13;
intended to represent  such a pool. This demandling system is probablv&#13;
an official statement of&#13;
Bank policy or strategy.   teasible only for a sizable market with several    Among developing countries. only the largest&#13;
generators ancd sophisticated management.           can expect to establish systems that bring the&#13;
Comments are welcome.                                                    benefits of true competition such as a competi-&#13;
Please call the FPD                                                                       optiin&#13;
Nore line to leave a  Conclusion                                         tive power pool or generator trading. Countries&#13;
message (202-458-11 11)                                                  with small power svstems (about 90 have less&#13;
or contact Suzanne   IntrodUcing independent power prodlucers in a    than 500 NMW) that are growing slowly could&#13;
Smith, editor. Room'I                                                                                 He,thnedo&#13;
G8105, The World Bank,   power svstem w here existing generators are in-    introduce [PPs only slowlv. Here, the need to&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,   efficient can bring about more efficient invest-    provide low clemancd risk to potential investors&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,   rnent. htr it is not sufficient to achieve the    (to compensate for the other risks ofdoing bLisi-&#13;
or Internet address&#13;
ssmithM@worldbank.org.   operating benefits of cotmpetition. fower and    ness in unfamiliar markets) suggests using long-&#13;
energy sales contracts are crucial to ensuring    term contracts that are carefully designed.&#13;
iDPrinted on recycled  efficient operation of the [PPs. true merit order&#13;
paper.               dispatch to achieve least-cost generation with       PIURtPA is lPublic Utilitv Regulatorv Poliues Act (1978).&#13;
current operating practices, and competition&#13;
among generators to ensure efficient operating    Robert Bacon, Industry and Energy Depatment&#13;
practices throughout the sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441655">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/05/441655/competitive-contracting-privately-generated-power-absence-competition-market
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/05/441655/competitive-contracting-privately-generated-power-absence-competition-market</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/05/441655/competitive-contracting-privately-generated-power-absence-competition-market</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980312102655/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980312102655/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1995-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>1999-08-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Competitive contracting for privately
            generated power - what to do in the absence of competition
            in the market
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Introducing independent power producers
            (IPPs) into a power system where existing generators are
            inefficient can deliver more efficient investment. But it is
            not sufficient to achieve the operating benefits of
            competition. Key to determining whether or not the IPPs and
            the system as a whole will operate efficiently are the power
            and energy sales contracts with the IPPs. The author surveys
            a range of power purchase agreements and highlights their
            risks and benefits for operational efficiency.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Competitive contracting for privately
            generated power - what to do in the absence of competition
            in the market
        </docna>
        <display_title>Competitive contracting for
            privately generated power - what to do in the absence of
            competition in the market</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1995/05/441655/competitive-contracting-privately-generated-power-absence-competition-market</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Markets and Market Access,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Power &amp; Energy Conversion,Access to Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Energy,International Economics and Trade,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Bacon, Robert</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980312102655</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Distribution &amp; Transmission</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 47</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Energy,International Economics and Trade,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Denationalization; Power distribution; Power
            generation; Electric power generation; Electric utilities;
            Purchase transactions; Energy industries; Energy supply;
            Energy prices; Market competition
            bidding,consumer price index,consumer
            prices,consumers,contractual arrangements,cost indexes,cost
            savings,energy costs,Energy Department,energy
            price,Generator,heat,indexation,market power,market
            share,marketing,potential investors,power sector
            reform,power system,price competition,profit
            motive,sales,sales agreements,suppliers,total costs
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>16906</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems Technologies and Operations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Thermal Power Generation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>