<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank         FPD Note No. 7                                            May 1994&#13;
Is Privatization Necessary?&#13;
John Nellis&#13;
The answer is a decided 'j'es. " Privatiz-  * The owner instructs management to&#13;
ation is necessary, and not simply to  follow the signals provided by the&#13;
improve the performance of public    market and gives it the autonomy to&#13;
enterprises-though the evidence is   do so.&#13;
striking that it can and does improve    * Management is rewarded and sanc-&#13;
performance. Privatization's essential    tioned on the basis of performance.&#13;
contributions are to "lock in the gains"&#13;
achieved earlier in reforming public    Evidence shows that the theory does&#13;
ownership or in preparing afirm for    indeed apply in practice-with two&#13;
sale, to distance the firm from the polit-  crucial qualifications. First, the full set&#13;
ical process, and to inoculate it against of necessary conditions is only rarely&#13;
the recurrence of the common and   met. And second, even when it is met,&#13;
deadly ailment ofpublic enterprises:   it tends to stay met for only a while;&#13;
interference by owners who have more  the necessary conditions cannot be&#13;
than profit on their minds.        made to endure.&#13;
Performance and ownership-         Principal and agents&#13;
the debate                         There are a number of modern amend-&#13;
ments to neoclassical reasoning that&#13;
Marketforces                       attempt to establish a clearer relation-&#13;
Neoclassical economic theory suggests  ship between ownership and efficien-&#13;
that the relationship between owner-   cy. These come mainly from public&#13;
ship and performance is tenuous; effi-   choice theory and the literature on&#13;
ciency is seen mainly as a function of   principal and agents. Operationally,&#13;
market and incentive structures. In  this reasoning says that private owner-&#13;
theory, it makes little difference whether  ship will produce superior efficiency&#13;
a firm is privately or publicly owned as  outcomes because of five factors:&#13;
long as:&#13;
o Private ownership establishes a&#13;
It operates in a competitive or con-  marketfor managers, leading to&#13;
testable market without barriers to  higher-quality management.&#13;
entry or, just as important, barriers    * Capital markets subject privately&#13;
to exit.                           ownedfirms to greater scrutiny and&#13;
= i)  Private Sector Development Department&#13;
0-FPD    Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
discipline than they do public enterprises. Public  mutual obligations and responsibilities of the princi-&#13;
enterprises often operate on Janos Kornai's fa-   pal and the agent; or the owner could constitute and&#13;
mous "soft budget constraint." Because of explicit  empower a new and more independent board of&#13;
or implicit guarantees from the state, public enter-  directors and give it explicit instructions to maximize&#13;
prises can borrow capital at less-than-market inter-  commercial profitability; or the owner could name a&#13;
est rates, and they often enjoy outright subsidies    powerful and independent chief executive officer,&#13;
and other concessions from the state (meaning     and give him or her a free hand. The fifth factor-&#13;
that they don't pay their taxes, their utility bills,  better representation of the interests of capital-is&#13;
their accounts payable to other public enterprises,   more difficult to resolve without some change in&#13;
customs duties, or the like).                     ownership, or at least some privatization of manage-&#13;
* Private firms are subject to exit much more often    ment-through management contracts, leases, fran-&#13;
than public enterprises. Private firms are more   chises, or concessions. But even here performance&#13;
subject to bankruptcy, liquidation, hostile take-  agreements and other mechanisms to create surro-&#13;
over, and closure than public corporations. When   gate capitalists are imaginable: for example, estab-&#13;
exit is a real possibility, there is a greater likeli-    lishing a holding company or companies and&#13;
hood that owners and managers will take active,    instructing them to act like private owners, or frag-&#13;
efficiency-enhancing measures to avoid it.        menting ownership among several different levels of&#13;
* Politicians interfere less in the affairs ofprivate  government or state agencies and making them de-&#13;
than public firms. Political interference is a major   pendent on the income generated by the enterprise.&#13;
cause of efficiency-reducing conditions in public    Both institutional approaches would presumably&#13;
enterprises; it manifests itself in overstaffing, un-    diminish the saliency of noncommercial objectives.&#13;
dercapitalization, inappropriate plant location,&#13;
wrong use of inputs, and many other costly acts.    Tried and tested?&#13;
* Private firms are supervised by self-interested   All of these theoretically applicable solutions have&#13;
board members and sharebolders, rather than by   indeed been tried, or are presently being tried,&#13;
disinterested bureaucrats, and are thus more likely  around the world-with some highly positive re-&#13;
than public firms to use capital efficiently and to    sponses. New Zealand's "corporatization" efforts of&#13;
maintain it.                                     the mid-1980s achieved efficiency and financial gains&#13;
in ten of eleven enterprises studied by Duncan and&#13;
Practical solutions                                 Bollard in Corporatization and Privatization:&#13;
The problem with all five of these arguments is that   Lessons from. New Zealand.' Korea's performance&#13;
one can readily conceive of mechanisms to correct    evaluation system for twenty-six of its government&#13;
the perceived deficiency-without changing owner-  invested enterprises reduced, for a time, financial&#13;
ship. For example, if finding and rewarding excel-    losses to zero. These financial gains were accompa-&#13;
lent managers is the issue, enterprises could recruit   nied by a declining ratio of costs to sales, indicating&#13;
outside the public sector, or even internationally,  efficiency gains. Korea's reform program relied&#13;
and offer incentive packages equal to private sector   heavily on a goal setting and review system-com-&#13;
scales. If the soft budget constraint is the problem,  plete with rewards-and a massive change in the&#13;
governments could eliminate all guarantees and stip-  boards of directors that reduced civil servant mem-&#13;
ulate that public enterprises must turn to commercial  bership to a small minority.&#13;
capital markets and act, and be treated, like any&#13;
private sector borrower. If exit is the constraint, gov-  The most powerful recent empirical evidence to sup-&#13;
ernments could liquidate persistently poorly per-   port the thesis that reform can work without owner-&#13;
forming public enterprises. if political interference  ship change comes from China. There are now about&#13;
is the dilficulty, then the owner and the enterprise  1.3 million township and village enterprises employ-&#13;
could sign a performance contract specifying the    ing 90 million people. They account for more than 20&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
percent of China's industrial production and are  That leaves a variance to explain-and ownership is&#13;
growing far more rapidly than the traditional state-    a strong candidate for a good part of the explana-&#13;
owned enterprise (SOE) sector. Their financial and    tion.&#13;
economic performance surpasses that of the tradi-&#13;
tional SOEs by two or even three times. They are a    Empirical work&#13;
stunning example of how positive performance can    The second strand of the argument is empirical. It is&#13;
be achieved by firms that are not privately owned-   based on several recent and rigorous studies that&#13;
but that are made to act as if they were.         have looked at firms before and after privatization.&#13;
These recent studies show generally, and impres-&#13;
Added to these positive cases are the findings of a    sively, improved performance after sale. A Journal of&#13;
fairly extensive literature, most of it dating from the   Finance article2-by Megginson, Nash, and van Ran-&#13;
early 1980s, that tried to measure public versus pri-   denborgh-compares the pre- and postprivatization&#13;
vate performance. This was done basically on a    financial and operating performance of sixty-one&#13;
"with and without" basis; that is, comparisons were   companies from eighteen countries in thirty-two&#13;
between roughly similar public and private enter-    industrial sectors. The study shows strong postsale&#13;
prises in operation. The conclusions reached were    performance-increased real sales, greater profitabil-&#13;
by no means unanimous, but more often than not    ity, increased investment spending, improvements in&#13;
the literature suggested that, after correcting for mar-  operating efficiency, and, most surprising, a slight&#13;
ket structure, there are no real differences between   increase in work forces.&#13;
public and private ownership. The policy implica-&#13;
tion is that perceived deficiencies of public enter-  A second study, on the welfare consequences of&#13;
prise performance can be corrected by changes in    selling public enterprises,3 was conducted by the&#13;
policy, incentives, and institutions, and that owner-   World Bank in collaboration with Boston University&#13;
ship change is not necessary.                     economists. This study looked at pre- and postsale&#13;
performance in profitability and productivity in&#13;
In light of all this, how can one still reasonably con-  twelve firms in four countries. It went on to construct&#13;
tend that ownership matters?                      an elaborate counterfactual, to determine what&#13;
would have happened had the enterprises not been&#13;
Why ownership matters                             privatized. The authors then were able to say "here&#13;
is what was actually happening before sale, here is&#13;
Probability                                       what actually happened after the sale, here is what&#13;
The first strand of the case is probabilistic in nature.  we reason would have happened under continued&#13;
While private firms do not always outperform pub-   government ownership." In constructing this scenar-&#13;
lic enterprises, the evidence shows that they usually  io, they did their best to isolate and neutralize the&#13;
do. For example, over the years, the World Bank   gains and losses due to factors other than divesti-&#13;
has noted that rates of return on equity invested in  ture. They then subtracted the hypothetical from the&#13;
industrial or commercial public enterprises often  historical, and thus derived a measure of the gains&#13;
are about a third of those in the country's industrial  due to ownership change. This study quantifies the&#13;
private sector. The overall contention is that there    welfare gains and losses of the various actors in the&#13;
are two spectra of performance from good to bad-  process; that is, the cosrs and benefits to the selling&#13;
one for public enterprises, one for private firms.  governments, purchasers-domestic and foreign-&#13;
There is a fair degree of overlap between the two.   workers, consumers, and competitors. The results&#13;
But the private sector performance spectrum ex-   are as follows: in eleven of twelve cases studied,&#13;
tends somewhat to the right of the public enterprise  there were positive welfare effects for society be-&#13;
performance spectrum-and mean performance for  cause of the sale, and improved performance at the&#13;
private enterprises is also somewhere to the right.    level of the firm.4&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Compromise and backsliding                                  cial over noncommercial aims, the results are, as we&#13;
The third and final strand of the argument for pri-         have seen in China, very good. But they tend not to&#13;
vate ownership is political and organizational in           last. In most instances there is pronounced backslid-&#13;
character. The idea is twofold. First, as noted, most   ing. The common story is that bad times make for&#13;
governments find it difficult if not impossible to          good policies-in crises governments do establish&#13;
apply the entire package of qualifying conditions           the precedence of commercial objectives, they do&#13;
that are essential for reforms short of ownership           impose a harder budget constraint, and they do give&#13;
change to work. The landscape, particularly in              autonomy to public enterprise managers to achieve&#13;
developing countries, and now in ex-socialist coun-   commercial aims. But again and again, when the&#13;
tries as well, is littered with partial attempts to im-    crisis fades, or when the regime changes, or when&#13;
pose reform where the government owners hadn't    some major political claim arises, commitment to the&#13;
the will or the fortitude or the knowledge or the           priority of commercial aims and to noninterference&#13;
capacity or the luck to impose the whole of the             in day-to-day management of the firm fades with it.&#13;
reform package-and the results were minimal,                Examples of backsliding include the New Zealand&#13;
modest, or nonexistent.                                     Post Office, the Japanese National Railway, Pakistan&#13;
public industrial enterprises, and some of the&#13;
There are innumerable examples in which govern-             Korean government invested enterprises.&#13;
ment owners kept prices for the products of suppos-&#13;
edly reforrmed public enterprises too low to cover          Conclusion&#13;
costs, out of fear of the political consequences of         Based on this reasoning and evidence, it is clear that&#13;
price increases. Governments may shut off direct            ownership matters-that it is a significant determinant&#13;
budget flows to public enterprises, but few then go    of the profitability and productivity of an enterprise.&#13;
on to block concessionary transfers from the bank-    Political and organizational factors are fundamental to&#13;
ing system. Governments grant operational autono-    the reason why. Ultimately, as Oliver Williamson is&#13;
my to managers, but not with regard to hiring and           fond of saying, "politics trumps economics."&#13;
firing, or plant location, or from whom to obtain&#13;
inputs. Technically innocuous board of director re-          Ian Duncan and Alan Bollard, Corporatization and Privatization:&#13;
forms have been halted in Kenya, Morocco, and                Lessonsfrom New Zealand (Auckland: Oxford University Press, 1992).&#13;
elsewhere because board membership is a lucrative    2 William L. Megginson, Robert C. Nash, and Matthias von Randenborgh.&#13;
"The Financial and Operating Performance of Newly Privatized Firms:&#13;
core part of the patronage system. The list is end-          An International Empirical Analysis," Journal of Finance 49(2): 403--52&#13;
less, and the point is obvious: most governments             (1994).&#13;
have noneconomic objectives for their public enter-          Ahmed Galal, Leroy Jones, Pankaj Tandon, and Ingo Vogelsang,&#13;
'rise systems. While they want them to be profitable    Welfare Consequences of Selling Public Enterprises: An Empirical&#13;
prise systems. Whlle they want them to be profitable    Analysis (New York: Oxford University Press, 1994).&#13;
and productive, they are most often unwilling or             There is much else that is striking in this study. For example, it shows&#13;
incapable of allowing these commercial aims to take    clearly that policy matters as well as ownership, that macroeconomic&#13;
clear precedence over the noncommercial. Thus,               liberalization in conjunction with privatization is a powerful combina-&#13;
tion, and that effective regulation must accompany (preferably pre-&#13;
their reformn efforts tend to be partial.                    cede) the privatization of infrastructure firms if divestiture is to yield its&#13;
full potential.&#13;
Second, in the few cases in which governments do&#13;
establish and maintain the precedence of commer-    John Nellis, Manager, Private Sector Development&#13;
This series is published to share ideas and invite discussion. It covers financial and private sector development as well as&#13;
industry and energy. The views expressed are those of the authors and are not intended to represent an official statement of&#13;
Bank policy or strategy. 63 Printed on recycled paper.&#13;
Comments are welcome. Please call the FPD Note line to leave a message: 202-458-1111; or contact Suzanne Smith, editor, Room&#13;
G8105, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC 20433, or Internet address ssmith7@worldbank.org.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441654">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/05/441654/privatization-necessary
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/05/441654/privatization-necessary</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1994/05/441654/privatization-necessary</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980312102723/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980312102723/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-05-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1994-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Is privatization necessary?
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Is privatization necessary? The author
            argues that privatization is necesary. Not only do privately
            owned firms usually outperform public enterprises, but
            privatization is the only way to "inoculate" a
            company against political interference. While governments
            may want public enterprises to be profitable and productive,
            they often are unwilling to allow commercial aims to take
            precedence over noncommercial aims.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Is privatization necessary?
        </docna>
        <display_title>Is privatization necessary?</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1994/05/441654/privatization-necessary</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Microfinance,Small Scale Enterprise,Municipal Financial Management,Private Participation in Infrastructure,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Industry,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Nellis, John</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980312102723</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Privatization-DV</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 7,FPD note no. 7</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Industry,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Private Sector Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Denationalization; Public enterprises;
            Capital markets; Private ownership
            autonomy,bankruptcy,boards of
            directors,Capital
            markets,company,competitors,corporations,corporatization,firms,industrial
            enterprises,investment spending,liquidation,operating
            efficiency,private
            enterprises,privatization,productivity,profitability,public
            enterprises,return on equity
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>16951</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Soft Budget Constraints</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>