<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>* ~~~1S1q7&#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 145                                                                                  June 1998&#13;
Promoting Regional Power Trade-&#13;
The Southern African Power Pool&#13;
Donial T          The Southern African Power Pool (SAPP), the first formal international pool to be set up outside&#13;
Jean-Pierre       North America and Western Europe, was inaugurated in 1995. While the utilities of southern Africa&#13;
Charpentier,      have been importing and exporting electricity for four decades, these trades occurred through&#13;
and Diane         bilateral contracts that were complex and often difficult to administer. The objective of shifting&#13;
Minogute&#13;
to the pool is to create a more efficient regional market. Although physically the pool is still&#13;
embryonic and trade volumes average roughly 3 percent of production, confidence in the market&#13;
and mutual trust between the members are being strengthened and sector coordination is&#13;
dramatically improved. This Note reviews the factors that have eased the way for the pool agree-&#13;
ments and the challenges that remain in getting the multilateral trading operation under way.&#13;
FIGURE 1 SOUTHERN AFRICAN POWER POOL                      Power exchange first arose because of the dis-&#13;
tribution of power sources in the region: a large&#13;
reserve of low-cost hydroelectricity in the north-&#13;
ern part (especially the Inga Reservoir in the&#13;
Democratic Republic of Congo and the Cahora-&#13;
-   DEMOCRATIC  - . . .s.    -  i            Bassa Reservoir in Mozambique), large reserves&#13;
REPUBLUiC        ,  -                       of cheap coal in South Africa, and the Kariba&#13;
OF CONGO        -                           Dam (on the border between Zambia and Zim-&#13;
L'_.g; az-f Z.7''.;&gt;'-"i,'' babwe), which, being in the middle of the re-&#13;
gional system, can play the "buffer" role. As the&#13;
*J .   t   . &lt;  MALAWI   network has been reinforced and extended,&#13;
MALAWI&#13;
many arrangements have arisen for the sale and&#13;
,, t- - ) - ;MOZAMBIQUE  wheeling of electrical power between countries&#13;
in the region.&#13;
The new pool agreement covers about 9 million&#13;
NAMIBIA   I   ZIMBABWE                            square kilometers and 200 million people. The&#13;
Cahora Bassa         number of customers of the interconnected na-&#13;
tional systems has been estimated at more than&#13;
4.1 million, though this figure understates the to-&#13;
tal number of retail customers because some of&#13;
AF PWRWA L  ~-                           the customers are distribution companies.&#13;
\             2 ~~~~~SWAZILAND&#13;
The SAPP members agreed to develop their&#13;
LESOTHO      -Existing or planned   pooling operations as a "loose pool" along the&#13;
power lines    lines of NORDEL/NordPool (Scandinavia),&#13;
The World Bank Group   Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Promoting Regional Power Trade-The Southern African Power Pool&#13;
SAPP members and   UCPTE (Western Europe), and such U.S. pools   inaugurated after the Inter-Governmental&#13;
their utilities    as the Midcontinent Area Power Pool before the    Memorandum of Understanding was signed by&#13;
Angola              1996 restructuring of the U.S. electricity market.   a majority of the SADC members. The memo-&#13;
Empresa            Loose pools emphasize the constant exchange    randum  of understanding and its subsidiary&#13;
National de        of information in order to maximize both the    agreements-the Inter-Utility Memorandum of&#13;
Electricidade (ENE)  economic and reliability benefits from trading    Understanding, the Agreement Between Oper-&#13;
and system autonomy. These pools do not use    ating Members, and the Operating Guidelines&#13;
Botswana&#13;
Botuwana Power     central dispatch of power plants, often relying    -have now been signed by all the SADC mem-&#13;
Corporation (BPC)  instead on long-term bilateral contracts for elec-   bers and their national power utilities.&#13;
tricity supply between generators and custom-&#13;
Democratic         ers. These contracts are supplenejented witlh   The SAPP agreeirmeniLs state that the pturpose of&#13;
Republic of Congo  short-term contracts and other deals under the   the pool is to allow its members to coordinate&#13;
Societe Nationale  overall agreement. Loose pools may provide cen-   the planning and operation of their systems&#13;
cldElectricitt (SNELI    tral services, however, including producing con-   while maintaining reliability, autonomy, and self&#13;
Lesotho            tinuous, real-time data to match generation and    sufficiency, and to share in the benefits of oper-&#13;
Lesotho Electricity  demand, developing indicative expansion plans,   ating the pool. The agreements incorporate the&#13;
Commission (LEC)   and implementing emergency procedures. Loose    SADC treaty, the SADC Dispute Resolution Tri-&#13;
Malawi             pools also establish detailed common design and    bunal, the SADC energy ministers, and the Tech-&#13;
Malawi Electricity  operational standards to ensure system security    nical and Administrative Unit. The Inter-&#13;
Supply Commission  and reliability and to facilitate trades.        Governmental Mnemorandum of Understanding&#13;
(ESCOM)                                                             establishes that the SAPP agreements must be&#13;
In the SAPP full membership is limited to the   interpreted in a manner consistent with the SADC&#13;
Moztaim.biqued     national utilities. Most are still vertically inte-   treaty and that the final and binding dispute reso-&#13;
Electricidade de&#13;
Mozambique (EDM)   grated, with a primary mandate of ensuring the   lution forum is the SADC Dispute Resolution&#13;
autonomy and self-sufficiency of the domestic    Tribunal. The energy ministers are responsible&#13;
Namibia            system. The benefits of the pool include reduc-   for resolving major policy issues in the SAPP&#13;
Namibia Power      tions or postponements in new requirements   and for admitting new members to the pool.&#13;
(NAMPOWER)         for generating capacity and reserves, reductions   The Technical and Administrative Unit provides&#13;
South Africa       in fuel costs, and more efficient use of hydro-   secretariat and other services to the SAPP ex-&#13;
Electricity Supply  electricity. To estimate the potential gains, a    ecutive committee, acts as liaison to the SADC.,&#13;
Commission (ESKOM)   Southern African Development Community    and seeks funding according to the recommen-&#13;
(SADC) electric po-wer study conducted in 1990-   dations of the executive committee.&#13;
Swaziland Electricity    92 compared the costs of integrated regional&#13;
(SEB)              development with those of independent de-   The SAPP is organized under the executive&#13;
velopment, in which each country follows a    committee, which acts as the board of direc-&#13;
Tanzania           strategy of self-sufficiency. The study showed   tors of the pool, and a management commit-&#13;
Tanzania Electricity  savings of USS785 million (1992 prices), or 20   tee, which oversees the administration of the&#13;
Supply Company     percent, over 1995-2010. Because the Demo-   pool. Three subcommittees serve under the&#13;
ITANESCD)          cratic Republic of Congo and South Africa were    direction of the management committee: the&#13;
Zambia             not members of the SADC at the time of the    planning subcommittee (which focuses on re-&#13;
Zambian Electricity  study, the comparison did not include their sys-   viewing wheeling rates annually and develop-&#13;
Supply Corporation  tem expansion plans, though it did account for   ing an indicative SAPP expansion plan every&#13;
(ZESCO)            energy trade opportunities. Including these two    two years), the operating subcommittee and&#13;
Zimbabwe           countries boosts the benefits significantly.     its associated coordination center, and the en-&#13;
Zimbabwe Electricity                                                vironmental subcommittee. The coordination&#13;
SupplyAuthority    The agreements                                   center, which is still being set up, will be re-&#13;
(ZESA)                                                              sponsible for such tasks as undertaking most&#13;
The Southern African Power Pool is based on    pool monitoring activities, carrying out oper-&#13;
agreements rather than on law. The pool was    ating and planning studies, determining trans-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
fer limits on tie-lines, administering a regional   ner (South Africa) act as a driver, encouraging&#13;
database, disseminating maintenance sched-   more passive parties.&#13;
ules, providing technical advice, and seeking&#13;
funding for its needs.                        The experience of the SAPP shows that in mov-&#13;
ing from pool agreements to implementation, it&#13;
Each member must meet its Accredited Capac-   is possible for some participants to move in&#13;
ity Obligation, a requirement that each utility   smaller, incremental steps toward the overall goals&#13;
have sufficient capacity to cover the forecast   set bv the agreements. While all participants must&#13;
monthly peak. Each member is also obligated   take consistent steps, they do not need to move&#13;
to supply emergency energy for up to six hours,   at the same pace. And while all participants have&#13;
to provide automatic generation control and    agreed to an international pool, it is reasonable&#13;
other facilities in its control area. to allow    to expect that self-sufficiency and autonomy will&#13;
wheeling through its system where technically   remain the priority for some members, at least&#13;
and economically feasible, to submit mainte-   through the first phase of operations. The pool&#13;
nance schedules, to disclose information and    agreements include provisions that recognize&#13;
costs related to thermal generating facilities,  these concerns while also encouraging greater&#13;
and to contribute toward the center's costs.  integration, for example, by permitting members&#13;
to meet their Accredited Capacity Obligation&#13;
A key element in the operation of the pool is  through a contract with another member. Not all&#13;
the SAPP pricing arrangement, set out in thir-   countries prefer such a gradualist approach, how-&#13;
teen detailed schedules in the operating agree-   ever: Botswana, Mozambique, and Namibia have&#13;
ment. These schedules cover four broad types   opted to rely more on importing power than on&#13;
of transaction: firm power contracts of varying   building new capacity. Regardless of the preferred&#13;
duration; nonfirm power contracts of varving    path, it is essential to set pool governance rules&#13;
duration: mutual support contracts such as op-   so that all members, large and small, perceive&#13;
erating reserve, emergency energy. and con-   that they have a voice.&#13;
trol area services; and scheduled outage energy,&#13;
energy banking, and wheeling.                 As national regulatory agencies develop and be-&#13;
gin to assert their authority there is a risk that&#13;
Implementation                                they might not be sufficiently attuned to the&#13;
needs of the regional market. Experience in other&#13;
Three major factors played a key part in the   countries shows that although a pool can oper-&#13;
development of the regional pool agreements:   ate where regulatory regimes differ, as they do&#13;
the availability of complementary power sources,   among SAPP countries, possibilities for gaming&#13;
an active regional organization for economic co-   or unfair advantage created by differences in&#13;
operation, and the political will to support in   regulatory systems can undermine members'&#13;
creased regional energy trade. The Southern   willingness to participate. So national-level regu-&#13;
African Development Community and its pre-   latory statutes should be carefully drafted so that&#13;
decessor, the Southern African Development Co-   the agency jurisdictions are properly defined,&#13;
ordination Conference, served as a focal point   directed and restrained in order to avoid regu-&#13;
for the promotion of regional integration, facili-  latorv obstacles to trade. There should also be&#13;
tating investment in projects (such as intercon-   periodic reviews of regulatory compatibility as&#13;
nection projects) that allowed increased regional   the SAPP develops. In addition, the need for a&#13;
power trade. The momenitum for regional inte-   consistenit approachi to t-ansiimission access is&#13;
gration, including increased power trade, was   becoming apparent as more independent power&#13;
further strengthened by the emergence of more   producers (IPPs) and independent transmission&#13;
democratic governments in several countries and    projects (ITPs) express interest in investing in&#13;
the cessation of hostilities in others. Also help-   the region. So far only Zambia has required its&#13;
ful has been having at least one country or part-   regulator to take into account SAPP interests.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Promoting Regional Power Trade-The Southern African Power Pool&#13;
A review of the SAPP's first year of operation    Fourth, to allow efficient operation of the pool&#13;
showvXs that several important practical issues    and encourage an IPP presence, all the SAPP&#13;
need to be addressed to support the develop-    utilities should unbundle their domestic trans-&#13;
ment of the pool. First, the power utilities in    mission pricing and ensure members adopt&#13;
each country need to be put on a more viable   identical rules to set transmission costs. In ad-&#13;
financial footing to ensure that they are credit-    dition, a study is needed to assess the effects&#13;
worthy and able to respond to commercial in-    on pool development of transmission pricing&#13;
centives for trading power, including the ability    under the SAPP and current national pricing&#13;
to generate foreign exchange. Toward this end,    policies.&#13;
commercialization programs are under way or&#13;
under consideration at half the utilities (EDM,    Fifth, SAPP members need to estimate and meet&#13;
ENE, ESCOM, ESKOM, ZESA, and ZESCO). Most   financing requirements for operations and new&#13;
advanced in power system  reform  are South    generation and transmission projects. In identi-&#13;
Africa and Zambia.                                  fying potential new projects, they should use&#13;
compatible generation and transmission plan-&#13;
Second, the SAPP members need to reach agree-    ning software that explicitly allows for risk analy-&#13;
ment on the design and staffing of the coordi-   sis and for dealing with hydrological uncertainty.&#13;
nation center, a politically challenging task, so&#13;
that the center can become operational. The key    Sixth, SAPP members need to harmonize&#13;
steps are deciding on a neutral location; select-    ESKOM's internal competitive generators pool&#13;
Viewvpoint is an open&#13;
forum intended to    ing a neutral manager with sufficient autonomy;    with the SAPP cooperative pool. The internal&#13;
encourage dissemina-  establishing a legal status; defining clear gover-    pool, set up in 1996, is based on the England&#13;
tion of and debate on  nance rules; setting guidelines for the interface    and Wales model and currently does not pro-&#13;
best prictvcesfor exa  between the center, SAPP members, and the    vide for access to third party operators. SAPP&#13;
panding the pnivate  SADC; identifying equipment needs, especially    members also need to address the risk that the&#13;
sector. The views pub-    computer hardware and software; training op-    different triggers for capacity addition (price&#13;
lished aire those of the&#13;
authors and should not    erators; twinning with a mature pool to develop    signals for the internal pool and a planned ap-&#13;
be attributed to the  skills; and developing a realistic budget. By the    proach for the other SAPP members) could lead&#13;
World Bank or any of  end of the first year SAPP members had made    to suboptimal investment.&#13;
its affiliated organiza-&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the    progress on only a few  of these issues. They&#13;
conclusions represent    had agreed to establish the center in Harare,    Finally, because the SAPP establishes a largely&#13;
official policy of the  Zimbabwe, separate from  ZESA, and had ad-    self-governing regime at the operating level,&#13;
World asak or of ts  vertised for a manager. The operating subcom-    and as experience in Argentina, Europe, and&#13;
or the countries they  mittee had drafted a constitution that was being    North America shows, members will need to&#13;
represent.          finalized. And training programs for operators    quickly set up an effective dispute resolution&#13;
To order additional  had been offered, with more under preparation.    process. Clear resolution procedures combined&#13;
copies p ease call                                                       with realistic enforcement could also help in&#13;
202-458-1111 or contact   Third, the pool would benefit from broadening    attracting new generation and minimizing na-&#13;
Room  ih-188,       its membership to include existing institutions    tional self-sufficiency concerns.&#13;
The World Bank,      that control or influence significant generation&#13;
Washington, NW,      or transmission, such as Hidroelectrica de Cahora    This Note draws heavily from Suipporting the Implementation of the&#13;
or Internet address  Bassa, the Copperbelt Energy Consortium, the    SonternAifncanPowerPool, forthcomingasanvorldB&#13;
ssmith7tBworldbank.org.   new private owner of the Power Division of the    cat Paper (Washington, D.C.).&#13;
The series is also   Zambia Consolidated Copper Mining Company,&#13;
available on-linieDoaTOLay(cretywkigih&#13;
lwww.v orldbank.org/  and the Zambezi River Authority. But this will   Donal T 0 Leary, (currently working with&#13;
html/fpd/notes/      mean developing procedures (voting rules) to    Siemens AG under the World Bank Staff&#13;
notelist.html).      give voice to and account for the interests of   Exchange Program), Jean-Pierre Charpentier,&#13;
(® Printed on recycled    these players as well as other new entrants, such    and Diane MIinogue, Energy Markets and&#13;
paper.               as IPPs and ITPs.                                   Reform Thematic Group&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441756">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/06/441756/promoting-regional-power-trade-southern-african-power-pool
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/06/441756/promoting-regional-power-trade-southern-african-power-pool</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1998/06/441756/promoting-regional-power-trade-southern-african-power-pool</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980901110428/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980901110428/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1998-06-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>1999-08-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Promoting regional power trade - the
            Southern African power pool
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Southern African Power Pool (SAPP),
            the first formal international pool to be set outside North
            American and Western Europe, was inaugurated in 1995. While
            the utilities of southern Africa have been importing and
            exporting electricity for four decades, these trades
            occurred through bilateral contracts that were complex and
            often difficult to administer. The objective of shifting to
            the pool is to create a more efficient regional market.
            Although physically the pool is still embryonic and trade
            volumes average roughly 3 percent of production, confidence
            in the market and mutual trust between the members are being
            strengthened and sector coordination is dramatically
            improved. This Note reviews the factors that have eased the
            way for the pool agreements and the challenges that remain
            in getting the multilateral trading operation under way.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Promoting regional power trade - the
            Southern African power pool
        </docna>
        <display_title>Promoting regional power trade -
            the Southern African power pool</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1998/06/441756/promoting-regional-power-trade-southern-african-power-pool</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Energy Technology &amp; Transmission,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Power &amp; Energy Conversion,Energy Trade,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Energy,Environment</teratopic>
        <count>Tanzania,Namibia,South Africa,Swaziland,Africa,Lesotho,Botswana,Malawi,Zimbabwe,Zambia,Angola,Mozambique,Congo, Democratic Republic of</count>
        <authors>
            <author>O'Leary, Donal T.</author>
            <author>Charpentier, Jean-Pierre</author>
            <author>Minogue, Diane</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Central Africa!$!80454</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southern Africa!$!80472</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980901110428</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Distribution &amp; Transmission</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 145</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Energy,Environment</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Regional participation; Trade partners;
            Pooling systems; Power generation; Utilities; Electricity;
            Management operations; Problem identification
            autonomy,bilateral
            contracts,coal,distribution companies,efficient regional
            market,electrical power between
            countries,electricity,Electricity demand,Electricity
            Supply,Energy Markets,energy ministers,energy trade,foreign
            exchange,new entrants,power,power lines,power plants,power
            pool,power system,power utilities,producers,regional power
            trade,regulatory
            systems,savings,subsidiary,transmission,transmission
            costs,transmission pricing
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Central Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southern Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>18347</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems Technologies and Operations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Thermal Power Generation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Free Trade Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Preferential Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>WTO Accession</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Technology &amp; Transmission</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Democratic Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Agreements and Negotiations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>