<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 132                                                                           November 1997&#13;
Has Price Cap Regulation of U.K. Utilities&#13;
Been a Success?&#13;
Richard Green     Developing the approach-a proposal    scheme would concentrate consumer protec-&#13;
for BT                                     tion where it was most needed while giving&#13;
BT some freedom to change the balance of its&#13;
The privatization of British Telecom (BT) in   prices. The scheme would be simple for the&#13;
1984 reintroduced the regulation of private  regulator to monitor, and it wvould minimize&#13;
infrastructure companies in the United King-  the risk of regulatory capture because it would&#13;
dom, after nearly forty years of public owner-   be nondiscretionary. Above all, Littlechild&#13;
ship. Two regulatory approaches were initially   hoped that the scheme would be temporary,&#13;
proposed: controlling BT's prices by setting a   for competition is by far the most effective&#13;
maximum rate of return,' and imposing an   means of protection against monopoly. He&#13;
output-related profits levy on BT at a rate that  therefore recommended that the scheme be&#13;
would fall as the company's output rose, giv-   adopted for five years, and reviewed after four.&#13;
ing it an incentive to keep output high and&#13;
prices low.                                 A price cap for British Gas&#13;
Professor Stephen Littlechild, an academic who   A second price cap was adopted for British&#13;
later became the first regulator of the electricity   Gas when it was privatized in 1986. This price&#13;
industry, was asked to choose between the two   cap is based not on individual prices, but on&#13;
schemes. But instead he proposed a third, a price   the average revenue yield from sales to small&#13;
cap system that the government adopted.   consumers-the value of sales divided by the&#13;
Littlechild argued that a maximum rate of return   volume of gas sold. This formula gives the com-&#13;
would limit BT's incentives to operate efficiently,   pany more freedom to introduce new tariffs,&#13;
while the effect of an output-related profits levy   since there are no controls on individual prices&#13;
remained uncertain. Expecting increased com-   and no need to worry about the weights in a&#13;
petition in telecommunications, he pointed out   basket. (See tables 1 and 2 for a comparison of&#13;
that if BT faced a levy that its competitors did  the two types of price controls and traditional&#13;
not, it could be at a significant disadvantage.    rate-of-return regulation.)&#13;
Littlechild proposed an explicit limit on the   A second change is the pass-through of the&#13;
prices that BT could charge in the areas where   cost of gas purchases to consumers so that they,&#13;
it wvas expected to retain some monopoly   not British Gas, bear the risk of changes in the&#13;
power-line rentals and local call charges. The   wholesale gas price. This price is outside Brit-&#13;
weighted average of a basket of these charges   ish Gas's control. but accounts for nearly half&#13;
should fall in real terms by a specified amotint  its costs. The formula became known as RPI -&#13;
each year. This was equivalent to saving that  AT + i.A X denotes the expected productivity&#13;
the charges should not increase by more than   increase (2 percent a year), and Y the pass-&#13;
RPI -X, where RPI is the increase in the retail  through of the cost of gas. In the years after&#13;
price index (a standard measure of general in-   priv-atization, the cost of gas fell significantly,&#13;
flation in the United Kingdom) and X is the   and the benefits were passed straight on to&#13;
real reduction in prices. He argued that this   consumers.&#13;
The World Bank Group . Finance, Private Sector, and infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WNl                Has Price Cap Regulation of U.K. Utilities Been a Success?&#13;
A price cap for water seas practically impossible and a permanent&#13;
control would be fieeded. Indirect competition&#13;
Littlechild was consulted again when the water   in the form of yardstick regulation (advocated&#13;
industrE was prepared for privatization, in 1986.   by Shleifer 1985) Eas possible, however, and&#13;
The industry wtas required to complete a large    Littlechild recommended using comparisons&#13;
backlog of investments, and prices were ex-         between companies ahen setting and resettinl&#13;
pected to rise to finance them. Once again,   price controls. Because prices 'ere expected&#13;
Littlechild recommended a control on prices   to rise, the scheme became known as RPI + K,&#13;
rather than profits, although it was clear that   although it was really RPI - X + Q, where Q is&#13;
direct competition betpeen water companies   the cost of investdgent to meet qualit targets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Revision of the first price control           peal their proposals, the regulators have in-&#13;
creased the amount of information they release&#13;
In 1988, it became clear that BT did not face   and generally argue that they follow the "MMC&#13;
enough competition to abolish the price con-   methodology." If a company knows that the&#13;
trol, so the regulator proposed a new control.   commission is likely to use the same method-&#13;
For the first five years. BT had faced a control   ology as the regulator. it also knows that it has&#13;
of RPI - 3 on line rentals and directly dialed   little to gain from an appeal. The commission's&#13;
domestic calls, and a subsidiary price control   role has brought a welcome increase in trans-&#13;
that limited any increase in line rentals to 2   parency in the resetting of price controls.&#13;
percent a year in real terms.2 The regulator&#13;
proposed a new control, RPI - 4.5, which would    One-time reductions&#13;
also bring some operator senrices into the bas-&#13;
ket of controlled prices.                     When the early price controls were reset, only&#13;
the value of X was changed, so prices stayed&#13;
The regulator gave little information on this   on a smooth path. But in 1994, Littlechild faced&#13;
decision at the time, but later explained how    different needs in resetting the price controls&#13;
the new value of X had been chosen. His staff  for the distribution businesses owned by the&#13;
had built a financial model of BT (in consulta-   twelve regional electricity companies in England&#13;
tion with the company) so that they could pre-   and Wales. These companies, given RPI + X price&#13;
dict BT's profits and rate of return on capital,   controls wlhen they were privatized in 1990, had&#13;
given a value of X. In 1988, BT earned more   subsequently earned high profits, so a large re-&#13;
than its perceived cost of capital, so the regu-   duction in prices was clearlv required. But if&#13;
lator chose a value of X predicted to eliminate   only the value of X was to be changed, Littlechild&#13;
the excess return by the end of the price con-   faced a difficult choice. If he set X so that prices&#13;
trol period (set at four years). This approach   reached the "correct" level at the end of the&#13;
has much in common with the calculations used   period, the companies would continue to earn&#13;
in rate-of-return regulation, although the fixed   high profits for several years, an excessive re-&#13;
review period and the regulator's ability to dis-   ward for their earlier cost reductions.&#13;
regard excessive costs give the company a&#13;
greater incentive to be efficient and force it to   The alternative was to set prices so that the com-&#13;
bear more risks. BT accepted this control; if   panies would receive an appropriate amount of&#13;
the company had rejected it, the issue would   revenue over the period as a whole. If the prices&#13;
have been decided by the Monopolies and    declined evenly from the present level, how-&#13;
Mergers Commission (MMC), the United   ever, they would have to fall well below their&#13;
Kingdom's competition tribunal.               long-term level to bring down total revenue,&#13;
creating future problems. Littlechild therefore&#13;
A check on the regulator's discretion         decided to implement a one-time cut in prices&#13;
followed by a control of RPI - 2, in order to&#13;
The Telecommunications Act of 1984, which    combine an acceptable total revenue with a sen-&#13;
set up the system of regulation, gave the Mo-   sible price level at the end of the period. Simi-&#13;
nopolies and Mergers Commission the role of   lar one-time cuts have since been made in the&#13;
'court of appeal," acknowledging the need for   price controls of British Gas Transco (gas trans-&#13;
a check on the regulator's discretion. The com-   mission and distribution) and the National Grid&#13;
mission has had to rule on six price cap dis-   Company (electricity transmission).&#13;
putes since 1992. These rulings have gradually&#13;
built up some case law, for while each case is   An assessment&#13;
decided individually, the commission has rec-&#13;
ognized the value of developing a consistent   Price controls in the United Kingdom have been&#13;
methodology. Not wanting companies to ap-   controversial. The initial price controls for the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Has Price Cap Regulation of U.K. Utilities Been a Success?&#13;
electricity companies and the water industry,   and returns the gains to consumers after a short&#13;
based on underestimates of the companies'   time. The high profits of the early 1990s were&#13;
scope for reducing costs, turned out to be over-   due largely to unanticipated, one-time produc-&#13;
generous, allowing them high profits. The 1994    tivity gains following privatization, which are&#13;
review of the electricity price controls prom-    unlikely to be repeated. The established method&#13;
ised to reduce the companies' revenue by more   for resetting price controls makes further ''mis-&#13;
than  a sixth over the period, which Littlechild                       takes"  unlikely. In  the  future, price  controls&#13;
thought would give them no more than an ad-   can be expected to give companies an incen-&#13;
equate return. But Northern Electric, threatened                       tive for efficiency without allowing them  to earn&#13;
with  a takeover, was still able  to  promise  to                      excessive profits.&#13;
make a one-time payment to shareholders in&#13;
cash  and  shares valued  at twice the price for                       l Rate-of-return regulationi, the traditional method of utilitv regula-&#13;
which  it had  been  sold  four years earlier and                        tion, is widely used in the United States. The regulator allows the&#13;
to  increase  future  dividends. This  caused  a                         company to charge the prices expected to produce profits equal&#13;
major political row, and Littlechild decided to                          to a fair rate of return on the fair value of the capital invested in&#13;
the company. If profits fall helow this level, the comnpany can&#13;
reopen  the  review   in  March  1995.3  Three                           request approval for a new set of prices. Investors therefore know&#13;
months  later, he  announced  additional price                           that profits should not be too low, and consumers know that they&#13;
cuts of about 10 percent, supported largely by                           should not he too high. The prohiem with this system is that it&#13;
gives the company little incentive to improve efficiency andi may&#13;
a different treatment of the  companies' asset                           even encourage inefficient behavior that raises the company's al-&#13;
values at flotation. Even these reductions were                          lowable revenues.&#13;
Viewpoint is an open                                                                               2 Like many other telecomamunications companies, BT had set line&#13;
forum intended o            less than some people had expected, and share                             rentals below, cost and call charges shove cost. To prepare for&#13;
encourage dissemina-        prices  later rose, partly  because  of takeover                          competition, the company needed to rehalance its prices, raising&#13;
tion of and debate on       bids. Littlechild received heavy criticism  for his                       rentals and reducing call charges, but that would increase the bills&#13;
ideas, innovations, and                                                                               paid by small consumers, who made relatively few calls. The RPI&#13;
best practIces for ex-     handling of thesituation.                                                 + 2 constraint svas imposed for political reasons, to limit the speed&#13;
panding the private                                                                                   of these increases.&#13;
sector. The views pub-      Following  these  events, some  commentators                              It had been generally assumed that the controls were finalized,&#13;
linhed are tboae of the                                                                               h ut hecause a final stage of formnal consultation remained hefore&#13;
authod and ahosd nofth      (such  as  Burns, Turvey,  and   Wkeyman-Jones                            they could be implemented, Littlechild was legally allowed to&#13;
be attributed to the         1995) suggested forms of profit sharing regula-                          change his proposals.&#13;
World Bank or any of        tion. Under such schemes, the regulator would                             It has been suggested that the interval hetsveen main reviews&#13;
its affiiiated orga d zan    continue to set a price control for several years                        couild he lengthened, to restore incentives. But h, the end of the&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the                                                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~period, prices (even aifter profit sharing) could diverge just as far&#13;
conclusions represent       at a time, but would also monitor the company's                           from costs as they would under a pure price cap and a shorter&#13;
official policy of the      costs  and  profits  from   year to  year. If profits                     review period, negating the main advantage claimed for profit&#13;
World Bank or of its                                                                                  sharig&#13;
Executive Directors         rose above a trigger level, the company would                                ring.&#13;
orthe countries they        have to reduce its prices, returning some of the&#13;
represent.                  'excess" profits to consumers. These suggestions                       References&#13;
To order additional         have gained  political support, and  some regu-                        Burns, P., R. Turvey, and TG. WVeymanJones. 1995. "Sliding Scale&#13;
copies please call          lators have considered  implementing  them, al-                           Regulation of Monopoly Enterprises."'Discussion Paper 11. Centre&#13;
202-458-1 1 11 or contact   though they have not yet done so. The practical                           for he Stuy of Regulated ndustries, London.&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,      thuhpatcl                                                              Littlechild, Stephen. 1983. Regu/at/on of Britisb Telecommtrunicatiotas&#13;
Room F6P-188,               problem  is that profit sharing would require au-                         Profitability. London: HMSO.&#13;
The World Bank,             dited cost information everyv year for calculating                     Shleifer, Andrei. 1985. "A Theory of Yardstick Competition." Rand&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,          the  allowable  prices, and  obtaining  this infor-                       Journal ofEconoetica 16(3): 319-27&#13;
Woah IntontD.C 20433        mation  would  place  a heavy  burden  on  both&#13;
ssmithl©worldbank.org.      firms and regulators. Profit sharing would also                        Richard Green, Department of Applied&#13;
The series is also          weaken companies' incentives to reduce costs.4                         Economics, University of Cambridge, and&#13;
available on-line                                                                                   Visiting Fellow  to the Economic Development&#13;
(www.woridbank.org/&#13;
html/fpd/notes/             The  utilities remain  unpopular in  the  United                       Institute of the World Bank&#13;
notelist.html).             Kingdom, but most experts would  be willing&#13;
e Printed on recycled       to defend the price control system  as one that&#13;
paper.                      gives companies an incentive to cut their costs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441716">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/11/441716/price-cap-regulation-uk-utilities-success
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/11/441716/price-cap-regulation-uk-utilities-success</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/11/441716/price-cap-regulation-uk-utilities-success</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980624165002/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980624165002/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1997-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>1999-08-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Has the price cap regulation of U.K.
            utilities been a success?
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Price controls -- typically reviewed
            every five years in the United Kingdom -- have been
            controversial. The author traces the development of U.K.
            price controls and explains that the initial controls for
            electricity and water companies, based on underestimates of
            the companies' scope for reducing costs, turned out to
            be overly generous, allowing them high profits. While some
            analysts have suggested annual profit-sharing regulation,
            the practical problem is that annual profit-sharing would
            place a heavy information burden on firms and regulators and
            would weaken companies' incentives to lower costs.
            Although the utilities are still unpopular in the United
            Kingdom, most experts would be willing to defend the
            periodic price control system as one that gives companies an
            incentive to cut costs and return the gains to consumers
            after a short time. The high profits of the early 1990s were
            due largely to unanticipated, one-time productivity gains
            following privatization that are unlikely to be repeated.
            The established method for resetting price controls makes
            further "mistakes" unlikely.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Has the price cap regulation of U.K.
            utilities been a success?
        </docna>
        <display_title>Has the price cap regulation of
            U.K. utilities been a success?</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1997/11/441716/price-cap-regulation-uk-utilities-success</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,International Economics and Trade,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Environment</teratopic>
        <count>United Kingdom</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Green, Richard</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980624165002</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Non-Sector Specific</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 132</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,International Economics and Trade,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Environment</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Multisector</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Regulations; Denationalization; Electricity;
            Public enterprises; Price controls; Rate of return;
            Consumers; Consumer prices; Water supply; Market
            competition; Telecommunications; Public services
            consumers,controlled prices,cost of
            capital,dividends,Economic
            Development,Mergers,Monopolies,price cap regulation,price
            control,price controls,price index,productivity,regulatory
            approaches,regulatory
            capture,retail,sales,takeover,telecommunications,total revenue,underestimates
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>17232</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Controls</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Controls </ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>United Kingdom</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>