<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>I 1-+31 13&#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 126                                                                                      September 1997&#13;
The Private Sector in Water and Sanitation&#13;
-How to Get Started&#13;
PenelopeJ.          The benefits from private participation in water   thirty years, for example, needs to be sure that&#13;
Brook Cowen         and sanitation depend on the level of risk and    it does not, in haste, gloss over details that will&#13;
responsibility the government hands over to the    later land it in messy renegotiations, with loss&#13;
private sector. But strong government commit-   of face to all concerned and reduced benefits to&#13;
ment and careful preparation are required if the    consumers. But governments often worry that&#13;
private sector is to take on significant risks and    detailed preparations take too much time. This&#13;
responsibilities. A government about to enter   Note, based on a set of World Bank toolkits&#13;
into a concession contract for twenty-five or   compiled from experiences in involving the pri-&#13;
vate sector in water and sanitation, reviews the&#13;
essential factors in choosing a privatization op-&#13;
tion and argues that preparation pays dividends.&#13;
BOX 1    TOOLKITS FOR PRIVATE SECTOR PARTICIPATION              What makes the business special?&#13;
IN WATER AND SANITATION&#13;
The activities of urban water and sanitation&#13;
The World Bank has recently published a set of toolkits to guide gov-  utilities range from impounding and treating&#13;
ernments in designing and implementing private sector arrangements  raw water, to distributing water and collecting&#13;
for water and sanitation. The toolkits focus on three sets of issues:  sewage, to treating sewage. In many ways,&#13;
How to choose a private sector participation option. What are the  decisions about how to involve the private sec-&#13;
options? What might you have to do to make your preferred option  tor in these operations resemble decisions&#13;
practicable? What are the risks?                              about privatization in any other utility sector.&#13;
&#149; Howto design the process for refining and implementing the    All such privatizations, for example, require&#13;
chosen option. What might a critical path look like? How do you  decisions on how to set up an independent&#13;
set up a government unit to run the privatization process? What  regulator and how to set and enforce service&#13;
can you expectfrom legal, financial, economic, and engineering  features that governments must take into ac-&#13;
advisers-and how do you go about hiring them? How do you      count in choosing and designing a contract and&#13;
design a bidding process? What can you do to keep the contract on  in designing a supporting policy framework:&#13;
track once you've chosen a private partner?                   * Water and sanitation systems are character-&#13;
&#149; How to ensure that contracts cover all the issues. What should a  ized by a high degree of natural monopoly.&#13;
management build-operate-transfer (BOT), or concession contract  Although competition is feasible in such lim-&#13;
cover? In writing or reviewing contractual documents for a con-  ited areas as building capacity and providing&#13;
cession, a BOT arrangement, or a management conact, how do      plumbing services, it is difficult to achieve in&#13;
you know if you've covered everything? What are your options for  distribution and collection, core activities in&#13;
allocating and managing the many risks that go with the contract?  water and sanitation (table 1). So governments&#13;
wanting to involve the private sector have&#13;
To order copies of the toolkits, contact the World Bank bookstore, tel: 1 202 473 4266,  been able to rely little on competition to assure&#13;
fax: 12024770604, or enail: books@wortdbank.org (quote stock number 14003)  good outcomes for consumers and have in-&#13;
stead had to devise regulatory systems for this&#13;
purpose.&#13;
LIW                 The World Bank Group * Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Private Sector in Water and Sanitation-How to Get Started&#13;
efficient use. In India, for example, many cit-&#13;
Activity                      Charactensticsefcompeti.on #ies go short of water while farmers continue to&#13;
Alloctionowaerreourcs Na lmo l  ineach  receive subsidized water for irrigation.&#13;
an. ragulation of use  hydmgeqsjrapbictl ~ott          * Water and sanitation are well suited to local&#13;
jsuch as a ierasiat          tiimanagement, and in many countries, respon-&#13;
apacit construction  i mporv ta nt  p usibility for service provision is decentralized&#13;
a- ccsstowterr-sources-                 to the provincial or municipal level. As a re-&#13;
lygeneration  Smalloumber ofpossihlo                   sult, complex interjurisdictional issues often&#13;
bep ensured -forall. Guarateein  access fortneed to be resolved before the private sec-&#13;
4MJIpt.a U1WVIJI~ ~fl~Jtor can be brought in.&#13;
Water treatmear  LoeaInlonopoly                   * Many of the assets of water and sanitation&#13;
poor will  Locaimops requiredesigningsubsi-       particiasystems are buried, so obtaining accurate in-&#13;
Lccal netwring  Lorvcal tonohvrpol r. A  omliatng tformation about them  is costly-increasing&#13;
the cost of preparing for private sector par-&#13;
Sewage treatmeor  Local monopoly                    ~ticipation, and the chance of surprises after&#13;
iquipinentandppliancesales   Competitivethe contract is signed.&#13;
plumbingng seraice  raw water resourcesamong      invBroad access to water and sanitation yields&#13;
titoftraditioalwaterndsaniatioe usts-irban cs t,important public health and environmental&#13;
benefits. Government interventions to pro-&#13;
mote these benefits are likely to remain after&#13;
privatization.&#13;
*Water is essential to life, and access to it must&#13;
be ensured for all. Guaranteeing access for the    None of these issues is a barrier to private sector&#13;
poor will sometiines require designing subsi-    participation-all arise under both public and&#13;
dies or schemes for reducing the cost of deliv-    private provision. But governments often sys-&#13;
ering services to the very poor. A complicating    tematically confront their implications only&#13;
factor for reformers is that existing systems for    when they begin to contemplate private sector&#13;
allocating scarce raw water resources among    involvement. Failure to adequately address&#13;
alternative uses-urban consumption, irriga-   these issues increases the risk that a government&#13;
tion, industry-are often incompatible with    will be unable to find a partner for its pre-&#13;
tABLE 2   THE MAIN OPTIONS FORPRIVATE SECTOR PARTICIPATION AND THEIR ALLOCATION OF RESPONSIBILITIES~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.. .. .. .. .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ferred form of private sector participation or   proving efficiency, constructing large-scale&#13;
that a private sector arrangement will fall short   projects, cutting the cost of public subsidies or&#13;
of its broad policy objectives.              redirecting them to the poor, and making the&#13;
sector more responsive to customers. All forms&#13;
The main private sector options-and          of private sector participation can be designed&#13;
who's doing what                             to improve technical and managerial capacity.&#13;
But whether the other objectives can be met&#13;
Different countries have adopted different op-   depends on which option is chosen and whether&#13;
tions for private sector participation. Trinidad   the government can do a good job on the en-&#13;
and Tobago is using a management contract   abling and regulatory environment. A poor job&#13;
for water and sewerage services and plans to   can lead to dissatisfied customers and difficult&#13;
replace it with a concession. Guinea has a lease   renegotiations with the private partner. Under&#13;
arrangement for water treatment and supply in  the Guinea lease, for example, consumers have&#13;
seventeen cities. Buenos Aires and several other   lost out because disputes over the division of&#13;
Argentine provinces have concessions for wa-   responsibilities between the government and the&#13;
ter and sewerage. And England and Wales have   operator have hampered new connections and&#13;
divested their water and sanitation utilities,  service improvements. The Buenos Aires con-&#13;
cession has led to better service, but there have&#13;
The main options can be clearly distinguished   been costly disputes over the definition of the&#13;
by how they allocate responsibility for such func-   regulator's role (for example, in determining in-&#13;
tions as asset ownership and capital investment   vestment requirements) and the handling of ad-&#13;
between the public and private sectors (table 2).  justments in tariff levels and structure.&#13;
The more risk and responsibility are passed to&#13;
the private sector, the more powerful are its in-   To determine which private sector options are&#13;
centives to improve services. Service contracts,   feasible-or what must be done to make a pre-&#13;
which confer little risk and responsibility on the   ferred option possible-a government needs&#13;
private sector, offer commensurately small gains   to undertake a range of analyses:&#13;
-and are simply not designed to address mana-   * An analysis of the state of the utility-looking&#13;
gerial inefficiency or chronic underinvestment.    at the current level and standard of service,&#13;
Concessions and divestitures are well suited to    the condition and serviceability of assets, the&#13;
tackling these problems-but demand more from   human resources, and the financial perfor-&#13;
government in commitment and preparation.      mance. Is information about the utility's assets&#13;
good enough to serve as a base for long-&#13;
In practice, private sector arrangements are of-    term contracts? If not, can better information&#13;
ten hybrids of these models. For example,      be produced rapidly? Where information&#13;
leases may pass some responsibility for small-    about the quality of underground pipes, for&#13;
scale investment to the private sector, and    example, is partial or inaccurate, revelations&#13;
management contracts may, like leases, have    about the true state of the system that come&#13;
revenue-sharing provisions that pass on some   after a concession contract has been signed&#13;
commercial risk. Options can also be used in   may lead to costly renegotiations.&#13;
combination-for example, a build-operate-      An analysis of the existing regulatory frame-&#13;
transfer contract for bulk water supply might  work-both general laws that might affect&#13;
be combined with a management or lease         private participation in the sector and sector-&#13;
contract for operating the distribution system.  specific laws and institutions focusing on pric-&#13;
ing and quality standards. Does the existing&#13;
Key factors in choosing an option              regulatory framework provide sufficient sup-&#13;
port for the private sector so that it will take&#13;
Governments seeking to involve the private sec-  on commercial risk? If not, can the necessary&#13;
tor in water and sanitation may have a range of  changes be made fairly easily? And if not, can&#13;
objectives-introducing greater technical and   parts of the regulatory function be simplified&#13;
managerial expertise and new technology, im-   or contracted out in the short term? Where&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Private Sector in Water and Sanitation-How to Get Started&#13;
Stak*hoder s,- :lPotential&#13;
00~~~~~pr and0000 pol 3200Vitical    otrecvrn        Goo infrtio          Develped reglatory  Good conty         benefits:   &#13;
:  :0 0 Opt:ion j 0 9 i 00 0 commtment00  000 0,  g tariffs  about te! Esy  stem  frafimework  cd rating   :  0 : f        :   of the option&#13;
Service0tf : 0 ;.;:0Unimportant  Not necessary     Possible to proceed    Minimal monitoring    Not necessary  Low&#13;
cont00 &gt;ri d                     =act  in the short term    with only limited  capacity needed&#13;
information&#13;
Management    LQwlooweoIeratn   referretFbntinot Aufflt~Ieattinfomintin s:M,    t~tffettito1in~   Not necessary&#13;
Nte; The shading signals@tedegreeof importance:  nt ignificant      mNderatenecessary&#13;
Etlow  Ehigh~~~~~~~~~~~~Hg&#13;
The views published in    regulatory capacity is weak, for example, col-              analysis can sometimes lead to redefinition of&#13;
this series are those of  lection of information on the utility's techni-             a private sector project-for example, re-&#13;
the authors and should&#13;
not he attributed no the  cal and  financial performance  could  be                   balancing planned investment expenditures&#13;
World Bank or any of      contracted out to a private auditing company.               between new production capacity and the re-&#13;
its affiliated organiza-  *An analysis of which stakeholders (employees,              habilitation of existing distribution systems.&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the&#13;
con clusions represenit   consumers, environmentalists, government&#13;
official policy of the    agencies) support private participation and              As table 3 shows, in a very simplified way, the&#13;
World Bank or of its      which oppose it. Can processes and policies              results of these analyses can point the govern-&#13;
Executive Directors&#13;
or the countries they     be put in place to meet stakeholder concerns?            ment to an appropriate choice of private sec-&#13;
represent.                Can the risk of political interference be mini-    tor option. If regulatory capacity is weak and&#13;
mized? Often, a key factor in the success of a           political commitment is low, for example, a con-&#13;
To order additional       private sector project is identifyin-g the con-    cession will be difficult to implement. Even with&#13;
copiestE plRease oiH calli0 0                                                                       00 0                    0 &#13;
2028 pL1 ose cntac        cerns of employees early on and finding con-    strong political commitment to a concession&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,    structive ways of addressing them-rather than            or divestiture, however, countries that lack a&#13;
Room F6P-1t8,             allowing those concerns to derail the reform             good business climate or a strong track record&#13;
The World Bank,           process later.                                           of successful private investment may not im-&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,    * An analysis of the financial viability of alter-    mediately be able to attract large-scale private&#13;
or internet address       native options. Do current tariffs cover costs?    financing  for infrastructure  projects. These&#13;
ssminh7c worldbank.org.   Can the private sector reasonably be expected            countries may need to start out with a man-&#13;
The series is also&#13;
availble on-line          to boost efficiency enough to meet the pro-              agement contract and work up to options that&#13;
(www.worldbank.org/       posed service objectives without increasing              demand more of the private sector.&#13;
html/fpd/notes/           tariffs? if not, will consumers be willing to pay&#13;
copiesleasehcall.&#13;
notelist8htm111 onc       higher tariffs? And if not, can grant finance            Pestelopej. Brook Cowen (pbrookcowen c&#13;
S Printed on recycled     (or subsidies to needy households) support    worldbank.org), Private SectorDevelopment&#13;
paper.                    service improvements? This kind of financial    Specialist, P rivate Sector Development Deparntment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441719">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/09/441719/private-sector-water-sanitation-started
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/09/441719/private-sector-water-sanitation-started</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/09/441719/private-sector-water-sanitation-started</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980219162800/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980219162800/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1997-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2000-10-24T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The private sector in water and sanitation
            : how to get started
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The more risk and responsibility a
            government hands over to the private sector in water and
            sanitation, the more powerful the incentives for better
            performance-but also the more demands on the government in
            commitment and preparation. So a government about to enter
            into a long partnership for a water concession or
            build-operate-transfer arrangement - typically for
            twenty-five to thirty years - needs to be sure that it does
            not overlook details that will later land it in messy
            renegotiations. A lease is less demanding, but offers
            smaller gains and will not fix such problems as chronic
            under-investment. It will, however, give the government time
            to prepare a longer-term option. In this Note, based on
            toolkits recently published by the World Bank, the author
            sets out the range of options for involving the private
            sector in water and sanitation and reviews the lessons on
            what can make or break a private participation process.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The private sector in water and sanitation :
            how to get started
        </docna>
        <display_title>The private sector in water and
            sanitation : how to get started</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1997/09/441719/private-sector-water-sanitation-started</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Brook Cowen, Penelope J.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980219162800</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Water Supply &amp; Sanitation</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 126</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Water; Denationalization; Sanitation;
            Private sector
            asset ownership,bulk water,bulk water
            supply,concession contract,construction,distribution
            system,distribution systems,dividends,environmental
            benefits,expenditures,financial
            viability,households,investment expenditures,municipal
            level,private participation,private participation in
            water,private sector,public health,quality standards,raw
            water,regulatory capacity,regulatory framework,regulatory
            systems,sanitation systems,sanitation utilities,Service
            contracts,service improvements,service provision,sewerage
            services,urban water,utilities,water resources,water
            supply,water treatment
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>17318</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Chlorination</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Disinfection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Filtration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Purification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>