<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 139                                                                                        April 1998&#13;
Reforming the Russian Electricity Sector&#13;
3Vargcaret Wilson    In early 1997 the Russian government approved in principle the now common model of electricity&#13;
sector reform: vertically separating generation, transmission, and distribution; introducing&#13;
competition where possible; strengthening the regulation of functions less amenable to&#13;
competition; and divesting government ownership. This model has been implemented in many&#13;
countries, and the story of the reform would be relatively routine if not for special characteristics&#13;
of the Russian power system: its size, diverse ownership, high level of nonpayments, and the&#13;
combined heat and power role of many generating plants. This Note outlines the challenges&#13;
posed by these characteristics and reports on reform achievements so far.&#13;
The first challenge to reform is the sheer size   smaller than the United States and Canada com-&#13;
and scope of the network. The Russian power   bined (table 1). Most of the generation capac-&#13;
system consists of more than 200 gigawatts of   ity is thermal (70 percent), with hydro (20&#13;
generation capacity, most of it interconnected    percent) and nuclear (10 percent) making up&#13;
by 2.5 million kilometers of high-voltage trans-   the balance. Regionally, however, there are&#13;
mission lines spanning an area only slightly    major differences. More than 50 percent of the&#13;
hydro capacity is in Siberia and the far east,&#13;
TABLE 1   THE RUSSIAN ELECTRICITY SECTOR                     while 80 percent of the nuclear capacity is in&#13;
the central (Moscow) and northwest regions.&#13;
Size        More thang 20(    megawatts.&#13;
Generation    827 billion kilowatt-hours (Wh) (1996).         The regions jealously guard their hydro capacity.&#13;
Fuielmix    45%gas,2O%hydroA18fi%/coal,10%nuclear,%oil.      They regard it as a source of low-cost power&#13;
for local industries and have little desire to see&#13;
Demand mix   WI6 indusial 1 1% residential, 39;f/ other       it blended into a national power supply. More-&#13;
(including services and agriculttre).            over, the system was originally designed to&#13;
Tariffs     hndustrial more than US$05kWh, residentiak        provide a fairly high degree of regional self-&#13;
US$0.02/kWh, with large regional differences.    sufficiency (transmission links between regions&#13;
Investment   low, financed through cash flow. Almost no debt  are often weak), and in many cases large parts&#13;
or external equity finance or private project    of these self-sufficient regions are now in other&#13;
0   0 i development.             ;               countries. The main dispatch center for the&#13;
Colleetions   11% cask, 590°h noas 300°h unpaid               northwest region, for example, was in Riga (now&#13;
Collection    11% cash, *8% moncash,30% unpaid.  in Latvia), and one of the primary transmission&#13;
Employees    921,00(1996.                                     lines from the central region to the Caucasus&#13;
region passes through Ukraine.&#13;
Alo DaMa are for T997 except where otherwise specified.  -&#13;
Souree: UES and Russian edew Em  Cominssion.                 Consequently, restructuring generation to create&#13;
a competitive market is not a straightforward&#13;
T  W    B&#13;
E a                The World Bank Group - Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Reforming the Russian Electricity Sector&#13;
in most of these new enterprises, however. The&#13;
government also divested part of its holding in&#13;
UES. It now owns about 52 percent of the shares,&#13;
foreign companies hold about 28 percent, and&#13;
Russian companies and individuals, including&#13;
company employees and managers, own the bal-&#13;
*l  X  E] T i .*    9    W ance (figure 1).&#13;
L  -   r   ;!1 ii I  q. ,5U3 As a result of this decentralized ownership, the&#13;
::IzV'   I_=5 N   j restructuring program requires the support of&#13;
a 'wide range of stakeholders. The Energos in&#13;
WieaocIearp1nntisewnoddivec4;thngovomnmeo.  .particular need to be persuaded of the ben-&#13;
b USowenipifbe&amp;Eorgsbnssha4#prcetflontbftdnl ovrnmntefits of change, since they own or manage more&#13;
than 60 percent of installed capacity. The&#13;
Energos regard the move to a competitive&#13;
process. Regional opposition, combined with   wholesale market as a threat to their autonomy,&#13;
serious risks that technical constraints will al-   a change that will end their control over dis-&#13;
low generators to game the system and extract   patch and oblige them to purchase high-cost&#13;
monopoly prices, has led the government to   power from the market rather than distribut-&#13;
adopt a cautious timetable for moving to a com-   ing low-cost power from their own plants. Some&#13;
petitive market.                             of the Energos understand that their power&#13;
would be dispatched first and that they would&#13;
Diversified ownership                        receive the system marginal price for it. But&#13;
they remain concerned about nonpayments on&#13;
The second challenge lies in the electricity   the wholesale market and about having to pay&#13;
sector's ownership structure. While many coun-   market service charges to sell and repurchase&#13;
tries began reform with a vertically integrated,   what they regard as their own power.&#13;
state-owned monopoly, the Russian govern-&#13;
ment in 1996 faced a sector that had already   Outside shareholders of UES also will have to&#13;
been partially restructured and privatized. Un-   be persuaded of the merits of restructuring, par-&#13;
til 1992 the electricity sector had been orga-   ticularly with regard to any divestiture of gen-&#13;
nized in vertically integrated companies, called   eration assets. While these shareholders would&#13;
Energos, in each of the seventy-two oblasts or   theoretically retain an equivalent ownership&#13;
regions. But when mass privatization began that   stake in newly formed generation companies,&#13;
year, the federal government moved to main-   they might not perceive these holdings as&#13;
tain its control over the power sector.      equivalent in risks or returns to their existing&#13;
holdings in an integrated UES.&#13;
The government formed a new company, RAO&#13;
EES Rossii (commonly referred to as Unified En-   Nonpayments&#13;
ergy Systems, or UES), and gave it ownership&#13;
of the country's largest hydro and thermal gen-   The third challenge is nonpayments. The root&#13;
erating stations (nuclear excepted), the high-volt-   causes are many. They include tax avoidance,&#13;
age transmission network, and the dispatch   profiteering on barter settlements, legal and po-&#13;
systems. The Energos were set up as separate  litical barriers to cutting off supply to "strategic"&#13;
companies to own and operate the smaller gen-   customers, and simple failure by the government&#13;
erating plants and the distribution networks, and   to collect adequate taxes or introduce sufficient&#13;
some of their stock was sold to employees and   spending discipline to ensure that energy sup-&#13;
managers under the voucher privatization pro-   plies to budget-funded agencies can be financed.&#13;
gram. UES retained at least a 49 percent interest   The lack of cash payments has jeopardized the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
financial viability of many power sector enter-   restructuring the electricity sector and has&#13;
prises, hampering their ability to introduce or   defined further steps as part of its 1998 program&#13;
maintain efficient operating systems or to respond   for economic reform. In 1997 the emphasis was&#13;
to changing market conditions. Moreover, bartcr   on consolidation at the center, with the federal&#13;
and other noncash instruments are an inefficient   government strengthening its governance of the&#13;
and costly basis for market transactions.    electricity sector and bringing new management&#13;
into UES. The new management team has fo-&#13;
Restoring payment discipline is key to moving   cused its initial efforts on restoring the company's&#13;
forward with the proposed restructuring and un-   financial viability. To this end,&#13;
bundling of the sector. Without this discipline,  New financial controls and audit procedures&#13;
many of the newly formed enterprises would     were introduced. UES and ten of the Energos&#13;
risk financial failure, which would both discredit    are being audited, and UES is moving to full&#13;
the reforms and invite renewed government in-    IAS accounting.&#13;
tervention. Nonpayments can be fully resolved    * The investment program has been reviewed&#13;
only at the interface with the customer, how-  and rationalized, and funding withdrawn for&#13;
ever, which is typically through the regional dis-  about forty projects deemed nonviable.&#13;
tribution company. Thus the federal authorities  Collections have been improved, increasing&#13;
cannot unilaterally address the problem, but   cash payments to the UES transmission divi-&#13;
must work through local entities.              sion by 250 percent and overall cash pay-&#13;
ments from 5 to 20 percent of revenues.&#13;
Competition and regulation                     New sources of capital are being explored,&#13;
including private sector participation in&#13;
The fourth challenge lies in the fact that many  planned new investment projects and a pos-&#13;
of the generation assets controlled by the     sible convertible bond issue for placement in&#13;
Energos are combined heat and power plants.    international financial markets.&#13;
These plants were built primarily to meet local&#13;
heating demands and are an integral part of the   The government has also taken initial steps to&#13;
extensive district heating networks that in many   introduce competition. It created an indepen-&#13;
large cities serve the majority of the population.   dent financial operator to establish a competi-&#13;
In the absence of competitive heating markets,  tive wholesale market among large industrial&#13;
heat prices for these plants are regulated by lo-   customers and generators. Model contracts&#13;
cal authorities, generally at a level equivalent to   were established for transactions, using the net-&#13;
the cost of heat-only boilers. Regulators and mu-   work as a common carrier. Principles for ac-&#13;
nicipalities are concerned about the integration    cess to the transmission and distribution&#13;
of competitive and regulated activities in a single   networks and for regulation of wheeling tariffs&#13;
entity, about the implications of this under the   are being established. A wholesale market,&#13;
current procedures for allocating joint and com-   being piloted in one region, counted two&#13;
mon costs, and about their ability to ensure that   generators and four customers among its par-&#13;
the Energos do not use the regulated heat mar-  ticipants by the end of the year. To participate,&#13;
ket to extract windfall profits from electricity   buyers must agree to pay cash, in advance,&#13;
cogeneration. With the system of regioinal regu-   and to eliminate payment arrears. In return they&#13;
lation still in its infancy and many of the local   receive a 35 percent discount on tariffs.&#13;
regulators lacking experience and expertise, this&#13;
added complexity is a serious concern.       The government has also undertaken to reorga-&#13;
nize generation, to boost operating efficiency&#13;
Achievements to date                         while laying a foundation for a competitive gen-&#13;
eration market. It has evaluated several&#13;
Despite these challenges, the government has   restructuring options in recent months, and the&#13;
taken meaningful steps toward reforming and    1998 program calls for finalizing and initiating&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Reforming the Russian Electricity Sector&#13;
the reorganization plan. Among the options is    The reorganization of generation, particularly&#13;
grouping the existing plants into generating com-    the increased focus on competition among sup-&#13;
panies, or Gencos, to create enough potentially    pliers, is also expected to reduce electricity&#13;
viable, independent entities for a competitive    prices. As new generating plants begin to comn-&#13;
market. Finally, the government has begun re-    pete with existing plants, investment proposals&#13;
moving electricity pricing distortions, increas-    are expected to become more rational and out-&#13;
ing tariffs to households by 32 percent and    of-date, inefficient units are expected to close&#13;
making a commitment to eliminate cross-    (plans for their closure are to be developed,&#13;
subsidies by 2000.                                    including programs to mitigate social impacts).&#13;
Next steps                                            Electricity prices still need to be adjusted to better&#13;
reflect the economic cost of supply. Wholesale&#13;
In 1998 reform  efforts will be extended out-    and industrial prices need to fall, and prices to&#13;
ward from  the center, and pilots will be ex-    households to rise. Efficiency improvements (in&#13;
panded to more regions. The four target areas    dispatch and operating practices) should help&#13;
of the 1998 program  are increasing cash col-   to bring down wholesale and industrial prices,&#13;
lections, improving dispatch of generators to    as will rebalancing when household tariffs are&#13;
lower average fuel costs, boosting operating    increased. Improved access to investment financ-&#13;
efficiency, and reducing pricing distortions.         ing is another potential source of tariff reduc-&#13;
tions. Because of limited access to capital&#13;
forum intended to     The government views financial viability of the    markets, electricity tariffs currently incorporate&#13;
encourage dissemina-  sector, particularly increased liquidity, as key to    full self-financing of new investments. But with&#13;
tion of and debate on  the success of the reform. While UES more than    improved financial viability, UES and the Energos&#13;
idens, innovations, and&#13;
best practices for ex-  tripled its cash collections in 1997, further im-    should be able to attract debt financing for at&#13;
panding the private   provements can be achieved only by resolving    least part of the investment program. That would&#13;
sector. The views pub-    the nonpayment problem at the customer inter-    allow prices to fall and would subject proposed&#13;
~ished are those of the&#13;
authors and should sot    face, that is, at the Energo level. Initial efforts in    investments to the discipline of review by the&#13;
be attributed to the  1998 will be mainly diagnostic, though arrange-    financial community.&#13;
World Bank or any of  ments have been made for the private sector to&#13;
its affiliated organiza-&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the    run the commercial operations of one Energo    Many problems remain to be resolved, and the&#13;
conclusions represent  under a management contract. Diagnostic efforts    commitment to reform periodically loses steam&#13;
official policy of the  initially will focus on ten regions. Consultants    as pressing political issues arise. But on bal-&#13;
Executivr Directors   will work with the Energos to identify the causes    ance the Russian government has taken im-&#13;
or the countries they  of the nonpayments in each region and test solu-    pressive steps toward creating a more efficient&#13;
represent.           tions. Actions to complement these initiatives will    and effective electricity sector.&#13;
To order additional   include increasing the electricity traded for cash&#13;
copies please call    on the wholesale market and improving payment    The World Bank has been a partner in the Rosian electricity sector&#13;
202-458-11 11 or contact    discipline among budget-funded agencies.         reform program for more than two years. It mobilized grant financing&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,                                                      to help the government formulate the reform, provided technical as-&#13;
Room F6P-lB88&#13;
Thoe Word Bank,       Improving dispatch could save an estimated    sistance loans to support restructuring programs, and extended adjust-&#13;
The World Bak,  Improvin    dispatch cold save an  stimated    mnnt loans to encourage sustained commitment to reformi.&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,    US$1 billion or more a year in fuel costs, and&#13;
Washingtoni, D.C. 20433, ...&#13;
or Internet address   initial steps to realize these benefits will take    Margaret Wilson (mwilson3@worldbank.org),&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.    place in 1998. UES, the federal regulatory agency,    Consultant, Europe and Central Asia Energy&#13;
The series is also    and consultants are developing an improved in-    Sector Unit&#13;
available on-line&#13;
wwvw.wo r ban k.org!  centive system, including dispatching guidelines&#13;
html/fpd/notes/       and procedures. New  guidelines are to be in&#13;
notelist.html).       place in at least one zone (of seven) by the end&#13;
@1 Printed on recycled  of June. If the pilot efforts are successful, they&#13;
paper                 will be extended to other zones.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="441758">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/04/441758/reforming-russian-electricity-sector
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/04/441758/reforming-russian-electricity-sector</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1998/04/441758/reforming-russian-electricity-sector</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980901105956/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/08/15/000009265_3980901105956/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1998-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2001-06-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Reforming the Russian electricity sector
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Russia's power system is enormous
            consisting of more than 200 gigawatts of generation
            capacity, most of it interconnected by 2.5 million
            kilometers of high-voltage transmission lines spanning an
            area only slightly smaller than the United States and Canada
            combined. In early 1997 the Russian government approved in
            principle the now-common model of electricity sector reform:
            vertically separating generation, transmission, and
            distribution; introducing competition where possible;
            strengthening the regulation of functions less amenable to
            competition; and divesting government ownership. This model
            has been implemented in many countries, and the story of the
            reform would be relatively routine if not for special
            characteristics of the Russian power system: its size,
            diverse ownership, high level of nonpayments, and the
            combined heat and power role of many generating plants. This
            Note outlines the challenges posed by these characteristics
            and reports on reform achievements so far.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Reforming the Russian electricity sector
        </docna>
        <display_title>Reforming the Russian electricity sector</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1998/04/441758/reforming-russian-electricity-sector</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Energy Technology &amp; Transmission,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,National Governance,Public Sector Economics,Electric Power</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Energy,Governance,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Russian Federation</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Wilson, Margaret</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Commonwealth of Independent States!$!80457</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980901105956</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Distribution &amp; Transmission</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 139</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Energy,Governance,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Power sector; Electricity; Competition
            (economic); Privatization; Corruption; Ownership;
            Decentralization; Power generation; Power sector reform;
            User fees; User charges
            accounting,cash
            payments,coal,cogeneration,debt,debt financing,economic
            reform,electricity,Electricity prices,electricity
            pricing,electricity sector,electricity sector reform,federal
            government,financial viability,generators,government
            ownership,heat,heating,international financial
            markets,oil,power,power plants,power sector,Private
            Sector,private sector participation,regulatory agency,tax,voltage
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Commonwealth of Independent States</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>18345</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems Technologies and Operations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Thermal Power Generation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Technology &amp; Transmission</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Financial Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Placement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>State Associations</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Russian Federation</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>