<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. 16539-ZA&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
September 4, 1997&#13;
Transport 1&#13;
Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENT&#13;
(as ot'Jul  31. 1997)&#13;
Currency Unit = Zambia Kwacha (K)&#13;
USS =K 1,00.00&#13;
SDR I = KI.767_00&#13;
K 1.000 =USS0-77&#13;
AVERAGE ANNUAL EXCHANGE RATE&#13;
Year = K per US Dollar&#13;
1994  669&#13;
1995  860&#13;
1996 = 1229&#13;
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES&#13;
I metric ton (tonne) =1000 kg or 2.205 pounds&#13;
I meter (m) = 3.2808 feet&#13;
I kilometer (km) = 0.6214 miles&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
AfDB = African Development Bank&#13;
CAP 464 = Roads and Road Traffrc Act&#13;
CAS = Country Assistance Strategy&#13;
DISS = Department of Infrastructure and Support Services&#13;
ECZ = Environment Council of Zambia&#13;
EIA = Environmental Impact Assessment&#13;
ERR = Economic Rate of Retumn&#13;
EU = European Union&#13;
FEDHAUL= Federation of Road Hauliers&#13;
GDP = Gross Domestic Product&#13;
H1vlS = Highway Management System&#13;
ICB  Intemational Competitive Bidding&#13;
IDA = Intemational Development Association&#13;
IMT = Intermediate Mleans ofTransport&#13;
MCT = Mlinistry of Transport and Communication&#13;
MFED   M Ministry of Finance and Economic Development&#13;
MWS = Ministr- of Works and Supply&#13;
MLGH = Ministr. of Local Govemment and Housing&#13;
NCB = National Competitive Bidding&#13;
NCC = National Council for Construction&#13;
NGO = Non-Govemmental Organization&#13;
NRB = National Roads Board&#13;
NRSC = Natibnal Road Safety Council&#13;
PSRP = Public Sector Reform Program&#13;
PSC = Project Steering Committee&#13;
Roads Dept. = Roads Department&#13;
RDC = Rural District Council&#13;
RIM I = Road Maintenance Initiative&#13;
ROADSIP = Road Sector Investment Program&#13;
RTTP = Rural Travel and Transport Program&#13;
SDR = Special Drawing Right&#13;
SRP = Social Recovery Project&#13;
SRPU = Social Recovery Project Unit&#13;
TETAP= Transport Engineering and Technical Assistance Program&#13;
UNCDF = United Nations Capital Development Fund&#13;
UNDP = United Nations Development Program&#13;
VOC = Vehicle Operating Costs&#13;
ZNTB = Zambia National Tender Board&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January I to December 31&#13;
Vice President:                 Catlisto Madavo. AFR&#13;
Country Director:               Phyllis Pomerantz, AFC02&#13;
Technical Manager:              Yusupha Crookes. AFTTI&#13;
Task Team Leader:               Stephen Brushett. AFTT1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
CREDIT AND PROJECT SUMMARY ...............................................1&#13;
1. SECTOR BACKGROUND ...............................................2&#13;
A. Country Background ................................................2&#13;
B. The Transport Sector ................................................3&#13;
C. The Road Subsector ................................................6&#13;
2. THE PROGRAM AND THE PROJECT ..............................................                                                                            19&#13;
A. Program and Project Objectives ...............................................                                                                    19&#13;
B. Rationale for IDA Involvement ...............................................                                                                    20&#13;
C Project Description ...............................................                                                                                21&#13;
D. Project Strategy ...............................................                                                                                 24&#13;
E. Project Cost ................................................ 25&#13;
F. Project Financing ...............................................                                                                                27&#13;
G. Foreign Funding ...............................................                                                                                  27&#13;
H. Local Funding ...............................................                                                                                     28&#13;
3. PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION .............................................                                                                                  31&#13;
A. Implementation Arrangements ...............................................                                                                       31&#13;
B. Technical Assistance and Training ...............................................                                                                 33&#13;
D. Disbursement ...............................................                                                                                     37&#13;
E. Auditing and Accounting ...............................................                                                                          39&#13;
F. Monitoring and Reporting ...............................................                                                                         39&#13;
G. Supervision ...............................................                                                                                      40&#13;
4. PROJECT BENEFITS AND RISKS .............................................                                                                              41&#13;
A. Project Benefits ...............................................                                                                                 41&#13;
B. Key Performance Indicators ...............................................                                                                        43&#13;
C. Poverty Reduction and Employment Generation ...............................................                                                      43&#13;
D. Development of Local Contractors ...............................................                                                                  44&#13;
E. Environmental Impact ...............................................                                                                              45&#13;
F. Sustainability .46.........................................                                .     .     ....................................... 46&#13;
G. Project Risks ........ 46&#13;
5. AGREEMENTS REACHED AND RECOMMENDATION .............................................                                                                  49&#13;
A. Agreements ...............................................                                                                                       49&#13;
B. Assurances Provided at Negotiations ................................................ 50&#13;
C. Recommendation ...............................................                                                                                    51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
TABLE 1- 1: 1994 MODE OF TRANspoRTING ZAMBIAN IMPORTS AND EXPORTS .............................................4&#13;
TABLE 1-2: 1994 PASSENGER VOLUME PER TRANSPORTATION .......................................................................5&#13;
TABLE 1-3: ROAD NETWORK ..........................................................................               12&#13;
TABLE 1-4: 1995 CONDITION OF SOME MAIN ROADS .........................................................................   12&#13;
TABLE 1-5: ESTIMATED DOMESTIC VEHICLE NUMBERS .........................................................................    14&#13;
TABLE 2- 1: SUMMARY OF PROJECT COST (US$ MILLION) ......................................................................... 26&#13;
TABLE 2-2: 1997-2002 ESTIMATED COSTS OF CIVIL WORKS (US$ MILLION) .............................................. 26&#13;
TABLE 2-3: SUMMARY OF PROBABLE PROJECT FINANCING (US$ MILLION) ................................................. 27&#13;
TABLE 2-4: SOURCES OF ROAD FUND RESOURCES (US$ MILLION) ............................................................... 30&#13;
TABLE 2-5: USES OF ROAD FUND RESOURCES (US$ MILLION) ..................................................................... 30&#13;
TABLE 3- 1: SUMMARY OF PROCUREMENT ARRANGEMENTS (US$ MILLION) ................................................ 35&#13;
TABLE 3-2: PROJECTED DISBURSEMENTS FISCAL YEAR ENDING JUNE (US$ MILLION) ................................ 37&#13;
TABLE 4- 1: LOCAL REVENUE REQuIREMENTS OF VARIOUS SCENARIOS ....................................................... 47&#13;
TABLE 4-2: FUEL LEVY PROCEEDS: RISK ANALYSIS SUMMARY ................................................................... 48&#13;
Definition of Terms&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
1-1      Letter of Road Sector Policy&#13;
2-1      Description of Civil Works Program&#13;
3-1      Project Implementation Schedule&#13;
3-2      Disbursement Schedule and Comparative Disbursement Profile&#13;
3-3      Monitoring and Implementation Indicators&#13;
3-4      Supervision Plan&#13;
4-1      Economic Analysis&#13;
List of Documents in the Project File&#13;
Map: IBRD No. 28475&#13;
This report is based on the findings of a Bank appraisal mission which visited Zambia June-July 1996,&#13;
comprising Stephen Brushett (Senior Operations Officer, Task Team Leader and Mission Leader), Ian&#13;
Heggie (Principal Roads Adviser), Subhash Seth (Highways Engineer), Robert Tillman (Senior&#13;
Environment Specialist), Toshiyuki Iwama (Transport Planner), Marianne Fay (Economist), Christina&#13;
Malmberg Calvo (Economist), Moctar Thiam (Consultant, Engineer), Ole Sylte (Consultant, Highway&#13;
Engineer) and George Sikazwe (Procurement and Disbursement Officer). Rosemary Cubagee (Consultant)&#13;
prepared the first draft of this report. Mary Ann Arouna, Marjorie Kingston, and Josiane Luchmun&#13;
provided editorial and administrative support in preparation of the report. Alan Coulthart, Alfred Nickesen&#13;
and Nwanze Okidegbe are the peer reviewers. Yusupha Crookes is the Technical Manager, Phyllis&#13;
Pomerantz is the Country Director, and Callisto Madavo is the Regional Vice President.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
CREDIT AND PROJECT SUMMARY&#13;
Borrower:                Government of the Republic of Zambia.&#13;
Implementing Agencies:    Ministry of Communications and Transport (MCT),&#13;
National Roads Board (NRB), Ministry of Works and&#13;
Supply, Roads Department (Roads Dept.), Ministry of&#13;
Local Government and Housing (MLGH), Ministry of&#13;
Finance and Economic Development, Social Recovery&#13;
Project Unit (SRPU).&#13;
Beneficiaries:           Road users, urban and rural communities, farmers, local&#13;
contractors and consultants.&#13;
Poverty:                 Program of Targeted Interventions.&#13;
Amount:                  SDR 51.5 million (US$70.0 million equivalent).&#13;
Terms:                   Standard IDA terms, with 40 years' maturity.&#13;
Commitment Fee:          0.50% on undisbursed credit balance.&#13;
On-Lending Terms:        Not applicable.&#13;
Financing Plan:          See Schedule.&#13;
Economic Rate of Return:  21% average for major road works.&#13;
Staff Appraisal Report:  16539-ZA&#13;
Map:                     IBRD No. 28475&#13;
Project Identification&#13;
Number:                  ZM-PA-3236&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
1. SECTOR BACKGROUND&#13;
A.   Country Background&#13;
1.1   Zambia is a land locked country with a surface area of about 750,000 km2and a&#13;
population of about 9.4 million, about half of whom live in urban areas. The country is&#13;
endowed with abundant land for agricultural expansion, a resource-base which includes&#13;
minerals, and a relatively unspoiled environment that hosts abundant wildlife and&#13;
considerable tourism potential. Zambia's rich endowment of copper at one time seemed&#13;
to ensure a glowing future. The reality has been vastly different. Since independence in&#13;
1964, Zambians have grown poorer and more heavily indebted, and the economy is&#13;
facing large external imbalances. Zambia's economic problems are partly due to lack of&#13;
diversification in the economy and to continued excessive reliance on copper, despite&#13;
falling prices and production since the mid-1970s. Coupled with this, its economic&#13;
policies in the past have failed to adapt to economic realities. Several partial economic&#13;
reform programs were initiated during the 1 980s, but these reforms were not sustained&#13;
and had little lasting effect. With the accumulation of arrears, Bank and IMF lending&#13;
operations were suspended between 1987 and March 1991 and again in September 1991.&#13;
In November 1991, the Movement for Multiparty Democracy (MMD), a political party&#13;
committed to policy reform, won the general elections. The new Zambian Government&#13;
cleared arrears to the Bank, agreed on a new Policy Framework Paper (PFP) with the&#13;
Bank and IMF, and began a Rights' Accumulation Program to clear arrears to the IMF.&#13;
Disbursements under IDA operations resumed in February 1992.&#13;
1.2   Over the past five years, the Zambian Government has sustained an ambitious&#13;
economic reform program designed to encourage movement towards a full market&#13;
economy and to significantly reduce the role of the state. Nearly all price and exchange&#13;
rate controls have been dismantled, import and export licensing has been eliminated,&#13;
interest rates have been decontrolled, the tariff structure has been compressed and&#13;
lowered, and comprehensive programs of civil service reform and parastatal privatization&#13;
have been started. These measures have helped create conditions conducive to increased&#13;
agricultural production and to the promotion of the private sector which over time should&#13;
reduce the country's dependence on the mining sector (especially copper) for output,&#13;
employment and exports. Economic performance has picked up relatively slowly thus far&#13;
and dependence of external financing for investment remains high. External assistance&#13;
from donors, however, slowed significantly in 1996 in large part due to concerns about&#13;
the conduct of the national elections held last November in which MMD was returned to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
power. A resumption of donor support at least to the levels obtaining in the early 1990s&#13;
together with a concerted effort to reduce external indebtedness, inter alia through the&#13;
recently approved Heavily Indebted Poor Countries' Debt Initiative, will be necessary to&#13;
ensure there is adequate funding for Zambia's ongoing reform effort.&#13;
1.3   The Government's main concerns over the medium term are to accelerate the&#13;
supply response in the Zambian economy and provide infrastructure for growth, to&#13;
directly reduce poverty, and to reform the public sector and strengthen governance. In&#13;
line with this and in furtherance of the overriding objective of poverty reduction, the&#13;
Bank's country assistance strategy (CAS) for the period 1997 to 1999 aims to support the&#13;
Government's program as follows: (i) create a stable macroeonomic environment as a&#13;
prerequisite for growth and employment; (ii) target assistance to the poor and vulnerable&#13;
groups; and (iii) promote private sector development and greater public sector efficiency&#13;
to stimulate more rapid and inclusive growth.&#13;
1.4   The dilapidated state of Zambia's infrastructure, particularly in transport and&#13;
power, is a serious obstacle both to economic growth, because of the country's distance&#13;
from export markets, and to poverty reduction, because of its widely dispersed rural&#13;
population. The Government's approach is to adopt comprehensive strategies in the&#13;
various infrastructure subsectors aimed at ensuring sustainable growth through reform of&#13;
the policy and institutional environment, through specific measures designed to increase&#13;
domestic resource mobilization to reduce dependency on external financing, and through&#13;
action to increase private sector participation to increase the efficiency of service&#13;
provision and to improve access to service. With regard to investment, the proposed&#13;
approach is to undertake comprehensive and integrated sector operations to ensure that&#13;
available funding is channeled to highest priority programs.&#13;
B.   The Transport Sector&#13;
1.5   The contribution of the transport sector to the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) has&#13;
fluctuated around 5% in recent years. In 1994, road transport contributed about 23%&#13;
compared to 27% from the railways to transport sector output. The volume of road&#13;
transport activity was adversely affected by drought in the period 1992-4 but still actually&#13;
rose in value in real terms by about 5% in 1994. About 2.2 million tonnes of the&#13;
country's imports and exports were transported by road in 1994 in comparison to only&#13;
400,000 tonnes by rail. In addition, the transport sector provides about 20,000 formal&#13;
sector jobs averaging about 4-5% of the total formal sector employment in the country.&#13;
1.6  In spite of the strategic importance of the transport sector to the Zambian&#13;
economy, resource allocation to the transport sectQr as a proportion of total national&#13;
capital investment in real terms is low and has been declining. In 1975, 13% of the total&#13;
capital investment was allocated to the transport sector. The equivalent allocation was&#13;
slightly under 7% in 1985 and less than 2% in 1994. Consequently, the general&#13;
deterioration of transport infrastructure in terms of both road and railway has accelerated,&#13;
making certain parts of the country impassable especially during the rainy season and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
exacerbating the isolation of poor, rural communities. This notwithstanding, the burden&#13;
of the transport sector on the recurrent budget is considerable and largely due to the&#13;
inefficiency of transport sector enterprises. Losses were estimated as equivalent to 12%&#13;
of total government revenue in 1990-91. This was due partly to enterprise deficits though&#13;
these have since been brought down somewhat by liquidation (Zambia Airways) and by&#13;
restructuring of these enterprises. This level of losses is also explained by the shortfall of&#13;
road user charges in relation to road sector expenditure.&#13;
1.7   The transport network in Zambia comprises five distinct modes of transport, viz.:&#13;
rail, road, civil aviation, inland water transport and pipeline. Increasingly, road transport&#13;
is becoming the most important mode for both freight and passengers. An overview of&#13;
Zambia's major modes of transport reveals that rail and road account for the movement of&#13;
three quarters of total import and exports. Air and water play a very insignificant role&#13;
while the role of the Zambia-Tanzania Pipeline (TAZAMA) is limited to the&#13;
transportation of spiked crude oil from Dar-es-Salaam in Tanzania to Ndola in Zambia.&#13;
Table 1-1: 1994 Mode of Transporting Zambian Imports and Exports&#13;
Exports                     Imports&#13;
Mode of Transport    Mt-Tonnes        Percent       Mt-Tonnes      Percent&#13;
Air                     27,485           2.8          261,751        10.2&#13;
Inland Waterway         10,274           1.1             146          -&#13;
Parcel Post                60             4- 24&#13;
Rail                   326,267          33.5           60,397        2.4&#13;
Road                   609,004          62.6         1,604,553       62.6&#13;
Pipeline         l                         -          635,883        24.8&#13;
Total                  973,1 10          100        2,563,074        100&#13;
Source: Ministry of Communication and Transport&#13;
1.8   The most important sea routes/ports for land locked Zambia are to: Dar-es-Salaam&#13;
in Tanzania; Durban and East London in South Africa; and Maputo, Beira and Nacala in&#13;
Mozambique. The railway network comprises two systems, i.e., Zambia Railways Ltd.&#13;
(ZR) and Tanzania-Zambia Railways Authority (TAZARA). The ZR network comprises&#13;
1,273 km linking the Copperbelt of Zambia to the seaports of Durban and East London in&#13;
South Africa. ZR is further connected to Zaire Railways as well as TAZARA at Kapiri&#13;
Mposhi. ZR plies from the Copperbelt via Lusaka to Livingstone in Southern Province.&#13;
TAZARA provides services between Dar-es-Salaam and Kapiri Mposhi. Locally,&#13;
TAZARA provides passenger services from Nakonde through Northern and Central&#13;
Provinces to Kapiri Mposhi.&#13;
1.9   Although Zambia Railways (ZR) has the capacity for transporting about 8.5&#13;
million tonnes annually, the actual performance has fallen steadily in recent years. For&#13;
most of the 1980s, the company carried about four million tonnes of freight and two&#13;
million passengers per year. The performance in 1994, however, stood at two million&#13;
tonnes of freight traffic and one million passengers. Problems of ZR include: Overage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
tracks; inadequate signaling system; inadequate motive power and rolling stock; deferred&#13;
maintenance and stiff competition from road hauliers; and high quality intercity bus&#13;
services. The financial condition of ZR has been on a deteriorating trend. During the&#13;
financial year 1994, revenue amounted to K27.8 billion on which ZR incurred an&#13;
operating deficit of over KI 0 billion against the anticipated operating surplus of K 1I&#13;
billion. Domestically, ZR plays an important but declining role in transporting&#13;
agricultural and mineral products, thus increasing the demands on Zambia's road&#13;
infrastructure. Some measures are now being taken to improve management of ZR.&#13;
Given the limited impact of reforms introduced to date, radical restructuring, which could&#13;
include concessioning of railway management to the private sector or outright&#13;
privatization, is being considered.&#13;
Table 1-2: 1994 Passenger Volume Per Transportation&#13;
Mode of Transport         Passenger Volume            Percent&#13;
Air                                   83,631                   18&#13;
Lake (Lakes Bangweulu &amp; Mweru)        29,900                    1&#13;
Rail (Zambia Railways only)         1,005,660                 37&#13;
Road (UBCZ only)                    1,200,000                  44&#13;
Total                               2,319,191                 100&#13;
Source: Ministry of Communications and Transport&#13;
1.10 TAZARA is jointly owned by the Government of Zambia and Tanzania and has a&#13;
total track of about 1,860 kms of which about 883 kms is in Zambia. The track extends&#13;
from Kapiri Mposhi in Zambia to the port of Dar-es-Salaam in Tanzania. Like Zambia&#13;
Railways, TAZARA has experienced operational problems and has been working at less&#13;
than half of designed capacity largely due to shortages of motive power, rolling stock and&#13;
poor signaling and maintenance. Recently, however, TAZARA has undergone a major&#13;
restructuring and comniercialization process. Both the Zambia and Tanzania sectors now&#13;
operate as cost/profit centers with some degree of autonomy although operational and&#13;
financial performance is still suboptimal.&#13;
1.11  Zambia Airways Corporation Limited (ZA) used to be Zambia's national flag&#13;
carrier. However, in December 1994, the corporation was liquidated after years of&#13;
chronic operational and management problems. In place of Zambia Airways, a number&#13;
of privately owned airlines have emerged including Zambia Express Airways and Aero&#13;
Zambia, both of which are competing for the airline passenger domestic and sub regional&#13;
market. The airlines provide an alternative to road transport at the top end of the market&#13;
for passenger service to Livingstone and to Ndola and the Copperbelt. Operation of&#13;
Zambia's four largest airports have been commercialized and these are run generally on&#13;
efficient lines by National Airports Corporation Limited (NACL). Civil aviation services&#13;
are regulated by the Department of Civil Aviation (DCA) which also operates 40 smaller&#13;
airports in Zambia at a loss.&#13;
1.12  Inland water transport is the most underdeveloped mode of transport in the&#13;
country although it has potential for exporting freight to Zaire, Burundi and Tanzania&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6 -&#13;
through this means. The sub-sector continues to be constrained and hampered by&#13;
deferred maintenance and lack of rehabilitation. Freight movement on Lake Bangweulu,&#13;
for example, declined by 53% between 1993 and 1994 with only 123 tonnes of cargo&#13;
carried in 1994. Movements may continue to be adversely affected by subregional&#13;
political instability.&#13;
1.13 The Ministry of Communications and Transport (MCT) is responsible for overall&#13;
transport policy and for supervision of transport sector institutions. The Government has&#13;
over the past few years tried to pursue policies to improve sector performance to respond&#13;
to the changing requirements of consumers. The policy framework has favored an&#13;
increasing the role of the private sector transport as well as increased competition within&#13;
the transport subsectors, especially, road and air. The policy, with regard to the transport&#13;
sector, is set out in the White Paper on Communications and Transport Policy of May&#13;
1995 which is currently in the process of being updated for formal adoption by Cabinet.&#13;
Recognizing that sector investment has not kept pace with the economic importance of&#13;
the sector, and that the investment that has taken place has mostly been ineffective in&#13;
terms of raising the levels and quality of service offered, the Government has arrived at&#13;
the following specific objectives:&#13;
(a)   ensure availability of sufficient resources from both private and public&#13;
sector to create capacity in the transport sector commensurate with the&#13;
requirements of the economy;&#13;
(b)   allocate available resources among transport modes to meet requirements&#13;
at minimum cost to society; and&#13;
(c)   establish a system of transport pricing that would ensure a reasonable&#13;
return on transport investment.&#13;
The white paper makes reference to the dualistic pattern of development in the&#13;
country and the need to ensure future transport sector development, especially in the road&#13;
sector, pays greater attention to the periphery than hitherto, in particular to effectively&#13;
support the agricultural sector. The Government also envisages that greater attention will&#13;
need to be paid to the mitigation of the adverse environmental impact of the transport&#13;
sector, with particular regard to the road sector.&#13;
C.   The Road Subsector&#13;
I.    Road Policy and Management&#13;
1.14 National road policy is laid down in the Roads and Road Traffic Act (CAP 464)&#13;
passed in 1959 with subsequent amendments. The Act defines the different types of&#13;
roads and lays down regulations governing their construction and maintenance. The Act&#13;
designates the following seven types of road: (i) inter-territorial main roads (T);&#13;
(ii) territorial main roads (M); (iii) district roads (D); (iv) rural district roads (RD); (v)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
rural roads (R); (vi) branch roads (B); and (vii) estate roads (E). All roads designated are&#13;
supposed to be assigned to a particular road authority in terms of the Act. T, M and D&#13;
roads fall under the responsibility of the Roads Department in the Ministry of Works and&#13;
Supply (MWS) except for those M and D roads which fall within a local authority area.&#13;
Local authorities under the Ministry of Local Government and Housing (MLGH) are&#13;
responsible for RD and R roads as well as for urban roads. In the case of B and E roads, a&#13;
highway authority is to be designated at the discretion of the minister. Responsibilities&#13;
are also assigned under the Act to the Department of Parks and Wildlife for the&#13;
management of roads within the boundaries of national parks and to the Ministry of&#13;
Agriculture, Food and Fisheries for the management of a limited network of roads leading&#13;
to agricultural camps and institutions.&#13;
1.15  While the legislation is fairly clear in that it sets out who is responsible for what,&#13;
there are a number of issues that need to be addressed and there is a need to update&#13;
aspects of the legislation to take account of current realities. Firstly, the role of all&#13;
institutions currently involved in the roads sector is not defined. MCT is now responsible&#13;
for setting overall policy on road transport. The Ministry of Finance and Economic&#13;
Development (MFED) has some responsibility for budgeting and planning processes in&#13;
the road sector under separate legislation. In addition, a National Roads Board (NRB)&#13;
has been recently established, under Statutory Instrument No. 42 of 1994, to manage and&#13;
administer the Road Fund and is under the supervision of a Committee of Ministers&#13;
chaired by the Minister of Communications and Transport. Secondly, not all roads in&#13;
Zambia have been designated and of those which have been designated not all have been&#13;
assigned to a particular road authority. This leaves responsibility for management&#13;
unclear, and as a consequence many of these roads have not been maintained. A related&#13;
issue is that the original designation of a particular road may be outdated and that the road&#13;
is not assigned to the most appropriate authority. Thirdly, another issue is that the Act&#13;
makes no specific provision for the financing of roads so that resources may not always&#13;
be available to go with the responsibilities assigned under the Act. This has in the past&#13;
had negative consequences for the quality of the road network. Government intends to&#13;
revise CAP 464 to address these issues and to provide a firmer legislative basis for its&#13;
evolving policy initiatives in the roads sector.&#13;
1.16 A number of other institutions are involved in the roads sector although these do&#13;
not have a direct management function for the road network. Under the Ministry of&#13;
Communications and Transport, the Road Traffic Commission is responsible for motor&#13;
vehicle testing, drivers licenses and road patrols. The National Road Safety Council&#13;
(NRSC), established by Act in 1995, is responsible for planning and programming of&#13;
road safety programs, accident recording and the dissemination of road safety&#13;
information. The Ministry of Environment and Natural Resources through the&#13;
Environment Council of Zambia (ECZ) is responsible for regulation and enforcement of&#13;
environmental legislation as it applies to the road sector. The Zambia National Tender&#13;
Board (ZNTB) has an oversight role in procurement and approves nearly all contracts for&#13;
services and supply.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
IL    Human Resources and Implementation Capacity&#13;
1.17  The capacity of the various road authorities to carry out their responsibilities is&#13;
limited in that the requisite resources, in terms of staff, tools and finance, have generally&#13;
not been made available on a timely and adequate basis. All the authorities are&#13;
constrained to a greater or lesser extent by inadequate capacity due, among others, to&#13;
unfavorable conditions of service prescribed for civil servants, cumbersome tendering&#13;
procedures for purchases of goods and services, delays in making payments for&#13;
completed works and services, low road plant and equipment serviceability due to limited&#13;
repair capacity, and inability to replace salvaged road plant equipment due to shortage of&#13;
capital funding. In addition, the road maintenance program has typically been undertaken&#13;
in the past through force account. This approach has deficiencies in that it depends&#13;
strongly on the experience and motivation of a limited number of supervisors and&#13;
managers. In addition, there are the drawbacks of using poorly trained and motivated&#13;
staff.&#13;
1.18  The Roads Department has suffered from a lack of experienced personnel and has&#13;
in the past found difficulty in retaining senior staff. This shortage of qualified staff was&#13;
and is primarily attributable to the poor terms and conditions of employment for Roads&#13;
Department staff. In 1993, the incomes of engineers including allowances were less than&#13;
15% of comparable staff in the private sector. In the last two years, however, this gap has&#13;
been reduced somewhat and there has been an influx of young Zambian graduate&#13;
engineers joining the Roads Department and only five of the 29 engineering posts are&#13;
presently vacant. 67 out of 84 authorized technician positions are filled. Whereas the&#13;
staffing of the department has thus improved, the quality of technical staff in terms of&#13;
experience to be able to plan, program, supervise, manage and control the work activities&#13;
is yet to be attained. Accordingly, the Department continues to rely on foreign technical&#13;
personnel in certain positions. Training and capacity building is being provided to the&#13;
newly recruited engineers through ongoing donor assistance to the road sector.&#13;
1.19 Under the Public Sector Reform Program (PSRP), a restructuring plan has been&#13;
prepared for the Roads Department as part of the overall restructuring of the Ministry of&#13;
Works and Supply. The plan was adopted in October 1994 although the implementation&#13;
only commenced in 1997. The structure is predicated on a policy of increased reliance on&#13;
the private sector for road construction and maintenance, the phasing out of force account&#13;
and the strengthening of contract management and contractor supervision capabilities.&#13;
Implementation of this structure would have significant implications for the staffing of&#13;
the Roads Department - up to two thirds of casual staff and up to 15% of regular staff&#13;
have been identified as surplus to requirements. It would also require the Roads&#13;
Department to dispose of most of its vehicle and plant pool. The new role of the&#13;
department would generate a demand for more highly qualified and experienced&#13;
personnel and would also require strengthening of the provincial road engineers' offices&#13;
which will fill a critical role in contract management. These changes are being&#13;
underpinned by institutional support programs inter alia from NORAD and FINNIDA.&#13;
In addition, IDA financing through the Transport Engineering and Technical Assistance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
Project (TETAP) is supporting the development of a highway management system&#13;
(HMS) to improve planning capability as well as the preparation of programs to improve&#13;
equipment management and maintenance.&#13;
1.20 No technical capacity for managing the road sector has previously existed in the&#13;
Ministry of Local Government and Housing (MLGH) and this is only now in the process&#13;
of being created. The Government has taken the policy decision to vest in the ministry&#13;
the overarching responsibility for urban and rural district (feeder) roads and has decided&#13;
to create three roads positions within the Department of Infrastructure Support Services&#13;
(DISS), newly established as a consequence of the PSRP for MLGH. The effectiveness&#13;
of this new arrangement cannot as yet be fully determined as these staff are only recently&#13;
recruited and are still in the process of being trained. At present, internal and external&#13;
consultants are supplementing DISS' capacity. Much of this support has been financed&#13;
by IDA through TETAP through which consultants are currently preparing the first&#13;
detailed inventory of feeder roads based on province by province surveys and providing&#13;
training in roads planning to the ministry and to local authority staff. At local authority&#13;
level, technical posts (Director/Deputy Director of Works) are usually only 50% filled&#13;
and the incumbents are called on to address a variety of sectors including roads. The&#13;
lower levels of staff have had limited exposure to roadworks and their capacity is&#13;
correspondingly limited. The capacity of local authorities for implementation of&#13;
roadworks is thus still limited in terms of both physical capacity and experience.&#13;
1.21  NRB is currently managed by a small secretariat reporting to an Executive&#13;
Secretary. Salaries of key staff are being funded externally through the end of 1997 and&#13;
there is a small government budget contribution to cover operating costs. The Board&#13;
itself comprises representatives of the private sector and the public sector. While&#13;
primarily an advisory body to a Committee of Ministers chaired by the Minister of&#13;
Communications and Transport, the NRB has generally been allowed to exercise full&#13;
discretion in the allocation of resources to road maintenance (see para 1.24). The Board&#13;
consists of five ex of icio members representing government ministries (Finance, Works&#13;
and Supplies, Transport and Communications, Local Government, and National&#13;
Commission for Development Planning) and seven members representing road users and&#13;
the business community (Chamber of Commerce, road transport industry, Automobile&#13;
Association, farmers, Institute of Engineers, Chartered Institute of Transport, Copperbelt&#13;
University). All Board members are nominated by the organizations they represent and&#13;
the board elects its own chairperson and vice chairperson (currently from the Chartered&#13;
Institute of Transport and the Automobile Association respectively). The ex officio&#13;
members of the board participate in discussion, but have no vote. There are standing&#13;
committees which make recommendations to the main Board on technical and financial&#13;
matters. Whilst the NRB has only been operational since October 1994, it has been quite&#13;
effective to date in managing the Road Fund despite its limited human resource base.&#13;
More resources than hitherto have been channeled into road maintenance and the works&#13;
have generally been well supervised. Accordingly, Government is favorable to an&#13;
increase in staff complement and to the responsibilities of the NRB in the management of&#13;
the road sector. As a first step, additional expertise in engineering, finance and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10-&#13;
procurement is being recruited to enable NRB to sustain and to subsequently increase the&#13;
size of the road maintenance program. From July 22, 1997 in terms of Statutory&#13;
Instrument No. 93 of 1997, NRB has been given clear authority to hire staff it requires on&#13;
appropriate terms subject to the cost not exceeding 5% of Road Fund revenues.&#13;
III.  Road Financing and Expenditure&#13;
1.22  Funding for road activities has been characterized in the past by lack of reliable&#13;
needs assessment, inadequate financing, heavy dependence on external sources,&#13;
unpredictable budgetary releases, limited accountability and insufficient value for money.&#13;
The level of road maintenance budgets have been erratic and disbursements often cut and&#13;
as a result maintenance programs have had to be deferred. In general, disproportionately&#13;
high amounts of the budget have been allocated to capital programs leaving insufficient&#13;
funds for maintenance. Consequently, while new roads were being constructed, the&#13;
existing network was being neglected resulting in deterioration of significant lengths of&#13;
the road network.&#13;
1.23  There are currently three major sources of funds for road programs: Government&#13;
budget, the donor community and, since 1994, the Road Fund. The Governnent has&#13;
consistently underfunded the road sector. Government's maintenance expenditure was&#13;
only 12% of the total network requirements in 1991, estimated then at US$33.0 million&#13;
equivalent, and has actually been in decline in real terms since. Of the amount budgeted&#13;
for maintenance, only a fraction has been actually released in recent years - the situation&#13;
has worsened with the advent of cash budgeting in 1995 such that effectively the budget&#13;
does not finance maintenance at all at this juncture. The bulk of Government funding for&#13;
the road sector which has been released is intended for counterpart contribution to the&#13;
capital program. Most funding for capital investment in the road sector has, however,&#13;
been made available in terms of donor grants and loans. In addition, it is estimated that&#13;
on average about 80% of maintenance requirements have been funded by donors in recent&#13;
years. This is unsustainable given that the injection of donor capital funds has not been&#13;
balanced by a proportionate increase in maintenance funds by the Government, at least up&#13;
to and including 1994. Over the past five years, annual donor commitments to the road&#13;
sector program have averaged about US$30.0 million per annum in current prices. This&#13;
support fortunately has been and continues to be extensive and well diversified although&#13;
new funding commitments have been adversely effected by the deterioration of donor&#13;
relations since 1996.&#13;
1.24 The Road Fund was re-established in 1993 under Section 8 of Part II of the&#13;
Finance (Control and Management) Act Cap 347 and has been administered since&#13;
October 1994 by the National Roads Board (NRB). A fuel levy of K10 per liter of petrol&#13;
and diesel subsequently increased to K30 per liter in January 1995 and to K40 per liter in&#13;
January 1996. From fiscal 1997, the fuel levy is to be set as a percentage of the&#13;
wholesale price of fuel, currently 15%. These resources accrue to the Road Fund for the&#13;
purpose of funding road maintenance, the only consistent local source of road&#13;
maintenance funds at present. The fuel levy is collected by the oil marketing companies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
and, since June 1997, channeled to the NRB through the Ministry of Communications&#13;
and Transport. Government is committed to streamlining these procedures and to&#13;
ensuring transparency in the flow and use of resources. The NRB has allocated money to&#13;
the Roads Department to maintain main, trunk, and district roads. Further funds have&#13;
been released to the local councils to carry out repairs on urban and feeder roads. Works&#13;
are actually managed by consulting engineers, and to a certain extent by the provincial&#13;
road engineers under the Roads Department, on behalf of these road authorities and&#13;
works are carried out by local private contractors. The fuel levy generated approximately&#13;
US$10.0 million in 1995 and this increased to US$13.0 million in 1996, which still&#13;
represents only 30% of maintenance expenditure requirements. This is currently&#13;
distributed on a regular basis to the various road authorities on the basis of the following&#13;
policy: Roads Department 40%, District Councils 40% and Urban Councils 20%. In&#13;
practice, district councils have been able to utilize only a fraction of this entitlement due&#13;
to capacity constraints. In 1996, disbursements to Lusaka and the Copperbelt towns&#13;
alone were about US$4.0 million equivalent. The amount of the fuel levy is also, at&#13;
present, insufficient to meet all maintenance needs. The Road Fund needs to be&#13;
supported from several sources rather than being totally reliant on the fuel levy.&#13;
Government has thus adopted a policy of paying over a portion of other road user&#13;
charges, e.g., transit fees and vehicle license fees, into the Road Fund to increase&#13;
resources available for maintenance. The Government has committed itself in its sector&#13;
policy letter to taking this approach from fiscal year 1998 (para 1.36).&#13;
IV.  Road Network&#13;
1.25  The extent of the entire road network in Zambia is not yet accurately established.&#13;
The total length of designated roads is about 37,000 kilometers whereas undesignated&#13;
roads may amount to up to 30,000 kilometers according to an estimate produced by&#13;
consultants financed by IDA under TETAP. This latter includes some 5,000 kilometers&#13;
of roads in Zambia's national parks which fall nominally under the responsibility of the&#13;
Department of Parks and Wildlife and an estimated 1,500 kilometers of urban roads. The&#13;
table below summarizes the road network by road class, road surface type and&#13;
responsibility. Zambia's designated road density works out to be 45 kilometers per&#13;
thousand square kilometers of land which is relatively low by Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
standards. By contrast, it has one of the highest lengths of road network per capita in&#13;
Africa, at 3,800 kilometers per million population, which adds to the challenge of&#13;
providing adequate funding for maintenance. A very high proportion of these roads are&#13;
paved in relation to the situation prevailing in Zambia's neighbors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12-&#13;
Table 1-3: Road Network&#13;
Road Surface (KM)&#13;
Road Class            KM of Roads       Paved       Earth       Gravel&#13;
Road Department&#13;
T-Roads                           3,225          3,085         140           -&#13;
M-Roads                           3,943          2,008         216        1,719&#13;
D-Roads                          13,696           1,289      5,670        6,537&#13;
Sub-Total                        20,864          6,582       6,026       8,256&#13;
Local Authorities&#13;
RD-Roads                         10,184              -       9,096        1,088&#13;
R-Roads                           5,714              -       5,714           -&#13;
Urban Roads                       1,543            700           -         843&#13;
Sub-Total                      17,441           700       14,810       1,931&#13;
Parks and Wildlife&#13;
Parks Roads                       5,162              -       4,000        1,162&#13;
Other Rural                      22,483              -      22,483           -&#13;
Grand Total                      65,950          7,282      47,319       11,349&#13;
Of Which Designated              36,762          6,582      20,836        9,344&#13;
Source: Roads Department and Bank Estimates&#13;
1.26   Designated roads are classified according to their construction design standard&#13;
with regard to formation width, carriageway width and surface type. Class 1 roads in&#13;
three subcategories are all bitumenised whereas Classes 11 and 111 roads are gravel&#13;
surface. Earth roads are not classified. A large part of the main road network was&#13;
constructed in the decade between 1965 and 1975. For a long time routine and periodic&#13;
road maintenance have been neglected mainly due to lack of funding. These roads are&#13;
now in the last part of their design life. For the paved network, in 1984 the proportion in&#13;
good, fair and poor condition was 40%, 30% and 30% respectively. However, by 1995&#13;
these proportions had worsened to 20%, 29% and 51 % respectively according to a survey&#13;
of just over 8,800 kilometers of trunk main and district roads. In addition, little or no&#13;
maintenance has been carried out on feeder roads and the condition of these roads is even&#13;
worse, an estimated 90% being in poor condition.&#13;
Table 1-4: 1995 Condition of Some Main Roads&#13;
Road Quality&#13;
Road Class        Good           Fair          Poor           Total&#13;
T-Roads               454           694          1,188           2,336&#13;
M-Roads               771           939          1,782           3,492&#13;
D-Roads               514            893         1,620           3,027&#13;
Total Length         1,739         2,526         4590            8,855&#13;
%             20%            29%           51%            100%&#13;
Source: Roads Department&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
V.   The Road Construction Industry&#13;
1.27  The road construction industry in Zambia is relatively underdeveloped. There&#13;
was a lack of incentive in the past to private sector involvement due to low and erratic&#13;
financing for maintenance and rehabilitation, to cumbersome public sector tendering and&#13;
payment procedures and to the predominant role in the past of public sector force&#13;
account. The Government has, however, now placed high priority on private sector&#13;
construction industry in line with its development objectives and has issued a National&#13;
Policy on the Construction Industry (NPCI). Under this policy, a National Council for&#13;
Construction (NCC) has been reestablished under the Societies Act with private and&#13;
public sector membership and with the goal of reviewing and proposing modifications to&#13;
standards, regulations and legislation affecting the industry and of monitoring&#13;
construction industry development. At present out of 554 formal sector contractors&#13;
registered with the Ministry of Works and Supply only 46 are registered as road&#13;
contractors. According to a recent study financed by IDA under TETAP, the capacity of&#13;
the local road construction industry is put at US$25.0 million per annum. Only 20% of&#13;
this capacity is Zambian majority owned and only about 50% of this capacity is currently&#13;
being utilized. Growth is still constrained by the perception of a lack of sufficient&#13;
demand and by aging and inefficient plant. Informal sector contractors or potential&#13;
contractors cannot readily be estimated but in terms of potential output, employment and&#13;
tumover may be equivalent to or greater than the formal sector. Some specific programs&#13;
are now underway, including the UNDP-funded feeder road program in Eastern Province,&#13;
to encourage labor-based contracting for which increasing opportunities are emerging in&#13;
routine maintenance and rehabilitation of feeder roads in areas where there is a lack of&#13;
existing construction capacity. Under NORAD funding, ILO has been supporting the&#13;
diversification of the Roads Training School's programs to cater for small contractors'&#13;
needs.&#13;
VI.  Road Transport&#13;
1.28 The number of vehicles registered in Zambia during 1975 - 1995 is shown below.&#13;
The data, which are not however considered to be fully reliable, indicate that between&#13;
1975 and 1988 the fleet declined considerably but since then it has more than doubled to&#13;
a fleet strength of 129,000 in 1995, the majority of which are passenger cars. Recent&#13;
survey findings and records at the Road Traffic Commission appear to suggest that the&#13;
private sector currently owns more than 95% of the total road passenger vehicles as well&#13;
as road freight fleet. On the basis of recent averages, there were about 12 vehicles per&#13;
1,000 population in Zambia compared to 47 in the SADC region and to about 20 in Sub&#13;
Saharan Africa as a whole.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
Table 1-5: Estimated Domestic Vehicle Numbers&#13;
Vehicle Type         1975    1980    1984    1988    1992    1995&#13;
|Motor Cycles             10,208    5,164   4,819   5,238    5,000    5,500&#13;
Passenger Cars           94,259   69,003   68,032   26,702   70,000   90,000&#13;
Buses &amp; Minibuses          855      957    1,064    2,545    2,500    4,500&#13;
Vans, Vanettes &amp; Ambulances    29,438   17,821   18,545   18,911   19,000   22,000&#13;
Trucks                   17,293   12,447   16,971    5,597    6,000    7,000&#13;
Total                   1 52,053  105,392  109,431   58,993  102,500  129,000&#13;
Source: Road Traffic Commission&#13;
1.29  Traditionally, road freight transport in Zambia had been broadly divided into three&#13;
main categories: parastatals, notably Contract Haulage (CHL), ZAM-TAN and the&#13;
Zambia Co-operative Federation (ZCF) transport division; members of the Truckers&#13;
Association of Zambia (TAZA)/Federation of Road Hauliers (FEDHAUL); and&#13;
independent and own account operators. Up until the mid-1980s, the road haulage&#13;
industry was dominated by parastatals but these have either collapsed through&#13;
inefficiency or have been very much reduced in importance. The advent of deregulation&#13;
and privatization has helped private haulage to emerge as a formidable force in the&#13;
domestic road haulage sector. The average number of operational trucks per day is&#13;
estimated at 60 and 2,000 for parastatals and private sector respectively. The average&#13;
distance covered per month per vehicle is 6,000 km and 12,000 km for parastatals and&#13;
private sector respectively. In this period also, the dominance of road freight over other&#13;
modes has been established - road accounted for 60% of all freight in 1994 compared to&#13;
under 20% in 1989.&#13;
1.30  Since the mid- 1 980s, the quality of road passenger transport has been generally&#13;
poor. During the 1 990s, public transport services can be described as a declining&#13;
dominance of the public sector and increasing importance of the private sector.&#13;
Following the temporary suspension of duty on commercial buses from 1994 and the&#13;
liquidation of the United Bus Company of Zambia (UBZ) at the beginning of 1995, the&#13;
number of passenger carrying vehicles has increased by an estimated 75%. Fares are now&#13;
broadly set by market forces with minimal government intervention which is seen as&#13;
generally favorable to further private sector involvement in passenger transport. The&#13;
Road Traffic Commission remains responsible for issuance of licenses and for vehicle&#13;
inspection. Rural areas are not fully catered for in terms of motorized transport. Survey&#13;
findings in three provinces, Luapula, Northern and Southern, confirm that walking and to&#13;
a lesser extent bicycles are the predominant means of transport (90% of trips) in villages,&#13;
the major explanatory variable being the poor state of roads in rural areas and the lack of&#13;
access to credit for small operators.&#13;
VII. Road Safety and Accidents&#13;
1.31  With a recent average of over 900 persons killed in road accidents every year,&#13;
Zambia has one of the highest fatality rates per 1,000 vehicles, both in the sub-region, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
among developing countries. About 118 persons are killed every year in road accidents&#13;
per every 1,000 vehicles in Zambia compared to an average of 71 in the SADC region or&#13;
about 62 in Sub Saharan Africa (average of sixteen countries). Pedestrians constitute&#13;
42% of fatal road accident victims in Zambia followed by passengers of motor vehicles at&#13;
36%. The poor are a disproportionally large element among pedestrian casualties.&#13;
Important causal factors relate to incompetent driving exacerbated by inadequate traffic&#13;
signs and faulty vehicles. Further, unmaintained and sub-standard roads have contributed&#13;
to accidents, especially on busy urban roads. Efforts to date to arrest the increasing&#13;
incidence of accidents have not been particularly effective. This has not been helped by&#13;
the involvement of a number of institutions in the area of road safety whose interventions&#13;
have not been well coordinated. The creation of a National Road Safety Council in 1995&#13;
with significant private sector involvement could address the issue more effectively in&#13;
future provided the Council would have adequate financial and human resources at its&#13;
disposal.&#13;
1.32  Road accidents cause both tangible and intangible costs to the economy. Tangible&#13;
costs include direct costs such as: (i) direct damage to the vehicles (replacement of parts);&#13;
(ii) policing and administration costs; (iii) medical treatment and indirect costs of injury;&#13;
(iv) reduction in output due to injury and death; and insurance costs. Intangible costs&#13;
include pain, grief and suffering and the risk of being involved in an accident. In&#13;
economic terms, it is estimated that the cost of road accidents to the Zambian economy is&#13;
over US$78.0 million or 2.3% of the Gross National Product (GNP) in 1995. Since all&#13;
vehicles are imported, this amount also represents the scarce foreign exchange that has to&#13;
be earned and spent.&#13;
VIII. Environmental Aspects&#13;
1.33  Historically, there had been neither emphasis on nor any legal requirements for&#13;
road authorities submitting environmental impact analyses (EIA) for road works. The&#13;
few EIAs which had been done on some roads had been as a result of the requirement by&#13;
some donor or international funding agencies. However, new EIA guidelines have been&#13;
finalized by the Environmental Council of Zambia (ECZ) and the necessary enabling&#13;
legislation passed - The Environmental Protection and Pollution Control (Environmental&#13;
Impact Assessment) Regulations, 1997. These regulations require that a project brief and&#13;
environmental impact study be performed for any new project, extension, or maintenance&#13;
of an existing project. The EIA guidelines will still need to be customized to the needs of&#13;
the road sector. The environmental impact of new road construction is considerable but&#13;
that of rehabilitation and maintenance programs much less so. Aspects which require&#13;
particular attention are: management of road realignment and diversion; borrow pits and&#13;
construction camps; and road safety during construction and/or maintenance. In advance&#13;
of proposed road sector investment program and under funding provided from TETAP,&#13;
the Government appointed a local consultant to provide an environmental impact analysis&#13;
and to propose specific mitigation measures, including the creation of environmental&#13;
management capacity in the roads sector. On the basis of this report, an environmental&#13;
management committee was established in October 1996 with private and public sector&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16-&#13;
participation to put together specific proposals for strengthening environmental&#13;
management in the roads sector. Among other things, the committee has drawn up terms&#13;
of reference and has arranged the recruitment of specialized consultancy services to firstly&#13;
prepare road sector environmental standards and guidelines for use in all future road&#13;
works, and to secondly staff an environmental management unit attached to Roads Dept.&#13;
for a pilot phase of two years.&#13;
IX.   Lessonsfrom Previous Bank Group Programs&#13;
1.34 Experience from three past highways lending operations in Zambia (Third&#13;
Highway Project loan number 1566-ZA, Second Highway Project loan number 563-ZA&#13;
and First Highway Project loan number 469-ZA) indicate the persistence of a number of&#13;
problems hampering effective sector development, i.e.: lack of commitment to road&#13;
maintenance; weak institutions and a shortage of qualified staff; inadequate planning and&#13;
programming; and insufficient and unpredictable budget allocations for road&#13;
maintenance. A number of these shortcomings are already being addressed through&#13;
measures Government has adopted such as increased, dedicated maintenance funding and&#13;
through an ongoing a program of studies, technical assistance and workshops to develop a&#13;
sustainable system for the management and financing of roads. The Bank Group is&#13;
making a major contribution to these efforts, through both the Road Maintenance&#13;
Initiative (RMI) and through TETAP. Through RMI, and particularly the February 1993&#13;
workshop, broad consensus was developed in Zambia on the need for institutional reform&#13;
and improvement in the financing arrangements for road maintenance - subsequent&#13;
decisions on the creation of the Road Fund and NRB owe a good deal to this initiative.&#13;
Through TETAP and as noted above, the Bank has tendered support to a number of&#13;
activities preparatory to the launching of a comprehensive sector investment program&#13;
including: strengthening of the management and financing of roads; support to the new&#13;
urban and feeder road function in MLGH; establishing a highway management system&#13;
(HMS) in Roads Dept.; studies on the construction and consulting industries and&#13;
equipment management and maintenance. In addition, the design of the proposed&#13;
program explicitly incorporates lessons learnt from recent Africa region experience in&#13;
building sustainable roads programs, notably in: Tanzania - Integrated Roads Project-IRP&#13;
(Credit No. 2149-TAN); Mozambique - Roads and Coastal Shipping Project-ROCS II&#13;
(Credit No. 2599-MOZ); and Ghana - Highway Sector Investment Program (Credit No.&#13;
2858-GH). Particular note has been taken of the following points: using an integrated&#13;
sector approach; carefully phasing policy reforms and investrnents; stimulating the&#13;
development of a local contracting industry through the provision of suitably packaged&#13;
works; resolving early in the project maintenance funding and organizational issues; and&#13;
emphasizing capacity-building by using short-term TA and local consultants, and&#13;
ensuring transfer of skills to identified counterparts.&#13;
1.35  Important lessons have also been gleaned from the experience of ongoing sector&#13;
investment programs in other sectors, including the health and agricultural sectors in&#13;
Zambia. The potential benefits from sector wide approaches are significant but&#13;
experience suggests that there are high risks especially where all preconditions are not in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
place. The lessons of experience suggest the following are particularly important: sector&#13;
investment and expenditure programs need to be embedded in good economic and sector&#13;
strategy; strong analytical underpinning to the design of the program is required including&#13;
adequacy of institutional arrangements and local capacity; broad participation of&#13;
stakeholders and genuine and committed leadership from the country is essential as&#13;
opposed to from the Bank or donor community. Experience in Zambia, especially in the&#13;
health sector, demonstrates the value of a flexible approach in that policy and program&#13;
implementation goals need to be reviewed, and adjusted where necessary on a regular&#13;
basis, as the real capacity of the country to deliver on the ground becomes apparent.&#13;
X     Road Sector Development Strategy&#13;
1.36 The government's road sector development strategy starts from the&#13;
aforementioned white paper on communications and transport (para 1.13). The strategy&#13;
also incorporates the key findings and recommendations of earlier sector studies, notably&#13;
the Road Maintenance, Organization and Training Study (RMOTS) completed in August&#13;
1993 under AfDB funding, which identified the need for sector reforms. The key&#13;
elements of the strategy to be followed in order to address the inadequacy of road&#13;
infrastructure, meet growing traffic demand and increase access in rural areas are set out&#13;
in the letter of March 21, 1997 of the Minister of Finance and Economic Development to&#13;
the President of the Bank which deals with road sector policies and the road sector&#13;
investment program and which is at Annex 1-1. The Government's sector strategy lays&#13;
particular emphasis on:&#13;
(a)   Creating an appropriate institutional framework for the management of the&#13;
road sector.&#13;
(b)   Rehabilitating priority roads in view of the large backlog of works.&#13;
(c)   Ensuring effective arrangements for the management and financing of&#13;
maintenance.&#13;
(d)   Developing the domestic construction and consulting industry.&#13;
(e)   Improving community accessibility and mitigating environmental impacts.&#13;
1.37  These strategic considerations have come about as a result of an intensive&#13;
preparation process piloted by the Government through MCT. The process has, however,&#13;
relied on significant input from the community of local stakeholders. A national task&#13;
force was established in June 1995 to prepare a road sector investment program after&#13;
extensive consultation with local stakeholders and with the donor and NGO communities.&#13;
The Bank has actively supported this process by providing part of the funding&#13;
requirements of preparing position papers - on inter alia road transport, road safety,&#13;
environmental considerations, selection criteria and community road management -&#13;
which were presented as a basis for discussion at a stakeholder workshop in February&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18-&#13;
1996. The workshop endorsed the proposed road sector investment program (ROADSIP)&#13;
which was subsequently discussed by and agreed to by the Committee of Ministers and&#13;
which forms the basis of the proposed operation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19-&#13;
2. THE PROGRAM AND THE PROJECT&#13;
A.   Program and Project Objectives&#13;
2.1   The overriding goal of the Government for the roads sector is to facilitate&#13;
economic growth and diversification (particularly in the agricultural sector) through&#13;
appropriate investments in road infrastructure and through a sustainable system for the&#13;
financing and management of the road network. The Government's medium term&#13;
program, ROADSIP, is expected over a 10-year time horizon to address this goal and has&#13;
the following other major objectives:&#13;
(a)   bringing a core network of 33,500 kilometers into maintainable condition;&#13;
(b)   bringing the condition of the road network to at least 50% good and about&#13;
10% poor for all types of road;&#13;
(c)   strengthening the technical and managerial capacity of road authorities;&#13;
(d)   creating employment opportunities in the road sector and alleviating&#13;
poverty through the creation of 30,000 new jobs in road maintenance;&#13;
(e)  improving road safety and reducing road accidents by at least 20%;&#13;
(f)  improving environmental management in the road sector through&#13;
establishing procedures and guidelines;&#13;
(g)   providing an enabling environment for improved road transport services&#13;
and increasing the truck and bus fleet by at least 20% in rural areas; and&#13;
(h)   developing a framework for the management of community roads and&#13;
promoting community participation in road management.&#13;
2.2   The project addresses the first time slice of the program for the period 1997-2002&#13;
and is expected to contribute to the realization of the program goals. The five specific&#13;
objectives of the project are:&#13;
(a)   reform of the road sector policy and institutional framework, including&#13;
changes to the legal framework for roads and road traffic management and&#13;
strengthening and refocusing the roles of sector institutions (NRB, Roads&#13;
Dept., and MLGH) aimed at enhancing capacity, increasing efficiency of&#13;
the use of resources and improving planning and implementation&#13;
performance;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-20-&#13;
(b)   strengthening of road sector financing aimed at ensuring the sustainability&#13;
of the road maintenance effort and reducing the strain on limited&#13;
government revenues with the specific targets of streamlining the&#13;
functioning of the Road Fund and increasing and diversifying road user&#13;
charges to ensure at minimum 70% coverage of periodic and routine&#13;
maintenance costs of the core network by 2002;&#13;
(c)   strengthening of the local construction and consulting industry in line with&#13;
country objectives of creating greater opportunities for the private sector to&#13;
participate in the design, construction and maintenance of roads and with&#13;
the specific target of creating 14,000 new jobs by 2002;&#13;
(d)   addressing the road maintenance and rehabilitation backlog through a&#13;
priority investment program with the specific target of increasing the&#13;
proportion of main roads in good condition to about 45% and the&#13;
proportion of feeder roads in good condition to about 15% of the network&#13;
by the year 2002; and&#13;
(e)   establishing a pilot program for community road management in at least&#13;
three districts to test approaches for sustainable improvements in&#13;
maintenance of these undesignated roads and to promote increased usage&#13;
of non-motorized transport means.&#13;
B.   Rationale for IDA Involvement&#13;
2.3   The Bank's Country Assistance Strategy (CAS) dated June 25, 1996, and&#13;
discussed by the Board July 18, 1996, supports the Zambian Government's development&#13;
objectives and policies. The Bank is supporting a three pronged strategy - helping to&#13;
create a stable macroeconomic environment, to promote private sector development and&#13;
greater public sector efficiency, and to target assistance to poor and vulnerable groups.&#13;
To this end, the Government wishes to address current transport infrastructure&#13;
deficiencies and has identified the need for integrated road sector development associated&#13;
with policies to increase private sector participation in the road sector, to increase the&#13;
volume of self financing and to improve rural accessibility. The CAS underlines the&#13;
importance of improved infrastructure, particularly in transport, for growth and for&#13;
poverty reduction. The Bank is uniquely well placed to help government deliver a road&#13;
sector program that is consonant with its development objectives. The Bank has been&#13;
strongly associated with the changes recently effected in the roads sector. Through the&#13;
1992 public expenditure review for the transport sector and through the Road&#13;
Maintenance Initiative (RMI), which is a multi-donor program managed by the Bank,&#13;
critical impetus has been given to sector reform, and to the establishment of the Road&#13;
Fund and the NRB in particular. The RMI program in Zambia is ongoing and provides&#13;
for a number of capacity building and dissemination programs which are helping build&#13;
consensus among stakeholders on the need for, and the direction of change, including&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
greater involvement of the private sector. IDA's involvement in the proposed program&#13;
will help ensure that stakeholder coordination is maintained throughout.&#13;
C.   Project Description&#13;
(a)   Civil Works&#13;
2.4   The civil works component will focus on the priority needs for road maintenance&#13;
and rehabilitation for the period 1997-2002 which is expected to cover about 22,000&#13;
kilometers out of the core network. The program also includes limited accessibility&#13;
improvement on up to 17,000 kilometers of feeder roads, including some currently&#13;
undesignated roads, only a portion of which will eventually be upgraded to full&#13;
engineering standard. The program is inclusive of ongoing works. The component&#13;
would include inter-territorial trunk, territorial main, district, and primary feeder and&#13;
urban roads in all provinces of the country. A large part of the unpaved road including&#13;
90% of the feeder roads and 41% of the district roads are non-engineered and are&#13;
inadequate in terms of both geometric dimensions and structural strength of the road&#13;
pavement. Poor/non-engineered roads will need to be upgraded to an acceptable standard&#13;
before they qualify for regular maintenance.&#13;
2.5   Given the large part of the core road network has suffered due to prolonged&#13;
backlog of road maintenance, the civil works program is based on an optimum balance&#13;
of: (a) carrying out routine and periodic maintenance on all good and fair roads in order&#13;
to avoid a further increase in the maintenance backlog; (b) rehabilitation of poor roads&#13;
based on priority ranking, based on economic rate of return for most main and urban&#13;
roads and on multi criteria selection for feeder roads and for some low volume main&#13;
roads, and the roads after rehabilitation would be placed under annual routine&#13;
maintenance and pluri-annual periodic maintenance program; (c) upgrading important&#13;
non-engineered roads based on the above agreed selection criteria; and (d) providing all-&#13;
weather possibility to the strategic links of non-engineered roads, particularly during peak&#13;
agriculture seasons. The strategy does not provide for any new road construction, but&#13;
rather places emphasis on gradually reducing the proportion of the road network that is&#13;
poor, i.e. from 56% to 19% for main roads and from 90% to 71% of feeder roads by the&#13;
end of project period. A detailed description is at Annex 2-1. The main sub-components&#13;
are as follows, with estimated base costs given in parentheses:&#13;
(a)   Routine maintenance (US$70.1 million). The annual routine maintenance&#13;
program would cover only good and fair roads, the volume of which will&#13;
increase over the course of the program. The program will amount to&#13;
about 6,700 km in 1997 and is expected to rise to 15,700 km by 2002.&#13;
(b)   Periodic Maintenance (US$75.6 million). The periodic maintenance&#13;
program would focus on preserving the network from further deterioration&#13;
especially unpaved roads with low traffic volume. The component would&#13;
include resealing/ resurfacing of about 1,200 km of paved roads and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
regravelling of 5,400 km of unpaved roads both inclusive of spot repairs&#13;
on the surface area of less than 10%. Periodicity for periodic maintenance&#13;
of both paved and unpaved roads would be generally in the range of 6 to&#13;
10 years.&#13;
(c)   Rehabilitation (US$145.0 million). Rehabilitation will be carried out on&#13;
1,200 km of paved trunk and main roads and on 300 km of paved urban&#13;
roads. After completing rehabilitation works the roads will be covered&#13;
under the regular maintenance program.&#13;
(d)   Upgrading (US$32.8 million). Upgrading of non-engineered roads is&#13;
necessary before they can be placed under a regular maintenance program.&#13;
The project would include the provisions for upgrading about 2,600 km of&#13;
unpaved (district and feeder) roads to acceptable engineering standards.&#13;
(e)   ImprovingAccessibility (US$24.0 million). Non-engineered roads not&#13;
covered under the phased program of upgrading must be kept passable,&#13;
especially during the peak agriculture season. This intervention will,&#13;
however, be carried out only on selected road sections on initially 17,000&#13;
kilometers falling to 14,400 kilometers by 2002 as selected roads are&#13;
upgraded during the project.&#13;
2.6   The program has been developed taking into account planning, implementation&#13;
and supervision capacity of NRB, Roads Dept. and MLGH, assessing the capacity of&#13;
local contractors and the expected availability of counterpart and donors financing,&#13;
including for ongoing works. The program is based on the most likely or medium case&#13;
scenario which is broadly consistent with the program proposed in Government's letter of&#13;
sector policy. But because of uncertainties regarding future implementation capacity and&#13;
funding availability, a low case and a high case scenario have also been developed and&#13;
are at Annex 2-1. The high case assumes that all the backlog of periodic maintenance will&#13;
be addressed during the project period and that the Government's quality improvement&#13;
goal for the program can be achieved within five years. The low case assumes none of&#13;
the backlog is addressed and that a very limited rehabilitation program is undertaken to&#13;
ensure no further network deterioration in aggregate. All three cases presume that the&#13;
routine maintenance requirements of the network in good and fair condition are met as&#13;
the first priority. The priority program for which works will commence in the first two&#13;
years has been defined in detail as a condition of negotiations (see para 5.1) whereas the&#13;
program for the outer years remains indicative at this stage. The program for the outer&#13;
years is to be firmed up after the process of annual review of program implementation has&#13;
determined the implementation capacity and the availability of local and foreign&#13;
financing and any proposals will have been made and agreed to by Government for&#13;
modifying the scope and objectives of the civil works program in these years. The&#13;
criteria for the selection of projects have been proposed by Government and agreed to by&#13;
IDA as a condition of credit negotiations (para 5.1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
(b)   Community Accessibility Program&#13;
2.7   The component for community road and road transport development (US$6.3&#13;
million) is aimed at improving access for the poor. In recognition of the importance for&#13;
the country's development of increasing the access of the poor to the market economy&#13;
and to essential services, a separate and innovative program will be included with the&#13;
objective of developing a framework for sustainable management of community road&#13;
infrastructure and of creating an enabling environment for the increased use of&#13;
intermediate means of transport (IMT). The program will be carried out in conjunction&#13;
with MLGH and the Social Recovery Project Unit(SRPU) and will start on a pilot basis&#13;
in one province (Eastern) in up to three districts and will eventually be mainstreamed on&#13;
the basis of the pilot exercise. Up to 500 km of roads and bridges are expected to be&#13;
covered under the program under about 70 separate subprojects to the cost of which&#13;
communities will contribute in cash or in kind. At least 10 subprojects are to be&#13;
implemented in the first year of the program. The component would also cover technical&#13;
assistance support in the areas of community development, including a roads technical&#13;
specialist for the SRPU; training support in the areas of participatory assessment; labor&#13;
based construction methods; and finance and business management; a program of studies&#13;
and a demonstration program for IMT options to increase rural mobility. The recently&#13;
established Zambia country program of the Rural Travel and Transport Program (RTTP),&#13;
which is administered by the Bank and which is funded by bilateral donors, will support&#13;
the pilot initiative. The legal status of community roads will be addressed as part of the&#13;
policy support component under the MCT (para 2.9)&#13;
(c)   Construction Industry Development Program&#13;
2.8   The component for promoting the development of local construction and&#13;
consulting capacity (US$2.8 million) is aimed at increasing capacity to meet growing&#13;
needs for road maintenance and rehabilitation and addressing constraints to the fuller&#13;
involvement of local contractors, particularly small labor based contractors, in the road&#13;
program. The component includes the following subcomponents: (a) technical assistance&#13;
for improving Government contracting policies and procedures, including streamlining of&#13;
contractor registration procedures, developing new simplified tendering procedures and&#13;
contract documentation, and streamlining of the legal framework; and (b) further&#13;
development of training programs for contractors with particular emphasis on labor based&#13;
methods and strengthening the capacity of the Roads Training School. The Ministry of&#13;
Works and Supply is responsible for construction industry development and will thus&#13;
coordinate this component. The ministry will work closely with the National Council for&#13;
Construction (NCC) which has been reestablished in July 1996 to provide a more&#13;
effective forum for the private sector to discuss issues and agree on action plans for&#13;
construction industry development. It is thus envisaged that support will be provided to&#13;
NCC through the project to enable it to effectively carry out its mandate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
(d)   Institutional Capacity Building&#13;
2.9   Technical assistance and training in the areas of policy support, implementation&#13;
support and institutional development (US$5.8 million). The strong focus of this project&#13;
is support to strengthening of sector capacity through restructuring road sector institutions&#13;
and improving management structures. The main elements of the component include:&#13;
(a) policy support: analysis and evaluation of the impact of program road sector&#13;
institutional strengthening measures; analysis and evaluation of measures taken to&#13;
strengthen road sector financing through streamlining management of the Road Fund and&#13;
diversifying road user charges; development of a road safety action program including&#13;
strengthening of NRSC; development of a program for the reform of the legal framework&#13;
for roads and road transport, including regulation and licensing of the private sector; and&#13;
improvement in axle load management; (b) implementation support: technical assistance&#13;
support to program implementation in NRB, to support to help manage the feeder road&#13;
program in MLGH and in local authorities, and to project supervision in Roads Dept.;&#13;
and (c) institutional development: develop NRB and Roads Dept. capacity in the&#13;
following areas: environmental analysis and monitoring, contracts management,&#13;
financial management, equipment management and maintenance, selection criteria,&#13;
procurement management and quality assurance, and data bases for core network&#13;
management; and develop an urban road management system for MLGH.&#13;
(e)   Engineering Services&#13;
2.10  Technical assistance for feasibility studies, engineering design and supervision of&#13;
rehabilitation and maintenance works (US$20.8 million).&#13;
D.   Project Strategy&#13;
2.11  The Government fully recognizes the seriousness of the sector problems and is&#13;
adopting a strategy of rationalizing the planning, construction and maintenance of roads,&#13;
of ensuring adequate funding is made available in a sustainable fashion, and addressing&#13;
the lack of road infrastructure to increase access especially in rural areas. The&#13;
govermment's strategy is to build carefully and sequentially on recent improvements in&#13;
the management and financing of roads through further strengthening of the policy and&#13;
institutional framework and to build up the size and scope of the maintenance and&#13;
rehabilitation program commensurate with available capacity. The medium term&#13;
objective remains that of deepening reform of the sector institutional framework in line&#13;
with the policy of fully commercializing the road sector. The Government expects that,&#13;
once road sector institutions have been strengthened as a first step in this direction under&#13;
the present program, rationalization of these institutions can take place with a view to&#13;
establishing a single national road organization with overarching responsibility for road&#13;
sector management. The sector policy letter clearly indicates Government's preparedness&#13;
to modify or accelerate this institutional strategy should this be necessary to address&#13;
problems and issues that may arise during implementation. The Government has&#13;
specified particular objectives for the coming five years for the road sector on which basis&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
it will determine how and over what period of time the balance of ROADSIP goals can be&#13;
achieved. There are three other important strategic developments which underpin the&#13;
program. Firstly, explicit attention is to be given to addressing constraints to the fuller&#13;
participation of the private sector in roads. Secondly, the program recognizes the&#13;
particular problems of rural accessibility and seeks to address this with a view to&#13;
increasing participation in the market economy. Thirdly, the government has sought to&#13;
actively involve all stakeholders in the preparation of the program and will support a&#13;
policy of systematic involvement of these groups in program implementation.&#13;
E.   Project Cost&#13;
2.12  The five-year project (including physical and price contingencies) is estimated to&#13;
cost US$459.8 million of which about 55% would be in foreign exchange. Of the base&#13;
costs of about US$383.2 million, about US$347.5 million would be for civil works,&#13;
including US$70.1 million on routine maintenance, US$75.6 million on periodic&#13;
maintenance, US$145.0 million on rehabilitation of selected roads, US$32.8 million on&#13;
upgrading of feeder roads, and US$24.0 million on accessibility improvement for feeder&#13;
roads. The cost of the community program would be US$6.3 million, US$2.8 million&#13;
would be the cost of the construction industry development program, US$5.8 million the&#13;
cost of the institutional capacity building and US$20.8 million the cost of engineering&#13;
services. The cost estimates for rehabilitation works were prepared in June 1996 and&#13;
updated in February 1997 based on the prices given in the recently awarded contracts.&#13;
The unit rates for maintenance operations were derived from the data entered in the HMS.&#13;
A summary cost table is included below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Table 2-1: Summary of Project Cost (US$ million)&#13;
Project Components                                     Local      Foreign   Total&#13;
A. Civil Works&#13;
*  Routine maintenance of the core network              51.9       18.2      70.1&#13;
*  Periodic maintenance of the core network             49.1       26.5      75.6&#13;
*  Rehabilitation of selected roads                     29.0      116.0     145.0&#13;
Upgrading offeeder roads                              6.6      26.2      32.8&#13;
*  Accessibility improvement for feeder roads            15.6       8.4      24.0&#13;
Subtotal Civil Works                                    152.2     195.3     347.5&#13;
B. Community Accessibility Program                        1.3       5.0       6.3&#13;
C. Construction Industry Development Program              0.0       2.8       2.8&#13;
D. Institutional Capacity Building                        1.9       3.9       5.8&#13;
E. Engineering Services                                   8.3      12.5       20.8&#13;
Total Base Costs                                        163.7     219.5     383.2&#13;
Physical Contingencies                                   15.3      20.0      35.3&#13;
Price Contingencies                                     26.3       15.0      41.3&#13;
Total Project Cost                                     205.3      254.5     459.8&#13;
2.13   The estimated annual costs of the various components of the civil works program&#13;
are given below. Maintenance expenditure will increase year-by-year as capacity is built&#13;
up and as the percentage of the network in good and fair condition increases.&#13;
Expenditure on maintenance in real terms is not, however, expected to stabilize until after&#13;
year 2002, in fact no earlier than.the year 2007, by which point the maintenance backlog&#13;
is expected to have been fully addressed. The rehabilitation program for the first two&#13;
years is largely based on the expected expenditure on ongoing or already committed&#13;
donor funded projects with the addition some of the works to be funded from the&#13;
proposed IDA credit.&#13;
Table 2-2: 1997-2002 Estimated Costs of Civil Works (US$ million)&#13;
Year                        1997/98      1999     2000       2001      2002       Total&#13;
Routine Maintenance           9.2        11.3     13.5       16.5       19.5       70.1&#13;
Periodic Maintenance         14.7        14.5     15.6       15.4       15.3       75.6&#13;
Subtotal                     23.9       25.8      29.1       31.9      34.8       145.7&#13;
Rehabilitation               15.0       30.0      33.0       25.0      42.0       145.0&#13;
Upgrading                     3.6         5.5      6.4        8.2       9.1        32.8&#13;
Accessibility Improvement     5.1         5.1      4.9        4.6       4.3        24.0&#13;
Grand Total                  47.6       66.4      73.4       69.7      90.4       347.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
F.    Project Financing&#13;
2.14  The total contribution from local sources is expected to be about US$157.8&#13;
million. Of this amount US$115.0 million is to be mobilized from the existing fuel levy&#13;
and US$16.0 million from other road user charges both to be channeled through the Road&#13;
Fund (see paras 2.16-2.17). An estimated US$14.5 million towards counterpart funding&#13;
for ongoing rehabilitation works and an additional US$12.3 million towards counterpart&#13;
funding of new upgrading and rehabilitation works will come from the Government&#13;
budget. The total estimated external financing requirement is thus put at US$302.0&#13;
million. IDA will provide US$77.5 million, of which about US$7.5 million from&#13;
ongoing projects, which would finance about 16% of the total project cost. The balance&#13;
is expected to be provided out of ongoing and new commitments by other donors.&#13;
Ongoing commitments are estimated at US$116.5 million and estimated new financing to&#13;
be negotiated in 1997 and to be made available for the project is US$65.0 million. With&#13;
satisfactory performance of the project, it is not anticipated that it would be difficult to&#13;
mobilize the balance of funding of US$55.5 million required for the project. In the event&#13;
that other donors cannot commit to this balance, accelerating additional IDA financing&#13;
could be considered. This will be explicitly built into the agenda for discussion at mid-&#13;
term review. In the event of less than satisfactory implementation performance, the low&#13;
case scenario for civil works comes into play for which no additional external financing&#13;
would be needed. A summary of the financing is given below.&#13;
Table 2-3: Summary of Probable Project Financing (US$ million)&#13;
Source         Local     Foreign     Total     Percent&#13;
Road Users          91.7       39.3      131.0      28.5&#13;
Government          26.8       0.0       26.8        5.8&#13;
Local Sub Total       118.5       39.3      157.8&#13;
Ongoing/Committed&#13;
IDA                                       7.5        1.6&#13;
AfDB                                      17.0       3.7&#13;
EU                                       20.0        4.3&#13;
Denmark                                  32.0        7.0&#13;
Germany                                   4.0        0.9&#13;
Japan                                    20.0        4.3&#13;
Norway                                     6.5       1.4&#13;
UNDP                                       6.5       1.4&#13;
Finland                                   2.0        0.4&#13;
Others                                     1.0       0.2&#13;
Foreign Sub Total      22.5       94.0      116.5&#13;
New financing&#13;
IDA                                          70.0      15.2&#13;
Norway                                       20.0       4.3&#13;
Denmark                                      40.0       8.6&#13;
New Foreign Sub Total  45.0       85.0      130.0&#13;
To be Identified       19.3       36.2       55.5      12.1&#13;
Grand Total        205.3      254.5      459.8     100.0&#13;
Source: Ministry of Communications and Transport and Bank estimates&#13;
G.    Foreign Funding&#13;
2.15 The proposed IDA credit of US$70.0 million would finance various components&#13;
of the proposed program. In addition, an estimated amount of U$6.5 million will be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
made available from the Zambia Agricultural Marketing and Processing Project&#13;
(ZAMPIP) to finance part of the costs of the feeder road upgrading and accessibility&#13;
improvement components. TETAP, which is currently scheduled to be completed mid-&#13;
1998, will continue to fund the technical assistance to the feeder road section in MLGH&#13;
up to an estimated amount of US$1.0 million. On closure of the IDA credit for TETAP,&#13;
currently scheduled after one extension for June 30, 1998, the balance of this&#13;
commitment will be absorbed under the new credit for the program.&#13;
2.16  A number of donors have ongoing commitments or programs under&#13;
implementation thus: (i) African Development Bank (AfDB) for US$17.0 million for&#13;
Great East Road rehabilitation Lusaka to Luangwa Bridge; (ii) European Union (EU)&#13;
US$20.0 million for the feeder roads program in Central and Copperbelt provinces,&#13;
Kabwe-Kapiri Mposhi engineering and Chisambe district road rehabilitation; (iii)&#13;
Norway US$6.5 million for main road rehabilitation in the Southern province&#13;
(Mazabuka-Monze); (iv) Denmark US$32.0 million for Kapiri Mposhi - Serenje&#13;
rehabilitation and Luangwa Bridge rehabilitation; (v) Germany US$4.0 million for&#13;
Western and North Westem provinces, both main and feeder roads, and for Livingstone-&#13;
Sesheke engineering; and (vi) Japan US$20.0 million for the first phase of Lusaka urban&#13;
roads' rehabilitation. Other donors include for US$6.5 million for feeder road&#13;
improvement in Eastern Province which is being executed by UNCDF in collaboration&#13;
with ILO.&#13;
2. 17 Support for institutional development is from Norway and Finland by way of the&#13;
continuation of ongoing programs through 1997. Norway is expected to continue its&#13;
assistance under a new four-year program agreement to be concluded in mid-1997 for a&#13;
total of about US$20.0 million which will also cover some civil works. Denmark is&#13;
expected to discuss additional program support for priority civil works with the&#13;
Government in the later part of 1997. Extension of ongoing programs of other donors is&#13;
also likely, but has been excluded from consideration in total foreign funding. In&#13;
addition, donor support will be forthcoming through the Zambia Country Programs of&#13;
the Road Maintenance Initiative (RMI) and Rural Travel and Transport Program (RTTP)&#13;
in the respective amounts of US$0.2 million and US$0.4 million over the program.&#13;
These programs are administered by IDA and managed in Zambia by respectively the&#13;
RMI Coordinator in MCT and the RTTP Coordinator in MLGH. An IDA-administered&#13;
grant from the Japanese Policy and Human Resource Development Fund of US$0.4&#13;
million has been made available for workshops, study tours and exchange programs and&#13;
technical assistance and training.&#13;
H.   Local Funding&#13;
2.18  Local funding is to cover 100% of an increased routine maintenance program and&#13;
on average the local cost portion of the periodic maintenance program, i.e., about 40% of&#13;
total cost - it is anticipated though (and built into IDA credit disbursements arrangements,&#13;
see para 3.18) that the local portion will increase over the life of the project. In addition,&#13;
on average about 10% of the rehabilitation program costs are projected to have to come&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
from local resources. In policy terms, the Road Fund is to finance out of its revenues (i)&#13;
as a first charge, routine and periodic maintenance on the core network in good and fair&#13;
condition, (ii) as a second charge, counterpart funding required on donor grants and loans&#13;
made available for rehabilitation the program (or by the government budget where&#13;
funding is insufficient) and (iii) Road Fund running costs from July 1997 onward, which&#13;
are not to exceed 5% of the proceeds of total Road Fund revenue. Appropriate legislation&#13;
to allow for (iii) was published July 1997 as a condition of credit negotiations (see&#13;
para 5.1). The long run goal is to develop the resource base of the Road Fund to bring it&#13;
to a level sufficient to cover the entire maintenance requirement of Zambia's entire core&#13;
network. This is estimated at US$45.0 million per annum in current prices as and when&#13;
the core network would have been brought into either good or fair condition by or about&#13;
year 2007.&#13;
2.19  Government's policy is that there should be cost sharing on urban and rural&#13;
district (feeder) roads as well as on community (unclassified) roads. Local authorities&#13;
will eventually be expected to contribute to the cost of road maintenance programs once&#13;
their present revenue generation constraints are addressed under the current urban&#13;
restructuring and government decentralization exercises. It is not anticipated that the&#13;
local authorities will be in a position to make such contributions during the project period&#13;
but this will need to be formally revisited as part of the review of financing arrangements&#13;
to be carried out prior to mid-term review. Communities, in kind or in cash, will be&#13;
expected to contribute to the cost of their road programs - this is to be set at 75% for&#13;
maintenance projects and 25% for rehabilitation projects. These arrangements will be in&#13;
place from the start of the program in the targeted pilot districts (see para 2. 7) and may&#13;
be adjusted as necessary by mid-term review.&#13;
2.20 Local funding will be channeled largely through the Road Fund rather than&#13;
through any annual allocation from Government's general budget. The exception is an&#13;
estimated amount of US$14.5 million representing Government's counterpart financing&#13;
obligations on ongoing or committed donor funded projects and an estimated US$12.7&#13;
million towards the cost of new commitments. The bulk of the resources for the Road&#13;
Fund will come from the fuel levy which is currently the only steady source of financing&#13;
for road maintenance. In addition, Government has agreed per its policy letter to allocate&#13;
from fiscal 1998 to the Road Fund a portion of the proceeds of road service license fees,&#13;
international transit tolls and weighbridge fines -- all of which are currently part of the&#13;
general budget. The expected impact on the Government budget would be a loss in&#13;
annual revenues of about US$2 million if estimated at current levels of collection&#13;
efficiency. This will be more than offset by the increase in VAT revenues that will be&#13;
generated by the increase in fuel levy (see para 4.1).&#13;
2.21  The Road Fund derived revenues of about US$11.0 million in 1996 from the&#13;
payment of fuel levy. There is a need to significantly increase the revenues generated by&#13;
the fuel levy as given below in the tables on sources and uses of funds for the Road&#13;
Fund. However, any plan to do so must bear in mind the need for the increase in the levy&#13;
to be gradual so as to allow the increased user costs to be offset by improved road&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
conditions and not so large as to result in Zambia's fuel prices being much higher than in&#13;
neighboring countries. Fuel levy increases are thus calibrated so that the induced increase&#13;
in the price of fuel does not exceed 3% per annum in real US$ terms throughout the&#13;
project period. Since the levy is now calculated on an ad valorem basis, at a rate of 15%&#13;
of the wholesale price, and since the wholesale price of diesel is lower than that of petrol,&#13;
the levy on diesel is correspondingly lower. This is a positive development since there is&#13;
a greater possibility of revenue leakage on diesel - trucks have an opportunity to fill up&#13;
with cheaper diesel in neighboring countries- and cross border price elasticities are&#13;
relatively high.&#13;
Table 2-4: Sources of Road Fund Resources (US$ million)&#13;
Year               1998       1999      2000       2001      2002      Total&#13;
Revenues from levyI&#13;
(a) Diesel                     8.3      11.4       14.6       18.1      20.5       72.8&#13;
(b) Gasoline                   4.7       6.5        8.4       10.4      11.8       41.8&#13;
Sub-Total                     13.0      17.9       23.0       28.5      32.2      114.6&#13;
Vehicle license fees           0.9       1.0        1.0        1.0        1.0       4.9&#13;
Transit fees                    1.9      1.9        2.0        2.0       2.1        9.8&#13;
Weighbridge fine/fees          0.5       0.4        0.3        0.1       0.0         1.3&#13;
Total                         16.3       21.1       26.2      31.6      35.4      130.6&#13;
1/     Based on a real increase of the levy from its 1997 level of 3.75 cents/liter for petrol and 3.5c/l for diesel to&#13;
8.25c/l and 7.6c/l respectively. For a constant real wholesale price of petroleum, this represents an increase&#13;
in ad valorem rate form the current 15% to 33% by 2002. For all else constant, fuel levy would increase&#13;
from 6.1% to 12% of petrol and diesel prices.&#13;
2/      This is based on 30% of the license fees being attributed to the Road Fund which is considered conservative.&#13;
Table 2-5: Uses of Road Fund Resources (US$ million)&#13;
Year                 1998      1999      2000       2001      2002    Total&#13;
Routine Maintenance Zi           10.5       13.6       16.9     21.6       26.6    89.1&#13;
Periodic Maintenance 2'           5.0       6.4        7.3       7.0        6.4    32.3&#13;
Rehabilitation, upgrading &amp;       0.0       0.0        0.7        1.4       0.4      2.5&#13;
access improvement&#13;
Running costs l/                  0.8        1.1        1.3       1.6        1.8     6.6&#13;
Total                             16.3     21.1       26.2      31.6       35.4    130.6&#13;
1/ Represents a ceiling of 5% of Road Fund revenues in line with Government policy. Actual costs are expected to&#13;
be below these amounts in any given year.&#13;
2/ Following ratios (rounded) will be included in performance benchmarks.&#13;
Year                 1998       1999     2000       2001      2002&#13;
Road Fund/Total&#13;
Routine and Periodic&#13;
Maintenance Requirements    %       33       40         50        60        70&#13;
Road Fund/Annual&#13;
Routine and Periodic&#13;
Maintenance Expenditure     %       65       75         80        90        95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
3. PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
A.   Implementation Arrangements&#13;
3.1   The project will be implemented by various authorities and agencies making the&#13;
fullest use of existing oversight, management and consultative structures. Given its&#13;
mandate for transport sector policy, MCT will retain overall responsibility for project&#13;
implementation and will appoint a Project Coordinator. A number of specific functions&#13;
outlined below will however be delegated to the NRB, including that of coordinating the&#13;
implementation of the civil works program. Roads Dept. will implement the main, trunk&#13;
and district roads program and the local authorities with the assistance of MLGH will&#13;
implement the urban and rural district roads program. The community accessibility&#13;
component will be implemented by the communities themselves with the help of the local&#13;
authorities and with technical assistance from the SRPU with financing of the RTTP.&#13;
Consultation with stakeholders impacted by project implementation will be assured by&#13;
the maintenance of structures established for this purpose under the RMI program and&#13;
under TETAP, i.e.: the Committee of Ministers under the chairmanship of the Minister of&#13;
Communications and Transport; a Project Steering Committee (PSC) at permanent&#13;
secretary level under MCT chairmanship; and the technical and financial subcommittees&#13;
of the NRB.&#13;
3.2   NRB will have the responsibility for coordinating implementation of the project,&#13;
for financial management for the project and for assembling all technical and financial&#13;
reports. NRB will approve the annual road program on the basis of the submissions made&#13;
by the various road authorities. NRB will manage the financing of road maintenance (as&#13;
now) as well as (in future) the financing for rehabilitation work under the project. The&#13;
role of existing road authorities will be focused on the preparation of longer term network&#13;
plans, annual programs for funding consideration and the implementation of the civil&#13;
works program (with the involvement of the private sector). Roads Dept. will be&#13;
responsible for establishing standards for maintaining and rehabilitating roads, for&#13;
developing road maintenance policies and for regularly updating the road data base in the&#13;
HMS. It will also be responsible for implementing rehabilitation and upgrading of trunk,&#13;
main and district roads - overall responsibility will be with the Assistant Director for&#13;
Operations with day-to-day management devolved to the contract management units&#13;
under the provincial road engineers. These units will be supplemented as necessary by&#13;
private consultants. The DISS in the MLGH will be strengthened through the infusion of&#13;
consultancy assistance on a medium term basis to provide support to local authorities in&#13;
planning road sector programs and through training for MLGH and local authority staff in&#13;
client management, who are expected to transfer their skills to the local authorities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32 -&#13;
Maintenance and rehabilitation of urban and rural roads remains ultimately the&#13;
responsibility of the relevant local authorities.&#13;
3.3   The NRB secretariat will be strengthened to enable it to effect its responsibilities&#13;
for ROADSIP. As a first step, the NRB is to employ three additional staff - a highway&#13;
engineer, a procurement specialist and a financial specialist - to meet these increased&#13;
responsibilities. These staff are being supported for a period of 4-6 months by short term&#13;
technical assistance funded under the IDA-administered Japanese PHRD grant. A short&#13;
term procurement specialist is helping NRB develop standard bidding documents&#13;
acceptable to IDA and other donors and assisting NRB staff on procurement management&#13;
and monitoring. Short term highway engineering and transport economics expertise has&#13;
helped to complete the analysis and preparation of the first two years core investment&#13;
program and to provide training to the new staff. For the initial two years of the program,&#13;
a management support team will be recruited composed of foreign and local consultants&#13;
to help coordinate the civil works program. Whether this arrangement would be extended&#13;
or not will be reviewed no later than the proposed mid-term review. In all events,&#13;
additional staff, expected to be up to three professionals and two support staff, may be&#13;
added to the NRB complement as implementation of the project gets underway to act as&#13;
counterparts to the project management team. Whereas the costs of the team are expected&#13;
to be funded externally, the costs of NRB staff will be recovered through the proceeds of&#13;
the Road Fund (see para 2.17)&#13;
3.4   A detailed project implementation plan (PIP) and implementation manual is under&#13;
preparation. The plan is summnarized at Annex 3-1. The draft PIP was presented to the&#13;
Bank as a condition of negotiations (para 5. 1). The PIP will be finalized and formally&#13;
adopted no later than credit effectiveness (see para 5.3). NRB is responsible for the&#13;
preparation of these documents. NRB is also responsible for managing the program&#13;
launch and for preparing the report on the completion of the program no later than&#13;
December 31, 2002. The implementation plan provides for a process of annual review of&#13;
project implementation which will take place not later than end of October each year.&#13;
The plan also provides for a mid-term review to take place not later than June 30, 2000.&#13;
3.5   The project is to be implemented over a five-year period from July 1, 1997. The&#13;
civil works program for this period has been prepared on an indicative basis in relation to&#13;
available implementation capacity in foreign and local construction industry and the&#13;
financial capacity of Zambia, and in particular of the road users (para 2.6). The program&#13;
to be comnmenced during the first two years has been defined in detail and has been&#13;
agreed by the Bank as condition of credit negotiations (see para 5.1). Consultancy&#13;
services for the design and engineering of the rehabilitation works in this program will be&#13;
tendered no later than credit effectiveness (see para 5.3). The maintenance program for&#13;
1998 will be prepared by no later than October 31, 1997 at which time tenders for&#13;
contracted work will be prepared and force account work allocated. The detailed program&#13;
for 1999, as well as the indicative program for 2000-2001, for both maintenance and&#13;
rehabilitation will be deternined no later than the annual review for 1998.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33 -&#13;
3.6   With regard to policy and institutional reform, the Government has discussed its&#13;
objectives extensively with the Bank and has concretized these through the letter of sector&#13;
policy signed March 21, 1997 which was a condition of credit negotiations (Para 5.1).&#13;
The reform program includes both short and medium term institutional restructuring,&#13;
terms of reference for the restructured road authorities and for the key positions. The&#13;
short term institutional restructuring (strengthening the NRB) shall take place before&#13;
credit effectiveness and, based on achievement of program implementation and outcome&#13;
of the Public Service Reform Program, a realistic medium term restructuring strategy of&#13;
road authorities will be prepared at the mid-term review.&#13;
3.7   With regard to financing reforms, Government intends to take action to ensure&#13;
the value of the fuel levy is maintained in real terms and is thus regularly adjusted to&#13;
ensure funding available for maintenance does not decline over time. From fiscal 1997&#13;
fuel levy is to be expressed as a percentage of the wholesale fuel price which Government&#13;
has undertaken in its sector policy letter to review on a regular basis. Government also&#13;
intends to take the necessary steps to provide from fiscal 1998 for the deposit into the&#13;
Road Fund of international transit fees, a portion of vehicle license fees and weighbridge&#13;
fines and fees. The financing requirements for the project will in all events be reviewed&#13;
on an annual basis to ensure the annual maintenance and rehabilitation program can be&#13;
funded.&#13;
B.   Technical Assistance and Training&#13;
3.8   Technical assistance services will be required during the life of the project,&#13;
particularly in the first two years, to ensure the various executing agencies have the&#13;
capacity and know how to implement the program effectively. This technical assistance&#13;
will be strongly linked to various measures, such as locally based and overseas training,&#13;
workshops, exchange programs and study tours, aimed at knowledge transfer and&#13;
building the capacity of Zambians in road authorities in a sustainable fashion. Because of&#13;
the maintenance backlog and because of the particular requirements brought about by&#13;
institutional restructuring, additional expertise will be needed to fill gaps and expand&#13;
capacity. Terms of reference for all technical assistance expected to be required have&#13;
been developed and will be agreed with IDA prior to implementation. The technical&#13;
assistance provided to Zambia through the RMI and RTTP programs is being integrated&#13;
into the single framework of ROADSIP. Also included is technical assistance to finalize&#13;
the preparation of ROADSIP and to disseminate the program and its objectives through a&#13;
series of upfront national and provincial workshops which is being financed through a&#13;
Japanese PHRD grant administered by IDA.&#13;
3.9   Policy support. Technical assistance in three components will be provided to&#13;
MCT with the broad objective of increasing the capacity for policy analysis and policy&#13;
formulation for the roads sector: (a) a Program Advisor for a period of 24 man months to&#13;
help strengthen the ministry's policy capacity, to provide training, and to advise on the&#13;
mid-term review of the road sector institutional and financing strengthening measures to&#13;
be taken; (b) technical assistance for the development of a road safety program, including&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34-&#13;
requisite institutional strengthening and financing reform, in the amount of 12 man&#13;
months of which half is expected to be local consultancy; and (c) technical assistance to&#13;
help Government revise the legal framework for the roads and road traffic management,&#13;
including Cap 464, in the amount of 12 man months with again half expected to be&#13;
provided by local consultancy.&#13;
3.10  Institutional development. Technical assistance will be provided to the respective&#13;
agencies to strengthen capacity in road management and financing. For NRB, a&#13;
management support team will be required to help create capacity in a number of areas&#13;
which will be critical to the program's effectiveness in a total amount of 108 man&#13;
months, i.e.: 36 man months for a highway engineer/team leader; 18 man months for&#13;
contracts management and procurement assistance; 18 months for financial management;&#13;
and 24 months for short term specialist assistance in training, quality control and in labor-&#13;
based maintenance methods. For Roads Dept., technical assistance will be required to&#13;
support the restructuring program and is envisaged to cover the following areas: 24 man&#13;
months for the start up of the environmental management unit with particular emphasis&#13;
on environmental analysis and monitoring; 12 man months of support to the restructuring&#13;
of the plant and vehicle pool and to improving equipment management and maintenance;&#13;
6 man months of assistance to the HMS unit for the further development of the data base&#13;
on the core network; and 6 man months on the development of selection criteria and&#13;
analytical tools. For MLGH, technical assistance will help further development of the&#13;
capacity in DISS for policy and planning in the roads sector and help strengthen local&#13;
authority capacity for roads and will specifically cover 12 man months of consultant&#13;
services for the development of urban road management systems. This will complement&#13;
the assistance already provided under TETAP for the development of capacity for rural&#13;
(feeder) road planning.&#13;
3.11  Implementation support. Short term technical assistance of 6 months will be&#13;
required to help strengthen the NRB to prepare the necessary program documents and to&#13;
assist to launch the program (see para 3.2). For Roads Dept., technical assistance&#13;
through two experts each for 24 months will be required to assist the contract&#13;
management units to be established in each provincial road engineer office. Consultancy&#13;
support for DISS in MLGH, a continuation of what has initially been provided for under&#13;
TETAP, to plan and administer road maintenance and rehabilitation for the rural (feeder)&#13;
road program is estimated as 24 man months. Provision is also made under Engineering&#13;
Services for consulting services for the preparation of feasibility studies, design,&#13;
economic evaluation, preparation and evaluation of tenders and supervision of contracts&#13;
estimated as 6% of the total estimated costs of civil works.&#13;
3.12  Under the community accessibility program, required technical assistance is&#13;
mostly to be provided locally with a view to strengthening the capability of communities&#13;
to manage their own programs. A roads engineer will be provided on a full time basis at&#13;
the SRPU to oversee the program and supervise the technical support to be provided in&#13;
the field to the communities. Allowance has also been made in project costing for short&#13;
term consultancy and training in participatory techniques, financial management and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
labor based methods. For the development of intermediate means of transport (IMT), the&#13;
required technical assistance will be contracted out to a local NGO who will be expected&#13;
to provide project management, field facilitation and technical services. Under the&#13;
construction industry development program, technical assistance will be provided to help&#13;
the Ministry of Works and Supply and the NCC in the areas of contractor registration,&#13;
tendering procedures and streamlining of the legal framework for contracting.&#13;
C.     Procurement&#13;
3.13   Procurement arrangements for the project are summarized below in Table 3.1.&#13;
Procurement of IDA-financed goods and works will be carried out in accordance with&#13;
Guidelines Procurement under IBRD Loan and IDA Credits (January 1995, Revised&#13;
January and August 1996). Selection and appointment of consultants will be in&#13;
accordance with the Guidelines: Selection and Employment of Consultants by World&#13;
Bank Borrowers (January 1997). Goods, works and consultants' services financed by&#13;
other donors would be procured in accordance with their respective guidelines.&#13;
Table 3-1: Summary of Procurement Arrangements (US$ million)&#13;
Items                     ICB        NCB         Others      NIF        Total&#13;
A. Civil Works&#13;
1. Routine Maintenance                  0.0        0.0         0.0        70.1        70.1&#13;
2. Periodic Maintenance               5.4 (3.6)    4.4 (3.2)  2.5 (1.5)    62.1     74.4 (8.3)&#13;
3 Rehabilitation                     33.5 (30.3)   5.1 (4.7)    0.0       106.4    145.0 (35.0)&#13;
4. Feeder Road Upgrading              8.0 (7.4)    3.3 (3.0)    0.0       22.5      33.8 (10.4)&#13;
5. Accessibility Improvement             0.0     4.5 (4.2)      0.0       19.5      24.0 (4.2)&#13;
6. Community Transport Infrastructure    0.0        0.0       2.5 (2.1)    2.8       5.3 (2.1)&#13;
B. Goods                                0.6 (0.5)    0.6 (0.5)    0.0        0.0        1.2 (1.0)&#13;
C. Consultants and Training&#13;
1. Intermediate Means of Transport      0.0         0.0       0.6 (0.6)   0.4        1.0 (0.6)&#13;
2. Construction Industry Development     0.0        0.0       1.6 (1.6)    1.2       2.8 (1.6)&#13;
3. Policy Support                        0.0        0.0       1.0 (1.0)   0.0        1.0 (1.0)&#13;
4. Implementation Support                0.0        0.0       1.4 (1.4)    0.0       1.4 (1.4)&#13;
5. Engineering Services                  0.0        0.0       3.9 (3.9)    16.9     20.8 (3.9)&#13;
6. Institutional Development             0.0        0.0       0.5 (0.5)   2.9        3.4 (0.5)&#13;
Total                  47.5 (41.8)  17.9 (15.6)   14.0(12.8)    304.8    384.2 (70.0)&#13;
Note: Figures in brackets are the respective amounts financed by IDA&#13;
-- NIF is NOT IDA-financed.&#13;
3.14 Civil works will be carried out under contract as detailed below. This is with the&#13;
exception of approximately US$9.0 million which will be under force account but which&#13;
will not be financed by IDA. Upgrading and rehabilitation will be carried out under&#13;
international competitive bidding (ICB) procedures for large contracts in excess of&#13;
US$1.0 million and otherwise under NCB, procedures for which have been reviewed at&#13;
appraisal and which have been brought into line with IDA requirements with the help of&#13;
technical assistance to NRB. A portion of periodic maintenance will be also under ICB,&#13;
with bulking up of the required work in the first two to three years to help address the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
backlog. Prequalification of contractors will be required for contracts valued in excess of&#13;
US$10 million. NCB contracts would be open to local and foreign firms up to a&#13;
maximum of US$1.0 million per contract. The NCB contracts would be packaged in a&#13;
variety of sizes to promote competition and provide incentive for local firms to compete&#13;
for work. Goods would be procured on the basis of competitive bidding, with use of ICB&#13;
for US$100,000 or above and NCB below this threshold.&#13;
3.15  For routine and periodic maintenance limited provision will be made for direct&#13;
contracting to encourage the development of recently trained small local contractors.&#13;
Under IDA financing, for periodic maintenance, these contractors will be eligible for only&#13;
one direct contract upon graduation from training of up to US$50,000 equivalent,&#13;
provided that they have not been previously awarded an ICB or NCB contract and&#13;
provided all such contracts and rates are subject to prior review by IDA. The average&#13;
estimated contract size of the routine maintenance is up to 10 km and for periodic&#13;
maintenance is up to 15 km. A ceiling of US$1.5 million for these contracts has been&#13;
established. A specific procurement procedure will be followed for community transport&#13;
infrastructure, that is rehabilitation and maintenance of community roads and bridges.&#13;
This procedure will be that adopted under the Second Social Recovery Project and&#13;
approved by IDA for infrastructure (microprojects) subcomponents, i.e., individual&#13;
contracts of an estimated value of US$50,000 equivalent or less to be procured on the&#13;
basis of at least three quotations from qualified community-based contractors up to an&#13;
aggregate amount of US$2 million. When sufficient community-based contracts are not&#13;
available, contracts may be awarded directly on the basis of standard rates to be agreed&#13;
with IDA.&#13;
3.16 For consulting services, the normal method of procurement will be on the basis of&#13;
quality and cost based selection (QCBS) from a short list of international and national&#13;
consultants. The exceptions are anticipated to be as follows: QCBS on the basis of a&#13;
short list of national consultants for engineering design and supervision of smaller civil&#13;
works and for consultancy services for the community accessibility component for up to&#13;
US$200,000 per contract; quality based selection (QBS) for the management support&#13;
team for NRB up to an aggregate amount of US$1.5 million; single source selection&#13;
where preexisting contracts under TETAP are extended for financing under the proposed&#13;
credit for strengthening MLGH and Roads Dept. institutional capacity and for IMT&#13;
studies up to an aggregate amount of US$500,000 and for engineering supervision&#13;
services where the detailed design has been carried out in a satisfactory manner by the&#13;
same firm; and individual consultants in case of components of the policy studies&#13;
program up to an aggregate amount of US$200,000.&#13;
3.17 Prior review thresholds will be US$100,000 for goods, US$250,000 for works,&#13;
US$100,000 for consulting firms, and US$50,000 for individual consultants. The first&#13;
five contracts let under NCB procedure will be subject to prior review regardless of&#13;
contract amount. For direct contracts, IDA will be provided a copy of specification and&#13;
the draft contract for prior review in each case. Procurement under the program will be&#13;
the responsibility of the relevant executing agencies with NRB carrying out a review and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
support role. A procurement management system will be established in NRB as a result&#13;
of the institutional capacity building program (see para 3.10) and appropriate training for&#13;
staff will be provided. NRB has developed standard forms of contract and standard&#13;
specifications for NCB for direct contracting and for labor based work. Agreement has&#13;
been reached with the National Tender Board that responsibility for these tenders subject&#13;
to an upper limit of US$100,000 (and later be increased up to US$600,000) will rest with&#13;
the NRB and the executing agencies. All ICB works and goods as well as consultants'&#13;
services' tenders will go through the established procedures. Consideration will be given&#13;
no later than mid-term review to further decentralization of the procurement review&#13;
process and strengthening the role of NRB.&#13;
D.   Disbursement&#13;
3.18 The credit is expected to be fully disbursed by March 31, 2003 as shown below.&#13;
The estimated disbursement schedule (Annex 3-2) is based on the detailed&#13;
implementation plan.&#13;
Table 3-2: Projected Disbursements Fiscal Year Ending June (US$ million)&#13;
Year      1997    1998  . 1999    2000    2001    2002  . 2003&#13;
Annual         0       6        9       14       25       15       1&#13;
Cumulative     0       6        15      29       54       69      70&#13;
% of Credit i0%        9%      21%     41%      77/s    99%      100%&#13;
The proceeds of the credit are expected to be disbursed in accordance with the allocation&#13;
by category shown below, over a period of 6 years. A provision has been made for&#13;
retroactive financing up to a ceiling of SDR 2 million (4% of the proposed credit arnount)&#13;
in respect of road rehabilitation projects for which tenders were let prior to negotiations&#13;
and for which contracts are expected to be signed prior to credit signature, but after&#13;
August 15, 1997.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38 -&#13;
Table 3-3: Disbursement Categories&#13;
Amount of   % of Expenditure&#13;
the Credit  to be Financed By&#13;
Category                       Allocated         IDA&#13;
1. Civil Works for Periodic Maintenance               2.7             90&#13;
.__ ___  2.7         60&#13;
2.4            30&#13;
2. Civil Works for Rehabilitation of selected roads  33.7             90&#13;
3. Civil Works for Upgrading feeder roads             10.0            90&#13;
4. Civil Works for Accessibility improvement of feeder roads  4.0     90&#13;
5. Civil Works for Community Transport Infrastructure  2.0            75&#13;
6. Equipment, Vehicles and Materials                  1.0             90&#13;
7. Consultants Services and Training                  8.7             100&#13;
8. Unallocated                                        2.7         as disbursed&#13;
Total                                                70.0&#13;
3.19 All applications to withdraw proceeds from the credit would be fully documented&#13;
except for: (i) expenditures for civil works including community roads with an estimated&#13;
value of US$250,000 or less; (ii) expenditures for goods of US$100,000 or less; and&#13;
(iii) expenditures on consulting services of US$100,000 or less for consulting firms and&#13;
US$50,000 or less for individual consultants for which reimbursement would be made&#13;
against statements of expenditure (SOE). Supporting documentation for expenditures&#13;
claimed against SOEs will be retained by NRB for review by periodic IDA supervision&#13;
missions and by external auditors.&#13;
3.20 To facilitate disbursement and reduce the volume of withdrawal applications, two&#13;
Special Accounts will be opened in a commercial bank on terms and conditions&#13;
acceptable to IDA. The Special Account A would be managed by NRB. The authorized&#13;
allocation to cover four months of expenditures is set at US$3.0 million. Upon&#13;
effectiveness the amount of US$1.5 million, 50% of the authorized allocation will be&#13;
deposited into the Special Account. The remaining balance will be made available as&#13;
disbursements reach SDR 7 million. The Special Account B would be managed by&#13;
SRPU for the sole purpose of facilitating the community transport infrastructure&#13;
component of the project. The authorized allocation for this account will be US$0.5&#13;
million of which 50% will be made available on declaration of credit effectiveness and&#13;
the balance as disbursements reach SDR 1.5 million.&#13;
3.21   A condition of disbursement for expenditures under the community accessibility&#13;
component will be that operational guidelines to be followed in approving and disbursing&#13;
grants to beneficiary associations as well as a memorandum of understanding setting out&#13;
the roles of all implementing agencies for this component will have been prepared and&#13;
agreed to by IDA (para 5.4).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
E.   Auditing and Accounting&#13;
3.22 The NRB will be responsible for coordinating project accounting, maintaining&#13;
overall records, producing an aggregated and consolidated project account, managing&#13;
disbursements and ensuring timely audited accounts. The NRB has been assuring this&#13;
function under TETAP in a satisfactory manner but will require increased capacity to&#13;
handle the additional volume of work under ROADSIP. This will be managed through&#13;
the additional of one full time qualified accountant and the provision of a financial&#13;
specialist on the management support team (see para 3.10). The specialist will help&#13;
develop accounting systems and procedures which will however remain on a cash rather&#13;
than an accrual basis.&#13;
3.23  Annual audits of the consolidated project account and subsidiary statements of&#13;
project activity undertaken by other road authorities will be carried out by external&#13;
auditors satisfactory to IDA. Under the Social Recovery Project, a separate account will&#13;
be prepared and audited on an annual basis for the community transport infrastructure&#13;
component. Terms of reference for these audits contain a component of technical audit to&#13;
provide independent verification of the achievement of physical targets. It has been&#13;
agreed at negotiations that audits will be submitted to IDA within six months of the end&#13;
of the respective financial year. Audits will include a separate auditor's opinion on the&#13;
Special Accounts and use of SOE procedure. Per terms of reference, a management letter&#13;
will be submitted to IDA with each audit report. Audits will be carried out by an&#13;
appropriately qualified firm.&#13;
F.    Monitoring and Reporting&#13;
3.24 NRB will be responsible for preparing monthly reports on the physical and&#13;
financial performance of the program against target. Proposed monitoring indicators are&#13;
at Annex 3-3. These have been reviewed at appraisal and have been agreed as a condition&#13;
of credit negotiations (para 5. 1). These reports are to be submitted, in the first instance,&#13;
to MCT for discussion and action as required. In the second instance, these reports will&#13;
be consolidated into a quarterly report which will be widely disseminated to IDA, the&#13;
donor community and the various local stakeholders. The content of the quarterly report&#13;
will be included in the PIP. NRB will also be responsible for producing annual reports of&#13;
achievements to be submitted one month before the Annual Review (see para 3.4). A&#13;
mid-term report will be produced no later than two months in advance of the Mid-term&#13;
Review. NRB will produce within six months of the closing of the IDA credit an&#13;
implementation completion report. Independent technical audits will be carried out on a&#13;
periodicity and according to terms of reference both satisfactory to IDA in order to verify&#13;
physical progress and to assess quality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
G.   Supervision&#13;
3.25  Overall, supervision will amount on average per annum to a total of 25 staffweeks&#13;
of field supervision and an additional 20 weeks for review of documents, reports, etc. at&#13;
headquarters and in the resident mission. This will require an annual budget of about&#13;
US$150,000 which is reflected in the business plan for Zambia. A detailed plan for the&#13;
field supervision of the program, including a summary of IDA requirements, is included&#13;
at Annex 3-4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41 -&#13;
4.  PROJECT BENEFITS AND RISKS&#13;
A.   Project Benefits&#13;
4.1   The project will help assure that there is adequate road infrastructure to underpin&#13;
Zambia's continuing economic reform effort. The program is affordable in terms of the&#13;
total resources available to Zambia for the sector and is reasonable in terms of the size of&#13;
Zambia's road network. The amount to be allocated to roads out of total investment is&#13;
within international norms. The project investment is equivalent to 1.9% of projected&#13;
GDP for Zambia, of which about 1.2% is represented by rehabilitation. This compares to&#13;
the figure of 2.2% derived from a study of about 33 developing countries undertaken in&#13;
the 1980s. An increasing portion of the local funding for this investment will come from&#13;
direct road user charges channeled through the Road Fund rather than through general&#13;
taxation. This has the benefit of ensuring scarce public funds are effectively utilized and&#13;
that the road users take on a steadily increasing proportion of total local funding with the&#13;
largest contribution to come from the most frequent users of roads in terms of kilometers&#13;
driven (through fuel levy payments) and from heavy vehicle owners (road service license&#13;
fee). As VAT of 20% is currently levied on top of the fuel levy, Government finances&#13;
benefit from increasing the fuel levy. This fiscal benefit is expected to be of the order of&#13;
US$12.7 million equivalent in 1996 prices over the period 1997-2002. This partly offsets&#13;
the loss of general tax revenue through the transfer of road user charges proceeds to the&#13;
Road Fund of US$9.8 million and the incremental cost to the budget of US$12.6 million&#13;
for the counterpart funding of the project for a net fiscal impact of negative US$9.7&#13;
million.&#13;
4.2   The project will help address deficiencies in the road network, increase the&#13;
proportion of the network in good condition, and improve sector management and&#13;
financing. At the national level, economic benefits will more than offset the direct&#13;
negative fiscal impact through the creation of higher taxable incomes from reduced&#13;
transport costs. The direct benefit to the road users of improvement in road conditions is&#13;
considerable and are expected to outweigh the financial cost occasioned by the higher&#13;
road user charges to finance road maintenance. Given the competitive structure of the&#13;
road transport industry, transport cost savings are very likely to be passed on to&#13;
consumers in terms of lower final product prices. A recent study by FEDHAUL has&#13;
indicated an additional cost of US$14,000 equivalent per annum per heavy vehicle for&#13;
incremental repairs occasioned by roads in poor condition. Given the current size of the&#13;
truck fleet and the current condition of Zambia's roads, meeting the project objective for&#13;
the improvement in the portion of roads in good condition is estimated to generate a gain&#13;
of about US$30.0 million or about 1% of GDP in avoided vehicle maintenance costs.&#13;
4.3   The methodology of assessing the benefits of the main roads and feeder roads&#13;
components of the project and the results of the economic analysis are set out in Annex 4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42 -&#13;
1. The basis for prioritizing main road subprojects will be economic rate of return (ERR)&#13;
subject to a threshold value of 12% representing the estimated opportunity cost for capital&#13;
in Zambia. For subprojects identified for the first two years program, ERRs are in the&#13;
range 12% to 42% with a weighted average of 21%. The estimates have been constructed&#13;
on the basis of HMS input data, determining the most cost effective rehabilitation option&#13;
with benefits representing vehicle operating cost (VOC) savings. Cost benefit streams&#13;
have been valued using economic prices, adjusting for duties and taxes included in&#13;
financial prices. Since the exchange rate is market determined and cost composition is&#13;
similar for costs and benefits, no conversion factor has been applied. The ERR estimates&#13;
are considered conservative and represent lower bound values given that no other benefits&#13;
- such as time savings and generated traffic - have been included and an assumed traffic&#13;
growth rate of 3% per annum has been used. Sensitivity analysis has been carried out for&#13;
different forecasts of traffic growth and a switching value analysis has been done for&#13;
capital cost variation. The first two years program contains the rehabilitation of a number&#13;
of sections of the Great North Road which assures international road traffic links with&#13;
Tanzania and is thus of strategic economic importance. The economic benefit arising&#13;
from avoiding the complete loss of any section of this road is likely to be considerable&#13;
and certainly greater than the VOC benefits. For the Chinsali-Nakonde section of this&#13;
road, the ERR for any rehabilitation or maintenance alternative is less than 12% on the&#13;
basis of VOC savings from existing traffic, but has been estimated at 28% when account&#13;
is taken of the economic benefit from generated traffic estimated as the equivalent of the&#13;
current traffic carried by the TAZARA railway.&#13;
4.4   Feeder roads have been prioritized on the basis of multi criteria analysis (MCA),&#13;
under which an important weight is given to agricultural production potential and access&#13;
of the rural poor to markets and services and under which an important role is assigned to&#13;
choices made by affected communities in each district The methodology has been&#13;
developed with the help of consultants under TETAP and has now been formally adopted&#13;
by Government as the basis for the subproject selection under the project. Through the&#13;
TETAP-funded road inventory, a primary core feeder road network has been determined&#13;
on a district by district basis. Specified economic and social criteria have been applied to&#13;
determine a priority ranking of primary feeder roads for each district. This prioritization&#13;
informs discussions which will take place on an annual basis involving communities,&#13;
district councils, MLGH staff and other stakeholders as to how the available resources&#13;
will be allocated among the priorities - for example the tradeoffs between allocating&#13;
resources to upgrading a few roads as opposed to improving accessibility on a larger&#13;
number of roads will be discussed and agreed at community level and will not be&#13;
centrally determined. For roads selected for full improvement, an "ex ante" and "ex post"&#13;
analysis will be undertaken to determine the net economic benefit.&#13;
4.5   A major project benefit will be job creation through the development of increased&#13;
opportunities for the local contracting and consulting industries. The Government's&#13;
medium-term goal for ROADSIP is 30,000 new jobs - it is expected that by 2002 about&#13;
14,000 new job opportunities will have been created thus. Other benefits of the program&#13;
would include increased marketed agricultural output as a result of the feeder road&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
component, improved access in rural areas to health and education facilities and human&#13;
resource development which will complement the policy and institutional building&#13;
components, and increased active participation of local communities in decision making&#13;
about road infrastructure.&#13;
B.    Key Performance Indicators&#13;
4.6   Improving the quality of information on the road sector and assuring that it is&#13;
effectively used to improve decision making, including but not limited to the allocation of&#13;
scarce financial resources, is a key benefit anticipated from the project. Key indicators of&#13;
successful project implementation will include inter alia: (a) efficient service delivery by&#13;
increasing number of kilometers of roads rehabilitated and then regularly maintained; (b)&#13;
improving service quality by lowering road transport unit costs and vehicle operating&#13;
costs; (c) sustainability of the road maintenance efforts by increasing road user charges&#13;
devoted to maintenance; (d) strengthening of local construction industry by increasing&#13;
the volume of work offered; (e) reducing poverty by creating job opportunities for both&#13;
skilled and unskilled workers ; and (f) increasing the percentage of classified roads in&#13;
good or fair condition. These are to be included in the PIP. IDA will focus on a subset of&#13;
these indicators designed to measure the critical success factors for implementation&#13;
success of all project components in terms of both qualitative and qualitative&#13;
improvements - these are given in Annex 3-3 and will be reviewed on a regular basis by&#13;
IDA and Government. (See para 3.23). Progress in the institutional reforms would be&#13;
monitored through completed studies, preparation of time-based action plans based on the&#13;
recommendation of the studies, and monitoring the realization of action plans through&#13;
regular progress reports which will be submitted on a quarterly basis to IDA.&#13;
C.   Poverty Reduction and Employment Generation&#13;
4.7   The project is expected to have a significant impact on poverty reduction and&#13;
includes specific targeted interventions particularly in the rural areas, through feeder road&#13;
rehabilitation and maintenance which will help reduce transport costs, increase mobility&#13;
and increase farm gate prices for small scale farmers. The project's initial focus is&#13;
expected to include three provinces, Northern, Luapula and Eastern, where 50% of the&#13;
core poor of Zambia live, as well as Western province where isolation and poor rural&#13;
access are particular acute and are major contributory factors to high poverty levels. This&#13;
is consistent with Government's development objective of reducing poverty, inter alia&#13;
through improving the income generating potential of the poor by enhancing their access&#13;
to productive resources. The project component dealing with the reconstruction and&#13;
rehabilitation of community (undesignated) roads will help develop participatory&#13;
approaches to road planning and maintenance which will empower poor communities.&#13;
Better rural district (feeder) roads and community roads are expected to help improve&#13;
food aid distribution in the event of future drought or hardship in the rural areas - poorly&#13;
maintained roads are recognized by NGOs and community groups to have been a major&#13;
stumbling block to the success of relief efforts in the recent past - and facilitate in good&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
years the marketing of agricultural surpluses. A significant number of new jobs will be&#13;
created through the project, especially as a result of the development of small scale labor&#13;
based contractors to compete for work on the urban and rural district feeder roads. In&#13;
order to measure progress on this front, it is proposed that two poverty reduction impact&#13;
assessments be undertaken during the life of the project and according to terms of&#13;
reference satisfactory to IDA - one prior to mid-term review and one within 6 months&#13;
prior to project completion.&#13;
D.   Development of Local Contractors&#13;
4.8   The project seeks to address all three current sets of problems of the construction&#13;
and consulting industry, i.e., financial, technical and Government procedures. In terms of&#13;
financial issues, the project will ensure timely and prompt payments to the contractors -&#13;
specific standards have been set and these will be monitored. Stable cash flow to the&#13;
Road Fund will ensure that the contracts are not suspended or terminated before&#13;
completion and the contractors will have the chance to better plan, allocate and utilize&#13;
their resources. This should result in reduction of costs, as has already been demonstrated&#13;
in the first two years of the operation of the NRB, and should enable development of&#13;
local contractors who can compete with the other regional and international bidders. It is&#13;
expected that, by the end of the project in 2002, there should be up to 300 contractors&#13;
active in routine and periodic maintenance and up to 70 contractors for rehabilitation&#13;
projects. The current turnover of the locally based contractors is about US$12.5 million,&#13;
whereas the capacity is estimated at US$25.0 million per year. The amount of work&#13;
available to the local contracting industry will rise during the project, from US$12.0&#13;
million in 1997 to US$28.0 million in 2002 expressed in 1996 prices. It is thus expected&#13;
that this capacity will be better utilized and further expanded during the life of the project.&#13;
4.9   Conventional civil work methods in Zambia had been equipment-intensive.&#13;
Construction projects were often managed by expatriates. The program aims at a&#13;
different approach that will seek to create incentives for use of labor-based methods for&#13;
road works and encourage a larger role for locally-based contractors and consultants.&#13;
Compared to the equipment based methods, labor-based methods can more effectively&#13;
mobilize domestic resources and can save foreign exchange. Labor-based methods can&#13;
be readily acquired by unskilled people and can be disseminated across a wide area since&#13;
are not dependent on heavy machinery with limited availability and enable road works to&#13;
be more easily performed in remote areas where unemployment is a prevailing problem.&#13;
Training to be provided under the program will help increase the productivity of small&#13;
scale contractors. Opportunities will be offered to retrenchees arising from the&#13;
restructuring of Roads Dept. as well as to contract managers within public service and to&#13;
local consultants. Upon graduation, contractors will be given work opportunity through&#13;
direct contract to demonstrate skills and experience acquired through training. (See para&#13;
3.15). After graduation and work training, the small scale contractors will be encouraged&#13;
to compete for further work through provision for small packaged contracts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
4.10  Under the project, the use of a standardized national competitive bidding&#13;
document is intended to facilitate the participation of local contractors. Improved&#13;
procurement management in the sector is expected to reduce delays, in particular with&#13;
regard to processing time for bids and for payments. In addition, for labor based works&#13;
under direct contract, a simplified document will help inexperienced contractors to more&#13;
easily manage their work.&#13;
E.   Environmental Impact&#13;
4.11  The project is focused on maintenance and rehabilitation of the road network.&#13;
Upgrading is expected to amount to less than 8% of the total cost of civil works. There&#13;
will be no construction of new roads other than a very limited amount of bridge and track&#13;
construction under the community accessibility component. Resettlement and vulnerable&#13;
minorities' plans are not anticipated for any subprojects envisaged under the project, and&#13;
not at all in the case of works already identified for the first two years program. The&#13;
adverse environmental impact is thus not considered likely to be major and the project&#13;
has accordingly been rated Category B.&#13;
4.12 An environmental analysis has been carried out and an environmental mitigation&#13;
plan prepared in conformity with the requirements of OD 4.1 on Environmental&#13;
Assessment for Category B programs. The work was carried out by a local consultant&#13;
working within the framework of the national task force which prepared ROADSIP. The&#13;
analysis was submitted to Government and to the Bank for review in June 1996 and&#13;
accepted with some minor revisions as a basis for an action plan for improved&#13;
environmental management in the roads sector. The analysis identified fourteen areas of&#13;
main environmental concern and has specified a range of measures to be taken. Out of&#13;
these fourteen, five have been highlighted for specific attention, i.e., destruction of&#13;
wildlife habitats and biodiversity; increased soil erosion leading to river and stream&#13;
siltation; soil and water contamination through chemical, oil and fuel spillage; increased&#13;
deforestation through road improvement and greater road usage; and disruption of&#13;
traditional lifestyles and increased sexually transmitted diseases.&#13;
4.13  The mitigation plan is part of a proposed environmental management program&#13;
which is intended to raise capacity in the road sector to address both immediate and likely&#13;
future environmental concerns. A environmental management working committee,&#13;
including the local consultant, has been tasked from September 1996 with the finalization&#13;
of this plan. The committee has made very good progress and has been made more&#13;
effective by drawing in private and public sector representation from a variety of&#13;
organizations, including ECZ. The plan includes four elements critical both to the&#13;
development of capacity and to building linkages between the sector program and&#13;
national environmental policy and guidelines, i.e., establishment of an environmental&#13;
management unit to be housed initially in the Roads Department with external funding&#13;
for technical assistance and training during the first two years of operation; development&#13;
of road sector environmental standards and guidelines, including review and&#13;
strengthening of the environmental clauses in use in NCB procurement documentation;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
carrying out environmental assessments on specific road improvement projects on a&#13;
selective basis; and carrying out monitoring and evaluation activity to ensure compliance&#13;
with environmental guidelines during the construction phase of projects. The&#13;
aforementioned committee will serve as a steering committee for the program during the&#13;
first two years of pilot operation.&#13;
F.    Sustainability&#13;
4.14   Clarified institutional roles, improved management structures and adequate&#13;
funding for road maintenance are key factors for sustainability. The project is expected to&#13;
enhance sustainability by addressing these factors in a coherent and effective manner.&#13;
Establishing an appropriate sector policy framework supported by strong and effective&#13;
institutions is the ultimate goal of the program. This will facilitate an improvement in the&#13;
quality of planning and programming in the roads sector. Given its revised status, NRB&#13;
is expected to have greater freedom to offer the terms and conditions which will attract&#13;
and keep qualified Zambian staff and to contract out services as far as possible. Road&#13;
financing will be addressed in such a way to ensure greater regularity and predictability&#13;
of financial flows to the sector which should reduce the fiscal burden and place greater&#13;
reliance on road user charges through the Road Fund to finance road expenditures. This&#13;
greater predictability, associated with a steady rate of increase in the resources made&#13;
available for road maintenance, are expected to create a sustainable market for road&#13;
construction services that will stimulate the creation of new small business and new jobs.&#13;
The participatory nature of program preparation, the involvement of the private sector in&#13;
the management of NRB, augur well for a high degree of program ownership on the part&#13;
of all Zambian stakeholders.&#13;
G.    Project Risks&#13;
4.1]5 The Government's program is an ambitious one, though its scope and objectives&#13;
are appropriate for bringing about a real improvement in the quality of road infrastructure&#13;
in Zambia. There are, however, substantial risks to be addressed. Under the project,&#13;
these risks have been allocated appropriately and mitigated to the extent possible. The&#13;
major outstanding risks are institutional and financial. On the institutional side,&#13;
considerable effort has gone into designing strengthening and restructuring measures&#13;
which attract the support of all stakeholders. There is a risk that these measures will not&#13;
succeed in improving sector management performance to the extent expected which could&#13;
in turn lead to delays in project implementation. The restructuring of existing&#13;
institutions, in particular of Roads Dept., depends on the effectiveness of the PSRP in&#13;
creating the conditions, including pay and incentives, which will facilitate the&#13;
professionalization of government services. In the event that these measures fall short,&#13;
Government anticipates in its letter of sector policy that alternative strategies which&#13;
including the acceleration of the pace of commercialization and rationalization of road&#13;
sector institutions will be considered. Therefore, the effectiveness of the new institutional&#13;
arrangements are to be assessed after each of the first two annual project reviews and any&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
adjustments will be made by the time of mid-term review. In addition to institutional&#13;
structure, it must be recognized that human and material capacity remains limited and this&#13;
weakness may be fully addressed only over the medium term. In the initial years of the&#13;
project, this constraint will have to be addressed by technical assistance and training, the&#13;
need for which is to be reassessed by mid-term review.&#13;
4.16   On the financial side, the risk is that the project will not be affordable and that&#13;
Government will not be able to raise the necessary local funding. Most local funding&#13;
will, however, come through road user charges and not through general tax revenues -&#13;
road users have expressed a willingness, in a general sense, to pay higher charges in the&#13;
interest of financing a larger road program than hitherto. These funding arrangements do&#13;
not fully mitigate the financial risk for the funding of local costs of the project -firstly,&#13;
the Government may not be in a position to agree to the projected increase in fuel levy&#13;
and road user charges and secondly the flow of funds, which is still through the&#13;
government budget process, could be delayed or diverted in the event of a deterioration in&#13;
fiscal and macroeconomic performance. There is a related risk of a shortfall on external&#13;
financing given that known new commitments for the road sector are less than the total&#13;
anticipated requirements for the project. These risks are being partially mitigated by&#13;
ensuring that the scope and objectives of the first two-year program are tailored to current&#13;
known local and external resource availability and adjusting the scope and objectives of&#13;
the outer years by mid-term review as a function whether this availability will actually&#13;
increase as projected or not. High and low case scenarios for the civil works program&#13;
have been developed as a function partly of the uncertainty about future financing levels&#13;
(see para 2.06). The financing implications of these scenarios is given below. The low&#13;
case represents the level to which total financing could fall without any further network&#13;
deterioration.&#13;
Table 4-1: Local Revenue Requirements of Various Scenarios&#13;
Required Local Required Road  Required G'mt  Required Max.&#13;
Total cost   Financing   Fund Revenues/i   Funding      Levy/2&#13;
Case      (US$, Mns)  (US$, Mns)    (US$, Mns)    (US$Mns)  (% Wholesale Price)&#13;
1. Low         372.45        123.89      100.45           23.44           0.23&#13;
2. Medium       459.80       157.78       130.62          27.16           0.33&#13;
3. High         617.75       188.63       151.53           37.10          0.43&#13;
1/ Fuel levy, international transit fees, weighbridge fines, and 30% of Road license fees&#13;
2/ This shows the level the levy needs to reach by 2002, assuming a constant domestic wholesale price&#13;
of fuel (K325/1 for petrol and K300/1 for diesel in 1996 Kwacha). For a 3% per annum decrease in&#13;
fuel consumption the equivalent amounts would be 30%, 42% and 55%.&#13;
4.17   A substantial part of local funding is from fuel levy proceeds. The fuel levy is&#13;
from fiscal 1997 onward calculated as percentage of the wholesale fuel price and thus&#13;
fuel levy proceeds are sensitive to changes in both fuel prices and fuel consumption. The&#13;
above analysis assumes that fuel prices in real local currency terms are constant, since the&#13;
fall in international fuel prices is expected to be of the same magnitude as the projected&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
depreciation of the Kwacha. It also assumes fuel consumption to grow at 3% per year in&#13;
line with expected GDP (and road traffic) growth. However, the relationship between&#13;
GDP and fuel consumption has historically been quite volatile and there is a risk that fuel&#13;
consumption could fall, thus reducing the expected proceeds form the fuel levy in any&#13;
given year. This risk, as well as a worst case scenario of a 4% p.a. increase in domestic&#13;
wholesale fuel prices have been modeled and are summarized below. To maintain&#13;
proceeds at the level anticipated for the year 2002 under the worst combination of&#13;
circumstances (4% p.a. increase in wholesale fuel prices, and a 3% p.a. decrease in&#13;
consumption), the fuel levy would have to reach the equivalent of US$0.105/1 for petrol&#13;
and US$0.097/1 for diesel. This is not considered to be unsustainable, although it is&#13;
certainly higher than the expected US$0.082/1 for petrol and US$0.076/1 for diesel if&#13;
wholesale prices remain constant and consumption increases.&#13;
Table 4-2: Fuel Levy Proceeds: Risk Analysis Summary&#13;
Fuel Consumption    Fuel&#13;
Increasing By 3%   Consumption&#13;
p.a.      Decreasing By&#13;
3%p.a.&#13;
2002          2002     l&#13;
Levy required to finance Medium Case Scenario:                         l&#13;
Petrol (k/i)                                 107            136&#13;
Diesel (k/l)                                 99             126&#13;
Levy as % wholesale price&#13;
For Wholesale Price of Fuel Constant        33%            42%&#13;
For Wholesale Price of Fuel Increasing by 4% p.a.  28%     36%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
5. AGREEMENTS REACHED AND&#13;
RECOMMENDATION&#13;
A.   Agreements&#13;
5.1   Prior to negotiations, the Government presented evidence satisfactory to IDA that&#13;
the following have been accomplished:&#13;
(i)  A letter outlining the Govermnent's road sector policies and road sector&#13;
investment program (paras 1.36, 3.6).&#13;
(ii) The publication of legislation providing for NRB powers to hire and pay for&#13;
its own staff (para 2.17, 3.2).&#13;
(iii) The draft project implementation plan and performance monitoring&#13;
indicators (para 3.4).&#13;
(iv) The proposed investment program for the first two years of the project&#13;
(para 2.6).&#13;
(v)  The selection criteria for the inclusion of roads in the proposed investment&#13;
program (para 2.6).&#13;
5.2   Prior to Board Presentation, the Government has taken the following actions&#13;
satisfactory to IDA:&#13;
(i)  The establishment of the environmental management unit and the adoption&#13;
of environmental standards and guidelines (para 4.12).&#13;
(ii) The issuance of a request for consultant proposals for the management&#13;
support team in NRB (para 3.2).&#13;
5.3   Prior to Effectiveness, the Government will take the following actions satisfactory&#13;
to IDA:&#13;
(i)  The finalization of the project implementation plan and performance&#13;
indicators (para 3.4).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
(ii) The employment of consultants for the management support team in NRB&#13;
(para 3.2).&#13;
(iii) The issuance of tenders for the engineering of all rehabilitation work to be&#13;
carried out during the first two years of the project (para 3.5).&#13;
5.4   Prior to credit disbursement on the community accessibility component, the&#13;
Government will provide operational guidelines and a memorandum of understanding on&#13;
the roles of the implementing agencies to be satisfactory to IDA (para 3.4).&#13;
B.   Assurances Provided at Negotiations&#13;
5.5   The Government provided assurances at negotiations that it will:&#13;
(a)  Carry out the project in accordance with the implementation plan, including&#13;
a mid-term review no later than June 30, 2000 and annual reviews&#13;
(commencing 1998) no later the October 31 of the preceding year, and&#13;
utilizing reporting procedures and performance monitoring indicators&#13;
acceptable to IDA (para 3.1).&#13;
(b) Maintain project accounting consistent with internationally accepted&#13;
standards, and submit annual audited financial reports no later than 6 months&#13;
after the end of each fiscal year according to terms of reference agreed with&#13;
IDA and maintain appropriate technical auditing standards acceptable to&#13;
IDA (paras 3.21, 3.22, 3.23).&#13;
(c)  Carry out policy studies, engineering feasibility and design studies,&#13;
institutional development and capacity building in implementing agencies&#13;
per the project and according to terms of reference to be reviewed with and&#13;
agreed to by IDA (paras 3.9, 3.10, 3.11).&#13;
(d) Adopt procurement procedures acceptable to IDA including the use of the&#13;
Bank standard bidding documents for works and goods under ICB and for&#13;
consultants services, the use of an agreed local bidding document for civil&#13;
works under NCB, and the use of a standard simplified document for the&#13;
procurement of small works and for directly contracted works (paras 3.5,&#13;
3.17).&#13;
(e)  Review the revenue requirements for the Road Fund on an annual basis and&#13;
utilize the proceeds of the Road Fund exclusively for routine and periodic&#13;
maintenance costs, for the counterpart contribution of donor funded projects&#13;
approved under the project, and for the operating costs of NRB not&#13;
exceeding 5% of total Road Fund proceeds in any year (para 3.7).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
(f)  Adopt and maintain agreed selection criteria for the inclusion of road&#13;
projects in the program and to agree not to undertake any works outside of&#13;
the project (para 2.6).&#13;
(g) Assure the continued function of the Highway Management System (HMS)&#13;
and the Roads Training School (RTS) throughout the life of the project and&#13;
to provide all the necessary funding for the respective programs to be agreed&#13;
on an annual basis with IDA no later than the date of the annual review&#13;
(paras 1.19, 1.27, 2.8, 2.9); and&#13;
(h) Carry out an action plan to improve road safety (See para 2.9).&#13;
(i)  Prepare and submit for agreement with IDA the operational guidelines and a&#13;
memorandum of understanding on the roles of the implementing agencies&#13;
for the carrying out of the community accessibility component of the project&#13;
(para 2.7).&#13;
C.   Recommendation&#13;
5.6   On the basis of the above actions, conditions and agreements, the proposed&#13;
Program would be suitable for support from an IDA credit of SDR 51.5 million (US$70.0&#13;
million equivalent).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
Definitions of Terms&#13;
Terms                                                                       Meaning&#13;
Routine                       Regular (often daily) maintenance activities carried out on the road including grading, clearing&#13;
Maintenance                   of drains, pothole patching, vegetation control, painting of signs and roadside furniture,&#13;
sweeping and major repairs.&#13;
l..............  .............................................................................I......................................................................................................&#13;
Periodic                      Maintenance activities which are carried out a number of times during the life of the road but&#13;
Maintenance                   with intervals of more than one year between them  (usually 3-7 years apart). This includes&#13;
resealing with single surface dressing or premix and painting of shoulders on paved roads and&#13;
regravelling to restore depleted  on gravel roads as well as spot repair for up to 10%  of the road&#13;
surface area.&#13;
Upgrading                     This is the work required to raise the standard of an existing road to a higher class of&#13;
engineered road, e.g. converting a gravel road to a paved road.&#13;
...........................................  ............................................................................................................................................................................... .....&#13;
Rehabilitation                This is work done in scarifying existing pavement by replacing poor base and sub-base in order&#13;
to restore to original design; and in case of paved roads: Resurfacing  (three options linked&#13;
with, roughness, rutting depth and extent and nature of cracks): slurry seal (superficial cracks,&#13;
few  ruts); single or double bituminous surface dressing; and premix carpetloverlay of&#13;
appropriate thickness. Options include spot repair in excess of 10%  of the road surface area&#13;
Reconstruction                A  category of rehabilitation involving replacement of below  standard parts of the road&#13;
structure. This can include scarifying existing pavement resurfacing (slurry soil, single or&#13;
double surface existing, premix). surface ripping up and recompacting pavement layers,&#13;
addition of new  pavement layers including strengthening and widening, reshaping etc.&#13;
Generally this follows the existing alignment but can include improvements to the vertical and&#13;
horizontal alignment isolated section. For unpaved roads reconstruction involves regravelling&#13;
to appropriate thickness.&#13;
..................................... ....................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
New  Construction             These are the activities required to construct a new  road when no road exists.&#13;
, ...................        ... ..................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
Designated Roads              This term  refers to legal declaration of the status of a road in terms of CAP 766 of the Laws of&#13;
Zambia. Roads are designated and formally gazetted in the Government Gazette.&#13;
l.~     ..    .........I............... I--.........................................I.............. ...........................................................................................................&#13;
Undesignated Roads  This refers to roads which have never been designated before as above. This group of roads&#13;
includes those roads which are often (but erroneously) referred to as "Unclassified Roads". An&#13;
Undesignated road is however always "unclassified" as the standard for the road has not been&#13;
specified.&#13;
lassified Roads               These are roads which have been legally designated and in addition the class or standard of&#13;
sections of the road has been specified. Classification of a road or sections of a road is based&#13;
on the design standard and surface type. For an example, an inter-territorial trunk (T) road&#13;
would be designated for its entire length as a "T" road in accordance with its function but the&#13;
standard may vary along its length as traffic levels vary. In this case the designation of the&#13;
road remains as "T" but the route consists of various classifications based on geometric&#13;
standards of the sections.&#13;
......................            ............................................................................................................................................................................... ....&#13;
Unclassified Roads            These are roads for which the geometric standards have not been specified. It is noted that all&#13;
Undesignated roads have not been classified and therefore are unclassified. It is also noted&#13;
however that standards for some designated roads (legally declared) have not been specified&#13;
and these designated roads are also unclassified.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
ROAD CONDITION&#13;
A. Paved Roads&#13;
Roughness based on International&#13;
Traffic Vehicles Per Day            Roughness Index&#13;
Good         Fair         Poor&#13;
00-299                   0-8          8-11         &gt; 11&#13;
300-999                  0-6          6-9          &gt; 9&#13;
1000+                    0- 5         5 - 8        &gt; 8&#13;
B. Gravel Roads&#13;
Comfortable Travel Speed (km/hr.)&#13;
-Type              Good         Fair              Poor&#13;
Main Gravel        &gt; 80       60 - 80             &lt; 60&#13;
I Other Gravel      &gt; 60       40 - 60             &lt; 40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
54 -&#13;
Annex 1-1&#13;
Page I of 10&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
Letter of Road Sector Policy&#13;
c,&#13;
?t4n:  LU&amp;L 25426tJ(WZc-                                            e&#13;
Tti= ZA 42221                                                                Pyptaqj&#13;
Fa* 23494                                                                .,VoJIF.,MO      IV&#13;
REPUBLIC OF Z7MBI&#13;
4ISTRY OF FIN4ANCE AND ECONOPi0IC D'EV!OPMEN?&#13;
OFFICE OF THE AfLNISTr&#13;
P.O. BOX 50062&#13;
EIDGEWAY, 15101&#13;
21st March 1997                                                        CrLANGAUROAI&#13;
LUSAZk&#13;
Mr. James D. Wolfensohn&#13;
President&#13;
World Bank&#13;
1818 H Steet, N.W.&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
TJNE  ST.ATES OF AMERICA&#13;
Dear Mr. Wolfensohn:&#13;
RE: ZAMBIA'S ROAD SECrOR POLICIES AND ROAD SECTOR INVEST ENT&#13;
PROGRAMNE (ROADSIP)&#13;
This letter summarises various policy measures which the Government intends to&#13;
pursue to support implementation of its road sector strtegy during the period 1997 to 2002.&#13;
The letter deals first with the Governmentes economic and social development policies; second&#13;
with transport sector policies; third with road sector; fourth with the Government's policies&#13;
and objectives for the road sector; and finally with the various road sector policy issues which&#13;
the Government intends to tackle during the period up to the year 2002.&#13;
Economic and Social Development Policies&#13;
2. Government's medium term macroeconomic poUcy framework has been desigzted to&#13;
promote economic growth with stability based on market determined allocation of resources.&#13;
In the MIedium Term Fmancial Framework (1996-1998) , priority spending focusses on those&#13;
sectors that support growth such as roads, agriculture and provision of social services.&#13;
The objectives of this policy framework are;&#13;
2.1   to speed up the institutional reform process through the Public Service Reform&#13;
Programme (PSRP);&#13;
2.2   to continue with the policy of economic libernlisatlon and further encourage the&#13;
release of the private sector initiative and investment to facilitate the attainment of positive per&#13;
capita growth; and&#13;
2.3   to pursue an ambitious privatisation   programme  aimed at increasing&#13;
participation of the private sector in the economy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
Annex 1-1&#13;
Page 2 of 10&#13;
It is only by achieving these objectives that government can provide on a sustainable basis,&#13;
basic social services, a social safety net for the vulnerable a2nd rehabilitate /maintain essential&#13;
economic and social infrastructure.&#13;
Transport Sector Policy Framework&#13;
3.     Government's policy objective framnework for the Communications and Transport sector&#13;
is to improve the operating efficiency and performance of the sector for the benefit of the&#13;
customers' changing requirements as spelt out in the transport policy White Paper 1995. The&#13;
primary objectives of the policy are to:&#13;
3.1   ensure availability of sufficient resources from the private and public sectors to&#13;
create capacity in the sector commensurate with the requiremnents of the economy;&#13;
3.2   allocate available resources among modes to meet requirements at minimum cost&#13;
to society; and&#13;
3.3   establish a system of pricing that will ensure a reasonable return on transport&#13;
investments.&#13;
4.     Government will therefore continue to accord high priority to rehabilitation and&#13;
maintenance of infrastructure  in order to stimulate and optimise the existing productive&#13;
capacities in the following sub-sectors of Communications and Transport:&#13;
4.1    CivilAviation: after, the liquidation of the National carrier, Zambia Airways,&#13;
Government's policy has been to liberalise the civil aviation industry to encourage and promote&#13;
private operations of airlines and airports. By the end of 1996, a total of eight (8) Zambian&#13;
registered private holders of air service permits were operating air transport services carrying&#13;
passengers and cargo on domestic, regional and international routes;&#13;
4.2    Rail transport: as railways are the backbone of the Zambian transport system,&#13;
I&#13;
accounting for a significant percentage of the movement of the country s imports and exports, the&#13;
Government is focussing on enhancing the railways capacity by commercialising it in order to&#13;
improve the performance of the sector;&#13;
4.3    Road Transport: both passenger and freight transportation have been liberalised.&#13;
Government efforts shall be confined to matters relating to safety and quality of service and&#13;
improving access to rural areas as a matter of priority;&#13;
4.4   Inland Waterways Transport: the Government policy shall be to encourage the&#13;
development of inland waterways and maritime transport by commercialising the sector;&#13;
4.5    Urban Transport: Government focus shall be to promote the use of mass transit&#13;
systems, after determination of an optimal modal mix, ensure quality of service and orderliness in&#13;
public transport operations; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-56 -&#13;
Annex 1-1&#13;
Page 3 of 10&#13;
4.6    Communications: to increase competition and efficiency throughout the economy&#13;
the former Posts and Telecommunications Corporation has been split into Zambia&#13;
Telecommunications Company (ZTC) and Zambia Postal services. The former is scheduled for&#13;
privatisation.&#13;
Background to the Road Sector&#13;
5.    Zambia has an area of 753,000 sq.km, with a total population in 1995 estimated at about&#13;
9.3 million inhabitants. The present state and future development of its economy is supported by a&#13;
multi-modal transportation system operated through various infrastructure including roads,&#13;
railways, airways, inland waterways, and pipelines. Among these, the road infrastructure is the&#13;
most significant in termns of network extent and dispersion across the country. Since the 1980s,&#13;
traffic has shifted from rail to road.&#13;
6.    In 1995, the total length of the road network was estimated at about 67,000 km made up&#13;
of 36,761 km of gazetted and designated roads under various functional classes and about&#13;
30,000 km of ungazetted roads. Road usage is about 129,000 motor vehicle units per day of&#13;
various types and about one million litres of fuel consumed per day including both petrol and&#13;
automotive diesel.&#13;
7.    At present, approxinately 20 percent of the road network is in good condition, 40&#13;
percent fair and 40 percent poor, due to persistent neglect of maintenance. The root cause for&#13;
failure to maintain the road network could be attributed to inadequate funding and poor&#13;
management of the Road Sector.&#13;
8.    Government decided to introduce a fuel levy in 1993 whose proceeds are deposited into&#13;
the Road Fund. The National Roads Board (NRB) was established in 1994 to manage and&#13;
administer the Road Fund for the purpose of maintaining and rehabilitating roads in the country.&#13;
Objectives of the Road Sector&#13;
9.    On the basis of the foregoing, the Government through its Ministry of Communications&#13;
and Transport (MCT) established a national task force in June i995 to prepare a Road Sector&#13;
Investment Programme (ROADSIP) after extensive consultation with local stakeholders and with&#13;
the donor and Non- Governmental Organisations(NGOs) comrnmunities. I note that the Bank has&#13;
actively supported this process by providing part of the funding requirements to prepare position&#13;
papers, which were presented as a basis for discussion at a stakeholder workshop in February&#13;
1996. The workshop endorsed the proposed ROADSIP which was subsequently discussed and&#13;
agreed to by my Government.&#13;
10.   The overall  objective of the Government is to facilitate economic growth and&#13;
diversification, particularly in the agriculture sector through appropriate investment in road&#13;
infrastructure. ROADSIP is to be implemented in two phases over a period of 10 years (1997-&#13;
2007) and is expected to lead to a substantial improvement in the quality of the road network and&#13;
road sector management. It is envisaged that the goals of phase 1 (1997-2002) of the programme&#13;
will be to:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-.57 -&#13;
Annex 1-1&#13;
Page 4 of 10&#13;
10.1  create a domestic sustainable system for financing and management of the&#13;
road network which will reduce dependence on erternal financing for maintenance and&#13;
rehabilitation;&#13;
10.2  increase the proportion of roads in good condition to no less than 50 percent of&#13;
the network, thus reducing vehicle operating costs;&#13;
10.3   address poor accessibility in the rural areas with emphasis on feeder roads&#13;
leading to productive areas;&#13;
10.4   put in place an accelerated programme to address the deterioration of selected&#13;
main and urban roads; and&#13;
10.5  put in place measures that will mitigate against adverse effects that road works&#13;
might have on the environment.&#13;
The Government has determined that ROADSIP will be the all encompassing programme for&#13;
road sector investments. Accordingly, Government intends that all future donor support wfll&#13;
be channelled through ROADSIP.&#13;
Road Sector Development Strategy&#13;
11.   In order to achieve the above objectives , the Government will adopt the following&#13;
strategies for road sector development:-&#13;
Strengthening Institutionalfframework.&#13;
11.1. Creating an appropriate institutional framework for management of the road&#13;
network- will be the Government's highest priority during this period.  This is to be&#13;
implemented in two phases:&#13;
11.1.1. strengthening the NRB, and complete restructuring of the Roads&#13;
Department (RD) in the Ministry of Works and Supply (MWS) and the Department of&#13;
Infrastructure and Support Services(DISS) in the NMinistry of Local Government and Housing&#13;
(MLGH) within the framework of the PSRP, to enhance the capacity, increase efficiency in&#13;
the use of resources and improve planning and implementation performance in the&#13;
management of the road sector; and&#13;
11.1.2. by mid-term review of ROADSIP, assess the opportunity to rationalise&#13;
these institutions by vesting in a single commercially oriented semi-autonomous NRB, full&#13;
responsibility for managing the road sector with Government retaining overall policy and&#13;
planning functions for roads.&#13;
Rehabilitating Priority Roads.&#13;
11.2. Given the large backlog of deferred maintenance, the civil works programme to&#13;
be financed under ROADSIP will focus on rehabilitation of roads classified as being in poor&#13;
condition.  The Government will develop and adopt consistent selection criteria and&#13;
specifications for road programmes and for maintenance standards to ensure scarce financial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-58 -&#13;
Annex i-1&#13;
Page 5 of 10&#13;
resources are applied to highest priority programmes. Priorities will be established on the&#13;
basis of:&#13;
11.2.1. economic rates of return(ERR) for main and trunk roads. The threshold&#13;
value of the ERR will be subject to agreement with the Bank prior to credit negotiatdons.&#13;
Government may seek agreement with the Bank  on specific projects that do not meet the&#13;
threshold value requirements, but are of high strategic priority andlor considerable social&#13;
benefis.&#13;
11.2.2. multi criteria ranking for feeder roads, and national parks access&#13;
roads.&#13;
Government will make intensive efforts to identify least cost most appropriate&#13;
solutions for rehabilitating roads. All roads rehabilitated under ROADSIP will be placed&#13;
under annual routine maintenance and periodic maintenance. Non-engineered roads will be&#13;
selectively upgraded, based on selection criteria to be agreed with the Bank. This stratgy&#13;
aims to reduce the proportion of the core road network classified as being in poor condition&#13;
from the current level of 40 percent to 20 percent by the end of phase one of the programme&#13;
period.&#13;
11.3. The rehabilitation programme under phase one is expected to cover 2100 km&#13;
of paved roads (Bituminous) and 4050 km of unpaved roads countrywide fUSS270 million].&#13;
The works to be undertaken  will include full reconstruction, upgrading of selected non-&#13;
engineered roads, spot improvement and minor rehabilitation. A first full year programme&#13;
of ROADSIP has been prepared by the Government and will be reviewed and agreed with the&#13;
Bank not later than credit negotiations . Bids will be invited for all works included in the&#13;
first year programme of ROADSIP and will be issued by credit effectiveness. The scope and&#13;
content of the rehabilitation programme wiU be reviewed annually by Government in&#13;
consultation with the Bank and stakeholders. As a matter of urgency,  the first year&#13;
proaramme includes priority main and urban roads which require immediate attention&#13;
through an accelerated rehabilitation programme.&#13;
Ensuring Effective MVaintenance.&#13;
11.4. During the past 20 years, the country's road network has suffered badly from&#13;
the neglect of maintenance and the Government is determined, with the assistance of the Road&#13;
Fund, to give high priority to routine and periodic maintenance of all roads classified as being&#13;
in good and fair condition. The annual routine maintenance programme will aim to cover&#13;
about 7,200 km in 1998 and this will rise to about 16,700 km by 2002 [USS 79 million]. The&#13;
periodic maintenance programme will likewise cover resealing/ resurfacing of about 4,100 km&#13;
of paved roads and regravelling of 2,180 km of gravel roads over the five year programme&#13;
period [USS 84 million].&#13;
MVanaging MVaintenance       -&#13;
1i.i.  Roads Department (RD):  The Government recognizes that the institutional&#13;
capacity of the RD to plan and implement road maintenance programmes has been seriously&#13;
eroded, largely on account of poor remuneration and inadequate funding . The Government&#13;
has recognized the need to address this issue and has therefore approved a plan to restructure&#13;
the RFD under the PSRP. The restructuring focuses on moving away from force account work&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-59-&#13;
Annex 1-1&#13;
Page 6 of 10&#13;
and turning the RD into an organization which plans and supervises work carried out by&#13;
private sector consultants and contractors. Specifically, the Government strategy is:&#13;
11.5.1. to phase out force account within a period of five (5) years starting&#13;
with Lusaka and Copperbelt provinces. The implementation of this strategy will be reviewed&#13;
on an annual basis and adjusted when necessary. The RD will only retain some small core&#13;
teams to undertake emergency work and maintenance work. In parallel with these steps,&#13;
training opportunities will be offered to enable redundant staff to move into the construction&#13;
industry as consultants or contractors;&#13;
11.5.2. at the same time, to take steps to commercialise the Department's&#13;
quarries  prior to privatising these entities within 5 years, in line with the phasing out of&#13;
force account;  to  hand over management of weigh-bridges  to the NRB to have them&#13;
managed under contract; and to delegate the management of pontoons to local communities&#13;
or other commercial entities, where feasible;.&#13;
11.5.3. to put particular emphasis on the strengthening of the Provincial Road&#13;
Engineer's (PREs) functions within the RD, under the PSRP. Accordingly, it has been&#13;
necessary to ensure appropriate experience and qualifications are required for the positions&#13;
which are to be advertised. If it proves impossible to recruit suitable staff, the Government&#13;
will assess with the Bank - no later than the time of the first annual review of ROADSIP- the&#13;
alternative course of action that could be adopted to ensure the effective supervision of&#13;
rehabilitation and maintenance works. This will include a deliberate intervention of&#13;
development of local staff to ensure that they acquire the necessary sidlls and experience to&#13;
enable them to undertake effective supervision of rehabilitation and maintenance works. On a&#13;
short term basis expatriate staff will be recruited for purposes of enhancing the capacity and&#13;
capability of Zambian technical personnel;&#13;
11.5.4. adopt measures to maintain an inventory and update the road condition&#13;
data through the Highway Management System (HMS); and&#13;
11.5.5. strengthen the planning and supervisory capacity of the RD to ensure&#13;
the consistent application of appropriate engineering standards and technical specifications.&#13;
11.6. Natonal Roads Board (NRB): The Government recognizes the effectiveness of&#13;
the IRB and has therefore assigned to it primary responsibility for overseeing implementation&#13;
of ROADSIP. To ensure it can perform this function and discharge the duties assigned to it,&#13;
the Government has agreed that the NRB should be strengthened. This will be done by&#13;
publishing appropriate legislation, prior to credit negotiations, which wil provide the NRB&#13;
with powers to:&#13;
11.6.1. recruit an Executive Secretary and other staff as may be needed to&#13;
manage the Road Fund and discharge the other duties assigned to the NRB under terms and&#13;
conditions of service determined by the NNRB; and&#13;
11.6.2. charge the costs of the NRB  staff, excluding the costs of any staff&#13;
financed under donor-financed aid programmes, against the Road Fund provided such costs&#13;
do not exceed 5 percent of the annual revenue derived from road user charges.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
Annex i-l&#13;
Page 7oflO&#13;
In addition, the Minister of Comunications and Transport wiU communicate&#13;
to the NRB, powers and arrangements under   which the NRB  will discharge its&#13;
responsibilities. The INR3 and the Road Fund were established through a Road Maintenance&#13;
Initiative(RMII) consultative process. Therefore, any substantive changes to the composition of&#13;
the Board will be by mutual agreement the Government and the World Bank.&#13;
11.7. Department of Infrastructure and Support Services (DISS): DISS has managed&#13;
to recruit two of the three staff forming part of its Roads Section. It is also receiving&#13;
Technical support from the International Development Agency (IDA) through an international&#13;
firmn of consultants financed under the Transport Engineering and Technical Assistance&#13;
Project (TETAP). At least three months before the end of the consultant's contract, the&#13;
MLGH will advise the Bank on what steps it intends to take to ensure it has the capacity to&#13;
continue supporting the urban and rural councils to rehabilitate and maintain their urban and&#13;
feeder road networks. These steps might involvement of private local consultants to take over&#13;
the support providing consultancy and project supervision services to local authorities.&#13;
Developing the Domestic Construction and Consulting Industy.&#13;
11.8. The Government strategy is to:&#13;
11.8.1. encourage  private  sector  involvement  in  road  construction,&#13;
rehabilitation and maintenance through assuring a predictable and growing market for the&#13;
local construction industry;&#13;
11.8.2. develop road maintenance and engineering skills, especially in labour&#13;
based construction methods;&#13;
11.9  The Government has therefore,  decided that the capacity of the domestic&#13;
consulting and construction industry needs to be enhanced and increased by removing any&#13;
constraints hampering active involvement of local consultants and contractors.    The&#13;
programme to address these constraints will be coordinated by the MWS in close&#13;
collaboration with the National Construction Council (NCC) and includes the following:&#13;
11.9.1. technical assistance to improve Government contracting policies and&#13;
procedures (including streainlining consultant, contractor registration procedures, developing&#13;
new simplified tendering procedures, contract documentation, and streamlining the legal&#13;
framework);&#13;
11.9.2. further development of training programmes for consultants and&#13;
contractors with particular emphasis on labour based work methods and strengthening the&#13;
capacity of the Roads Training School;&#13;
11.9.3. provision  of equipment to   local contractors through  leasing&#13;
arrangements. Funding is to be identified-to help the expansion of Zambian leasing companies&#13;
into the small equipment business;&#13;
11.9.4. provision of credit financing to medium scale contractors through the&#13;
financial system; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-61 -&#13;
Annex 1-1&#13;
Page 8 of 10&#13;
11.9.5. encouragement of joint ventures between foreign contractors and&#13;
consultants and indigenous consultants and contractors to build the capacity and capability.&#13;
Improving MVanagement of Roads Deparrment P!ant and Equipment.&#13;
11.10. Government strategy is to improve the management of plant and equipment&#13;
owned by the RD. In view of the low availability rate of plant and equipment in the&#13;
Department coupled with the decisioa to phase out force account, Government has decided to&#13;
11.10.1.     dispose of all unsenriceable plant and equipment;&#13;
11.10.2.     down-size the existing Mechanical Engineering Section (MES) in&#13;
the RD in line with the PSRP;&#13;
11.10.3.     establish a small unit in each province. for emergency work&#13;
holding only the minimum amount of equipment subject to the proviso that in remote&#13;
provinces, a larger pool may be held to facilitate hire of equipment to the private sector; and&#13;
11.10.4.     review  the need for these units and identify any excess&#13;
equipment to be disposed of, after the first year of the programme&#13;
Mfobilising and allocadon of Road Sector Revenues.&#13;
11.11. Government policy is that local financing shall cover an increasing share of&#13;
sustainable maintenance and rehabilitation costs during the programme period. An estimated&#13;
US$14.5 million representing Government's counterpart financing obUgations to on-going&#13;
donor financed projects which will continue to be fnanced from the Government 's general&#13;
budget. Al road user charges will be channelled through the Road Fund. Road Fund&#13;
resources will be allocated as follows:&#13;
11.1.1.i     as a first charge, routine and periodic maintenance of all core&#13;
roads classified as being in good and fair condition;&#13;
11.11.2.     as  a  second  charge,  counterpart  funding  of  donor-financed&#13;
rehabilitation programmes; and&#13;
11.11.3.     the costs of managing the Road Fund which are not to exceed 5&#13;
percent of the road fund revenues mobilised through road user charges).&#13;
11.12. In line with the need to increase the sustainable flow of resources through the&#13;
Road Fund, the Government shall consider increasing road user charges and ensure that in&#13;
future the bulk of such revenues are channelled to the Road Fund to fund maintenance and&#13;
rehabilitation. Specifically, the Government intends from fiscal year 1998, to allocate to the&#13;
Road Fund , international transit fees, weighbridge fines, and a portion of road service&#13;
license. From fiscal year 1997, fuel levy is expressed as a percentage of the wholesale fuel&#13;
price, which shall be reviewed  on an annual basis.  The Government recognises the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
Annex I-]&#13;
Page 9 of 10&#13;
importance of streamlining procedures for managing fuel levy proceeds to the benefit of the&#13;
programme. The Government has therefore decided that henceforth, Zambia National Oil&#13;
Company (ZNOC) shall directly deposit proceeds from the fuel levy into the Ministry of&#13;
Finance and Economic Development account, who in turn shall channell it without delay into&#13;
the Road Fund.&#13;
Improving, Community Accessibility.&#13;
11.13. The Government recognises the importance of bringing as many roads as&#13;
possible under regular maintenance, particularly in rural areas where many roads do not&#13;
form part of the public road network, but are nevertheless important for agriculture and to&#13;
enable rural communities to gain access to essential services. ROADSIP will therefore include&#13;
a programme of community accessibility designed to develop an institutional framework for&#13;
sustainable management of community roads, bridges,culverts, canals,tracks and trails. The&#13;
programme will be carried out in conjunction with Social Recovery Projects (SRP) for&#13;
construction and rehabilitation of roads, and-the NRB for maintenance. The programme will&#13;
start on a pilot basis . Based on the results of the pilot, the Government will consider main-&#13;
streaming the scheme throughout the country.&#13;
11.14. The community accessibility programme also aims to encourage the increased&#13;
use of low-cost intermediate means of transport(IMT) which are affordable to rural&#13;
populations such as draught animals, carts, motorised and non-motorised two and three&#13;
wheelers. To this end, the programme will include studies on past and current experiences&#13;
with INIT in Zambia, assessments of policy and regulation and a demonstration project to&#13;
promote IMT.&#13;
Mitigating Environmental Impacts.&#13;
11.15. The plan for dealing with potential environmental impacts includes four&#13;
elements critical both to the development of capacity and to building linkages between the&#13;
sector programme and national environmental policy and guidelines. They include:&#13;
11.15.1.     establishment of an environmental management unit to be&#13;
housed initially in the RD with external funding for technical assistance and training during&#13;
the first t-o years of operation;&#13;
11.15.2.     development of road sector environmental guidelines, including&#13;
review and strengthening of the environmental clauses in use in national competitive bidding&#13;
(NCB) procurement documentation;&#13;
11.15.3.     carrying  out environmental assessments on specific road&#13;
improvement projects on a selective basis; and&#13;
11.15.4.     carrying put monitoring and evaluatioa activity to ensure&#13;
compliance with environmental guidelines during the construction phase of projects.&#13;
Improving Road Safety&#13;
11.16. Government is mindful of the unsatisfactory state of road safety in the country&#13;
and has agreed that the National Road Safety Council (NRSC), under the MCT, should&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
Annex I-1&#13;
Page 10 of 10&#13;
prepare an Action Plan which would have as its target improving road safety and reducing&#13;
road accident fatalities by at least 20 percent by the year 2002. The Action Plan would be&#13;
prepared and presented to the Bank by the first annual review of ROADSIP.&#13;
Revising Road Sector Legislation&#13;
11.17. Many, if not most, of the above policy initiatives have implications for the&#13;
Roads and Road Traffic Act, Chapter 766 of the Laws of Zambia ( CAP 766) and the various&#13;
amendments passed since 1959. Government therefore intends to revise CAP 766 during the&#13;
course of ROADSIP to brine it up to date, to reflect the policy decisions taken since 1959 and&#13;
to put the Road Fund and the NRB on a firm legislative basis. Much of the preliminary work&#13;
required to revise CAP 766 has already been done and Government intends to work towards&#13;
having legislation ready for consideration by Parliament during the 1999 session. The scope of&#13;
the intended legislation will be discussed with the Bank not later than the mid-term review of&#13;
ROADSIP.&#13;
Reviewing Implementation of ROADSIP&#13;
11.18. Since ROADSIP has a large number of components, and includes several&#13;
important policy reforms, the Government intends to review the programme with the Bank&#13;
and other donors on an annual basis. At the mid-point of the planned implementation period,&#13;
the Government will also undertake a more detailed review of progress with the Bank and&#13;
other donors. During these reviews, there will be a general review of progress against the&#13;
various targets established in the programme implementation manual, together with a review&#13;
of progress in implementing the policy measures included in this letter of sector policy. Based&#13;
on these reviews, the Government may then request the Bank to discuss the provisions in this&#13;
letter and amend them to reflect changes in the overall macro-economic environment, agreed&#13;
new directions occasioned by unexpected opportunities or constraints, and changes that reflect&#13;
lessons learned in relation to the desired policy objectives of ROADSIP. If necessary, the&#13;
CGovernment will request that these amendments be reflected in appropriate changes made to&#13;
the credit agreement.&#13;
12.   I trust that the above policy framework gives confidence that an effective and efficient&#13;
road network is one of the country's highest priorities and that the Government is willing to go&#13;
to great lengths to ensure we achieve this objective.&#13;
Yours sincerely&#13;
RON M&#13;
MINISTER OF-FINANCE &amp;&#13;
ECONOtMIC DEVELOPMIENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
Annex 2-la&#13;
Page 1 of 4&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
Description of Civil Works Program&#13;
1) Routine Maintenance&#13;
Year     km&#13;
Paved    G Main   G         Feeder   P Urban  G Urban  Subtotal&#13;
District&#13;
1997/98      3748      394      1896       150      382       160     6730&#13;
1999       4418       496     2040      1400       382      210      8946&#13;
2000       5091       904      2184     2000       382       260    10821&#13;
2001       5452      1662      2528     2700       432       360    13134&#13;
200'2       5746     2159      3172     3600       482       460    15619&#13;
Total      24454     5616    11819      9850      2062      1451    55251&#13;
Year     US$ m&#13;
Paved    G Main   G         Feeder   P Urban  G Urban  Subtotal&#13;
District&#13;
1997/98      4.62      0.67     2.90      0.09      0.57     0.36      9.21&#13;
1999        5.45     0.85      3.12      0.84     0.57      0.47     11.29&#13;
2000        6.28      1.54     3.34      1.20     0.57      0.58     13.51&#13;
2001        6.72      2.84     3.87      1.62     0.64      0.81     16.50&#13;
2002        7.08      3.69     4.85      2.16     0.71      1.03     19.53&#13;
Total      30.15      9.60     18.08     5.91      3.05     3.26    70.05&#13;
Note: Paved road includes Trunk (T), Main (M), District (D) roads.&#13;
2) Periodic Maintenance&#13;
Year     km&#13;
P Trunk  P Main    G Main  P District G District Feeder   P Urban  G Urban  Subtotal&#13;
1997/98       434       36       102        75      144       850         0       50       1691&#13;
1999        313        36       407       75       144         0        0        50       1025&#13;
2000           0       36       758       75       344         0        0       100       1313&#13;
2001           0       36       497        75      644         0        0       100       1352&#13;
2002           0       36        71       75      1144         0        0       100       1426&#13;
Total        747      180      1836       374     2420       850         0      400       6807&#13;
Year     US$ m&#13;
P Trunk  P Main    G Main  P District G District Feeder   P Urban  G Urban  Subtotal&#13;
1997/98      7.99      0.66      1.24     1.10      1.44     1.70      0.00      0.60      14.74&#13;
1999        5.76     0.66      4.92      1.10     1.44      0.00     0.00      0.60       14.50&#13;
2000        0.00      0.66     9.16      1.10     3.45      0.00      0.00      1.21      15.59&#13;
2001        0.00      0.66     6.01      1.10      6.46     0.00      0.00      1.21      15.44&#13;
2002        0.00      0.66     0.86      1.10    11.48      0.00      0.00      1.21      15.31&#13;
Total      13.75      3.31    22.19      5.51     24.28      1.70     0.00      4.83      75.58&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
Annex 2-la&#13;
Page 2 of 4&#13;
3) Rehabilitation&#13;
Year    km                                             US$ m&#13;
P Trunk  P Main   P Urban  Subtotal           P Trunk  P Main   P Urban  Subtotal&#13;
1997/98      125        0         0      125              15.00     0.00     0.00      15.00&#13;
1999        203       47        0       250             24.36      5.62     0.00      29.98&#13;
2000        203       47        75      300              24.36     5.62     3.00      32.98&#13;
2001        113       70        75      233              13.56     8.42     3.00      24.98&#13;
2002        356       70       150      526              30.13     5.97     6.00      42.10&#13;
Total      1000      234       300     1434             107.41    25.62    12.00     145.04&#13;
4) Upgrading of Feeder Roads                  5) Accessibility Improvement for Feeder Roads&#13;
Year    km        US$ mn                      Year    km        US$ mn&#13;
1997/98      400      3.64                    1997/98    17000      5.10&#13;
1999        600      5.46                     1999      17000      5.10&#13;
2000        700      6.37                     2000      16300      4.89&#13;
2001        900      8.19                     2001      15400      4.62&#13;
2002       1000      9.10                     2002      14400      4.32&#13;
Total      3600    32.76                      Total     80100    24.03&#13;
Notes:&#13;
Accessibility Improvement will be applied on the average 15% of the length mentioned in table 5).&#13;
Source: RD and own estimation&#13;
Unit Costs (US$ per km)&#13;
P Trunk  P Main   G Main   P District G District Feeder   P Urban  G Urban&#13;
Routine Maintenance    1233     1233     1709     1233      1530      600     1480       2246&#13;
Periodic             18412    18412    12086    14729    10033       2000    21600      12086&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Rehabilitation      120000   120000      N.A.    N.A.    N.A.    N.A.   40000            N.A.&#13;
Upgrading of Unengineered Feeder Roads            9100&#13;
Accessibility Improvement for Feeder Roads        2000&#13;
Notes:&#13;
For paved T and M roads with relatively low traffic a low cost rehabilitation with unit cost of US$ 84650 per&#13;
km will be&#13;
applied in the fifth year.&#13;
Source: RD and own estimation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
Annex 2-la&#13;
Page 3 of 4&#13;
Base Cost in US$ million&#13;
Low Case      1997/98  1999   2000   2001   2002   Total&#13;
Routine           9.21   10.73  12.13  13.63  15.39  61.10&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Periodic         8.57   7.04   7.04   7.04   7.04  36.74&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Rehabilitation   11.67  20.74  21.26  38.30  38.82  130.79&#13;
Upgrade           3.28   4.91   5.73   7.37   8.19  29.48&#13;
Improve          4.59   4.59   4.40   4.16   3.89  21.63&#13;
Accessibility&#13;
Total           37.31  48.02  50.56  70.51  73.33 279.73&#13;
Base Case     1997/98  1999   2000   2001   2002   Total&#13;
Routine          9.21   11.29  13.51  16.50  19.53  70.05&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Periodic         14.74  14.50  15.59  15.44  15.31  75.58&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Rehabilitation   15.00  29.98  32.98  24.98  42.10  145.04&#13;
Upgrade           3.64   5.46   6.37   8.19   9.10  32.76&#13;
Improve           5.10   5.10   4.89   4.62   4.32  24.03&#13;
Accessibility&#13;
Total           47.69  66.33  73.34  69.74  90.37 347.46&#13;
High Case     1997/98  1999   2000   2001   2002   Total&#13;
Routine          9.21   11.08  14.25  17.61  21.82  73.98&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Periodic         7.12  19.85  19.85  26.47  26.47  99.75&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Rehabilitation  42.75  75.10  63.38  49.16  24.54 254.92&#13;
Upgrade          3.64   5.46   6.37   8.19   9.10  32.76&#13;
Improve           5.10   5.10   4.89   4.62   4.32  24.03&#13;
Accessibility&#13;
Total           67.82  116.58  108.75  106.04  86.24 485.44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
Annex 2-la&#13;
Page 4 of 4&#13;
Length in km&#13;
Low Case       1997/98  1999   2000   2001   2002   Total&#13;
Routine          6,730   8,424  9,701  11,099  12,777 48,732&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Periodic         1,253    488    488    488    488  3,206&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Rehabilitation      80    250    280    379    409   1,398&#13;
Upgrade           360    540    630    810    900  3,240&#13;
Improve         15,300  15,300  14,670  13,860  12,960  72,090&#13;
Accessibility&#13;
Base Case      1997/98  1999   2000   2001   2002   Total&#13;
Routine          6,730   8,946  10,821  13,134  15,619 55,251&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Periodic         1,691   1,025   1,313   1,352   1,426  6,807&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Rehabilitation     125    250    325    258    576   1,534&#13;
Upgrade           400    600    700    900   1,000  3,600&#13;
Improve         17,000  17,000  16,300  15,400  14,400  80,100&#13;
Accessibility&#13;
High Case      1997/98  1999   2000   2001   2002   Total&#13;
Routine          6,730   8,793  11,417  14,212  17,701  58,853&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Periodic         1,260   1,316   1,316   1,769   1,769  7,430&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Rehabilitation    403    708    779    820    589  3,299&#13;
Upgrade           400    600    700    900   1,000  3,600&#13;
Improve         17,000  17,000  16,300  15,400  14,400  80,100&#13;
Accessibility&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
Annex 2-lb&#13;
Page 1 of 2&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
ROAD SECTOR IN VESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
The Core Main Roads Program&#13;
Civil works on some of the main roads has been already started, partly under donor&#13;
financing. They are mentioned in Table (1) below. Of the remaining paved main roads&#13;
the road sections for which reconstruction, overlay and/or repair/reseal is also included&#13;
for the first two years of the program, are summarized in Table (2). The selection has&#13;
been based on cost benefit analysis with the highest priority being given to roads&#13;
demonstrating the highest economic rates of return (ERR) with benefits measured&#13;
primarily on the basis of vehicle operating cost savings (VOC). The methodology&#13;
underlying this analysis and the results of the various tests carried out are given in Annex&#13;
4-1. All ongoing and planned roads are a part of the overall yearly civil works program&#13;
described in the tables in Annex 2-la.&#13;
(1) Ongoing&#13;
Road           Section           Length    Major Financing    Type of Intervention&#13;
No.                           Implemented      Source&#13;
TOO1   Monze - Mazabuka           64 km    NORAD           Rehabilitation&#13;
T001   Mazabuka - Kafue           58 km    NORAD           Repair/Reseal&#13;
T002   Kapiri Mposhi - Serenje   198 km    DANIDA          Overlay&#13;
T004   Lusaka - Luangwa Bridge   375 km    AfDlB           Rehabilitation&#13;
T004   Luangwa Bridge                      DANIDA          Rehabilitation&#13;
MOOS   Mutanda - Jct Dl 81        104 km    GRZ            Reconstruction&#13;
MO10   Livingston - Shesheke     201 km    KfW             Under Feasibility Study&#13;
MO11   Choma - Namwala            169 km    GRZ            Reconstruction&#13;
D181   Jct M008 - Kasempa         47 km    GRZ             Reconstruction&#13;
D286   Manyinga - Mwinilunga     220 km    KfW             Upgrading&#13;
D469   Luanshya - Mpongwe         62 km    GRZ             Reconstruction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69-&#13;
Annex 2-lb&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
(2) Priority Roads Included in First Year Program&#13;
Road            Section             Length     Major Financing    Type of Intervention or&#13;
No.                              Implemented       Source               Remarks&#13;
TOO1    Zim Border - Livingstone       6 km                     Repair/Reseal&#13;
T002    Chirundu - Kafue              80 km    _                Repair/Reseal&#13;
T002    Kabwe - Kapiri Mposhi        68 km     EU               Reconstruction, Repair/&#13;
I                                         ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Reseal&#13;
T002    Serenje - Mpika             235 km     IDA              Repair/Reseal&#13;
T002    Mpika - Chinsali            168 km     IDA              Maintenance&#13;
T002    Chinsali - Nakonde          210 km     IDA              Maintenance&#13;
T003    Chingola - Kasumbalesa       46 km                      Overlay, Repair/Reseal&#13;
T004    Km 233 - Km 260              27 km                      Overlay&#13;
T005    Chingola - Solwezi          172 km                      Reconstruction&#13;
M004   Ndola - Mwambeshi             43 km                      Overlay, Repair/Reseal&#13;
M006   Kafulafuta - Luanshya         43 km                      Overlay, Repair/Reseal&#13;
M009   Lusaka - Mumbwa               65 km      IDA             Reconstruction,&#13;
I_________                 ______________                Repair/Reseal&#13;
M009   Mumbwa - Mongu                 86 km     IDA             Reconstruction,&#13;
_________  c___________________________  =____________  c___________  R epair/R eseal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
Annex 2-ic&#13;
Page 1 of 4&#13;
THE CORE FEEDER ROADS PROGRAM&#13;
1.    On the basis of comprehensive surveys carried out so far in five provinces, Zambia's&#13;
core feeder roads network has been estimated at 19,000 km. I The data collected indicates that&#13;
less than five percent of the primary network is in good or fair condition. The remainder is poor&#13;
or very poor. Under ROADSIP, improvement efforts will be of two types: i) upgrading which&#13;
will upgrade unengineered roads to acceptable engineering standards; and ii) accessibility&#13;
improvements which focus specifically on drainage and improvement of well known trouble&#13;
spots. Each district council, with advice from the MLGH central rural roads unit, will determine&#13;
the specific program in its jurisdiction. The strategy of each council will therefore need to strike&#13;
a compromise between upgrading and accessibility improvement. During ROADSIP, core&#13;
feeder roads in fair condition will receive periodic maintenance and then be included in a&#13;
sustainable routine maintenance program. All good feeder roads will be placed under routine&#13;
maintenance.&#13;
2.    It is foreseen that a total amount of US$ 60 million will be allocated to feeder roads&#13;
during the first five years of ROADSIP. IDA support to feeder roads will be US$16 million, i.e.,&#13;
one third of the total feeder roads program, and will be destined for three provinces--Luapula,&#13;
Northern, and Western. These provinces have been selected in consideration of on-going and&#13;
planned support by other donors to feeder roads.&#13;
3.    Given the scenario outlined in the table below, which assumes that US$ 60 million is&#13;
available for feeder roads over five years and that all core roads will receive some intervention,&#13;
3,600 km would be upgraded and the remainder of the core network would receive accessibility&#13;
improvements. Following this strategy, 56 percent of the funding ($33 million) will be allocated&#13;
to upgrading, 40 percent to accessibility improvement ($24 million) and four percent to periodic&#13;
maintenance ($2 million). At the end of the five year program, 4,600 km of feeder roads (24&#13;
percent of the core network) would be in good or fair condition receiving regular maintenance&#13;
compared to less than five percent of the feeder road network in year one, and 14, 400 km of the&#13;
core network (the remaining 76 percent) would have received annual accessibility improvements&#13;
during five years, something which will have significantly improved accessibility in rural&#13;
Zambia.&#13;
The surveys estimate that there are about 34,000 km of feeder roads in Zambia. On the basis of socio-&#13;
economic criteria, these have been divided into primary, secondary and tertiary feeder roads. The&#13;
primary roads constitute the core feeder roads network.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
Annex 2-ic&#13;
Page 2 of 4&#13;
Improvement (1cm)                               Routine&#13;
Upgrading    Access    Per. Maint.              Maintenance&#13;
Year    $9, 1 00/km   $2000/km    $2,000/km    Total km     (km)&#13;
1         400       17,000        1,000     18,400e-&#13;
2         600        17,000                  19,000       1,400&#13;
3         700        16,300                  19,000       2,000&#13;
4         900        15,400                  19,000       2,700&#13;
5        1000        14,400                  19,000       3,600&#13;
Total km    3,600       80,100                  19,000&#13;
Total $   33 million  24 million*    2 million  I&#13;
*Accessibility Improvements will be made on 15 percent of the core network which is not in good&#13;
or fair condition or scheduled for upgrading.&#13;
**The 600 km of roads scheduled for upgrading in the second year will not receive any&#13;
improvement in the first year.&#13;
Methodology for Feeder Roads Program&#13;
4.    The feeder roads methodology constitutes an important part of a long-term effort to&#13;
bring coherence and order into the management of local road system in Zambia. Under&#13;
ROADSIP, all core feeder roads are expected to be designated as the responsibility of local&#13;
councils. As such, the function and condition of the core feeder roads will be monitored&#13;
periodically as part of the local road management system. The feeder roads program has been&#13;
developed using a four step methodology. Guided by a technical process (steps 1 through 3 of&#13;
the feeder roads methodology), each local council determines the specific program interventions&#13;
in its jurisdiction (step 4):&#13;
i. The first step involves a comprehensive inventory and condition survey of all roads&#13;
in rural Zambia excluding only those which are under the designated responsibility of&#13;
the Roads Department and the National Parks Services. The inventory therefore includes&#13;
all RD and R roads which are the responsibility of local councils as well as currently&#13;
undesignated roads which may have been constructed by NGOs, freestanding projects,&#13;
and communities.&#13;
ii. The second step divides the feeder roads network into three levels--primary,&#13;
secondary and tertiary--according to set of network based criteria. A primary feeder&#13;
road must satisfy three criteria: a) link with another all-weather road and form a coherent&#13;
link between population and production centers and the national road network; b) form a&#13;
loop, on its own or in combination with other roads, to facilitate passenger and goods&#13;
transport; and c) not duplicate the function served by other roads in the network, i.e.,&#13;
roads in flat and rolling terrain should be 15-20 km apart or in very hilly terrain 7-10 km&#13;
apart. The primary roads will constitute the core feeder roads network.&#13;
iii. The third step ranks the primary/core feeder roads according to socio-economic&#13;
importance using ordinal rankings. This multi-criteria analysis includes, among other&#13;
factors, population served by the road, presence of social and economic facilities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
Annex2-lc&#13;
Page 3 of 4&#13;
(schools, clinics, markets, crop stores/processing facilities, administrative services),&#13;
projected increase in traffic volume, current and potential agricultural production and&#13;
programmed development activities. An example of how the criteria has been applied is&#13;
given in Box 1. These criteria have been discussed and agreed to by key stakeholders&#13;
including the Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Fisheries and the National Roads Board&#13;
which has significant road user representatives in its committees. The multi-criteria&#13;
analysis, in addition to providing an initial ranking of the core feeder roads, informs and&#13;
facilitates the discussions among local constituents.&#13;
iv. The centerpiece of the methodology is the fourth andfinal step which results in the&#13;
feeder roads program for each council based on constituent priorities. The MLGH rural&#13;
roads unit presents the outcome of step one through three to individual councils and their&#13;
2&#13;
constituents. Based on the resource envelope , each district council, with the assistance&#13;
of the MLGH rural roads unit, decides whether to fully upgrade a few roads or do a&#13;
mixture of full upgrading and accessibility improvements. The MLGH rural roads unit&#13;
acts as technical adviser to the council and will assist the councils to make technically&#13;
informed decisions and draw up a plan which meets local priorities.&#13;
5.     As part of the technical and consultative process, each council gains a clear grasp of the&#13;
network for which it is responsible and an understanding of the maintenance requirements of this&#13;
network. A detailed feeder roads program has been developed in consultation with the 15 local&#13;
councils in Luapula and Northern Provinces. The process is expected to commence in Western&#13;
France in early 1998. The first two years of the program will address the full upgrading of 12 of&#13;
the 15 councils. The typical council elected to fully upgrade about 20 percent of its network&#13;
providing low cost accessibility improvements to the rest of the core network. This amounts to&#13;
an estimate of 1380 kilometers of feeder roads for upgrading. Responsibility for some of the&#13;
secondary and tertiary roads may be assumed by communities as part of the community&#13;
accessibility program. This program encourages communities to claim ownership for roads&#13;
which provide access to their locality.&#13;
2 The resource envelope for each district has been determined using a simple formula. Since MLGH&#13;
currently is not using any composite index for allocating resources among districts, the rural roads&#13;
unit is using a simple formula based on road and population density and economic activity. The total&#13;
index is derived by adding: population index + road index + activity index = total index. The range&#13;
of indices is from a total of 3 for the districts with the lowest road density, the lowest population&#13;
density and the lowest economic activity to 9 for the economically most active districts with the&#13;
highest road density and the highest population. The resource envelope for each district is then&#13;
determined by a weighted proportion of its total index and kilometers of core feeder roads.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
Annex 2-ic&#13;
Page 4 of 4&#13;
Box 1. Ranking offeeder roads using multi-criteria analysis&#13;
The feeder roads inventory covered all roads in each district. Socio-economic data was assembled in 8&#13;
different indices (see below). Given the scant data available on traffic flows and agricultural production&#13;
along individual roads in rural Zambia, these indices act as a proxy to rank the network according to&#13;
economic and social importance. Indices a) through d) combine into an economic dimension scale; indices&#13;
e) through j) combine into a social dimension scale. The socio economic justification index is arrived upon&#13;
by adding the two together. Roads are subsequently ranked according to their combined socio-economic&#13;
index. Equal weight has been granted to all factors which are each assigned a number between I and 10.&#13;
The higher the index, the more important the road. For example, road X, which is a currently unclassified&#13;
road in Mporokoso district in the Northern province, was rated as indicated the table above. The economic&#13;
dimension scale was 22/4=5.5; the social index is 26/4=6.5. The combined socio-economic index is 6.0&#13;
which gives this road a rather high ranking, specifically considering that it is unclassified.&#13;
Jndex                                       Road X&#13;
a) current agricultural production index      9&#13;
b) potential marketed production index        7&#13;
c) existing production facilities index       3&#13;
d) planned development projects index         3&#13;
e) population served by road index            9&#13;
f) social facility intensity index            3&#13;
i) potential traffic and mobility index       9&#13;
j) employment creation potential index        5&#13;
The resultant ranking of feeder roads is subsequently subjected to local level consultations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Republic of Zambia&#13;
Road Sector Investment Program&#13;
Implementalion Schedule&#13;
b6         1997        1998          1999         2000         2001         2002         2&#13;
ID   Task Name                                              Duration   3 0Q4 Q1 02 Q3lQ4|1 IQ2 Q3 Q4 Q Q|Q2 Q3 Q4Q1 Q2 Q3 Q4 1Q  02 03 |Q41Q1 0231 Q2&#13;
1   1. Road Maintenance (Routine and Periodic)                 1325d     O     !&#13;
2       Detailed Maintenance Program for 1997                     4w&#13;
3       Perform Maintenance for 1997                             52w&#13;
4       Detiled Maintenance Program for 1998                      4w&#13;
5       Perform Maintenance for 1998                             S2w&#13;
6       Detailed Maintenance Program for 1999                     4w&#13;
7       Perform Maintenance for 1999                             52W&#13;
8       Detailed Maintqnance Program for 2000                     4w&#13;
9       Perform Maintenance for 2000                             52w&#13;
10       Detailed Maintenabce Program for 2001                     4w&#13;
11       Perform Maintenance for 2001                            52w&#13;
12   2. Road RehabilitationlUpgrading/Accessibility Improvement  1326d      .                                     !      -&#13;
13       Preparation of 5 Year Outline Rehabilitation Program     4w |&#13;
14       Preparation of Detailed Program for 1997198 - 1998199    4w&#13;
15       Finalize Detailed Program for 1997198                    4w&#13;
16       Perform Civil Works for 1997198                         52w&#13;
17       Finalize Detailed Program for 1998199                    4w&#13;
18       Perform Civil Works for 1998199                         52w&#13;
19       Preparation of Detailed Program for 1999100 - 2001/02    6w&#13;
20       Finalize Detailed Program for 1999/00                     4w             ..&#13;
| Task               _" Summary                                            Rolled Up Progress&#13;
Project: Zambia RSIPI_&#13;
Date: 6/9/97                       Progress                        .     Rolled Up Task&#13;
|Milestone          *RollbdUp Milestone&#13;
Annex 3-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Republic of Zambia&#13;
Road Sector Investment Program&#13;
Implementation Schedule&#13;
-96        1997         1998          1999         2000          2001          2002         2&#13;
ID   Task Name                                                Duration  Q3 f4 01  42 Q3IQ4 Q1 1Q21031Q4I Q IIQ21031Q41Q1 102Q3104 Qi1 1021Q31Q4 Q1 1Q2 131Q4        2&#13;
21       Perdorm Civil Works for 1999100                           52w                                                 -&#13;
22       Finalize Detailed Program for 2000101                      4w&#13;
23       Perform Clvil Works for 2000101                           52w                                                              -&#13;
24       Finalize Detailed Program for 2001102                      4w&#13;
25       Perform Civil Works for 2001/02                           52w&#13;
26   3. Community Accessibility Program                           1310d            .                          .mm&#13;
27       Community Transport Infrastructure                       1310d       :                   -&#13;
-    - I ~ ~          ~          ~ ~ ~ MMO&#13;
28           Implementation of Pilot Project in one province       78w&#13;
29           Training for staff and community representalives      159w |.&#13;
30           Implementation extended to other provinces           184w&#13;
31       Intermediate Means of Transport                           630d&#13;
32           Study on IMT                                          53w&#13;
33           Implementation of a Pilot Project                     53w&#13;
34   4. Construction Industry Development Program                 1140d       .                                            m             m    l,&#13;
35       Government Procedures                                     300d&#13;
36           Streamlining of Registration Process                  24w&#13;
37           Sirnplify Tendering and Contract Document              8w&#13;
38           TA to MWS and NCC                                     52w&#13;
39       TrainingPrograminRTS                                    1140d              .l.0l;&#13;
40           Development of Contractor Training Program             90d       :    *                                   __;_._._.______&#13;
Task                 _                 Summary                                Rolled Up Progress&#13;
Project: Zambia RSIP                Progress                               RolledUTs &#13;
Milestone         *ARolled Up Milestone O&#13;
Annex 3-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Republic of Zambia&#13;
Road Sector Investrnent Program&#13;
Implementation Schedule&#13;
.6        1997          i998        i999          2000         2001         2002         2&#13;
ID   Task Name                                              Duration  Q3Q4Q10Q2Q3|Q4 IQ1Q2IQ3IQ4IQIQ2IQ3IQ4IQ1|Q2IQ3IQ4QIQ2Q3I Q4Q1Q2Q3Q4QQ2&#13;
41           Set up and Implement Contractor Training Program   210w&#13;
42   5. Capacity Building and Training                          1146d&#13;
43       A. Policy Support                                      1042d       ._i&#13;
44           Policy Advisor                                     104w&#13;
45           Update Transport Sector Policy Framework             40d&#13;
46           Study on Improving the Management and Financin       50d       I&#13;
52          Institutional Strengthening of Roads Authorities    104w&#13;
53           Restructuring Road Fund                            104w_                                   __&#13;
54           Road Safety Action Program                          225d&#13;
63           Road Traffic Legislation                            225d&#13;
72       B. Implementation Support                               385d&#13;
73           TA to NRB                                           225d&#13;
82           TA to RD                                            385d&#13;
91           TA to DISS                                          385d                                              i&#13;
100      C. Institutional Development                            885d&#13;
101          Highway Engineer/Team Leader                        885d&#13;
110          Contracts ManagemenUProcurement                     365d&#13;
119          Financial Management                                365d                                 i&#13;
128          Short Term Specialists                              265d&#13;
137          Environmental Management                            495d&#13;
Task                 _       _        Summary                  _           Rolled Up Progress&#13;
Project: Zambia RSIP&#13;
Date: 619A97                       Progress                              Rolled Up Task_-&#13;
Milestone         *Rolled Up Milestone &#13;
Annex 3-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Republic of Zambia&#13;
Road Sector Investment Program&#13;
Implementation Schedule&#13;
1'97    I ~ . 1998        1999          2000          2001         2002          2&#13;
ID   Task Name                                                Duration    fQi Q1lQ2Q3JQ4Q1O2JQ3JQ4IQ11Q2Q3Q4Q1Q2Q3Q4QQ23Q4Q1Q2Q3Q4J1 Q2&#13;
146           Restructuring Plant and Vehicle Pool                 365d&#13;
155           HMS Unit                                             235d&#13;
164          Selection Criteria and Analytical Tools               235d&#13;
173           Urban Road Management System                         235d        :           _                           ,             ,,&#13;
182  6. implementation Banchmarks                                 1380d&#13;
183      Project Launch                                              4w              i&#13;
184      First Year Annual Review                                    4w        .,&#13;
185      Second Year Annual Review                                   4w&#13;
186       Mid Term Review                                            4w&#13;
187      Third Year Annual,Review                                    4w&#13;
188      Fourth Year Annual Review                                   4w&#13;
189      fifth Year Annual Review                                    4w &#13;
190      ICR                                                        96d&#13;
Task                      _           Summary                    _           Rolled Up Progress&#13;
Project: Zambia RSIPPrgesRldUpTk&#13;
Date: 6/9/97                        Progress                               Rolld Up Task&#13;
Milestone                             Rolled Up Milestone 0&#13;
Annex 3-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
Annex 3-2&#13;
Page I of 2&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
DISBURSEMENT SCHEDULE&#13;
Appraisal Estimate&#13;
Cumulative                       Standard&#13;
Amount          Amount                       Disb. Profile&#13;
FY        Qtr.      (US$ million)   (US$ million)    Percentage     for Transport&#13;
FY98       Dec-97           0               0              0%              0%&#13;
Mar-98           1               1              1%              0%&#13;
Jun-98           1              2              3%              0%&#13;
FY99       Sep-98           2               4              6%              0%&#13;
Dec-98           2               6              9%              0%&#13;
Mar-99           2               8             11%              1%&#13;
Jun-99          2               10             14%             3%&#13;
FY00       Sep-99           2               12             17%             5%&#13;
Dec-99           3              1 5            21%              6%&#13;
Mar-00           3              18             26%              8%&#13;
Jun-00          3               21             30%             10%&#13;
FY01       Sep-00           5              26              37%             12%&#13;
Dec-00           3              29             41%             14%&#13;
Mar-01           4              33             47%             18%&#13;
Jun-01          6               39             56%             22%&#13;
FY02       Sep-01           7              46              66%            30%&#13;
Dec-01           8              54             77%             38%&#13;
Mar-02           5              59             84%             38%&#13;
Jun-02          5               64             91%             40%&#13;
FY03       Sep-02           4               68             97%            42%&#13;
Dec-02           1              69             99%             48%&#13;
Mar-03           1              70             100%            54%&#13;
Jun-03          0               70            100%             56%&#13;
FY04       Sep-03                                                          58%&#13;
Dec-03                                                         66%&#13;
Mar-04                                                         74%&#13;
Jun-04                                                         80%&#13;
FY05       Sep-04                                                          86%&#13;
Dec-04                                                         93%&#13;
Mar-05                                                         98%&#13;
Jun-05    __99%&#13;
FY06       Sep-05                                                         100%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
Annex 3-2&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
DISBURSEMENT SCHEDULE&#13;
COMPARATIVE DISBURSEMENT PROFILE&#13;
100                                       *  *&#13;
90&#13;
80&#13;
70&#13;
60&#13;
50                                                         ort Profile (Zartbia)&#13;
40                       4SARestimate&#13;
20&#13;
10&#13;
0&#13;
o  N~ 'D co      0  cm'IT'~ co co 0  C4-  v  co  co 0&#13;
Quarters&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
Key Perforinance Indicators&#13;
Objectives                   Performance hidicators           Unit        12/98         12/99        12/00         12/01        12/02        1 MeansofVerification&#13;
Input Indicators&#13;
To increase road sector financing    Funding made available (annual basis)  UJS$ M                                                                   Project Progress Reports&#13;
Financial Audit&#13;
1. Fuel Levy                                          13.0         17.9        23.0         28.5           32.2&#13;
2. Olher Road User Charges                             3.3          3.3          3.3          3.1           3.1&#13;
3. Budget                                              4.6          5.2          5.1          4.1           8.1&#13;
4. IDA Funding&#13;
* ROADSIP                                            8.0         10.0         15.0        26.0           11.0&#13;
* Other                                              2.0          3.5          1.0          0.0           0.0&#13;
5. Donor lunding                                      38.8         29.4        26.9           9.0          32.0&#13;
To bring Lhe core road network  Civil works contracts awarded                                                                                        Project Progress Reports&#13;
into a maintainable condition    1. Periodic Maintenance               USS M           13.74        13.5         14.59        14.94         14.81&#13;
Km         1,576.0       954.0       1,229.0      1,308.0       1,379.0&#13;
2. Reihabilitation                    US$ M           15.0         29.98        32.98        24.98         42.10&#13;
Km           125.0       250.0        300.0         233.0         526.0&#13;
Output Indicators                                                                                                                                                                              O&#13;
'I'o improve road Iransport services   Completion of road works          Km                                                                          Project Progress Reports&#13;
anid reduce transport cost      1. Routine Mainitenanicc (aniual)                   6,730.0      8,946.0     10,821.0     13,134.0      15,619.0   'Technical Audit&#13;
2. I'criodic Maintcianice (cumilalive)             3,691.0      2,716.0      4,029.0      5,381.0       6,807.0&#13;
3. Reliabilitationi (cumulative)                     125.0        375.0       675.0         908.0       1,434.0&#13;
4. Feeder Road Upgrading (annual)                    400.0        600.0        700.0        900.0        1,000.0&#13;
To address improved conimnunity  Completion of community road projecis   No.           I0          25           40            56           70        Project Progress Reports&#13;
accessibility                                                            Km            70.0     160.0          280.0        400.0         500.0      SRPU Reports&#13;
Outcome Indicators&#13;
To bring the condition of road  % of foad network; in good conditiosi                                                                                I IlMS&#13;
network at least 50% good        I. Paved roads                                        29.0         37.0         39.0         41.0          47.0    Field Surveys&#13;
2. Unpaved roads                                       8.0          9.0          8.0         17.0          33.0    Technical Audit&#13;
3. Feeder roads                                        2.0          5.0          7.0         11.0          I 5.0&#13;
To alleviate poverty through    Create employment opportunities in Ilic  No.        2,000        5,000        8,000       33,000        14,000      lProject Progress Reports&#13;
crealion of new jobs            labor-based consitriction works&#13;
Impact Indicators&#13;
To improve road safety by       Accident dala per year                   No.                                                                         Projecl Progress Reports&#13;
reducing road accidents by at least                                                                                                                  Aniual 'Iransport&#13;
20%/o                           1. Road accidents                                   8,200        7,800        7,500        7,200         7,000       Stalistics              )&#13;
2. Fatalities                                        870          830          800          770           750                              0   X&#13;
To strengthen local construction  Number of contractors trained          No.                                                                         Project Progress Reports02&#13;
industry                                                                                                                                             NCC Reports&#13;
1. Routinie Maintenanice                              60         180          300          300            300                                   U4&#13;
2. Rehabilitation                                      5           20           30           50            70&#13;
Flapsed Iine betwccn invoice           I)ays          14           10           10           10            10&#13;
subnIissioi and paymncti           I           I             I            I            I             I            I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
Annex 3-4&#13;
Page I of 2&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
SUPERVISION PLAN&#13;
Approximate                                                                       Staff&#13;
Date of Input                                                                    Weeks&#13;
(Mo/yr.)                   Activity                  Expected Skill Required    in Field&#13;
Oct/Nov 1997    Project Launch:                      Transport Specialist           15&#13;
Review: progress of the program so far;   Highway Engineer&#13;
including civil works and policy reforms;  Specialist for Institutional&#13;
the first year maintenance program;  Reform&#13;
procurement status; status of stakeholder   Rural Transport Specialist&#13;
participation.                       Procurement Specialist&#13;
Develop: action plans on institutional  Legal Counsel&#13;
reform, community accessibility program   Disbursement Officer&#13;
and construction industry development&#13;
program&#13;
May/Jun l998    Supervision 1:                       Transport Specialist           12&#13;
Review: status of capacity building  Highway Engineer&#13;
prograrns, achievements to date in road    Rural Transport Specialist&#13;
maintenance and rehabilitation,      Environment Specialist&#13;
environmental management&#13;
improvement, action plan on restructuring&#13;
:_____________  plant pool, review studies on IMT.&#13;
Oct/Nov         First Annual Review:                 Transport Economist            12&#13;
1998            Review: institutional strengthening of  Highway Engineer&#13;
other road authorities, training progress;   Rural Transport Specialist&#13;
progress on institutional reform; second    Procurement Specialist&#13;
year maintenance program and indicative  Financial Analyst&#13;
program for 2000-2001 both for&#13;
maintenance and rehabilitation; audit&#13;
performance.&#13;
Develop: labor based maintenance and&#13;
rehabilitation methods, third year road&#13;
maintenance and maintenance plan,&#13;
evaluation according to performance&#13;
indicators.&#13;
Feb/March 1999  Supervision 2                        Transport Economist            12&#13;
Preparation for mid-term review,     Highway Engineer&#13;
assessment of 1998 outturn numbers,  Specialist for Institutional&#13;
economic evaluation thus far, review  Reform&#13;
studies on institutional and financing  Transport Economist&#13;
reform performance to date.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
Annex 3-4&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
Approximate                                                                      Staff&#13;
Date of Input                                                                   Weeks&#13;
(Mo/yr.)                  Activity                  Expected Skill Required    in Field&#13;
Oct/Nov 1999    Second Annual Review                 Transport Specialist           8&#13;
Review third year road maintenance  Highway Engineer&#13;
program, progress on policy reform;  Rural Transport Specialist&#13;
development of contractors; performance&#13;
of road works&#13;
Feb/Mar 2000    Supervision 3                        Transport Specialist           6&#13;
Review evaluation of performance    Highway Engineer&#13;
according to performance indicators for   Transport Economist&#13;
mid-term review, progress on legal&#13;
reform and transport policy action plans&#13;
Jun/July 2000    Mid-Term Review:                    Transport Specialist          20&#13;
Review: performance of road authorities  Highway Engineer&#13;
and need for further reform, progress on   Rural Transport Specialist&#13;
capacity building program, efficiency of   Financial Analyst&#13;
road fund management, development of   Specialist for Institutional&#13;
private contractors, community       Reform&#13;
development and participation,      Procurement Specialist&#13;
achievements on road maintenance and    Disbursement Specialist&#13;
rehabilitation, progress on legislation  Legal Counsel&#13;
review.&#13;
Develop: staff training goals;&#13;
environmental and traffic safety action&#13;
plans,; financial management systems                                    l&#13;
OctlNov 2000    Third Annual Review                  Transport Specialist          10&#13;
Review: institutional performance,  Highway Engineer&#13;
achievement on civil works; effectiveness  Rural Transport Specialist&#13;
of financing reforms; development of  Environmental Specialist&#13;
community ownership, progress on&#13;
environmental management, fourth year&#13;
maintenance program                                                     l&#13;
May/June 2001   Supervision 4                        Transport Specialist           6&#13;
Review on: Progress on policy reform;    Highway Engineer&#13;
development of contractors; performance  Transport Economist&#13;
of road works&#13;
Sept/Oct 2001    Fourth Annual Review                Transport Specialist           8&#13;
Review on: achievement on civil works;   Highway Engineer&#13;
progress on policy reform; development   Rural Transport Specialist&#13;
of community ownership; fifth year  Procurement Specialist&#13;
maintenance program r&#13;
March/April     Supervision 5 and ICR                Transport Specialist          12&#13;
2002            Review: Assessment on project        Highway Engineer&#13;
performance, reevaluation of costs and    Rural Transport Specialist&#13;
benefits, preparation of draft ICR.  Specialist for Institutional&#13;
Reform&#13;
Transport Economist&#13;
Estimated Field Supervision Staff Weeks                      125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
Annex 4-1&#13;
Page I of 7&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
ECONOMIC ANALYSIS&#13;
Methodology and Results for Priority Main Roads Program&#13;
1.    The main direct benefit from main road pavement improvements is the reduction&#13;
of vehicle operating costs (VOC). These in turn will usually result in lower transport&#13;
costs for people and goods, when there is a competition in the road transport sector.&#13;
Traffic volumes on the Zambian roads are generally low; only T roads in the Copperbelt&#13;
province and near townships experience 500 and more vehicles per day while M roads in&#13;
rural areas and n roads often carry less than 100 vehicles per day. The analysis has been&#13;
based on the data &amp;-lIected and stored in the Highway Management System (HMS) under&#13;
the IDA financed Transport Engineering and Technical Assistance project (TETAP).&#13;
Because the origin and destination of the traffic on these roads are not known and traffic&#13;
demand is not likely to be suppressed due to the present road conditions, no consideration&#13;
has been made for generated traffic. Traffic generation, time savings and other benefits&#13;
are likely to be positive but not included in the analysis, so that the VOC savings&#13;
represent a lower bound.&#13;
2.    The roads analyzed show in general high roughness because of the years of&#13;
neglected maintenance caused by lack of resources. However, because of the generally&#13;
low traffic volume and a sound initial engineering standards with relatively strong road&#13;
subbase, the deterioration of the roads is estimated to be slower than a case one would&#13;
expect from present surface conditions. For this reason, reconstruction is limited to a&#13;
minimum amount and repair/reseal options were selected whenever possible. Once the&#13;
backlog maintenance is covered, the roads would be put to regular annual maintenance&#13;
program. The sections of the road as well as selection of the proposed intervention type&#13;
for the capital investment have been selected based on ERR justified by VOC savings.&#13;
The road sections with economic rate of return (ERR) of 12% and above over a twenty&#13;
year analysis period have been included.&#13;
3.    The cost and road condition data were collected and input during the period from&#13;
April to September 1995. The unit costs in the HMS, as mentioned in Table A, were&#13;
developed as the average costs for the works carried out under the Roads Department in&#13;
1995 and were revised end 1996 based on recent contract documents from the Roads&#13;
Department. Since the exchange rate is market determined, and composition of the labor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 84 -&#13;
Annex 4-1&#13;
Page 2 of 7&#13;
and equipment costs is assumed to be similar for costs and benefits the conversion factor&#13;
is assumed to be 1. RTIM3 based economic analysis was conducted with the traffic&#13;
growth rate of 3 % which is taken from the recent experience and future projected&#13;
economic growth of the country, which is however on conservative side. A complete&#13;
output of the economic analysis with detailed data for each link between years 1997 and&#13;
2016 is included in the Project Implementation Plan (PIP). Table B shows the ERR and&#13;
the cost for the roads which satisfied the ERR threshold of 12 % for the base case&#13;
scenario and which are included in the first two years program. The overall ERR for all&#13;
priority paved road improvements is 21 %.&#13;
4.    Sensitivity Analyses were conducted on the high priority roads to test the impact&#13;
of: (i) variations from the initial normal traffic growth (3 %) and (ii) the effect of capital&#13;
cost variation. The result for each road in the priority program is in Tables C and D. The&#13;
priority roads in general remain economically sound even in case of low traffic growth of&#13;
1 % p.a. Only the ERR of M4 would turn out to be less than 12 %. The results of&#13;
switching value analysis shows that except for M4, which already has 12% ERR at the&#13;
base cost estimate, roads would remain economically viable for capital costs increase of&#13;
up to 105%.&#13;
5.    Detailed feasibility studies have been conducted for the Great North Road (T2)&#13;
from Kapiri Mposhi to Nakonde. The road is divided into four sections with an&#13;
approximate length of 200 km for each of the sections. The traffic level is generally low&#13;
with a current daily traffic level of around 500 vehicles at Kapiri Mposhi. The level&#13;
gradually decreases towards the Tanzanian border where the traffic is less than 100&#13;
vehicles per day. The origin - destination survey shows that a high percentage (up to 80&#13;
%) of the traffic is regional or international long distance traffic, so that the major benefit&#13;
would arise from the reduction of the VOC.&#13;
6.    Rehabilitation on the Sections 1 and 2 will be economically feasible and included&#13;
in Tables B and C. Staged construction is proposed for the Section 2 where further&#13;
strengthening of the road surface is scheduled after 6 or 12 years, depending on the&#13;
condition of the road. This strategy has the advantage of reducing the high initial&#13;
investment costs. On the Sections 3 (Mpika - Chinsali) and 4 (Chinsali - Nakonde) no&#13;
rehabilitation option is justified economically because of low traffic benefits. For these&#13;
two sections continuous maintenance with patching and reseal will be the only feasible&#13;
option to keep the road passable for heavy traffic. Only one link of the Section 4, which&#13;
has already failed, will be reconstructed to ensure cross border traffic to use the road.&#13;
The ERR resulting from the maintenance is 22 % for the Section 3 while for the Section 4&#13;
the value is 8 %. The Section 4 is the last section of the Great North Road towards the&#13;
Tanzanian Border and the only road link to Tanzania from Zambia. This link is of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
Annex 4-1&#13;
Page 3 of 7&#13;
strategic importance for the country because if this section becomes impassable the&#13;
international road link to Tanzania would be lost. In addition, the road backs up the&#13;
TAZARA. If TAZARA collapses, all traffic to Tanzania would be diverted to the road.&#13;
The volume of the diverted traffic is estimated to be the order of 85 over-five-axle trucks&#13;
per day with 6 % increase per year. Incorporating this potential traffic volume the ERR&#13;
would be 28 % which is taken as a proxy indicator of the net economic benefit to Zambia&#13;
for maintaining this road link. The detailed sheet of the economic analysis is shown in&#13;
Table E and F.&#13;
Table A&#13;
HMS Input Costs for Intervention Categories&#13;
Costs (US$)&#13;
Intervention      Economic    Financial      Forex&#13;
Routine maintenance   1030.54/km    1499.38/km   360.30/km&#13;
Patching               18.00/m2      27.31/m2     9.09/m2&#13;
Reseal                  1.80/m2       2.68/m2     0.91/m2&#13;
Slurry seal             1.48/m2       2.23/m2     0.75/m2&#13;
DBST**                  9.84/m2      14.83/m2     5.34/m2&#13;
Overlay**              11.48/m2      14.56/m2     8.03/m2&#13;
Reconstruction         19.67/m2      24.94/m2    13.77/m2&#13;
Notes:  * Includes grading&#13;
*e Includes regulation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
Annex 4-1&#13;
Page 4 of 7&#13;
Table B&#13;
ERR and NPV of High Priority Main Roads&#13;
Proposed           NPV at&#13;
Intervention Type        12%             Economic  Roughness&#13;
Discount           Capital    Range in&#13;
Route                                     Repair/      Rate     ERR       Cost    IRI for the&#13;
No.     Proposed Section    Rehab.   Reconstr  Reseal  (US$ m)   %      (US$ m)    Section&#13;
Ti     Zimbabwe Border    5 km                1 km      0.4     25 %      0.4      5.2 - 6.6&#13;
- Livingstone&#13;
T2      Chirundu - Kafue                    72 km       2.2     23 %       1.4        4.5&#13;
T2     Kapiri Mposhi -    39 km   96 km    62 km        5.0     15 %      20.7     2.9 - 7.8&#13;
Serenje&#13;
T2      Serenje - Mpika                    235 km      2.9      14 %      14.2    2.7 - 6.0&#13;
T3      Chingola -         15 km             13 km      6.1     42 %      2.6      2.9 - 7.4&#13;
Kasumbalesa&#13;
T4      Km233 -Km          11 km    3km      9km        0.3      16%       1.3     7.1 -9.0&#13;
260 at Kachalola                                                                    l&#13;
T5     Chingola -                  101 km              2.2      18 %       3.6     3.4 - 8.1&#13;
Solwezi&#13;
M4     Ndola -             29 km    3 km    11 km       4.0     12 %       3.6     4.1 - 5.8&#13;
Mwambeshi&#13;
M6     Kafulafuta -         4 km            30 km       1.3     23 %       1.1     4.0 - 6.1&#13;
Luanshya                                                                            l&#13;
M9     Lusaka -            36 km    10 km    33 km     3.9      22 %      4.9      4.5 - 10.0&#13;
Mumbwa&#13;
M9     Mumbwa-             27 km    13 km    26 km      1.7     18 %      4.1     4.0 - 10.0&#13;
Mongu&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87-&#13;
Annex 4-1&#13;
Page 5 of 7&#13;
Table C&#13;
Sensitivity to Traffic Growth&#13;
ERR at 1%    ERR at 3%    ERR at 5%&#13;
Traffic      Traffic      Traffic&#13;
Route                                    Growth p.a.  Growth p.a.  Growth p.a.&#13;
No.           Proposed Section          (Low Case)  (Base Case)  (High Case)&#13;
TOOI   Zimbabwe Border - Livingstone        22 %         25 %          27 %&#13;
T002    Chirundu - Kafue                    20 %         23 %          27 %&#13;
T002    Kapiri Mposhi - Serenje             N.A.          15 %         19 %&#13;
T002    Serenje - Mpika                     N.A.          14 %         N.A.&#13;
T003    Chingola - Kasumbalesa              37 %         42 %          47 %&#13;
T004    Km 233 - Km 260 at Kachalola        13 %          16%          19%&#13;
T005    Chingola - Solwezi                  14 %          18 %         21 %&#13;
M004   Ndola - Mwambeshi                    10 %          12 %         14 %&#13;
M006   Kafulafuta - Luanshya                21 %         23 %          25 %&#13;
M009   Lusaka - Mumbwa                      20 %         22 %          25 %&#13;
M009   Mumbwa - Mongu                       15 %          18 %         21 %&#13;
Table D&#13;
Sensitivity to Capital Cost Variations&#13;
% Capital Cost Increase&#13;
Route                                     to Yield 0 NPV at 12 %&#13;
No.            Proposed Section              Discount Rate&#13;
TOOl   Zimbabwe Border - Livingstone             70.0 %&#13;
T002   Chirundu - Kafue                          59.5 %&#13;
T002   Kapiri Mposhi - Serenje                   27.3 %&#13;
T002   Serenje - Mpika                            12.7%&#13;
T003   Chingola - Kasumbalesa                    104.6 %&#13;
T004   Km 233 - Km 260 at Kachalola               17.0 %&#13;
T005   Chingola - Solwezi                        28.8 %&#13;
M004  Ndola - Mwambeshi                           0.0 %&#13;
M006  Kafulafuta - Luanshya                      50.5 %&#13;
M009  Lusaka - Mumbwa                            55.6 %&#13;
M009  Mumbwa - Mongu                             30.1 %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
Annex 4-1&#13;
Page 6 of 7&#13;
Table E&#13;
Economic Analysis for the Great North Road Sections 3 and 4&#13;
Routine+Periodic Maintenance vs. No Maintenance&#13;
Section 3                        Section 4             Section 4 with traffic from TAZARA&#13;
Year        Costs   VOC saving Total Benefit   Costs   VOC saving Total Benefit  Costs   VOC saving Total Benefit&#13;
1    2.53       0.00      -2.53       1.12       0.07      -1.05       4.12       0.18      -3.94&#13;
2    0.17       0.12      -0.05       2.00       0.08      -1.92       0.21       0.26       0.05&#13;
3    0.17       0.25       0.08       1.00       0.10      -0.90       0.21       0.35       0.14&#13;
4    0.17       0.39       0.22       0.21       0.10      -0.11       0.21       0.42       0.21&#13;
5    0.17       0.55       0.38       0.21       0.10      -0.11       0.21       0.79       0.58&#13;
6    0.17       0.70       0.53       0.21       0.11      -0.10       0.21       1.22       1.01&#13;
7    0.17       0.87       0.70       0.21       0.25       0.04       0.21       1.69       1.48&#13;
8    1.84       1.05      -0.80       2.31       0.40      -1.90       2.31       2.21       -0.10&#13;
9    0.17       1.24       1.07       0.21       0.58       0.37       0.21       2.79       2.58&#13;
10    0.17       1.45       1.28       0.21       0.76       0.55       0.21       3.43       3.22&#13;
11    0.17       1.67       1.50       0.21       0.97       0.76       0.21       4.13       3.92&#13;
12    0.17       1.90       1.74       0.21       1.19       0.98       0.21       4.88       4.67&#13;
13    0.17       2.15       1.99       0.21       1.36       1.15       0.21       5.71       5.50&#13;
14    0.17       2.91       2.74       0.21       1.54       1.33       0.21       6.61       6.40&#13;
15    1.84       3.50       1.65       2.31       1.74      -0.57       2.31       7.59       5.28&#13;
16    0.17       3.55       3.38       0.21       1.95       1.74       0.21       8.65       8.44&#13;
17    0.17       3.60       3.43       0.21       2.17       1.96       0.21       9.51       9.30&#13;
18    0.17       3.65       3.49       0.21       2.41       2.20       0.21       10.44      10.23&#13;
19    0.17       3.70       3.54       0.21       2.66       2.45       0.21       11.42      11.21&#13;
20    0.17       3.73       3.56       0.21       2.86       2.65       0.21       12.25      12.04&#13;
ERR                               22%                               8%                               28%&#13;
NPV at 12% in US$ m               3.67                             -1.41                            12.67&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
Annex 4-1&#13;
Page 7 of 7&#13;
Table F&#13;
Sample Economic Analysis Output&#13;
T002 Serenje - Chinsali&#13;
Without Project       With Project                 Benefits&#13;
Increase in                                 Avoided&#13;
Year     VOC      Recurrent    VOC       Capital  VOC saving  Civil Works    Total&#13;
Costs                Costs              Expenditure&#13;
1   14.26      0.01       14.26      3.20       0.00      -3.19      -3.19&#13;
2   14.99      0.01       14.72      5.50       0.28      -5.49      -5.22&#13;
3   15.79      0.02       15.32      5.50       0.48      -5.48      -5.01&#13;
4   16.64      0.02       15.94                 0.69       0.02      0.72&#13;
5   17.55      0.03       16.61                 0.94       0.03      0.97&#13;
6   18.52      0.04       17.34                 1.18       0.04       1.22&#13;
7   19.51      0.05       18.16      18.50      1.36      -18.46     -17.10&#13;
8   20.55      0.05       16.60                 3.95       0.05      4.00&#13;
9   21.65      0.05       17.27                 4.37       0.05      4.43&#13;
10   22.81      0.06       17.94                 4.87      0.06       4.93&#13;
1 1   24.05     0.06       18.64                 5.41      0.06       5.47&#13;
12   25.39      0.06       19.37                 6.02      0.06       6.08&#13;
13   26.84      0.06       20.16     11.30       6.68      -11.24     -4.56&#13;
14   28.40      0.07       18.60                 9.80      0.07       9.87&#13;
15   30.09      0.07       19.25                10.84      0.07       10.91&#13;
16   31.87      0.07       19.91                11.95      0.07       12.02&#13;
17   33.64      0.07       20.61                13.03      0.07       13.10&#13;
18   35.27      0.07       21.32                13.94       0.07      14.02&#13;
19   36.65      0.08       22.08      2.70      14.57      -2.63      11.94&#13;
20   37.82      0.08       22.85                14.97       0.08      15.05&#13;
ERR        14%&#13;
NPVat 12%      $2.85 m&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA&#13;
PROJECT TO SUPPORT A&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM&#13;
List of Documents in the Project File&#13;
Ministry of Communications and Transport: Statement of Communications and&#13;
Transport Sector Policy. Draft white paper dated May 1995.&#13;
Ministry of Communications and Transport: Road Sector Investment Program&#13;
(ROADSIP) Project Proposal. Task Force Report dated February 1996. Final&#13;
version dated April 1997.&#13;
Ministry of Communications and Transport: "Roads 2001 - The Way Forward".&#13;
Workshop at Mulungushi Conference Center, Lusaka, February 27-29 1996.&#13;
Workshop communique. Papers prepared for the workshop. Miscellaneous&#13;
documentation.&#13;
Ministry of Communications and Transport: "Roads 2001 - The Action Plan,&#13;
Workshop to Launch ROADSIP," July 9-11, 1997, Lusaka. Paper prepared for&#13;
the workshop. Miscellaneous documentation.&#13;
Ministry of Communications and Transport: "Environmental Analysis of Road&#13;
Sector Investment Program" by Julius Chileshe in association with Chalo&#13;
Consultants, July 1996.&#13;
Ministry of Communications and Transport: "Study to Improve Management and&#13;
Financing of Roads" by Louis Berger International. Draft final report dated&#13;
September 1996 with comments of the Government and the World Bank. Monthly&#13;
progress reports. Proceedings of a Workshop on How to Improve Road&#13;
Management in Zambia, January 16-18, 1996.&#13;
Ministry of Communications and Transport: "Establishing a Road Renumbering&#13;
and Mapping System for Zambia" by Carl Bro International, May 1996.&#13;
Ministry of Local Government and Housing: "A Rural Feeder Road Support&#13;
Program" by GITEC Consultants. Inception report dated September 1995.&#13;
Monthly progress reports. Report on screening and selection of feeder roads,&#13;
assessment and evaluative framework dated September 1996.&#13;
Reports on the Great North Road for the Ministry of Works and Supply, Roads&#13;
Department:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
"Economic Assessment for Kapiri Mposhi-Nakonde Road" by Norconsult, May&#13;
1997.&#13;
"Economic Analysis of the Great North Road between Kapiri Mposhi and&#13;
Nakonde" by VWL International, June 1996.&#13;
Engineering Design Reports and Economic Evaluation Reports for&#13;
(a) Section 1 Kapiri Mposhi-Serenje by Carl Bro International&#13;
(b) Section 2 Serenje-Mpika by RITES/Burrow Binnie Zambia&#13;
(c) Section 3 Mpika-Chinsali by Gauff Ingenieure&#13;
(d) Section 4 Chinsali-Nakonde by VWL International&#13;
Engineering and economic reevaluation for Section 1 by COWI Consult.&#13;
Ministry of Works and Supply: "Highway Management System" by Carl Bro&#13;
International in association with Danish Road Directorate and Ranking&#13;
Engineering Consultants. Interim Report dated May 1996. Various Working&#13;
Documents and System Manuals. HMS output, cost assumptions, economic&#13;
analysis for the core investment program 1997-2002.&#13;
Ministry of Works and Supply, Roads Department: "Equipment Management and&#13;
Maintenance Study" by Crown Agents Institutional Development Group. Final&#13;
report dated September 1996 with Government and World Bank comments.&#13;
Ministry of Works and Supply, Roads Department: "The Civil Works&#13;
Construction Industry, The Building Construction Industry, The Consulting&#13;
Services in Zambia" by Kampsax International in association with Brian&#13;
Colquhoun, Hugh O'Donnell and Partners (Zambia). Final report dated July 1996&#13;
with Government and World Bank comments.&#13;
Ministry of Works and Supply, Roads Department: "A Study of Labor-Based&#13;
Contracting in Zambia" by IT Transport. Final report dated November 1995.&#13;
Restructuring Report for the Ministry of Works and Supply by Management&#13;
Development Division, Cabinet Office dated November 1994.&#13;
Cap 464 Roads and Road Traffic Act and amendments.&#13;
Statutory Instruments and other legal instruments pertaining to the National Roads&#13;
Board and the Road Fund.&#13;
United Nations Development Program/United Nations Capital Development&#13;
Fund: Project Agreement for Rehabilitation and Maintenance of Feeder Roads in&#13;
Eastern Province.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
Supplemental Annexes&#13;
(1)  Organizational Charts&#13;
(2) Road Network Data&#13;
(3) Vehicles per Population 1992&#13;
(4)  Comparative Road Accident Statistics&#13;
(5) Detailed Project Costs&#13;
(6)  Description of the Community Accessibility Component&#13;
(7) Description of Construction Industry Development Program&#13;
(8) Financing Local Revenue Requirements&#13;
(9) Project Implementation Organization&#13;
(10) Standard Packaging Plan and Indicative Packaging Plan for IDA Funded&#13;
Civil Works&#13;
Staff working papers as follows:&#13;
(1)  Restructuring of Road Sector Institutions&#13;
(2) Terms of Reference&#13;
(3) Draft Detailed Implementation Plan&#13;
(4) Proposed Classification of Road Contractors&#13;
(5) Economic Analysis working papers&#13;
(6) Recent Donor Financing for the Road Sector&#13;
(7) Environmental Mitigation Plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IBRD&#13;
24                                                                                                                                        3 2                                3&#13;
K-h" R.)o                                             TANZANIA&#13;
ROAD SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM                                                                                                      NIP. F.9.Q    &amp;#1; I&#13;
1997-2002 MAIN ROADS PRIORITY PROGRAM                                                                                                                                   T&amp;#1; Mb-&#13;
COMPLETED AFTER 1990 OR ONGOING                         TRUNK AND MAIN ROAD5                       r kkd-o&amp;#1;&amp;#1;                                                   INI k&#13;
OVERLAY / RECONSTRUCTION                                RAILROADS&#13;
. . . . .REPAIR / RESEAL&#13;
RIVERS&#13;
6 K.- b,&#13;
o SELECTED CITIES&#13;
SWAAAPS&#13;
PROVINCE CAPITALS&#13;
PROVINCE BOliNDARIES&#13;
&amp;#1;KASAMA&#13;
NATIONAL CAPITAL&#13;
WERI'lAlIONAL BOUNDARIFS&#13;
c&#13;
DEM. REP&#13;
(&amp;#1;MANSA&#13;
OF CONGO&#13;
k. PI&#13;
SOLWEZ                                                                                                                                                       12&#13;
A N G 0 L A&#13;
N 0 R T H&#13;
W E S T E R N&#13;
- - - - - - - - - -11&#13;
SI-&#13;
?&#13;
-p.&#13;
MALAWI&#13;
14&#13;
KABWE&#13;
3&amp;#1;                               3,4&#13;
K,, .[,,o                                                                                                                                                                                                             KENYA&#13;
R.ANDA_-&amp;#1;&#13;
MONGU&#13;
OF&#13;
TAN7,\r4lA&#13;
A&#13;
Kl- [11&#13;
Ng-           ON.&#13;
E R N                                 0                                                                                                                 ANGOLA&#13;
Mm-q-y                     ......&#13;
S --9P.')k",bP&#13;
MOZAMBIQUE&#13;
s iD                                                             Z  I M   B A  BW E                                                      ZIMBABIE&#13;
NAMIBIA BOT&amp;#1;&amp;#1;IANA&#13;
,cc&#13;
Z-b&#13;
0                       15C&#13;
GSTOrIE&#13;
NAMIBI                                                                                                                                                             SOUTH AFRICA&#13;
2A&#13;
jULY 1-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="442693">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/09/442693/zambia-road-sector-investment-program-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/09/442693/zambia-road-sector-investment-program-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/09/442693/zambia-road-sector-investment-program-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1998/11/17/000009265_3980625101258/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1998/11/17/000009265_3980625101258/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>2993</credit_no>
        <datestored>2001-04-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1997-09-04T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Zambia - Road Sector Investment Program Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The major objectives of the Road Sector
            Investment Program Project are: (a) bringing a core network
            of 33,500 kilometers in maintainable condition; (b) bringing
            the condition of the road network to at least 50 percent
            good and about 10 percent poor for all types of road; (c)
            strengthening the technical and managerial capacity of road
            authorities; (d) creating employment opportunities in the
            road sector and alleviating poverty through the creation of
            30,000 new jobs in road maintenance; (e) improving road
            safety and reducing road accidents by at least 20 percent;
            (f) improving environmental management in the road sector
            through establishing procedures and guidelines; (g)
            providing an enabling environment for improved road
            transport services and increasing the truck and bus fleet by
            at least 20 percent in rural areas; and (h) developing a
            framework for the management of community roads and
            promoting community participation in road management. The
            project components include: civil works; community
            accessibility program; construction industry development
            program; institutional capacity building; and engineering services.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Zambia - Road Sector Investment Program Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Zambia - Road Sector Investment
            Program Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1997/09/442693/zambia-road-sector-investment-program-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>ZM-Road Sec. Investment Prog. Support Proj.
            -- P003236</projn>
        <docty>Staff Appraisal Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Regional Rural Development,Urban Transport,Roads &amp; Highways,Public Sector Economics,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Transport</teratopic>
        <count>Zambia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southern Africa!$!80472</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980625101258</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Roads and highways,Central government administration,Vocational training,General transportation sector</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Transport</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Transportation</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Community participation; Construction
            industry; Nongovernmental organizations; Road &amp; highway
            deterioration; Road &amp; highway maintenance; Road &amp;
            highway planning; Road maintenance; Road safety; Road
            surfaces; Roads &amp; highways
            accident
            recording,accountability,Accounting,Agriculture,airports,Ambulances,Auditing,autonomy,bus,bus
            services,Buses,carriageway,civil
            service,Construction,current prices,Debt,deficits,designated
            roads,district roads,drivers,drivers licenses,Earth
            roads,Economic Analysis,economic growth,Economic
            performance,economic policies,economic
            reform,Employment,estate roads,feeder roads,financial
            performance,financing of roads,FISCAL YEAR,Framework,Freight
            movement,freight traffic,freight transport,FUEL,Gravel,Gross
            Domestic Product,Haulage,Highways,Housing,IMT,interest
            rates,inventory,Key Performance
            Indicators,legislation,liquidation,Local authorities,Local
            Contractors,local councils,Local Government,LOCAL
            REVENUE,MAIN ROADS,Minibuses,Mode of Transport,modes of
            transport,Motor Cycles,motor vehicle,National Roads,Natural
            Resources,operating surplus,PASSENGER,passenger
            cars,passenger service,passenger vehicles,Performance
            Indicators,Poverty Reduction,private sector,private sector
            participation,privatization,Public Sector,public sector
            efficiency,Public Sector Reform,railways,Rate of
            Return,reform programs,resource allocation,resource
            mobilization,road authorities,road authority,road
            construction,road density,Road Financing,road
            infrastructure,Road Maintenance,Road Maintenance
            Initiative,Road Quality,Road Safety,Road Sector,road
            surface,Road Traffic,road transport,road transport
            industry,road user charges,Road users,Roads,roads
            planning,roadworks,routine maintenance,rural
            communities,rural population,rural roads,Safety
            Council,safety programs,Supervision,Sustainability,Technical
            Assistance,traffic,transparency,Transport,transport
            infrastructure,transport investment,transport
            policy,Transport Sector,TRANSPORTATION,Trucks,undesignated
            roads,urban roads,Vans,vehicle license fees,Vehicle
            Operating Costs,vehicles
        </keywd>
        <owner>Transport Practice Group (AFTTR)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southern Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF040725-ZAMBIA: TRANSPORT SECTOR,TF037852-MALAWI - ROAD MAINTENANCE AND REHABILITATION,TF029564-PHRD-ROADS SECTOR INVESTMENT PROGRAM</trustfund>
        <repnb>16539</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health and Traffic Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Traffic Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Construction Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Regional Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Traffic and Road Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Roads</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Zambia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>