<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                              Documentof&#13;
                                           TheWorldBank&#13;
&#13;
                                   FOROFFICIAL USEONLY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   ReportNoT7624&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                                   ONA&#13;
&#13;
                                        TRUST FUNDGRANT&#13;
&#13;
                             INTHE AMOUNT OFUS$40 MILLION&#13;
&#13;
                              TO THE MINISTRY OF EDUCATION&#13;
&#13;
                            OFTHE IRAQIGOVERNINGCOUNCIL&#13;
&#13;
                                                 FORAN&#13;
&#13;
                     EMERGENCYTEXTBOOK PROVISIONPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    World BankIraqTrust Fund&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              May 13,2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HumanDevelopmentSector&#13;
MiddleEastand NorthAfrica Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricted distribution and may be used by recipients only inthe performance of their&#13;
official duties. Its contents may not otherwise be disclosed without World Bank authorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                            CURRENCY EQUIVALENT&#13;
                      (Exchange Rate Effective March22, 2004)&#13;
                                Currency Unit=US$&#13;
                              US$l = Iraqi Dinar 1,400&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   FISCAL YEAR&#13;
                                 January to December&#13;
&#13;
                       ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
CPA           Coalition Provisional Authority&#13;
DARM          DiwanAI Rikaba ElMalia (Iraqi Supreme Audit Institute)&#13;
EERP          Emergency EducationRehabilitation Project&#13;
ESRP          Emergency School Rehabilitation Project&#13;
FMR           FinancialMonitoringReports&#13;
GDP           Gross Domestic Product&#13;
I C B         International Competitive Bidding&#13;
ITF           World Bank IraqTrust Fund&#13;
MIM           Master ImplementationManual&#13;
MOE           Ministry o f Education&#13;
M O F         MinistryofFinance&#13;
MOPDC         Ministryo fPlanning and Development Cooperation&#13;
N C B         National Competitive Bidding&#13;
PAC           Project Advisory Committee&#13;
PMT           Project Management Team&#13;
PP            Procurement Plan&#13;
SBD           Standard BiddingDocument&#13;
SOE           Statement o f Expenditures&#13;
TA            Technical Assistance&#13;
TOR           Terms o fReference&#13;
TVET          Technical, Vocational Education and Training&#13;
UNDB          UnitedNations DevelopmentalBusiness&#13;
UNDG          United Nations Development Group&#13;
UNESCO        UnitedNations Educational, Scientific andCultural Organization&#13;
UNICEF        UnitedNations Children's Fund&#13;
USAID         UnitedStates Agency for InternationalDevelopment&#13;
WB            World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Vice President                               Christiaan Poortman&#13;
Country Director                            Joseph Saba&#13;
Sector Director                             Michal Rutkowski&#13;
Sector Manager                               Regina Bendokat&#13;
Task Team Leader                             Peter Buckland&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                      FOROFFICTALUSEONLY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    IRAQ&#13;
&#13;
                    EMERGENCY TEXTBOOK PROVISIONPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                             Table of Contents&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                    Page&#13;
                                                                                                    No.&#13;
       Currency Equivalent. Abbreviations and Acronyms&#13;
&#13;
       Grant andProject Summary&#13;
&#13;
       A.Background and Strategy ...........................................................           1&#13;
&#13;
       B.BankResponse and Strategy .......................................................            3&#13;
&#13;
       C.Detailed Project Description .......................................................         4&#13;
&#13;
       D.InstitutionalArrangements andProjectImplementation .......................                   6&#13;
           Project Management ..............................................................          6&#13;
           Procurement .......................................................................        7&#13;
           Disbursement ......................................................................        9&#13;
           Financial Management ...........................................................           10&#13;
           Project Supervision ...............................................................        12&#13;
&#13;
       E.Financialand Economic Justification ............................................             13&#13;
&#13;
       F. Risks ..................................................................................    14&#13;
&#13;
        Annexes&#13;
        Annex 1: Detailed Project Costs .....................................................         17&#13;
        Annex 2: Project Management ........................................................         20&#13;
        Annex 3: Procurement Plan ...........................................................        23&#13;
        Annex 4: Financial Management Arrangements ...................................               27&#13;
        Annex 5: Selection Criteria for Printing o f Textbooks ...........................           37&#13;
        Annex 6: Project Implementation Schedule .........................................           38&#13;
        Annex 7 : Result-Based SupervisionPlan ............................................          39&#13;
        Annex 8: Timetable o fKey Project Processing Events ............................             40&#13;
        Annex 9: Name o f Staff/Consultants who worked on the Project ................               41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricted distributionandmay be used by recipients only in&#13;
the performanceof their official duties Its contents may not be otherwise disclosed&#13;
                                                     .&#13;
without World Bank authorization               .&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                              IRAQ&#13;
&#13;
           EMERGENCYTEXTBOOK PROVISION PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                    Grant and ProjectSummary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Grant Recipient:     Ministryo fEducationo fthe GoverningCouncil o fIraq&#13;
&#13;
Beneficiary:         Ministryo fEducation&#13;
&#13;
ImplementingAgency:  Ministryo fEducation&#13;
&#13;
Loan/Credit/Grant:   World Bank IraqTrust Fund(ITF) Grant&#13;
&#13;
Amount &amp; Terms:      US$40million on ITF grant terms&#13;
&#13;
Objectives &amp;         The objective o f the Project i s to improve conditions of&#13;
Description:         learning inprimary and secondary schools throughthe&#13;
                     urgentprovision o fprimary and secondary school&#13;
                     textbooks.&#13;
&#13;
ProjectAppraisal     This Project has beenprepared inaccordance with&#13;
Document:            Emergency Recovery Assistance procedures (Operational&#13;
                     Policy 8.50). As such, there i s no Project Appraisal&#13;
                     Document for this Project.&#13;
&#13;
Disbursement:        The grant is expected to be fully disbursed byDecember&#13;
                     31, 2005.&#13;
&#13;
ProjectID Number:    PO88945&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                   EMERGENCY TEXTBOOK PROVISION PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                         TechnicalAnnex&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A.       BACKGROUNDAND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
Country background&#13;
&#13;
1.       Abundant natural and humanresources enabled Iraqto attain the status o f a middle-&#13;
income country inthe 1970s. The country developed good infrastructure and well-performing&#13;
education and healthcare systems, widely regarded as the best inthe MiddleEast. Income per&#13;
capita rose to over US$3,600 inthe early 1980s. Since that time, successive wars and a&#13;
repressive, state-dominated economic system have stifled growth and developmentand&#13;
debilitatedbasic infrastructure and social services. Intemational trade sanctions imposed in&#13;
1991took a toll on the economy. Despite the country's rich resource endowment, Iraq's&#13;
human development indicators are now among the lowest inthe region, andincome per&#13;
capita dropped to about US$770-1,020 by 2001,with continued decline thereafter. Although&#13;
there i s a paucity o f reliable economic data, 2003 GDP i s estimated at about US$l3-17&#13;
billion, or about US$480-630 per person, assuming a population o f about 26.3 million.&#13;
&#13;
Current Challengesand InternationalResponse&#13;
&#13;
2.       Followingthe recent war, Iraq faces enormous challenges, and the situation i s still&#13;
evolving. Inaddition to a complicated political transition, Iraq needs to rebuildsocial&#13;
cohesion and implement an economic transition from a centrally-planned economy to a&#13;
diversified market economy. It will be particularly important to mitigate the temporary&#13;
adverse effect o f reforms on the poor and vulnerable.&#13;
&#13;
3.       A Needs Assessment covering fourteen sectors, preparedjointly bythe World Bank&#13;
and UnitedNations Development Group (UNDG) andwith the participation o f the&#13;
Intemational Monetary Fund, estimated that Iraqrequires about US$36 billion over four&#13;
years, and the Coalition Provisional Authority (CPA) estimated separately that Iraq requires&#13;
about US$l9 billion over four years for areas not coveredby the Needs Assessment, such as&#13;
security and oil.&#13;
&#13;
4.       At anIntemationalDonors' Conference for IraqinMadrid on October 23-24,2003,&#13;
donors expressed support for the Needs Assessment and pledgedabout US$32 billion for the&#13;
four-year period covered by the Needs Assessment. Donors also asked the World Bank and&#13;
UNDGto set up an IntemationalReconstructionFundFacility for Iraqto ensure swift,&#13;
flexible, and coordinated donor financingfor priority investments consistent with the Need&#13;
Assessment. The Facility consists o f two trust funds-a    World Bank IraqTrust Fundand a&#13;
UNDGTrust Fund-each            with its own intemal governance procedures andwith management&#13;
structure that ensures close coordination.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     2&#13;
  EducationSector&#13;
&#13;
  5.       The education system inIraqwas widely regarded as one o f the best inthe Middle&#13;
  East regionuntilthe 1980s. Betweenthe 1960s andthe 1990s, Iraqmade great progress in&#13;
  enrollment at all levels o f education and achieved near universalprimaryenrollment by 1980.&#13;
  For the last decade o f the twentieth century, the system deteriorated seriously as Iraq engaged&#13;
  inthree major conflicts andexperienced over adecade ofinternational sanctions.&#13;
&#13;
  6.       Primary school enrollment fell to 93 percent in2000, while secondary school&#13;
  enrollment went from 47 percent to 38 percent. More serious, however, was a large drop in&#13;
  attendance. A UNICEF Multiple Indicator Cluster Survey (MICS) reported in2000 that as&#13;
  many as 23 percent o f primary school age children were not attending school, with&#13;
  significantly higher rates among girls and inrural areas. This deterioration created or&#13;
  exacerbated inequities by gender, urban/rural location, andregion. Other sub-sectors,&#13;
  especially technical andvocational education, also experienced stagnation or decline.&#13;
&#13;
  7.       Quality also declined at all levels o f the education system:teaching and learning&#13;
  conditions deteriorated; teacher quality eroded; curriculum content was distorted or became&#13;
  outdated; and policy and system development came to a standstill. This decline inquality&#13;
  was reflected indeteriorating internal efficiency, made worse by growing poverty. Indeed,&#13;
  poverty emerged as the major cause o f non-attendance, as more o f the direct costs o f&#13;
  provisionwere transferred to households despite the official policy of free education.&#13;
&#13;
  8.       Behind these developments was a substantial collapse inpublic investment inthe&#13;
  education system. In 1988/1989 the education budget was US$2.5 billion (about 6 percent o f&#13;
  GDP) and expenditure per student was approximately US$620. Over the 1993-2002 period,&#13;
  the annual average expenditure per student stood at approximately US$47, fundedlargely&#13;
  from the Oil-for-Food Program.&#13;
&#13;
  9.       Duringthe 1990s, textbook provision to schools came under severe financing&#13;
  restrictions; and the previous practice o f issuing a full set o fnew textbooks to every student&#13;
  every year was replaced by a rationing system inwhich textbooks were recycled for two or&#13;
  more years. Duringthe events of April 2003, almost all MOE stores and offices inthe central&#13;
  and southern govemorates were looted and many were burned. A number o f warehouses&#13;
  containing textbooks and paper were also destroyed, along with the government printing&#13;
' press inBaghdad, and nearly all master film o f existing textbooks. Textbooks had also come&#13;
  to reflect the curriculum distortions o f the previous regime. As an emergency measure,&#13;
  UNICEF and UNESCO managed the process o f removing the more offensive material inthe&#13;
  textbooks. Financedby USAID and Oil for Food funds, they also managed the printingof&#13;
  textbooks for the 2003/2004 school year, despite considerable operational difficulties&#13;
  experienced as a result o f the bombing o f the UNoffices inAugust 2003. Inthe end around&#13;
  40% o fneeded textbooks were printedand distributed, although some arrived late inthe&#13;
  school year. For the school year 2004-2005, the M O Erequested that the ITF finance the&#13;
  reprinting anddistribution o f textbooks.&#13;
&#13;
  10.      The priorities identifiedinthe UNDG/World Bank Joint Needs Assessment represent&#13;
  a national consensus and were endorsed by the Minister o f Education at a meeting inAmman&#13;
  inOctober 2003 attended by senior officials from the Ministry ofEducation (MOE) and from&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                3&#13;
the World Bank, UNICEF, UNESCO, USAID and the Coalition Provisional Authority&#13;
(CPA). These priorities are included inthe MOE Situation Analysis ("Education inIraq:&#13;
Current Situation andNew Perspectives") o f December 2003.&#13;
&#13;
11.     Duringthe AmmanconsultationinOctober 2003, agreement was reachedbetween&#13;
the MOEand Iraq's major development partners on the following priorities: (i)     capacity&#13;
buildingfor the development ofa strategic framework for the sector, (ii)   emergency&#13;
rehabilitation and supplies (including textbooks), (iii)&#13;
                                                       initiating curriculum reform process,&#13;
(iv) addressing immediateneeds inteacher training, and (v) initiatingpolicy dialogue on&#13;
technicalhocational education and training (TVET).&#13;
&#13;
12.     The textbook provision activities inthis project were approved by the Iraq Strategic&#13;
ReviewBoardinFebruary 2004.&#13;
&#13;
13.     International experience o f education reform andreconstruction inpost-conflict&#13;
societies underlines the importance o f quick and visible highimpact activities to address the&#13;
most urgent system needs backedby intensive capacity buildingfor education authorities.&#13;
This is necessaryto lay the groundwork for the development o f a comprehensive education&#13;
strategy aligned with the emergingwider development vision o f the new political authorities.&#13;
The successful resumption of schooling inIraqinSeptember 2003 was an important&#13;
achievement. However, the education sector remains fragile, and recent momentum can only&#13;
be maintained ifthe minimumconditions for leaming are established inschools for the&#13;
2004/2005 school year, as part o f a more comprehensive process o f capacity buildingfor&#13;
wider system reform andmodernization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B.      BANK RESPONSEAND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
 14.    InJanuary 2004, the World Bank's Boardo fExecutive Directors discussed an&#13;
InterimStrategyNote o fthe World Bank Group for Iraq(Document NumberR2004-0008)&#13;
and authorized the Bank to act as administrator o f the World Bank IraqTrust Fund(the&#13;
"WBITF" or "the Trust Fund").&#13;
&#13;
 15.    The World Bank Group's interimstrategy, which covers the period February-October&#13;
2004, focuses on (i)  building Iraqi capacity neededurgently for the reconstructionprogram;&#13;
(ii)preparing and starting to implement. emergency operations to generate employment and&#13;
restore essential infrastructure and services; and (iii)&#13;
                                                      laying thefoundation for the medium-&#13;
termprogram, through studies and policy advice.&#13;
&#13;
 16.    The strategy relies on the World Bank IraqTrust Fundto finance projects, and on&#13;
Bank budget for economic and sector work and policy advice. The interimwork program&#13;
includes four proposedprojects amounting to US$400-600 million that will be financed from&#13;
the Iraq Trust Fundto the extent resources are available (projects will bephased if&#13;
insufficient resources are available). A multi-sectoral institutional capacity buildingprogram&#13;
has already commenced. The InterimStrategy originally provided for a single Emergency&#13;
Education Rehabilitation Project (EERP) that incorporatedthe textbook provision activities&#13;
inthis project, together with the schoolrehabilitation activities inthe Emergency School&#13;
RehabilitationProject (ESRP). Inorder to ensure delivery o f textbooks at the start o f the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 4&#13;
2004-2005 school year, the EERP was split into these two education projects. Other projects&#13;
under fast-track preparationinclude an emergency community-based rural infrastructure and&#13;
emergency infrastructure reconstruction. The interimstrategy also includes buildingblocks&#13;
o f analytical work to support the transition to a diversified market economy and to develop a&#13;
social protection system. Analytical work has been grouped into three clusters: economic&#13;
reform and transition; public sector management; andpovertyand safety nets, andtwo&#13;
sectors (health and education).&#13;
&#13;
17.     The Bank was the lead agency for education inthe UNDG/World Bank Joint Needs&#13;
Assessment, and has worked closely with UNICEF, UNESCO, USAID, and CPA. It i s well&#13;
positioned to play a leading role inbothrepair and reconstruction and capacity-building for&#13;
reform. It has considerable accumulated experience insupportinglarge-scale repair and&#13;
rehabilitation projects inpost-conflict settings. The support for school rehabilitation and&#13;
textbooks will be complemented by the range o f capacity-building activities inkey policy&#13;
areas such as educationreform, education management, teacher policy, curriculum&#13;
development, TVET, and higher education financed initiallythrough a first Capacity&#13;
BuildingProject.&#13;
&#13;
18.     Lessons of Post-Conflict Experience Applied: Basedon the World Bank's recent&#13;
experience inpost-conflict countries such as East Timor, Bosnia, Algeria, Sierra Leone, West&#13;
Bank and Gaza, and Kosovo, a number o f important lessons have been leamed and&#13;
introduced into the design o f the project. First, experience has shown the value of early and&#13;
visible impact, and the importance o f resumptiono f normal schooling operations to permit&#13;
the education authorities to focus energy on wider system reform. This project targets that&#13;
issue directly. A second lesson is the importance o f capacity buildinginthe ministry.This&#13;
project will be complementedby a range o f capacity-building activities inthe Capacity&#13;
BuildingProject I. thirdlesson is the importance o fearly and effective collaboration with&#13;
                     A&#13;
other development partners coordinated by the government. The project draws upon the&#13;
extensive collaborationwith other development partners that have beenactive inIraq, and&#13;
builds on complementary activities coordinated through the MOE. Finally, becauseo fthe&#13;
particular difficulties o f implementation and supervision where security conditions make&#13;
access to the country very difficult, the project draws on experience gained inother similar&#13;
circumstances, such as Algeria.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C.      DETAILED PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
&#13;
Objectives&#13;
&#13;
19.     Theprincipal objective o fthe Project is to improve conditions o f leaming inprimary&#13;
and secondary schools through the urgent provision o fprimary and secondary school&#13;
textbooks.&#13;
&#13;
Component 1:Provisionof Textbooks (US$39.5 million)&#13;
&#13;
20.     The grant will finance the printingand distribution o f about 69 million textbooks for&#13;
six million students inall governorates, for the school year 2004/2005. This quantity covers&#13;
over 600 titles for all 12 grades o f the primaryand secondary system. Criteria for the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 5&#13;
selection o f textbooks to be financed by the grant give the highest priority to primaryand&#13;
secondary textbooks, with special attentionto final grades o f each phase. Primaryand&#13;
secondary textbooks have priority over teacher manuals, teacher guides, and vocational and&#13;
teacher education materials. Annex 5 provides further details on these selection criteria.&#13;
&#13;
21.      The M O Ehas provided written assurancethat the textbooks covered bythe grant&#13;
have beensystematically reviewedby panels o f Iraqi educators and teachers, and material&#13;
that could give serious offense to other national, ethnic, or religious groups has been&#13;
removed.&#13;
&#13;
22.      The MOE undertook a review inApril o f existing stocks o fpaper to assess quantity&#13;
and quality. Currently the M O E has in stock between 9,000 and 11,000 tons o fpaper o f&#13;
acceptable quality purchased under the Oil-for-Food program. This i s sufficient for 25 - 30&#13;
milliontextbooks, or approximately 33-40 percent o frequirementsandwill facilitate an early&#13;
start to printing o f the most urgent textbooks. Printingwill therefore be procured through a&#13;
combination o fNational Competitive Bidding(NCB) and InternationalCompetitive Bidding&#13;
(ICB). Printing of textbooks usingthe stocks o fpaper inthe MOE will be procured through&#13;
NCB. For the remainder o fthe textbooks, ICB will be used, and printerswill be required to&#13;
obtain the paper as part o f their contracts. Filmfor the printingofbooks will be provided to&#13;
printersby the MOE.&#13;
&#13;
23.      The MOEhas already prepared lists, technical specifications, and schedules o f&#13;
requirements for ICB andN C B exercises amounting to US$29.38 million (ICB) and US$9.9&#13;
million (NCB) covering all the textbooks. Draft biddingdocuments to initiate advance&#13;
procurement have already been drafted andtendered, so that textbooks can be printedand&#13;
delivered intime for the opening o f schools inSeptember 2004.&#13;
&#13;
24.      Printers will be required intheir contracts (NCB) to collect paper from M O E stores&#13;
and deliver the books to the govemorates according to the M O E plan, bypassing the central&#13;
warehouses inBaghdad. While some warehouses were destroyed, adequate warehousing&#13;
facilities exist inmost govemorates, and where these are inadequate, arrangements will be&#13;
made to use other facilities such as recreation halls inschools (delivery should take place&#13;
largely during the school vacation). Further distribution to district distribution centers and&#13;
schools will be handledby the govemorates using existing procedures, and financedby the&#13;
MOE. The MOEprepared a detailed distributionplanindicating how andwhenbooks will&#13;
reach the schools. Allowance has been made inthe attached implementation schedule for&#13;
possible delays inthe distribution o f textbooks because o fthe highnumber o frisks&#13;
associated with the project.&#13;
&#13;
25.      The grant will also finance technical assistance and training intextbook production,&#13;
as needed to support efforts by the MOE to ensure that textbooks reflect curriculum&#13;
development trends and modernintemational standards.&#13;
&#13;
Component2: ProjectManagementandCapacityBuilding(US$0.50 million)&#13;
&#13;
26.      Underthis component, the grant will finance thebasic costs o fthe Project&#13;
Management Team (PMT) to manage the project, andthe technical assistance and capacity&#13;
buildingnecessary to ensure effective project management and transfer o f skills to the MOE&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  6&#13;
staff. The MOEwill cover the costs o f the staff of the PMT, except for up to five consultants&#13;
employed from Project funds to fillkey capacity gaps. The grant will finance office&#13;
equipment, fbmiture and operating costs necessary to manage the Project. Operating costs&#13;
include (i) the maintenance o f office equipment; (ii)  transportation andtravel, includingper&#13;
diem allowances for Project staff intravel status; (iii) o f office space; (iv) office&#13;
                                                         rental&#13;
supplies, utilities and office administration, including translation, printingand advertising;&#13;
(v) fuel costs; (vi) communication costs; (vii) costs for production o fbiddingdocuments;&#13;
(viii) commercial bank charges; and (ix) any other Project management support costs as&#13;
agreed by the Recipient and the Administrator, but excluding salaries o f the Recipient's civil&#13;
servants. Because o f the highrisk environment and the institutional capacity limitations, the&#13;
grant will finance technical assistance and training inproject management, procurement, and&#13;
financial management, as well as audit costs. Further details of the arrangements for project&#13;
management are provided in Section D.&#13;
&#13;
D.      INSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTS AND PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
27.     Project scope. The Project will finance the provision o f essential textbooks for&#13;
primarykecondary education to all primary and secondary schools inall 18 govemorates.&#13;
&#13;
Project Management&#13;
&#13;
28.     The MOE suffered major dislocation and loss o f its human and technical resources as&#13;
well as its physical infrastructure and i s ina transitional phase. It has major logistical and&#13;
sectoral challenges and needs more time to reorganize, restructure, andbuild its capacity to&#13;
manage the sector. Inview o f this situation, it was agreed that a "core team" o f senior M O E&#13;
staff and hiredconsultants (where expertise is lacking) will constitute the Project&#13;
Management Team (PMT). The M O E will have overall responsibility for the coordination&#13;
and execution o f all project activities, and will be guided by a Project Advisory Committee&#13;
(PAC) as described below.&#13;
&#13;
29.     M O E directorates at the governorate level suffered less dislocation and there i s&#13;
sufficient technical expertise to serve Project needs. These Directorates will have&#13;
responsibility for arranging storage and delivery o f textbooks from govemorates to schools.&#13;
&#13;
30.     Annex 2 provides more detailed information on the structure o f project management,&#13;
as well as a matrix of responsibilities of the agencieshodies involved inthe project.&#13;
&#13;
31.     Proposed Staffing o f the PMT. For the sake o f efficiency, this PMT will also have&#13;
responsibility for the concurrent US$60million Emergency School Rehabilitation Project&#13;
(ESW).The PMTwill beheadedbyaProject Team Leader andup to 10professionals,&#13;
depending onworkload requirements. It i s expected that six PMT staff will be senior M O E&#13;
officials and five will be consultants hiredto bring external expertise for the life o fthe two&#13;
projects while transferring capacity to MOE staff. The staff o f the PMT will receive special&#13;
training and orientation inkey aspects ofproject management includingprocurement and&#13;
financial management. The P M T will beresponsible for planning and coordinationo f all&#13;
project activities, financial management (accounting and disbursements), procurement o f&#13;
goods and consulting services (and related contract management), and monitoring and&#13;
evaluation to ensure timely implementation and coordination o f all project activities. At the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 7&#13;
completion o fthis project, staff responsible for textbook activities will revert to their original&#13;
posts inthe MOE. For the sake o f simplicity, there i s one organizationalchart for the PMT&#13;
that serves both Projects. Some posts and functions inthat chart relate to the ESRP.This&#13;
Project will cover costs o fPMT for the first six months, after which costs will be covered&#13;
from the ESRP grant.&#13;
&#13;
32.     The PMT will work closely with the planning departments o f the Directorates inall&#13;
18 governorates to assist in all aspects o f planning, coordination, and supervision o f&#13;
distribution related to the project.&#13;
&#13;
33.     Ad hoc Consultants. The PMT will be assisted by consultants hiredon anad hoc basis&#13;
whenever the need arises. Project funds have beenbuilt into the project to provide for such&#13;
services that could include technical advice on textbooks, etc.&#13;
&#13;
34.     Proiect Advisory Committee (PAC). Project oversight will be providedby the PAC,&#13;
chaired by a representative o f the MOE, comprising members from the Ministry o f Planning&#13;
and Development Cooperation and the Ministry o f Finance. The Committee will meet at least&#13;
quarterly to: (i)ensure accomplishment o fthe project objective, (ii) and guide project&#13;
                                                                       oversee&#13;
design, (iii)facilitate coordination with key ministries and donors, (iv) monitor keyproject&#13;
indicators, and (v) ensure adequate operational and maintenance funding. The PAC will&#13;
endorseproject plans and budget allocations. When the PAC considers matters relating to the&#13;
ESRP, it will include a representative o f the Ministry o fHousing and Construction.&#13;
&#13;
Procurement&#13;
&#13;
General&#13;
&#13;
35.     Procurement for this project will be carried out in accordance with the World Bank's&#13;
 "Guidelines: Procurement Under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" dated May 2004; and&#13;
"Guidelines: Selection and Employment of Consultants by WorldBank Borrowers ''dated&#13;
May 2004, and the provisions stipulated inthe Legal Agreement. The general description o f&#13;
various items under different expenditure categories are described below. For each contract&#13;
to be financed by the grant, the different procurement methods or consultant selection&#13;
methods, the need for prequalification, estimated costs, prior review requirements, and time&#13;
frame are agreed between the Recipient and the Bank project team inthe Procurement Plan&#13;
(PP). The PP will be updated as requiredto reflect the actualproject implementationneeds&#13;
and improvements ininstitutional capacity. The project will allow for domestic preference as&#13;
per Bank procurement guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
36.     Advance Procurement. As textbooks will need to be inthe hands o f students by the&#13;
beginning o f the 2004 school year, advanced procurement o f textbooks has already started.&#13;
Consultants to provide procurement management support and buildcapacity will be procured&#13;
duringMay.&#13;
&#13;
37.     Procurement of Goods. Goods procured under this project will includeprintingo f&#13;
textbooks, office furniture, equipment,and supplies needed for the project implementation.&#13;
Theprocurement will be done usingthe Bank's Standard BiddingDocuments (SBD) for all&#13;
ICB and usingNational SBD satisfactory to the Bank for NCB. Textbook printingwill be&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  8&#13;
procured usingI C B for some titles and N C B for others. N C B procedure will be usedfor&#13;
those quantities o f textbooks that match the available quantities o fpaper already available in&#13;
the MOE stores inBaghdad. Duringthe pre-appraisal and appraisal missions, the Bank&#13;
assisted the MOE team to prepare the biddingdocuments for printingthe textbooks using&#13;
I C B procedures. These were completed and have beentendered. Shopping procedures will be&#13;
used for procurement o f goods o f small values such as office suppliesand equipment as&#13;
described inthe procurement plan.&#13;
&#13;
38.     Selection o f Consultants. Consultant services procuredunder this project will include:&#13;
selection o f a procurement specialisth to assist the PMT inall procurement-related issues&#13;
including: provision o f training to the M O E procurement staff and physical spot checks;&#13;
selection o f individual consultants and/or firms to providetraining; and capacity buildingin&#13;
financial management. Short lists o f consultants for services estimated to cost less than&#13;
US$50,000 equivalent per contract maybe composed entirely o fnational consultants in&#13;
accordance with the provisions o fparagraph 2.7 o f the Consultant Guidelines.It i s expected&#13;
that shortlists o f consultants may be less than six as the security conditions inIraqmaynot&#13;
attract enough intemational consultants to work inIraq.&#13;
&#13;
39.     Operating Costs: The grant will finance expenditures directly related to the&#13;
management o f the project such as: (i)    maintenance o f office equipment; (ii)transportation&#13;
and travel, including per diem allowances for Project staff intravel status; (iii)  rental o f&#13;
office space; (iv) office supplies, utilities and office administration, including translation,&#13;
printingand advertising; (v) fuel costs; (vi) communication costs; (vii) costs for production&#13;
o fbiddingdocuments; (viii) commercial bank charges; and (ix) any other Project&#13;
management support costs as agreedby the Recipient and the Administrator, but excluding&#13;
salaries o f the Recipient's civil servants. These items which will be financed by the project&#13;
will beprocuredusing the MOE administrative procedures which are satisfactory to the&#13;
Bank.&#13;
&#13;
Assessment of the agency's capacity to implement procurement&#13;
&#13;
40.     Procurement activities will be carried out by MOE. The M O E Supply Department i s&#13;
staffedby three officials, including a procurement officer experienced intextbook printing&#13;
and another qualified technical staff. They will support the qualified P M T procurement staff&#13;
incarrying out procurement. A simpleproject implementationmanual is underpreparation(it&#13;
is expected that the manual will be ready by June 2004) and the PMT will use this manual in&#13;
the implementationof the project. Ifnecessary, this will be aligned with the Master&#13;
ImplementationManual (MIM) as soon as this becomes available.&#13;
&#13;
41.     A generic assessment o fMOE's capacity to implement project procurementwas&#13;
conducted inMarch 2004. Given that the security conditions preventedthe Bank project team&#13;
from traveling to Iraqat the time o f the project preparation, a quick assessment o fthe capacity&#13;
o f the MOE to implement procurement actions for the project was also carried out by the&#13;
team's Senior Procurement Specialist duringMarch-April 2004 through discussions with&#13;
M O E staff inJordan duringpre-appraisal andappraisal o fthe project. Basedon that, the&#13;
generic assessmenthas beenrevised to reflect the MOE's capacity to implement procurement.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               9&#13;
42.     The Bank procurement specialist has already provided training to the MOE&#13;
procurement staff who will conduct procurement. The training included procurement&#13;
planning, biddingdocument preparation for printing textbooks usingBank SBD, .&#13;
procurement guidelines, procedures and methods for procurement o f goods and selection of&#13;
consultants. Further procurement training on bidevaluation was conducted duringthe Project&#13;
appraisal mission and will continue throughout project implementationby the procurement&#13;
management consultant. A Project Launch Workshop will also be planned at the project start.&#13;
&#13;
43.     Most o f the issues and risks concerning the procurement component for&#13;
implementation o f the project havebeenidentified inthe generic assessment o f M O E&#13;
capacity to implement project procurement and include: (i)  the lack o f good laws and&#13;
regulations, of modem standard documentation, and the habits acquired by procurement staff&#13;
inthe previous era whichwill take timeto change; (ii)   weakness of procurement staff inuse&#13;
o fBank procurement guidelines and intemational sound procurement practice; (iii)   inability&#13;
o fBank procurement staffto supervise the project inthe field; and (iv) delays in&#13;
implementing the procurementplandue to lack o f experience inprocurement planning and&#13;
the volatile security conditions inIraq. The corrective measures which have been agreed&#13;
upon are: (i) a procurement officer will behired to bepart o f the PMT; (ii)procurement&#13;
                                                                             a&#13;
consultant will be recruited to assist the PMT inprocurement, train the MOE staff on&#13;
procurement, establish a procurementmonitoring andreporting system, and conduct physical&#13;
spot inspections; and (iii)a decree was issued inApril 2004 by the Minister o f Education to&#13;
rectify the shortcomings inthe current procurementpractice referred to above. The overall&#13;
project risk for procurement is high.&#13;
&#13;
Procurement Plan&#13;
&#13;
44.     The grant Recipient, at appraisal, developed a Procurement Plan (Annex 3) for project&#13;
implementationwhich provides the basis for the procurement methods. This plan has been&#13;
agreed between the Recipient and the project team on April 30,2004, and i s available at the&#13;
MOE-PMT inBaghdad. It will be available inthe project's database and on the Bank's&#13;
extemal website. The Procurement Planwill be updated in agreement with the Project Team&#13;
as required to reflect the actual project implementationneeds and improvements in&#13;
institutional capacity.&#13;
&#13;
Frequency of Procurement Supervision&#13;
&#13;
45.     Inaddition to theprior review supervisionto becarried out from Bank offices, and&#13;
based on the capacity assessment o fthe Implementing Agency, at least one supervision&#13;
mission every three months to visit the field to carry out post review o f procurement i s&#13;
planned. Where security conditions make travel to Iraqimpossible for Bank staff, the Bank&#13;
 will employ a MonitoringAgent, an independent firm, which will operate inIraq and support&#13;
 the Bank incarrying out it supervision function.&#13;
&#13;
 Disbursement&#13;
&#13;
 46.     The proposedgrant o fUS$40 million will be disbursed over aperiod startingMay&#13;
 2004 and up to the grant closing date o f December 31,2005. It is anticipatedthat 90% o fthe&#13;
 Grant will be disbursed by December 2004, with the textbook development activities&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               10&#13;
scheduled for completion inJune 2005. However, because o f the high risks associated with&#13;
the project causingpossible significant delays, provisionhas been made for the project to&#13;
remain effective untilDecember 2005. Annex 1describes the allocation of the grant proceeds&#13;
by component and expenditure category.&#13;
&#13;
47.     MOEwill execute the Project's activities, inclose collaboration withboththe&#13;
MinistryofPlanning andDevelopment Coordination(MOPDC) which follows andmonitors&#13;
the implementation of the country's investmentbudget and the Ministry of Finance (MOF)&#13;
which will make provision for the project activities inthe budget and its supplements.&#13;
&#13;
48.     Grantproceeds willbe disbursed inaccordance with the appropriate policies and&#13;
procedures o f the Bank. Developments inthe banking sector and the intemational transfer&#13;
mechanisms will be monitored closely by the Bank team. To mitigate risks associated with&#13;
financial management and the banking sector inIraqpayments to printers and contractors in&#13;
this project will be made by direct paymentbythe Bank. Once authorized by the MOE, direct&#13;
payments will be made by the World Bank via a global transaction bank directly into the&#13;
account o f the printer or contractor in a commercial bank capable o f receiving funds&#13;
transferred from the intemationalbankingsystem.&#13;
&#13;
FinancialManagement&#13;
&#13;
49.     Assessment Summaw. The project i s the first operation for Iraq under the ITF. The&#13;
financial management risk associated with this operation i s highdue to the limitedknowledge&#13;
about the Iraq government financial systems, controls, andprocedures. Inaddition, due to the&#13;
current security situation, it has not beenpossible to carry out an on-site financial&#13;
management assessment at the MOE. A detailed risk assessment i s included inAnnex 4.&#13;
&#13;
50.     The financial risks will be mitigated byputtinginplace additional controls and&#13;
procedures including (i)  the PMT maintaining simple parallel accounting systems for project&#13;
expenditures; (ii) the PMT will be assigned competent financial staff from the M O E who will&#13;
be supported, as needed, by expert financial management consultants; (iii)separate financial&#13;
                                                                              a&#13;
audit of the project expenditures will be carried out by an independent auditor; (iv) the&#13;
disbursements by the Bank will be madeprimarily by direct payments to suppliers supported&#13;
by documentation, and (v) the Project withdrawal applications will be the subject of a review&#13;
by the MonitoringAgent.&#13;
&#13;
5 1.    The additional financial controls and procedures will supplement the existing financial&#13;
controls andprocedures o f the MOE.Duringthe implementation o fthe project boththe&#13;
additional controls and procedures and the govemment's financial controls and procedures&#13;
will be monitored.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
52.     Conclusion o f the Financial Management Assessment. A financial management&#13;
assessment has been carried out inAmman by interviewing Iraqi officials from various&#13;
ministries including MOE, MOF, and MOPDC concentrated on: (i)         identifyingthe applicable&#13;
procedures to introduce the grant proceeds as a supplementto the M O E FY 04 budget; (ii)&#13;
assessingthe current financial management practices at the M O E to identify the risks&#13;
associated with the project and proposingmitigation actions to reduce and manage such risks;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                11&#13;
and(iii) assessingthe M O E warehousing practices to ensure their adequacy and to identify the&#13;
availability o ftraceable audit evidence for the delivery o fthe books to the warehouses and the&#13;
distribution to the schools thereafter.&#13;
&#13;
53.     Financial Management arrangements. For the proposedproject, the grant funds will&#13;
be made available to the MOE. The MOE will thencontract with various printingcompanies&#13;
for the printingo ftextbooks andwill contract for the other project support activities. The&#13;
MOE will work inclose collaboration with the MOPDC, which is responsible for monitoring&#13;
the implementationo fthe country investment budget; andwith the MOF, which will record&#13;
the grant funds inthe M O E budget, as spelled out inthe budget and its supplements.&#13;
&#13;
54.     The project financial resources will bemanaged within the framework o fthe Iraqi&#13;
government systems. Thus all payments will be subject to the applicable controls, rules and&#13;
regulations o f the government, in addition to the PMT verifications and approvals. These&#13;
controls are applied by the MOF, the MOE, and the Diwan A1Rikaba ElMalia (DARM)&#13;
(Iraqi Supreme Audit Institute). These controls, plus the engagement o f an external&#13;
independent auditor, with intemational experience, will be used to provide reasonable&#13;
assurancethat the funds are used for the intendedpurposes. The M O F will recordthe Trust&#13;
FundGrant as revenueinthe MOEbudget. MOEverifications and controls areperformedby&#13;
the payable department,the ministry's internal audit unit, the director general or the minister,&#13;
dependingonthe payment value, andthe PMT.&#13;
&#13;
55.     To mitigate risks associatedwith disbursement, payments from project funds&#13;
authorized by MOEwill be made to consultants andprinters through direct payments by the&#13;
Bank.With respect to the project management component andpayments below the threshold&#13;
o f US$lO,OOO,    the flow o f funds mechanismwill include the opening o f a Revolving Account&#13;
bythe MOEwith an advance, made availablebythe MOF, to the project. Smallpayments&#13;
will be financed through this Revolving Account and will bereimbursedbythe Bankto the&#13;
M O E uponpresentation o f supporting invoices, proof o fpayment and a signed withdrawal&#13;
application. The PMT and the main financial counterparts from M O E will be subject to&#13;
intensivetraining inBank disbursementprocedures.&#13;
&#13;
56.     To ensure that the MOE, through the PMT, i s able to: (i)   follow on the project funds&#13;
andmanage the direct payment applications, (ii)    integrate budgeted activities for performance&#13;
comparison and decision making; and (iii)     generate timely reports for project management&#13;
andmonitoring purposes, and to ensure continuity, the services o f a financial officer and an&#13;
accountant (these officials will also service the ESRP) within the PMT will manage these&#13;
tasks inclose cooperation with the main MOE finance department. The P M T will be&#13;
responsible for maintaining the project accounts, issuingthe direct payment applications and&#13;
preparing the project Financial MonitoringReports (FMR) for the use o f the Bank team,&#13;
MOE, MOF, and the MOP. As the project will generate about one hundred financial&#13;
transactions, initially and untilan accounting system capable o f generating the required&#13;
reports i s installed, a spreadsheet applicationwill be used to record and generate the project&#13;
accounts andreports. The champions from MOE finance department, including the intemal&#13;
auditor, who will follow the project activities, have been identified by the MOE. These&#13;
champions will be subject to intense training on Bank guidelines allowing them to understand&#13;
the project structure and the implementation procedures, starting with the Project Launch&#13;
Workshop, scheduled for June 2004. These procedures will be detailed inthe project&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 12&#13;
implementation manual under preparation. The format and content o fthe various project&#13;
reports, to be generated by the MOE, havebeen agreed upon duringthe appraisal mission.&#13;
&#13;
57.      Inaddition to the statutory audit performedbythe DARM,an external independent&#13;
auditor with international experience will be engaged to perfonn the project audits and issue&#13;
an independent opinion on the project financial statements. M O E will remit to the Bank not&#13;
later than two months from December 31,2004 and December 31,2005, the project audit&#13;
report.&#13;
&#13;
58.      Financial Covenants. As requiredunder regular Bank lendingoperations, the Grant&#13;
Agreement with the Recipient will obligate the recipient, among other things, to maintain an&#13;
appropriate and adequate financial management system, including records and accounts, and&#13;
prepare financial statements adequate to separately reflect the operations, resources, and&#13;
expendituresrelatedto the activity financed underthe grant from the ITF.The Grant&#13;
Agreement also obligates the recipient to have the accounts, records, and financial statements&#13;
ofthe grant to be audited for each fiscal year by a qualified auditor acceptable to the&#13;
Administrator inacceptable scope and standards. The audit report along with the related&#13;
financial statements shouldbe submittedto the Administrator not later than two months after&#13;
the end o f each fiscal year. The Recipient i s obligated to retain until at least one year after&#13;
submittingthe last audit report all records and supporting documents for grant expenditures.&#13;
Uponrequest o f a donor, a copy o f the audit report and financial statements will be provided.&#13;
The auditor selection process will be launched directly after the Grant Agreement i s signed.&#13;
An Escrow account will be usedto pay the auditor after the project closing date. The project&#13;
Financial Management arrangements and identifiedrisks are detailed inAnnex 4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Project Supervision&#13;
&#13;
 59.     Project activities should be completed by June 30,2005. Supervision will include&#13;
 visits to MOE, MOF, and MOPDC, and to the textbook distribution centers to review&#13;
 implementationprogress, impact o f the project activities and related documentation. A&#13;
 results-based supervision plan i s attached inAnnex 7.&#13;
&#13;
 60.     The Bank, as the ITFAdministrator, will supervise ITF-fundedoperations in&#13;
 accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures. While stafftravel to Iraqi s&#13;
 restricted, supervision o frecipient-executed operations, including NGOs, will be carried out&#13;
 through consultants andthe Monitoring Agent. Each ITF-fundedoperation will include a&#13;
 results-based supervision planthat reflects realities on the ground&#13;
&#13;
 61,     Reporting to Donors. The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in&#13;
 respect o fthe funds deposited by the donors with the Bank under the ITF. Within ninety (90)&#13;
 days o f eachMarch31, June 30, September 30, and December 31, the Bank will prepare, on a&#13;
 cash basis, an unaudited statement o freceipts, disbursements, and fundbalance with respect&#13;
 to the ITF and forward a copy to each donor. Each such statement will be expressed inUnited&#13;
 States dollars, the currency inwhich the ITF funds will be maintained by the Bank. In&#13;
 addition, within one hundred and eighty (180) days o fthe completion o f all disbursements&#13;
 relating to activities financed from the ITF, the Bank will prepare on a cash basis an unaudited&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    13&#13;
financial statement o f receipts, disbursements,and fund balance with respect to the ITF and&#13;
forward a copy to each donor.&#13;
&#13;
62.      The Bank will fumish the donors:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         (a)      on a semi-annual basis, a consolidated report describingthe operations o f the&#13;
                  ITF(including contributions, disbursements, and implementationprogress) in&#13;
                  the preceding six months (paras. 54 and 61); and&#13;
&#13;
         (b)       on an annual basis, a management assertion, together with an attestation from&#13;
                  the Bank's external auditors, concerning the adequacy o f internal control over&#13;
                  cash-based financial reporting for trust funds as a whole.&#13;
&#13;
63.      The Bank will require a financial statement audit o f the ITF to be performed by the&#13;
Bank's external auditors on an annual basis. The costs o f such an audit, including the internal&#13;
costs o f the Bank with respect to such an audit, will be charged to the ITF. The Bank will&#13;
provide each donor with a copy o f the auditors' report.&#13;
&#13;
64.       The Bank, as Administrator o fthe ITF, will maintain close consultation and&#13;
coordination with the donors. The Bank will provide each donor to the ITF with semi-annual&#13;
reports on its quarterly ex-post evaluation of the activities undertaken by the Monitoring&#13;
Agent. Within six months o f completion o f the activities, or o f full disbursemento f the&#13;
contributions, whichever comes later, the Bank will provide a final progress report to each&#13;
donor, together with a copy o f the independent review ofthe performance o f the Monitoring&#13;
Agent. Upon request by any donor, the Bank will send to such donor the draft and final&#13;
reports received by the Bank from the MonitoringAgent on the activities financedby the&#13;
contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
E.        FINANCIAL AND ECONOMICJUSTIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
65.       This project i s prepared as part o f the Interim Strategy o fthe World Bank to address&#13;
the urgent reconstructionneeds of Iraq and according to emergency recovery assistance (OP&#13;
8.50). The lack o f reliable statistics, the limitedeconomic information, and the speed at which&#13;
the project is prepared prevent more detailed analysis, a recognizedconstraint inpreparing&#13;
such operations. However, the benefits o f the project's investment are expected to be&#13;
substantial compared to its costs as it addresses urgent needs inan environment o f a&#13;
devastated infrastructure, deteriorating quality, and escalating needs. The project will support&#13;
the provision o ftextbooks for six million students at an average cost o fUS$7 per student.&#13;
This will have a direct impact on the conditions o f learning andhelp enhance the quality o f&#13;
education.&#13;
&#13;
66.       Sustainability does not present a major challenge for this project. The total cost o f&#13;
textbook provision represents a relatively small share o f the total annual costs o f education,&#13;
 and it i s anticipated that the cost o f textbook provision will be incorporatedinto the M O E&#13;
 annual budget as the revenue and expenditure situation normalizes. Inthe eighties the&#13;
 education system inIraq flourished and compared favourably with the middleincome&#13;
countries. In 1989,the education budget represented six percent o f GDP and expenditure per&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     14&#13;
student was US$620. However, following three wars and a decade of international trade&#13;
embargo, expenditure per student dropped to US$47 per year in2002. The resumption of oil&#13;
exports inIraq andthe reform policies that arebeingintroduced are expected to stimulate&#13;
sustainable growth over the medium-termandprovide resources for basic social services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
F.       R I S K S&#13;
&#13;
67.      This Project is being undertaken inan uncertain and highlyriskyenvironment. The&#13;
table below summarizes the key project risks identified, and indicates which measures are&#13;
beingtaken to mitigate these risks. The major risk for the project is inability ofMOEto have&#13;
the textbooks printed or distributed because o f security issues, as highlightedbelow among&#13;
others. The Environmental Category i s C and no safeguard policies have been triggered.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Transition from CPA to a new Iraqi                           Keeping project simple. Working closely with&#13;
administration-unknown outcomes that could            H      Ministryofficials to ensure ownership. Working&#13;
affect project implementation                                closely with CPA,&#13;
Administration changes inMOE -jeopardizing                   Buildingrelationships at the technical levelwith&#13;
current commitment to project design and              H      current officials to ensure continuity inevent o f&#13;
inputs                                                       changes.&#13;
Sectoral priorities-difficult to establish inthe             Ongoing communication with Bank counterparts&#13;
current political setting--possible disagreements            working with MOF, MOP. Involving all concerned&#13;
between MOE and other controlling Agencies                   agencies inthe design of the project andthrough&#13;
(MOF, MOPDC)                                                 the PAC.&#13;
                                             From( Imponents 1 outputs&#13;
                                                             Providing an adequate number o f textbooks that&#13;
&#13;
Textbooks could be diverted to black market           M      are free o f charge to students; direct delivery by&#13;
                                                             printers to directorates; local publicity about&#13;
                                                             textbook availability.&#13;
                                                             MOEhas developed an action planto identify&#13;
Problems with the availability of textbook                   titles that do not have film and-urgently arranged&#13;
printingfilmfor some titles couldimpede               H      for its production. CDs o f available titles from&#13;
timely availability o f textbooks in schools                 UNICEFandUNESCO will be forwarded to MOE&#13;
                                                             by these agencies.&#13;
&#13;
Paper for NCB textbooks could be inadequate,                 MOEhas assessed quality and quantity o fpaper in&#13;
&#13;
o f poor quality or lost intransfer to printers       M      stock. Printers will be responsible for collection o f&#13;
                                                             paper from MOE for printing.&#13;
                                                             This is a risk beyond the control o f MOE or WB.&#13;
                                                             Delivery o f textbooks and conducting supervision&#13;
Security conditions deteriorate making                       by private contractors rather than MOEmay help&#13;
distribution o f textbooks difficult                  S      reduce visibility. Distribution to Govemorates is&#13;
                                                             responsibility of printers, who are required to&#13;
                                                             insure the textbooks.&#13;
                                                             MOEreports that warehouse capacity is adequate&#13;
&#13;
 Storage o f textbooks may present problems           M      at all but three governorates. MOE will make&#13;
                                                             alternative arrangements for storage inschool&#13;
                                                             buildings(not classrooms).&#13;
                                                             MOEhas responsibility for distributionfrom&#13;
Distribution from governorates to schools may                governorate storage to schools. MOE will use long&#13;
 encounter difficulties                               M&#13;
                                                              standing practice o f paying for schools to collect&#13;
                                                             books. This is not funded from the Proiect.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     15&#13;
                      Risk                        Rating                  Mitigation Measures&#13;
                                                           Capacity-building will focus on local staff. Where&#13;
                                                           possible, support from international TA will be&#13;
                                                           provided through virtual meetings, and meetings in&#13;
Difficulty inhiringexpatriate TA consultants         S     Amman. Inthe event that local capacity is initially&#13;
wherever local expertise i s lacking.                      not adequate for rapid implementation, the MOE&#13;
                                                           has agreed to the use o f agents for relevant aspects&#13;
                                                           o f implementation and monitoring inthe early&#13;
                                                           stages.&#13;
                                                           Consultants will be contracted to assist in&#13;
&#13;
The Bank's inability to carry out in-country               supervision. Inaddition, special monitoring&#13;
                                                     S     instruments will be designed for ITF-financed&#13;
supervision                                                projects and used o f MOE implementation staff,&#13;
                                                           supervision consultants and Monitoring Agent.&#13;
                                                Pocurementisks&#13;
                                                           A decree was issuedby the Minister o f Education&#13;
The lack o f good laws and regulations, of&#13;
modern standard documentation, and the habits              (April 2004) rectifying shortcomings inthe current&#13;
                                                     H&#13;
acquired by procurement staff inthe previous               procurement practice at the MOE. Continuous&#13;
&#13;
era, which will take time to change                        training to be providedby an international&#13;
                                                           procurement consultant..&#13;
                                                           The international procurement consultant will&#13;
                                                           provide assistance to the P M T inprocurement on&#13;
Weakness o f procurement staff inuse o f Bank&#13;
procurement guidelines and international sound       H     World Bank procurement guidelines, bidding&#13;
&#13;
procurement practices                                      document preparation, bids evaluation and also&#13;
                                                           will provide training inprocurement. Close&#13;
                                                           supervision by Bank staff.&#13;
                                                           Recruitment o f local consultants to conduct spot&#13;
Inability o f Bank procurement staff to supervise&#13;
project inthe field                                  H     physical inspection and assist the PMT in&#13;
                                                           reporting.&#13;
Delays in implementing the procurement plan                The international procurement management&#13;
due to lack o f experience inprocurement             H     consultant will provide assistance to the P M T in&#13;
planning and the volatile security conditions in           procurement related issues and also will provide&#13;
Iraq                                                       training inprocurement.&#13;
Overall Procurement Risk                             H&#13;
                                           Finan&#13;
Inherent Risk&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Undetermined financial management capacity&#13;
inthe MOE.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Limited capacity to manage financial&#13;
requirements o f the Project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Counterpart Funds&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall Inherent Risk&#13;
&#13;
Control Risk&#13;
Lack o f familiarity with Bank guidelines and&#13;
                                -&#13;
regulations inMOE.&#13;
Flow o f funds: difficulties inmaking payments&#13;
to suppliers inside and outside 1raq;possible&#13;
risks associated with Iraqbanking sector.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 16&#13;
&#13;
                       Risk                     Rating                Mitigation Measures&#13;
Staffing: Lack o f financial management skills         An experiencedFO inPMT will be responsible for&#13;
inPMT.                                           H     the project accounting.&#13;
                                                       Financial Operations chapter o f the Project&#13;
Accounting policies and procedures: may not            ImplementationManual, will define financial&#13;
meet Bank management and reporting               M     policies and procedures. The control policies&#13;
requirements.                                          applicable to the MOE will be used to follow on&#13;
                                                       the project accounts.&#13;
                                                       The Minister will assign one intemal auditor&#13;
Internal audit: Existing arrangements for              (champion) to focus on the project transactions.&#13;
intemal audit may not be adequate or may not     M     This auditor will be introduced to the project and&#13;
be familiar with project requirements.                 trained on Bank guidelines in the Launch&#13;
                                                       Workshop.&#13;
                                                       Extemal audit will be carried out by an&#13;
                                                       independent auditor acceptable to the Bank with&#13;
Extemal audit: Unknown capacity o f auditing           intemational experience. There was no capacity&#13;
firms inIraq.                                     H&#13;
                                                       assessment for the audit profession in Iraq to&#13;
                                                       determine capability to perform audits as per ISA.&#13;
                                                       TORSrequire intemational experience inauditing.&#13;
Reporting and Monitoring: Current MOE                  A "ring-fenced" project accounting systemwill&#13;
systems do not generate required reports.         H    generate the data for the FMRs.&#13;
Information systems: Not hnctioningreliably             Simple spreadsheet-based reporting format will be&#13;
inMOE                                             H    putinplace at LaunchWorkshop (June 2004)&#13;
Overall Control Risk                              H&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     17&#13;
                                                                                              Annex 1&#13;
&#13;
                               EmergencyTextbooksProvisionProject&#13;
                                         DetailedProjectCosts&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Component                                                       Trust Fund        MOE         Total Costs&#13;
                                                                   US$             US$           US$&#13;
1.Provision o fTextbooks                                         39,505,OOG    14,965,000     54,470,000&#13;
2. Project Management and Capacity Building                         495,000          35,000      530,000&#13;
TOTAL                                                            40,000,000    15,000,000     55,000,000&#13;
&#13;
MOE contribution represents the valueofpaperprovided from its stocks.&#13;
Component 2 - Proiect Manaaement and Capacitv Building includes the provision of equipment, furniture,&#13;
consultants 'fees for project management and support to project management expenditures.&#13;
MOE contribution represents salaries of MOE staff that will manage theproject.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Table B: Allocationof Grant Proceeds&#13;
&#13;
              ExpenditureCategory                     I           Amount                   Financing&#13;
                                                                  inUS$               I    Percentage&#13;
 1.Printingof textbooks                                             37,280,000                100%&#13;
 2. Consultants' services                                              375,000                100%&#13;
 3. Goods                                                              200,000                100%&#13;
 4. Operating costs                                                    100,000                100%&#13;
 5. Training:                                                           45.000                100%&#13;
 Unallocated                                                         2,000,000&#13;
 Total Grant Costs                                                  40,000,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Table C: DisbursementSchedule&#13;
                                              Calendar Year&#13;
&#13;
 Quarter-CY               Q3-2004       Q4-2004         41-2005      Q2-2005           Q3-2005      Q4-2005&#13;
 Absolute               27,750,000   11,400,000         805,000         15,000          15,000        15,000&#13;
 Cumulative             27,750,000   39,150,000     39,955,000      39,970,000      39,985,000    40,000,000&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     """" """" " " " "&#13;
                                                      0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0&#13;
'I 8                                                                    y&#13;
&#13;
3 0&#13;
- "I                                                                              ,-...-.--&#13;
      h h h h h h h       h h h h h h h h h h h h&#13;
        V I " " " " " "                              --------.--.-.-.--&#13;
                                                              m,            0   m y m,    y&#13;
        0 0 0 0 0 0 0     "0"0" " " " " " " " " 9&#13;
                               0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rd&#13;
L&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       Annex 2&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Emergency Textbook Provision Project&#13;
                                                                                                            Project Management&#13;
&#13;
A.             Project Management Structure&#13;
The Project Management Team below will also have the responsibility o f the Emergency&#13;
School Rehabilitation Project (ESRP).The team will start with the core personnel required for&#13;
this project, and buildto full size as the ESRP demands grow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     Minister of Education                                                                       Project Advisory Committee (PAC)&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                              Chair MOE. Members MOPDC&amp; MOF&#13;
                                                                                                IL                                                                                                                                                                    I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              Ministry of Education Other Departments                       .&#13;
&#13;
                             .......................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                      1                          1                                                    1                                                                               1&#13;
                                                                         Project Management Teim (PMT) within the MOE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       Project Team Leader&#13;
                                                                                                                                        (PTL) -&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                       Planning&#13;
                                                          Administration                                                                       -                                                     Monitoring&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                     Evaluation&#13;
    Technical&#13;
    Assistance               :                        Staffing:2                                                                                                                                     Staffing: 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   !     Ad hoc       j      i                                                                                                                                                                                                                          :    Technical&#13;
   ! Evaluation     i---: --,    -----                                                                                                                                                                                                                  :    Assistance&#13;
                                                 I&#13;
   !1. Committees&#13;
      -.-.-.-.-.-.-.I        .i               v&#13;
       -.- -.-.-.-.-.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   ...&#13;
   ;      Ad hoc             :                  Engineering &amp; Procurement                                                                                                                                                                                * I  Financial !&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         * .&#13;
   j    Evaluation     ;--&gt;---+                                    Civil Works&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                    Financial Management                                          +---:?     Management I&#13;
   ! Committees                                                     Textbooks                                                                                                                                                                            .&#13;
   ................    i i                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   Consuitants&#13;
                                                         ConsultingServices                                                                                                                                                                              : !!&#13;
&#13;
    r'-&#13;
    ,    - -&#13;
          Ad hoc              i                A Staffing:                3                                                                                                                  Staffing: 2&#13;
    .......................................................................................................&#13;
    1   Evaluation     + - - &gt; - - - - - - A&#13;
&#13;
    e  Committees j           :                                                                                                                                                                                                                          :&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 School LevelCoordination&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                  ...........................&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                Stakeholders&#13;
                                                                                                                 Teachers, Students,Parents&#13;
                                         ;. ..........................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 B.     ResponsibilityMatrix&#13;
 This table identifieskey responsibilities for each functional area.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        AgenciedBodiesInvolved&#13;
 No.    Activities                                                    k&#13;
I                                                                     o o % p $ s @&#13;
                                                                          W&#13;
                                                                      E Z a a " a * a 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 1This account will deposit MOE advancedfunds, the advance will be returned to MOFuponproject closure&#13;
  FinancialManagement consultants&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Key:&#13;
R=Review/Clear    E=Execute        S=Support      A=Approve          N=Notified&#13;
&#13;
Legend:&#13;
PMT:ProjectManagement Team (inMOE);               MOE:Ministry of Education;&#13;
DIR:DirectorateofEducationat Governorate level;            SCH: School;       MOF:Ministryof Finance;&#13;
AUD: FinancialAuditor; WB: World Bank (Administrator ofthe Trust Fund); PRO: Procurement&#13;
Consultant; PAC:Project Advisory Committee&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Textbook consultants to advise inbidevaluations, distribution logistics, etc.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    Annex 3&#13;
&#13;
                         I r a qEmergency Textbook Provision Project&#13;
                                       Procurement Plan&#13;
&#13;
I. GENERAL&#13;
&#13;
1.      Project information:&#13;
Country:                                  Iraq&#13;
Recipient:                                The Iraqi Ministryo fEducation&#13;
Project Name:                             Emergency Textbooks ProvisionProject&#13;
Project No.:                              PO88945&#13;
Grant Amount:                            US$40,000,000 from the World Bank Iraq Trust Fund&#13;
Project Implementing Agency (PIA):        The Ministryo fEducation&#13;
&#13;
2.      Bank's approval Date of the Procurement Plan: April 30,2004&#13;
&#13;
3.   Date of General Procurement Notice: March26,2004&#13;
4.   Period covered by this procurement plan: first year&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11.     GOODS AND WORKS AND NON-CONSULTING SERVICES.&#13;
&#13;
1.      Prior Review Threshold: Procurement Decisions subject to Prior Review by the&#13;
        Bank as stated inAppendix 1to the Guidelines for'Procurement:&#13;
&#13;
           Procurement Method                Prior Review Threshold             Comments&#13;
 1.    Shopping (Goods)                First three purchase ordedcontracts&#13;
 2.    NCB (Goods)                     &gt;=us$loo,ooo&#13;
 3.    ICB andNCB (Reprinting          All&#13;
       Services for textbooks)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.      Reference to (if any) Project OperationaVProcurement Manual&#13;
&#13;
The Project Management Team (PMT) will use the Master ImplementationManual (MIM)&#13;
prepared by the Bank for Iraq. It i s expected that the MIMwill be ready by end o fMay 2004.&#13;
Untilthe master implementationManual isready, the PMT willprepare a simpleProject&#13;
Operation Manual by grant approval.&#13;
&#13;
3.      Any Other Special Procurement Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
The reprinting services for textbooks will be procuredusing advance procurement andalso&#13;
the selection o f a procurement consultant.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.     ProcurementPackageswith MethodsandTime Schedule&#13;
&#13;
    1                                                        6        7            8            9&#13;
&#13;
   Ref.    Contract                                      Domestic I Review    1Expected  I&#13;
   No.     Descripti                            ificatio Preferenc by Bank       Bid-&#13;
              on            US$      Method                  e      (Prior t               Comments&#13;
                                                                              1Opening    1&#13;
                                                          (yestno)   Post)       Date&#13;
 ETPP.1   Reprinting                                     Yes       Prior       May 17,     Advance&#13;
 RAQ.11 services                                                               2004        procurement&#13;
 2004     for&#13;
          Textbooks&#13;
 ETPP.1   Reprinting                                     No        Prior&#13;
 RAQ.21 services                                                                           procurement&#13;
 2004     for&#13;
          Textbooks&#13;
 ETPP.1   Reprinting                                     No        Prior       July 1,     Advance&#13;
 RAQ.31    services                                                            2004        procurement&#13;
 2004      for&#13;
          Textbooks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
111.    SELECTION OF CONSULTANTS&#13;
&#13;
1.      Prior Review Threshold:Selection decisions subject to Prior Review byBank as&#13;
stated inAppendix 1to the Guidelines Selection and Employment o f Consultants:&#13;
&#13;
              SelectionMethod               Prior Review Threshold             Comments&#13;
   1. CompetitiveMethods (Firms)         &gt;=us$loo,ooo&#13;
   2.  Single Source (Firms)             All&#13;
   3 . IndividualConsultants             &gt;=US$50.000&#13;
  I4. ISingle Source (individual)      1 All&#13;
&#13;
2.      Shortlistcomprisingentirely of nationalconsultants: .&#13;
&#13;
A short list ofconsultants for services, estimatedto cost lessthanUS$50,000 equivalent per&#13;
contract, may be comprised entirely o f national consultants inaccordance with the provisions of&#13;
paragraph 2.7 o fthe Consultant Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
3.      Any Other SpecialSelectionArrangements:&#13;
&#13;
The selection o f aprocurement management consultant will bebased on QCBS under&#13;
advance procurement. The short list may include less than 6 firms because o fthe volatile&#13;
security conditions inIraqwhich do not attract international consultants to work inIraq. If&#13;
there are not enough firms interested inworking on this assignment, the selection method&#13;
couldbe changed to either CQ or single source with Bank clearance.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.     ConsultancyAssignmentswith SelectionMethodsandTime Schedule&#13;
&#13;
   1             2                3            4               5              6              7&#13;
&#13;
 Ref.    Descriptionof        Estimated   Selection      Review        Expected        Comments&#13;
 No.     Assignment           cost        Method         byBank        Proposals&#13;
                              US$                        (Prior / Post) Submission&#13;
                                                                       Date&#13;
         Selection of a         75,000    Guidelines     Prior         May 15,         Advance&#13;
         Procurement                      for                          2004            procurement&#13;
         consultant                       individual&#13;
&#13;
         Selection of PMT       45,000                                  May 15,        Advance&#13;
         consultants                      for                           2004           procurement&#13;
                                          individual&#13;
                                          consultants&#13;
         Curriculum            225,000                   Prior          September&#13;
         review                                         I               2004&#13;
         Auditing               30,000    CQ            I Prior         May 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IV.     IMPLEMENTINGAGENCY CAPACITY BUILDINGACTIVITIES WITH TIME&#13;
        SCHEDULE&#13;
&#13;
The agreed Capacity BuildingActivities are listedwith time schedule&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Expectedoutcome/                  Estimated Estimated Start           Comments&#13;
  ActivityDescription                cost        Duration      Date&#13;
&#13;
  Training on procurement, setting     75,000    4 months      July     Internationalconsultant&#13;
  up aprocurement monitoring                     (3 trips to   2004     (individual)&#13;
  systemat the ministryof                        Iraq)&#13;
  education, support the PMT in&#13;
  biddingdocument preparation,&#13;
  bids evaluation, reporting and&#13;
  spot physical inspection&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      Annex 4&#13;
&#13;
                          Iraq: Emergency Textbook Provision Project&#13;
                                        Financial Management&#13;
&#13;
I. ExecutiveSummaryandConclusion&#13;
&#13;
1.       Theproject is the first operation for Iraq underthe ITF. The financial management risk&#13;
associated with this operation is highdue to limitedknowledge about the Iraq government&#13;
financial systems, controls and procedures. Inaddition, due to the current security situation, it&#13;
has not been possible to carry out an on-site financial management assessment at the MOE.&#13;
&#13;
2.       The financial risks will be mitigatedbyputtinginplace additional controls and&#13;
procedures including (a) the PMT maintaining simple parallel accounting systems for project&#13;
expenditures (b) the PMT will be assigned competent financial staff from the MOE who will&#13;
be supported, as needed, by expert financial management consultants (c) a separate financial&#13;
audit o f the project expenditures will be carried out by an independent auditor (d) the&#13;
disbursements by the Bank will be madeprimarily by direct payments supported by&#13;
documentation, and (e) the Project withdrawal applications will be the subject o f a review by&#13;
the MonitoringAgent.&#13;
&#13;
3.       The additional financial controls and procedures will supplement the existing financial&#13;
controls andprocedures o f the MOE. Duringthe implementation o f the project boththe&#13;
additional controls and procedures and the government's financial controls and procedures&#13;
will be monitored.&#13;
&#13;
4.       The financial management assessment, performed inAmman by interviewing Iraqi&#13;
officials from various ministries and from M O E concentrated on understanding the&#13;
government structure, the accounting systems, accounting policies andprocedures, budgeting&#13;
systems, reporting, staffing, internal controls policies andprocedures, internal and external&#13;
auditing arrangements as practiced in Iraq. The findings, the identifiedrisks andproposed&#13;
mitigation actions are summarized as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                        Rating              Comments&#13;
 1. ImplementingEntity  Satisfactorywith    Risk The MOEhas never implementedBank-financedprojectsand is not&#13;
                        limitations         familiar with Bank requirements,procedures andguidelines. However, the&#13;
                                            Ministry has inplaceafinancial systemdesignedto follow on its budget and&#13;
                                            expendituresas definedinthe legalframeworkapplicable to Ministries in&#13;
                                            Iraq.&#13;
                                            Mitigation: A PMT is beingestablishedwithin MOE. This PMTwill be&#13;
                                             following on the projectactivities and accounts andwill generate the project&#13;
                                            reports includingthe FMRs.Also the team to follow on processingthe&#13;
                                             projecttransactionswithin MOEwill be identifiedandwill be subjectto&#13;
                                            training. This will reducethe number of queries and expeditepaymentsas&#13;
                                             invoiceswill be processedby staffinformedabout the projectand aboutthe&#13;
                                             Bankrequirements.&#13;
 2. FundsFlow           Satisfactory         Risk:The projectwill be fundedthroughone source. Inorder for the project&#13;
                                             funds to bedisburseda supplementto the MOE budgetneed to be&#13;
                                             introduced.&#13;
                                             Mitigation:MOF has startedthe neededactionto introducethebudget&#13;
                                             supplement and providefund advances to theproject.Howeverto mitigate&#13;
                                             the transfer and Bankingrisks, direct paymentswill be used under the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                      28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              roject.&#13;
                                            iB: Foreign exchangetransactions by the Iraqi authority is allowed.&#13;
 3. Staffing             ;atisfactorywith     l i s k Preparationof direct payment requestswill be handledby the PMT&#13;
                         imitations           taff. The project funds will be disbursedinaccordance with the applicable&#13;
                                            iws requiringthe approvalof the MOE finance department, MOE intemal&#13;
                                              uditor and MOE DG or minister in additionto the PMT verificationand&#13;
~                                             pproval.The MOE financedepartment is staffed with 50 employees, out of&#13;
                                            ihich 15 are university graduates.The risk identified here is alanguage one.&#13;
                                            AOE staffhave limitations relatingto the Englishlanguage.As contracts&#13;
                                              nd invoiceswill be in Englishthis may result in limited invoiceverification.&#13;
                                            rlitigation: Within the projectoperatingexpenditure aprovisionfor&#13;
                                            ranslationhas beenincluded.Thiswill be usedto translatethe above if&#13;
                                            ieeded.Also the PMT will be staffed with aFO with good Englishskills.&#13;
                         Satisfactorywith    t i s k The Proceduresin place are basedon the laws applicableto Iraq&#13;
 andProcedures           imitations         iublic sector. However,the projectwill be introducingsome additions to&#13;
                                              heseproceduresmainly the PMT activitiesandthe generationof quarterly&#13;
                                              irojectreports.&#13;
                                              rlitigation: A Financialchapter within the projectOperationsManual&#13;
                                              houldbepreparedto introduceanddefinethe projectfinancial activities&#13;
&#13;
 1                                            letailingthe information anddocumentsflow relatedto the projectandthe&#13;
                                              elationbetweenMOE andthe PMT.&#13;
 5. ProjectControls      Satisfactory         The budget i s preparedby the MOF, the projectexpenditureswill be&#13;
                                              lisbursedinaccordancewith the applicablelawsrequiringthe approval of&#13;
                                              he MOE finance department, MOE internalauditorand MOE DG or&#13;
                                              ninister in addition to the PMT verification and approval.There shouldbe&#13;
                                              :lear segregation ofdutiesand responsibilities.&#13;
                                              Mitigation: The PMT will ensure that bank guidelines are followed and the&#13;
                                              iirect paymentsare reconciledwith the project accounts.&#13;
 6. Flow of information  Satisfactory         4s per applicableregulations,all invoicesshould be accompaniedby a&#13;
 betweenthe MOE and                           .eceipt and official letter signedby the warehouse manager andthe&#13;
 the Education                                :ducation director in the provinceidentifying the quantitiesand type o f&#13;
 directorates and                             Zoods received.&#13;
 warehouses in the&#13;
 provinces&#13;
 7. InternalAudit        Satisfactory with    Risk The intemal auditorsreportdirectly to the minister and needto&#13;
                         limitations          approve all payments.This audit is o f compliance nature. The risk identified&#13;
                                              is about the auditornot beinginformedabout the Bank guidelineswhich in&#13;
                                              certaincases do divergefrom the current practice.&#13;
                                              Mitigation: The Minister will assignone auditorto follow on the project&#13;
                                              transactions. This auditorwill be introducedto the projectand trained on&#13;
                                              Bank guidelines.&#13;
                         NIA                  The SA1(DAW), as per applicable laws, performannualaudits on&#13;
                                              ministriesandpublic agenciesthat receive public funds. A reviewto&#13;
                                              determinethe scope of this audit has not beenperformed. However,in&#13;
                                              additionto the D A W audit, theproject will be auditedby externalauditors&#13;
                                              with intemationalexperienceto be engagedunderTORSacceptableto the&#13;
                                              Bank.Becauseof the lack of knowledgeabout the auditprofessioninIraq,&#13;
                                              there maybe aneedto engagesuch auditorsfrom outside the country.&#13;
  9. Reportingand        Unsatisfactory       Risk The MOE accountingsystemis not capableof generatingquarterly&#13;
  Monitoring                                  projectreports.&#13;
                                              Mitigation: This risk will be containedthroughring fencingaparallel&#13;
                                              accountingsystemthat will follow on the projectaccounts and be managed&#13;
                                              by the PMT. FinancialMonitoring Reports(FMR) will be generated&#13;
                                              quarterlythroughthe parallel system. Due to the small number of&#13;
                                              transactionsunderthe project spread sheet applicationswill be used,&#13;
                                              initially, to record andgenerate the projectreports.&#13;
                          Unsatisfactory      The systems inplace are manual.&#13;
                          Satisfactory        Risk: The MOE honors paymentsby issuingchecks and reconciles the Bank&#13;
                                              account transactionsperiodically.&#13;
                                              Mitigation: The prior reviewthreshold, undertheproject, has beenassigned&#13;
                                              at a low value thus F384 needto be preparedto most of the contracts signed&#13;
                                               underthe project.The MOEwill havedirect access to contractdatathrough&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           the Bank's Client Connections System&#13;
11. RiskManagement     Unsatisfactory      The present FMsystem inplace partially meet the project needs. The&#13;
                                           controls are adequate. A financial officer has been identified and will be&#13;
                                           engaged. The risk of not generating project reports will be contained by&#13;
                                           "ring fencing" the accounting activity .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6.      The project will disburse from within the government budget thus all payments will be&#13;
subject to the applicable controls, rules and regulations inaddition to the PMT verifications&#13;
and approvals. These controls are applied by the MOF; the MOE; and the DiwanA1RikabaEl&#13;
Malia (DARM) (beingthe Iraqi SupremeAudit Institute). These controls, plus the&#13;
engagement o f an external independent auditor, with international experience, will be used to&#13;
follow on the grant funds. The M O F will allocate the funds to the MOE, while M O E&#13;
verifications and controls are performed by the payable department, the ministry's internal&#13;
audit unit, the director general or the minister, depending on the payment value, and the PMT.&#13;
The following chart presents the invoice approval process. Also expenditures are committed&#13;
bythe MOEupon approvalo fthe activity.&#13;
&#13;
7.      Presently, all activities and financial information are prepared manually. Accordingly&#13;
the systems inplace are not able to generate periodical project reports such as the Financial&#13;
MonitoringReports (FMRs) and other similar reports that will be usedfor monitoring and&#13;
decision making.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                             30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    r                                                                                Invoice Processing Chart&#13;
          ~~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Invoice &amp;&#13;
            supportive&#13;
         documentation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   .&#13;
  Intemal Audit, verify invoice&#13;
  and authorize payment&#13;
  (compliance verification)&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   PMT, Verify invoice and request&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   authorization as per payment&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   threshold. Minister to approve all&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   payments above the equivalent o f&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   5 Million ID.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          After approval ofthe Minister,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          PMT to prepare the direct&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          payment (DP) and do accounting&#13;
&#13;
signature                                                                                                                                                 entry inthe project accounting&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          system.&#13;
                         1&#13;
I Government book keeuine entrv                                                      I&#13;
I                        +&#13;
                                                                               ................................                                                                                        DiwanA1Rikaba El&#13;
                                                                               4................................                       Independent                                                     Malia (Supreme&#13;
&#13;
              ;. A.                                                                                                                                                                                    Audit institute)&#13;
&#13;
              i :&#13;
              .j......j............................................................................................................................................................................................ ;        j&#13;
              I .&#13;
              : :                                                                                                                                                                                                            :&#13;
                    .........................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11.     MOE ProjectArrangements&#13;
&#13;
8.      BudgetAccount: A supplement to the MOEbudget will be introduced, byMOF, for&#13;
the project value. Accordingly a budget account underchapter eight will be created for the&#13;
project. The account will be usedto recordthe grant proceeds expected to be disbursedduring&#13;
the 2004 fiscal year. All project payments will be committed and thereafter charged to this&#13;
account. This account will be reconciled on a monthly basis with the parallel accounting&#13;
system that will record indetail the project financial transactions andprovidethe detailed&#13;
reports.&#13;
&#13;
9.      AccountingSystem:The review o fMOE capacity indicates that the existing system&#13;
has inplace standard controls. However, the system i s not able to generate the kindo f timely&#13;
reports required for project management andmonitoring purposes. Therefore, parallel&#13;
arrangements are being put inplace to overcome this. This project accounting and reporting&#13;
will be undertakenby the PMT inconjunctionwith existing MOEcontrol procedures and&#13;
applicable laws. The PMT will include a full time Financial Officer and an accountant to meet&#13;
the financial management needs o f this project andthe ESRP for which the PMT i s also&#13;
responsible. The financial team within the PMT will coordinate closely with the M O E&#13;
financial department and will follow on the project accounts and the generate project reports&#13;
including the Bank-requiredFMRs. As the project will generate about hundred financial&#13;
transactions, initially spreadsheet application will be usedto record and generate the project&#13;
accounts and reports. A template has been designed and was delivered to the MOE&#13;
representatives during appraisal.&#13;
&#13;
10.     Flow of Information:The books will be delivered to the governorates at the various&#13;
warehouses across the country. As per applicable laws all invoices for delivered goods should&#13;
be accompanied with a copy o fthe warehouse entry voucher and a letter signedby the director&#13;
general o f education. Accordingly, all delivery from the warehouses will be accompanied by&#13;
out-of-warehouse vouchers. To facilitate the compilation o f the stock lists o f books at the&#13;
various warehouses, each governorate will remit to the ministry inBaghdad, on monthly&#13;
basis, the inand out quantities.&#13;
&#13;
11.     Manualof FinancialProcedures:The procedures ofthe project andthe parallel&#13;
accounting solution, managed by the PMT, are not all reflected inM O E legal framework. In&#13;
order to ensure the accuracy and completeness o f the parallel system data and to define the&#13;
relation between all departments involved with the project implementation, the PMT financial&#13;
officer, assisted by an external financial consultant, will prepare the project Financial Manual,&#13;
as a chapter within the project implementation manual by June 30 2004. The manual will ,&#13;
integrate the applicable laws and outline the parallel systemby detailing:&#13;
&#13;
        -       The Financial Officer's responsibilities within the PMT andhisrelationship&#13;
                with the MOE financial department;&#13;
&#13;
                The insertion o fthe Project inthe FY 04 Budget.&#13;
&#13;
                The project accounting system;&#13;
&#13;
                The budgetingprocess;&#13;
&#13;
                The reconciliation procedures, timing and output between the two systems;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        -      The document flow;&#13;
        -      The fiequency and forms o fthe financial reports;&#13;
        -      Bankingarrangements for the project account;&#13;
        -      The procedures to be followed for the preparationo fdirect payment requests&#13;
&#13;
111.    Flow of Funds and Controls&#13;
&#13;
12.     All invoices, either for advance payments or for actual incurredexpenditures, will be&#13;
subject to applicable controls and procedures inaddition to the PMT verification and&#13;
approval. These invoices will be approved by the appropriate MOE departments and will be&#13;
honored through direct payment requests signed by the M O E authorizedstaff and supported&#13;
with copies o fthe invoices. With respect to the project management component andpayments&#13;
below the threshold o f US$lO,OOO, the flow o f finds mechanism will include the opening of a&#13;
revolving account to deposit an advance, made available inUS.Dollars by the MOF to the&#13;
project. Such small payments will be financed throughthis account and will be reimbursedto&#13;
MOE uponpresentation o f supporting invoices, proofo fpayment and a signed withdrawal&#13;
application.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 I&#13;
                                                4&#13;
                                                                               I&#13;
                                                 I&#13;
                                                 I&#13;
                                                 I&#13;
                                                 I&#13;
                                                 I&#13;
                                                 I&#13;
                                                 1&#13;
                        DP                       I&#13;
                                                 I                             1&#13;
                                                                               i&#13;
                                                 I                             I&#13;
                   (Replenishment)               I&#13;
                                                 I&#13;
 D P                                             I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         Financial&#13;
                                     Revolving Account&#13;
                                                                         Monitoring&#13;
&#13;
                  1                                                      Reports&#13;
                                                                            (FMRs)&#13;
&#13;
                                                 I      4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Suppliers, small&#13;
                                        payments less then&#13;
                                        $10,000                            Finance fund&#13;
                                      I                                    allocation&#13;
                                                                           advance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            CONTRACTORS,  SUPPLIERS &amp; CONSULTANTS&#13;
&#13;
         ~&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IV.    Projectreports&#13;
&#13;
13.    Quarterlv: The MOEwill generate FinancialMonitoringReports and submitthem to&#13;
the Bank as part o fthe project progress report, or separately. These reports are madeup of:&#13;
&#13;
       FinancialReports:to include a cash flow statement, beginning andendingproject&#13;
       cash balances and an expenditure report by activity or contract comparing actual and&#13;
       planned expenditures. Also, a narrative report explaining all variances that exceed&#13;
        15% when compared to plan and the proposed corrective actions shouldbe included as&#13;
       an annex to the financial reports.&#13;
&#13;
       PhysicalProgress Reports:to includenarrative information andoutput indicators&#13;
       linkingfinancial information with physical progress. For this report, the number of&#13;
       books received and distributed by govemorate should be included.&#13;
&#13;
       ContractsReports:providing information on the textbook printingcontracts,&#13;
       showing contract financial status against plan, including information on all authorized&#13;
       contract variations.&#13;
&#13;
These reports should be remittedto the Bank within 45 days from the end o f the period,&#13;
commencing May 31,2004. The proposed format o f the reports i s inthe project files andhas&#13;
been agreed uponwith the MOE representatives during appraisal.&#13;
&#13;
14.    Annuallv:. AuditedProject Financial Statements (PFS) will be submitted to the Bank.&#13;
PFS, will include:&#13;
&#13;
    (i)Statement of sources and utilization of funds, indicating funds received and&#13;
           expenditures.&#13;
    (ii)&#13;
       Appropriate schedules classifying project expenditures by activity and by govemorate,&#13;
            showing cumulative balances.&#13;
    (iii)&#13;
        Statement ofpayments made usingSOE procedures as defined inthe legal agreement.&#13;
&#13;
V.      AuditingArrangements&#13;
&#13;
15.     Inadditionto the verificationperformedbythe DARM, an extemalindependent&#13;
auditor with international experience, will be engaged to perform the project audit and issue&#13;
an independent opinion on the project financial statements. The extemal audit report will&#13;
encompass all Project activities and will be inaccordance with intemationally accepted&#13;
auditing standards. MOE will remit to the Banknot later than two months after December 31,&#13;
2004 and December 31,2005 the project audit report. The auditor selection process will be&#13;
launched directly after the grant agreement i s signed. An Escrow account will be usedto pay&#13;
the auditor after the project closing date. The audit report o f the project accounts will include&#13;
an opinion on the PFS and will include a separate opinion for the payments made using SOE&#13;
procedures. Inaddition to the audit reports, the auditor will prepare a "management letter"&#13;
identifying any observations, comments and deficiencies, inthe system and controls, that the&#13;
auditor considers pertinent, and will provide recommendations for their improvements.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
VI.      DisbursementArrangements andAssociated Risk&#13;
&#13;
 16.     To mitigate the financial risks, disbursements o fproject funds will bemade to&#13;
contractors, consultants and printersthrough direct payments only. Direct payment&#13;
applications will be prepared by the PMT and submittedto the Bank by MOE. Authorized&#13;
signatories, names and corresponding specimens o f their signatures will also be submittedto&#13;
the Bank.However, given the difficulties inbanking transaction from and to Iraq, the cost&#13;
associated with such direct payment may be considerable and could affect the project overall&#13;
costing. It i s imperative that the routing to be followed for transfer o f funds to Iraq be&#13;
identified.&#13;
&#13;
 17.      Withrespect to the project management component andpaymentsbelow the threshold&#13;
 o f US$lO,OOO, the flow o f funds mechanismwill include the opening o f a revolving account&#13;
 to deposit an advance, made available indollars by the M O F to the project. Such small&#13;
 payments will be financed through this account and will be reimbursed to M O Eupon&#13;
 presentation o f supporting invoices, proof o fpayment, and a signed withdrawal application.&#13;
 The PMT andthe main financial counterparts from MOE willbe subject to intensivetraining&#13;
 inthe Bank disbursement procedures.&#13;
&#13;
 VII.     RiskAnalysis&#13;
&#13;
 18.      The following summarizes the risk assessment findings for the project:&#13;
&#13;
-                                              Risk      Comments&#13;
 Inherent Risk&#13;
                                                         The Bank engaged a consulting firmto assess the&#13;
                                                         current Iraq institutional structure and propose&#13;
 Undetermined financial management capacity    H&#13;
 inthe MOE.                                              mitigating measures (ongoing). Meanwhile,&#13;
                                                         knowledge was built through interviews with the&#13;
                                                         MOE, MOF and Ministryo fPlanning.&#13;
                                                         A P M T staffed with a qualified FinancialOfficer&#13;
 Limited capacity to manage financial&#13;
 requirements of the Project.                  S         willfollow onthe project accounts and generate&#13;
                                                         the project reports.&#13;
                                                         The Iraqi contributionto the project will be inkind&#13;
&#13;
 Counterpart Funds                             L         i.e. the provision o f paper for textbooks, and the&#13;
                                                         costs o f staff assigned to the PMT. Inventories&#13;
                                                         have beentaken o f the available stocks o f paper.&#13;
 OverallInherent Risk                          S&#13;
&#13;
 ControlRisk&#13;
  1.Implementing entity                        H         Training will be provided to MOE and P M T staff&#13;
                                                         o n Bank guidelines and regulations The MOEhas&#13;
                                                         not implementing Bank-financed projects inthe&#13;
                                                         past.&#13;
  2.Funds Flow                                 H         The flow o f funds will concentrate on using direct&#13;
                                                         payment requests; however, the banking and&#13;
                                                         payment system in Iraqcreates a risk factor for&#13;
                                                         such payments.&#13;
  3.Staffing                                   H         An experienced FO will be hiredto follow onthe&#13;
                                                         project accounting while MOE controls will be&#13;
                                                         applied.&#13;
  4.Accounting Policies and procedures         M         Upon finalizing the project's FinancialOperations&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Manual, well-defined financial policies and&#13;
                                                       procedures will be inplace. However the control&#13;
                                                       policies applicable to the MOE will be used to&#13;
                                                       follow o n the project accounts.&#13;
 5.Internal Audit                           M          The Minister will assign one auditor to follow on&#13;
                                                       the project transactions. This auditor will be&#13;
                                                       introduced to the project and trained on Bank&#13;
                                                       guidelines.&#13;
 6.Extemal audit                            H          Extemal audit will be carried out by an&#13;
                                                       independent auditor acceptable to the Bank with&#13;
                                                       intemational experience. There was no capacity&#13;
                                                       assessment for the audit profession inIraqto&#13;
                                                       determine capability to perform audits as per ISA&#13;
 7.Reporting and Monitoring                 H          With "ring fencing" the accounting activity the&#13;
                                                       project will report on the basis o f the FMRs.&#13;
 8.Information systems                      H          This riskwill be reduced throughthe installation&#13;
                                                       o f an accounting software to follow on the project&#13;
                                                       accounts and transactions&#13;
Overall ControlRisk                         H&#13;
&#13;
VIII. Bank Supervision&#13;
&#13;
19.      The first supervisionmission after effectiveness will take the form o f a launch&#13;
workshop where a seminar on Bank rules, regulations and guidelines will bepresented.&#13;
Supervision will intensify initially inorder to ensure that the PMT and the M O E finance&#13;
champions are well trained on Bank guidelines and procedures. Where security conditions&#13;
make travel to Iraqimpossible for Bank staff, the Bank will employ a MonitoringAgent, an&#13;
independent firm, which will operate inIraqand support the Bank incarrying out its&#13;
supervision function.&#13;
&#13;
IX.      DisbursementArrangements.&#13;
&#13;
20.      The grant will be disbursedover a period o f 18 months. Managing the project funds and&#13;
all related financial transactions, including preparation and submission o f direct payment&#13;
applications throughout the project will be the responsibility ofMOE supported by the PMT.&#13;
The allocation o f grant proceeds by expenditure category are summarized inAnnex 1.&#13;
&#13;
Use of Statements o f Expenditures (SOEs)&#13;
&#13;
21.      Duringimplementation, SOEs will beusedfor all expenditures relatingto (a)&#13;
goodshooks under contracts costing less than US$lO,OOO equivalent each; (b) services under&#13;
consultant firms contracts and individualconsultant contracts costing less than US$10,000&#13;
equivalent each (c) Project operating cost and (d) training; under such terms and conditions as&#13;
the Bank will specify by notice to the Borrower. The supporting documentationwill be&#13;
maintainedby M O E and made available for review by Bank representatives upon request,&#13;
documentationrelating to SOEs will beretained for up to one year from the date the Bank&#13;
receives the second grant audit report.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                         36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Action                                       DueDate&#13;
Finalize Financial Officer Contract          After grant Agreement Signature&#13;
Launch the Auditor selection Process         After grant Agreement Signature&#13;
Send Authorize Signatory letter to Bank      After grant Agreement Signature&#13;
Open Prqject Account and Deposit MOF Advance M a y 15,2004&#13;
Finalize Project Financial Manual            June 15,2004&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   Annex 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       EmergencyTextbook ProvisionProject&#13;
                              Iraq Ministry of Education&#13;
                          TextbookPrintingPriority Criteria&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.  General Education (Grades 1-6) and intermediate (Grades 1-3) and Secondary (Grades&#13;
    4-6) has priority over vocational and technical training&#13;
2.  Primary (Grades 1-3) has priority over other primary grades (Grades 4-6)&#13;
3.  Final grades before the BaccaloriateExams (Primary Grade 6 and Intermediate Grade&#13;
    3 and Secondary Grade 6) over other primary, intermediate and secondary grades&#13;
4.  Curriculum textbooks have priority on extra-curricula ones i.e. supplements,manuals,&#13;
    etc. for advanced schools&#13;
5.  For vocational schools, priority o f industrial section on other sections&#13;
6.  Priority o fbooks requiredinlarge numbersover those o f small numbers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
PRIORITY CRITERIA&#13;
&#13;
1.  To ensure supplyo ftextbooks to students ingeneral education (primary, intermediate,&#13;
    secondary) as it is the required basic education&#13;
2.  To ensure the supply o ftextbooks to Grades 1-3 o fprimary education as it is&#13;
    considered an incentive for school attendance and has psychological effect on students&#13;
3.  Curriculum textbooks represents the first basic step inthe printingprocess as&#13;
    compared to the manuals for handwriting, reading, or for advanced students&#13;
4.  Industrial education represents the largest o f technical education andtherefore&#13;
    supplyingtextbooks for this kindo f education gives it apriority&#13;
5.  Supplying textbooks to large numbers o f students has a wide impact and gives a good&#13;
    impression to the students and the community of the special care givento education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Preparedby Ministryof Education&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    a w&#13;
   4sl     i&#13;
           1&#13;
&#13;
           II&#13;
           i&#13;
           iI&#13;
           I&#13;
           iiii1&#13;
           i&#13;
          ii&#13;
           iI&#13;
           iii&#13;
           Ii&#13;
           i&#13;
00&#13;
m          ii&#13;
           ii&#13;
           i&#13;
           i&#13;
           I&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                           39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 Annex 7&#13;
&#13;
                                EmergencyTextbook ProvisionProject&#13;
                                      Result-BasedSupervisionPlan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Total (Ist Total (2nd contracted&#13;
                                                              Date           Date           NCB:          ICB       TOTAL&#13;
&#13;
  Directorate                   priority      priority                   contracted      Textbooks Textbooks Textbooks&#13;
&#13;
                              textbooks) textbooks) textbooks)&#13;
                                                        (1st priority (2nd priority       Delivered    Delivered   Delivered&#13;
                                                                         textbooks)      by 08/31/04 by 09/30/04 by 12/31/04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TBD: To be determined: 6 million 2nd priority textbooks distribution plan to be identifiedand included by end of May2004&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                  40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Annex 8&#13;
                Emergency Textbook Provision Project&#13;
             Timetable of Key Project Processing Events&#13;
&#13;
Sequence                                       Timing&#13;
Time taken to DreDare andDrocessthe Droiect    6 months&#13;
Identificationandpreparation mission           November 2003&#13;
Appraisal                                      April 24,2004&#13;
Negotiations                                   Mav 4.2004&#13;
Grant approval                                 May 15,2004&#13;
Planned Effectiveness                          May 15,2004&#13;
Planned Closing Date                           December 31.2005&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                         41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Annex 9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      EmergencyTextbookProvisionProject&#13;
                 Namesof staffkonsultantswho worked on the project&#13;
&#13;
Name                                 Function&#13;
Peter Buckland                       Task Team Leader. Sr. Education SDecialist&#13;
Mohammed Allak                       Sr. Education Economist/Consultant&#13;
Celine Gavach                        Operations Analyst&#13;
Vasilios Demetriou                   Sr. Imdementation SDecialist/Consultant&#13;
Majed El-Bayya                       Sr. Procurement Specialist&#13;
David Webber                         Lead Financial Management SDecialist&#13;
Hadi Abushakra                       Lead Counsel&#13;
Robert BouJaoude                     Sr. Financial Management Specialist&#13;
Stefanie Brackman                    Environmental SDecialist&#13;
Concepcion Esperanza del Castillo    Sr. Social Scientist&#13;
Nancy-Jean Seigel                    Team Assistant&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Ad Hoc Advisory Committee&#13;
&#13;
Name                      Function&#13;
Joseph Saba               Country Director&#13;
Regina Bendokat           Education Sector Manager&#13;
Nicholas Krafft           IraqCountry Program Coordinator&#13;
Alfred Nickesen           Manager, OPCS Representative&#13;
Nadiib Sefta              Regional Procurement Advisor&#13;
Sherif Arif               Regional Environmental and Safegards Advisor&#13;
Tufan Kolan               IraqTrust FundManager&#13;
Aloysius Ordu             Regional Quality Advisor&#13;
Samia Msadek              RegionalFinancial Management Manager&#13;
Faris Hadad-Zervos        Sr. Operations Officer&#13;
Kathrvn Funk              Sr. Countrv Officer&#13;
Hadi Abushakra            Lead Counsel&#13;
David Webber              Lead Financial Management SDecialist and Finance Officer&#13;
Robert Bou Jaoude         Sr. Financial Management hecialist&#13;
Hiba Tahboub              Sr. Procurement Specialist&#13;
James Stevens             Sr. Operations Officer, Peer Reviewer. ECSHD&#13;
Christine Allison         Lead HumanDevelopment Specialist, Peer Reviewer, SASHD&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5054590">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/05/5054590/iraq-emergency-textbook-provision-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/05/5054590/iraq-emergency-textbook-provision-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/05/5054590/iraq-emergency-textbook-provision-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/08/20/000112742_20040820115521/Rendered/INDEX/T7624.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/08/20/000112742_20040820115521/Rendered/PDF/T7624.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2004-05-13T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2004-08-20T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Iraq - Emergency Textbook Provision Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objective of Emergency Textbook
            Provision Project is to improve conditions of learning in
            primary and secondary schools in Iraq through the urgent
            provision of primary and secondary school textbooks.  The
            project has a major component, the provision of textbooks.
            The grant will finance the printing and distribution of
            approximately 69 million textbooks for six million students
            in all governorates, for the school year 2004/2005. This
            quantity covers over 600 titles for all 12 grades of the
            primary and secondary system. Criteria for the selection of
            textbooks to be financed by the grant give the highest
            priority to primary and secondary textbooks, with special
            attention to final grades of each phase. The secondary
            component, project management and capacity building, will
            finance the basic costs of the Project Management Team (PMT)
            to manage the project, and the technical assistance and
            capacity building necessary to ensure effective project
            management and transfer of skills to the Ministry of
            Education (MOE).
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Iraq - Emergency Textbook Provision Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Iraq - Emergency Textbook
            Provision Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2004/05/5054590/iraq-emergency-textbook-provision-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>IQ-Iraq Emergency Textbook Provision Project
            -- P088945</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Business Environment,Primary Education,Business in Development,Teaching and Learning</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <count>Iraq</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe, Middle East and North Africa!$!107234</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Middle East!$!80463</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000112742_20040820115521</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Primary education,Secondary education</subsc>
        <admreg>Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <prdln>Special Financing</prdln>
        <sectr>Education</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Accounting systems, audits, civil servants,
            curriculum, curriculum development,  education materials,
            education projects, education reform, Education
            Rehabilitation, education sector, educators, employment,
            enrollment, expenditure, expenditure categories,
            Expenditures, external auditors, financial reporting,
            financial statements, financial systems, financial
            transactions, girls, households, human development,
            institutional capacity, internal audit, learning, manuals,
            Primary school, Primary school enrollment, Printing, public
            sector, rural infrastructure, School Rehabilitation,
            secondary school textbooks, secondary schools, social
            services, teacher, teacher education, teacher quality,
            teachers, teaching, textbook distribution, Textbooks,  trust
            funds, Vocational Education,
            account,accounting,accounting
            systems,accounts,achievement,advertising,attestation,audit
            evidence,auditors,audits,contractors,curriculum,curriculum
            development,decision making,direct costs,education
            materials,education projects,education reform,Education
            Rehabilitation,education
            sector,educators,employment,enrollment,exercises,expenditure,expenditure
            categories,Expenditures,financial reporting,financial
            statements,girls,human development,internal
            audit,laws,learning,manuals,Needs Assessment,Primary
            school,Primary school enrollment,Printing,Procurement,public
            sector,Reporting,safety,School
            Rehabilitation,schooling,secondary school
            textbooks,secondary schools,social services,support
            costs,teacher,teacher education,teacher
            quality,teachers,teaching,textbook
            distribution,Textbooks,Vocational Education
        </keywd>
        <owner>Human Development Group (MNSHD)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Emergency Recovery Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe, Middle East and North Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Middle East</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF051094-IRAQ TRUST FUND-SUB-ACCOUNT FOR
            RECIPIENT-EXECUTED TFS,TF051095-ITF - EMERGENCY TEXTBOOK
            PROVISION PROJECT (RECIPIENT-EXECUTED),TF053541-IRTF - TEXTBOOK PROVISION
            PROJECT (BANK-EXECUTED)</trustfund>
        <repnb>T7624</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Name List</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generics</ml:concept><ml:concept>List of Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Off patent drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textbooks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Research and Surveys for Public Contracts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuous Vocational Training (CVT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Technical Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical Vocational Education and Training Policies and Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical and Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Education and Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education/HD Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Expenditures in Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance of Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning Materials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Iraq</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>