<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>270&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           privatesector        P U B L I C          P O L I C Y      F O R       T H E&#13;
&#13;
   NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         NOTE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             2004&#13;
                                                                                                             Output-Based Aid in Water&#13;
                 APRIL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Franz Drees, Jordan         Lessons in Implementation from a Pilot in Paraguay&#13;
                                                                                 Schwartz, and Alexander&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Bakalian                    Paraguay's aguateros--small private water companies--form an important&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             part of the water sector, serving about 9 percent of the total population&#13;
                                                                                 Franz Drees&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 (fdrees@worldbank.org)      (or about 17 percent of those with piped water supply). But until&#13;
                                                                                 is a sector leader, and     recently they operated only in urban areas, where water resources are&#13;
                                                                                 Jordan Schwartz&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 (jschwartz3@worldbank.org)  abundant and they could choose customers based on their ability to pay&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 is a senior infrastructure&#13;
                      PRESIDENCY                                                                             the full costs of providing service. A new World Bank­funded initiative&#13;
                                                                                 specialist, in the World&#13;
                                                                                                             seeks to attract aguateros and construction firms active in the water&#13;
                                VICE                                             Bank's Latin America and&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 the Caribbean Region.       sector to unserved rural areas and small towns by providing an output-&#13;
                                                                                 Alexander Bakalian&#13;
                                                                                                             based aid subsidy, awarded through competitive bidding. The initiative is&#13;
                                                                                 (abakalian@worldbank.org)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 is a senior water supply    the first attempt anywhere to apply this approach to rural and small-&#13;
                                    DEVELOPMENT                                  specialist in the World&#13;
                                                                                                             town water sector investment. This Note reviews the early lessons.&#13;
                                                                                 Bank's Middle East and&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 North Africa Region.&#13;
                                               SECTOR                                                         In the late 1990s water and sanitation officials in        SENASA, responsible for providing water and&#13;
                                                                                                              Paraguay, together with the World Bank, began to        sanitation service to rural communities with fewer&#13;
                                                                                                              consider the most cost-effective way to expand water    than 10,000 inhabitants, has reached about&#13;
                                                     PRIVATE                                                  service coverage. The government first looked to its    37 percent of that population segment (or about&#13;
                                                                                                              national water and sewerage utility (Empresa de         18 percent of households nationwide). In the&#13;
                                                                                                              Servicios Sanitarios del Paraguay, or ESSAP), respon-   process it has created more than 1,000 water users&#13;
                                                                                                              sible for urban areas, and its rural water agency       associations, which assume responsibility for ser-&#13;
                                                            GROUP&#13;
                                                                                                              (DirecciónGeneraldeSaludAmbiental,orSENASA).            vice provision in their community. SENASA the-&#13;
                                                                                                                 The national utility offers piped water to less      oretically contributes only 40 percent of the cost&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 BANK                                         than 30 percent of households nationwide--only          of constructing systems in larger communities&#13;
                                                                                                              half those in its service area, defined as cities and   andabout82percentinsmallsettlements.Butthe&#13;
                                                                                                              towns with populations of more than 10,000.             actual subsidies it provides are far larger, since&#13;
                                                                                                              Constrained by heavy debt service obligations,          communities often fail to make agreed cash con-&#13;
                                                                     WORLD                                    ESSAP is unlikely to be able to serve as a vehicle for  tributions or to service their debt.&#13;
                                                                                                              expandingservicetoParaguay'sunconnectedperi-               SENASA, in considering the water users asso-&#13;
                                                                          THE                                 urban communities anytime soon.                         ciations as a vehicle for expanding service,&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
O U T P U T - B A S E D A I D I N W A T E R L E S S O N S I N I M P L E M E N T A T I O N F R O M A P I L O T I N P A R A G U A Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    recognized that many found it difficult to charge                                       Quality and scope of service. What service qual-&#13;
                                    tariffs recovering full costs. As a result, reliance                                    ity and characteristics would be required?&#13;
                                    on public financing remained high. Public sub-                                          Incentive structure and subsidy design. How&#13;
                                    sidies for rural water and sanitation systems have                                      could private providers be enticed to serve&#13;
                                    amounted to an estimated US$300­400 per con-                                            the targeted communities with a mandate for&#13;
                                    nection. At the current level of public financing,                                      universal or near-universal access? If public&#13;
                                    Paraguay would need more than 20 years to                                               subsidies were needed, how could they be&#13;
                                    reach 85 percent coverage in rural areas.                                               structured so as to minimize the cost to the&#13;
                                        Alongside the two public entities, small pri-                                       government and the community while maxi-&#13;
2&#13;
                                    vate providers known as aguateros supply water to                                       mizing the likelihood of sustainable service?&#13;
                                    about 500,000 people in periurban areas,                                                Bidding process and variable. How would the&#13;
                                    mainly in the greater metropolitan region of                                            bidding be structured, and what variable&#13;
                                    Asunción. Aguateros have constructed piped                                              would it be based on?&#13;
                                    water supply systems over the past 20 years with                                        Legal, regulatory, and contractual framework.&#13;
                                    no public financing. Indeed, many have not reg-                                         Given the water sector's legal structure, who&#13;
                                    istered as businesses, operating as part of                                             would have regulatory responsibility for tar-&#13;
                                    Paraguay's active informal sector. Paraguay's                                           iffs and service quality? How would that&#13;
                                    aguateros have an average age of about 12 years,                                        responsibility be reflected in contracts?&#13;
                                    while the oldest have been operating for more&#13;
                                    than 20. Their systems average around 300 con-                                    Quality and scope of service&#13;
                                    nections, but some have as many as 3,000.1                                        To meet the minimum requirements of safe, reli-&#13;
                                        Altogether, aguateros serve around 9 percent of                               able service, it was decided that the private opera-&#13;
                                    Paraguay'spopulation--orabout17percentofall&#13;
                                    Paraguayans with piped water supply. In some                                                 Minimum subsidy bidding in output-&#13;
                                    departments aguateros provide water for more                                        Box      based aid schemes&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      1&#13;
                                    people than the two public entities combined.&#13;
                                        A 2002 survey of 1,000 households served by                                              Over the past decade several Latin American governments&#13;
                                                                                                                                 have sought to induce private operators to make socially&#13;
                                    aguateros found that 90 percent were satisfied&#13;
                                                                                                                                 desirable--though not always financially viable--invest-&#13;
                                    with the service and 75 percent were unwilling&#13;
                                                                                                                                 ments in rural areas by offering one-time subsidies cover-&#13;
                                    to pay more for better service.2 The overall cus-&#13;
                                                                                                                                 ing part of the capital costs. The private operators recover&#13;
                                    tomer satisfaction with lower rates and a some-&#13;
                                                                                                                                 the rest of their costs through user tariffs. To minimize&#13;
                                    what lower level of service led to a conclusion                                              costs, governments use competitive bidding based on the&#13;
                                    that, subject to suitable groundwater condi-                                                 minimum subsidy offered. Chile pioneered this approach in&#13;
                                    tions, aguateros represented a viable alternative                                            telecommunications in 1994­95. Several low-income coun-&#13;
                                    for expanding service into periurban areas.                                                  tries (Colombia, Guatemala, Peru) have followed suit,&#13;
                                                                                                                                 extending the approach to such sectors as transport, rural&#13;
                                    The output-based aid pilot                                                                   electricity, and water and sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
                                    Given the constraints of the state water utility                                                 In parallel, development agencies such as the World&#13;
&#13;
                                    and the traditional water users association                                                  Bank began to explore ways to move from financing&#13;
                                                                                                                                 inputs (typically, physical assets) to financing outputs (serv-&#13;
                                    model, Paraguayan officials concluded that pri-&#13;
                                                                                                                                 ices provided or results achieved) to ensure the best use&#13;
                                    vate providers would be the best means of reach-&#13;
                                                                                                                                 of public funds while achieving development objectives.&#13;
                                    ing    unserved            communities                 and      rapidly&#13;
                                                                                                                                 They devised a subsidy approach--output-based aid--&#13;
                                    expanding rural coverage. SENASA agreed to&#13;
                                                                                                                                 using public funds to reimburse private operators for part&#13;
                                    implement a pilot output-based aid program to                                                of their investment after they demonstrate that they have&#13;
                                    attract aguateros and local construction compa-                                              delivered the service contracted for. The reimbursement&#13;
                                    nies to small towns, large villages, and periurban                                           method may range from cash paid per connection out of&#13;
                                    communities (box 1). The program was to be                                                   an offshore escrow account (as in Guatemala's rural elec-&#13;
                                    implemented in several phases so that lessons                                                trification program) to vouchers given to consumers for&#13;
                                    could be incorporated along the way.                                                         use as payment to private operators.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Still, several questions remained:&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
tors would be contracted to build water networks                                                  to the technical requirements and offered the low-&#13;
that included a borehole, a system for disinfection,                                              est connection fee would be declared the winner.&#13;
an elevated or pressurized ground storage tank,                                                   Onceselected,operatorscouldchargeusersforthe&#13;
and a distribution system with household connec-                                                  connection fee in installments at a defined interest&#13;
tions. Meters could be installed at the discretion of                                             rate. Operators would recover their costs from the&#13;
the operator unless a customer requested one.                                                     connectionsubsidy(paidbySENASA)andthecon-&#13;
Standards for water quality, pressure, and hours of                                               nectionchargeandtariff(bothpaidbyusers).Each&#13;
service would be set out in a contract between the                                                town would have the right to reject the winning bid&#13;
community and the operator. Perhaps most                                                          if it considered the connection fee too high.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                          3&#13;
important, the operator would be required to con-                                                     The lowest bid emerging from the first round&#13;
nectanyhouseholdwithinthedefinedservicearea                                                       of competition was extremely competitive, com-&#13;
that requested a connection and paid the fee.                                                     mitting the winning consortium--two construc-&#13;
                                                                                                  tion companies and an aguatero--to build systems&#13;
Incentive structure and subsidy design                                                            in all four towns at US$200­217 per connection&#13;
Inthefirstphaseofthepilotitwasdeterminedthat                                                      (table 1). The commitment from the towns&#13;
a per-connection subsidy would be needed to                                                       ranged from US$50 to US$67 per connection. To&#13;
attract operators to the four participating com-                                                  make it easier for poor residents to pay, the win-&#13;
munities. To assure SENASA that the subsidy costs                                                 ning consortium hired them during construction&#13;
would be less than the traditional cost to the state                                              (mostly to dig pipe trenches), paying them with&#13;
of rural water supply systems, the subsidy was fixed                                              cash and with vouchers to reduce their connec-&#13;
at US$150 for each connection up to the maxi-                                                     tion fee. In addition, many residents opted to pay&#13;
mum number of connections set for each com-                                                       the connection fee in installments at a "social"&#13;
munity'sservicearea.Thissubsidywaslessthanthe                                                     interest rate not to exceed 24 percent a year (with&#13;
current theoretical one of about US$200 per con-                                                  payments in guaraníes).&#13;
nection and far less than the actual subsidies that                                                   Thesuccessofthefirstroundofbiddingshowed&#13;
SENASA paid in some communities. Tariffs for                                                      SENASA that there would be enough competition&#13;
metered and unmetered connections were set in                                                     for the right to build the systems. That allowed the&#13;
agreement with the communities and incorpo-                                                       bidding in the second phase to be structured so&#13;
rated into the bidding documents.                                                                 that towns would not have to assume the risk, with&#13;
                                                                                                  the bidding variable changed from the connection&#13;
Bidding process and variable                                                                      charge paid by users to the connection subsidy.&#13;
Private operators would be invited to bid on the fee                                              Connection charges as well as tariffs were negoti-&#13;
they would charge users up front to connect to                                                    atedbySENASAandthewaterusersassociationfor&#13;
their system. The bidder that was both responsive                                                 the participating towns and incorporated into the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Table     The bidding process&#13;
&#13;
1                                                  Phase 1                                                         Phase 2&#13;
            Fixed components                       Subsidy to private operator of US$150                           Per-connection charge of US$80 for households and&#13;
                                                   per connection                                                  US$112 for businesses and institutions&#13;
                                                   Tariffs paid by users                                           Tariffs paid by users&#13;
            Bidding variable                       Connection charge to users                                      Connection subsidy from the government&#13;
            Winning bid                            US$200­217 per connection                                       To be determined&#13;
            Party assuming risk of&#13;
            uncompetitive bid                      Community                                                       Government&#13;
            Preliminary design provided&#13;
            in bidding documents?                  Noa                                                             Yesb&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
a. Bidding documents specified simple borehole, disinfection, storage, and single-settlement distribution system.&#13;
b. Preliminary design specified surface water intake, filtration and disinfection systems, elevated and ground storage tanks, and multisettlement distribution system.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
O U T P U T - B A S E D A I D I N W A T E R L E S S O N S I N I M P L E M E N T A T I O N F R O M A P I L O T I N P A R A G U A Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
bidding process. The maximum connection sub-                            pletes components of the system. Given the&#13;
sidy that bidders could request was capped to pre-                      difficulties small construction companies&#13;
vent excessive costs to the state.                                      face in mobilizing investment capital, this&#13;
                                                                        staggered release of payments should allow&#13;
Legal and regulatory framework                                          greater competition for contracts.                                viewpoint&#13;
Paraguay's water sector law of 2000 assigns the                         SENASA and the water users association. This con-&#13;
right to operate water supply systems to the exec-                      tract sets out SENASA's agreement to provide a&#13;
utive branch of government, which may delegate                          subsidy for system construction once the water&#13;
                                                                                                                                          is an open forum to&#13;
it to municipalities or departmental governments.                       users association has signed the concession&#13;
                                                                                                                                          encourage dissemination of&#13;
Service provision by the private sector and water                       contract with the operator.&#13;
                                                                                                                                          public policy innovations for&#13;
users associations is regulated through 10-year                         Operator and the water users association. This simple&#13;
                                                                                                                                          private sector­led and&#13;
permits in systems of less than 2,000 connections                       concession contract defines the service area and&#13;
                                                                                                                                          market-based solutions for&#13;
(around 10,000 people) and concessions of up to                         sets coverage targets. It also provides the opera-&#13;
                                                                                                                                          development. The views&#13;
30 years in larger systems. Permits can be awarded                      torwithexclusivityinthisarea,defineswaterand&#13;
                                                                                                                                          published are those of the&#13;
through simple bidding procedures, while con-                           service quality standards and penalties for non-                  authors and should not be&#13;
cessions require national (or international) com-                       compliance, provides adjustment formulas for                      attributed to the World&#13;
petitive bidding.                                                       tariffsandfees,andestablishescompensationfor                      Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
    Regulations adopted in October 2002 match                           early termination of the contract.                                organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
&#13;
tariffs to different service levels to allow for differ-                To ensure that the water users associations                       the conclusions represent&#13;
&#13;
ences in the characteristics of service providers. At             understand their obligations as signatories to                          official policy of the World&#13;
&#13;
the minimum service level the regulations require                 the two contracts, a local institute has been pro-                      Bank or of its Executive&#13;
&#13;
that water meet chemical and bacteriological                      viding training in contract administration.                             Directors or the countries&#13;
&#13;
safety standards. Failure to comply with the stan-                                                                                        they represent.&#13;
&#13;
dards can trigger the suspension of a permit in                   Results&#13;
addition to penalties.                                            The winning bidder in the first phase, awarded its                      To order additional copies&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  contract in August 2002, has nearly completed                           contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
&#13;
Contractual arrangements                                          three of the four systems and is already supplying                      managing editor,&#13;
&#13;
Under the terms of the pilot and the water sector                 water. But it never started the fourth system                           Room I9-009,&#13;
&#13;
law, communities (through the water users asso-                   because of a legal dispute between the community                        The World Bank,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                          1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
ciations) contract private operators to build and                 and an aguatero holding an operating permit for&#13;
                                                                                                                                          Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
operate water supply systems in their area under                  part of the service area. This community has been&#13;
10-year permits. SENASA manages the construc-                     replaced with another. The response from the&#13;
                                                                                                                                          Telephone:&#13;
tion phase and acts as an arbitrator between the                  communities that have received service has been&#13;
                                                                                                                                          001 202 458 7281&#13;
community and the operator during the opera-                      overwhelmingly positive thanks to the rapid&#13;
                                                                                                                                          Fax:&#13;
tion phase. Supporting this structure is a triangle               progressfromconceptiontoconstruction,allwith-&#13;
                                                                                                                                          001 202 522 3480&#13;
of mutual obligations set out in contracts govern-                out up-front cash contributions from the commu-&#13;
                                                                                                                                          Email:&#13;
ing the relationships between the three parties:                  nities. In the second phase bids for an integrated&#13;
                                                                                                                                          ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
    SENASA and the operator. This contract, based                 system supplying three towns were received in late&#13;
    on the standard World Bank bidding docu-                      February 2004 and are now being evaluated.&#13;
                                                                                                                                          Produced by Grammarians,&#13;
    ment for small works, governs the construc-                                                                                           Inc.&#13;
    tion phase (defining the technical standards,&#13;
    supervision, subsidy, guarantees, and the                     Notes                                                                   Printed on recycled paper&#13;
    like). In the first phase of the pilot all subsidy                  1. Consorcio Asociación Euroestudios-Hidrocontrol,&#13;
&#13;
    payments (apart from an advance) were with-                   "Revisión de la Estrategia de SENASA, Informe Final"&#13;
&#13;
    held until the operator had demonstrated                      (SENASA, Asunción, Paraguay, 2001).&#13;
&#13;
    that it had successfully provided the connec-                       2. The survey was designed with a 95 percent confi-&#13;
&#13;
    tions, forcing the private sector to mobilize                 dence interval and 3 percent margin of error.&#13;
&#13;
    most of the construction financing. In the&#13;
    second phase shares of the total subsidy pay-&#13;
    ment will be released as the operator com-&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     T h i s N o t e i s a v a i l a b l e o n l i n e :&#13;
                                                                                  h t t p : / / r r u . w o r l d b a n k . o r g / V i e w p o i n t / i n d e x . a s p&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5137060">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/04/5137060/output-based-aid-water
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/04/5137060/output-based-aid-water</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/04/5137060/output-based-aid-water</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/09/20/000090341_20040920134544/Rendered/INDEX/299910PAPER0VP02701water1paraguay.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/09/20/000090341_20040920134544/Rendered/PDF/299910PAPER0VP02701water1paraguay.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2004-04-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2004-09-20T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Output-based aid in water
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Paraguay's aguateros-small private
            water companies-form an important part of the water sector,
            serving about 9 percent of the total population (or about 17
            percent of those with piped water supply). But until
            recently they operated only in urban areas, where water
            resources are abundant and they could choose customers based
            on their ability to pay the full costs of providing service.
            A new World Bank-funded initiative seeks to attract
            aguateros and construction firms active in the water sector
            to unserved rural areas and small towns by providing an
            outputbased aid subsidy, awarded through competitive
            bidding. The initiative is the first attempt anywhere to
            apply this approach to rural and smalltown water sector
            investment. This Note reviews the early lessons.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Output-based aid in water
        </docna>
        <display_title>Output-based aid in water</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2004/04/5137060/output-based-aid-water</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Conservation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Dress, Franz</author>
            <author>Schwartz, Jordan</author>
            <author>Bakalian, Alexander</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20040920134544</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 270</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            bidding, communities, construction,
            covering, debt, groundwater, income, Latin American, Middle
            East, operators, permits, pipe, piped water, pressure,
            PRIVATE SECTOR, PUBLIC POLICY, quality standards, regulatory
            framework, rural communities, rural water, rural water
            supply, rural water supply systems, sanitation, sanitation
            systems, service area, service providers, service provision,
            storage tanks, surface water, technical standards, trenches,
            water companies, water intake, water quality, water
            resources, water sector, water supply, water supply systems
        </keywd>
        <owner>KM and Outreach-IFC (FPDKM)</owner>
        <repnb>29991</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Allocation and Bulk Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Network</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal and Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Allocation and Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>