<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                      GUATEMALA&#13;
&#13;
                           FinancialSector Adjustment Loan&#13;
                                    (Loan 7130-GU)&#13;
               Release of the Second Tranche    - Waiver of  One Condition&#13;
                               Tranche Release Document&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.      The US$l50 million Financial Sector Adjustment Loan (FSAL)was approved by&#13;
the Board on June 25, 2002. The loan was declared effective on December 18, 2002 and&#13;
the first tranche was disbursed shortly thereafter. The closing date o f this loan has been&#13;
extended to December 31, 2005. This loan was designed to assist the Guatemalan&#13;
Government to implement its Financial Sector Reform Program, aimed at bringingabout&#13;
a stronger and better functioning banking sector, able to withstand external shocks and to&#13;
increase prudent lending to the private sector, opening access to groups and enterprises&#13;
today largely excluded from bank financing (micro, rural and small and medium&#13;
enterprise financing).  The Bank loan would finance the needs o f the Government's&#13;
economic program related to the strengthening o f the financial sector.&#13;
&#13;
2.      The remainder of this memorandum summarizes progress in implementing the&#13;
reform Program, and reports on actions taken by the Guatemalan Government to meet&#13;
specific conditions for the release o f the Second Tranche o f the FSAL. Waiver for the&#13;
condition concerning the capitalization o f the Central Bank, as contained inparagraph 2&#13;
o f Schedule 3 o f the Loan Agreement, i s sought on the grounds that said condition has&#13;
been partially met as detailed in paragraphs 2land 22 o f this report. Based on the&#13;
assessment that the Ministry o f Finance, the Central Bank and the Superintendency o f&#13;
Bankshave met all other Second Tranche conditions, this memorandumrecommends that&#13;
a waiver be granted with respect to the pending condition and that the Second Tranche&#13;
(US$50 million) be released.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I. KEYOBJECTIVESOFTHE GOVERNMENT'SFINANCIAL SECTOR&#13;
REFORMPROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
3.      The broader policy objective of this proposed loan i s to assist the Guatemalan&#13;
Government to implement its Financial Sector Reform Program, aimed at bringing about&#13;
a stronger and better functioning banking sector, able to withstand external shocks and to&#13;
increase prudent lending to the private sector, opening access to groups and enterprises&#13;
that have been largely excluded from bank financing (micro, rural and SME financing).&#13;
The Bank loan helps finance the needs of the Government's economic programrelated to&#13;
the strengthening of the financial sector.&#13;
&#13;
4.     Based on the results of the FSAP (Financial Sector Assessment Program)&#13;
conducted during the second half of 2000, the Guatemalan authorities, with assistance&#13;
from the Bank (as part of post-FSAP technical assistance provided by Bank staff), the&#13;
IMFandthe IDB,embarked on afinancial sector reformprogramaimedat addressingthe&#13;
sector's problems ina comprehensive manner. The reform programinvolves:&#13;
&#13;
    (A) Financial Sector Legal/Regulatory Reforms: The program includes: (i)       reform&#13;
        of the monetary policy legal framework for the conduct of monetary and&#13;
        financial policy; (ii) of the financial sector legal framework aimed at:&#13;
                              reform&#13;
        strengthening the regulation of financial groups and creating an orderly market&#13;
        exit mechanism, enhancing credit risk management, and increasing access to&#13;
        financing; (iii)reform of bank supervision legal framework aimed at&#13;
        strengthening the autonomy of the supervisory authorities, enhancing their legal&#13;
        and institutional capacity to supervise financial groups, and rising banking sector&#13;
        regulation towards international standards; (iv) stronger legislation to prevent&#13;
        money laundering so as to reduce illegal activities and comply with international&#13;
        norms; and (v) presentation to Congress of new legislation on insurance, secured&#13;
        transactions, and non-bank financial intermediaries, with the objective of&#13;
        expanding credit access.&#13;
&#13;
   (B) Bank Regularization/ConsolidationProgram: This part of the programconsists&#13;
        o f (i)the establishment of a mechanism to handle consolidation and&#13;
        recapitalization of banks; (ii) regularization or liquidation of several insolvent&#13;
        banks; and (iii)consolidation of the banking system through mergers and&#13;
        acquisitions.&#13;
&#13;
   (C) Strengthening of the Superintendency of Banks (SB) and the Central Bank&#13;
        (BANGUAT). This part of the reform program consist of securing technical&#13;
        assistance to help both institutions to implement the program of legal and&#13;
        regulatory reforms andthe bank regularizatiodconsolidation program.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
11.      PROGRESS IN IMPLEMENTING THE GOVERNMENT'S FINANCIAL&#13;
SECTOR REFORMPROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
5.       The Guatemalan Government has made major advances in the implementationof&#13;
its financial sector reform program, including measures implemented prior to Board&#13;
Presentation incompliance with the FirstTranche Releaseof the loan.&#13;
&#13;
(A)LegalandRegulatoryReformsto Strengthenthe FinancialSector&#13;
&#13;
6.      Between October 2001 and April 2002, prior to Board presentation of loan,&#13;
Congress approved a package of five financial sector laws. These laws were prepared&#13;
with technical advice from the Bank, IDB and IMF. The new laws have given Guatemala&#13;
a state of the art financial sector legal framework. Four of the laws were enacted on June&#13;
1,2002.&#13;
&#13;
7.      CentralBank Law. This Law addressesmost of the shortcomings of the previous&#13;
legislation, including the following:&#13;
&#13;
        Clear statement of objectives. It establishes that the fundamental objective of the&#13;
        central bank i s to achieve and maintain price stability and redefines the&#13;
        instruments of monetary policy as a function of this objective (open market&#13;
        operations, exchange operations and lender of last resort--LOLR--operations).&#13;
&#13;
        Greater autonomy. The law reaffirms the role of the Monetary Board (MB) to&#13;
        determine the monetary, credit and exchange rate policy of Guatemala, but&#13;
        delegate to BANGUAT the capacity to implement such policies through an&#13;
        Implementation Committee.         It also establishes that the President and Vice-&#13;
        president of BANGUATwould be nominatedby the President of the Republic for&#13;
        a period of four years and stipulates the basic qualifications for these positions&#13;
        andthe causes for their removal.&#13;
&#13;
        Greaterfinancial au$onomy. The law establishes that the State will guarantee the&#13;
        maintenance over time of BANGUAT's capital to strengthen its capacity to&#13;
        implement monetary policy. It also establishes that the central bank will transfer&#13;
        its eventual surpluses to the Treasury, after making the reserve provisions&#13;
        established by law, and that the Ministry of Finance (MOF) will absorb the&#13;
        accumulated losses sufferedby BANGUATas a result of Government policies.&#13;
&#13;
        Greater transparency and accountability.          The law includes a number of&#13;
       provisions concerning transparency and accountability, including: (i)  the financial&#13;
       statements of BANGUAT have to comply with internationally accepted norms&#13;
       and principles, and be audited by external auditors; (ii)the President of&#13;
       BANGUAT will appear before Congress twice a year to give account of the&#13;
       results of the monetary, exchange rate, and credit policies; and (iii) BANGUAT&#13;
       will periodically publish information of its activities, general balance and&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       financial statements, as well as summaries of the debates of the MB with respect&#13;
       to the determination of monetary, exchange rate and credit policies.&#13;
&#13;
       Limited Lender of Last Resort (LOLR) assistance. The new law specifies that&#13;
       BANGUAT will be able to provide short term credit to banks inthe system solely&#13;
       to cover temporary liquidity deficiencies up to 50 percent of the bank's&#13;
       computable equity, at an interest rate no lower than the average lending rate&#13;
       applied by the petitioner bank. The law prohibits BANGUAT from engaging in&#13;
       other activities including lendingor providing guarantees to the State.&#13;
&#13;
8.     Monetary Law. This Law modernizes the monetary legislation, particularly inthe&#13;
area of exchange rate policy. The new law guarantees the free convertibility of the&#13;
currency, and the free movement of capital.&#13;
&#13;
9.    Banking and Financial GroupsLaw. This law has the following main features:&#13;
&#13;
      Improved bank licensing provisions. The law establishes the minimum entry&#13;
       requirements for new banks and provides the SB with the authority to deny the&#13;
      participation of promoters, shareholders or administrators who have any&#13;
      impediment under the law. It also establishes the prohibition that entities not&#13;
       subject to SB supervision mobilize resources from the public, except savings and&#13;
      loan cooperatives which are ruledby specific laws.&#13;
&#13;
       Consolidated supervision and regulation of financial groups, including ofS-shore&#13;
      banking.      The law includes norms for the constitution, organization and&#13;
      functioning of financial groups.     It gives the SB the faculty to presume the&#13;
      existence of a financial group if there are common interests among its members&#13;
      and empowers it to carry out consolidated supervision of all the enterprises of a&#13;
      financial group to evaluate and control the risks faced by the group as a whole.&#13;
      The law requires the elaboration and presentation of consolidated financial&#13;
      statements by the financial groups and establishes lendinglimits to related parties.&#13;
&#13;
      Equal treatment of ofS-shore banks. The law establishes the treatment given to&#13;
      off-shore entities (which are licensed in a foreign country but have their assets&#13;
      and liabilities in Guatemala) that form part of a financial group, in order to&#13;
      measure the risks of the group. Off-shore entities have to obtain authorization to&#13;
      operate within six months of the effectiveness of the law.&#13;
&#13;
      Improved bank regulatory framework and prudential rules. The law establishes&#13;
      the minimum capital of banks and financial groups as 10 percent of the risk-&#13;
      weighted assets, with the weights to be applied established by regulation, and&#13;
      requires the adoption of regularization plans in cases of capital deficiencies. The&#13;
      law also mandates the application of accounting norms issued by the MB based&#13;
      on generally accepted accounting principles and international accounting norms.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Improved governance and transparency of banking institutions.             The law&#13;
       establishes rights and duties of the banks' and groups' management councils and&#13;
       the maintenance of systems of internal controls. It empowers the SB to determine&#13;
       minimumrequirements and scope of the external audit and provides disclosure of&#13;
       information guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
       Limited deposit insurance scheme. The law creates a deposit insurance fund&#13;
       (Fondo de Proteccidn al Ahorro, FOPA) administered by BANGUAT, to&#13;
       guarantee the safety of bank deposits, up to 420,000 (US$2,600) per individualor&#13;
       entity in a local bank or subsidiary of a foreign bank. Deposits in off-shore&#13;
       entities are not guaranteed. It is constituted by: quotas paid by participating&#13;
       banks, return on investments of the fund, proceeds from liquidation of banks and&#13;
       sale of adjudicated assets, and Government contributions.&#13;
&#13;
       EfJicient bank resolution mechanism. The law establishes mechanisms for bank&#13;
       restructuring and market exit of insolvent institutions.         These go from a&#13;
       regularization plan (in case of capital deficiency) proposed by the bank and&#13;
       approved by the SB, to suspension of operations, exclusion of assets and&#13;
       liabilities, and liquidation.&#13;
&#13;
10.   Money Laundering Law.          This law makes money laundering a crime and&#13;
provides for appropriate sanctions.     It also creates a Specific Unit Against Money&#13;
Launderingwithin the SB ("Intendencia de Verificaci6n Especial").&#13;
&#13;
11.   Bank SupervisionLaw. This law has the following main features:&#13;
&#13;
      Enhanced supervisory and sanctioning power. The law specifies the functions of&#13;
      the SB, which include, among others, to: enforce the laws and regulations;&#13;
      supervise the financial entities to ensure that they maintain adequate liquidity and&#13;
      solvency; provide instructions to overcome deficiencies; impose sanctions; have&#13;
      access to all relevant information; carry out its supervision and inspection on a&#13;
      consolidated basis; evaluate the policies, procedures, norms and systems of the&#13;
      entities; and request from the MB the liquidation of failed entities.&#13;
&#13;
      Greater autonomy. The law provides for the Superintendent to be nominated by&#13;
      the President of the Republic for a four year term.         It also establishes the&#13;
      eligibility requirements and impediments for exercising the position and the&#13;
      causes for his removal.&#13;
&#13;
      Legal protection of SB stafl      The law establishes that the SB will provide a&#13;
      mechanism to finance the legal expenses for the defense of its functionaries in&#13;
      case of legal actions against them derived from the exercise of their functions, and&#13;
      provides personal immunity to the Superintendent of Banks and authorities of the&#13;
      institution.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                              6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(B)Bank Regularization/ConsolidationProgram&#13;
&#13;
 12.     Prior to loan approval, the authorities intervened and suspended the equity and&#13;
administrative rights of the shareholders of three small failed banks: Promotor,&#13;
Metropolitan0 and Empresarial, and two financieras: Financiera Agrocomercial and&#13;
Financiera Metropolitana.       The authorities fully reimbursed the depositors of the&#13;
intervened banks through a contingency credit line extended by BANGUAT. All three&#13;
banks are under liquidation procedures.&#13;
&#13;
 13.     Creation of the Bank Capitalization Fund. The new banking legislation limits&#13;
the ability of BANGUAT to provide funds to capitalize, restructure or close distressed&#13;
banks. Instead, it establishes a bank resolutionmechanism that involves the exclusionof&#13;
assets and liabilities of a failed bank, and their transfer to other institutions. A solvent&#13;
bank that acquires the liabilities (deposits) may find that it needs additional capital to&#13;
meet the regulatory capital standards. A Bank Capitalization Fund (FCB) has been&#13;
created to provide these banks with capital in the form of subordinated loans (tier-two&#13;
capital). The FCB was created as a trust fund managed by BANGUAT, in the same law&#13;
that approved the Bank FSAL.&#13;
&#13;
(C)Strengtheningof the SB and BANGUAT&#13;
&#13;
14.     Together with the FSAL, the Board approved a US$5.0 million technical&#13;
assistance loan (FSTAL) to assist BANGUAT and the SB to implement the new financial&#13;
legislation, and prepare future legal reforms.&#13;
&#13;
111.    ACTIONS TAKEN TO FULFILL THE SECOND TRANCHE RELEASE&#13;
CONDITIONS&#13;
&#13;
A.      SatisfactoryProgressincarryingout the Program&#13;
&#13;
      LoanAgreement, Article 11, Section2.02 (d) (i): Bank to be satisfied, basedon&#13;
      evidence satisfactory to the Bank, with the progress achieved in the carrying&#13;
      out of the Program.&#13;
&#13;
15.     This conditionhas been met. A letter of Sector Development Policy, signed by&#13;
the Minister of Finance dated May 20, 2002, describes the Program supported by Loan&#13;
7130-GU.      The Bank i s satisfied that the Borrower has complied with these&#13;
commitments, which include: the passage of key financial laws; the issuingof regulations&#13;
to   implement      these   laws;   and    the   initial  implementation       of  a  bank&#13;
regularizationkonsolidation program.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                              7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 B.      Macroeconomic Performance&#13;
&#13;
        Loan Agreement, Article 11,Section 2.02 (d) (ii):Bank to be satisfied, based on&#13;
        evidence satisfactory to the Bank, that the macroeconomic policy framework is&#13;
        satisfactory.&#13;
&#13;
 16.     This condition has been met.         The last Stand-By Arrangement (SBA) of&#13;
 Guatemala with the IMF (for SDR84 million), covered the period June 18, 2003, to&#13;
March 15, 2004. The program supported by the agreement was designed to consolidate&#13;
 the macroeconomic stability and accommodate additional government spending related to&#13;
the Peace Accord, including an increase in expending in social services, while increasing&#13;
international reserves and further lowering inflation.       The program was completed&#13;
 successfully. Although Guatemala does not have at the moment a program with the IMF,&#13;
there has been progress toward agreement on an economic program that could be&#13;
 supported by a new SBA. The new SBA could be presented to the Board in early&#13;
December and would support the authorities' program to maintain macroeconomic&#13;
 stability, keep the public debt low, while providing for higher social and investment&#13;
spending, continue financial sector reforms, and foster strong and sustainable economic&#13;
growth.&#13;
&#13;
 17.     The new administration that took office in January 2004, faced a deteriorating&#13;
fiscal situation, aggravated by the elimination of the tax on sales of assets (IEMA), which&#13;
had been declared unconstitutional in December 2003. The new Government has acted&#13;
swiftly to address the fiscal situation.    It instituted budgetary cuts except for social&#13;
expenditures, and secured Congressional support for a short-term tax package which was&#13;
approved in June 2004. The tax package incorporates changes to the corporate income&#13;
tax, a 6 to 8 percent tax on alcoholic drinks, an extraordinary and temporary tax in&#13;
support of the Pace Agreement; and the authorization for a 45.3 billion (US$671 million)&#13;
treasury bond issue. Two major objectives of the tax reform are to keep the budget&#13;
deficit within the 2 percent of GDP target, and increase the tax ratio to 12 percent of&#13;
GDP, as required by the Peace Agreement.           In mid-August 2004, the Government&#13;
announced an Economic Reactivation Plan that includes actions to: (i)           improve the&#13;
climate for business and exports; (ii) set out a series of publidprivate investment projects&#13;
in infrastructure, tourism, and construction; and (iii)increase investment in poor&#13;
communities on health, education, basic services andjob creation.&#13;
&#13;
18.      The Central Bank estimates a real GDP growth rate of 2.6 percent in 2004, up&#13;
from 2.1 percent in 2003.      This growth rate is slightly higher than the 2.4 percent&#13;
population growth.    Inflation for 2004 i s estimated at 7 percent, compared with 5.8&#13;
percent in 2003. Projections for 2005 are for a real GDP growth of 3.2 percent, with&#13;
inflation of about 5 percent. Guatemala's financial sector has strengthened substantially&#13;
since 2000, due to improvements in prudential regulatory framework and stepped-up&#13;
onsite inspections. As of end-April 2004, the risk-weighted capital adequacy was well&#13;
above the regulatory level of 10percent (14.8 percent for onshore banks and 12.8 percent&#13;
for offshore banks). The situation of the banks i s still fragile due to the low level of&#13;
provisions and excessive amount of related lending. However, the authorities have made&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
progress in the licensing, supervision and registration of financial conglomerates,&#13;
including offshore banks which are now required to be part of licensed conglomerates in&#13;
 order to operate. All these positive outcomes are linked to actions supported by the&#13;
FSAL.&#13;
&#13;
 C.     Other Actions&#13;
&#13;
      Loan Agreement, Article 11, Section 2.02 (d) (iii):     Bank to be satisfied, based&#13;
       on evidence satisfactory to the Bank, that the actions described in Schedule 3&#13;
      of the Loan Agreement have beentaken inform and substance satisfactory to&#13;
      the Bank:&#13;
&#13;
               Schedule 3, Part (1)of the LoanAgreement: Enactment of regulations&#13;
               (reglamentos)of BANGUAT's organic law (Ley Orghnicadel Banco de&#13;
               Guatemala), dated June 2,2002, which regulations should address the&#13;
               following topics: (i)governance of BANGUAT; and (ii)                reserve&#13;
               requirement rules.&#13;
&#13;
 19.    This condition has been met. Regulations issued addressing the governance of&#13;
BANGUAT include the following resolutions: (i)       JM-189-2002 "Determination of the&#13;
periodicity of the ordinary sessions of the Monetary Board";            (ii)JM-192-2002&#13;
"Designation of the authorities of BANGUAT to integrate the Execution Committee and&#13;
designation of technical advisors"; (iii)   JM-193-2002 "Regulation of the Execution&#13;
Committee"; and (iv) JM-305-2002 "Administrative Structure of BANGUAT".&#13;
&#13;
20.     The regulationissued addressing reserve requirement rules is ResolutionJM-177-&#13;
2002 "Regulation of Bank Reserve Requirement" and its modification: Resolution JM-&#13;
244-2002.&#13;
&#13;
               Schedule 3, Part (2) of the Loan Agreement: Capitalization of&#13;
               BANGUAT has been completed though the issuing of bonds to settle&#13;
               pastfiscal losses.&#13;
&#13;
21.     This condition has been partially met. Article 83 of the Central Bank Law&#13;
establishes that the equity of BANGUAT will be restored through the issuing of a 100&#13;
year zero-coupon bond to settle its fiscal losses due to the cost of the monetary policies&#13;
up to end 2001. As requiredby the Law, an audit was conducted which determined that&#13;
the debt to BANGUAT amounted to Q16,873 million. The MB through resolution JM-&#13;
287-2002 issued a favorable opinion to the issuing of the bond to settle this debt, and the&#13;
MOF requested Congressional authority to issue the bond. Congress refused to approve&#13;
such bond, even if it did not involve any real financial cost to the Govemment. The new&#13;
Government intends to re-introduce the bill to the new Congress which, they argue, i s&#13;
more inclined to approve the issuing of the bond. However, there i s no definite time&#13;
frame for this.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22.     We consider this condition as partially met because the expected effect of the&#13;
recognition of the old debt to BANGUAT has already taken place. On this basis, the&#13;
Board i s requested to waive this condition. The issuing of the long term bond was an&#13;
accounting device to avoid showing that BANGUAThad a negative capital. With the recognition&#13;
of the debt, the accounts of BANGUAT have ceased to show the "old debt" as accumulated&#13;
losses. They show instead a (differed) long-term asset (debt to be paid by the MOF). The most&#13;
important issue i s that the new losses after-2002be compensated with performing bonds, which i s&#13;
a condition for thirdtranche disbursement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Schedule 3, Part (3) of the Loan Agreement: Enactment of new&#13;
                 regulations (reglamentos)to strengthen the financial paymentssystem,&#13;
                 which regulations shall include a clear definition of BANGUAT's&#13;
                 responsibilities, risk managementrules, and enhancedefficiency.&#13;
&#13;
23.     This condition has been met. BANGUAT through Management Agreement 6-&#13;
2002 of August 2, 2002, created the Payments System Committee, in charge of the&#13;
coordination and follow up of the implementation of the of the project for the&#13;
Modernization of the National Payments System, Resolution JM-303-2002 approved the&#13;
restructuring of BANGUAT, including, among others, the creation of the Payments&#13;
System Section. Resolution JM-51-2003 of April 23, 2003, approved the regulation of&#13;
the Chamber of Bank Compensation within BANGUAT, which includes, as an annex, the&#13;
Instructions for the Standardization of Checks inthe NationalBanking System.&#13;
&#13;
                Schedule 3, Part (4) of the Loan Agreement: Enactment of regulations&#13;
                 (reglamentos) of the Borrower's banking law (Ley de Bancos y Grupos&#13;
                Financieros, dated June 2, 2002), which regulations should&#13;
                comprehensively cover the following topics: (i)             entry rules; (ii)&#13;
                minimumrisk management arrangements and governance principles&#13;
                to be adopted by banks; (iii) adequacy, loan classification and&#13;
                                                   capital&#13;
                provisioning, and remaining prudential rules; (iv) accounting norms,&#13;
                including consolidation rules following international standards; (v)&#13;
                exit mechanisms including the procedures related to FOPA; and (vi)&#13;
                sanction rules.&#13;
&#13;
24.    This condition has beenmet.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       (i)      Rulesfor entry of new institutions in the banking system: Resolution JM-&#13;
                185-2002, "Regulation for the authorization, constitution, and merger of&#13;
                national private banks and the establishment of branches of foreign banks''&#13;
                was replaced by Resolution JM-78-2003, "Regulation for the Constitution&#13;
                of National Private Banks and the Establishment of Branches of Foreign&#13;
                Banks", and Resolution JM-90-2003, "Regulation for the Authorization of&#13;
                Merger of Banking Entities, the Acquisition of Shares of one Banking&#13;
                Entity by Another of Similar Nature and the Cession of a Substantial&#13;
                Share of the BaIance of a Banking Entity".&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                          10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Minimum risk managementarrangements and governanceprinciples to be&#13;
            adopted by banks: Circular No. 1216-2003 of April 20, 2003, contains the&#13;
            "Dispositions for the Verification of Policies and Risk Committees".&#13;
            Resolution JM-141-2003, "Regulation for the Administration of Credit&#13;
            Risk", which includes minimumnorms for the credit process.&#13;
&#13;
             Capital adequacy, loan classijication and provisioning, and remaining&#13;
            prudential rules:   Resolutions issued: (i) JM-46-2004, "Regulation for the&#13;
            determination of the minimum equity required for the exposure to the risks&#13;
            applicable to banks and financial institutions".             JM-182-2002,&#13;
            "Regulation for financial operations with related persons or persons that&#13;
            are part of a risk unit". JM-183-2002, "Regulation for the valuation of&#13;
            credit assets and norms to determine and classify those of doubtful&#13;
            recovery" which was replaced by JM-141-2003, "Regulation for the&#13;
            Administration of Credit Risk" and includes norms for the valuation of&#13;
            credit assets and the minimum information of debtors.          JM-54-2004,&#13;
            "Regulation about the capital adequacy for off-shore entities, stock&#13;
            exchanges, enterprises specialized in financial services, warehouses, and&#13;
            foreign exchange offices, which are part of a financial group".&#13;
&#13;
            Accounting noms, including consolidation rules following international&#13;
            standards. Norm for the Consolidation of Financial Statements was&#13;
            approved by the SB inAgreement 13-2004.&#13;
&#13;
            Exit mechanisms, including theprocedures related to FOPA. Resolutions&#13;
            issued: JM-187-2002, "Dispositions and Regulations for the Fondo Para la&#13;
            Protecci6n del Ahorro FOPA"; and JM-223-2002,         "  Regulation of the&#13;
            Junta de Exclusi6nde Activos y Pasivos".&#13;
&#13;
            Sanctions Noms: Resolutions issued: JM-186-2002, "Regulation for the&#13;
            application of the sanctions contemplated inArt. 99 of Decree No.19-2002&#13;
            of the Congress of the Republic; Law of Banks and Financial Groups";&#13;
            and Agreement of the SB No.43-2002, "Sanctions Regime for obliged&#13;
            persons defined inthe Law Against Money Laundering".&#13;
&#13;
           Schedule 3, Part (5) of the LoanAgreement: Evidencethat FOPA: (i)&#13;
           i s fully operational and premiums are being paid by banks; and (ii)&#13;
           has adequate funding to reimburse depositors of banks under&#13;
           liquidation.&#13;
&#13;
25.  This conditionhas beenmet.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   (i)  FOPA isfully operational and premiums are being paid by banks Resolution&#13;
        issued JM-187-2002, "Regulations for the Fondo Para la Protecci6n del&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        Ahorro". BANGUAThas submitted to the Bank a certification indicating that&#13;
        as of October 26, 2004, all the banks in the system are paying their monthly&#13;
        premiums to FOPA.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   (ii) FOPA has adequatefunds to reimburse depositors of banks under liquidation:&#13;
        As of May 31, 2004, the equity of FOPA amounted to 41,127.2 million, of&#13;
        which 4597.0 million are in US dollars (US75.5 million), from the proceeds&#13;
        of the first tranche of the Financial Sector Adjustment Loan.&#13;
&#13;
            Schedule 3, Part (6) of the Loan Agreement: Enactment of regulations&#13;
            (reglamentos) of the Borrower's banking supervision law (Ley de&#13;
            Supervision Financiera, dated June 2, 2002, which regulations should&#13;
            address the following topics: (i)    minimum requirements for external&#13;
            audits; and (ii) SBlabor relationsframework.&#13;
&#13;
26.  This condition hasbeen met.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     (i)    Minimum requirement for external audit: The minimum requirement was&#13;
            issued with Agreement No. 56-2002 of the SB "Contracting and scope of&#13;
            the external audits" and resolutions: JM-26-2003, "Regulation for the&#13;
            registration of external auditors"      and JM-26-2003, "Regulation of&#13;
            minimumrequirements that have to be incorporatedin the contracting of&#13;
            external auditors of specialized enterprises when they form part of a&#13;
            financial group".&#13;
&#13;
     (ii) SB labor relations framework: Resolution JM-195-2002, "Internal&#13;
            regulation of labor relations between the Superintendency of Banks and its&#13;
            employees".&#13;
&#13;
            Schedule 3, Part (7) of the Loan Agreement: Evidence that the SB&#13;
           action plan agreed with the Bank for the application the Borrower's&#13;
           new financial legal framework has met following benchmarks: (i)      risk&#13;
           management committees are in place for all of the banks of the&#13;
           Borrower's system; and (ii) management manuals have been&#13;
                                              risk&#13;
           adopted by all the banks of the Borrower's banking system, and&#13;
           furtherverified by SB.&#13;
&#13;
27.  This condition hasbeenmet.&#13;
&#13;
   (9   Risk management committees are in place for all of the banks of the&#13;
        Borrower's system:        Circular 1216-2003 was issued concerning risk&#13;
        management including the establishment of risk management committees.&#13;
        Compliance of all the banks in the system has been verified as indicated in&#13;
       reports issued by the SB: 3601-2003 and 694-2004.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     (ii)   Risk management manuals have been adopted by all the banks of the&#13;
            Borrower's banking system, andfurther verified by SB: Circular 1216-2003&#13;
            establishes that among the aspects to be verified by the SB is that the policies&#13;
            and procedures for risk management shall be part of a risk manual. Banks&#13;
            were given up to June 15, 2004 to present their credit manuals to the SB. The&#13;
            SB presented to the Bank areport dated July 6,2004, signed by the Intendente&#13;
            of Studies and Systems, stating that all the banks in the system had submitted&#13;
            their risk management manuals to the SB.&#13;
&#13;
                Schedule 3, Part (8) of the Loan Agreement: Satisfactory progress has&#13;
                been made in carrying SB's program of in situ supervisions of the&#13;
                Borrower's national.&#13;
&#13;
28.      This condition has been met. As of December 31, 2002, the SB completed the&#13;
Valuation of Credit Assets in almost all the banks in the system, in accordance to Art. 53&#13;
of the Banking Law. Reports have been given to all the banks in the system, except two&#13;
entities, and the results have been discussed with the affected entities, which have taken&#13;
actions to reduce their risks andor strengthen their patrimony. The SB has presented to&#13;
the Bank a certification signedby the Superintendent of Banks, dated October 25, 2004,&#13;
indicatingthat the SB i s in a secondphase of review of the credit portfolio and provisions&#13;
of the affected banks, with satisfactory results that are recorded in the SB report of each&#13;
bank.&#13;
&#13;
                Schedule 3, Part (9) of the Loan Agreement: Evidence that&#13;
                supervision procedures and related necessary tools to implement the&#13;
                Borrower's money laundering law (Ley Contra el Luvado de Diner0           IC&#13;
                OtrosActivos, dated December 17,2001) are being applied.&#13;
&#13;
29.     This condition has been met. In April 2002, the regulation of the Money&#13;
Laundering Law was issued: Government Agreement No. 118-2002 of the President of&#13;
the Republic, In accordance to Art. 32 of the Law, Congressional Decree No. 67-2001&#13;
was issued creating within the SB the Intendencia de Verificacio'n Especial (IVE), which&#13;
i s the Analysis Unit for money laundering in Guatemala. WE i s fully operational and the&#13;
GAFI (Review Group for the Americas) has indicated that Guatemala meets all 25&#13;
qualification criteria.&#13;
&#13;
                Schedule 3, Part (10) of the LoanAgreement: The Borrower has taken&#13;
                irrevocable actions to initiate either merger, full regularization, full&#13;
                capitalization or liquidation of two selected undercapitalized banks of&#13;
               the Borrower's bankingsystem, as agreed with the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
30.     This condition has been met. The Government capitalized Banco Hipotecario&#13;
Nacional (CHN) with QlOO million to allow it to absorb Banco del Ejkrcito (Resolution&#13;
JM-288-2002). Afterwards, the Government capitalized C H N with 4193.9 million to&#13;
allow the merger of CHN and Banco del Nororiente (BANORO) - (Resolution JM-34-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2003). The Government has agreed with the IMF to conduct a strategic diagnostic of&#13;
CHN.&#13;
&#13;
               Schedule 3, Part (11) of the Loan Agreement: Evidence that FFCB is&#13;
               fully operational, its Operating Principles and Procedures have been&#13;
               made effective, and a coordination unit for its operation has been&#13;
               created and is adequately staffed.&#13;
&#13;
31.     This condition has been met. The FFCB (renamed FCB) was created by&#13;
Congressional Decree No. 74-2002.          On December 23, 2003 the ESCRITURA&#13;
CONSTITUTNA of the fund was signed; and on February 23, 2004, the fund's&#13;
Technical Committee staff was nominated by the MOF and BANGUAT. The operating&#13;
principles and procedures of the FCB have been prepared with the assistance of external&#13;
consultants, funded by the Financial Sector Technical Assistance Loan.        Staff of&#13;
BANGUATand SB involvedinthe operation of the FCB has been trained by the external&#13;
consultants.  The operating principles and procedures, approved by the Technical&#13;
Committee were approved by the MOF through ministerial agreement No. 51-2004 of&#13;
October 4, 2004.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IV     CONCLUSION&#13;
&#13;
32.    All the conditions required under the Loan Agreement for the release of this&#13;
Second Tranche, except for the condition for which a waiver i s being requested, have&#13;
been met.   Subject to the no-objection of the Board, management will inform the&#13;
Borrower of the availability of the Second Tranche for disbursement.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5295973">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/10/5295973/guatemala-financial-sector-structural-adjustment-loan-project-release-second-tranche-waiver-one-condition
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/10/5295973/guatemala-financial-sector-structural-adjustment-loan-project-release-second-tranche-waiver-one-condition</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/10/5295973/guatemala-financial-sector-structural-adjustment-loan-project-release-second-tranche-waiver-one-condition</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/11/08/000160016_20041108101519/Rendered/INDEX/304680GT.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/11/08/000160016_20041108101519/Rendered/PDF/304680GT.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>7130</loan_no>
        <docdt>2004-10-29T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2004-11-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Guatemala - Financial Sector Structural
            Adjustment Loan Project : release of second tranche - waiver
            of one condition
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This report proposes a waiver of one
            condition for the release of a second tranche in the amount
            of US$50.0 million to continue supporting Guatemala's
            financial sector reform program. The Bank loan supports
            actions to: (1) reform the legal framework for the conduct
            of monetary and financial policy; (2) reform the financial
            sector legal framework aimed at strengthening the regulation
            of financial groups, creating an orderly market exit
            mechanism, and enhancing credit risk management; (3)
            strengthen the legal framework for bank supervision,
            including consolidated supervision of financial groups; (4)
            enact legislation to prevent money laundering to reduce
            illegal activities; and (5) consolidate the banking system
            through the restructuring or closure of insolvent banks,
            mergers, and acquisitions. Progress in implementing the
            reform program supported by this loan has been impressive
            and, as a result, there has been a significant strengthening
            of the banking sector. A waiver is sought for condition 2,
            "Capitalization of the Central Bank completed through
            the issuing of bonds to settle past fiscal losses", on
            the grounds set forth in paragraphs 21 and 22 of the Tranche
            Release Document.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Guatemala - Financial Sector Structural
            Adjustment Loan Project : release of second tranche - waiver
            of one condition
        </docna>
        <display_title>Guatemala - Financial Sector
            Structural Adjustment Loan Project : release of second
            tranche - waiver of one condition</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2004/10/5295973/guatemala-financial-sector-structural-adjustment-loan-project-release-second-tranche-waiver-one-condition</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>GT-Guatemala Financial Sector Adjustment
            Loan -- P074530</projn>
        <docty>Tranche Release Document</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Financial Intermediation,Financial Crisis Management &amp; Restructuring,National Governance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Guatemala</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Central America!$!80455</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20041108101519</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <subsc>Banking,Payments, settlements, and remittance systems,Non-compulsory pensions and insurance,Central government administration</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Finance,Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <owner>Finance &amp; Private Sector (LCSPF)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Structural Adjustment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Central America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>30468</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Currencies and Exchange Rates</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>SME Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Standards</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Resolution and Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deposit Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>MSME Finance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Guatemala</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>