<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>30394&#13;
la~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~- ....&#13;
.~~~~~~~&#13;
3                           jCrude Oil Prices&#13;
Robert Bacon and         Predicting     Price    Differentials Based         on  Quality&#13;
Silvana Tordo&#13;
Many developing countries are becoming oil exporters, producing&#13;
Robert Bacon            crude oils that often differ markedly in quality from               those principally&#13;
is the maiager, and     traded. Governments must predict the prices of such crudes to&#13;
*,   .Silvano ltordo    forecast revenue and evaluate the fairness of the price they receive&#13;
(stordo@wiorldbank.org) a&#13;
senior energy economist,  from  companies selling on their behalf. Oil companies and industry&#13;
in the world Banks Oil  consultants have models for analyzing price! differentials with well-&#13;
antd Gas Polic't Division.&#13;
An na-Maria Ku ,,, of the known "marker" crudes, but these models have not been widely&#13;
Anzna-Maria KX-11,/ of the&#13;
International Finance    known or adapted to account for increasingly              important quality&#13;
Corpt'oation s Oil, Gas,&#13;
Corortion' Oil,Gas,     characteristics such as acidity. This Note explains a methodology for&#13;
o__      Chemicals, and Alining&#13;
Credit Reviiezt znd     price analysis and a new        extension for incorporating acidity, which&#13;
o   Portfolio Diviion asisted  can have a big effect on the price differential.&#13;
with data collet(ion.&#13;
The world produces and trades more than 160   all these cases governments need to understand&#13;
varieties of crude oil, which range widely in  the revenue implications of new production&#13;
price: while the United Kingdom's Brent Blend  streams, because these can account for a large&#13;
averaged US$43.04 in August 2004, Syrian      share of their budget. Long-term price forecasts&#13;
Heaxvy averaged US$29.97. Such large differen-  are regularly published for kev cnides-such as&#13;
O                                tials show why a single price cannot serve as a  Brent Blend, West Texas Intermediate, or&#13;
forecast for all crudes.I                     Dubai-but no forecasts are published for other&#13;
In recent years many new producer countries  crudes. Instead, forecasts for a "marker" crude are&#13;
have started to export substantial amounts of  adjusted by a discount (or premium) specific to&#13;
tie                              crude oil, including Azerbaijan, Chad, Equatorial  each crude that is based on various aspects of&#13;
Guinea, Kazakhstan, and Sudan. Several others  quality.&#13;
are promoting petroleum exploration, with good   Under production sharing contracts the gov-&#13;
prospects offindingcommerciallyviable amounts  ernment often relies on the oil company to sell&#13;
of oil. And existing producers are opening new  its share. Similarly, under royalty agreements&#13;
Wt         m                     fields where the quality of oil can differ greatly  the concessionaire usually sells the oil and trans-&#13;
from that of fields already under production. In  fers the royalties, linked to the price of crtide, to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CRUDE OIL PRICES PREDICTING PRICE DIFFERENTIALS BASED ON QUALITY&#13;
the government. Since the price governments  index that includes various types of acid. Some of&#13;
receive may differ, sometimes substantially,  these acids pose no particular problems in the&#13;
from the well-publicized marker crude prices,  refinery process. But above a certain limit acidity&#13;
they need to understand the factors that influ-  has a corrosive effect on refineries. Blending low-&#13;
ence the discount. For new producer countries,  TAN with high-TAN crude can deal with this&#13;
where the quality of crude may differ substan-  problem, but it increases logistical costs. New&#13;
tially from that of the marker crudes, this under-  refineries constructed using special materials can&#13;
standing is critical for projecting revenue and  tolerate higher acidity but are few in number.&#13;
2                           establishing more trusting relationships with oil  Thus crudes with a high TAN (greater than&#13;
companies.                                   around 0.5), because they limit the options for&#13;
refining, are likely to command a discount.&#13;
Defining quality                                In  recent years  high-TAN   crude  has&#13;
Crude oils differ from one another in a large  accounted for a growing share of the global oil&#13;
number of chemical and physical properties,  supply: an industry study reports that crude with&#13;
many of which play an important part in their  a TAN greater than 1.0 increased from 7.5 per-&#13;
refining and subsequent sale as petroleum prod-  cent of the global supply in 1998 to around 9.5&#13;
ucts. Until now statistical analysis of price dif-  percent today.2 For West African crude the pic-&#13;
ferentials has focused on two main properties:  ture is even more dramatic: in 2001 only 5 per-&#13;
the specific gravity (lightness) measured in  cent had a TAN greater than 1.0, but by 2006&#13;
degrees API (a scale devised by the American  this share is expected to rise to 13 percent. If a&#13;
Petroleum Institute) and the percentage of sul-  high TAN means a substantial discount, this&#13;
fur content by weight.                       forecast has important implications for devel-&#13;
Lighter crudes (with higher API) produce a  oping countries depending on oil for a large&#13;
larger number of lighter products, such as gaso-  share of government revenue. Moreover, if the&#13;
line, which have higher resale value. So other  share of high-TAN crude grows more rapidly&#13;
qualities being  equal, lighter crudes are   than the refineries able to accommodate it are&#13;
expected to sell at a premium  over heavier  constructed, the discount can be expected to&#13;
crudes. By extension, if the prices of all petro-  increase.&#13;
leum products rise by the same percentage&#13;
amount, the absolute price differential between  Relating quality to discounts&#13;
a heavy crude and a light crude (the discount)  Oil companies and analysts have developed&#13;
can be expected to grow.                     models for predicting discounts, some of which&#13;
A high sulfur content has an adverse effect on  are commercially available as off-the-shelf prod-&#13;
the value of crudes, because it leads to higher  ucts. But these models have centered on API&#13;
operating costs for refineries due to special pro-  and sulfur content. The growing importance of&#13;
cessing and maintenance requirements. In addi-  high-TAN crudes, especially from developing&#13;
tion, in many countries new legislation mandates  countries, calls for extending these models. Two&#13;
lower sulfur content for gasoline and diesel. So  approaches have been used. The first is based on&#13;
a high-sulfur (sour) crude is expected to sell at a  a simple pairwise comparison of crudes identi-&#13;
discount relative to a low-sulfur (sweet) crude of  cal in all major aspects of quality except the one&#13;
the same API. And an increase in the share of  being investigated. The second is based on a&#13;
high-sulfur crude in the world market, or a rela-  regression model that can simultaneously incor-&#13;
tive increase in the demand for low-sulfur prod-  porate all quality differences.&#13;
ucts, is expected to result in larger discounts for  If crude oils differ in only one dimension of&#13;
high-sulfur crudes.                          quality, pairwise comparisons can be used to&#13;
Another important property is acidity. The  relate the price differential to that difference in&#13;
recent emergence of West African and other pro-  quality. But any single comparison would be&#13;
ducers has led to an increase in the supply and  affected by factors relating to the period or to&#13;
number of crudes with high acidity as measured  nonquality characteristics of the crudes being&#13;
by the total acid number (TAN), an aggregate  compared. As a result, a series of comparisons&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
for several different crudes or for several differ-  The model as presented above is static. Thus&#13;
ent periods will not yield identical results, so that  it would predict that the set of price differentials&#13;
the results need to be averaged over a group of  between all crudes would stay constant as long as&#13;
crudes. This approach can be extended to com-  the qualities of the crudes remained constant. In&#13;
parisons of crudes differing in more than one  fact, a plot of the average price difference&#13;
dimension of quality by utilizing a series of pair-  between crudes, period by period, shows sub-&#13;
wise comparisons.                             stantial movement, roughly matching the move-&#13;
A regression model overcomes these difficul-  ment of the Brent price, with a greater spread of&#13;
ties by simultaneously incorporating differences  differentials at higher prices. To allow for the&#13;
in all important qualities in relation to the price  hypothesis that a given difference in API has a&#13;
differential. Assuming that the effects of a one-  greater effect at higher prices, the API dil'feren-&#13;
unit difference in quality are the same regard-  tial term is modified by scaling it by the current&#13;
less of the crudes being considered, and that the  Brent price. Another extension to the imodel&#13;
effects of differences in several measures of  introduces a lagged value of the price differen-&#13;
quality are additive, the discount effect can be  tial into the equation, recognizing that price dif-&#13;
formulated as follows:                        ferentials may not fully adjust within a month&#13;
(the data period used) to a change in the aver-&#13;
A price = a + X1 b, (A qualityi)      age Brent price within that period, but thal some&#13;
adjustment may spill over into the next month.&#13;
where A price is the difference in price between&#13;
a given crude and some marker crude, A quali-  Estimating the model&#13;
tyi is the difference in quality i between that  Estimating the model required identifying the&#13;
crude and the marker crude, X represents the  crudes for which data on both quality specifica-&#13;
sum of the qualities (three in the case consid-  tions and spot prices were publicly available for&#13;
ered below), and a and bi are parameters to be  a number of months. Data on 56 crudes were col-&#13;
established by regression analysis.          lected for the period January 2003-June 2004,&#13;
In this model the parameter b measures the  with data on quality taken from several Web sites&#13;
effect on the price differential of a one-unit  and data on monthly average prices (fob) taken&#13;
increase in the difference in each dimension of  from the Platts Oilgram Price Report.&#13;
quality between the crude in question and the   Brent Blend was taken as the reference crude,&#13;
marker crude.                                 since it is among the most common markers for&#13;
Although a regression model will not fully  commercial deals. Brent is a high-quality light&#13;
explain each difference in price in terms of dif-  crude (API of 38.3) with low sulfur (0.37 percent)&#13;
ferences in quality, evidence for a large number  and a very low TAN (0.07), so that most other&#13;
of crudes can identify effects common to all.  crudes would be expected to sell at a discount rel-&#13;
Moreover, since the effects (other than those  ative to it. During the period analyzed the price of&#13;
relating to the general oil price level) are not  Brent ranged between US$25 and US$38 a barrel.&#13;
expected to change rapidly, the model should    The model that was estimated includes sev-&#13;
be applicable to a succession of intervals and the  eral refinements to the simple framework&#13;
values of the coefficients should be stable. So  described above:&#13;
data for a number of crudes and for a number  * The difference in API is multiplied by the&#13;
of periods can be used in the same regression   current Brent price because the absolute dif-&#13;
(utilizing a pooled cross-section time-series   ference in the lightness of the cride is&#13;
approach). The quality characteristics of each  expected to lead to a larger absolute price dif-&#13;
crude are assumed to remain stable throughout   ferential when the general oil price is higher.&#13;
each period, since there is no published evi-  a The difference in TAN is included only for&#13;
dence on changes over time. But if the period   crudes whose TAN is above 0.5, allowing for&#13;
used is too long, the physical characteristics of  the assumption that below a certain thresh-&#13;
crude oils, especially blends, may change       old refiners need to take no special action.&#13;
enough to introduce inaccuracies.             * Freight rates between Europe and the region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CRUDE      OIL   PRICES     PREDICTING PRICE DIFFERENTIALS BASED ON QUALITY&#13;
The case of Syrian Heavy illustrates how the model can be used to estimate what a price would have been given the model's&#13;
assumptions. Syrian Heavy has low API (24.1), a high sulfur content (3.9 percent) but a TAN (0.17) below the threshold at&#13;
which the model takes it into account.&#13;
viewpoint&#13;
Price of Brent Blend in June 2004                                                =  US$35.04&#13;
Discount in May 2004                                                             = -US$5.93&#13;
Effect of lagged discount                        = 0.67 (5.93)                   = -US$3.98                     is an open forum to&#13;
Effect of lower API                              = 0.00154 x 35.04 (24.1 - 38.3)  = -US$0.77                    encourage dissemination of&#13;
Effect of higher sulfur                          = 0.27 (3.9 - 0.37)             = -US$0.95                     public policy innovations for&#13;
Effect of higher TAN                             = 0 (0.17 - 0.07)               = -US$0.00                     private sector-led and&#13;
Effect of transport differentials                                                = -US$0.28                     market-based solutions for&#13;
Total predicted discount relative to Brent                                       = -US$5.98                     development. The views&#13;
Actual discount relative to Brent                                                = -US$6.24                     published are those of the&#13;
Predicted Syrian Heavy price at actual Brent price                               =  US$29.06                    authors and should not be&#13;
Actual Syrian Heavy price                                                        =  US$28.80                    attributed to the World&#13;
Bank or any other affiiiated&#13;
The strong coherence between the prediction and the actual data confirms, within the margin of error of such a regression  organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
model and taking quality characteristics into account, that the price of Syrian Heavy conformed to those of other crudes.&#13;
the conclusions represent&#13;
official policy of the World&#13;
Bank or of its Executive&#13;
from   which the other crudes originate are             tions, to see whether there was anything unusual            Directors or the countries&#13;
introduced     to  allow  for systematic     differ-     about the actual price received (box 1).                   they represent.&#13;
ences due to transport costs and for varia-&#13;
tions over time due to changes in transport              Conclusion                                                 To order additional copies&#13;
costs. This term      also  includes a constant          A regression model relating price differentials            contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
effect common to all crudes.                             to differences in quality characteristics can be a         managing editor,&#13;
All variables are strongly significant and of            valuable tool for analyzing       the price of new          Room F 4K-206,&#13;
the expected sign, and the overall squared cor-             crudes whose quality differs greatly from      that of      The World Bank,&#13;
relation coefficient is 80 percent. The coeffi-             the marker crude. This capability enables gov-              1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
cient of the lagged price differential is estimated         ernments whose country produces such crudes                 Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
at 0.67. The long-run effects of the variables,             to better forecast future revenue streams and to&#13;
evaluated as if the Brent price settled at some             verify that the prices received from       companies        00 202 458 728&#13;
constant level, are as follows:                             selling the oil on their behalf are reasonable.             Fax:&#13;
001 202 522 3480&#13;
Per unit of sulfur                       -US$0.82                                                                       Email:&#13;
Per unit of TAN                          -US$0.88                                                                       ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
Per unit of API per dollar of Brent +US$0.0047              Notes&#13;
This Note is taken from   a larger study now under      Produced by Grammarians,&#13;
The interpretation of the API coefficient is             preparation.                                               Inc.&#13;
particularly interesting. At a price of US$20 a                 ]. Conventionall) the industry focuses on absolute&#13;
barrel for Brent each degree of API is worth                (dollar) differentials rather than relative (percentage) dif-  Printed on recycled paper&#13;
9.4¢, while at a price of US$40 it is worth 18.8¢,          ferentials.&#13;
supporting     the  hypothesis     that differentials          2. Anne    Shafizadeh, Gregg   McAteer, and John&#13;
increase as crude prices rise.                              Sigmon, "High-Acid Crudes." paper presented at Crude&#13;
The model can be used to predict the price               Oil Quality Group meeting. New Orleans,January 30,2003&#13;
of future streams of crude of known            quality      [http://www.coqg.org/20030130special.asp].&#13;
under assumed Brent prices or to "backcast" by&#13;
estimating what the price of a known crude&#13;
would have been        given the model's assump-&#13;
This Note is available online:&#13;
http://rru.worldbank.org/PublicPolicyjournaI&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5496306">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/10/5496306/crude-oil-prices-predicting-price-differentials-based-quality
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/10/5496306/crude-oil-prices-predicting-price-differentials-based-quality</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/10/5496306/crude-oil-prices-predicting-price-differentials-based-quality</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/12/09/000012009_20041209143656/Rendered/INDEX/30394.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/12/09/000012009_20041209143656/Rendered/PDF/30394.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2004-10-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2004-12-09T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Crude oil prices - predicting price
            differentials based on quality
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Many developing countries are becoming
            oil exporters, producing crude oils that often differ
            markedly in quality from those principally traded.
            Governments must predict the prices of such crudes, to
            forecast revenue and evaluate the fairness of the price they
            receive from companies selling on their behalf. Oil
            companies, and industry consultants, have models for
            analyzing price differentials with well-known
            "marker" crudes, but these models have not been
            widely known, or adapted to account for increasingly
            important quality characteristics, such as acidity. This
            note explains a methodology for price analysis, and a new
            extension for incorporating acidity, which can have a big
            effect on the price differential.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Crude oil prices - predicting price
            differentials based on quality
        </docna>
        <display_title>Crude oil prices - predicting
            price differentials based on quality</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2004/10/5496306/crude-oil-prices-predicting-price-differentials-based-quality</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Energy Demand,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Access to Markets,Markets and Market Access,Oil Refining &amp; Gas Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Energy,Industry,International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Bacon, Robert</author>
            <author>Tordo, Silvana</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000012009_20041209143656</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 275</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Energy,Industry,International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Crude oil; Oil pricing; Oil exporting
            countries; Quality differentiation; International trade; Oil
            revenues; Fairness; Price distortions; Acidity; Price
            controls; account, acid, acidity, acids, API, average
            prices, Chemicals, crude oil, CRUDE OIL, developing
            countries, International Finance, legislation, matching,
            Oil, Oil Prices, OIL PRICES, oils, petroleum, physical
            characteristics, price forecasts, producers, refining,
            regression analysis, royalties, selling, spot prices,
            spread, statistical analysis, streams, sulfur, Web sites
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off of VP, FPD - WB (FPDVP)</owner>
        <repnb>30394</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Demand</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Refineries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>