<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                  Document o f&#13;
                                                 The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
                                        FOR OFFICIAL USEONLY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      ReportNo: T7641-AF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                       FOR A PROPOSEDGRANT&#13;
&#13;
                                           OF SDR 18.4MILLION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  (US$27.0MILLIONEQUIVALENT)&#13;
&#13;
                                                      TO THE&#13;
&#13;
                               ISLAMICREPUBLIC OF AFGHANISTAN&#13;
&#13;
                                                      FOR A&#13;
&#13;
                PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION CAPACITY BUILDING PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               December27,2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
South Asia Region Financial Management Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricteddistribution and may be usedbyrecipients only inthe performance oftheir official&#13;
duties. Its contents may not otherwise be disclosed without World Bank authorization&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                       CURRENCY EQUIVALENT&#13;
           (exchange rate is Kabulbasedopenmarket buying rate)&#13;
                          effective October 5, 2004&#13;
&#13;
                 Currency Unit      -            Afghani&#13;
                 U S $ 1            =    45.0    Afghani&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     GOVERNMENT FISCAL YEAR&#13;
                            March21 -March20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Vice President: Praful C. Pate1&#13;
                         Country Director: Alastair McKechnie&#13;
Director, Operational and Quality Services: Barbara Kaka&#13;
          Manager, FinancialManagement: Robert Saum&#13;
                        Task Team Leader: Anne Tully&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       ..&#13;
                                       11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                           FOROF'FICTALUSEOPTLY&#13;
                                   ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
             AACA         Afghanistan Assistance CoordinationAuthority&#13;
             AFMIS        Afghanistan Financial Management InformationSystem&#13;
             AIA          Afghanistan InterimAdministration&#13;
              ARCS        Audit Report Compliance System&#13;
              ARDS        Afghanistan ReconstructionDevelopment Services&#13;
              ARTF        Afghanistan ReconstructionTrust Fund&#13;
              CAO         Control andAudit Office&#13;
              CQ     *    Consultant Qualifications&#13;
              DAB         D a Afghanistan Bank&#13;
              DBER        Development Budget and External Relations&#13;
              DFID        Department for International Development&#13;
              EPAP        Emergency Public Administration Project&#13;
              FMIS        Financial Management InformationSystems&#13;
              FMR         Financial Monitoring Report&#13;
              GDP         Gross Domestic Product&#13;
              HR          Human Resources&#13;
              IARCSC      Independent Administrative Reform and Civil Service Commission&#13;
              IBRD        International Bank for Reconstruction and Development&#13;
              ICB         International Competitive Bidding&#13;
              IDA         International Development Association&#13;
              IFAC        International Federation of Accountants&#13;
              INTOSAI     International Organization o f Supreme Audit Institutions&#13;
              IRoA        Islamic Republic o f Afghanistan&#13;
              MOF         Ministry of Finance&#13;
              NDF         National Development Framework&#13;
              NCB         National Competitive Bidding&#13;
              NDF         NationalDevelopment Framework&#13;
              PACBP       Public Administration Capacity BuildingProject&#13;
              PAR         Public Administration Reform&#13;
              PAREM       Public Administration Reform and Economic Management&#13;
              PPU         Procurement Policy Unit&#13;
               PRR        Priority Reform and Restructuring&#13;
               PSIB       Programmatic Support for Institution Building&#13;
               QCBS       Quality and Cost Based Selection&#13;
               RFP        Request for Proposal&#13;
               SA         Special Account&#13;
               SAF        Securirig Afghanistan's Future&#13;
               SBD        Standard Bidding Documents&#13;
               SDR        Special Drawing Rights                                     9&#13;
               SDU        Special Disbursement Unit&#13;
               SOE        Statement of Expenditures&#13;
               SY         Solar Year&#13;
               TA         Technical Assistance&#13;
               TSS        Transitional Support Strategy&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricted distributionand may be used by recipients only in&#13;
the performance of their official duties. I t s contents may not be otherwise disclosed&#13;
without W o r l d Bank authorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                 ISLAMIC REPUBLICOFAFGHANISTAN&#13;
                 PUBLICADMINISTRATION CAPACITYBUILDING PROJECT&#13;
                                                TECHNICALANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                               TABLEOFCONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
I CountryBackgroundandStrategy&#13;
 .                                                 ..........................................................................................    1&#13;
      A. Country Background...................................................................................................... 1&#13;
      B. Government Economic ManagementStrategy..............................................................                                    1&#13;
&#13;
I1 IDA RESPONSE&#13;
  .                   ......................................................................................................................&#13;
      A. Bank's Transitional Support Strategy............................................................................. 3                     3&#13;
&#13;
      B. Rationale for IDA'SInvolvement inPublic Administration andEconomic&#13;
         Management...................................................................................................................           4&#13;
      C. The Firstand SecondEmergencyPublic Administration Projects................................                                              4&#13;
&#13;
I11 The ProposedProject&#13;
   .                           .............................................................................................................     6&#13;
      A. Project Objective............................................................................................................ 6&#13;
      B. Project Approach............................................................................................................            6&#13;
      C. Project Description.........................................................................................................            7&#13;
&#13;
I V ProjectImplementationandOversightArrangements&#13;
  .                                                                                        ....................................................  12&#13;
      A. ImplementationArrangements..................................................................................... 12&#13;
      B. Procurement,FinancialManagement. andAudit Arrangements.................................                                                 13&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 14&#13;
      D. MonitoringandEvaluation..........................................................................................&#13;
      C. Project Oversight..........................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 14&#13;
&#13;
V BenefitsandRisks&#13;
  .                     ..................................................................................................................       14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Boxes&#13;
Box 1.Economic ManagementVision ...........................................................................................                       2&#13;
Box 2. PAREM Initiatives to Build a ModernPublic Administration and StrengthenCore&#13;
      Functions.............................................................................................................................. 3&#13;
Box 3. Key Achievements under EPAP Iand I1............................................................................. 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex&#13;
Annex 1: Termsof Reference for Major Technical Assistance Packages....................................                                           16&#13;
      Component 1. StrengtheningProcurement Capacity within Government........................                                                   16&#13;
      Component 2. StrengtheningFinancial Management Capacity withinGovernment .......18&#13;
      Component 3: StrengtheningInternal Audit Capacity withinGovernment .....................                                                   20&#13;
      Component 4: StrengtheningExternal Audit Capacity withinGovernment ....................                                                    22&#13;
Annex 2: ProcurementArrangements........................................................................................... 25&#13;
      Attachment 1: Proceduresfor National Competitive Bidding..........................................                                         27&#13;
Annex 3: Financial Management and DisbursementArrangements ............................................                                          29&#13;
Annex 4. Monitoring.....................................................................................................................&#13;
             . .                                                                                                                                 34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 iv&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           I.COUNTRYBACKGROUND STRATEGY AND&#13;
&#13;
A. Country Background&#13;
&#13;
1.     Afghanistan has achieved much in the three years since December 2001 when the&#13;
Afghanistan Interim Administration (AIA) was inaugurated in Kabul. Picking up the reins o f&#13;
governance at that point the AIA was confronted with an economy reeling from protracted&#13;
conflict and drought, more than five million people displaced as refugees in neighboring&#13;
countries, economic activities steered in an informal or illicit direction by insecurity, and a state&#13;
that had become virtually non functional in terms of policy making and service delivery -&#13;
although the structures and many staff remained.        The achievements that have been made&#13;
subsequently are significant, and inAfghanistan's context, remarkable.&#13;
&#13;
2.     Afghanistan's economy has performed strongly in the past two and half years with non-&#13;
drug Gross Domestic Product (GDP) reaching US$ 4.6 billion in 2003/04 (corresponding to a&#13;
GDP per capita o f about US$200 per year), an increase o f almost 50 percent, albeit from a very&#13;
low base. This is mainly attributable to the recovery o f agriculture from the drought, revival o f&#13;
economic activities after major conflict ended, and the commencement o f reconstruction efforts.&#13;
This solid performance has been supported by the Government's sound macroeconomic policies&#13;
-ahighlysuccessfulcurrencyreforminlate2002,aprudentnooverdraftpolicyprohibiting&#13;
domestic financing o f the budget deficit, conservative monetary policy, and good management o f&#13;
the exchange rate. Progress has been made in mobilizing domestic resources as well as donor&#13;
assistance in support o f the Government's medium-term development program, with&#13;
expenditures financed by external assistance increased to more than US$ 2 billion in 2003/04.&#13;
The Government has also made considerable progress in formulating the budget and developing&#13;
a medium-term expenditure framework.&#13;
&#13;
3.      These achievements notwithstanding, the challenges remain enormous in improving&#13;
security throughout the country, reestablishing national unity, developing institutions with a&#13;
capacity to formulate and implement policies, reaching out to provinces to collect revenues and&#13;
deliver services, and implementing the Government's long-term vision for the future o f&#13;
Afghanistan.&#13;
&#13;
B. Government Economic Management Strategy&#13;
&#13;
4.      Following its inauguration, the Government quickly took the initiative in formulating&#13;
Afghanistan's development strategy. InApril 2002, it formulated a comprehensive development&#13;
strategy -the National Development Framework (NDF) -which outlined a strong agenda to&#13;
rebuild institutions and implement structural reforms within a stable macroeconomic framework.&#13;
The NDF was also a significant step in underpinning a truly Government-led reconstruction&#13;
process. The NDF provides a framework to coordinate the Government's programs and donor&#13;
assistance and also provides the basis for preparingthe National Budget.&#13;
&#13;
5.      The NDF was further underpinned by a report released by the Government in March&#13;
2004: Securing Afghanistan's Future: Accomplishments and the Strategic Path Forward (SAF).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SAF' sets out a comprehensive framework and investment program based on outcome targets to&#13;
be achieved in 2015 to align with the Millennium Development Goals Framework. It provides&#13;
an assessment o f the investment and recurrent cost requirement over a seven-year horizon,&#13;
identifying a requirement for external assistance inthe range o f US$ 27 billion over this period.&#13;
The report provided the basis for a major donor meeting heldinBerlin inMarch 2004 where the&#13;
international community pledged US$ 8.2 billion for reconstruction and security activities over&#13;
the next three years (SYl383-1385), with US$4.4 billion pledgedfor SY1383 alone.&#13;
&#13;
6.       These strategy documents have as their core the principle o f a well-functioning state that&#13;
i s accountable to its citizens and able to ensure the delivery o f services in an equitable, efficient,&#13;
and effective manner. The Government's objective o f providing an enabling environment for&#13;
growth requires an effective central government that can reestablish national unity on the basis o f&#13;
strong institutions and the rule of law. The SAF report laid out a vision inthe area o f economic&#13;
management (box 1) and several specific goals, including:&#13;
&#13;
         0    A well-functioning and well structured security sector based on institutions that&#13;
              facilitate a return to normalcy inthe political, economic, and social spheres;&#13;
&#13;
         0    An effective public administration that is small and focused on core functions; more&#13;
              diverse and decentralized; better skilled, equipped and managed; more accountable;&#13;
              and more representative interms o f gender and ethnicity; and&#13;
&#13;
         0    A budget that is affordable and sustainable on a multi-year basis. and enables&#13;
              delegation o f authority based on strong accountability mechanisms.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Box 1. Economic Management Visiona&#13;
e    A budget that is affordable and sustainable-robust revenue capacity with effective collection processes and&#13;
     an expenditure structure that is affordable with minimal donor assistance.&#13;
e    A budgetprocess which is:&#13;
&#13;
     0 multi-year, and tied to policy development through a strategicplanningprocess;&#13;
&#13;
     0 comprehensive,integrating capital and operating components and including all sources o f revenues and&#13;
       all expenditures; and&#13;
&#13;
     0 results-based, inwhich budgets are developed on a program basis and focused on outputs and outcomes&#13;
       rather than inputs.&#13;
e    Increaseddelegatedauthority for financial management, concurrent with stronger accountability meclzanisms.&#13;
e    Modern, electronic financial management systems in place to ensure efficient cash management, timely&#13;
     payments and disbursements, and accurate financial accounting.&#13;
e    Transparency in reporting to decision-makers and the public so that decisions are based on timely information&#13;
     and Government can be held accountable for the use o f public resources.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
a Securing Afghanistan's Future: Accomplishmentsand the Strategic Path Forward, March 2004.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7.        To achieve these goals and build a modern, transparent, and effective public&#13;
administration at central, provincial, and district levels, the Government needs to address three&#13;
&#13;
  Prepared incollaboration with the Asian Development Bank, the Intemational Monetary Fund,the UnitedNations&#13;
Development Program, the UnitedNations Assistance Mission for Afghanistan, andthe World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
inter-related issues: (a) redefining the roles and mandates of line ministriesand aligning staffing&#13;
to the new roles; (b) reforming public sector pay scales to recruit and retain qualified&#13;
professionals and buildcore public administration capacity; and (c) effectively utilizing technical&#13;
assistance to support implementation of public administration reforms including increasing&#13;
Government's absorptive capacity and regulatory power.&#13;
&#13;
8.      While still at an early stage, the Government's Public Administration Reform and&#13;
Economic Management (PAREM) Program is laying down the basis for addressingthese issues&#13;
(box 2). It i s also setting the framework for Government to transition from "buying-in" core&#13;
public administration capacity to utilizing technical assistance to kick start and sustain key&#13;
functions within Government.&#13;
&#13;
     Box 2. PAREM Initiatives to Build a Modern Public Administrationand StrengthenCore Functions&#13;
    The Ministry of Finance (MOF) has initiated several measures to consolidate its functions and strengthen its&#13;
    capacity.&#13;
    Systems for preparation of the ordinary and development budgets have been progressively improved and&#13;
    updated.&#13;
    Improvements have been made inbudget executionand treasury functions -including improvements to payroll&#13;
    processes throughout the country - with parallel improvements in Da Afghanistan Bank (DAB) payment&#13;
    systems.&#13;
    Efforts at administrative reform are being spearheaded through the Priority Reform and Restructuring (PRR)&#13;
   process whereby staff in departments who undertake administrative reforms receive interim additional&#13;
    allowances. (This is being supplementedby aPRR Superscaleto attract exceptional staffing resources.)&#13;
    These efforts will help lay the basis for abroad-basedprogramto streamline and rationalize ministries.&#13;
    A Lateral Entry program has beenestablishedto inject fresh capacity into line ministries to acceleratethe reform&#13;
    effort.&#13;
    A full pay and grading review i s underway with the aim of providing an appropriate pay and incentive&#13;
    framework to attract and retain quality staff inGovernment.&#13;
    Technical assistance is being designed with a greater focus on capacity building including developing the legal&#13;
    and regulatory frameworks, defining systems based on clearly identified needs, and strengthening human&#13;
    resource(HR) capacityto operate these systems over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9.      All of these efforts are expected to result in an expansion of absorptive capacity&#13;
consistent with the experience inother post-conflict countries which has shown that the capacity&#13;
to absorb development assistanceincreasesdramatically after approximately three years.&#13;
&#13;
                                            11.     IDARESPONSE&#13;
&#13;
A. Bank's Transitional Support Strategy&#13;
&#13;
10.     The reconstruction strategy developed by the Government of Afghanistan forms the&#13;
framework within which the Bank's Transitional Support Strategy (TSS) has been prepared.&#13;
Approved in March 2003, the TSS sets out priorities for Bank financial and non-financial&#13;
assistance based on the areas o f comparative advantage of the Bank and the particular situation&#13;
in Afghanistan.       The TSS focuses on four strategic areas: (a) improving livelihoods; (b)&#13;
strengthening the fiscal strategy, institutions andmanagement; (c) implementinggovernance and&#13;
public administration reform; and (d) enabling private sector development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
B. Rationalefor IDA'sInvolvementinPublicAdministrationandEconomicManagement&#13;
&#13;
11.     Both the first and second TSS for Afghanistan emphasizedthe need for Afghans to be in&#13;
the "driver's seat" with regard to managing the reconstruction and development process. Under&#13;
the Government's steadfast direction, donors have increasingly supported Government programs&#13;
and accepted the budget as the instrument for managing donor resources. In parallel, the&#13;
Government has had to demonstrate its ability to manage resources in an effective and&#13;
transparent manner, with an increasing emphasis on rules-based economic governance and&#13;
effective capacity building.&#13;
&#13;
12.     Within the governance and public administration reform strategic areas, the Bank's&#13;
strategy has been to identify pragmatic opportunities for action inthe short term, initiating a set&#13;
of immediate reforms which would be supportive of longer-term improvements in public&#13;
administration. It.has entailed: (a) ensuringthat emergency capacity i s inplace, especially inkey&#13;
fiduciary areas, while launching medium-term capacity building efforts; (b) undertaking&#13;
extensive diagnostic work along with ongoing technical and policy advice to identify and address&#13;
key constraints; (c) identifying short-term goals that are fully owned by the Government and&#13;
agreedwith all major donors; and (d) providinggap financing whenneeded.&#13;
&#13;
13.     The First and Second Emergency Public Administration Projects (EPAP Iand 11)&#13;
primarily supported the first and second prongs of the above strategy. Other Bank instruments,&#13;
including analytical work and policy dialogue in administrative reform, as well as the&#13;
Programmatic Support for Institution Building (PSIB) adjustment operation, have supported the&#13;
thirdand fourthprongs.&#13;
&#13;
14.     This strategy initially focused on achieving progress in governance and public&#13;
administration reform through quick-wins, and in ways that did not undermine medium-term&#13;
goals. As the Bank has engaged in an increasingly substantive policy dialogue with the&#13;
Government in the area of administrative reform, a progressive shift has been made toward&#13;
supporting medium-term solutions to build capacity within Government, including:&#13;
(a) supporting broader public expenditure legislative reform agenda covering budget,&#13;
procurement, and audit laws; (b) strengthening sub-national governance through the Afghanistan&#13;
Stabilization Programme; (c) rationalizing ministries through the PRR process; (d) reforming pay&#13;
and payroll systems; and (e) strengthening financial control, reporting, audit, and procurement&#13;
systems.&#13;
&#13;
C. The First and Second EmergencyPublicAdministrationProjects&#13;
&#13;
15.     EPAP Iwas IDA's first operation in Afghanistan and totaled US$ 10 million. It was&#13;
approved in April 2002 and became effective in June 2002. The objective of the project was to&#13;
put inplace emergency capacity inkey public administration areas to facilitate the use of donor&#13;
and own resources for urgent reconstruction and development efforts. It also aimed to support&#13;
some basic steps toward building a transparent, well-functioning public administration. EPAP I&#13;
was comprised of three components:&#13;
&#13;
        e   Procurement Strengthening Component to support the transparent and efficient&#13;
            utilizationof donor resourcesthrough employment of a procurement agent;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        0    Treasury DepartmentStrengtheningComponentto kick start the budget execution&#13;
             and expenditure accounting and reporting functions through employment of an&#13;
             international financial management agent; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        0    Audit Capacity Strengthening Component to ensure the timely audit o f&#13;
             Government expenditure through engagement o f an Audit Agent.&#13;
&#13;
16.     In June 2003 a follow-up project (Second Emergency Public Administration Project,&#13;
EPAP 11) was approved. EPAP I1provided supplemental financing for the procurement and&#13;
financial management contracts supported under EPAP I.EPAP I1also provided funds for the&#13;
Government's Public Administration Reform program (PAR), implemented by the Independent&#13;
Administrative Reform and Civil Service Commission (IARCSC) andjointly financed with the&#13;
Department for International Development (DFID). These funds support activities to strengthen&#13;
the functions o f the IARCSC inimplementing the PRRprocess and other priority activities inthe&#13;
PARprogram.&#13;
&#13;
17.     EPAP Iand I1have been core elements o f IDA's first and second TSSs, providing the&#13;
underpinning fiduciary arrangements for the entire IDA portfolio.                      This enabled IDA to&#13;
reactivate operations with Afghanistan very quickly in the post-conflict period. In addition,&#13;
IDA's early support in these areas enabled the Government to quickly build credibility with&#13;
donors as to their ability to effectively manage donor and own resource. This i s reflected inthe&#13;
increasing numbers o f donors prepared to channel funds either directly through the Treasury or&#13;
via the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund (ARTF). EPAP I1 has also enabled the&#13;
Government to lay the basis for reforming the administrative arrangements within government.&#13;
&#13;
18.     A mid-term review was conducted of EPAP Iand EPAP I1in early 2004. The review&#13;
concluded that the projects had made significant progress in achieving their objectives (box 3)&#13;
particularly in the context o f Afghanistan's extremely limited capacity and engagement with the&#13;
international community over the past twenty years. Early assistance focused on the provision o f&#13;
emergency capacity in critical fiduciary areas.              Because o f the emergency nature o f this&#13;
assistance, broader institutional development and capacity building activities did not proceed as&#13;
quickly as expectations in this regard. In some areas, the lack o f a medium-term framework for&#13;
systems development, regulatory reform, and capacity building inhibited further progress being&#13;
made, particularly inexpanding the activities to line ministries and provinces.&#13;
&#13;
                               Box 3. Key Achievements under EPAP Iand I1&#13;
    As o f mid-November 2004, the Afghanistan Reconstruction Development Services (ARDS) has processed 202&#13;
    contracts with a value of USD 392.9m with a further 42 contracts in preparation estimated at USD 257m. A&#13;
    draft procurement law has been prepared and between 110 and 150 procurement staff from line ministries have&#13;
    receivedtraining inbasic and specific procurement rules.&#13;
    In the Treasury, a functioning computerized general ledger and payments system is in place with some&#13;
    networking o f components; significant improvements have been made in cash management, grant management,&#13;
    bankreconciliations, revenue recording, and the recording of budget appropriations and allotments.&#13;
    The Auditor General has completed the audits o f the financial statements o f ARTF, the state budget, and an&#13;
    increasing number o f IDA and ARTF-funded projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
19.     The mid-term review concludedthat continued operational assistance would be necessary&#13;
to maintain standards o f fiduciary control for the near term, and in order to maintain donor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
confidence in the Government's fiduciary       mechanisms. At the same time, the Government&#13;
considers it crucial to transition from "buying-in" capacity to developing it within Government&#13;
within a clearly articulated medium-term development framework. Inresponse to this, IDA and&#13;
the Government have had extensive dialogue during the last six months on a coherent medium-&#13;
term public expenditure management reform and capacity building strategy that addresses&#13;
legislative, regulatory, and institutional reforms and development o f management control&#13;
systems and HR. The Government has requested IDA assistance inthe implementation o f such a&#13;
strategy. The proposedproject i s prepared inthis context.&#13;
&#13;
                                   111. THEPROPOSEDPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
A. ProjectObjective&#13;
&#13;
20.     The overall objective o f the project i s to assist the authorities in developing the capacity&#13;
to manage public expenditures in an effective, transparent, and accountable manner in order to&#13;
achieve satisfactory and sustainable development outcomes in Afghanistan. The project will&#13;
have a particular focus on enhancing the performance o f public sector procurement, financial&#13;
management, and accountability systems.&#13;
&#13;
21.      Success inmeetingthe project's objective will be measured by:&#13;
&#13;
         0  Establishment and implementation o f sound regulatory and control frameworks for&#13;
            budget execution and fiscal reporting, andpublic sector procurement;&#13;
&#13;
         0  Further development o f core systems for budget execution, Government accounting,&#13;
            andinternaland externalaudits;&#13;
&#13;
         0  Development o f HRto effectively manage and operate these critical systems; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         0  Operational performance (technical efficiency) o f the fiduciary management&#13;
            functions.&#13;
&#13;
B. ProjectApproach&#13;
&#13;
22.      The proposed project combines technical assistance (TA) for continued operational&#13;
support in core fiduciary functions with assistance for implementation of legislative, regulatory,&#13;
and institutional reforms; systems development; and HR development. The project will reflect&#13;
the lessons learned in the first two projects by putting into effect a clear capacity building&#13;
strategy ineach area based upon the following:&#13;
&#13;
         0  Ensuring capacity building activities are firmly grounded ina medium-termstrategic&#13;
            planfor development o f the core functions withinGovernment;&#13;
&#13;
         0  Facilitating the long-term sustainability o f capacity buildingthrough establishment o f&#13;
            an appropriate legal, regulatory, and control environment;&#13;
&#13;
         0  Ensuringthat further systems development is based on a medium-term approach to&#13;
            requirements and a full understandingo f local conditions and capabilities;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
           Ensuringthat key functions are defined and established not only in the core central&#13;
           agencies but also inthe line ministries;&#13;
&#13;
           Ensuringcounterpart staff are inplace inthese core functional areas so that effective&#13;
           knowledge transfer can take place;&#13;
&#13;
           Ensuring terms o f reference for technical assistance service providers accord adequate&#13;
           consideration to on-the-job training and knowledge transfer with key milestones&#13;
           identified inorder to monitor progress; and&#13;
&#13;
           Separating major training activities from the delivery o f operational support&#13;
           consultancy services to maximize value-for-money and to avoid the risk that urgent&#13;
           operational support objectives will crowd out essential capacity building activities.&#13;
&#13;
23.     The Government wishes to examine options for bringing about many o f the necessary&#13;
institutional improvements in public expenditure management, where possible, through&#13;
relationships (twinning) with experienced and well-performing institutions/agencies in other&#13;
countries.   Twinning with experienced entities in the core functional areas may provide&#13;
opportunities to integrate know-how transfer and on-the-job staff training. Twinningalso has the&#13;
advantage o f sensitizing Government staff to an experienced well-functioning organization, a&#13;
dimension that consultancy assignments often lack. The Government has requested that the&#13;
various TA components under the project be examined for the degree to which twinning&#13;
arrangements could be utilized for some activities, particularly those related to strategic&#13;
development and capacity building. This approach does not preclude the need for separate&#13;
contracting o f operational or specific tasks where appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
C. Project Description&#13;
&#13;
24.     Inpursuit ofthese objectives, the project is comprisedoffive components:&#13;
&#13;
         Component 1:          Strengthening Procurement         Capacity within      Government&#13;
         (US$9,000,000)&#13;
&#13;
25.     Under the Procurement Strengthening Component o f the EPAP Iand 11, a central&#13;
Procurement Agent was contracted to put in place emergency procurement capacity to facilitate&#13;
rapid, transparent utilization o f donor resources for reconstruction and development.         This&#13;
component was implemented by the Afghanistan Assistance Coordination Authority (AACA)&#13;
and subsequently by the ARDS.&#13;
&#13;
26.      The EPAP mid-term review recognized that the provision o f emergency centralized&#13;
procurement capacity was essential early on in Afghanistan's reconstruction effort.          It also&#13;
concluded that there would be a continued need for centralized procurement services for some&#13;
time. However, the Government now wishes to see an accelerated effort to build procurement&#13;
capacity within line ministries to enable them to perform key procurement functions to adequate&#13;
standards.   This is also critical for improving eligibility levels under the recurrent cost&#13;
component o f the ARTF.          This will require focused assistance in capacity building,&#13;
organizational reform, and legal/regulatory development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27.     This component of the project will provide technical advisory support, equipment, and&#13;
training to the ARDS Procurement Unit and a nascent Procurement Policy Unit (PPU) in order&#13;
to:&#13;
&#13;
        A. Support line ministrieswith the direct procurement process, particularly in relation&#13;
             to donor programs, for the next three years through a consultancy contract with a&#13;
             procurement facilitation firm. An allowance i s included to cover operating costs o f&#13;
             the Procurement Unit within the ARDS through June 2005 when it i s expected that&#13;
             the costs will be met by the Government.&#13;
&#13;
        B. Undertake a procurement capacity building program within line ministries so that&#13;
             they can progressively be accredited with increased delegated authority for&#13;
             procurement management within an agreed institutional and legal framework. This&#13;
             program (which will include activities to promote Afghan private sector&#13;
             participation in procurement) will not only focus on central ministries but will also&#13;
             reach out to staff in provinces, districts, and municipalities. The capacity building&#13;
             program will include programs to:          (i)train staff and implement a coherent&#13;
             certification system; (ii)strengthen the procurement function within Government&#13;
             through the PRR process; and (iii)transfer procurement responsibility to line&#13;
             ministriesaccordingto a series o fperformance milestones.&#13;
&#13;
        C. Support the promulgation and implementation o f the new procurement law and&#13;
             regulations and establishment o f a PPUwithin Government.&#13;
&#13;
28.     The Government has already issued a contract to a consulting firm, Rites o f India, for the&#13;
assistance set out insubcomponent 1(A).&#13;
&#13;
        Component 2: Strengthening Financial Management Capacity within Government&#13;
        (usss,ooo,ooo)&#13;
29.     The Government has begun a program o f financial management improvement which i s&#13;
expected to have far-reaching consequences for the manner and processes o f financial&#13;
transactions, recording, accounting, and reporting over the next several years. The extent o f&#13;
these reforms is evolving but includes budget and expenditure reforms and improved accounting,&#13;
financial reporting, and internal controls. The Government has drafted a new Public Finance and&#13;
Expenditure Management Law which i s expected to be approved before parliamentary elections&#13;
in the middle of 2005 (this approval is a trigger for the second Programmatic Support for&#13;
Institution Buildingoperation).&#13;
&#13;
30.     The current Government fiscal management system i s under the administration o f the&#13;
M O F which is responsible for budget preparation, budget execution, accounting, reporting,&#13;
payroll, revenue and customs administration, debt management, cash management and a range o f&#13;
functions inGovernment asset administration.&#13;
&#13;
31.     The mid-term review o f EPAP Iand I1found that the Treasury, with the support o f the&#13;
financial management agent, had made significant progress in reestablishing core Government&#13;
financial management systems. Core check printing, budget control, and accounting functions o f&#13;
an Afghanistan Financial Management Information System (AFMIS) have been implemented.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Significant improvements have been made in cash management, grant management, bank&#13;
reconciliations, revenue recording, andthe recording o f budget appropriations and allotments.&#13;
&#13;
32.     The Government now wishes to consolidate this progress, and ensure that further&#13;
progress in implementing financial management systems at the center is matched by similar&#13;
attention to development o f capacity and procedures within line ministries and provinces. The&#13;
Government also wishes to ensure that any further development o f the AFMIS is done in a way&#13;
that takes into account the particular circumstances within Afghanistan and incorporates results&#13;
from a systematic review o f the medium- to long-term financial management information&#13;
requirements o f the Government. While the EPAP review concluded that the current AFMIS&#13;
had proven to be effective in quickly establishing a computerized Treasury payment and&#13;
accounting system, it requires significant further developmenthpgrading to meet the needs o f&#13;
Government over the longterm, including ultimately serving the provinces and line ministries.&#13;
&#13;
33.     The financial management component will provide TA, equipment, and training to the&#13;
M O F and line ministries in the achievement o f core financial management objectives including&#13;
attaining higher levels of efficiency in budget execution, fiscal reporting) accounting, and&#13;
internal controls. Activities under this component will include:&#13;
&#13;
        A. ComprehensiveFinancial Management Information Systems (FMIS)Architecture&#13;
            Study to determine a framework for the phased implementation o f an integrated&#13;
            FMIS for Government over the medium to long term. The grant includes a provision&#13;
            for the Government to quickly implement early recommendations o f the study in&#13;
            agreement with IDA.&#13;
&#13;
        B. Technical advisory support to the MOF and to line ministries to strengthen core&#13;
            M O F functions including budget execution) fiscal reporting and accounting, and&#13;
            internal control.   Activities are expected to include: strengthening the financial&#13;
            management regulatory framework) including drafting needed regulations and&#13;
            policies based on the new Public Expenditure and Financial Management Law;&#13;
            establishing core functions and systems in each area; facilitating new systems&#13;
            integration; identifying HR requirements and conducting a comprehensive training&#13;
            needs assessment; coordinating training activities; and providing operational support&#13;
            and on-the-job training in core functional areas. While this will primarily cover&#13;
            Treasury functions, scope i s retained within the project to support other key MOF&#13;
            development priorities as necessary.&#13;
&#13;
        C. Managerial and Professional Development Training in Public Sector Financial&#13;
            Managementfor MOF and line minktry stafJ           This will be based upon the needs&#13;
            assessment conducted under subcomponent 2 (B).&#13;
&#13;
        Component 3:         Strengthening Internal Audit Capacity within Government&#13;
        (US$4,000,000)&#13;
&#13;
34.     The mid-termreview identified the lack of an effective internal audit function as a critical&#13;
constraint to improving public expenditure management within Government. There are currently&#13;
designated internal audit departments operating in key line ministries that report directly to their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ministers. They do not carry out work that would be considered to comply with recognized&#13;
international internal auditing standards. Audit work i s currently focused on the identificationof&#13;
irregularities and the investigation of potential corruption and fraud. No reviews of internal&#13;
control processesare carried out.&#13;
&#13;
35.     This component will provide technical advisory services, training, and equipment to&#13;
support the internal audit function within Government. The establishment of an effective&#13;
internal audit service, following generally recognized international standards of internal auditing&#13;
and control, will help to improve public sector accountability and governance. It will also&#13;
support the establishment of sound financial management within the public sector including&#13;
more effective execution of the Government budget. The specific objectives of this component&#13;
are to:&#13;
&#13;
        0   Help establish an audit committee to provide oversight of the Internal Auditing&#13;
            Service;&#13;
&#13;
        0   Create an organizational structure which will remove the current influence of&#13;
            individualministries over the work of internal audit;&#13;
&#13;
        0   Strengthen the working practices of internal audit to carry out more operational&#13;
            reviews and evaluationsof internal control systems; and&#13;
&#13;
        0   Provide training and support to facilitate this transition.&#13;
&#13;
36.     A program of professional and technical training for internal audit staff will also be&#13;
identified. This may be conductedinconjunction with that for other MOF staff andthose ofthe&#13;
Control and Audit Office (CAO).&#13;
&#13;
        Component 4:           Strengthening External Audit Capacity within Government&#13;
        (US$4,500,000)&#13;
&#13;
37.     The Control and Audit Regulation issued under the Budget Law in 1985 makes the&#13;
General Control and Inspection Presidency of the Council of Ministers (now the CAO) the&#13;
supreme audit authority for the whole of Government, providing expost external audit. The&#13;
primary activities of the CAO are to check budget expenditure and revenue collection for&#13;
compliance with regulations and report discrepancies for corrective action. The CAO audits the&#13;
FinalAccount of the MOF and also undertakes external audits inthe provinces.&#13;
&#13;
38.     Since August 2002 the Audit Agent funded under EPAP Ihas provided operational&#13;
support and capacity building assistance to the CAO. It has also assisted inpreparing a draft HR&#13;
assessment covering training needs, training strategy, HR management, and a staff qualifications&#13;
inventory. A range of training activities, both formal (including training in English, computer&#13;
literacy, and basic accounting) and on-the-job training through the conduct of audits, have been&#13;
conducted with more than 100 CAO staff taking part. Inaddition, an audit law has been drafted&#13;
as well as a draft strategic plan.&#13;
&#13;
39.     These early steps have been successful inreestablishingthe CAO as a working institution&#13;
but have not developed the institution and its staff sufficiently for them to conduct financial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
statement audits to international standards without substantial professional assistance.        A&#13;
program o f assistance for several more years will be neededto achieve this goal.&#13;
&#13;
40.    The external audit component will provide technical advisory services, equipment, and&#13;
training to support the CAO in strengthening capacity to provide comprehensive auditing&#13;
services in accordance with the International Organization o f Supreme Audit Institutions&#13;
(INTOSAI) auditing standards. TA will be providedto the CAO inorder to:&#13;
&#13;
    A. Undertake core audit operations to acceptable international standards and to provide on-&#13;
       the-job training for staff inthe CAO.&#13;
&#13;
    B. Strengthen the audit environment and the capacity o f the CAO to conduct audits to&#13;
       international standards. Activities will include: (i) assistance in the development o f the&#13;
       audit regulatory environment including the completion o f any necessary legislation and&#13;
       regulations; (ii)conduct o f a comprehensive HR and training needs assessment to&#13;
       determine the managerial and professional training requirements o f CAO staff; and (iii)&#13;
       coordination o f training identified under the needs assessment.&#13;
&#13;
    C. Conduct a program o f managerial and professional development training for CAO staff.&#13;
       This will be based on the needs assessment conducted under subcomponent 4 (B).&#13;
       Training activities may be conducted jointly with training under the internal audit and&#13;
       financial management components.&#13;
&#13;
    D. Developprofessionalaccountingandaudit capacity inthe public and private sectors.&#13;
&#13;
    E. Develop the system for scrutiny and response to audit reports including responses by&#13;
       involved ministries and scrutiny by a Public Accounts Committee o f the Parliament.&#13;
&#13;
        Component&#13;
        (us$l,soo,ooo)5:      Other Institutional     Strengthening and       Capacity  Building&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
41.    EPAP I1provided support for the Government's emerging administrative reform program&#13;
implemented through the IARCSC. Although assistance inthis area has recently been launched,&#13;
the need for additional funding is already anticipated.      This may include assistance to the&#13;
Government inrationalizing ministries and in implementing a government-wide pay and grading&#13;
review. Fundshave beenincluded under this component to cover additional assistance as well as&#13;
emerging priority needs o f the Government inareas related to the overall project objective. The&#13;
envisaged areas o f assistance include:&#13;
&#13;
        0  Further support for the IARCSC inthe management o fthe PAR program;&#13;
&#13;
        0  Support for the Government inmanaging donor-funded TA; and&#13;
&#13;
        0  TA to the MOF to develop and implement strategies to transform itself into a&#13;
           strategically focused, service oriented, professionally staffed institution and a best-&#13;
           practice leader for the government sector over a five-year period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
42.     Cost Estimates. The costs estimated for each component are based on calculations&#13;
performed by the Bank team using unit rates on contracts under the current EPAP Iand I1&#13;
projects.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Component                                                                                                                                                                                         US$&#13;
        ................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................x&#13;
             1. StrengtheningProcurementCapacitywithin Government                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   9,000,000&#13;
         .................................................................................&#13;
            2. StrengtheningFinanc                                                                                                                                                                   city within Government&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                     .............................................                         ...............................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     8,000,000&#13;
        ..................................................................................&#13;
            3. StrengtheningInterna                                                                                                                                                                  inGovernment&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                     ......................................................................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    4,000,000&#13;
         ................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................T&#13;
            4. StrengtheningExternal Audit Capacity within Government                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               4,500,000&#13;
            5. Other Institutional Strengtheningand CapacityBuilding                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 1,500,000&#13;
                                                  Total                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        27,000,000&#13;
&#13;
                                        Iv.                  PROJECT IMPLEMENTATIONAND OVERSIGHT ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
A. ImplementationArrangements&#13;
&#13;
43.     The project has three implementing agencies:                                                                                                                                                                                                               ARDS/PPU, MOF, and the CAO.&#13;
Subcomponent 1 (A) and (B) will be managed by the ARDS. The Government i s inthe process&#13;
of reviewing the number and organizational structure o f ministries and it i s likely that the&#13;
procurement facilitation function currently held by ARDS may be moved into a new ministry.&#13;
Implementation responsibility for the procurement facilitation and capacity building&#13;
subcomponents will be moved accordingly. Subcomponent 1 (C) will be implemented by a&#13;
nascent PPU. Final location o f the PPU has yet to be determined. Inthe interimthe ARDS will&#13;
manage this subcomponent but commencement o f major activities will not occur until such time&#13;
as the location o f the PPU i s determined.&#13;
&#13;
44.     The M O F will implement the financial management components and internal audit&#13;
components. The external audit component will be implemented by the CAO. The CAO will&#13;
also take the lead in implementing the activities relating to the audit environment and audit&#13;
standards in conjunction with other relevant agencies. Component 5 will be managed primarily&#13;
by the MOF who will approve requests for assistance under this component inclose liaison with&#13;
the IARCSC.&#13;
&#13;
45.      CounterpartArrangements. As agreed with the Government, each o f the components&#13;
will be managed by a clearly designated counterpart team. Indeed, the experience of EPAP Iand&#13;
I1 demonstrated that the lack o f counterpart staff within implementing agencies severely&#13;
underminedefforts at capacity building.&#13;
&#13;
46.     Inthis regard, sustained progress on PRR implementation will be important. All of the&#13;
implementing agencies, except for the ARDS, have or are in the process o f applying for PRR.&#13;
The Treasury and Internal Audit Directorates of the MOF are well advanced in recruiting new&#13;
staff to PRR scales. The CAO has also attained stage 2 PRR status and it is anticipated that the&#13;
Procurement Unit will come under PRR status in the next budget. These institutional reform&#13;
efforts will help to provide a conducive operating environment to reforms and capacity building.&#13;
The IARCSC will monitor progress in PRR implementation, identify major issues, and seek&#13;
solutions with concerned line ministries to resolve them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                         12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
B. Procurement,FinancialManagement,and Audit Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
47.      The Government has expressed a strong desire to explore the possibility o f using&#13;
twinning arrangements for delivery of capacity building TA in the key public expenditure&#13;
management areas. Normally, twinning arrangements are characterized by a closer involvement&#13;
betweenthe two parties than is generally obtained ina standard client-consultant relationship.&#13;
&#13;
48.      The Government i s in the process o f identifying potential twinning partners for the&#13;
various capacity buildingactivities. Should twinning arrangements fail to materialize within the&#13;
agreed time frame, procurement for consultancy contracts to provide the technical services&#13;
required will follow normal Bank procurement guidelines.          Each implementing entity i s&#13;
responsible for providing terms of reference and selection criteria to the ARDS Procurement&#13;
Unit which, with support from the procurement facilitation consultant, will undertake the&#13;
procurement process for the remaining contracts. These arrangements are designed to ensure&#13;
compliance with IDA procurement procedures and expedite implementation o f project activities.&#13;
Annex 2 provides more information on procurement arrangements.&#13;
&#13;
49.      IDA has gained considerable experience over the past two years as to the functioning of&#13;
the Government's financial management system. The overall assessment is that the country's&#13;
financial  management system has improved, but that further progress i s needed particularly in&#13;
line ministries where capacity i s very weak. Fiduciary risks have, however, been mitigated by&#13;
the engagement o f the financial management consultant and the Government's decision to&#13;
centralize payment and receipt processing through the Treasury. This project will focus on&#13;
strengthening the financial management system within Government.           IDA has initiated in&#13;
FY2005 a Country Financial Accountability Assessment, along with a Country Procurement&#13;
Assessment Report, as part o f a planned Public Expenditure Review to be delivered inFY2006.&#13;
&#13;
50.      Disbursements from the grant will be transaction based. Approximately 70 percent o f&#13;
the grant proceeds will be disbursedthrough direct payments to consultants or twinning partners.&#13;
The Grant Agreement will provide a Special Account (SA) with an authorized allocation o f up to&#13;
US$ 1,000,000 to facilitate payment for other eligible project expenditures. This SA will be&#13;
opened and maintained in a commercial bank or Afghanistan's central bank on terms and&#13;
conditions acceptable to the Association.&#13;
&#13;
51.      Retroactivefinancing. A provision has been made to reimburse the Government for&#13;
payments it makes, up to a maximum o f US$ 3 million equivalent, for eligible project&#13;
expenditures incurred after November 1, 2004 and up to the signing o f the Development Grant&#13;
Agreement, in accordance with the Bank's procurement guidelines. In particular, and given its&#13;
urgency and priority, this provision i s expected to be utilized in part to facilitate the early&#13;
mobilization o f the procurement facilitation consultant.&#13;
&#13;
52.      Audit. The CAO, with the support o f the audit consultant, will audit the accounts o f the&#13;
project under terms o f reference acceptable to IDA. The annual project financial statements,&#13;
audited by the CAO, will be submitted within six months of the close of the Government's fiscal&#13;
year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C. Project Oversight&#13;
&#13;
53.     Broad oversight and management o f EPAP Iand I1proved to be difficult as a result o f&#13;
multiple implementing agencies. The Government has therefore agreed that a project oversight&#13;
committee, chaired by the MOF, will be established to monitor progress under the various&#13;
components, ensure coordination, and approve reallocations within the budget total where&#13;
needed.&#13;
&#13;
D. Monitoringand Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
54.     Monitoring and evaluation will be based upon a set o f specific and monitorable&#13;
legislative, policy, institutional, and HR development actions (monitoring indicators) that are&#13;
critical for achieving the project objectives and are clearly linked to results.          Specific&#13;
benchmarks will be agreed between the Government and TA providers early in implementation&#13;
so as to measure specific progress inmeeting capacity building objectives. Intensive supervision&#13;
by IDA during the first half o f the project period is planned to help ensure that any&#13;
implementation issues are dealt with promptly. At a minimum, a full supervision mission i s&#13;
needed twice a year, comprising appropriate specialists from each of the component areas. The&#13;
MOF will have the primary responsibility to prepare and furnish to IDA quarterly progress&#13;
reports highlightingprogress in undertaking the actions required to achieve project development&#13;
objectives. Annex 4 provides details on monitoring indicators.&#13;
                                      v. BENEFITSAND RISKS&#13;
&#13;
55.     The project will support the Government's effort to build solid foundations for a modern,&#13;
effective, and accountable public administration with a particular focus on building the capacity&#13;
o fpublic institutions to manage resources for better budgetary outcomes and development results&#13;
on the ground. Successful implementation o f the project will help to provide assurance to the&#13;
Afghan public as well as the international community as to the effective and accountable&#13;
utilization o f external assistance and thus, secure the country's continued access to development&#13;
assistance. There are several significant risks as described below.&#13;
&#13;
56.     Thefragile political environment is a major risk factor which poses some uncertainties&#13;
as to the Government's ability to stay on course during the post-election period and over the&#13;
medium term with regard to the broad legislative, policy, and institutional reforms that are&#13;
necessary for sustainability o f the project's outcomes, To partially address this risk, IDA will&#13;
intensify dialogue with the new Government's cabinet, and with senior management in line&#13;
ministries to continue building up and broadening the ownership of the reforms and capacity&#13;
buildingprograms supported bythe project.&#13;
&#13;
57.     The inability of implementing agencies to adequately recruit counterpart staff will&#13;
continue to constitute a risk to the capacity building strategy. Having adequate counterpart&#13;
teams in place will be especially critical to the success o f those components using twinning&#13;
arrangements. Provision o f substantive TA may weaken the urgency for some agencies to&#13;
aggressively recruit and fill key positions. The project will cxefully monitor this and sequence&#13;
packages o f training and other capacity buildinginitiatives with continuing progress inrecruiting&#13;
competent staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
58.     Lack of clarity over functional responsibilities between internal audit and external&#13;
audit and between departments within MOF may inhibit progress in a number o f areas and&#13;
create overlap and confusion. The MOF i s in the process o f defining its overall vision and&#13;
strategies to achieve the vision for the next five years. Among other things, the strategies will&#13;
address its internal structure and its relationship with other Government ministriedagencies,&#13;
including the CAO. The project-supported capacity building programs will be implemented in&#13;
line with the agreed division o f roles and functions.&#13;
&#13;
59.     Difficulty in attracting suitably qualified twinning partners may delay project&#13;
implementation. In recognition o f this risk, the Government has agreed that a specific time&#13;
frame will be set within which a search for suitable partners will be undertaken. If twinning&#13;
arrangements fail to develop within the agreed time frame, procurement for consultancy services&#13;
for major technical assistance packages will commence immediately.         Until such time as&#13;
experienced twinning partners andor selected consultants have staff in place to support the&#13;
Treasury, the core staff o f the incumbent financial management consultants will be retained so&#13;
that there are no unnecessary disruptions inbudget execution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       ANNEX1: TERMS REFERENCE MAJOR&#13;
                            OF              FOR          TECHNICAL    ASSISTANCEPACKAGES&#13;
&#13;
Component1. StrengtheningProcurementCapacitywithinGovernment&#13;
&#13;
1.       Background. As part o f the mid-term review o f EPAP, a review o f progress o f the&#13;
procurement component o f EPAP Iand EPAP I1was conducted in January 2004. The purpose&#13;
o f this review was to identify key constraints to achieving the EPAP Iand I1objectives and to&#13;
recommend future actions and a scope o f work for implementing the procurement component o f&#13;
the proposed third public administration project, namely the Public Administration Capacity&#13;
Building Project (PACBP).&#13;
&#13;
2.       A number of constraints were identified and recommendations made most notably with&#13;
respect to the need to more substantively transfer procurement capacity as well as responsibility&#13;
for procurement functions to line ministries. Insummary these issues included:&#13;
&#13;
         0  Procurement capacity at all levels in the Government is limited. This i s a serious&#13;
             impediment to reform and ways must be found to create interest inthis reform at the&#13;
            highest political level, as well as on an operational level.&#13;
&#13;
         0   There are a number o f obstacles to developing capacity, for example: (i) o f    lack&#13;
             adequate training (both inthe public and private sectors); (ii) misunderstanding o f the&#13;
             scope o f the procurement function; (iii)inappropriate regulations; (iv) lack o f&#13;
             common internal structures to deal with procurement inthe line ministries; (v) lack o f&#13;
             communication between trained procurement staff and senior administrators; and&#13;
             (vi) no clear incentives for improvement and ownership.&#13;
&#13;
         0   There i s no consistency in the organizational structures o f the line ministries with&#13;
             respect to the procurement function.       In transferring procurement capacity and&#13;
             responsibility to the line ministries, flexibility is required to retain and/or remodel&#13;
             internal administrative structures as appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
3.       The review recognizedthat there would be a continued need for centralized procurement&#13;
services for some time. But there needed to be an accelerated effort to build procurement&#13;
capacity within line ministries so that they can progressively be accredited with increased&#13;
delegated authority for procurement management within a structure and agreed institutional and&#13;
legal framework.&#13;
&#13;
4.       Proposed Services. The services required as part o f the procurement component of&#13;
PACBP can be grouped into three main categories: (i)           procurement facilitation consultancy&#13;
services; (ii)capacity building; and (iii)     the legal and institutional framework development&#13;
(regulatory reform). As a result o f the significant scope o f work involved, these components will&#13;
likely be awarded inseparate lots.&#13;
&#13;
5.       Subcomponent I (A). The ARDS i s in the process o f finalizing the recruitment o f a&#13;
consultant to provide services for the first component, i.e., procurement facilitation consultancy&#13;
services. This consultancy will continue to provide support to line ministries inthe procurement&#13;
o f major goods, works, and services funded under donor and government-fundedprograms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6.      Subcomponent 1 (B). Capacity Building. The objective will be twofold: to build the&#13;
capacity o f procurement officers o f the client and its line ministries, and to strengthen the&#13;
organizational structure of the procurement function within procuring entities with a view to&#13;
transferring responsibility to them.&#13;
&#13;
7.      This will require the development and implementation of a: (i)     sustainable nationwide&#13;
capacity building strategy to take into account the requirements not only o f central government&#13;
but also provincial andmunicipal government as well as the private sector; (ii)  program to assist&#13;
and facilitate the achievement o f PRR status for a number o f key ministries to be identified;&#13;
(iii) totransferprocurementcapacityandresponsibilitytolineministriesaccordingtoaset&#13;
     plan&#13;
of milestones; and (iv) system o f attestation whereby the performance o f ministries can be&#13;
assessedagainst identified benchmarks.&#13;
&#13;
8.      The process envisaged involves the creation o f a sustainable capacity buildingprogram&#13;
for individual procurement officers in the Government leading to certification and the ultimate&#13;
creation o f a class o f procurement professionals. This program will be conducted using national&#13;
training structures which will need to be developed by the technical adviser. This must be seen&#13;
as part o f a process through which procuring entities also develop their own internal capacity to&#13;
conduct procurement efficiently and is, therefore, linked to the assistance to be provided to&#13;
procuring entities under this component to achieve PRR status.&#13;
&#13;
9.      The ultimate goal o f this component is to transfer responsibility for procurement to line&#13;
ministries and other procuring entities that have demonstrated satisfactory procurement capacity&#13;
(both in terms o f individual procurement officers and internal organization o f the procurement&#13;
function) and to do so gradually using milestones indicating increasing levels o f capacity. The&#13;
entire process will be gauged through an attestation system which will provide benchmarks&#13;
against which achievement inattaining the milestones can be measured.&#13;
&#13;
10.     Subcomponent 1 (C). Servicesfor Legal and Institutional Framework Development.&#13;
This proposedassignment shall carry forward the task o f achieving the desired status o f legal and&#13;
institutional framework development for procurement inthe country.&#13;
&#13;
11.     The objectives of this component, therefore, are to complete the legal framework and to&#13;
assist in the development o f the appropriate institutional framework and effective review&#13;
mechanisms to secure implementation o f the new public procurement law and related&#13;
procurement reforms. This component requires focus on a strategy to develop and improve the&#13;
institutional framework. This will involve:&#13;
&#13;
        0   Completion o f the legislative framework through the drafting and adoption o f&#13;
            appropriate secondary legislation;&#13;
&#13;
        0   Assistance with the establishment o f a PPU at an appropriate hierarchical level in&#13;
            Afghanistan;&#13;
&#13;
        0   Design and implementation of an independent complaints review mechanism together&#13;
            withthe rules ofprocedure andwork systems; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        0   Training o f review panel members in appropriate procurement matters and dispute&#13;
            resolution techniques.&#13;
&#13;
Component2. StrengtheningFinancialManagementCapacitywithin Government&#13;
&#13;
12.     Background.      The current Government figcal management system i s under the&#13;
administration of the MOF which i s responsible for budget preparation, budget execution,&#13;
accounting, reporting, payroll, revenue and customs administration, debt management, cash&#13;
management, and a range o f functions inGovernment asset administration.&#13;
&#13;
13.     The Government has begun a program of financial management improvement which i s&#13;
expected to have far-reaching consequences for the manner and processes o f financial&#13;
transactions, recording, accounting, and reporting over the next several years. The extent o f&#13;
these reforms i s evolving but includes budget and expenditure reforms and improved accounting,&#13;
financial reporting, and internal controls. The Government has drafted a new Public Finance and&#13;
Expenditure Management Law which i s expected to be approved by the end o f December 2004&#13;
(thisapproval is atrigger for the secondPSIB).&#13;
&#13;
14.     The review of EPAP Iand I1found that the Treasury, with the support o f the financial&#13;
management agent, had achieved much since August 2002 when the financial management agent&#13;
contract was signed. Core check printing, budget control, and accounting functions o f an&#13;
AFMIS have been implemented in the Treasury o f the MOF. Significant improvements have&#13;
been made in cash management, grant management, bank reconciliations, revenue recording, and&#13;
the recording o f budget appropriations and allotments.&#13;
&#13;
15.     A PRR proposal for the Treasury Department is under implementation which will enable&#13;
the Treasury to restructure its operations and staffing to improve services to customers,&#13;
streamline internal operations, and improve implementationo f Government policy.&#13;
&#13;
16.     However, capacity buildinghas not progressed as much as planned due to several factors.&#13;
Delays in recruiting staff under the PRR have inhibited capacity transfer. Work pressures to&#13;
support critical Treasury operations, data collection and cleanup, and transaction processing&#13;
activities divertedthe attention o fthe financial management agent.&#13;
&#13;
17.     Inaddition, the EPAP review concluded that althoughAFMIS hadproven to be effective&#13;
inquickly establishing a computerizedTreasury payment and accounting system, it has still not&#13;
become a fully comprehensive and functional management information system able to meet the&#13;
needs o f Government over the long term, including ultimately serving the provinces and line&#13;
ministries. It has been agreed that further development o f the system should be based on a&#13;
systematic review o f the long-term financial management information requirements o f the&#13;
Government as proposed inthe study TOR and as outlined below.&#13;
&#13;
18.     Objectives.   The objectives o f the Government in the area o f financial management&#13;
include maintaining appropriate fiduciary standards to provide reasonable assurance to the&#13;
Afghan public and to international donors that Government resources and donor funds are&#13;
subject to appropriate allocation and expenditure controls. An important objective is achieving&#13;
compliance with international standards o f financial management, including the use o f&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
internationally recognized accounting, auditing, and reporting standards enabled by modern&#13;
technology and software applications.&#13;
&#13;
19.      Scope of Services. The financial management component will assist MOF and line&#13;
ministries to build capacity and attain higher levels o f efficiency in budget execution and&#13;
financial reporting. This assistance will be provided through Financial Management Technical&#13;
Advisory Services (either through a regular consultancy or a specifically identified twinning&#13;
arrangement with another experienced public expenditure management institution), a separate&#13;
training contract, and the conduct and phased implementation o f a financial management systems&#13;
architecture study. Specific milestones will be set over the period o f the contract to achieve the&#13;
objectives o f the component.&#13;
&#13;
20.      Subcomponent 2 (A). FMISArchitectureStudy. Under EPAP Ia fledgling AFMIS was&#13;
established.    It has proven to be effective in quickly establishing a computerized Treasury&#13;
payment and accounting system but, as it was designed to focus on these core functions, it falls&#13;
short o f being a fully comprehensive and functional management information system able to&#13;
meet the needs o f Government over the long term. The Government would now like to extend&#13;
the functionality and reach o f this system in a way that takes into account the particular&#13;
circumstances within Afghanistan and after a systematic review o f the medium- to long-term&#13;
financial management information requirements o f the Government.&#13;
&#13;
21.      FreeBalance software i s the core application o f the current AFMIS. It is expected that&#13;
AFMIS will continue to run on the FreeBalance software over the next few years; however, its&#13;
longer-term retention will depend upon the recommendations o f a systems architecture study&#13;
which will seek to define an overall systems architecture for the central, provincial, and district&#13;
governments inAfghanistan to serve as a roadmap for a phased implementation.&#13;
&#13;
22.      The objective o f the study i s to determine and describe the core business processes and&#13;
the associated user andtechnical requirements for AFMIS ina way that would meet the needs o f&#13;
Government over the long term. The solution need not be the same at each level o f Government,&#13;
but a seamless interface of data and information across all levels is required. The systems should&#13;
be sufficiently flexible to enable subsequent changes to be incorporated. The resulting solutions&#13;
may then be implemented at different times but the Government will have the assurance that the&#13;
overall financial management architecture i s well designed and integrated and incorporates the&#13;
latest risk management techniques.&#13;
&#13;
23.      In order to define these requirements it will be necessary for the consultants to work&#13;
closely with counterparts in the Government and with TA advisors to arrive at an agreed&#13;
financial management framework. These requirements will then form the basis o f a Request for&#13;
Proposal (RFP) to identify suitable systems solutions that are able to be interfaced with the&#13;
Government's approved business processes and phased implementation plan. The consultant&#13;
will support the Government in the preparation of the RFP and also support the Government&#13;
through the procurement stage that follows, ifnecessary.&#13;
&#13;
24.      The project provides limited funds for rollout o f financial management systems&#13;
depending upon the outcome o f the systems study and decisions o f the Government with regard&#13;
to the appropriate pace o f development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25.    Subcomponent2 (B). Financial Management Technical Advisory Services.                  This&#13;
assignment, which will continue and expand upon the work o f the previous financial&#13;
management consultancy, has a number o f distinct butrelated components:&#13;
&#13;
            Operating, maintaining, and enhancing the existing AFMIS, including on-the-job&#13;
           training for Government staff;&#13;
&#13;
           Processing transactions for the national budget including World Bank-funded projects&#13;
           and projects o f other donors incorporated inthe budgeto f IRoA;&#13;
&#13;
           Further developing the chart o f accounts to meet International Monetary Fund&#13;
            Government Finance Statistics reporting standards and budget management&#13;
           requirements;&#13;
&#13;
           Accounting and periodic financial reportingto the Government and donors;&#13;
&#13;
           Implementingverified payroll plan;&#13;
&#13;
           Reviewing the financial control framework; developing and implementing financial&#13;
           regulations consistent with public financial expenditure management law;&#13;
&#13;
           Developing the cash management function inthe Treasury o f MOF;&#13;
&#13;
           Preparing and implementing a Treasury development strategy; and&#13;
&#13;
           Developing an HR management strategy, assessing training needs, and coordinating&#13;
           the training component undertaken under a separate contract.&#13;
&#13;
26.    At the end of the three-year period of assistance it is expected that full systems handover&#13;
and knowledge transfer to Government staff will be achieved. A set o f milestones will be&#13;
established early inassignment inception to measure performance.&#13;
&#13;
27.    Subcomponent 2 (C). Financial Management Training. This component will be&#13;
developed following the training needs assessment undertaken by the financial management&#13;
technical advisor. The purpose o f having a separate training component i s to provide a dedicated&#13;
training team that can focus exclusively on training needs and not be distracted from this task by&#13;
day-to-day operational crises. On-the-job training will, however, continue to be provided by the&#13;
financial management technical advisor who is best placed to convey information about the&#13;
financial management system.&#13;
&#13;
Component3: StrengtheningInternalAudit Capacitywithin Government&#13;
&#13;
28.    Background. There are currently designated internal audit departments operating inkey&#13;
line ministries which report directly to their ministers. They do not carry out work that would be&#13;
considered to comply with recognized intemational internal auditing standards. The internal&#13;
audit departments cannot be regardedas independent, being heavily influenced by the ministries&#13;
withinwhich they function. There is no higher independent authority to oversee their work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
29.     Internal audit work i s currently focused on identification o f irregularities and&#13;
investigation o f potential corruption and fraud. Where crime i s identified, cases are passed to the&#13;
Attorney General for legal action. No reviews o f internal control processes are carried out.&#13;
&#13;
30.     Ministries carry out internal audit training themselves mainly through the use o f internal&#13;
seminars to discuss problems and resolve issues. No formal academic or professional training in&#13;
internal auditing is available in Afghanistan. Some "proactive" work i s being carried out (e.g.,&#13;
by internal auditors in the Ministries o f Education and Telecommunications) to provide&#13;
recommendations for improvements in operational effectiveness. The level o f information and&#13;
communication technologies knowledge and experience within the current internal audit&#13;
departments is very low. There i s no attempt to carry out internal audits using automated tools.&#13;
&#13;
31.     Objectives.   The specific purpose o f this component i s to establish the necessary&#13;
framework within the M O F and other key ministries for an effective internal audit service which&#13;
follows generally recognized international standards for internal auditing. The initial focus will&#13;
be on providing a modern internal auditing service within the MOF. Work will then be done to&#13;
extend this to other ministries based upontheir size and levels o f expenditure.&#13;
&#13;
32.     The wider objective o f this component i s to contribute to the establishment o f sound&#13;
financial management within the public sector. This will make possible greater accountability&#13;
for financial expenditures o f the Government -both centrally and in the provinces, provide a&#13;
means to operate standard income and expenditures controls, and support an independent review&#13;
of the processes.    The introduction o f sound internal financial controls will enable greater&#13;
transparency inthe Government's decisionmaking.&#13;
&#13;
33.     Scope of Services. Technical advisory services, equipment, and training will be provided&#13;
to support the Director o f the Internal Audit Department inthe MOF withthe following activities&#13;
to:&#13;
&#13;
         0  Establish a cadre o f trained internal auditors firstly inthe M O F and then in other key&#13;
            ministries. While this i s in process, work will continue inthe existing internal audit&#13;
            departments.&#13;
&#13;
         0  With the MOF, develop internal auditing policies, standards, and regulations to be&#13;
            referenced in an Internal Audit Manual. This manual will be used to extend the&#13;
            development o f internal auditing to other ministries.&#13;
&#13;
         0  Review the organizational structure o f internal auditing departments inministries and&#13;
            propose organizational changes to adopt the best structure to facilitate the changed&#13;
            working practices within the Government's overall reform effort.&#13;
&#13;
         0  Conduct initial audits, then cadres o f internal auditors will carry out audit reviews&#13;
           within each ministry. The results o f each audit will then be used to specify more&#13;
            focused testing to be carried out by the auditors who have not yet beentrained inthe&#13;
            new working practices (as well as providing an assessment o f the effectiveness o f&#13;
            internal control).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        0   Develop further cadres of internal auditors with internal audit training until all&#13;
            internalauditors are fully trained inmodern internal audit methods.&#13;
&#13;
        0   Launch comprehensive training of internal auditors based on a training needs&#13;
            assessment to be undertakenby the internal audit consultant and in conjunction with&#13;
            training of other MOF and CAO staff.&#13;
&#13;
34.     Outputs. The main output of these activities will be a modern functionally independent&#13;
internal audit service which will be free from operational duties that will be available to offer&#13;
advice and assistance to managers in mitigating business risk to achieve the objectives of their&#13;
ministries and the Government.&#13;
&#13;
Component4: StrengtheningExternalAudit Capacitywithin Government&#13;
&#13;
35.     Background. At the end of Taliban rule, the overall external audit environment in&#13;
Afghanistan was very weak as could be expected after 20 years of war and instability. At that&#13;
time, the financial reporting framework had almost completely broken down particularly with&#13;
regard to provincial reporting and the production of final accounts. There was inadequate&#13;
capacity withinthe CAO andwithinother ministries and departments. While on paper there was&#13;
a relatively sound, systematic approachto expenditure management with laws, regulations, and&#13;
manuals containing controls and transaction recording processes, in reality, the system was not&#13;
operational.&#13;
&#13;
36.     The primary activities of the CAO are to check budget expenditure and revenue&#13;
collection for compliance with regulations and report discrepancies for corrective action. The&#13;
independence of the Auditor General has been confirmed by Presidential Decree. The Control&#13;
and Audit Regulation issued under the Budget Law in 1985 makes the General Control and&#13;
InspectionPresidency of the Council of Ministers (now the CAO) the supreme audit authority for&#13;
the whole of Government under the Auditor Generalproviding expost external audit. The CAO&#13;
audits the FinalAccount of the MOF and is also undertaking external audits inthe provinces.&#13;
&#13;
37.     Since August 2002, an audit agent funded by a World Bank grant under EPAP Ihas been&#13;
providing operational support and capacity building assistance to the CAO. Although it was not&#13;
originally envisaged that the audit agent would play a significant role in the conduct of audits,&#13;
the scarcity o f qualified accountants and the lack of understanding o f financial statement audits&#13;
within the CAO has meant that the audit agent has had to play a significant role in the actual&#13;
conduct of audits. During this period, the CAO has completed or is inthe process of completing,&#13;
with the assistance of the audit agent, the audit of a number of World Bank and ARTF-funded&#13;
projects, the audit of ARTF contributions to the recurrent budget, and the audit of the state&#13;
budget.&#13;
&#13;
38.     The audit agent also prepared a draft HR assessment covering training needs, training&#13;
strategy, HR management, and a staff qualifications inventory. A range of formal training&#13;
activities including English, computer literacy, and basic accounting, and on-the-job training&#13;
through the conduct of audits have been conducted with more than 100 CAO stafftaking part. In&#13;
addition, an audit law has beendrafted as well as a draft strategic planpreparedfor the CAO.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
39.     These early steps have been successful inreestablishing the CAO as a working institution&#13;
capable of absorbing institutional strengthening assistance, but it has not developed the&#13;
institution and its staff sufficiently for them to conduct financial statement audits to international&#13;
standards without substantial professional assistance. A program of assistance for several more&#13;
years will be neededto achievethis goal.&#13;
&#13;
40.     Within the CAO, most senior staff have beenreplaced and more qualified persons have&#13;
been recruited at lower levels.      The current level of audit staff is 190 out of an authorized&#13;
complement of 315. Because local graduates with modern accounting knowledge are generally&#13;
unavailable and also because many of the recent recruits have law or other degrees, there i s a&#13;
need for additional professional training on entry.&#13;
&#13;
41.     Objectives. This component seeks to consolidate and enhance the improvements made&#13;
over the past two years to enable the CAO to increasingly provide comprehensive auditing&#13;
services inaccordance with INTOSAI auditing standards.&#13;
&#13;
42.     Assistance will be provided through: (i)     technical advisory services in audit operations&#13;
and capacity building; (ii)   professional training; (iii) to strengthen professional accounting&#13;
                                                         TA&#13;
and audit standards and capacity throughout the country; and (iv) TA to develop the system for&#13;
scrutiny and responseto audit reports including responsesby involvedministries and scrutiny by&#13;
a legislative Public Accounts Committee.&#13;
&#13;
43.     Subcomponent 4 (A). Technical Advisory Services. Technical advisory services will&#13;
provide support to the Auditor General's office in audit operations, institutional strengthening&#13;
through capacity building, on-the-job training, and development of the regulatory environment.&#13;
Specific milestones will be set over the period of the contract to achieve capacity building&#13;
objectives. Key activities will be:&#13;
&#13;
        (a) Support to Audit Operations. Assistance will be provided to the Auditor General's&#13;
        Office for audit operations with a focus on direct, technical audit support and informal&#13;
        on-the-job training to the CAO teams undertaking audits of the SY1383, 1384, and 1385&#13;
        financial statements for the ARTF, the Government's annual accounts, IDA and ARTF&#13;
        projects, and selectedprojects fundedby other donors.&#13;
&#13;
        On-the-job training provided during actual audit of accounts is regarded as a key part of&#13;
        the capacity building being provided to CAO staff through knowledge transfer. While&#13;
        the participation of local staff on actual audits as part of their training program may&#13;
        increase audit costs, this additional cost is more than compensated by the knowledge&#13;
        transfer achieved and the overall contribution to capacity building.&#13;
&#13;
        (3) Institutional Strengthening The new Audit Adviser will be expected to continue to&#13;
        provide high-level, strategic institutional development advice to assist the CAO to&#13;
        progress toward a modern supreme audit institution with effective influence on the audit&#13;
        environment and governance framework in Afghanistan. To this end, the adviser will&#13;
        assist the CAO in completing the Strategic Development Plan and further developing its&#13;
        HR development strategy to enable the CAO to perform the majority of audits of grants&#13;
        and loans to Government to appropriate international standards. The adviser will propose&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        specific milestones to be achieved in capacity building such as increased numbers o f&#13;
        local staff leading audits. In particular, the consultant will undertake a training needs&#13;
        assessment and complete revision o f the HR development strategy within the first six&#13;
        months o f the assignment. A separate consultant or twinning arrangement will assist in&#13;
        the development and implementation o f an effective audit law and in the subsequent&#13;
        writing o f regulations.&#13;
&#13;
44.     Subcomponent 4 (B). Professional and Technical Training. Assistance has been&#13;
provided to CAO staff with core capacity building through basic classroom training in audit,&#13;
accountancy, English, and computer skills. Continuation o f this basic training will be contracted&#13;
separately, possibly as a twinningarrangement inconjunction with training o f internal audit staff&#13;
and other MOF staff. Training needs and possible suppliers or twinning arrangements will be&#13;
identified through the training needs assessmentconducted under subcomponent 4 (A).&#13;
&#13;
45.     Subcomponent 4 (C). Accounting and Auditing Professional Standards. Trained&#13;
accountants and a legislative framework to regulate accounting are needed to improve&#13;
governance in both the private and public sectors. The terms o f reference o f this activity will&#13;
include assistance in establishing the accounting profession and the supporting regulatory and&#13;
academic frameworks.        The various degree courses o f Kabul University related to financial&#13;
management and accounting do not incorporate a modern curriculum and academic capacity has&#13;
eroded. There is currently no accounting profession or professional body inAfghanistan. There&#13;
i s a need to establish an overall accounting framework, including establishing a Government&#13;
supported body responsible for adopting the International Federation o f Accountants (IFAC)&#13;
international standards, regulating the accounting profession, and setting new curricula for the&#13;
main academic bodies delivering accounting training at the various levels. This subcomponent&#13;
may be undertakenas part o f a twinning arrangement.&#13;
&#13;
46.     Subcomponent4 (0).Public Accounts Committee. The terms o f reference will include&#13;
establishing a system o f response and scrutiny for external and internal audit reports to improve&#13;
the effectiveness of audit.     The Constitution has paved the way for elections and eventual&#13;
creation o f legislative scrutiny bodies.    Currently, only two percent o f Government bodies&#13;
respond to audit reports on their activities. There i s no involvement o f the MOF in dealing with&#13;
audit reports. An overall assessment o f the actions taken by Government agencies on the most&#13;
recent audit reports should be made through a comprehensive survey.&#13;
&#13;
47.     A formal evaluation o f options for developing an overall framework for the scrutiny and&#13;
follow-up o f audit reports based on models in other countries should be made and a system for&#13;
Afghanistan designed. Assistance should be provided in the formation o f an interim ad-hoc&#13;
scrutiny committee to examine heads o f agencies on recent audit reports and subsequently to&#13;
help the National Assembly in any action that it wishes to take in the formation o f a Public&#13;
Accounts Committee. This subcomponent may be undertaken as part o f a twinning arrangement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           ANNEX2: PROCUREMENTARRANGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
A. General&#13;
&#13;
48.    Procurement for the proposedproject would be carried out inaccordance with the World&#13;
Bank's "Guidelines: Procurement Under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" dated May 2004 and&#13;
"Guidelines: Selection and Employment of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers" dated May&#13;
2004 and the provisions stipulated in the Legal Agreement. The general description o f various&#13;
items under different expenditure categories are described below. For each contract to be&#13;
financed by the grant, procurement methods, consultant selection methods, prequalification&#13;
requirements, estimated costs, prior review requirements, andtime frame will be agreed between&#13;
the recipient and the Bank in the procurement plan. The procurement plan will be updated at&#13;
least annually or as requiredto reflect the actual project implementation needs and improvements&#13;
ininstitutional capacity.&#13;
&#13;
49.    Procurement of Goods and Works. Procurement of goods under this project will be&#13;
done using the Bank's Standard Bidding Documents (SBD) for all International Competitive&#13;
Bidding (ICB) and national SBD agreed with (or satisfactory to) the Bank for National&#13;
Competitive Bidding (NCB). Goods estimatedto cost US$ 200,000 equivalent or more shall be&#13;
procured through ICB. Goods estimatedto cost less than US$200,000 may be procured through&#13;
NCB. Goods may be procured through shopping for contracts estimated to cost less than US$&#13;
100,000 equivalent. All contracts estimated to cost more than US$ 200,000 will be subject to&#13;
IDA'Sprior review.&#13;
&#13;
50.     Procurement of works under this project will likely be limited to upgrading offices or&#13;
training rooms. Procurement will be done using the Bank's SBD for all ICB and national SBD&#13;
agreedwith or satisfactory to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
51.    Selection of Consultants.      Consultants' services would be required under the five&#13;
components of the project. The main services packages include:&#13;
&#13;
Component 1: Strengtheningof Procurement Capacity within Government&#13;
&#13;
        0   Central ProcurementFacilitationConsultant&#13;
&#13;
        0   Procurement Capacity Building and Legal and Institutional Reform&#13;
&#13;
Component 2: StrengtheningFinancial Management Capacity within Government&#13;
&#13;
        0   Financial ManagementConsultant to support Treasury Functions&#13;
&#13;
        0   Conduct of a Comprehensive Financial Management Information Systems (FMIS)&#13;
            Architecture Study&#13;
&#13;
        0   Implementation of the Recommendations ofthe FMISArchitecture Study&#13;
&#13;
Component 3: StrengtheningInternal Audit Capacity withinGovernment&#13;
&#13;
        0   Consultancy Servicesto Support Internal Audit Operations and Capacity Building&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Component 4: Strengthening External Audit Capacity within Government&#13;
&#13;
        0  Audit Consultant Services to Support the CAO inAudit Operations&#13;
&#13;
      . 0  TA to Strengthen Professional Accounting and Audit Standards and Capacity&#13;
           throughout the Country&#13;
&#13;
        0  TA to Developthe System for Scrutiny andResponse to Audit Reports&#13;
&#13;
Component 5: Other Institutional Strengthening andCapacity Building&#13;
&#13;
Possible contracts are:&#13;
&#13;
        0  support for the IARCSC inmanagingthe PARprogram;&#13;
&#13;
        0  supportfor the Governmentinmanagingdonor-funded TA; and&#13;
&#13;
        0  broad-based training for the MOF and line ministriesas a result o f ongoing reforms to&#13;
           the financial management framework within Government.&#13;
&#13;
52.     For services exceeding US$ 200,000, preferred method o f selection will be Quality and&#13;
Cost Based Selection (QCBS) and for less than US$ 200,000, selection by Consultant&#13;
Qualifications (CQ) may be adopted. Selection o f firms will be carried out using the Bank's&#13;
standard RFP. For selection o f individual consultants, the relevant provisions in the Bank&#13;
guidelines shall be followed. With respect to selection o f consulting firms, IDA's prior review&#13;
will be required for contracts estimated to cost the equivalent of US$ 100,000 or more. With&#13;
respect to selection o f individual consultants, IDA's prior review will be required for contracts&#13;
estimated to cost the equivalent o f US$50,000 or more.&#13;
&#13;
53.     Training. Several smaller packages o f training will be identified following training&#13;
needs assessments conducted under the main TA packages. Flexibility will be needed as to how&#13;
to package these depending on the particular needs and potential service providers identified.&#13;
&#13;
54.     Operational Costs. The operational costs of the ARDS would be funded after the&#13;
effectiveness ofthe prGect andup to June 30,2005. The cost i s estimated to be US$ 500,000.&#13;
&#13;
B. Procurement Plan&#13;
&#13;
55.     A procurement plan has been developed for project implementation which provides the&#13;
basis for applicable procurement methods. This plan has been agreed between the recipient and&#13;
the project team and i s available in project files.  The procurement plan will be updated in&#13;
agreement with the project team annually or as required to reflect the actual project&#13;
implementationneeds and improvements ininstitutional capacity.&#13;
&#13;
C. Frequency of Procurement Supervision&#13;
&#13;
56.     Procurement supervision will be carried out during the project supervision missions&#13;
which are expected to be twice a year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 26&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 1: Proceduresfor NationalCompetitiveBidding&#13;
&#13;
A. Advertising&#13;
&#13;
57.     The invitation for bids shall be advertised ina newspaper of local circulationinthe areas&#13;
where the civil works are to be provided and the goods are to be supplied. Inthose areas where&#13;
this is not possible, the invitation for bids shall be posted at such place or places as shall be&#13;
appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
58.     The invitation for bids shall be in local language and in such other language as may be&#13;
deemed appropriate by the borrower's department or agency concerned, and shall include the&#13;
information referred to in the model invitation for bids set forth in the Bank's sample bidding&#13;
documents for procurement o f goods and small works.&#13;
&#13;
59.     With due regard to the nature of the civil works to be provided and the goods to be&#13;
supplied, the time period for bid submission from the date o f invitation shall be sufficient to&#13;
allow potential bidders a reasonable time to prepare and submit their bids. It shall be no less&#13;
thanthirty (30) calendar days unlessotherwise agreedwiththe Bank.&#13;
&#13;
B. Eligibility&#13;
&#13;
60.     The eligibility o f bidders and the origin o f goods supplied shall be as defined under the&#13;
"Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits," published by the Bank in&#13;
May 2004 (the Guidelines).&#13;
&#13;
61.     Foreignbidders shall be allowed to bid ifthey wishto do so.&#13;
&#13;
62.     Joint ventures between foreign and local firms shall not be a condition for eligibility.&#13;
Foreign bidders shall be allowed to bid alone. Nevertheless, foreign bidders may be required to&#13;
have a local agenthntermediary inthe borrower'sterritory.&#13;
&#13;
C. Bidding&#13;
&#13;
63.     Inadditionto the invitation for bids, the biddingdocuments shall includethe following:&#13;
&#13;
        0   instructions to bidders, includingthe criteria to be used for bidevaluations&#13;
&#13;
        0   conditions of contract&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        0  technical specifications&#13;
&#13;
        0   bidform and price schedules&#13;
&#13;
        0  performance security (ifpossible)&#13;
&#13;
64.     Incase of civil works, the bidding documents shall also include a bill of quantities or a&#13;
breakdown of the lump sumprice, as the case may be.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
65.    Bids may be expressed in local currency or insuch other foreign currency as may be set&#13;
forth in the invitation for bids. Ifthe currency o f payment set forth in the invitation for bids i s&#13;
the local currency, the invitations may indicate that there i s no obligation on the part o f the&#13;
borrower's department or agency requesting the bids to convert into foreign currency the&#13;
amounts to be paid.&#13;
&#13;
66.    Bidding documents shall be prepared inthe local language or in such other language as&#13;
may be deemed appropriate by the borrower's department or agency concerned.&#13;
&#13;
67.    Bids may be delivered by courier mail or by hand at the place set forth for such purposes&#13;
inthe invitation for bids.&#13;
&#13;
68.    Bids shall be opened publicly to allow representatives o f the bidders to attend if they so&#13;
desire. Bids shall not be modified after the opening o f bids except to correct arithmetical errors.&#13;
All bids shall be opened at the same time.&#13;
&#13;
69.    Bids may not be rejected for the sole purpose o f obtaining lower bids. The borrower&#13;
shall consult with the Bank prior to rejecting all bids or soliciting new bids. All bids may not be&#13;
rejected and new bids invited on the same specifications solely for the purposes o f obtaining&#13;
lower prices, except in cases where the lowest evaluated bid exceeds the cost estimates by a&#13;
substantial amount. In such cases the borrower may, as an alternative to rebidding and with the&#13;
prior concurrence o f the Bank, negotiate with the lowest evaluated bidder to try to obtain a&#13;
satisfactory contract and, failing a satisfactory response, with the next lowest evaluated bidder.&#13;
Rejection o f all bids may be permissible when bids are not substantially responsive or in case o f&#13;
a lack o f effective competition.&#13;
&#13;
70.     In the comparison of bids between local and foreign bidders, no domestic or regional&#13;
preference to local bidders shall apply. Bids shall be compared on the basis o f delivered price,&#13;
inclusive o f any prevailing duties.&#13;
&#13;
71.     Contracts shall be awarded to the lowest evaluated responsive bidder. Price negotiation&#13;
with bidders shall not be undertaken before the contract is awarded except as provided in&#13;
paragraph 68 above.&#13;
&#13;
72.     The award o f contract shall be made within the period specified in the bidding&#13;
documents. This period shall be determined in each case (goods or works) depending on the&#13;
complexity o fthe contract and the approval.&#13;
&#13;
73.     A bid evaluation report shall be prepared by the borrower's department or agency&#13;
requesting the bids setting out a record o f all bids submitted, the reasons for disqualification o f&#13;
any bids, the criteria, weighing and evaluation o f all responsive bids, the recommended award&#13;
and, if recommended award i s to other than the lowest price bidder, the reasons therefore. The&#13;
concerned borrower's department or agency shall furnish to the Bank a translation inthe English&#13;
language o f such bid evaluation report in accordance with paragraphs 2 and 3 or Appendix 1 to&#13;
the Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     ANNEX3: FINANCIALMANAGEMENT                                                                                                                                                           AND DISBURSEMENT                                                                                          ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
    A. Country Issues&#13;
&#13;
    74.                                  The Bank has gained substantial experience and understanding o f the financial&#13;
    management environment in Afghanistan through the large number o f projects under&#13;
    implementation over the past two years. This project i s the primary instrument to continue and&#13;
    enhance the fiduciary measures put inplace duringthe past two years to ensure transparency and&#13;
    accountability for the funding provided by the Bank and other donors. During preparation o f&#13;
    PACBP, a detailed review was undertaken o f the effectiveness of its predecessors, EPAP Iand&#13;
    11. Lessons have been drawn from this review to strengthen the fiduciary aspects of PACBP.&#13;
    These lessons will also feed into the ongoing Country Financial Accountability Assessment to be&#13;
    undertaken as part o f an integrated Public ExpenditureReview.&#13;
&#13;
    75.                                  Further details o fthe activities carried out under EPAP Iand I1are included inthe text o f&#13;
    the Technical Annex and in Annex 1. In summary, EPAP Iand I1assisted the Government to&#13;
    ensure that appropriate fiduciary standards were inplace for public expenditures including those&#13;
     supported by the Bank and the donor community.                                                                                                                                                                                                                               PACBP will help to ensure that these&#13;
     standards are further enhanced and that capacity i s developedwithinthe Government to maintain&#13;
     andimprove these fiduciary standards.&#13;
&#13;
     B. RiskAnalysis&#13;
&#13;
     76.                                  The table below identifies the key risks that the project may face andindicates how these&#13;
    risks are to be addressed.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                         Risk&#13;
                                                                                Risk                                                                                                Rating                                                                                                             Risk Mitigation Measures&#13;
................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................TM&#13;
    InherentRisk&#13;
 ................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
    Country InherentRisk                                                                                                                                                                       H                               "Ring fencing" ofproject fknds to the extent possible&#13;
................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
    Project Financial Management Risk                                                                                                                                                           S                              Intensive supervisionby IDA team, including FMspecialists&#13;
    PerceivedCorruption                                                                                                                                                                        H                               Govemment commitment, internal controls and new internal&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                               audit will all help reduce the highrisk of corruption&#13;
              OverallInherent Risk                                                                                                                                                             H&#13;
&#13;
................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
    ControlRisk&#13;
................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
     1. Weak Implementing Entity                                                                                                                                                              M                                Will be supportedby financial managementconsultant&#13;
................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
    2. Funds Flow                                                                                                                                                                             M                                Follows flow establishedinprevious projects&#13;
    3. Staffing Shortages                                                                                                                                                                      H                               New salary levels andrecruitment processesthrough the PRR&#13;
................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                               will assist recruitment&#13;
...........................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
    4. Accounting Policies and Procedures                                                                                                                                                     M                                 Will follow international standards&#13;
    5. Lack o f Internal Audit                                                                                                                                                                M                                Newly-created internal audit departmentwill review project&#13;
................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                internal control systems&#13;
............................................................................................................................................................&#13;
    6. Weak External Audit                                                                                                                                                                    M                                 Strengthenedunder the project&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            "................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................9&#13;
    7. InadequateReporting and Monitoring                                                                                                                                                     M                                 Strengtheningthe SpecialDisbursement Unit(SDU) i s a&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                               priority for the new financial management consultantto&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                               provide information that will comply with agreed format of&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                Financial Monitoring Reports (FMRs); also revisions in&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                Chart of Accounts will facilitate preparation of FMRs&#13;
              Overall Control Risk                                                                                                                                                            A4&#13;
    Note: Risk rating: H=hip.hrisk: S=substantialrisk: M=modest risk: N=neglinible risk&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C. StrengthsandWeaknesses&#13;
&#13;
        1. Strengths&#13;
&#13;
77.      The main strength is the Government's commitment to accountability andtransparency in&#13;
its operations which provides assurance to the Bank and other donors that the measures in place&#13;
to ensure appropriate utilization o f funds will not be circumvented. The Government support for&#13;
PACBP i s a strength in itself, given its focus on improving financial management within&#13;
Treasury operations, the public procurement function, the internal audit function, and the&#13;
external audit functions o f the Auditor General.&#13;
&#13;
         2. Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
78.      The main weakness in this project, as in many others in Afghanistan, i s the ability to&#13;
attract suitably qualified and experienced counterpart staff. Reform o f the terms and conditions&#13;
o f civil service work i s ongoing through the PRR and other processes. These reforms, coupled&#13;
with the intensive training programs included in the project, are expected to improve the&#13;
situation.&#13;
&#13;
         3. Implementing Entities&#13;
&#13;
79.      Although the major recipient i s within the MOF, there are three implementing entities for&#13;
the project located inthree agencies that will require close coordination:&#13;
&#13;
         e   Directorates o f the Treasury and Internal Audit inMOF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         0   ProcurementUnitinARDS/PPU&#13;
&#13;
             C A O&#13;
&#13;
The required coordination will be assuredthrough a project oversight committee.&#13;
&#13;
         4. Funds Flow&#13;
&#13;
80.      The flow o f funds will be similar to previous projects inAfghanistan. Project funds will&#13;
be deposited in the SA to be opened and maintained at DAB or in a local commercial bank.&#13;
Capacity interms o f delivery o f service and charges for the services will have to be assessed by&#13;
the M O F and arrangements formalized before moving from the existing practice o f placing this&#13;
account in DAB. The SA, in keeping with current practices for other projects in Afghanistan,&#13;
will be operated by the SDU inthe Treasury Department o f the MOF. Requests for payments&#13;
out of SA funds will be made to the SDU by the relevant implementing entities.&#13;
&#13;
81.      Inaddition to paymentsout of SA funds, the implementingentities could also request the&#13;
SDU to make direct payments to consultants or consulting firmshwinning partners, and special&#13;
commitments for contracts covered by letters o f credit. Such requests will follow World Bank&#13;
procedures. Consolidation o f this information from the implementing entities will be done in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SDU. It i s expected that all implementing entities will undertake a monthly reconciliation o f&#13;
data with SDU.&#13;
&#13;
82.     Most project payments are expected to be made to either international or local firms&#13;
which have bank accounts in either DAB, a local commercial bank, or an overseas bank. All&#13;
project payments will be made either through bank transfers into the account o f such firms or by&#13;
way o f check payment with account details written on the check.&#13;
&#13;
        5. Retroactive Financing&#13;
&#13;
83.     Retroactive financing, not exceeding US$ 3.0 million equivalent, i s envisaged for&#13;
expenditures incurred inaccordance with Bank's procurement procedures duringthe four months&#13;
prior to the grant signing date.&#13;
&#13;
84.     Most specifically, but not exclusively, at the Government's request the project will&#13;
retroactively finance consultant's services for the ARDS procurement facilitation component o f&#13;
approximately US$ 500,000 (two percent o f the total IDA grant amount), for expenditures&#13;
incurred subsequent to November 1, 2004 and prior to signing o f the Grant Agreement. SDU&#13;
and ARDS will jointly maintain a proper accounting of all expenditures incurred in the above&#13;
manner, along with all the supporting documents to enable IDA to verify these expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
        6. Staffing&#13;
&#13;
85.     The Treasury and CAO office i s staffed with existing governmental staff supported by&#13;
local and international consultants. The Internal Audit Department o f the M O F i s inthe process&#13;
of recruiting staff under PRR. The ARDS Procurement Unit i s currently staffed by local&#13;
consultants recruited by ARDS and paid for under EPAP I.It i s expected that these staff will&#13;
transfer to Government budget salaries under PRR inthe nextbudget.&#13;
&#13;
86.     Efforts are also being made in Treasury to bring local consultant staff on to the&#13;
Government payroll either through the PRR process by offering super scales or through the&#13;
lateral entry program o f Government for more skilled/qualified local Afghan staff. Some o f the&#13;
local consultant staff may be available for hire by the new financial management consultant.&#13;
&#13;
        7. Accounting Policies and Procedure&#13;
&#13;
87.     The project will follow standard governmental financial management policies and&#13;
procedures. It will use the Chart o f Accounts which has been developed for previous projects&#13;
and which i s currently being upgraded. Project accounts will be consolidated centrally in the&#13;
MOF through the SDU in the Treasury.            Consolidated project financial statements will be&#13;
prepared for all sources and uses o f project funds.&#13;
&#13;
        8. Internal Audit&#13;
&#13;
88.     The project financial management systems will be subject to review by the newly&#13;
established Internal Audit Directorate o f the MOF according to work programs to be determined&#13;
by the Director o f Internal Audit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        9. ExternalAudit&#13;
&#13;
89.     An audit waiver was given in the first year of EPAP Iprimarily because all payments&#13;
were made directly to firms and supported by invoices and details. Inthe second year, a limited&#13;
scope audit o f the ARDS runningcost funded out o f EPAP Ihas been requested. IDA retains the&#13;
right to have the project accounts audited by the Auditor General, supported by the audit&#13;
consultant funded under the project. Terms o f reference for the audit will be satisfactory to IDA&#13;
and will include audit o f the project financial statements, the SA, and statements o f expenditures&#13;
(SOEs). The annual audited project financial statements will be provided to the Bank within six&#13;
months o f the end o f each fiscal year. The Audit Report Compliance System (ARCS) will track&#13;
the following for PACBP:&#13;
&#13;
  ImplementingAgency               Audit                     Auditors              Due Date&#13;
          MOF             Special Account, Project        Auditor General         September 21&#13;
                             Financial Statements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        I O . Reporting and Monitoring&#13;
&#13;
90.     FMRs will be used for project monitoring and supervision. FMRs are prepared centrally&#13;
in SDU with Development Budget and External Relations Department (DBER) being&#13;
responsible for consolidating the reports for donors. These current FMRs are produced based on&#13;
records kept on Excel spreadsheets because the present Chart o f Accounts i s incapable o f&#13;
capturing data based on components. The Government is inthe process o f revising the Chart o f&#13;
Accounts with advice from IDA, which will facilitate the production o f timely, accurate, and&#13;
more meaningful FMRs.&#13;
&#13;
91.     A review o fthe FMRsprepared to date on IDA projects reveals that SDU has not been in&#13;
a position to provide the necessary information relating to component-wise expenditure as well&#13;
as correct category-wise breakdown. Strengthening the SDUto enable it to perform its functions&#13;
effectively will be one o f the priorities o f the financial management consultant until such time as&#13;
line ministries can effectively carry out this function.&#13;
&#13;
92.     Quarterly FMRs will be produced showing:                (i)sources and uses of funds by&#13;
disbursement category and project component; (ii)physical progress; and (iii)status o f&#13;
procurement activities. The implementing entities will forward the relevant details to SDU for&#13;
consolidation and submission to IDA within 45 days o f the end o f each quarter.                 The&#13;
Government and IDA are currently working on a proforma FMRfor all Bank projects.&#13;
&#13;
93.     Annual project accounts will be consolidated in the MOF, in the Treasury Department,&#13;
supported by the financial management consultant. Consolidated project financial statements&#13;
will beprepared for all sources and uses o fproject funds.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     32&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                             12. Allocation of Grant Proceeds&#13;
&#13;
94.                          Financing Percentage. The financing                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    Amount                                       Financing&#13;
percentage is set at 100 percent as per the                                                                                                                                                                                                          ExpenditureCategory                                                                                             (US$m) Percentage&#13;
approved "Country Financing Parameters."                                                                                                                                                                                          .............................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       Goods and Works                                                                                                                                    .80                               100%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       Consultants' Servicesand                                                                                                                 24.00                                       100%&#13;
95.                          Disbursement Method. Disbursements                                                                                                                                                                     .....................................................................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                Training&#13;
&#13;
from the IDA credit would be transaction-based                                                                                                                                                                                     ....................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        Operational Costs                                                                                                                                 .50                                100%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       Unallocated                                                                                                                                    1.70                                  100%&#13;
(replenishment,                                                                              reimbursement,                                                                                    direct                                  Total                                                                                                                                    27.00&#13;
-payment,&#13;
     -                                              and                             payments                                                   under                                   Special&#13;
Commitments) with full documentation or against SOEs as appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
96.                           Use of SOEs. Disbursementswill be made on the basis of SOEs for: (i)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                contracts for&#13;
civil works costing less than US$ 100,000 equivalent; (ii)                                                                                                                                                                                                                      contracts for goods costing less than&#13;
US$ 100,000 equivalent; (iii)                                                                                                             contracts for individual consultants costing less than US$ 50,000&#13;
equivalent; and (iv) contracts for consultant firms costing less than US$ 100,000 equivalent and&#13;
training and incremental operating costs.&#13;
&#13;
97.                          Special Account. An SA will be opened and maintained inDAB or a commercial bank&#13;
on terms and conditions acceptable to the Association, and would be operated by the Treasury&#13;
Department in MOF in accordance with the Association's operational policies. The authorized&#13;
allocation of the SA would be set not to exceedUS$ 1,000,000.&#13;
&#13;
98.                          Minimum application size. Applications for replenishment to the SA will be submitted:&#13;
(a) at least monthly regardless of amount, or (b) when the SA balance is reduced by 40 percent,&#13;
whichever comes first.                                                                                                        The minimum application size for withdrawal applications for&#13;
reimbursement,direct payment, or for applications for Special Commitments is US$ 200,000.&#13;
&#13;
99.                          Authority to withdraw credit funds.                                                                                                                                                            MOF will retain the right to sign and submit&#13;
withdrawal applications to the Association basedon the requests received from the implementing&#13;
agencies.&#13;
&#13;
                              12. Action Plan&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Action                                                                                                                                         ResponsiblePerson                                                                                                                             TargetDate&#13;
 .....&#13;
    F,MR..foEats.co?firmed................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................P&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   IDAiMOF(DBER)                                                                                                                                     At negotiations&#13;
     Govemment is revisingits CAO, whichwill                                                                                                                                                       IDAiMOF                                                                                                                                           By end ofthis fiscal&#13;
     facilitate the productionoftimely and                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           year&#13;
     accurateFMRs; IDA will provide advice to&#13;
 ................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................&#13;
     facilitate this revision&#13;
     Efforts to be made for retentionof local                                                                                                                                                      MOF(Treasury)iCAOIARSS/CSC                                                                                                                        During transitionphase&#13;
  ................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................s&#13;
     Afghan staff working for the present agents                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     ofthe new agents&#13;
&#13;
 100.                          With these agreements and the systems already in place, the financial management&#13;
arrangements are considered to be adequate to meet the Bank's requirements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                         33&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                              ANNEX4. MONITORING&#13;
&#13;
      Goals                                                 Monitoring Indicators&#13;
Improvements        Regulatory Framework, New budget law and financial regulations promulgated and under&#13;
inpublic sector     implementation; new audit law andregulations promulgated and under implementation.&#13;
financial&#13;
management          Systems Development. Key businessprocesses identified and agreed for core financial&#13;
with a focus on     management functions; specific policies, processes, systems and standards established for internal&#13;
budget              and external audit functions; plan agreed for a phased implementation o f a hlly functional&#13;
&#13;
execution,          AFMIS throughout Government.&#13;
government          H R Capacity. Sustained implementation o fPRR in institutions responsible for core financial&#13;
accounting and      management functions; on-the-job and professional training programs inplace and designed to&#13;
reporting, and      meet specifically agreed capacity development milestones so that staff can take over operation o f&#13;
enhancement of      functionslsystems within defined period o ftime.&#13;
internal and&#13;
external            Budget Execution. Effectiveness o f cash flow planning, management and monitoring; evidence&#13;
controls and        that budgeted resources reach spending units in a timely and transparent manner; effectiveness o f&#13;
accountability      internal controls; effectiveness o f internal audit; effectivenesss of payroll controls.&#13;
                    Accounting and Reporting. Timeliness andregularity o f data reconciliation; timeliness, quality&#13;
                    and dissemination of in-year budget execution reports; timeliness and quality o f audited financial&#13;
                    statements submittedto the legislature and donors.&#13;
                    External Accountability,Audit and Scrutiny. The scope and nature o f external audit; follow up&#13;
                    o f audit reports by the executive or audited entity; legislative scrutiny o f external audit reports.&#13;
&#13;
                   ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Improved            Regulatory Framework. New public procurement law and regulations promulgated and under&#13;
governance in       implementation; establishment o f a procurement policy law at an appropriate hierarchy within&#13;
public              Government.&#13;
procurement&#13;
and increased       Systems Development. Establishment o f procurement functions and performance benchmarks in&#13;
efficiency,         line ministries.&#13;
&#13;
transparency,       HR Capacity. Lineministry procurement staff trained and accredited according to agreed&#13;
accountability      certification plan; procurement units within line ministriesmeetingperformance benchmarks and&#13;
and                 having increased authority for procurement.&#13;
competitiveness&#13;
o fpublic           Economy, Efficiency and Transparency. Percentage o f contracts subject to competitive bidding;&#13;
procurement         absence o f major delays inthe processing and payment o f contracts; comparability o f prices paid&#13;
                    bythe public sector to pricing of items available inthe market place; regular publicationo f&#13;
                    opportunities and outcomes o f public contracts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             34&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5536031">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/12/5536031/afghanistan-public-administration-capacity-building-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/12/5536031/afghanistan-public-administration-capacity-building-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/12/5536031/afghanistan-public-administration-capacity-building-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/01/07/000090341_20050107085158/Rendered/INDEX/T7641.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/01/07/000090341_20050107085158/Rendered/PDF/T7641.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-01-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2004-12-27T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Afghanistan - Public Administration
            Capacity Building Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Public Administration Capacity
            Building Project for Afghanistan aims to assist the
            authorities in developing the capacity to manage public
            expenditures in an effective, transparent, and accountable
            manner in order to achieve satisfactory and sustainable
            development outcomes in Afghanistan. The project will have a
            particular focus on enhancing the performance of public
            sector procurement, financial management, and accountability
            systems. Success in meeting the project's objective
            will be measured by: establishment and implementation of
            sound regulatory and control frameworks for budget execution
            and fiscal reporting, and public sector procurement; further
            development of core systems for budget execution, government
            accounting, and internal and external audits; development of
            HR to effectively manage and operate these critical systems;
            and operational performance (technical efficiency) of the
            fiduciary management functions.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Afghanistan - Public Administration Capacity
            Building Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Afghanistan - Public
            Administration Capacity Building Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2004/12/5536031/afghanistan-public-administration-capacity-building-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>AF-Public Admin Cpacity Building Project -- P084736</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Business Environment,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Business in Development,Public Sector Economics,National Governance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Afghanistan</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20050107085158</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <subsc>General public administration sector</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Account, accountability, Accountants,
            Accounts, audit departments, audit reports, auditing
            standards, audits, Bidding, budget appropriations, budget
            control, budget deficit, budget execution, budget process,
            cash management, central ministries, corruption, Cost
            Estimates, debt, debt management, direct payments, Economic
            Management, elections, employment, Expenditures, Financial
            Accountability, financial accounting, Financial Management,
            financial management systems, financial reporting, financial
            statements, fiscal management, Government accounting, Gross
            Domestic Product, Internal Audit, internal auditing,
            internal controls, laws, legal framework, Management
            Capacity, management contracts, Management Information,
            Management Information Systems, Management Strategy,
            municipalities, National Budget, operating costs,
            organizational reform, organizational structure, payroll,
            payroll systems, private sector, private sector
            participation, Procurement, procurement procedures, public
            expenditure, public expenditure management, Public
            Expenditure Review, public expenditures, Public Finance,
            public resources, public sector, public sector
            accountability, recurrent cost, reforms, regulatory
            environment, regulatory framework, reporting, revenue
            collection, service delivery, service providers,
            supervision, Transparency, treasury
        </keywd>
        <owner>Financial Management Unit (SARFM)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Technical Assistance Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T7641</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Procurement Implementing Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Standard Bidding Documents</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Research and Surveys for Public Contracts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Internal Financial Control (PIFC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tracking Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuing Judicial Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Education, Training and Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Training Curriculum</ml:concept><ml:concept>Training Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Procurement Laws</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Internal Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Accounting and Reporting</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Education and Training</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Afghanistan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>