<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>&amp;#12;&#13;
       MOVING FROM PROTEST TO PROPOSAL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      BUILDING THE CAPACITY OF CONSUMER&#13;
&#13;
        ORGANISATIONS TO ENGAGE IN URBAN&#13;
&#13;
                   WATER SUPPLY AND SANITATION&#13;
&#13;
                         SECTOR REFORM IN AFRICA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa i&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Published June 2004&#13;
&#13;
Jointly authored and published by Consumers International and WSP&#13;
&#13;
Copyright WSP and Consumers International&#13;
&#13;
Cover pictures © WSP&#13;
&#13;
Designed and printed by Imagetek (Pvt) Ltd, P.O. Box CY1139, Causeway, Harare, Zimbabwe. Tel.: (263-4) 792529&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
About Consumers International&#13;
&#13;
C        onsumers International is an independent, non-profit and non-political federation of consumer organisations&#13;
         formed in 1960, and currently linking 250 organisations in 115 countries. The organisation has an observer&#13;
         status with the United Nations Economic and Social Council and its specialised agencies such as FAO, WHO,&#13;
Codex Alimentarius etc, as well as with regional and sub-regional institutions such as the Economic Community of&#13;
WestAfrican States (ECOWAS). TheAfrica Office (ROAF) co-ordinates and provides support through research, infor-&#13;
mation networks, publications, regional and international seminars, workshops, etc. to more than 120 organisations&#13;
in 46 countries in Africa. The main function of the ROAF is to build and develop the consumer movement in Africa&#13;
and to represent consumers at regional and international fora.&#13;
www.consumersinternational.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
About the Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&#13;
T       he Water and Sanitation Program (WSP), is a multi-donor trust fund program with the main funding partners&#13;
        being the governments of Australia, Austria, Belgium, Canada, Denmark, France, Germany, Luxembourg, the&#13;
        Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom, and the UNDP and the World Bank.&#13;
The Program's mission is to help poor people gain sustained access to water supply and sanitation (WSS) services.&#13;
Administered by the World Bank, WSP works in partnership with country client governments, external support&#13;
agencies and other leading support agencies to improve various institutional, technological and service delivery&#13;
options and to promote large-scale programs to improve service delivery to the poor. It also identifies and analyses&#13;
key sector problems, identifies solutions, documents and shares lessons from the field and disseminates information&#13;
at local, national, regional and global level. For more information please visit: www.wsp.org.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ii Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                 MOVING FROM PROTEST TO PROPOSAL&#13;
&#13;
 BUILDING THE CAPACITY OF CONSUMER ORGANISATIONS TO ENGAGE&#13;
IN URBAN WATER SUPPLY AND SANITATION SECTOR REFORM IN AFRICA&#13;
&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
&#13;
FOREWORD............................................................................................................................................ iv&#13;
&#13;
   AMADOU KANOUTE, REGIONAL DIRECTOR OF CONSUMERS INTERNATIONAL OFFICE FOR AFRICA ...........................................................................iv&#13;
&#13;
   PIERS CROSS, REGIONAL MANAGER, WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM-AFRICA ......................................................................................................iv&#13;
&#13;
ACRONYMS AND ABBREVIATIONS .......................................................................................................................................... vi&#13;
&#13;
CHAPTER 1 INTRODUCTION .................................................................................................................................................... 1&#13;
&#13;
   1.1 Context ........................................................................................................................................................................... 1&#13;
&#13;
   1.2 The Consumer Movement in Africa ................................................................................................................................ 1&#13;
&#13;
   1.3 The Project Design......................................................................................................................................................... 2&#13;
&#13;
   1.4 Objective of This Report ................................................................................................................................................. 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHAPTER 2 IN-COUNTRY ACTIVITIES .................................................................................................................................... 4&#13;
&#13;
   2.1 Chad............................................................................................................................................................................... 4&#13;
&#13;
   2.2 Senegal .......................................................................................................................................................................... 4&#13;
&#13;
   2.3 Zambia ........................................................................................................................................................................... 4&#13;
&#13;
   2.4 Kenya ............................................................................................................................................................................. 4&#13;
&#13;
   2.5 Common Themes ........................................................................................................................................................... 4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHAPTER 3 ISSUES AND CHALLENGES IN CONSUMER ENGAGEMENT .......................................................................... 6&#13;
&#13;
   3.1 Issues ............................................................................................................................................................................. 6&#13;
&#13;
   3.2 Challenges ..................................................................................................................................................................... 7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHAPTER 4 MODELS AND STRATEGIES FORM ENGAGEMENT WITH CONSUMER ORGANIZATIONS&#13;
&#13;
            AND CONSUMERS ............................................................................................................................................. 10&#13;
&#13;
   4.1      In the Beginning -- Getting Consumer Organizations Involved ........................................................................... 10&#13;
&#13;
   4.1.1    Country Reviews .................................................................................................................................................. 10&#13;
&#13;
   4.1.2    Workshops ........................................................................................................................................................... 11&#13;
&#13;
   4.1.3    Capacity Building ................................................................................................................................................. 12&#13;
&#13;
   4.1.4    Networking ........................................................................................................................................................... 12&#13;
&#13;
   4.2      The Next Step ­ Engaging and Representing Consumers Themselves .............................................................. 13&#13;
&#13;
   4.2.1    Advocacy .............................................................................................................................................................. 13&#13;
&#13;
   4.2.2    Service Provision ................................................................................................................................................. 14&#13;
&#13;
   4.2.3    Consumer Education ............................................................................................................................................ 15&#13;
&#13;
   4.2.4    Representing Consumers .................................................................................................................................... 16&#13;
&#13;
   4.3      Project Learning ­ Models for Replication .......................................................................................................... 18&#13;
&#13;
   4.3.1    Models to Engage Consumer Organizations ....................................................................................................... 18&#13;
&#13;
   4.3.2    Models for Engaging Consumers ......................................................................................................................... 19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHAPTER 5 CONCLUSIONS................................................................................................................................................... 20&#13;
&#13;
ANNEX 1­ DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF IN-COUNTRY ACTIVITIES ..................................................................................... 21&#13;
&#13;
       CHAD ............................................................................................................................................................................. 21&#13;
&#13;
       KENYA ............................................................................................................................................................................ 21&#13;
&#13;
       SENEGAL......................................................................................................................................................................... 22&#13;
&#13;
       ZAMBIA ........................................................................................................................................................................... 22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa                            iii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Foreword&#13;
&#13;
AMADOU KANOUTE, REGIONAL DIRECTOR OF CONSUMERS INTERNATIONAL AFRICA OFFICE (ROAF)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumers International (CI) has been involved in water                                   organisations assess the options based on their merit in&#13;
issues because affordability, quality and choice are key                                  delivery and impact in making water and sanitation&#13;
consumer concerns within any given services sector. The                                   available to consumers; particularly the most&#13;
focus of consumer organizations has been to ensure that                                   disadvantaged ones. "This open minded approach to&#13;
consumers have access to affordable and safe water and                                    ownership, which most development partners have&#13;
that consumer organizations participate in the regulatory                                 expressed, is not often matched by their negotiations in&#13;
framework through some form of representation or                                          national situations. We believe that the question of&#13;
formal and informal consultation mechanisms.                                              ownership is one for national governments to decide in&#13;
                                                                                          consultation with their citizenry1." These may change&#13;
As CI and its members could not get their voice heard in                                  from country to country and indeed from city to city,&#13;
the first generation of water and sanitation sector reforms                               taking into account what works best to ensure consumer&#13;
undertaken by our governments in Africa, we decided                                       access, given local conditions and peculiarities.&#13;
to get to the ground to pilot projects on alternative&#13;
approaches that would facilitate accessibility (financial                                 The objectives of our partnership with the Water and&#13;
and geographical) to water and sanitation.                                                Sanitation Project was to improve access and control by&#13;
                                                                                          disadvantaged and marginalized consumers to clean&#13;
In Senegal, ADEETels through a European Commission                                        water and sanitation. This was to be done through the&#13;
grant conducted a demonstrative project whereby it                                        enhancement of the capacity of consumer organisations&#13;
provided 52 water points and 600 home sewage systems                                      to effectively engage in policy debate and formulation&#13;
for residents in three peri-urban districts of Dakar. In the                              whilst at the same time mobilising communities for&#13;
Chadian capital of N'djamena where only 2.8% of the                                       specific projects and advocacy. We are happy with the&#13;
populace has access to water through the taps, the ADC                                    outcome of the project and the impact it has had, as you&#13;
of Chad worked with local community groups to build                                       will read in the report.&#13;
a water point, which now serves 2000 households in one&#13;
district of N'djamena. The project cost was US$2000                                       We would like to acknowledge all participating&#13;
dollars.                                                                                  organizations in this project,ADEETelS of Senegal;ADC&#13;
                                                                                          of Chad; CIN of Kenya and ZACAof Zambia. CI staff in&#13;
Then the time came for a change in focus. The African                                     the various regional offices: inAfrica, LatinAmerica and&#13;
consumer moved away from demonstrating alternative                                        Europe, also inputted into the elaboration of this&#13;
models for access to water and sanitation towards the                                     document. This has truly been an excellent exercise in&#13;
establishment of effective public interest review and                                     cross fertilisation of experiences and ideas within the&#13;
regulation.                                                                               global consumer movement. The staff and consultants&#13;
                                                                                          of the WSP who inputted their time, effort and skills&#13;
Consumer participation is one very important aspect of                                    towards this project must also be acknowledged.&#13;
this. For consumers to effectively participate in water and&#13;
sanitation sector reform they need the knowledge, skills,                                 I would like to thank all our project partners, who have&#13;
&#13;
access to information and the forum to facilitate their                                   made this project a reality. These include the Department&#13;
&#13;
participation.                                                                            For International Development of the United Kingdom&#13;
                                                                                          (DFID), the African Capacity Building Foundation&#13;
&#13;
Statistics of water sector reviews had indicated that non-                                (ACBF), the Water and Sanitation Programme and&#13;
&#13;
connected consumers in the informal and peri-urban                                        NORAD, the Ministry for Foreign Cooperation of&#13;
&#13;
were paying as much as 3 to 10 times more for water                                       Norway.&#13;
&#13;
because of ineffective regulatory mechanisms and&#13;
because of policy which were not targeted to take into                                    Finally, let me commend the ROAF staff, especially&#13;
&#13;
consideration the needs of the less fortunate in our                                      Nessie Golakai and IbrahimaAidara, for their unstinting&#13;
&#13;
societies. This illustrated the need to involve civil society                             efforts in coordinating our work in the area of utilities ­&#13;
&#13;
organisations and the wider public in a debate on                                         which brought together so many players- and for&#13;
&#13;
strategies and options for the reform in order to develop                                 drafting the synthesis report.&#13;
&#13;
sustainable policies that are well targeted and which&#13;
integrate pro-poor strategies.&#13;
&#13;
Consumers International is not for or against any model&#13;
of utility management, be they public or private or any&#13;
degrees in between. Our membership is too diverse for&#13;
us to promote any specific type of ownership. Consumer&#13;
&#13;
1Speech by CI President, Marilena Lazarrini to the World Bank, Washington. May 4, 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
iv Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PIERS CROSS, REGIONAL MANAGER, WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM - AFRICA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumer engagement is arguably the weakest pillar of&#13;
the reform of urban water and sanitation institutions                               This report illustrates the scale of the challenge facing&#13;
currently underway in manyAfrican cities. Early reform                              organizations that wish to establish effective consumer&#13;
initiatives neglected consumers, and the consumer                                   representation in African water and sanitation service&#13;
movement is only now beginning to engage in the sector                              management, but, we hope, also presents the starting&#13;
to give water and sanitation consumers an effective voice.                          point for the development of more effective approaches.&#13;
                                                                                    For consumers to participate effectively in water and&#13;
                                                                                    sanitation sector reform they need better knowledge of&#13;
This project, which looked at methods and strategies for&#13;
                                                                                    the sector and effective mechanisms to facilitate their&#13;
of building the capacity of consumer organisations in                               participation. We hope that this report will encourage&#13;
urban water supply and sanitation, derives from a joint                             both consumer bodies and service providers alike to put&#13;
collaboration between Consumers International (CI), the                             more effective methods of consumer engagement into&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program (WSP). CI and WSP                                      place.&#13;
collaborated on this project to learn about what&#13;
approacheswouldacceleratesustainableservicedelivery,                                WSP wishes to offer its sincere thanks to all the&#13;
especially to the poor and marginalized inAfrican cities,                           organizations that contributed to and supported this&#13;
in order to be able to inform future institutional reforms.                         project. In particular thanks are due to the four&#13;
                                                                                    participating consumer organizations, CI staff, and the&#13;
                                                                                    staff and consultants of the WSP - particularly the&#13;
WSP has been increasingly involved in pro-poor urban                                contribution of Clarissa Brocklehurst, who managed the&#13;
service reform. WSP comes to the arena of consumer                                  project for WSP and helped draft the synthesis report.&#13;
engagement with a proven track record in participatory                              We would like to thank our financing partners,&#13;
and community engagement approaches, and an                                         particularly the World Bank-administered Bank&#13;
eagerness to learn more about the established consumer                              Netherlands Water Partnership and the donors of the&#13;
&#13;
movement. We are very pleased that this project                                     WSP.&#13;
&#13;
stimulated the exchange of experiences and ideas both&#13;
within the global consumer movement and between the&#13;
consumer movement and water and sanitation experts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa v&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
ADC                  Association de Défense des Consommateurs du Tchad&#13;
ADEETelS             Association de Défense des Usagers de L'Eau, de l'Electricité, des Télécommunications et des&#13;
                     Services du Sénégal&#13;
BNWP                 Bank Netherlands Water Partnership&#13;
CI                   Consumers International&#13;
CIN                  Consumer Information Network of Kenya&#13;
CI-ROAF              Consumers International Africa Office&#13;
CI-ROLAC             Consumers International Latin America and the Caribbeans Office&#13;
CO                   Consumer Organization&#13;
CSO                  Civil Society Organization&#13;
DFID                 Department for International Development (UK)&#13;
NWASCO               National Water and Sanitation Council (Zambia)&#13;
VAT                  value-added tax&#13;
WSP                  Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
ZACA                 Zambia Consumers Association&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
vi Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Chapter 1: Introduction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.1 Context&#13;
&#13;
Water is essential to life, to development and to every                                 a need to develop a project which would increase the&#13;
aspect of human endeavour. Though access to water has                                   capacity of consumer organizations (COs) to assess the&#13;
improved for many African consumers living in urban                                     water reform process from a standpoint of consumer&#13;
areas, the rapid pace of urbanization threatens to offset                               protection, and articulate the options and strategies to&#13;
these gains. The region will experience a quadrupling                                   ensure consumer protection.&#13;
of its urban population from 130 million in 1990 to 500&#13;
million in 20202.                                                                       The objective of the project was well summed up by one&#13;
                                                                                        of the partners, who commented on the need for&#13;
In manyAfrican cities, the water treatment, distribution,                               consumer organizations to "move from protest to&#13;
and metering systems are antiquated and have suffered                                   proposal" ­ leaving behind emotional protest to focus&#13;
from a lack of maintenance. This results in great                                       on concrete and substantive proposals to engage with&#13;
inefficiencies, including high water losses.Added to this                               the water reform process and champion the needs of the&#13;
are weak administrative systems for billing and revenue                                 most vulnerable consumers. .&#13;
collection. Together this means that much water is&#13;
"unaccounted for" ­ that is, the utility never receives any&#13;
payment for it. The result is the familiar scenario of a                                1.2 The Consumer Movement in Africa&#13;
&#13;
utility which cannot achieve financial health, struggles                                In order to fully understand the context of the project, it&#13;
to provide its existing customers with an adequate level                                is necessary to understand the consumer movement as&#13;
of service, and cannot even contemplate reaching out to                                 a whole, and its remarkable development in Africa. The&#13;
the un-connected.                                                                       modernconsumermovementreallybeganinthelate19th&#13;
                                                                                        century in the United States with the beginning of mass&#13;
In order to improve the water supply and sanitation                                     production of products and bulk distribution over long&#13;
system and meet the growing demand for water, many                                      distances, resulting in the need for consumer awareness&#13;
African governments and municipalities are                                              of product quality and safety. The Consumer Union was&#13;
contemplating or have undertaken some form of urban                                     created in the United States in 1936 and by the late 1950s&#13;
water and sanitation sector reform. This usually requires                               many European countries had also established consumer&#13;
a radical overhaul of legal, regulatory and institutional                               organizations. These first began to be federated in the&#13;
frameworks and often entails some form of public-                                       early 1960s as the International Organization of&#13;
private partnership (even though private sector                                         Consumers Unions (IOCU), now Consumers&#13;
participation can be a controversial and emotive issue).                                International. Consumer movements in other parts of the&#13;
Cost recovery is often one of the main objectives of the                                world - Africa, Asia and Latin America - began in the&#13;
reform, in order to ensure financial sustainability for the                             1960s and beyond.&#13;
agencies that deliver water and sanitation services.&#13;
However many governments have done little to facilitate                                 Perhaps in no other area in the world has the consumer&#13;
dialogue with civil society on the most appropriate                                     movement grown as rapidly as in Africa. In 1991,&#13;
nature and form of these reforms or to solicit inputs as                                Consumers International was working with 21 groups&#13;
to how the interests of different segments of society can                               in 16 African countries. By October 1995, that number&#13;
best be recognized and everyone's needs addressed.                                      increased to 82 organizations in 39 countries. In 2000, 45&#13;
                                                                                        countries out of 53 in Africa hosted a consumer&#13;
Within this framework of rapid urbanization and urban                                   organization ­ more than 120 independent organizations&#13;
water sector reform, competing demands for water for                                    in total. Although some countries - Kenya, Mauritius,&#13;
industrial and commercial and domestic use continue                                     South Africa, Tunisia and Zimbabwe - have strong&#13;
to outpace the existing capacities. Industrial and                                      organizations that were established about 20 years ago -&#13;
commercial needs are often prioritized at the expense of                                the median age of a consumer group inAfrica is less than&#13;
consumer demands, particularly those of poor and                                        10 years old. This means that although there is a great&#13;
disadvantaged consumers who live in informal,                                           deal of potential, there is also a great deal of inexperience.&#13;
spontaneous and peri-urban settlements, which is also&#13;
where most of the population growth is expected to                                      The growth of the consumer movement in Africa can be&#13;
occur.                                                                                  attributed to a number of interconnected factors:&#13;
                                                                                        ·          The end of totalitarian regimes in many African&#13;
Given the above, Consumers InternationalAfrica felt that                                           countries and the development of multi-party&#13;
the interests of consumers, particularly the poor and                                              political systems. Civil society organizations&#13;
vulnerable, were not being given a platform in the urban                                           flourished in this atmosphere of increased political&#13;
water reform process. It was felt that there was therefore                                         tolerance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
UN Habitat 2001 Water for African Cities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
·        The implementation of structural adjustment                                                     The project contained the following elements, in order&#13;
         programs and the diminishing role of                                                            of implementation:&#13;
         governments as providers of essential goods and                                                  1.   Country Reviews to provide an overview of the&#13;
         services meant consumers felt more vulnerable                                                         provision of water and sanitation services, the&#13;
         and needed more information than in the past.                                                         legislative and regulatory framework and&#13;
·        The feeling on the part of consumers that trade                                                       recommendations for positive action/change that&#13;
         liberalizationmustbeaccompaniedbyglobalrules                                                          would benefit vulnerable, marginalized&#13;
         and regulations.                                                                                      consumers/non-consumers, and to begin a&#13;
·        The interest of foundations and other donor                                                           processofself-learningonthepartoftheconsumer&#13;
         institutions in consumer and other civil society                                                      organizations in each country.&#13;
         groups to press for good governance and private                                                  2.   National Stakeholders Meetings to bring&#13;
         sector performance, as well as to improve public                                                      together all stakeholders in the water sector. The&#13;
         awareness on citizens' rights and responsibilities.                                                   aim was to present the country review for&#13;
·        The work of Consumers International's Office for                                                      verification and improvement and also to help&#13;
                                                                                                               define a consumer role and plan of action on&#13;
         Africa (ROAF) which aided in establishing new&#13;
                                                                                                               engagement in water sector.&#13;
         consumer organizations in several African&#13;
                                                                                                          3.   Capacity Building and Training on water sector&#13;
         countries and enhanced the visibility and&#13;
                                                                                                               management and issues as well as communication&#13;
         recognition of consumer organizations.&#13;
                                                                                                               skills. Many consumer organizations lack the&#13;
                                                                                                               knowledge and skills to intervene effectively in&#13;
                                                                                                               the discussions around water reforms. The aim of&#13;
1.3      The Project Design&#13;
                                                                                                               the training was to demystify the terminology and&#13;
CI's project "Empowering Vulnerable Consumers to                                                               workings of the water sector so as to enable&#13;
Access and Influence Water and Sanitation Services" was                                                        consumer to be informed participants in the&#13;
conceived and received joint funding from the United                                                           debate.&#13;
Kingdom's Department for International Development                                                        4.   Advocacy and campaigns by partner consumer&#13;
(DFID), the African Capacity Building Foundation                                                               organizations and the national network&#13;
(ACBF) and the Water and Sanitation Program (WSP)                                                              participants, leading to a better understanding&#13;
supported by the Bank Netherlands Water Partnership                                                            amongcivilsocietyandgovernmentsoftheimpact&#13;
(BNWP). The project commenced in January 2002. Its                                                             of local and national legislation/regulation and&#13;
aims were to improve the access and control by                                                                 practices on the water and sanitation services on&#13;
disadvantaged consumers over water and sanitation in                                                           vulnerable consumers and options which would&#13;
African countries by supporting the involvement of                                                             help improve their access to these services.&#13;
consumer organizations in the sector. The project                                                         5.   Consumer Awareness and Education provided&#13;
encouraged consumer organizations to be contributors                                                           to at least one community in each of the four&#13;
to reform processes and to represent the interests of poor                                                     countries. This training was related to their water&#13;
consumers in the water and sanitation sector.                                                                  and sanitation rights and responsibilities. The&#13;
                                                                                                               training was also designed to support and inform&#13;
Consumers International Africa Office (CI-ROAF)                                                                their local and national efforts to improve their&#13;
provided overall project coordination. The project                                                             access to and control over their water and&#13;
partners were:                                                                                                 sanitation services, and to provide practical advice&#13;
·        Association de Défense des Consommateurs du                                                           and solutions.&#13;
         Tchad(ADC);                                                                                      6.   Pilot Projects were undertaken in each of the&#13;
·        Consumer Information Network of Kenya (CIN);                                                          above communities aimed at improving the&#13;
·        Association de Défense des Usagers de L'Eau, de                                                       services available. These projects varied in nature&#13;
&#13;
         l'Electricité, des Télécommunications et des                                                          from local advocacy and representation&#13;
&#13;
         Services du Sénégal (ADEETelS); and                                                                   campaigns to implementing local, affordable,&#13;
&#13;
·                                                                                                              equitable water and sanitation services. The type&#13;
         Zambia Consumers Association (ZACA).&#13;
                                                                                                               of project chosen was guided by the participatory&#13;
                                                                                                               research of the first year.&#13;
This synthesis document is one of the outputs supported&#13;
by WSP's contribution to the CI-ROAF project. WSP's&#13;
main input into the project was in the form of capacity                                                  1.4   Objective of This Report&#13;
building and training elements and is part of a wider&#13;
WSP project entitled "Urban Water Supply and                                                             This report was compiled at a drafting synthesis&#13;
Sanitation Sector Reform: Building Capacity for Civil                                                    workshop organized in Lisbon, Portugal from October&#13;
Society Engagement" supported by the Bank                                                                11th to 12th 2003, at which representatives of the&#13;
Netherlands Water Partnership (BNWP)3 .                                                                  Consumers Organizations from each of the four project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3&#13;
WSPhas created a website for this project which can be visited at www.wsp.org/05_Initiatives_cbpcs.asp.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 2 Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
countries, CI-ROAF and WSP participated. The aim of                                2004 at which the concept of a general model and strategy&#13;
the drafting workshop was toÊsynthesize the regional                               for involving consumer organizations in sector reform&#13;
experience from the project. This included assessing                               was presented to a wider audience of 24 consumer&#13;
models of engagement for COs in water reform process                               representatives from 20 countries. Experiences of these&#13;
and examining how these models can be put to work for                              COs in the defining and advocating for the consumer&#13;
other COs regionally and globally. In order to do this,                            interest in water sector reform where shared, and these&#13;
workshop participants presented their experiences to                               experiences have also been integrated in the report. The&#13;
date in water sector reform nationally and analyzed the                            report thus contains many examples from both the&#13;
effectiveness of these strategies for empowering                                   project countries and other countries in the region.&#13;
consumers, and increasing their representation and&#13;
access to water.                                                                   This report is intended for use by other consumer&#13;
                                                                                   organizations, wider civil society and public interest&#13;
Apreliminary summarized draft of a general model and                               institutions, government agencies, donors, academics&#13;
strategy for involving consumers organizations in sector                           and other institutions with interest in the water sector. It&#13;
reform was presented at the Consumers International                                is hoped that it will also provide useful insights and&#13;
World Congress workshop on "Public Utilities and                                   information for organizations and agencies seeking to&#13;
Consumer Empowerment" on October 14th in Lisbon                                    increase consumer participation in the water and&#13;
for comments. A regional dissemination workshop was                                sanitation sector.&#13;
organized in Dakar, Senegal from March 15th to 16th,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Chapter 2:                In-Country Activities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumer organizations have conducted a range of                                        2.3      Zambia&#13;
activities within the scope of this project. The activities                             In Zambia, the rate of access to water is 70% and 43%&#13;
have differed according to the local context, hence the                                 respectively in the urban and rural sectors. Many&#13;
impacts have also been varied. Below is a summary of                                    residents of peri-urban settlements without access to the&#13;
the prevailing situation at the time the project was                                    water network are forced to rely on water vendors. Most&#13;
undertaken, and a summary of the outcomes of activities.                                connected consumer pay flat rates for water ­ which are&#13;
A more detailed description of activities and outcomes                                  not dependent on the amount they use - and this has&#13;
can be found in Annex 1.                                                                resulted in a lot of water wastage in the community.&#13;
                                                                                        Government and consumers alike owe huge arrears to&#13;
                                                                                        the utilities and this has impacted on their ability to&#13;
2.1    Chad&#13;
                                                                                        extend services.&#13;
Access to water is very limited in Chad, with a national&#13;
coverage of only 23.5% (17% in the rural areas and 30%                                  These and other issues were highlighted in the country&#13;
in urban areas). Only about 2.8% of households in Chad                                  review carried out by the Zambian Consumers&#13;
have taps in their homes. The remaining households                                      Association (ZACA). ZACA presented its findings and&#13;
obtain water from public standposts, wells, surface water,                              recommendation at a national stakeholder meeting, and&#13;
rain water and water vendors.                                                           also took part in a live TV discussion with the water&#13;
                                                                                        regulatory body and the association of water utilities to&#13;
Through its country review and national stakeholder                                     discuss the issue of water and consumers. ZACA has&#13;
meetings       the        Association             de      Défense         des           been appointed a member of the National Water Supply&#13;
Consommateurs (ADC) (the Association for Consumer                                       and Sanitation Council in Zambia (NWASCO), the body&#13;
Detectors) presented a memorandum from consumers                                        which regulates the sector.&#13;
on the key issues and concerns for consumers and&#13;
recommendations to the Prime Minister and the                                           2.4      Kenya&#13;
President of Parliamnent. ADC followed this up with a&#13;
                                                                                        In Nairobi, the capital city of Kenya, approximately 60%&#13;
peaceful march from August 19 to 20 August 2003&#13;
                                                                                        of the poor live in informal settlements. In these areas,&#13;
demanding water and electricity as basic consumer&#13;
                                                                                        water kiosks and standpipes remain the principal sources&#13;
rights. More than 3000 consumers participated. Major&#13;
                                                                                        of water. The Nairobi City Council has a recommended&#13;
recommendations from ADC were accepted by the&#13;
                                                                                        retail price for water at such vending points, however&#13;
Chadian government and integrated in the national&#13;
                                                                                        there is inadequate enforcement of this policy, and the&#13;
water and sanitation policy document.&#13;
                                                                                        regulatory framework on pricing water in informal&#13;
                                                                                        settlements is weak. Consumers therefore end up paying&#13;
2.2     Senegal&#13;
                                                                                        as much as ten times more for water compared to higher-&#13;
Senegal has undergone an extensive water sector reform                                  income consumers in formal settlements. Consumers&#13;
process which has resulted in coverage and service                                      Information Network (CIN) decided to focus its country&#13;
improvements. However residents of many peri-urban                                      review and activities on this issue.&#13;
districts (who are) outside the formal network or cannot&#13;
afford connection fees have to depend on water vendors,                                 The Consumer Information Network (CIN) launched an&#13;
and pay several times the rates most connected                                          advocacy program with a series of letters to the&#13;
households pay. Sanitation coverage remains low;                                        government. It has also been working closely with a local&#13;
whereas access to potable water now stands at 87% of                                    informal settlement called Korogocho to facilitate the&#13;
the urban population only 37% is connected to a sewage                                  construction of water and sanitation points.&#13;
system.&#13;
                                                                                        CIN has now been appointed as a member of a&#13;
Association de Défense des Usagers de L'Eau, de                                         government-civil society consultative committee in&#13;
l'Electricité, des Télécommunications et des Services du                                charge of proposing a pro-poor strategy for the planned&#13;
Sénégal (ADEETelS) (Association for protection of users                                 Integrated Water Management Policy.&#13;
of water, electricity, telecommunication services of&#13;
Senegal) through its country review and national                                        2.5      Common Themes&#13;
stakeholders meeting, identified key recommendations                                    Each organization has focused on a specific themes and&#13;
including the need to improve sanitation and review the                                 issues which are of priority in their national and local&#13;
subsidy regime in order to better target poor consumers.                                setting. However across these four countries there are&#13;
ADEETelS has now been nominated to serve on the                                         some common themes:&#13;
management committee for the next phase of the reform&#13;
process in Senegal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4  Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
· Access is the biggest priority - especially for                                        consumption. Middle- to high-income consumers&#13;
  consumers in peri-urban and informal settlements                                       are benefiting from these subsidies because they can&#13;
  ­ and utilities are unable or unwilling to extend                                      afford to connect.&#13;
  services                                                                      ·        While quality of water has not come up as a major&#13;
· Price is an issue, due in part to overall affordability                                issue among consumers in most of the countries&#13;
  but also because of equity concerns. There are often                                   reviewed (in contrast to other consumer goods,&#13;
  wide price differentials between the amounts paid                                      where quality of the commodity is an important&#13;
  by connected and unconnected consumers                                                 issue), quality of service is an issue with consumers&#13;
· Tariff and subsidies systems are often complicated                                     complaining of poor service delivery in terms of&#13;
  and inequitable. Low-income consumers who most                                         water cut-offs without prior notice, irregular billing&#13;
  need subsidies are outside of the main water system                                    and poor customer complaints mechanisms&#13;
  and hence do not benefit from any subsidies on                                ·        Regulatory frameworks are lacking or ineffective.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Chapter 3:                Issues and Challenges in Consumer Engagement&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumers and consumer organizations have, in the                                       consumer rights within the context of the provision of&#13;
past, tended to be detached from policy debates                                         water and sanitation services, there are core issues that&#13;
concerning issues of management and reform in the                                       that a consumer organization must understand. These&#13;
water sector. The focus has been mainly on issues and                                   are often complex issues which take COs well beyond&#13;
topics which relate to consumer access and redress in                                   theirusualsphereofexperienceandexpertise. Theywere&#13;
the sector. The realization that the nature and form of                                 discussed at length at the drafting workshop, and a&#13;
utility reform ultimately impacts on consumer access has                                summary list is presented below.&#13;
encouraged consumer groups to become more actively&#13;
involved and technically skilled to engage in debates&#13;
                                                                                        Price and Affordability&#13;
around water and sanitation.&#13;
                                                                                        The price of water supply and sanitation, referred to as&#13;
                                                                                        the tariff, is based on certain price-setting principles&#13;
This has raised many opportunities as well as posed&#13;
                                                                                        determined by many actors, including the water utility&#13;
challenges for COs. As consumer issues affect a wide&#13;
                                                                                        itself, the government, and in some cases an independent&#13;
spectrum of sectors, time and resources are of critical&#13;
                                                                                        regulator. It is important to understand what costs are&#13;
importance and COs have to be strategic in their&#13;
                                                                                        included in determine the water tariff, and whether cost&#13;
approach in order to maximize their limited resources.&#13;
                                                                                        alone is the sole determinant of price. It is also important&#13;
This therefore begs the question "What are the issues that&#13;
                                                                                        to understand the relationship between the price&#13;
COs should be concerned about and how can consumers&#13;
                                                                                        consumers pay and the true cost of running the utility.&#13;
and COs effectively engage?"&#13;
                                                                                        An important issue may be whether, for instance, the&#13;
This chapter highlights issues that influence consumer&#13;
                                                                                        cost of inefficiency is passed through to consumers ­ that&#13;
access to water and sanitation and the quality of service&#13;
                                                                                        is, consumers are paying for the fact that much water is&#13;
they obtain. It also outlines the obstacles consumer&#13;
                                                                                        unaccounted for. The utility may find it difficult to keep&#13;
organizations face in representing consumer interests in&#13;
                                                                                        prices down if some large consumers, for instance&#13;
water and sanitation, and makes a few recommendations&#13;
                                                                                        government offices, do not pay their bills. It is also very&#13;
on how they can overcome these obstacles in order to&#13;
                                                                                        important to understand the nature and source of any&#13;
effectively engage in a debate on these issues.&#13;
                                                                                        subsidies in the system ­ are there direct subsidies from&#13;
                                                                                        government to the utility, are there hidden subsidies, and&#13;
3.1     Issues&#13;
                                                                                        are there subsidies between classes of consumers? How&#13;
Of paramount concern to consumer organizations is                                       well, and how transparently, do all these subsidies&#13;
consumer protection.Akey reference point for consumer                                   operate?&#13;
protection is the eight basic consumer rights:&#13;
1.    basic needs&#13;
                                                                                        Barriers to access&#13;
2.    safety&#13;
3.    information                                                                       While there is often a great deal of discussion of the price&#13;
&#13;
4.    choice                                                                            of a product or commodity, in the water and sanitation&#13;
&#13;
5.    representation                                                                    sector one of the major issues may not be price, but&#13;
&#13;
6.    redress                                                                           instead access to the commodity in the first place. The&#13;
&#13;
7.    consumer education                                                                reasons that consumers, especially poor consumers, are&#13;
&#13;
8.    healthy environment                                                               unable to connect to a water supply or sewerage system&#13;
                                                                                        may be many and complex. There may be strong&#13;
Consumers do not only have rights, but also                                             disincentives for network expansion and the addition of&#13;
responsibilities. These include the responsibilities to be                              new customers which constrain governments, public&#13;
critically aware, to act, to have social concerns, to be                                utilities or private operators. These must be analyzed&#13;
environmentally aware and to show solidarity with                                       and understood. They may include such things as&#13;
consumers in different categories and geographical                                      subsidized tariffs, the nature of a contract with an&#13;
locations. These responsibilities place on consumers --                                 operator, technological or geographical aspects of un-&#13;
and their representative consumer organizations -- an                                   served areas, legislation, land tenure requirements and&#13;
onus to act to ensure that their rights are respected. They                             a lack of funding for investments in the network. There&#13;
also require that consumers themselves are actively                                     may be complicated links between price and access (for&#13;
participating to ensure that the sector has the needed                                  instance keeping prices low for existing customers&#13;
support and input to work efficiently.                                                  meaning that no funds are available to extend the&#13;
                                                                                        network to new users). These barriers must be fully&#13;
All of these rights and responsibilities are of relevance                               understood by COs wishing to advocate for the interests&#13;
in the water and sanitation sector. In order to contribute                              of the poor, and may lead COs into challenging&#13;
to the debate on water sector reform and make                                           situations, where the interests of existing consumers are&#13;
suggestions for options and strategies that would protect                               in conflict with future consumers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6  Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Utility management                                                                 is important for COs to understand and analyze them&#13;
There are many forms of utility management, each with                              carefully. In particular, the type of representation and&#13;
certain strengths and weaknesses. Consumer                                         participation by civil society interest groups must be&#13;
organizations need to understand what model is                                     examined.&#13;
currently being utilized and what models are being&#13;
considered for the future, and how consumer rights can                             The reform process&#13;
be strengthened and protected within each framework.                               In order to participate in the process of reform, it is&#13;
Forms of utility management include both public                                    necessary to examine and understand the nature of the&#13;
management and the many types of public-private                                    process, the provisions for making it transparent, and&#13;
partnerships. These partnerships may give a range of                               the provisions for making information available to civil&#13;
responsibilities to private suppliers of services, with the                        society groups such as consumer associations. Civil&#13;
government usually playing a key role of asset                                     society organizations may have to be prepared to make&#13;
ownership, investment planning and regulation. Not all                             a case for more transparency, and to request detailed and&#13;
private sector participation is the same; it is important                          timely information on the government's plans in the&#13;
to understand the type of partnership agreement fully,                             sector.&#13;
and the responsibilities and obligations placed on both&#13;
the public and private partners (which are quite different,                        3.2        Challenges&#13;
for instance, in a concession contract than in a                                   Consumer organizations face numerous obstacles and&#13;
management contract), as this will have an impact on                               constraints in their quest to engage effectively in the&#13;
how consumer issues are handled.                                                   sector. One of these is the sheer size of the problem. The&#13;
                                                                                   gap between the current situation and the ideal, in which&#13;
Quality norms and standards                                                        there is active, vibrant and representative consumer&#13;
Do norms exist for such things as bacteriological quality                          representation, is huge. The question is thus ­ how can&#13;
of water, how are they enforced, and how are they                                  COs get "to scale" at country level, and begin to bridge&#13;
enshrined in contracts and sector development plans?                               the massive gap between what exists now, and what&#13;
                                                                                   would be a desirable situation in terms of consumer&#13;
Service level standards                                                            voice? What needs to be done to simply ensure that COs&#13;
Are there standards for such things as a guaranteed                                themselves are discussing water and sanitation sector&#13;
number of hours of service or a minimum pressure, how                              issues in an informed way, and to ensure that consumers&#13;
are these standards documented and enforced, and how                               themselves are making their perspectives heard?&#13;
are they enshrined in contracts and sector development                             The project partners discussed these at length in order&#13;
plans?                                                                             to come to terms with the challenges, and to determine&#13;
                                                                                   methods to overcome them. The challenges, and some&#13;
Billing practices                                                                  ideas for solutions, are explained below.&#13;
&#13;
The accuracy, frequency and fairness of billing have a&#13;
                                                                                   Lack of capacity and resources to engage in the water&#13;
great impact on consumers. It is important to understand&#13;
                                                                                   supply and sanitation sector&#13;
the basis on which bills are prepared, and the methods&#13;
used.                                                                              COs find it difficult to identify the best starting point to&#13;
                                                                                   address the challenge of establishing consumer&#13;
Redress Mechanisms                                                                 representationinthesector.Ingeneral,COslackexpertise&#13;
                                                                                   in the specific terminology and technicalities of the water&#13;
Redress mechanisms are an important part of consumer&#13;
                                                                                   and sanitation sector. In most cases, this sector is a new&#13;
protection. The redress mechanisms in place, and their&#13;
                                                                                   one for them, and the learning curve is steep. In&#13;
strengths and weaknesses, have to be fully understood.&#13;
                                                                                   particular, the participants from the four countries in the&#13;
                                                                                   project felt they lacked knowledge in such specifics as&#13;
Alternative technologies                                                           the nature of private sector contracts, the responsibilities&#13;
Many countries have found that alternative, innovative                             they place on operators and the incentives they create.&#13;
andlow-costtechnologiescanprovideimportantbenefits                                 As private sector participation is often an important issue&#13;
for utilities and customers. In particular, alternative                            in reform, the need to understand these legal and&#13;
technologies can sometimes allow low-income customers                              contractual issues places an additional burden on COs.&#13;
to gain access to services they could not afford previously.&#13;
In some cases, consumer lobbying may encourage                                     Added to this is the fact that responsibility for and&#13;
utilities to consider alternatives. However, the                                   management of the water and sanitation sector is often&#13;
appropriateness of these technologies for the local and                            scattered around many different ministries and agencies,&#13;
national context must be examined. It may be necessary                             making it difficult to identify the focal point, design&#13;
to make changes in regulations and standards to                                    advocacy, and effectively target the appropriate decision-&#13;
accommodate them.                                                                  makers.&#13;
&#13;
Governance                                                                         It is necessary to identify short term achievable goals to&#13;
The legislative and institutional framework for the water                          build up credibility and support before embarking on&#13;
supply and sanitation sector may be complicated, but it                            more complex, long term objectives. An additional&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
challenge is the need for financial resources to obtain&#13;
expert advice and carry out the capacity building and                                      Example: In Chad, the water sector review conducted by&#13;
advocacy planning needed. Consumers International at                                       the ADC of Chad enabled the consumer organization to&#13;
regional level (CI-ROAF) can help, but only within the                                     identify the core problems and bottlenecks to consumer&#13;
structure of the organization (which, as a membership                                      access in Chad. This helped the organization to articulate&#13;
organization, is based on a large degree of autonomy of                                    a well-defined position, presented to government, on the&#13;
the country-level associations). Ultimately, COs must                                      need to create a special fund for network expansion, and a&#13;
respond to local demands, and this means generating                                        proposal that it be financed through the value-added tax&#13;
local capacity and resources. However, COs must take                                       on water.&#13;
advantage of any training or capacity building that other&#13;
agencies make available (including CI itself).                                           Relationship with media&#13;
                                                                                         It is very important that COs are heard when there is a&#13;
COs identified the recommended solutions as:&#13;
·                                                                                        problem and have their opinion sought by the media.&#13;
       training and capacity building in such issues as&#13;
                                                                                         However, here too COs sometimes suffer from a lack of&#13;
       tariff setting, regulation, institutional and legislative&#13;
                                                                                         credibility and profile. Added to this is the fact that&#13;
       framework of water management, advocacy and&#13;
                                                                                         consumer stories do not always "sell" and may not be&#13;
       communication&#13;
·                                                                                        attractive to the media.&#13;
       Engagement of consultants and experts to work&#13;
       with COs&#13;
·                                                                                        The recommended solutions are:&#13;
       Technical support to COs                                                          ·      COs need to develop stories from a human-interest&#13;
  Example: The stakeholder meetings in both Kenya and                                           perspective to interest and engage the media&#13;
  Senegal provided opportunities for training and technical                              ·      COs need to respond to the topical issues on water&#13;
  support. For example, the Kenya Water Institute organized                                     in an informed manner, and engage media attention&#13;
  training on tariff setting and subsidies at the stakeholder&#13;
  workshop held by CIN. This training enabled participants                               Relationship with Consumers&#13;
  to understand the dynamics of tariff setting in Kenya, but                             The communication channels with consumers are not&#13;
  it also helped to identify weakness in the tariff setting regime                       always straightforward. COs speak on consumers'&#13;
  -- such as the fact that the present subsidy model is not                              behalf, but lack regular feedback (few COs in African&#13;
  well-targeted. The Senegal workshop organised by                                       countries could afford to run "hot lines"). COs rely on&#13;
  ADEETelS included a one-day capacity building workshop                                 consumer complaints which may not be representative.&#13;
  that centred on regulation, tariff setting and                                         There is also a disconnect between CO staff members,&#13;
  communication. Participants learned to understand the                                  who are mainly middle class, and very poor consumers.&#13;
  theoretical basis of the various models of regulation and                              Poor consumers may feel that consumer organizations&#13;
  tariff setting, and also how to effectively communicate their                          -- and indeed other civil society organizations -- are&#13;
  advocacy strategy to the wider public.                                                 taking advantage of their poverty to create jobs and&#13;
                                                                                         income for themselves. This may lead to resentment.&#13;
Relationship with government&#13;
COs complained of a lack of government openness and                                      There is also often reluctance on the part of consumers&#13;
will to work with civil society in the water supply and                                  to actively engage. Consumers expect consumer&#13;
sanitation sector. They felt that the actions of the                                     organizations to represent them. The role of COs is to&#13;
government tended to be shrouded in secrecy and civil                                    educate consumers to protect themselves. In addition to&#13;
society organizations were viewed as interlopers. COs                                    this, consumers may be interested in their rights, but not&#13;
often suffer from the lack of a formal relationship with                                 necessarily their responsibilities. This means that at times&#13;
government ­ they need to be officially recognized. There                                the message delivered by the CO may not be popular&#13;
is a need to establish a cooperative relationship with                                   (for instance that consumers should pay for services and&#13;
government and to be seen as a partner with similar aims                                 preserve the financial sustainability of service providers).&#13;
(that is, the well being of consumers/citizens).&#13;
                                                                                         The recommended solutions to these problems were for&#13;
COs complained of a lack of information, but also a lack                                 COs to:&#13;
of credibility ­ the two are clearly connected.                                          ·      Establish viable communication channels with&#13;
                                                                                                consumers--forexample,establishpublicdialogue&#13;
The recommended solutions for COs were to:&#13;
                                                                                                in the communities to solicit views and identify key&#13;
·      Establish the credibility of COs in the sector by&#13;
                                                                                                allies in the community, and then work through&#13;
       presenting government with a unique and well-&#13;
                                                                                                them to gain support and acceptance. This should&#13;
       informed          position          and       alternatives          for&#13;
                                                                                                not be "one-off" but a continuous process&#13;
       consideration.                                                                    ·      Develop the capacity to process complaints in order&#13;
·      Ensure that COs are not seen just as critics, but&#13;
                                                                                                to develop policy positions and use these to&#13;
       organizations providing constructive alternatives.&#13;
                                                                                                influence policy-makers. CI-ROAF has developed&#13;
·      Lobby the government on the need to facilitate&#13;
                                                                                                a training manual "How to Conduct Research"&#13;
       dialogue, and the benefits of this dialogue for&#13;
                                                                                                which outlines how to turn complaints into policy&#13;
       integration of broader interests in the policy making&#13;
                                                                                                and also how to do participatory research among&#13;
       process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8   Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
     consumers/communities and use this information&#13;
     to define a policy position.                                                  An additional issue is that consumer issues are not seen&#13;
                                                                                   at first glance as part of the "normal" development&#13;
   Example: In Malawi, the Consumer Association of                                 agenda. This leads to a need to position COs and&#13;
   Malawi organizes focus group discussions with local                             Consumers International in the development sector as&#13;
   communities to discuss issues relating to access to water                       organizations that have a role to play in combating&#13;
   and sanitation. The community participates in identifying                       poverty. It is also necessary to convince others who focus&#13;
   indicators for research, collaborates in the research itself                    on the poor that consumer issues fit their agenda ­ a point&#13;
   and aids in formulating recommendations. A                                      of view which may be unfamiliar to them.&#13;
   representative from the community is then selected to&#13;
   speak on behalf of the community to policy-makers.                              Recommended solutions include:&#13;
                                                                                   ·        ensuring each partner's role, mandate, competence&#13;
Relationships with donors                                                                   and objectives of partnership are discussed and&#13;
Like many civil society organizations, COs often benefit                                    clarified at the outset&#13;
from donor support. However, there is often a mismatch                             ·        encouraging greater flexibility on the part of donors&#13;
between donor expectations and objectives and what                                          when dealing with projects with COs&#13;
COs can or want to achieve. Funding for alternative                                ·        fostering greater communication and openness to&#13;
models and actions may not be made available should                                         new ideas on the part of both parties&#13;
these models not fall within the institutional objectives&#13;
of the funding partner. Both of these problems can result                          Relationships with other COs and NGOs&#13;
in instability and un-sustainability of donor-funded                               COs experience competition for funding, information,&#13;
projects.                                                                          powerandterritorywithotherCOs,andsometimesother&#13;
                                                                                   NGOs. Relations with other COs are complicated by the&#13;
While donor-funded projects can bring needed structure                             fact that consumer interests are not always monolithic,&#13;
and professional advice, COs sometimes feel that donors                            and there can be many points of view and approaches in&#13;
want to micro-mange the project they have funded for                               addressing them. From the point of view of other NGOs&#13;
them, and that they expect results according to a rigid                            in the sector, the consumer agenda is very wide. COs&#13;
and inflexible plan. The activities of the consumer                                must represent all consumers, not just those who are poor&#13;
movement do not always lend themselves to rigid                                    ­ this is different from the agenda of other development&#13;
planning or the delivery of pre-determined outputs.                                NGOs, who work exclusively for the poor. COs are thus&#13;
                                                                                   seen as "fringe" organizations both within poverty&#13;
Engaging with donors can also result in a multiplicity of                          alleviation debates and in the water and sanitation sector.&#13;
actors ­ sometimes with different and even conflicting&#13;
interests ­ which can impede the specific strengths of                             The recommended solutions are to:&#13;
COs which are flexibility and speed in action. Ideally,                            ·        Define a clear consumer perspective and tailor COs&#13;
the relationship with donors should be a two-way                                            inputs to the debate accordingly ­ what can COs&#13;
learning process. COs should use the donor perspective                                      contribute which other organizations cannot? What&#13;
to bring about professionalization, and learn from it to                                    distinct and thought-provoking points of view do&#13;
focus not just on activities but also impact. Donors                                        they have?&#13;
should recognize that working in such activities as                                ·        Consider working with, rather apart from, other&#13;
advocacy and capacity building is a slow process that                                       established players, and work towards buy-in of&#13;
cannot necessarily be boxed into an objective or time                                       the consumer agenda and its integration within the&#13;
frame.                                                                                      wider development agenda.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Chapter 4:                Models and Strategies for Engagement with Consumer&#13;
                          Organizations and Consumers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.1    In the Beginning ­ Getting Consumer                                              watersupplyandsanitationsector,placefactsandfigures&#13;
       Organizations Involved                                                           in the hands of the COs, and initiate a process of learning.&#13;
                                                                                        They also gave COs the opportunity to assess the existing&#13;
The first phase of this project focused on methods to&#13;
                                                                                        information and data, and analyse it from a consumer&#13;
engage COs and to facilitate their entry into the debate&#13;
                                                                                        angle.&#13;
about water and sanitation sector reforms in their&#13;
countries. There are already consumer organizations in&#13;
                                                                                        In some cases the COs hired consultants to undertake&#13;
46 countries inAfrica which are structured organizations&#13;
                                                                                        the country reviews, and in others they did the work in-&#13;
representing consumer concerns across a wide spectrum&#13;
                                                                                        house. In discussion, the participants agreed that some&#13;
of issues.&#13;
                                                                                        combination of the two is needed, in order to both build&#13;
                                                                                        capacity and ensure a high-quality product. Achallenge&#13;
The ways that the COs in the four project countries                                     in hiring consultants is that expertise is required to guide&#13;
became involved initially include:                                                      and evaluate their work (such as writing a Terms of&#13;
·    Carrying out country reviews                                                       Reference or monitoring progress) and this expertise is&#13;
·    Holding workshops or national stakeholder                                          difficult to attain.&#13;
     meetings&#13;
·    Arranging for their own capacity building.                                          Example: COs need to move away from the anecdotal to a&#13;
                                                                                         fact-based approach. For instance, prior to its involvement&#13;
&#13;
These are discussed in turn, including the role that                                     in this project, ADC in Chad had taken a stance against&#13;
&#13;
consumer associations played, and what we learned in                                     the levying of VAT on water in Chad. They felt that this&#13;
&#13;
this project with respect to their strengths and                                         would negatively impact on access by making water too&#13;
&#13;
weaknesses.                                                                              expensive for poor consumers. However as a result of the&#13;
                                                                                         country review, ADC found that only 2.8% of the Chadian&#13;
                                                                                         populace obtained water through the water mains, and that&#13;
4.1.1   Country Reviews                                                                  this segment could actually afford to pay the VAT. It&#13;
In all four countries the COs first carried out country                                  therefore changed its position to advocate for a special fund&#13;
reviews. These reviews were designed to examine the                                      for network expansion, financed by the revenue raised as a&#13;
                                                                                         result of the VAT on water. The following table summarises&#13;
                                                                                         the learning from country reviews:&#13;
  Lessons from Country Reviews&#13;
&#13;
   Role of Consumer&#13;
   Organization                                     Strengths                                                 Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
  · Carry out themselves                      ·     Carrying out country reviews, or                    ·     Need basic competence within association&#13;
                                                    collaborating with consultants,                           in order to be able to either carry out&#13;
                                                    builds capacity                                           reviews or commission them ­this is hard&#13;
                                                                                                              to obtain&#13;
&#13;
  · Commission consultants                    ·     Country reviews can provide a                       ·     Difficult to request consultants to provide&#13;
                                                    better understanding of the                               information when you don't know what&#13;
                                                    problem and can lead to new                               you are looking for&#13;
                                                    perspectives&#13;
&#13;
  · Combination                               ·     Provides a look at issues from                      ·     Competent and affordable consultants are&#13;
                                                    a unique consumer                                         hard to find&#13;
                                                    perspective&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        ·     Expensive, and sometimes hard to get&#13;
                                                                                                              information if you are not in the sector&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        ·     Field work can be dangerous if the&#13;
                                                                                                              community is not approached cautiously&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        ·     May be difficult for COs to get access to&#13;
                                                                                                              certain types of information and data&#13;
                                                                                                              (consultants may be able to help)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        ·     Doing reviews in-house creates risk that&#13;
                                                                                                              something is missed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10  Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.1.2   Workshops&#13;
&#13;
Workshops were used in three of the four countries as a                             weaknesses of workshops. In summary, they are&#13;
forum to present the results of the country reviews and                             excellent opportunities to create networks and build&#13;
develop an action plan to a variety of sector stakeholders                          awareness, but can also backfire if the CO is not ready to&#13;
&#13;
­ in this context they were referred to as "National                                present high-quality material. Bringing in many&#13;
                                                                                    stakeholders can be difficult for a CO that is new to the&#13;
Stakeholder Workshops". They were also used as&#13;
                                                                                    water sector, and requires considerable up-front work.&#13;
opportunities to hear the perspectives of the other                                 There is a danger that other stakeholders may be critical&#13;
stakeholders, and to listen to invited resource people on                           and not receptive to another organization entering the&#13;
topics identified as capacity building priorities.                                  sector. However, if COs indicate an honest willingness&#13;
                                                                                    to learn, and show they can provide a clearly unique and&#13;
Workshops can also be used at the beginning of an                                   valuable perspective, the workshops can be very&#13;
initiative to "kick-start" a process and inform key                                 productive. The advantage of workshops is that they&#13;
stakeholders of what you intend to do.                                              provide a public forum for both giving and receiving&#13;
                                                                                    information..&#13;
The table below summarizes the strengths and&#13;
&#13;
Lessons from Stakeholder Workshops&#13;
&#13;
Role of Consumer&#13;
Organization                 Strengths                                                                   Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
· Host                    · Enables validation of country reviews                                  · Difficult to find resource people&#13;
· Facilitate              · Contributes to improvement of country · Time consuming and expensive to&#13;
                                 reviews                                                                 arrange&#13;
                          · Allows a forum to articulate and action · Invitationofotherstakeholdersrequires&#13;
                                 plan                                                                    careful planning and networking in&#13;
                          · Establishes credibility of CO and creates                                    advance&#13;
                                 networks                                                          · "One shot" ­ last minute cancellations&#13;
                          · Creates opportunity for capacity building                                    or unforeseen events may result in&#13;
                          · Creates opportunity to disseminate                                           failure&#13;
                                 consumer perspective                                              · Risk of showcasing weaknesses instead&#13;
                          · Raises awareness (especially if there is                                     of strengths if country reviews or action&#13;
                                 press coverage)                                                         plan not well-thought-out or presented&#13;
                          · May identify hitherto unknown allies in · Participants may have expectations&#13;
                                 industry or the regulatory body                                         which COs cannot meet (in terms of&#13;
                          · May reinforce the CO position if                                             professionalism and quality of research)&#13;
                                 discussions go well                                               · Others in sector may not be willing to&#13;
                                                                                                         listen to "new entrant"&#13;
                                                                                                   · Difficult to discuss complex issues in&#13;
                                                                                                         large groups&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.1.3   Capacity Building&#13;
&#13;
CI-ROAF, WSP, and all four of the COs themselves                                        In practice, the COs found capacity building hard to&#13;
recognized that they needed capacity building. (In fact,                                arrange. They struggled with the dilemma of "not&#13;
the expressed need for this was the main reason for                                     knowing what they didn't know". As one participant&#13;
WSP's involvement. The WSP also recognized that the                                     put it: "You need capacity building to define your&#13;
project will help to familiarize World Bank staff about                                 capacity building needs". As new issues came to the&#13;
the concerns, role, capacity and potential of civil society                             COs' attention, they found it difficult to arrange objective&#13;
groups, and enhance their capacity to engage with them.                                 capacity building, as resource people were hard to find&#13;
WSP's support for the project came through a BNWP-                                      in-country.&#13;
financed project aimed at increasing the capacity of civil&#13;
society organizations.)&#13;
                                                                                        The list of issues identified as capacity building needs&#13;
                                                                                        included:&#13;
In Zambia, Senegal and Kenya, some capacity building&#13;
was provided through the National Stakeholder                                           ·       tariffs and subsidies&#13;
Workshop. Zambia and Senegal subsequently identified&#13;
further capacity building needs, which will be                                          ·       regulation&#13;
undertaken by the CO through national institutions and&#13;
other NGOs.                                                                             ·       models of private sector participation&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        ·       utility management&#13;
Lessons from Capacity Building&#13;
&#13;
Role of Consumer&#13;
Organization                     Strengths                                                                 Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
· Recipients                   · COs can build capacity of other · "Don't know what you don't know" ­&#13;
· Supplier                           organizations, other partners and                                      hard for COs to create capacity building&#13;
                                     stakeholders toseeaconsumerperspective                                 agenda before they understand major&#13;
                                     and understand consumer issues                                         sector issues&#13;
&#13;
                               · Cross fertilization between COs is a very · Need resources for resource people,&#13;
                                     powerful tool                                                          training workshops etc.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      · Suitableresourcepeoplehardtofindin-&#13;
                                                                                                            country&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.1.4   Networking&#13;
There are many institutions and organizations active in                                 government agencies active in water and sanitation in&#13;
the water sector and sanitation sector. These                                           order to access information, establish joint positions and&#13;
organizations have accumulated knowledge and                                            advocate on common themes.&#13;
information, established key contacts and linkages, and&#13;
learnt how to engage a range of stakeholders in the sector.                             Networking need not restrict itself to the national and&#13;
These linkages -- both institutional and personal -- are                                regional arena only. Water sector reform is taking place&#13;
important for consumer organizations to tap into in order                               globally and is being influenced by such regional and&#13;
to identify and articulate a well-informed consumer                                     multilateral agreements as the United Nations&#13;
position. In addition, many civil society organizations                                 Millennium Development Goals, the World Trade&#13;
have found it useful to form broad coalitions around                                    Organization's GeneralAgreement on Trade in Services,&#13;
common themes and issues in order to achieve "critical                                  and the New Partnership for Africa's Development&#13;
mass" and advocate for change.                                                          (NEPAD). There are common issues around which civil&#13;
                                                                                        society, including COs, need to share information and&#13;
Consumer organizations in all countries network with                                    undertake regional and global advocacy.&#13;
local communities, other civil society organizations and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12  Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Lessons from Networking&#13;
&#13;
Role of Consumer&#13;
Organization                  Strengths                                                                  Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
· Initiators               · Information sharing                                                   · Differing institutional mandates and&#13;
                                                                                                         objectives can clash and limit&#13;
· Members                  · Cross fertilization between COs other                                       networking&#13;
                                  CSOs and government&#13;
&#13;
                           · Strength in numbers around common · Limited commitment to coalitions&#13;
                                  themes                                                                 because of individual institutional focus&#13;
&#13;
                           · Improves                  policy          positions         and&#13;
                                  recommendations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.2    The Next Step ­ Engaging and Representing                                      among others, ammunition and racehorses were exempt.&#13;
       Consumers Themselves                                                           The Burkina Faso Consumer Organization (LCB) launched&#13;
The next step for the consumer organizations in this                                  a campaign against the tax on water, arguing that water&#13;
project, once they understood the sector, was to engage                               was a more important good than ammunition and&#13;
in country-level activities aimed at educating,                                       racehorses. LCB first met with members of parliament. As&#13;
representing and engaging consumers themselves.                                       a result of these discussions, a petition was sent to&#13;
                                                                                      parliament. At the same time, LCB sent a letter to the&#13;
The activities used in order to achieve this included:                                Government, outlining their position and their demands.&#13;
·    Advocacy in various forms                                                        Volunteers with LCB approached people paying their bills&#13;
·    Becoming a service provider                                                      at the offices of the water company and asked for signatures&#13;
·    Representing consumers on regulatory boards and                                  in support of the demand to lift the new tax on water. The&#13;
     at other sector institutions                                                     signatures were later handed to the Government. Within a&#13;
·    Carrying out consumer education.                                                 month of starting the campaign, which received a great&#13;
                                                                                      deal of media coverage, the Government changed the&#13;
4.2.1    Advocacy                                                                     threshold above which VAT on water was charged, raising&#13;
                                                                                      it from 15 cubic meters per month to 50 cubic meters per&#13;
AlltheCOsinvolveddidadvocacyinonewayoranother,&#13;
                                                                                      month. This means in practice that VAT on water would&#13;
and this was considered a vital activity. When done in&#13;
                                                                                      not be levied on most domestic consumption.&#13;
the context of a good relationship with the media and&#13;
policy-makers, advocacy can allow wide dissemination&#13;
                                                                                    2.      Direct consumer action ­ this entails mobilizing&#13;
ofissues,andcreatesopportunitiestoinfluencedecisions.&#13;
                                                                                            consumers to demonstrate for a specific issue. An&#13;
                                                                                            important feature of successful direct consumer&#13;
Various methods of advocacy were used. A major&#13;
                                                                                            action is being able to demonstrate that COs can&#13;
challenge for COs is to identify clearly what they want&#13;
                                                                                            mobilize people in large numbers. However, events&#13;
to see changed and to maintain a continuous, permanent&#13;
                                                                                            such as demonstrations must be handled very&#13;
and well-targeted program of advocacy (including&#13;
                                                                                            carefully indeed as they can easily go wrong, attract&#13;
education of stakeholders) aiming at achieving that&#13;
                                                                                            people who are not really interested in the issue, or&#13;
objective, rather than relying on a string of "one-off"&#13;
                                                                                            end in violence. Being aware of these risks, COs&#13;
events; that is, moving "from protest from proposal".&#13;
                                                                                            often have carefully designed strategies for dealing&#13;
                                                                                            with these things.&#13;
Forms of advocacy used by the COs included:&#13;
1.   Lobbying government through petitions, letters,                                  Example: ADC in Chad organized a peaceful consumer&#13;
     meetings and informal discussions - in these                                     march to press government to recognize water and&#13;
     instance consumers, through COs, define their                                    electricity as basic consumer rights, and to begin action on&#13;
     positions and present these to government for                                    the recommendations put forward by the ADC on water&#13;
     consideration.                                                                   sector reform. More than 3000 consumers participated. As&#13;
                                                                                      a result, the government integrated some of the&#13;
 Example: In 1993, the Government of Burkina Faso                                     recommendations into the national water and sanitation&#13;
 introduced a value-added tax on goods and services. Water,                           policy.&#13;
 except for a small amount per month, was to be taxed as&#13;
 well. The Government had not imposed the tax on all goods:                         3.      Using the media - which can be a very effective&#13;
                                                                                            toolingettingamessagetoconsumersandsparking&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
     a national debate on an issue. For instance,                                       4.2.2      Service Provision&#13;
     consumers calling in to radio shows and expressing&#13;
     their views on the air can create pressure on national                             In Senegal, ADEETelS was already actively engaged in&#13;
     government to effect needed change.                                                service provision, where some local cells of the&#13;
                                                                                        organization run standposts. ADEETelS had embarked&#13;
                                                                                        upon service delivery because they wanted to&#13;
   Example: The Association des Consommateurs du Mali                                   demonstrate that it was possible to sell water at prices&#13;
 (ASCOMA) conducted a country review and consumer                                       that were less than those charged at many of the stand&#13;
 survey on access to water and electricity in Mali. The                                 posts in the city, and to provide competition. This&#13;
 findings and recommendations were presented to                                         decision was taken mainly as the prescribed tariffs for&#13;
 government in June 2003. The government however made                                   water sold at the existing privately-run taps were not&#13;
 no commitment and took no action. ASCOMA therefore                                     being adhered to, and the agency tasked with regulating&#13;
 organised a press conference to inform the public about                                prices did not respond to the campaigns and advocacy&#13;
 their findings and also participated in several radio and                              efforts undertaken by ADEETelS.&#13;
 TV dialogues in French and the local language to speak&#13;
 about the problems of consumer access in the utility sector.                           In Chad, ADC has been working with local community-&#13;
 The government took note and reconvened another meeting                                based organizations to install a borehole which now&#13;
 with ASCOMA and other stakeholders at which ASCOMA                                     serves 2000 households in two districts. The borehole has&#13;
 recommendations were debated, refined and accepted. A                                  now been handed over to the local community group to&#13;
 mechanism for regular consultation between ASCOMA,                                     run.&#13;
 the regulator and the utility company was also established.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Lessons from Advocacy&#13;
&#13;
Role of Consumer&#13;
Association                      Strengths                                                                 Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
 · Initiate                    · Can result in wide dissemination of issues · Can be difficult to do if communication&#13;
                                                                                                            skills are lacking&#13;
 · Manage                      · Can result in influencing key decisions&#13;
&#13;
 · Participate in              · Can draw upon and use the · Requires resources to pay for travel,&#13;
     others'                         professionalism of members                                             media space/air time, volunteer&#13;
     campaigns                                                                                              expenses&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      · Can be difficult to coordinate the&#13;
                                                                                                            relationship between other NGOs and&#13;
                                                                                                            even other COs (who may work at cross-&#13;
                                                                                                            purposes)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      · Difficult to do while still learning about&#13;
                                                                                                            sector issues&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      · Requiresstrongrelationshipwithmedia&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      · Mass advocacy can be difficult if there&#13;
                                                                                                            is a lack of consumer education&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      · Can be difficult to design a message -&#13;
                                                                                                            people may be willing to rally around&#13;
                                                                                                            their rights as consumers, but less&#13;
                                                                                                            willing to accept their responsibilities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14  Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In Kenya, CIN has been a catalyst, facilitating the                                 4.2.3        Consumer Education&#13;
construction of a water and sanitation point by providing                           Consumer education is closely related to advocacy. As&#13;
training and material to the community, who have then                               noted with advocacy, COs felt there was a need to have&#13;
constructed the point and manage it.                                                continuous programs of consumer education, with good&#13;
                                                                                    targeting.&#13;
There is great debate over the wisdom of COs becoming&#13;
service providers. Some see it as a logical step in winning                         A major point of debate is to what extent consumer&#13;
the confidence of consumers and demonstrating a hands-                              education is the role of government. COs feel that at least&#13;
on approach to the sector. Others fear that it is a "slippery                       some consumer education should be the responsibility&#13;
slope" and creates too many problems in terms of mixing                             of government, either directly, or through COs which it&#13;
up the role of COs with that of the utility providers they                          supports. One of the problems is that government often&#13;
wish to lobby, and creating risks such as internal conflict                         "divorces" itself, resigning responsibility for consumer&#13;
and misuse of revenue.                                                              education and leaving this to COs (which are under-&#13;
                                                                                    resourced, and have to turn to donors for funding).&#13;
There is general consensus that, even when it is&#13;
undertaken, this is not a long-term role for COs. The role                          Inordertocommunicateeffectivelywithconsumers,COs&#13;
of the CO in service provision should be mainly as a                                need to identify and target consumer groups based on&#13;
demonstrator and facilitator. COs might want to act as a                            the issues they face in accessing water supply and&#13;
catalyst in setting up services, which are then handed                              sanitation services. COs need to use the best means of&#13;
over to community management, perhaps with CO                                       reaching the different target groups, which could vary ­&#13;
supervision.However,eventhisrepresentsariskinterms                                  for instance newspaper inserts, TV and radio spaces,&#13;
of the potential "slippage" of responsibilities, leaving                            press conferences, education through entertainment such&#13;
COs with obligations they don't want, rather than being                             as plays, dramas and song, or community based focus&#13;
able to disappear from the management arrangement.                                  group discussions may be appropriate depending upon&#13;
                                                                                    the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Lessons from Service Provision&#13;
&#13;
  Role of Consumer&#13;
  Organization                  Strengths                                                                Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
 · Become a                · Raises visibility                                                     · Can jeopardize image and credibility&#13;
     service&#13;
     provider              · Providespeopleinterestedintheconsumer · CandistractfrommainobjectiveofCOs&#13;
                                  movement with concrete evidence of&#13;
 · Manage a                       commitment to their needs                                        · May create temptation to pursue profit-&#13;
     demonstration                                                                                       making (also risk of ignoring planned&#13;
     project in            · Can increase membership and mobilize                                        price in the future and raising prices in&#13;
     service                      consumers                                                              order to generate more revenues)&#13;
     provision&#13;
                           · Creates new and interesting relationship · Creates conflict of interest (can a CO&#13;
                                  with main service provider                                             carry out effective advocacy on prices if&#13;
                                                                                                         they themselves are selling water?)&#13;
                           · Can demonstrate alternative service&#13;
                                  delivery is possible&#13;
&#13;
                           · Can drive prices down&#13;
&#13;
                           · Can educate COs in the realities of service&#13;
                                  delivery&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                        4.2.4      Representing Consumers&#13;
 Example:In the Seychelles, the National Consumer Forum&#13;
 (NATCOF) has developed a credible and visible relationship                             Consumers are often called upon to represent consumers&#13;
&#13;
 with the local media. The organization has a regular column                            on regulatory boards and other bodies. Two of the&#13;
&#13;
 in the weekly paper, and ensures that on such days as World                            consumers associations which took part in the project&#13;
&#13;
 Water Day the organization feeds the media with stories                                have representatives who sit on such boards. ZACAhas&#13;
&#13;
 and articles on consumers and water. As the theme for                                  just been invited to be a member of the National Water&#13;
&#13;
 World Consumer Rights Day 2004 was "Water is a                                         Supply and Sanitation Council (NWASCO), and&#13;
&#13;
 Consumer Right", NATCOF organized consumer                                             ADEETelS has both a seat on the board of the state asset-&#13;
&#13;
 education on the need for sustainable use of water and water                           holding company in Senegal (SONES) and has just been&#13;
&#13;
 conservation in collaboration with the local radio station                             appointed a member of the management committee for&#13;
&#13;
 and the water utility company. Experts from both the                                   the next phase of water sector reform.&#13;
&#13;
 ministry responsible for water and the water utility were                              A challenge for COs is to correctly represent consumer&#13;
 invited to an on-air discussion and consumers were invited                             perspectives and opinions on issues which arise at such&#13;
 to call in and raise issues. At the end of the program a quiz                          bodies. There are various means by which consumer&#13;
 was held and prizes awarded.                                                           organization can solicit consumer views on issues of&#13;
                                                                                        concern:&#13;
 Example: In Tunisia, the consumer organization has                                     1.      Consumer/marketsurvey­thisentailsdeveloping&#13;
 developed a tripartite relationship between itself, the                                        a survey instrument and using this instrument as a&#13;
 ministry in charge of water, and the water utility company.                                    basis for conducting interviews in the field with a&#13;
 This alliance has developed a consumer education program                                       selected sample population. For example in Mali,&#13;
 and methodology to educate consumers on such issues as                                         the consumer organization ASCOMA, in&#13;
 water wastage - which is of primary importance in Tunisia&#13;
 as it is a desert country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Lessons from Consumer Education&#13;
&#13;
 Role of Consumer&#13;
 Organization                       Strengths                                                              Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
 · Educate                     · Raises visibility                                                    · Requires specific expertise in&#13;
    members                                                                                                 community education&#13;
    and                        · Ensures that consumers know rights and&#13;
    consumers at                     understand issues                                                · Risk of getting it wrong ­ must be sure&#13;
    large about                                                                                             of issue, understand culture and target&#13;
    sector issues,             · Allows consumers to make informed                                          message well&#13;
    consumer                         choices&#13;
    rights and                                                                                        · Risk of delivering the wrong message if&#13;
    responsibilities           · Results in changed behaviour which                                         the sector is not well understood&#13;
                                     benefits society as a whole (i.e. water&#13;
                                     wastage, prompt bill payment)                                    · May be difficult, and even risky, for&#13;
                                                                                                            educators to work in some areas&#13;
                               · Can increase membership and credibility&#13;
                                     of CO (adds value)&#13;
&#13;
                               · Supports advocacy activities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16  Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    collaboration with a research consultant designed                                      COs. Members of the public can bring complaints&#13;
    a research questionnaire to identify impacts and                                       to COs who either refer them to the appropriate&#13;
    issues of concern to consumers as a result of the                                      agency, or try and represent the consumer to get&#13;
    waterandelectricityreformprocessinMali.Atarget                                         the problem solved. Knowledge of these complaints&#13;
    population in the capital representing a range of                                      helps COs to understand the issues and concerns&#13;
    incomeswasidentifiedandinterviewed.Theresults                                          faced by consumers.&#13;
    were collated and integrated into a sector review&#13;
    document prepared by ASCOMA and formed the                                     Internally within CI the question has been raised as to&#13;
    basis of ASCOMA representation on behalf of                                    the appropriateness of COs taking positions within&#13;
    consumers in Mali                                                              regulatory structures. For COs in Latin America for&#13;
                                                                                   example, it was deemed best for COs to operate outside&#13;
2.  Focus group discussions ­ this form of information                             of the official structures as they feared that consumer&#13;
    gathering is best done on a community basis. It is a                           ability to criticize the regulatory structures could be&#13;
    two-way learning process for both community and                                compromised. In addition to this there was the problem&#13;
    researcher. It however requires knowledge of the                               of secrecy as COs would be bound by confidentiality as&#13;
    methodology. This is the methodology employed                                  members of the regulatory board and this would restrict&#13;
    by the Consumer Association of Malawi, which                                   their ability to bring certain issues to the public domain.&#13;
    goes into local communities, mainly rural, and                                 In this context some countries in Latin America such as&#13;
    organises meeting of women, youth and men to                                   Colombia, have established consultative or advisory&#13;
    discuss the problem of access to water in their                                bodies to advise the regulator. These bodies are&#13;
    communities. The communities can then engage                                   composed of representatives of consumer, utilities and&#13;
    actively on how they perceive the problem and                                  industry experts. In Argentina a special tripartite&#13;
    make suggestions on how to improve the situation                               commission was established, involving providers,&#13;
    in their communities. One drawback of this                                     consumers and regulators, to deal with consumer&#13;
    approach is that findings are peculiar to a specific                           concerns. However many African members felt that&#13;
    community and may not be comparable across                                     working from within the regulatory board was the best&#13;
    communities.                                                                   solution within theAfrican context as it gave COs greater&#13;
                                                                                   opportunity to instigate changes.&#13;
3.  Complaints handling ­ this is a core function of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Lessons from Representing Consumers&#13;
&#13;
  Role of Consumer&#13;
  Organization                 Strengths                                                                Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
 · Represent              · Opportunity to influence sector from · Can be a "façade"&#13;
    consumers                    within&#13;
    through a                                                                                     · If technical issues not understood,&#13;
    seat on the           · Allows decisions of Board to be reviewed                                    capacity for meaningful representation&#13;
    Board                        by those with a consumer perspective (if                               lost ­ need training&#13;
                                 consumers stay away, decisions will be&#13;
                                 made anyway)                                                     · Risk that COs will be "captured" and&#13;
                                                                                                        become part of a dysfunctional system&#13;
· Consultative            · Opportunity to lobby&#13;
    and                                                                                           · Can jeopardize autonomy and&#13;
    participatory         · Creates relationship with and access to                                     independence&#13;
    status                       decision          makers           (and     access         to&#13;
                                 information)                                                     · Lackofaccesstoinformationcaninhibit&#13;
                                                                                                        participation&#13;
· Certify the             · COs have greater leeway to act if&#13;
    appointment                  regulations or policies are against&#13;
&#13;
    of regulator                 consumer interest&#13;
&#13;
                          · Input into decision-making processes&#13;
                                 through formal or informal hearings&#13;
&#13;
                          · Ward against regulatory capture by&#13;
                                 companies and or political interest.&#13;
                                 Appointees know that consumers will&#13;
                                 verify their continuance based on the&#13;
                                 actions they took to ensure consumer&#13;
                                 protection&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.3    Project Learning ­ Models for Replication                                        system quality, access, tariffs and institutional barriers&#13;
                                                                                        to consumer participation. The research was&#13;
4.3.1    Models to Engage Consumer Organizations                                        implemented by the team of consultants, with the&#13;
                                                                                        consultant in each country "twinned" with a CO member&#13;
                                                                                        from that country, where an active consumer&#13;
Project Model&#13;
                                                                                        organization could be found.&#13;
The sequence of the elements used by this project started&#13;
with country reviews commissioned by each CO (or                                        After the research was complete, a national workshop&#13;
carried out by CO members themselves). The objective                                    was held in each country (with the exception of Mexico&#13;
was to evaluate the situation, strengthen the credibility                               - the Mexican workshop was piggybacked to the regional&#13;
oftheCO,andmakeitmoreprofessional.Ineachcountry,                                        workshop) to deliver the findings. Aregional workshop,&#13;
the reviews were followed by a workshop to which as                                     held in Santiago, Chile, followed this at which a regional&#13;
many sector stakeholders as possible were invited. This                                 analysis was presented. The regional workshop attracted&#13;
workshop was designed to mobilize opinion and bridge                                    participants from academia, the World Bank, a citizens&#13;
the gap between the stakeholders. The workshop was                                      group from the US and the governments and regulatory&#13;
also intended to provide new insights, which would                                      agencies of the respective countries. Participants also&#13;
further strengthen the review (and revision of the country                              included ex-regulators and international experts. The&#13;
review was a next step). The workshop was also designed                                 regional workshop resulted in 50 proposals for actions&#13;
to be a forum at which the interventions of the CO would                                by regulators, consumers and private enterprises. In&#13;
be designed and an action plan developed.                                               some countries, further capacity building and research&#13;
                                                                                        were initiated.&#13;
           The sequence of elements was thus:&#13;
                                                                                        This model had both strengths and weaknesses. It&#13;
                          Country Review                                                allowed for initial capacity-building of the COs through&#13;
                                                                                        the inception workshop, and the twinning of professional&#13;
                                                                                        consultants with CO members also built capacity. The&#13;
 National Stakeholders Workshop/Capacity Building                                       iterative process meant that COs were well-prepared to&#13;
                                                                                        discuss issues in a substantive way by the time of the&#13;
                                                                                        regional workshop. However, it was expensive and some&#13;
           Revision of Country Review Report                                            critics have said it had a tendency to be academic. The&#13;
                                                                                        relationship between the consultants and the COs was&#13;
                                                                                        difficult as the consultants (who were academics or&#13;
     Country Level Interventions with Consumers                                         independent researchers) did not necessarily understand&#13;
                              Themselves                                                the objectives of the COs or share their vision.&#13;
&#13;
While the initial country review was an opportunity to                                  The sequence of elements was thus:&#13;
learn more about the sector, the participants in the project&#13;
found that more capacity was needed to enable them to                                              Inception Workshop/Capacity Building&#13;
properly design the research.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Latin America Model                                                                                                      Research&#13;
&#13;
In Latin America, a similar project was carried out from&#13;
1997 to 1999. This project was much larger in scope (for                                                        National Workshops&#13;
instance, it encompassed not only water, but also&#13;
electricity and telecommunications), and it was&#13;
implemented by Consumers International Office for                                                               Regional Workshop&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean in collaboration with&#13;
COs in five countries (Mexico, Colombia, Brazil, Peru&#13;
and Chile). Funding was provided by DFID.                                                             Proposals for Action/Interventions&#13;
&#13;
The sequence of elements started out with an inception&#13;
workshop designed to let stakeholders know what the                                     Proposed Hybrid Model&#13;
COs planned to do. CI-ROLAC staff working on the&#13;
                                                                                        After examining the strengths and weaknesses of the&#13;
project, international experts, experts from each country,&#13;
                                                                                        model used in the project and that used in LatinAmerica,&#13;
and a regional team of consultants engaged by&#13;
                                                                                        the participants of the project proposed another possible&#13;
Consumers International participated in the workshop.&#13;
                                                                                        sequence of elements for initial engagement of consumer&#13;
The purpose of this workshop was to brief the national&#13;
                                                                                        organizations.&#13;
researchers on the state of the international debate in the&#13;
                                                                                        In this model, the process would start with a "research&#13;
different sectors and agree on a methodology.&#13;
                                                                                        formulationworkshop"atwhichadvicewouldbesought&#13;
                                                                                        on the issues to be examined in the country review. This&#13;
The inception workshop was followed by research into&#13;
                                                                                        workshop could be regional, or at country level, though&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18  Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
there would be many advantages to having it at regional                             thorough research and understanding of the issues. To&#13;
level. This workshop would also be used as a forum for                              be most effective and credible, this must include research&#13;
capacity building on technical issues and general water                             among consumers themselves. COs need to have clear&#13;
and sanitation sector reform plans.                                                 objectives when engaging with consumers, and the&#13;
                                                                                    ability to be both flexible yet "stay on course" when&#13;
The country review would then be carried out, and                                   carrying out a program of activities.&#13;
presented at a national stakeholders workshop. This&#13;
would be followed by practical capacity building on such                            There is a wide variety of channels available to COs when&#13;
issues as communications and advocacy, and also on                                  engaging with consumers, including the media, schools,&#13;
other issues which the research had highlighted. The final                          meetings, and direct action. An effective program of&#13;
step would be the activities designed to engage                                     engagement may require several channels at once in&#13;
consumers themselves.                                                               order to both ensure the message is heard, and to lend&#13;
                                                                                    credence to it. The channels must be carefully chosen,&#13;
The proposed hybrid model is thus:                                                  and the messages developed with care.&#13;
&#13;
 Research Formulation Workshop/Capacity Building                                    As the examples in this report have illustrated, COs in&#13;
                                                                                    Africa are already engaging with consumers on water&#13;
                                                                                    and sanitation issues through:&#13;
             Research/Field visits by staff                                         ·       Participatory research&#13;
                                                                                    ·       Focus group discussions&#13;
                                                                                    ·       Meetings&#13;
            National Stakeholders Workshop                                          ·       Phone-in, on-air radio shows&#13;
                                                                                    ·       Eliciting signatures for petitions&#13;
                                                                                    ·       Consumer education in schools&#13;
&#13;
              Practical Capacity Building                                           ·       Marches and demonstrations&#13;
                                                                                    ·       Participation in service provision&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    Globally, there are many other examples of engagement&#13;
       In-country Activities to Engage Consumers&#13;
                                                                                    with consumers, for instance the very effective "Report&#13;
                                                                                    Cards" used in India to allow consumers to regularly&#13;
                                                                                    express their opinions on service levels and customer&#13;
4.3.2    Models for Engaging Consumers&#13;
                                                                                    relations for utilities such as water and electricity.&#13;
Consumers are a wide and divergent group and as such&#13;
the issues that affect them and the method of reaching                              There is much rich experience to be shared. Expanding&#13;
them differs. As was amply documented during this                                   consumerengagementinthewatersupplyandsanitation&#13;
project, consumer organizations need to carefully                                   sectorwillrequirethattheseinnovativeapproaches,from&#13;
identify the issues they wish to take action on, the                                both within Africa and beyond, are further developed,&#13;
objectives they wish to achieve, their target consumer                              adapted and replicated.&#13;
groups, and the best means of reaching those groups.&#13;
COs need to create a sequence of systematic,&#13;
complementary activities ­ avoiding impulsive and&#13;
unplanned actions ­ which are designed as a result of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Chapter 5:                Conclusions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumers are important stakeholders in the water and                                   interests of consumers with enthusiasm, dedication and&#13;
sanitation sector (many would argue the most important)                                 tenacity. In order to do this they must build their own&#13;
and there is an urgent requirement for their voice to be                                capacity and credibility. With the will and trust of&#13;
heard during the process of sector reform. This                                         governments, the support of donors and the&#13;
requirementgoesbeyondconsultation--aneffectiveand                                       encouragement of the development community they are&#13;
permanent mechanism is needed for consumers to                                          well-placed to do this.&#13;
participate actively. The consumer movement has a long&#13;
and impressive history in bringing the interests of                                     This report has outlined the methodology and strategies&#13;
consumerstotheforefront,butatthesametimehasmuch                                         used by four pioneering consumer organizations in&#13;
to learn about the development and management of                                        Africa to build understanding of the issues and raise&#13;
"public good" services such as water and sanitation.                                    profile. The selected approaches varied, but all combined&#13;
                                                                                        research and learning with action; an important mix for&#13;
Consumers themselves are by no means a monolithic                                       active organizations seeking to respond to rapidly&#13;
group; there are differing categories of consumers with                                 unfolding current events, build on existing&#13;
differing needs and capacities. At times their objectives                               programming, and remain accountable and relevant to&#13;
may not necessarily coincide, but all consumers need                                    a membership base. Drawing from this range of&#13;
access to information and the technical support and                                     experience, this report documents lessons learned from&#13;
capacity building to understand issues in the water and                                 different types of engagement in the water and sanitation&#13;
sanitation sector. As consumer representatives,                                         sector. These case studies presented here by no means&#13;
Consumer Organizations must be vigilant and critical,                                   represent the full spectrum of possible approaches, but&#13;
and continue to call on governments to make the water                                   the lessons learned represent a good starting point for&#13;
sector function properly in terms of price, quality, access,                            consumer organizations seeking to establish themselves&#13;
equity and sustainability, whilst ensuring transparency                                 in the water and sanitation sector.&#13;
and good governance.&#13;
                                                                                        The scale of the challenge posed in establishing effective&#13;
As this report has outlined, COs in Africa face many                                    representation of water and sanitation consumers in&#13;
challenges in establishing themselves as significant                                    urban Africa is daunting ­ but it is a vital and much-&#13;
players in the water and sanitation sector, but they also                               neglected dimension to water and sanitation sector&#13;
have the potential to bring a unique and important                                      reform. More resources are required, more tools need to&#13;
perspective. The consumer movement has demonstrated                                     be developed, and more work is needed to support&#13;
its commitment to poverty alleviation, and there are                                    consumer organizations in Africa and to enable them to&#13;
consumer organizations in many, if not most, African                                    move "from protest to proposal", and become&#13;
countries, many supported at regional and international                                 permanently established as important, vital and effective&#13;
level by Consumers International. These organizations                                   stakeholders in the sector.&#13;
are ready to take up the challenge of representing the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20  Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 1 ­ Detailed Description of In-country Activities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Chad&#13;
                                                                                     In terms of advocacy, theADC is now advocating for the&#13;
In Chad theAssociation de Defense des Consommateurs&#13;
                                                                                     following:&#13;
of Chad (ADC) had previously been involved in the&#13;
water sector through the provision of a water point which                            ·       All revenues from the value added tax on water&#13;
&#13;
serves 2000 households in two peri-urban districts of                                        should be allocated to a special fund for network&#13;
&#13;
N'djamena, namely Am-tounkouin and Sabangali                                                 extension.&#13;
&#13;
districts. It had also actively lobbied government to                                ·       A decrease in the price of water sold by private&#13;
eliminate the value added tax (VAT) on water, as ADC                                         vendors through a municipal regulation&#13;
considered the VAT to be a contributing factor to low                                ·       Periodic water quality testing by the municipality&#13;
access to water in Chad. With the onset of this project                              ·       Revision of the contract between the State and&#13;
ADC undertook familiarization of the water sector in                                         Vivendi, the private water utility operator, to ensure&#13;
Chad. This aided the organization to identify the core                                       investment and extension in the sector. The present&#13;
problems and bottlenecks to consumer access to water                                         contract does not include any performance&#13;
in Chad and also help the ADC better understand the                                          efficiency indicators to ensure that more consumers&#13;
water sector in Chad. This, for instance, changed ADC's                                      are connected to the network.&#13;
position on the VAT tax on water. Since access to water&#13;
was mainly being enjoyed by the better-off Chadians,                                 ADC is also in the process of working with community&#13;
the removal of VAT on water would actually not benefit                               organizations in several districts to construct boreholes.&#13;
the poor (who had no or limited access), but the better-                             These water points will be operated and managed by&#13;
off who were the only consumers receiving a service. The                             the local communities. Each community will receive&#13;
ADC therefore amended its position on the VAT                                        training on how to operate and maintain the water points&#13;
accordingly.                                                                         and also consumer education on water conservation and&#13;
The country review results were then discussed at a                                  sanitation.&#13;
national training workshop, which brought together 40&#13;
participants from the public sector ( water and sanitation                           ADC also wants to put in place a system to collect solid&#13;
ministries), NGOs, the Water Company, the European                                   waste from peri-urban areas so as to improve sanitation&#13;
Union delegation in Chad and consumers/resident                                      and prevent waste from contaminating the groundwater&#13;
groups fromAm-tounkouin and Sabangali districts; who                                 from which the water points will draw water.&#13;
were ADC local partners in this project. The results of&#13;
this workshop were as follows:                                                       Kenya&#13;
·    Improvement of the country review report from                                   The Consumer Information Network (CIN) prepared a&#13;
     inputs, comments and criticism at the meeting                                   case study of the Korogocho slum, one of the largest&#13;
·    Adoption of the revised country review document                                 informal settlements in Nairobi. During preparation of&#13;
·    Formulation and adoption of short term plan of                                  the case study, CIN collected and analyzed information&#13;
     action for consumers in the water sector                                        in order to develop a good understanding of the&#13;
·    Enhanced visibility of ADC and consumers as key                                 legislative and regulatory framework relating to water&#13;
     players in water sector reform in Chad                                          services provision to the urban poor. The case study&#13;
·    Recommendations from the country review and                                     revealed many issues that were of great concern in order&#13;
&#13;
     stakeholder meetings incorporated into national                                 to enhance access to water services by vulnerable&#13;
&#13;
     water and sanitation strategy document.                                         consumers, paramount being inadequate policy and the&#13;
                                                                                     lack of a regulatory framework for water pricing in&#13;
ADC organized a peaceful march from August 19th to                                   informal settlements. For a variety of reasons, one of&#13;
20th 2003 demanding water and electricity as basic                                   which is that vendors do not observe the pricing&#13;
&#13;
consumerrights.Morethan3000consumersparticipated.                                    guidelines, poor consumers in the slums pay more than&#13;
ADC also had working sessions with the 1st Vice                                      ten times more for water than consumers with piped&#13;
&#13;
President of the national legislative assembly to present                            connections.&#13;
&#13;
the concerns of consumers. ADC has also presented to&#13;
the government a memorandum from consumers on the                                    After the research was complete, CIN organized a three-&#13;
&#13;
key issues and concerns for consumers relative to water                              day workshop in Nairobi in February 2003 to present its&#13;
&#13;
and sanitation access in Chad with recommendations on                                findings and initiate a national network on water and&#13;
&#13;
the way forward. ADC is now focusing its activities on                               sanitation. Outputs of the workshop were as follows:&#13;
&#13;
educating consumers on their rights within the water                                 ·       Improvement of the research report from inputs,&#13;
sector. This will be done through information and                                            comments and criticism at meeting&#13;
training documentation, newsletters and weekly radio                                 ·       Creation of a network active in civil society&#13;
programmes on a local FM station. ADC also intends to                                        organizations active in water&#13;
conduct periodic water quality checks.                                               ·       Formulation and adoption of short term plan of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      action for consumers in the water sector                                           academics, the ombudsman, press and civil society&#13;
·     Enhanced visibility of CIN and consumers as key                                    organizations such as ADC (Association de Defense des&#13;
      players in water sector reform in Zambia. CIN is                                   Droits des Consommateurs or Association for Defense&#13;
      now regularly consulted by the Ministry of Water                                   of the Rights of Consumers) of Chad, ENDA, CONGAD&#13;
      and on issues relating to the urban water sector                                   (Confederation of the NGO of Development in Senegal),&#13;
      reform process in Kenya. The same applies to local                                 CARITAS and local consumer associations.&#13;
      press now calling on CIN to contribute their                                       The meeting analyzed the water and sanitation reform&#13;
      perspectives to debates on policy and topical issues                               process in Senegal and discussed the role of civil society&#13;
      on water.                                                                          organizations in the reform process. The meeting was&#13;
                                                                                         preceded by a capacity building session. Training&#13;
&#13;
CINwroteapetitiontotheKenyangovernmentoutlining                                          centered on regulation tariff setting and communication.&#13;
&#13;
its concerns about the water reform process. The Ministry                                This training session made it possible for participants to&#13;
&#13;
responded, and has since appointed CIN a member of a                                     understand the theoretical basis of the different models&#13;
&#13;
government-civilsocietyconsultativecommitteecharged                                      of regulation and tariff setting and also how to&#13;
&#13;
with of proposing a pro-poor strategy for the Integrated                                 communicate their advocacy strategy more effectively&#13;
&#13;
Water Management Policy.                                                                 to the wider public.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CIN is also working with a community resident                                            The stakeholder meeting highlighted the following:&#13;
&#13;
association in Korogocho to develop a plan to enable the                                 ·       The "first generation" of water and sanitation&#13;
residents to apply for and run their own water points. In                                        reforms were done without consultation&#13;
this regard CIN will be conducting meetings with                                         ·       Regulatory framework does not unbundled the&#13;
community leaders, and carrying out consumer                                                     roles of policy making, ownership and part of&#13;
education and training.                                                                          operation&#13;
                                                                                         ·       Inaccurate targeting of subsidies&#13;
Senegal                                                                                  ·       Sanitation given a low priority&#13;
&#13;
In Senegal, the Association de Defense des Usagers de                                    ·       Poor extension of sanitation network and water&#13;
L'Eau, de l'Electricite, des Telecommunications et des                                           connections.&#13;
Services of Senegal (ADEETelS) had previously been                                       ·       Technology standards enshrined in legislation&#13;
involved in the implementation of a project which                                                makes expansion un-necessarily expensive (the&#13;
provided 52 water points and 600 home wastewater                                                 diameter of mains required could be reduced, thus&#13;
systems (puisards) to consumers and households in five                                           reducing costs)&#13;
peri-urban districts of Dakar. This project arose as a                                   ADEETelS developed a plan of action with included the&#13;
means to demonstrate to policy-makers in Senegal that                                    following elements:&#13;
water could be provided cheaply to peri-urban                                            ·       More focused research on targeted subsidies (the&#13;
consumers and managed by local resident associations.                                            tranche sociale of the tariff structure) and advocacy&#13;
ADEETelS now has a seat on the board of the State Asset                                          based on findings&#13;
Holding company, which owns and controls the water                                       ·       Enhanced involvement of consumer organizations&#13;
supply assets (SONES: Societé Nationale des Eaux du                                              from the onset of the second generation of reforms&#13;
Senegal or National Society of Water of Senegal). SONES                                  ·       Engagement with government in discussion on the&#13;
has also extended its network to areas of the ADEETelS                                           type of institution and mechanism for regulation&#13;
project which has made it easier and cheaper for                                         ·       Advocacy for the creation of a mechanism for&#13;
consumers to get connections to their compounds either                                           regulation of water prices at private taps&#13;
individually or collectively. This has also improved water                               ·       Discussion of options for representation at local and&#13;
access for local residents.                                                                      central levels&#13;
                                                                                         ·       Advocacy for change of legislation on technology&#13;
&#13;
Within the framework of the present project, ADEETelS                                            to ensure greater access to water and sanitation&#13;
                                                                                         ·&#13;
conducted a country review examining the institutional                                           Advocacy for the establishment of transparent&#13;
&#13;
and legislative framework of water sector reform in                                              mechanisms for water quality testing and standards&#13;
&#13;
Senegal and the obstacles this present to consumer access                                        and the establishment of a national standard&#13;
                                                                                         ·&#13;
and representation. The findings of this country review                                          Consumer education and information.&#13;
&#13;
were presented at a national stakeholder meeting held&#13;
in November 2003.                                                                        ADEETelS will conduct these actions in the second phase&#13;
                                                                                         of this project. It has also held numerous meetings with&#13;
&#13;
The stakeholder meeting brought together the principal                                   policy-makers and company managers to present and&#13;
&#13;
actors in water in sanitation in Senegal. Representatives                                articulate consumer views on the process and the impact&#13;
&#13;
of the Ministry in charge of water and the Ministry in                                   it is having on consumers.&#13;
&#13;
charge of environment and sanitation, SDE (Senegalaise&#13;
Des Eaux or Senegalese of Water), SONES, ONAS (Office                                    Zambia&#13;
&#13;
National d'Assainissement du Senegal or National                                         In Zambia the Zambia Consumer Association (ZACA)&#13;
Agency of Sanitation of Senegal), PSE (Projet Sectoriel                                  conducted a country review focused on the Copperbelt&#13;
Eau or Sectorial Water Project), WSP, World Bank,                                        Province of Zambia. The country review collected&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22   Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
information which helped the Association get a deeper                               ·          Advocacy and lobbying on several key issues&#13;
understanding of the water and sanitation situation in                                      -     Need for government to fulfil its commitment&#13;
Zambia, identify roles that can be played by consumer                                             to capitalize the water utilities by making grants&#13;
organizations, and make recommendations for actions                                               and funds available. This would enable water&#13;
that would bring improvements for poor and vulnerable                                             utilities to rehabilitate and extend the network&#13;
in the sector.                                                                              -     Payment of Government arrears, seen in this&#13;
ZACA conducted a national stakeholder workshop and                                                context as a consumer equity issue as&#13;
training meeting in August 2003 at which major                                                    Government is the single largest debtor to the&#13;
stakeholders in the provision of water and sanitation                                             water utilities.&#13;
services were invited.                                                                      -     Convincing consumers to be diligent in&#13;
The aims of the workshops were:                                                                   payment would require that government lead&#13;
·    To present the result of the draft country review by                                         by example.&#13;
     ZACA                                                                           ·       Consumer education on&#13;
·    To identify key advocacy issues and develop                                            -     The need for consumers to pay bills in order to&#13;
     strategiesforconsumeradvocacyandanactionplan                                                 ensure the sustainability of the water supply&#13;
     for ZACA; and                                                                                system&#13;
·    To build ZACA's capacity to understand issues of                                       -     The need to conserve water&#13;
     regulation, tariffs, subsidies, private sector                                         -     Rights and obligations of consumers within the&#13;
     participation and other reform issues.                                                       Zambian water sector&#13;
                                                                                    ·       Training of ZACA members' in the different forms&#13;
The results of this workshop were as follows:                                               of regulation and subsidies models the advantages&#13;
·    Improvement of the country review report through                                       and disadvantages of each, as well as training on&#13;
     inputs, comments and criticism from participants                                       how tariffs rates are determined&#13;
     at the meeting                                                                 ·       Further study on the development of alternative&#13;
·    Formulation and adoption of a short term plan of                                       tariff and subsidy structures in Zambia. The country&#13;
     action for consumers in the water sector; and                                          review revealed that subsidies are poorly targeted&#13;
·    Enhanced visibility of ZACA and consumers as key                                       resulting in benefits accruing to the better off rather&#13;
     players in water sector reform in Zambia. Since this                                   than the poor consumers. There is a need to suggest&#13;
     meeting ZACA has been nominated as the                                                 alternative options for consideration under the&#13;
     consumer representative to the board of the water                                      Zambian context.&#13;
     regulatory agency in Zambia.&#13;
The workshop was attended by representatives from                                   During the stakeholder meeting the National Water&#13;
government, commercial water utilities, the regulator,                              SupplyandSanitationCommissioninformedZACAthey&#13;
and non-governmental organizations involved in the                                  were to be appointed as the consumer representative on&#13;
water and sanitation sector. The workshop also drew                                 the regulatory body.&#13;
resource persons from, commercial water utilities, the&#13;
water and sanitation regulator, and WSP. Representatives                            On March 15, 2004, to mark World Consumer Rights Day,&#13;
from Consumers International,Africa Office (CI - ROAF)                              ZACA organised a live TV debate with representatives&#13;
and Consumer Information Network (CIN) of Kenya                                     of the water regulatory commission and the association&#13;
were also present.                                                                  of water utilities in Zambia and ZACA to discuss the&#13;
                                                                                    problems of access to water and sanitation and to discuss&#13;
Based on country review findings and the contributions                              possible means of expanding coverage.&#13;
from the workshop, ZACA identified the problems of&#13;
poor access (people not connected to the network), weak                             Note: the country review documents, which serve as&#13;
redress mechanisms and inefficiencies by the utilities,                             background documents to the National Stakeholder&#13;
as key areas for intervention. ZACA intends to do this                              meetings, are available on request from the consumer&#13;
through various strategies, including:                                              organizations or from CI-ROAF.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Moving from Protest to Proposal: Building the Capacity of Consumer Organisations to Engage in Urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform in Africa 23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Consumers International Africa Office (ROAF)            Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
31 A Lincoln Road, Belgravia,                           Regional Office for Africa&#13;
Private Bag A6215 Avondale,                              Hill Park Building, Upper Hill&#13;
Harare, ZIMBABWE&#13;
                                                         P.O. Box 30577, Nairobi, KENYA&#13;
Tel: (+263-4) 302283, 307259/60&#13;
                                                         Tel: +254-20-3226000&#13;
Fax: (+263-4) 303092&#13;
                                                         Fax: +254-20-3226386&#13;
E-mail: roaf@harare.iafrica.com&#13;
                                                         E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
http://www.consumerinternational.org/roaf&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumers International                                 Sub-Regional Hub for Western Africa&#13;
&#13;
London Head Office                                       3, Place de I'Indépendance&#13;
&#13;
24,Highbury Crescent                                     Immeuble SDIH, 10 éme étage&#13;
London N51 RX, UNITED KINGDOM                            B.P 3296, Dakar, SENEGAL&#13;
Tel: (+44-20) 7226-6663                                  Tel: +221 8426584&#13;
Fax: (+44-20 )7354-0607                                  Fax: +221 849 50 27&#13;
E-mail: Consint@consint.org&#13;
http://www.consumersinternational.org&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Sub-Regional Hub for Southern Africa&#13;
Consumers International                                  The World Bank&#13;
Latin America Office (ROLAC)&#13;
                                                         Ave. Kenneth Kaunda #1224&#13;
Las Hortensias, 2371, Providencia&#13;
                                                         Caixa Postal 4053&#13;
Santiago, CHILE&#13;
                                                         Maputo, MOZAMBIQUE&#13;
Tel: (+56-2) 335-1695&#13;
                                                         Tel: +258-1-492861&#13;
Fax: (+ 56-2) 231-0773&#13;
E-mail: consint@consint.cl                               Fax: +258-1-492893&#13;
&#13;
http://www.consumidoresint.ci&#13;
&#13;
Consumers International&#13;
Asia Pacific Office (ROAP)&#13;
Lot 5-1 Wisma WIM&#13;
No.7 Jalan Abang Haji Openg&#13;
Taman Tun Dr Ismail&#13;
600000 Kuala Lumpur, MALAYSIA&#13;
Tel: (+ 603) 772-61599&#13;
Fax: (+ 603) 772-68599&#13;
E-mail: consint@ciroap.org&#13;
http://www.consumersinternational.org/roap&#13;
&#13;
Office for Developed and Transition Economies (ODTE)&#13;
24,Highbury Crescent&#13;
London N51 RX, UNITED KINGDOM&#13;
Tel: (+44-20) 7226-6663&#13;
Fax: (+44-20 ) 7354-0607&#13;
E-mail: odte@consint.org&#13;
http://www.consumersinternational.org/odte&#13;
&#13;
Sub-regional Office for West and Central Africa (PWCA)&#13;
Villa No.8651, Sacré Coeur II,&#13;
Casier Postal No. 2 Dakar-Fann,&#13;
Dakar, SENEGAL&#13;
Tel: (+221) 824 9055, 825 6947&#13;
Fax: (221) 824 80 06&#13;
E-mail: ci-pwca@sentoo.sn&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5546995">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/06/5546995/moving-protest-proposal-building-capacity-consumer-organisations-engage-urban-water-supply-sanitation-sector-reform-africa
        </url>
        <availablein>French,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="000009486_20050114081932" node_id="5546995"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/06/5546995/moving-protest-proposal-building-capacity-consumer-organisations-engage-urban-water-supply-sanitation-sector-reform-africa</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/06/5546995/moving-protest-proposal-building-capacity-consumer-organisations-engage-urban-water-supply-sanitation-sector-reform-africa</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/01/13/000009486_20050113171414/Rendered/INDEX/313060PAPER0ENGLISH0af1protest.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/01/13/000009486_20050113171414/Rendered/PDF/313060PAPER0ENGLISH0af1protest.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-01-13T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2004-06-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Moving from protest to proposal : building
            the capacity of consumer organisations to engage in urban
            water supply and sanitation sector reform in Africa
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In order to improve the water supply and
            sanitation system and meet the growing demand for water,
            many African governments and municipalities are
            contemplating or have undertaken some form of urban water
            and sanitation sector reform.  This usually requires a
            radical overhaul of legal, regulatory and institutional
            frameworks and often entails some form of public private
            partnership (even though private sector participation can be
            a controversial and emotive issue).  Cost recovery is often
            one of the main objectives of the reform, in order to ensure
            financial sustainability for the agencies that deliver water
            and sanitation services.  The objective of the project was
            summed up by one of the partners, who commented on the need
            for consumer organizations to "move from protest to
            proposal" - leaving behind emotional protest to focus
            on concrete and substantive proposals to engage with the
            water reform process and champion the needs of the most
            vulnerable consumers.  This report discusses the methods and
            strategies for building the capacity of consumer
            organizations in urban water supply and sanitation, derived
            from a joint collaboration between Consumers International
            (CI), the Water and Sanitation Program (WSP).  CI and WSP
            collaborated on this project to learn about what approaches
            would accelerate sustainable service delivery, especially to
            the poor and marginalized in African cities, in order to be
            able to inform future institutional reforms.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Moving from protest to proposal : building
            the capacity of consumer organisations to engage in urban
            water supply and sanitation sector reform in Africa
        </docna>
        <display_title>Moving from protest to proposal :
            building the capacity of consumer organisations to engage in
            urban water supply and sanitation sector reform in Africa</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2004/06/5546995/moving-protest-proposal-building-capacity-consumer-organisations-engage-urban-water-supply-sanitation-sector-reform-africa</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Conservation</subtopic>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Africa</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009486_20050113171414</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Alternative technologies, bacteriological
            quality, billing, Capacity Building, cities, civil society,
            Civil society organizations, communities, construction,
            Consumer Information, domestic use, electricity, high water,
            Integrated Water Management, land tenure, legislation, local
            capacity, municipalities, negotiations, potable water,
            private sector, programs, Public Utilities, quality of
            water, regulatory framework, safe water, SANITATION,
            Sanitation coverage, sanitation policy, SANITATION SECTOR,
            sanitation services, service delivery, service management,
            service providers, Service Provision, sewage, sewage
            systems, sewerage, standpipes, standposts, suppliers,
            surface water, transparency, Tunisia, urban areas, urban
            population, URBAN WATER, URBAN WATER SUPPLY, urbanization,
            WATER SUPPLY, water system, water treatment, water
            utilities, water utility, water wastage, wells, Zambia, Zimbabwe
        </keywd>
        <owner>Office of the Regional Vice Pres (AFRVP)</owner>
        <repnb>31306</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            De la protestation a la proposition :
            renforcer les capacites des organisations de consommateurs a
            s'engager dans la reforme du secteur de l'eau et
            de l'assainissement en milieu urbain en Africa
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Chlorination</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Disinfection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Filtration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Purification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumer Protection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>