<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Annual Review of World&#13;
Bank Staff Learning FY04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Cristina Ling Chard&#13;
&#13;
Diana J. Arango&#13;
&#13;
Shreyasi Jha&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annual Review of World&#13;
Bank Staff Learning FY04&#13;
&#13;
Cristina Ling Chard&#13;
Diana J. Arango&#13;
Shreyasi Jha&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WBI Evaluation Studies&#13;
No. EG05-104&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank Institute&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
December 2004&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                               ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
This evaluation report was prepared for the Learning Board under the overall guidance of&#13;
Nidhi Khattri, Acting Manager, Institute Evaluation Group. The report was discussed by&#13;
the Learning Board at a meeting chaired by Ms. Phyllis Pomerantz, Chief Learning&#13;
Officer on November 1, 2004.&#13;
&#13;
This report would not have been possible without the careful and hard work of Maria&#13;
Beatriz Camargo Cardenas, and Paul Date. The authors also gratefully acknowledge the&#13;
special efforts by Moria Deborah Sutherland for providing IEG with learning catalog data&#13;
and Humberto S. Díaz for administering evaluation questionnaires and formatting the&#13;
final report. Finally, we especially thank Marlaine Lockheed for her thoughtful review.&#13;
&#13;
WBI Evaluation Studies are produced by the WBI Evaluation Group (IEG) to report&#13;
evaluation results for staff, client, and joint learning events. An objective of the studies is&#13;
to get the findings out quickly, even if the presentations are less than fully polished. The&#13;
papers carry the name of the author and should be cited accordingly. The findings,&#13;
interpretations, and conclusions expressed in this paper are entirely those of the author&#13;
and do not necessarily represent the view of the World Bank Group. WBI Evaluation&#13;
Studies are available on line at:&#13;
&#13;
http://info.worldbank.org/etools/WBIEG/publications/index.cfm?pg=Home&amp;Intro=yes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Vice President, World Bank Institute                              Ms. Frannie Léautier&#13;
Chief Learning Officer                                            Ms. Phyllis Pomerantz&#13;
Acting Manager, Institute Evaluation Group                        Ms. Nidhi Khattri&#13;
Task Team Leader                                                  Ms. Cristina Ling Chard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                             ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ACT    Accounting Department&#13;
ACS    Administrative and Client Support&#13;
AFR    Africa Region&#13;
ASTD   American Society for Training and Development&#13;
DEC    Development Economics&#13;
DL     Distance Learning&#13;
EAP    East Asia and Pacific Region&#13;
ECA    Europe and Central Asia Region&#13;
ESSD   Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Vice Presidency&#13;
ETC    Extended Term Consultant&#13;
ETT    Extended Term Temporary&#13;
EXT    External Affairs&#13;
FSE    Financial Sector&#13;
FY02   Fiscal Year 2002&#13;
FY03   Fiscal Year 2003&#13;
FY04   Fiscal Year 2004&#13;
F2F    Face to Face&#13;
GA-GD  Staff in grades A through D&#13;
GE     Staff in grade E&#13;
GF     Staff in grade F&#13;
GG     Staff in grade G&#13;
GH     Staff in grade H&#13;
GSD    General Services Department&#13;
HDN    Human Development Network&#13;
HLM    Hierarchical Linear Model&#13;
HQ     Headquarters&#13;
HRS    Human Resources&#13;
ICC    Intra-class Correlation&#13;
IEG    Institute Evaluation Group&#13;
IFC    International Finance Corporation&#13;
ISG    Information Solutions Group&#13;
INF    Infrastructure Network&#13;
IT     Information Technology&#13;
JPA    Junior Professional Associate&#13;
K&amp;S    Knowledge and Skills&#13;
LCR    Latin America and the Caribbean&#13;
LP     Learning Plan&#13;
LEG    Legal&#13;
LMS    Learning Management System&#13;
MIGA   Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
MENA   Middle East and North Africa&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          iii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MGT     Management&#13;
OLP     Other Learning Providers&#13;
OPCS    Operational Policy and Country Services&#13;
PI      Process and Interaction&#13;
P&amp;T     Professional and Technical&#13;
PREMDEC Poverty Reduction and Economic Management - Development Economics&#13;
PSD     Private Sector Development&#13;
PSI     Private Sector Development and Infrastructure&#13;
RM      Resource Management&#13;
SAR     South Asia Region&#13;
SEC     Corporate Secretariat&#13;
SLC     Strategic Learning Center&#13;
STC     Short-Term Consultant&#13;
STT     Short-Term Temporary&#13;
VPU     Vice-Presidency Unit&#13;
WB      World Bank&#13;
WBI     World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
iv&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS.........................................................................ii&#13;
&#13;
ACRONYMS.........................................................................................iii&#13;
&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS............................................................................v&#13;
&#13;
EXECUTIVE SUMMARY........................................................................vii&#13;
&#13;
1. INTRODUCTION ...............................................................................1&#13;
&#13;
2. METHODOLOGY...............................................................................2&#13;
&#13;
    Selection Procedure and Evaluation Administration ............................................... 2&#13;
&#13;
    Evaluation Instruments.............................................................................................. 3&#13;
&#13;
    Activity Drop Rates................................................................................................... 3&#13;
&#13;
    Participant Response Rates ....................................................................................... 4&#13;
&#13;
3. ACTIVITY AND PARTICIPANT SAMPLE................................................ 5&#13;
&#13;
    Activity Sample......................................................................................................... 5&#13;
&#13;
    Participant Sample..................................................................................................... 8&#13;
&#13;
4. COMPARING FY03 AND FY04 BENCHMARKS.......................................12&#13;
&#13;
    Comparing FY03-FY04 Benchmarks ..................................................................... 13&#13;
&#13;
    Comparing Activity Sponsors Using Respondent Level Data................................ 15&#13;
&#13;
5. MODELING TRAINING QUALITY.......................................................21&#13;
&#13;
    Variables.................................................................................................................. 22&#13;
&#13;
    Multilevel Analysis ................................................................................................. 24&#13;
&#13;
    Multilevel Modeling Results................................................................................... 27&#13;
&#13;
6. CONCLUSIONS................................................................................32&#13;
&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
&#13;
    Annex A: Activity Questionnaire........................................................... 34&#13;
&#13;
    Annex B: Participant Questionnaire......................................................... 36&#13;
&#13;
    Annex C: Course Audience: Distribution of Respondent Unit,By Activity&#13;
             sponsor............................................................................... 37&#13;
&#13;
    Annex D: Distribution of Respondents by Unit in Activity Content Type......... 42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                 v&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   Annex E: Ratings For Jointly Sponsored Courses in FY04............................... 43&#13;
&#13;
   Annex F: Mean Ratings of Activity Characteristics, FY03-FY04 (1=low;&#13;
           5=high)...................................................................................................... 44&#13;
&#13;
   Annex G: Variable Definitions...................................................... ...... 45&#13;
&#13;
   Annex H: HLM Between-Group Model Testing Cross-level&#13;
           effects between grade level and course TOPICS.............................. 46&#13;
&#13;
   Annex I: Key Determinants of Activity Quality, by Sponsor............................. 47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
vi&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                               EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This report evaluates staff learning activities offered in FY04. IEG compiled level one&#13;
evaluation questionnaires completed by 4,750 respondents in 317 staff learning activities.&#13;
We examine the results of these surveys to monitor staff training and evaluate which&#13;
factors can improve it.&#13;
&#13;
On the whole, training quality ratings increased markedly in FY04 from FY03. There&#13;
were significant increases in participant ratings in three of the five key dimensions of&#13;
training quality: (a) relevance to the Bank's mission, (b) overall quality, and (c)&#13;
usefulness of training; ratings of (d) course applicability to job, and (e) perceived&#13;
increases in knowledge and skills (K&amp;S) remained statistically the same in the two fiscal&#13;
years. However, it is important to note that applicability to job dropped below the ASTD&#13;
benchmark.&#13;
&#13;
Overall, the number of learning sponsors above the Bank benchmarks significantly&#13;
improved this year, nearly doubling from 22 percent of the sponsors in FY03 to 43&#13;
percent of sponsors in FY04. In other words, in FY04, nearly half of sponsors exceeded&#13;
the benchmark in four of the five key dimensions of activity quality.&#13;
&#13;
A comparison between FY03 and FY04 was drawn by the type of learning provider:&#13;
Professional and Technical (P&amp;T) Network, Other Networks, Regions, and Other&#13;
Learning Providers. The P&amp;T Networks and Other Networks substantially improved&#13;
across the first three dimensions in FY04 (relevance to the Bank's mission, overall&#13;
quality, and usefulness of training) and Regions improved significantly in relevance to&#13;
the Bank's mission. However, ratings of job applicability and knowledge and skills&#13;
decreased significantly among P&amp;T Networks and Regions in FY04.&#13;
&#13;
In order to better understand these trends, we also examined how sponsors fared&#13;
according to Bank benchmarks at the respondent level and also when controlling for class&#13;
size. Thus, calculations of the five key dimensions of activity quality were based on (a)&#13;
all respondents in activities offered by an activity sponsor, and (b) all courses belonging&#13;
to that sponsor. The first method is the raw score based on a denominator of all&#13;
respondents. The second method controls for class size and is based on a denominator of&#13;
the number of activities offered by the sponsor. A comparison of both methods led to our&#13;
conclusions about the individual sponsors.&#13;
&#13;
Activities sponsored by ACS, ISG, and P&amp;I were rated consistently above benchmarks in&#13;
FY04. On the other hand, activities sponsored by ESSD and INF were consistently rated&#13;
below the benchmarks in FY04. These differences were demonstrated to be largely due to&#13;
activity features, as well as participant traits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        vii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A series of multi-level models were conducted to examine why activities sponsored by&#13;
these networks were rated significantly below benchmark in terms of perceived activity&#13;
quality (a composite variable comprised of the five key dimensions listed above).&#13;
&#13;
The results from these analyses showed that higher training quality is not associated with&#13;
sponsor when activity features are included in the equation. Specifically, participant&#13;
ratings of three main pedagogical dimensions explained most of the variance in the model&#13;
of activity quality. The pedagogical dimensions were:&#13;
&#13;
            (a) Training content- better ratings especially in larger classes, those with 21&#13;
                 or more participants increased training quality;&#13;
&#13;
            (b) Presentation organization- better ratings of presentation order increased&#13;
                 participant ratings of training quality; and&#13;
&#13;
            (c) Training materials- higher assessments of course materials led to&#13;
                 significantly more favorable ratings of training quality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Hierarchical Linear Model results also showed that perceived activity quality was&#13;
associated with two activity features:&#13;
&#13;
            (d) Longer courses, those with durations longer than 2 days, on average; and&#13;
&#13;
            (e) Smaller class sizes, those with 21 or fewer participants, on average.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Additionally, HLM results indicated that activity quality ratings were also explained by&#13;
participant traits:&#13;
&#13;
    · Motivation to participate "to enhance current work performance" significantly&#13;
        increased perceived quality ratings;&#13;
&#13;
    · Grade level indicated that ACS staff rated activities higher, on average; and&#13;
&#13;
    · Participants who reported that the activity was included in their learning plans&#13;
        were more likely to rate activities more positively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
viii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                    1. INTRODUCTION&#13;
&#13;
1.1     The Learning Board reports that more than three thousand staff learning activities&#13;
took place in FY04 (N=3,300), with a total cost of over $81.7 million, almost 18 percent&#13;
more than the $69.5 million originally allotted.1 These activities include a variety of&#13;
learning opportunities such as formal face-to-face courses as well as e-learning events&#13;
and informal brown-bag lunches. These also include all joint staff and client learning&#13;
activities.&#13;
&#13;
1.2     Given the enormous resources allocated to staff learning, the Learning Board has&#13;
requested the World Bank Institute Evaluation Group (IEG) to monitor the progress of&#13;
these learning activities. As part of this mandate, IEG conducts level one evaluations of&#13;
staff learning on an on-going basis.2 In FY04, IEG evaluated 317 courses, an increase of&#13;
nearly one third from FY03 (N=242 courses). Our sample of evaluated courses in FY04&#13;
represents approximately ten percent of formal staff learning events for the year, and&#13;
approximately 30 percent of unique activities delivered. In the courses evaluated in&#13;
FY04, we gathered data from 4,750 respondents.&#13;
&#13;
1.3     In this report, we examine participants' assessments of staff training.&#13;
Specifically, we examine respondents' evaluations of training quality based on the&#13;
following key dimensions:&#13;
&#13;
    · relevance to the Bank's mission;&#13;
&#13;
    · overall quality;&#13;
&#13;
    · usefulness of training;&#13;
&#13;
    · applicability to job; and&#13;
&#13;
    · perceived increases in knowledge and skills.&#13;
&#13;
We estimate the determinants of these dimensions using multi-level hierarchical&#13;
modeling. In the following section, we discuss our methodology for conducting level one&#13;
evaluations, sampling, and response rates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1"Building Staff Capacity for Development: Update on the Staff Learning Program- FY04." Learning&#13;
Board Executive Summary, FY04.&#13;
2IEG also conducts staff learning evaluations at levels two, three and four, the results of which are&#13;
published elsewhere in a series of separate reports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                    2. METHODOLOGY&#13;
&#13;
2.1      In FY04, we drew a random sample of courses for level one evaluation stratified&#13;
by sponsor. We obtained general course information from training coordinators and the&#13;
Learning Catalog.          Also, we gathered data for our evaluations through standard&#13;
questionnaires administered in a uniform method to course participants. We discuss the&#13;
methods for data collection in detail below.&#13;
&#13;
                SELECTION PROCEDURE AND EVALUATION ADMINISTRATION&#13;
&#13;
2.2      The selection procedure used in FY04 was to draw a random sample of four staff&#13;
training events by sponsor from the learning catalog on a bi-weekly basis.3 If more than&#13;
four courses were eligible for evaluation within each sponsor, the courses were selected&#13;
randomly by a computerized random number generator. Course eligibility was based on&#13;
the following criteria:&#13;
&#13;
    · Activities were registered as formal events (i.e. no brown bags or conferences) in&#13;
         the learning catalog two weeks before the activity began;&#13;
&#13;
    · Bank staff comprised at least half of attendees;&#13;
&#13;
    · Course delivery mode was face to face or distance learning; and&#13;
&#13;
    · The course had not been previously evaluated by IEG in FY044.&#13;
&#13;
2.3      For each selected course, we asked training coordinators to submit the course&#13;
agenda and fill out a short questionnaire about the event logistics (e.g., start and end&#13;
dates, number of participants expected; see Annex A). Upon receiving the information&#13;
necessary for coordinating the evaluation, we scheduled the evaluation and prepared the&#13;
course questionnaires with the title and dates.5 The survey administrator delivered the&#13;
evaluations to participants on the first day of the learning event. While the standard&#13;
procedure was to introduce the survey to participants in person, explain how to fill out the&#13;
form, and to emphasize the importance of participant feedback, there were instances&#13;
where instructors refused to comply, and the survey administrators were forced to leave&#13;
the questionnaires for participants to complete without the benefit of instruction.&#13;
Completed forms were collected at the end of each course by an IEG staff member (see&#13;
Annex B).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3We selected 40 courses during each selection period in order to meet our target of evaluating 20 activities&#13;
(we explain later why all selected courses are not evaluated).&#13;
4When sponsors offered fewer than ten courses in the fiscal year, it was necessary to evaluate additional&#13;
offerings of the same course to meet the minimum requirement.&#13;
5Activities for which the course administrators did not respond with the necessary information after several&#13;
requests and reminders were dropped.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                    EVALUATION INSTRUMENTS&#13;
&#13;
2.4      The data for the analyses presented in this paper are compiled from the level one&#13;
evaluations and information provided by course administrators about the activity. The&#13;
activity questionnaire asks training coordinators to detail the logistics of the event as&#13;
mentioned above as well as give some background information on the activity such as&#13;
sponsor, training content (i.e. Bank Operations, Behavioral and Social, Executive&#13;
Management, Information and Technology, Professional and Technical), the learning&#13;
approach (i.e. interactive versus formal), and the history, design, and delivery of the&#13;
training.&#13;
&#13;
2.5      The evaluation questionnaires focus on participant satisfaction with the course&#13;
overall as well as with course specifics: course delivery, design, and substance. In terms&#13;
of individual benefit, respondents reported the extent to which the course fulfilled their&#13;
learning needs, increased their knowledge and skills, and how much it related directly to&#13;
their jobs. Perceptions of course quality, usefulness, and relevance to the Bank's mission&#13;
were also asked to determine participant satisfaction. Assessments of the activity include&#13;
participants' ratings of subject matter, order in which the content is presented, the&#13;
materials and the balance of time spent on theoretical content, practical content,&#13;
instructors' presentation, audience participation and overall pace of the training.&#13;
&#13;
                                      ACTIVITY DROP RATES&#13;
&#13;
2.6      We evaluated 317 activities out of a total of 480 selected for evaluation in FY04&#13;
and dropped 163 courses from the evaluation sample.6 The share of dropped courses in&#13;
FY04 (34 percent), decreased sharply from previous years (46 percent in FY03 and 50&#13;
percent in FY02). This suggests that evaluation has become more prominent on the&#13;
learning agenda.&#13;
&#13;
2.7      In FY04, approximately one third of these dropped courses (N=46) were&#13;
cancelled, postponed, or had inaccurate course dates published in the learning catalog.&#13;
Another third (N=44) did not provide the essential information necessary for evaluation.&#13;
We dropped the remaining courses (N=73) for the following reasons: the sponsor or&#13;
facilitator did not agree to evaluation being administered; another previously scheduled&#13;
evaluation was to be delivered that date; course was cancelled due to low enrollment;&#13;
course was evaluated once already in FY; trainers opt out because activity is a pilot&#13;
offering; problems were incurred during overseas mail delivery of questionnaires; the&#13;
local sponsor did not administer the evaluation survey; the activity was actually for&#13;
clients rather than Bank staff (advertised as both in the learning catalog); and the activity&#13;
was not a formal training session but was advertised as such in the learning catalog (e.g.&#13;
conference) (See Table 1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6Drop rates were highest among activities sponsored by: WBI (82 percent), ECA (76 percent), HRS (70&#13;
percent), PSI (68 percent), ESD (55 percent), and RM (52 percent).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                        Table 1. Evaluation Sample Drop Rates, by Reason&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           No. of&#13;
      Reasons Courses are Dropped from Sample                                             Courses Percentage&#13;
                                                                                          Dropped&#13;
      Course postponed / Cancelled / Dates of course changed/ Dates of course not           46       28%&#13;
      officially set / Dates in the Learning Catalogue incorrect&#13;
&#13;
      No information received / Uncooperative contact                                       44      27%&#13;
&#13;
      Other previously scheduled evaluation is being delivered to the participants           1       1%&#13;
&#13;
      Course dropped due to low enrollment                                                  13       8%&#13;
&#13;
      Sponsor / Facilitator did not agree to evaluation being administered                  16      10%&#13;
&#13;
      Repeat course that has been previously evaluated during FY                             2       1%&#13;
&#13;
      Evaluation delivery failed (e.g. overseas mail never received)                         2       1%&#13;
&#13;
      Evaluation delivery failed: Sponsor/Trainer promises to administer survey and fails    2       1%&#13;
      to do so&#13;
&#13;
      The course is advertised as staff and client but less than half of audience is Bank    0       0%&#13;
      staff (not evident until contacting training coordinator)&#13;
&#13;
      Not a training session (e.g. Conference or brown bag lunch) - not evident until       12       7%&#13;
      contacting training coordinator&#13;
&#13;
      Other / Miscellaneous                                                                 18       11%&#13;
&#13;
      Pilot offering                                                                         7       4%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        PARTICIPANT RESPONSE RATES&#13;
&#13;
2.8      Six thousand four hundred and seven participants attended the courses evaluated&#13;
in FY04. Of this total, 4,750 completed the Level-1 questionnaire, for a response rate of&#13;
79 percent. This shows great improvement in cooperation by participants in comparison&#13;
to the response rate in FY03 of 67 percent.7 Perhaps learning sponsors are taking heed of&#13;
the Chief Learning Officer's emphasis on the importance of level one evaluations and&#13;
are, therefore, encouraging trainers to instruct participants to complete the survey&#13;
instruments. We discuss our sample further in the following section.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7This is similar to the adjusted response rate of 78 percent in FY03.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
            3. ACTIVITYAND PARTICIPANT SAMPLE&#13;
&#13;
3.1    We used data at two levels of analysis for this evaluation ­ participant level and&#13;
course level. This chapter describes the participant and course sample used for this&#13;
evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
                                               ACTIVITY SAMPLE&#13;
&#13;
3.2    A total of 317 learning activities were evaluated in FY04. The World Bank&#13;
designed (88 percent) and delivered (83 percent) the majority of these activities. External&#13;
consultants designed and delivered the remaining. Activity duration ranged from one to&#13;
eleven days with the average activity lasting approximately two days (mean=1.8, std&#13;
dev=1.5). The following sections describe the activities' sponsorship, general curriculum&#13;
content and participant affiliation.&#13;
&#13;
Courses Evaluated&#13;
&#13;
3.3    Over half the evaluated staff learning activities were provided by six institutional&#13;
sponsors (Figure 1). The largest proportion of courses evaluated came from ESSD (14&#13;
percent); PREM-DEC (12 percent); ISG (11 percent); OPCS (9 percent); and PI and EXT&#13;
(7 percent each). Our sample also includes courses from HDN (6.6 percent), ACT and&#13;
INF (4 percent each), AFR (3.7 percent), HRS (3.5 percent), ACS (3 percent), EAP-SAR&#13;
(3 percent), LCR (3 percent), ECA (2.9 percent), WBI (2.6 percent), MGT (2.6 percent),&#13;
and LEG (1.7 percent).&#13;
&#13;
                                Figure. 1 Distributions of Course Evaluations by&#13;
                                                Learning Sponsor, FY04&#13;
                           20&#13;
&#13;
                           18&#13;
&#13;
                           16&#13;
                             13.91&#13;
                  ses      14&#13;
&#13;
                           12    11.5910.72&#13;
                                           8.99&#13;
                     ourc  10&#13;
&#13;
                            8                  6.96 6.96 6.67&#13;
                         %  6                                4.06 4.063.77 3.48&#13;
                            4                                                  3.192.902.90 2.902.61 2.61 1.74&#13;
                            2&#13;
&#13;
                            0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Sponsor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3.4      Figure 2 compares the distributions of activities evaluated with total courses&#13;
offered in FY04.8 The evaluation sample grossly under-represents ISG courses because&#13;
of the abundance of ISG courses offered throughout the year. In order to adequately&#13;
represent all sponsors, we evaluate proportionately fewer ISG courses than their share in&#13;
the total. However, in order to account for differences in the distributions, we weight our&#13;
sample to match the distribution of courses offered in FY04.                                                   Thus, we weight&#13;
respondents from ISG more heavily to match the number of participants in the population&#13;
at large. Conversely, we assign smaller weights to ESSD respondents because they are&#13;
over-represented in our sample.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Figure 2. FY04 Distribution of Unique Courses Offered and&#13;
                                                   Evaluated, by VPU&#13;
                  30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  20&#13;
&#13;
             %&#13;
                  15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  0&#13;
                                C        N   PI                       S                       R&#13;
                       ISG&#13;
                           ESSD  DE-      HD    INF       WBI CTA EXT  HR LCR&#13;
                                                    OPCS                      MGT ECA ACS FRA         PSD LEG  OED SEC&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               EAP-SA&#13;
                                    PREM&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Learning Sponsor                  Offered            Evaluated&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Activity Content&#13;
&#13;
3.5      During FY04, the largest percentage of activities evaluated were Professional and&#13;
Technical (44 percent); followed by Bank Operations (24 percent); Information&#13;
Technology (17 percent); Behavioral and Social (13 percent); Executive Management (2&#13;
percent) and Other (1 percent).&#13;
&#13;
3.6      Compared to FY02 and FY03, the shares of Information Technology related&#13;
activities and Behavioral and Social activities have remained constant within the range 13&#13;
to 17 percent. The share of Professional and Technical activities increased in FY04 (44&#13;
percent) compared to FY03 (31 percent), but was less than in FY02 (53 percent). By&#13;
comparison, the share of Bank Operations related activities declined to 24 percent in&#13;
FY04 compared to FY03 (31 percent) but was above the FY02 level (17 percent). The&#13;
share of Executive Management activities also declined from 5 percent in FY03 to 2&#13;
percent in FY04. Figure 3 shows the percentage of activities evaluated by content type in&#13;
FY02, FY03 and FY04.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8Multiple sponsors are factored into the distributions by treating each sponsor in jointly delivered activities&#13;
equally. In other words, each sponsor in a jointly delivered activity is given equal credit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                Figure 3. Percentage of Activities Evaluated by Content Type, FY02- FY04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    60&#13;
                                   53&#13;
&#13;
                    50                              44&#13;
&#13;
                    40&#13;
                                     31                                     31&#13;
                %   30                                                        24&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    17&#13;
                    20                                                                                    17 17&#13;
                                                                                            13                              16 14 13&#13;
                    10                                                                                                                                  5&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      0            2        2  1          0         0  1 1&#13;
                    0&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                sd                      r&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              ations                                                                      Mgmt                                           Othe&#13;
                                                                        Bank                                                                                                      Funt&#13;
                                                     Technical                                                                              Social&#13;
                                                                                                                               Behavioral&#13;
                                     Professional             &amp;                     Oper       Information   Technology                                       Exec.                   Trus&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       FY02   FY03                 FY04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Activity Respondents&#13;
&#13;
3.7      Twenty-six percent of respondents attended activities sponsored by ESSD (14&#13;
percent) and PREM-DEC (12 percent). OPCS, EXT, HDN, ISG and INF accounted for 8&#13;
to 5 percent of the respondents. PI, ECA, ACS, ACT, HRS, EAPSAR, AFR, LCR, MGT,&#13;
SEC, EXTPI and LEG accounted for fewer than 4 percent of the total respondents. Figure&#13;
4 shows the distribution of respondents by sponsors with one or more percentage of&#13;
respondents in FY04 respondent sample.9&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Figure 4. Distribution of Respondents by&#13;
                                                                                        Learning Sponsor, FY04&#13;
                                  16&#13;
                                                 14.25&#13;
                                  14&#13;
                                                               12.12&#13;
                      s           12&#13;
                       nt&#13;
                         de       10&#13;
                                                                    8.34&#13;
                           onpseR  8                                    7.46&#13;
                                                                              6.39       6.26&#13;
                                   6                                                         5.29&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           3.89         3.67&#13;
                                 % 4                                                                                        3.05         2.88 2.81  2.412.24        1.82 1.821.67&#13;
                                   2                                                                                                                                                      1.30 1.27 1.25&#13;
&#13;
                                   0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        Sponsor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.8      Not surprisingly, the two largest sponsors in terms of courses evaluated, ESSD&#13;
(14 percent) and PREM &amp; DEC (12 percent), also trained the largest number of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9Staff learning in FY04 included both single sponsored activities and multi-sponsored activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                 7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
respondents (14 percent and 12 percent respectively).10 In contrast, while ISG sponsored&#13;
more courses (11 percent) than OPCS (9 percent), OPCS trained more respondents (8&#13;
percent) than ISG (6 percent). Likewise, while PI represented the same percentage of&#13;
courses as EXT (7 percent each), EXT registered significantly more respondents (7&#13;
percent) than PI (4 percent). These findings show that PI and ISG register fewer&#13;
participants in their courses even though they offered more or equal number of courses as&#13;
some other sponsors. This is just what we would expect given that they are forced to&#13;
control for course size (e.g., ISG training rooms can only hold a maximum of 16&#13;
participants.)&#13;
&#13;
3.9        ESSD accounted for the most number of respondents in FY04 (14 percent). This&#13;
was a significant gain compared to FY03 when it was in the fifth place with only 8&#13;
percent of the total respondents. In both FY02 and FY03, PREM accounted for the most&#13;
respondents (15 percent in FY02 and 22 percent in FY03). However, in FY04, PREM-&#13;
DEC was in the second place with 12 percent of the total respondents. Participation in&#13;
OPCS sponsored courses also declined in FY04 (8 percent) compared to FY02 (14&#13;
percent) and FY03 (11 percent). On the other hand, EXT and ECA increased&#13;
participation significantly in FY04 accounting for 7 percent and 4 percent of the&#13;
respondents compared to FY03 when they both had less than 1 percent of the total share&#13;
of respondents.&#13;
&#13;
3.10    As emphasized in the FY03 evaluation report, an important aspect of the Learning&#13;
Board's activities is to encourage participants to enroll in courses across units and not&#13;
necessarily be restricted to taking courses offered by their units. In Annex C, we present&#13;
the distribution of participants by units and course sponsors. Similar to our findings in&#13;
FY03, we find that participants from regions are more likely to take courses from their&#13;
own unit. Among the networks, P&amp;T networks such as HDN, ESSD and PREM courses&#13;
are more likely to have participants from their units. This suggests that region-sponsored&#13;
courses and P&amp;T network courses are designed specifically for participants working in&#13;
their areas.&#13;
&#13;
                                         PARTICIPANT SAMPLE&#13;
&#13;
3.11    Our participant sample consists of 4,750 respondents. Most of the respondents&#13;
were World Bank Staff (87 percent), of whom 71 percent were based in headquarters and&#13;
29 percent were stationed in the field.&#13;
&#13;
3.12    In both FY03 and FY04, the majority of the respondents come from the regional&#13;
VPUs. Figure 5 illustrates the total number of respondents by the VPU in which they&#13;
work. In FY04, the Africa region accounted for the largest total number of respondents&#13;
(n=661); followed by ECA (n=436), EAP (n=333), LCR (n=290), and SAR (n=240). The&#13;
only non-regional unit with a large number of participants was ESSD with the fourth&#13;
largest number of respondents (n=306). Other than ESSD, the other units with large&#13;
number of respondents were PREM (n=231), HDN (n=158), IFC (n=158), HRS (n=146),&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10As participant data is not available for the activities that are not evaluated, we rely on the evaluation&#13;
sample of respondents to make inferences about the population at large.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WBI (n=138) and OPCS (n=112). Units with less than 100 respondents include: ISG,&#13;
DEC, LEG, FSE, MIGA and PSI.11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Figure 5. Total Respondents by Unit, FY04&#13;
&#13;
                              700&#13;
                                  661&#13;
&#13;
                              600&#13;
               stn            500    436&#13;
                  de&#13;
                              400&#13;
                    onpseR.oN           333&#13;
                                           306 290&#13;
                              300                  240 231&#13;
&#13;
                              200                         158147 146138&#13;
                                                                       112&#13;
                                                                            82&#13;
                              100                                               78 75&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      15 11 7&#13;
                               0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Participation Motivation&#13;
&#13;
3.13    More than half of staff (59 percent) cited "enhance performance in&#13;
current/planned assignment" as their primary motivation for taking the training course.&#13;
The second most important motivation for taking a course was cited as "professional&#13;
interest and growth" (32 percent). Only five percent of the respondents cited&#13;
"networking" as being their main motivation. These findings are similar to those reported&#13;
in FY03. These findings suggest that for the majority of the participants the main&#13;
motivation for selecting a course is guided by their current work as opposed to future&#13;
career opportunities that may be enhanced by internal networking within the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
3.14    While the majority of respondents indicated that their primary motivation was to&#13;
enhance their current work performance, only 33 percent reported including these&#13;
activities in their individual learning plans.&#13;
&#13;
Grade Levels&#13;
&#13;
3.15    Figure 6 represents respondents' grade levels in FY04. Staff in grades GA-GD&#13;
comprised nearly a quarter (23 percent) of the respondents; 9 percent came from GE&#13;
level; 19 percent each from GF and GG and none from GH and above level. In addition,&#13;
our sample included short term consultants (10 percent), short term temporary (2 percent)&#13;
and respondents who identified themselves as "other" (19 percent).12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11The "Other" category refers to respondents who selected "other" on the survey for their work unit. There&#13;
were 207 non-staff respondents who stated they were "clients" on the questionnaire and participated in&#13;
WBI courses that were jointly offered to staff and client.&#13;
12Respondents in the "other" category include JPAs etc.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3.16    The distribution of the respondents by their grade level in FY04 is very similar to&#13;
FY03. In FY03, the largest percentage of participants came from grade GA-GD (23&#13;
percent), GE (11 percent), GF (24 percent) and GG (18 percent). However, unlike in&#13;
FY03 when 7 percent of the participants were from GH grade or above, in FY04 there&#13;
were no respondents from this grade. The number of STC taking courses in FY04&#13;
increased slightly, as compared to FY03.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          Figure 6. Respondent by Grade Level, FY03 and FY04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     30&#13;
&#13;
                                     25&#13;
                       s                  23              23                         24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        dentn        20                                                19 1819                                                              19&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                 FY03&#13;
                                     15&#13;
                             espoR                                                                                                                               FY04&#13;
                                                              11 9&#13;
                                  of 10                                                                                                           1&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  0&#13;
&#13;
                                  %                                                                               7                             8         7&#13;
&#13;
                                      5&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    0  1            2&#13;
&#13;
                                      0&#13;
                                         GA-GD                 GE                     GF   GG                      GH+  STT                     STC       OTHER&#13;
                                                                                          Grade Level&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.17    The types of courses attended by respondents differed according to their grade&#13;
level (Figure 7). Information Technology courses attracted the highest proportion of&#13;
ACS staff (46 percent) of all types of courses. Behavioral and Social courses also had the&#13;
largest proportion of participants with grades A through D (33 percent). Bank Operations&#13;
and Professional Technical courses attracted a generally even mix of grade levels with&#13;
slightly more representation from higher level staff (51 and 50 percent, respectively).&#13;
Executive management courses included mostly participants who were GG and higher or&#13;
those who checked off the "other" category.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Figure 7. Percent of Respondents by Grade Level and Content Type&#13;
                      50&#13;
                      45&#13;
&#13;
          s           40&#13;
                      35&#13;
                      30&#13;
           ndent&#13;
                      25&#13;
&#13;
                espoR 20&#13;
                       15&#13;
                     % 10&#13;
                                    5&#13;
                                    0&#13;
                                            NSO                                               T                         N&#13;
                                                                     ALI&#13;
          ETC/S                                                                                                                                      REH&#13;
                                                                        SOC                                                                                        LACINH&#13;
          ETT/S                                ATIR                                            MENEG                     IOTA       YGOL&#13;
                                                                                                                             MRO                        OT&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                         EC&#13;
          GA-GD                                    OPE                                              NA                                                                     /T&#13;
                                                                                                                                INF     TECHNO&#13;
          GE                                                                                          MA&#13;
                                                      NK                   VIORAL                                                                                            ALNO&#13;
          GF                                            BA                                              IVE                                                                      SI&#13;
          GG                                                                     HAEB&#13;
&#13;
          OTHER                                                                                            ECUT                                                                    ESFO&#13;
                                                                                                               EX                                                                      PR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Participant Unit and Course Type&#13;
&#13;
3.18    We also analyzed the types of courses attended by participants from various&#13;
VPUs in order to examine the type of audience for each course type. Annex D presents&#13;
the percentages of respondents in various types of courses by units. Bank Operations&#13;
attracted maximum number of participants from regions: Africa (16 percent), ECA (15&#13;
percent), EAP (10 percent), LCR (8 percent) and SAR (6 percent). Behavioral/Social&#13;
courses were most popular with participants from Human Resources (11 percent)&#13;
followed by the Africa region (10 percent). A large proportion of participants from ISG&#13;
(13 percent) attended Executive Management courses. Information Technology courses&#13;
were attended most often by staff from the Africa region (13 percent) followed by IFC&#13;
(10 percent). Profession/Technical courses were also very popular with participants from&#13;
the Africa region (16 percent). It is not surprisingly that a majority of participants in&#13;
various types of courses are from the Africa region since participants from the Africa&#13;
region account for the largest share of participants overall.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
         4. COMPARING FY03 AND FY04 BENCHMARKS&#13;
&#13;
4.1      We established new Bank benchmarks for FY04 using respondent level data&#13;
(n=4,555) and course level data (n=317).13 These benchmarks are based on the average&#13;
scores given by participants on: (a) assessment of the course's applicability to the&#13;
participant's job; (b) perception of the degree to which knowledge and skills increased&#13;
and the percentage of respondents giving high ratings (4-5); (c) course relevance to&#13;
Bank's mission; (d) overall course quality; and (e) usefulness of the course.14 We draw&#13;
comparisons both longitudinally between FY03 and FY04, and in relation to the industry&#13;
standards set forth by the American Society for Training and Development (ASTD).&#13;
&#13;
Comparing overall quality, usefulness and relevance in FY03 and FY04&#13;
&#13;
4.2      The courses improved in FY04. Figure 8 compares the percentage of respondents&#13;
giving high ratings to courses (i.e., percentage of respondents giving a rating of 4-5) on&#13;
overall quality, usefulness and relevance in FY03 and FY04. We find that the percentage&#13;
of respondents giving high ratings on overall quality, usefulness and relevance of courses&#13;
significantly increased in FY04 compared to FY03 (quality:  = 26.88**; usefulness:     2&#13;
&#13;
2=54.94**; and relevance: 2=70.48**).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Figure 8. Respondents Giving High Ratings to Courses, by FY03-04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   90&#13;
                                                89%                                      89%&#13;
                                   89&#13;
&#13;
                                   88&#13;
                                                                     87%&#13;
                                   87&#13;
                      nts&#13;
                                   86&#13;
                         ndeop           85%                                      85%&#13;
                                   85&#13;
&#13;
                                   84&#13;
                              Res                            83%&#13;
                                 % 83&#13;
&#13;
                                   82&#13;
&#13;
                                   81&#13;
&#13;
                                   80&#13;
                                         Overall quality   Overall usefulness  Relevance to Bank's&#13;
                                                                                    Mission&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             FY03     FY04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
13In the FY04 questionnaire, participant ratings ranged from 1 (low) to 7 (high). In order to get comparative&#13;
figures between FY04 and FY03, we rescaled the ratings from a 7 point scale to a 5 point scale as follows:&#13;
1 1; 2&amp;3 2; 4 3; 5&amp;6                  4; and 7 5.&#13;
14Annex F presents the weighted average ratings of activity characteristics: (a) material used during the&#13;
course; (b) the order in which the content was presented; (c) training content quality; (d) the extent to&#13;
which the training achieved its desired objective; and (e) the extent to which the training fulfilled&#13;
respondent's learning needs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Comparing applicability to job and increase in knowledge and skills&#13;
&#13;
4.3     Respondents were also asked to assess the course's applicability to their job and&#13;
the degree to which their knowledge and skills increased. Figure 9 presents the FY03-04&#13;
mean ratings of course applicability to job and perceptions of increases in knowledge and&#13;
skills side by side to the ASTD benchmarks. There were no significant differences&#13;
between the two fiscal years. The mean rating for job applicability was 4.16 in FY04 and&#13;
4.14 in FY03. Average perceived increase in knowledge and skills was 4.21 in FY04&#13;
compared to 4.23 in FY03.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Figure 9. Participant's Assessment of Job Applicability of&#13;
                                Training and Increase in Knowledge and Skills, FY03-FY04&#13;
                           4.40&#13;
                                                       4.23           4.23&#13;
                                             4.16                             4.21    4.20&#13;
                           4.20     4.14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           4.00&#13;
&#13;
                           3.80&#13;
                 rating&#13;
                           3.60&#13;
                       Mean&#13;
                           3.40&#13;
&#13;
                           3.20&#13;
&#13;
                           3.00&#13;
                                      Applicability to Job            Knowledge and skills&#13;
&#13;
                                                          FY03 FY04 ASTD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.4     While statistically significant differences between FY03 and FY04 do not exist,&#13;
the Bank's FY04 average for job applicability is significantly lower than the most&#13;
recently published ASTD benchmark15 4.23, (t=-6.69**). However, the Bank's FY04&#13;
average rating of increases in knowledge and skills was statistically the same as the&#13;
ASTD benchmark, 4.20.&#13;
&#13;
                                 COMPARING FY03-FY04 BENCHMARKS&#13;
&#13;
4.5     To gain insight into differences in perceived training quality across the Bank, we&#13;
compared benchmarks in FY03 and FY04 across: Regions, P&amp;T Network SCLs, Other&#13;
Networks and Other Learning Providers (OLP)16. Table 2 shows the ratings on overall&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
15Van Buren, Mark E. and William Erskine 2002. Learning Outcomes: ASTD's Fourth Annual Report on&#13;
Standards for Evaluating Organizations' Investments in Education and Training Report 2002.&#13;
16Each category includes the following sponsors: Professional and Technical Networks (PREM &amp; DEC,&#13;
INF, HDN, ESSD); Other Networks (PI, OPCS, MGT, ISG, ACS); Regions (MENA, LCR, ECA, EAP,&#13;
SAR, AFR), and Other Learning Providers (WBI, SEC, LEG, HRS, GSD, EXT, ACT).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
quality, usefulness, relevance, applicability to job and increase in knowledge and skills&#13;
across categories for FY03 and FY04.17&#13;
&#13;
           Table 2: FY03-FY04 Ratings of training quality by learning provider&#13;
&#13;
                                                      FY03         FY04      t-value&#13;
&#13;
                        P &amp; T Networks&#13;
&#13;
                        Overall quality                0.82         0.84       2.42*&#13;
&#13;
                        Overall usefulness             0.81         0.86      3.16**&#13;
&#13;
                        Relevance to Bank's Mission    0.86         0.88      3.07**&#13;
&#13;
                        Applicability to Job           4.11         4.01      -5.69**&#13;
&#13;
                        Knowledge and skills           4.15         4.06      -6.18**&#13;
&#13;
                        Regions&#13;
&#13;
                        Overall quality                0.92         0.93       0.87&#13;
&#13;
                        Overall usefulness             0.89         0.87       0.66&#13;
&#13;
                        Relevance to Bank's Mission    0.90         0.92      2.20**&#13;
&#13;
                        Applicability to Job           4.32         4.09      -8.08**&#13;
&#13;
                        Knowledge and skills           4.31         4.25      -2.25*&#13;
&#13;
                        Other Networks&#13;
&#13;
                        Overall quality                0.90         0.94      5.33**&#13;
&#13;
                        Overall usefulness             0.88         0.91      3.87**&#13;
&#13;
                        Relevance to Bank's Mission    0.86         0.89      4.00**&#13;
&#13;
                        Applicability to Job           4.24         4.29       2.68*&#13;
&#13;
                        Knowledge and skills           4.36         4.36       0.29&#13;
&#13;
                        Other Learning Providers&#13;
&#13;
                        Overall quality                0.91         0.88      -3.2**&#13;
&#13;
                        Overall usefulness             0.87         0.87        0.5&#13;
&#13;
                        Relevance to Bank's Mission    0.87         0.88       1.62&#13;
&#13;
                        Applicability to Job           4.23         4.23       0.08&#13;
&#13;
                        Knowledge and skills           4.25          4.2      -2.35*&#13;
&#13;
                        ** p&lt;0.01; * p&lt;0.05&#13;
&#13;
4.6       Overall the networks show marked improvement in FY04. Both P&amp;T Networks&#13;
and Other Networks show significant improvement in overall quality, usefulness and&#13;
relevance to Bank's mission in FY04. Other Networks showed significant increase in&#13;
applicability to job.&#13;
&#13;
4.7       On the other hand, P&amp;T Networks showed a substantial decrease in both&#13;
applicability to job and knowledge and skills. Likewise job applicability and knowledge&#13;
and skills declined among Regions in FY04. However, Regions improved significantly in&#13;
relevance to the Bank's mission. Other learning providers decreased in overall quality&#13;
and K&amp;S.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
17We also report the t-statistic which indicates whether the difference between FY03 and FY04 ratings is&#13;
statistically significant.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.8     These results suggest that P&amp;T Networks and Regions should pay particular&#13;
attention to two dimensions of training: (a) making courses more applicable to people's&#13;
jobs, and (b) increasing participant knowledge and skills.&#13;
&#13;
          COMPARING ACTIVITY SPONSORS USING RESPONDENT LEVEL DATA&#13;
&#13;
4.9     We examine how learning sponsors fared vis-a-vis the benchmarks in FY04&#13;
compared to FY03. We calculate an overall aggregate index across all sponsors in the&#13;
five key training dimensions: knowledge and skills (K&amp;S); job applicability; relevance;&#13;
use and overall quality. We assign a score of one when a sponsor rated above Bank&#13;
average, 0.5 when a sponsor rated same as Bank average, and a score of zero when a&#13;
sponsor rated below Bank average. Thus, the maximum score a sponsor could achieve&#13;
was five, indicating the sponsor was consistently above the benchmark, and the minimum&#13;
score was zero, if they were always below the benchmark. We then calculated the&#13;
percentage of sponsors that fell into the following ranges across the spectrum from high&#13;
to low: 4-5, 3-4, 2-3, 1-2, 0-1 and 0 in the two fiscal years. Figure 10 illustrates the two&#13;
distributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Figure 10. Percentage distribution of Sponsors by their Overall&#13;
                                                   Aggregate Index Rankings&#13;
&#13;
                              45                                                                   43&#13;
&#13;
               s              40&#13;
                or            35&#13;
                                                                                       29&#13;
                  onspS 30    25                                        22                      22&#13;
                  of&#13;
                    egatnecreP20                          17                       17&#13;
&#13;
                              15   11          11 10          10&#13;
                              10      5                                     5&#13;
                               5&#13;
&#13;
                               0&#13;
                                     0         0 to 1      1 to 2       2 to 3      3 to 4      4 to 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              FY03     FY04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.10    We find significant improvement in the proportion of learning sponsors that were&#13;
above the Bank benchmark in FY04 compared to FY03. Nearly half of sponsors in FY04&#13;
(43 percent) rated above the Bank benchmarks in more than four criteria, compared with&#13;
only 22 percent of sponsors in FY03. Likewise, in the next highest category (3 to 4), 29&#13;
percent of sponsors rated higher than the Bank benchmark in FY04, as compared to 17&#13;
percent of sponsors in FY03. On the other hand, the proportion of sponsors in the lower&#13;
categories (2-3, 1-2, 0-1 and 0) was higher among FY03 than FY04.&#13;
&#13;
4.11    Thus, overall there has been marked improvement in the proportion of learning&#13;
sponsors meeting and surpassing the Bank benchmarks in FY04 as compared to FY03.&#13;
To gain insight into which training criteria learning sponsors can improve, we depict the&#13;
sponsors' ratings in Table 3 with respect to training quality dimension.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
          4.12       Table 3 illustrates the benchmarks for single sponsors. We evaluated courses&#13;
          from a wider spectrum of learning providers in FY04 by including courses from: MENA,&#13;
          SEC, EAP, and PI. Columns one and two show whether respondents' ratings of K&amp;S and&#13;
          applicability are significantly above, below, or the same as the bank average and the&#13;
          ASTD benchmark. Columns three, four, and five show whether or not 85 percent of&#13;
          respondents gave high ratings (4 or 5) for quality, usefulness, and relevance (with a dark&#13;
          circle indicating that 85 percent or more respondents gave scores of 4 and 5). Annex E&#13;
          presents the ratings by joint activity sponsors in FY04.&#13;
&#13;
           Table 3: Respondent level ratings of FY04, Q1-Q4, learning programs, by activity&#13;
                                                                   sponsor&#13;
              Single      Increase Knowledge           Job              Overall         Overall        Relevance to&#13;
            Sponsors          and Skills18        Applicability19      Quality20      Usefulness*   The Bank's Mission * No. of Respondents&#13;
&#13;
              ACS                (                     (                  (              (                 (                    139&#13;
&#13;
              HRS                (                     (                  (              (                 (                    127&#13;
&#13;
              ISG                (                     (                  (              (                 (                    285&#13;
&#13;
                PI               (                     (                  (              (                 (                    177&#13;
&#13;
            EAP-SAR              (                     )                  (              (                 (                    154&#13;
&#13;
              ECA                (                     )                  (              (                 (                    167&#13;
&#13;
              EXT                )                     (                  (              (                 (                    340&#13;
&#13;
              GSD                )                     (                  (              (                 (                     8&#13;
&#13;
              LCR                (                     )                  (              (                 (                     69&#13;
&#13;
              AFR                )                     )                  (              (                 (                    137&#13;
&#13;
              LEG                )                     )                  (              (                 (                     57&#13;
&#13;
             MENA                )                     )                  (              (                 (                     19&#13;
&#13;
              MGT                )                     )                  (              (                 (                     90&#13;
&#13;
             OPCS                )                     )                  (              (                 (                    390&#13;
&#13;
              ACT                (                     )                  (              (                 *                    131&#13;
&#13;
              HDN                *                     *                  (              (                 (                    306&#13;
&#13;
           PREM-DEC              *                     *                  (              *                 (                    551&#13;
&#13;
              WBI                )                     )                  *              *                 (                     24&#13;
&#13;
              SEC                )                     )                  *              *                 *                     59&#13;
&#13;
              ESSD               *                     *                  *              *                 (                    626&#13;
&#13;
              INF                *                     *                  *              *                 *                    241&#13;
&#13;
          For columns 1 and 2,  (=   higher than Bank/ASTD average,        )=   Bank/ASTD average,  *=   below Bank/ASTD&#13;
&#13;
          average; for columns 3, 4 and 5,  (=  meets or exceeds Bank benchmark,      *=  does not meet Bank benchmark&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18The benchmark is the Bank average rating (4.20), statistically the same as the ASTD standard (4.21).&#13;
19The benchmark is the Bank average rating (4.18), statistically the same as the ASTD standard (4.21).&#13;
20The benchmark is 85% of respondents in a course gave ratings of 4 or 5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Knowledge and Skills&#13;
&#13;
4.13    The first column of Table 3 shows the ratings on knowledge and skills by learning&#13;
sponsors. Comparing K&amp;S in FY04 to the Bank/ASTD benchmark of 4.20, we find that&#13;
38 percent of sponsors (ACS, HRS, ISG, PI, EAP-SAR, ECA, LCR, and ACT) rated&#13;
higher than the Bank average. Forty-three percent of sponsors (EXT, GSD, AFR, LEG,&#13;
MENA, MGT, OPCS, WBI, and SEC) were rated statistically the same as the Bank&#13;
average, while 19 percent of sponsors (HDN, PREM-DEC, ESSD, and INF) rated&#13;
statistically below the Bank average.&#13;
&#13;
4.14    ACS, ACT, EAP-SAR, LCR, and ISG continued to surpass the Bank benchmark&#13;
in FY04. Sponsors who rated below the FY03 benchmark, EXT, GSD, ECA, and LEG&#13;
improved their ratings in FY04 to either above or equal to Bank average. HRS improved&#13;
its rating to above the FY04 benchmark from just meeting the benchmark in FY03.&#13;
&#13;
4.15    Courses sponsored by AFR, OPCS, and WBI remained equal to the Bank&#13;
benchmark in FY04. Although, ESSD and HDN met the Bank benchmark in FY03, they&#13;
fell below the FY04 benchmark. PREM and INF remain below benchmark in FY04.21&#13;
&#13;
Job Applicability&#13;
&#13;
4.16    The second column of Table 3 shows the assessments of training applicability to&#13;
job across course sponsors. We find that 28 percent of sponsors (ACS, HRS, ISG, PI,&#13;
EXT and GSD) were statistically higher than the Bank benchmark of 4.18. Fifty-two&#13;
percent of learning sponsors (EAP-SAR, ECA, LCR, AFR, LEG, MENA, MGT, OPCS,&#13;
ACT, WBI and SEC) met the Bank benchmark while 19 percent of the single sponsors&#13;
(HDN, PREM-DEC, ESSD, and INF) were below.&#13;
&#13;
4.17    ACS was the only sponsor consistently above the Bank benchmarks in FY03 and&#13;
FY04. ISG, GSD, HRS, and EXT improved their ratings in FY04 to above the Bank&#13;
average. LEG also improved by meeting the Bank average in FY04 after rating below&#13;
average in FY03. AFR, ECA, OPCS, and WBI remained equal to the FY04 benchmark.&#13;
&#13;
4.18    On the other hand, some sponsors rated lower on job applicability in FY04&#13;
compared to FY03. EAP-SAR, ACT and LCR dropped from being above the benchmark&#13;
in FY03 to just meeting the FY04 benchmark. ESSD, INF, and HDN were equal to the&#13;
FY03 benchmark but decreased below Bank benchmark in FY04. PREM continued to&#13;
remain below the benchmark in FY04.&#13;
&#13;
Quality of Training&#13;
&#13;
4.19    The third column in Table 3 illustrates whether or not 85 percent of respondents&#13;
in a course gave high ratings (4 or 5) for quality (with a dark circle indicating that 85&#13;
percent or more respondents gave scores of 4 and 5). We find that 81 percent of sponsors&#13;
(ACS, HRS, ISG, PI, EXT, GSD, EAP-SAR, ECA, LCR, AFR, LEG, MENA, MGT,&#13;
OPCS, ACT, PREM-DEC, and HDN) rated above the Bank benchmark in FY04.&#13;
&#13;
21The following learning sponsors were evaluated for the first time in FY04: MENA, MGT, and SEC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Nineteen percent of sponsors (WBI, SEC, ESSD, and INF) rated below the Bank&#13;
benchmark.&#13;
&#13;
4.20    In FY04, EXT, GSD, LEG, and PREM-DEC improved their ratings to meet the&#13;
benchmarks for overall quality of training. On the other hand, ESSD and INF remained&#13;
below the benchmark. WBI dropped from meeting the benchmark in FY03 to falling&#13;
below in FY04.&#13;
&#13;
Usefulness of Training&#13;
&#13;
4.21    The fourth column of Table 3 presents the ratings of overall usefulness across&#13;
course sponsors. Three-quarters of sponsors (76 percent) were equal to or higher than the&#13;
Bank benchmark (ACS, HRS, ISG, PI, EXT, GSD, EAP-SAR, ECA, LCR, AFR, LEG,&#13;
MENA, MGT, OPCS, ACT, and HDN). Only 24 percent of sponsors (PREM-DEC, WBI,&#13;
SEC, ESSD, and INF) rated significantly below the Bank benchmark in FY04.&#13;
&#13;
4.22    GSD and LEG improved in FY04 by meeting the benchmark. However, PREM-&#13;
DEC and INF remained below the FY04 benchmark. WBI and ESSD decreased in FY04&#13;
after meeting the benchmark in FY03.&#13;
&#13;
Relevance to Bank's Mission&#13;
&#13;
4.23    The fifth column of Table 3 shows the respondent's ratings across sponsors on the&#13;
basis of the relevance of their training to the Bank's mission. We find that 86 percent&#13;
(ACS, HRS, ISG, PI, EXT, GSD, EAP-SAR, ECA, LCR, AFR, LEG, MENA, MGT,&#13;
OPCS, PEMDEC, WBI, ESSD, and HDN) of the sponsors rated above the Bank&#13;
benchmark and only 14 percent (ACT, SEC and INF) rated below the benchmark.&#13;
&#13;
4.24    Relevance to the Bank's mission improved in courses sponsored by ISG, LEG,&#13;
and GSD. On the other hand, INF remained below the Bank benchmark in FY04 and&#13;
ACT dropped from meeting the benchmark in FY03 to below in FY04.&#13;
&#13;
Overall Quality&#13;
&#13;
4.25    The average ratings of activities of two sponsors fell below Bank or ASTD&#13;
benchmarks in at least four of the above five categories: ESSD and INF. We explore the&#13;
reasons for this pattern of lower ratings in subsequent analyses.&#13;
&#13;
Comparing Activity Sponsors Using Course-Level Data&#13;
&#13;
4.26    At the request of the Learning Board in FY04, we also calculated the benchmarks&#13;
for learning programs across activity sponsors at the course level. In order to compute the&#13;
benchmarks using course level data, we first calculate the average respondent ratings in&#13;
each of the five categories at the course level. We then aggregate the course averages by&#13;
sponsors to obtain the benchmarks across sponsors. This formula controls for the class&#13;
size thereby reducing the influence of larger classes on the overall rating. Further, all&#13;
sponsors are represented equally for jointly sponsored courses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.27      Table 4 illustrates sponsor ratings based on course level data. Columns one and&#13;
two show whether average course ratings of K&amp;S and applicability are significantly&#13;
above, below, or the same as the bank average and the ASTD benchmark. Columns&#13;
three, four, and five show whether 80 percent of courses meet the benchmark of 85&#13;
percent of respondents giving high ratings (4 or 5) for quality, usefulness, and relevance&#13;
(with a dark circle indicating that 80 percent or more of courses met the benchmark).&#13;
&#13;
   Table 4: Course Level Ratings of FY04, Q1-Q4, Learning Programs by Activity&#13;
                                       Sponsor (where course N&gt;=5)&#13;
&#13;
                   Increase&#13;
                 Knowledge and                                             Overall       Relevance to Bank's&#13;
Single Sponsors     Skills       Job Applicability   Overall Quality      Usefulness          mission        No. of Courses&#13;
&#13;
       PI            )                (                  (                  (                   (                 24&#13;
&#13;
     ACS             )                )                  (                  (                   (                 11&#13;
&#13;
     LEG             )                )                  (                  (                   (                   6&#13;
&#13;
      ISG            (                (                  (                  (                   *                 37&#13;
&#13;
   EAP-SAR           )                )                  (                  (                   (                 10&#13;
&#13;
     LCR             )                )                  (                  *                   (                   8&#13;
&#13;
     ECA             )                )                  (                  (                   *                 10&#13;
&#13;
     HRS             )                )                  *                  (                   (                 12&#13;
&#13;
     OPCS            )                )                  *                  *                   (                 31&#13;
&#13;
     ACT             (                )                  *                  *                   *                 14&#13;
&#13;
  PREM-DEC           *                *                  *                  *                   (                 40&#13;
&#13;
     HDN             *                *                  *                  *                   (                 23&#13;
&#13;
     EXT             )                )                  *                  *                   *                 24&#13;
&#13;
     WBI             )                )                  *                  *                   *                   9&#13;
&#13;
     MGT             )                )                  *                  *                   *                   9&#13;
&#13;
     AFR             *                )                  *                  *                   *                 13&#13;
&#13;
     ESSD            *                *                  *                  *                   *                 48&#13;
&#13;
      INF            *                *                  *                  *                   *                 14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Note: Bank benchmark= 80% of activities are courses with 85% of participant ratings 4 and 5&#13;
&#13;
For columns 1 and 2, (=    higher than Bank/ASTD average,      )=    Bank/ASTD average, *=below     Bank/ASTD&#13;
&#13;
average; for columns 3, 4 and 5, (   = meets or exceeds Bank benchmark,    *   = does not meet Bank benchmark.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Knowledge and Skills&#13;
&#13;
4.28      The first column compares sponsors' mean ratings of knowledge and skills to the&#13;
Bank benchmark.22 Only two sponsors (ISG and ACT) rated above the benchmark while&#13;
two-thirds (61 percent) of the sponsors (PI, ACS, LEG, EAP-SAR, LCR, ECA, HRS,&#13;
OPCS, EXT, WBI and MGT) met the Bank benchmark in increasing knowledge and&#13;
skills. The remaining third (or 28 percent, including: PREM-DEC, HDN, AFR, ESSD,&#13;
&#13;
22A total of 18 sponsors that offered 5 or more courses were included in this comparison.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
and INF) were rated below the Bank benchmark in terms of increasing knowledge and&#13;
skills.&#13;
&#13;
Job Applicability&#13;
&#13;
4.29   The second column in Table 4 presents the assessment of job applicability across&#13;
course sponsors. Two sponsors (PI and ISG) of the total of 18 sponsors with 5 or more&#13;
courses were rated above average in terms of the job applicability of their training&#13;
courses. Nearly two-thirds of the sponsors were rated statistically same as the Bank&#13;
benchmarks (ACT, ACS, AFR, LEG, EAP-SAR, LCR, ECA, HRS, OPCS, EXT, WBI&#13;
and MGT). Twenty-two percent of the sponsors offered courses that were rated below the&#13;
Bank benchmark in terms of their job applicability (PREM-DEC, HDN, ESSD, and INF).&#13;
&#13;
Quality of Training&#13;
&#13;
4.30   Majority of the sponsors (61 percent) offered courses that were rated below the&#13;
Bank benchmarks in terms of their overall quality of training. These sponsors are: ACT,&#13;
AFR, HRS, OPCS, EXT, WBI, PREM-DEC, HDN, MGT, ESSD, and INF. Only 39&#13;
percent of the sponsors were higher than the Bank benchmark (PI, ACS, LEG, ISG, EAP-&#13;
SAR, LCR, ECA).&#13;
&#13;
Usefulness of Training&#13;
&#13;
4.31   The fourth column of Table 4 shows the overall usefulness of courses across&#13;
sponsors. Similar to the rating for overall quality, we find that 61 percent of course&#13;
sponsors were rated below Bank benchmark for overall usefulness of their training (LCR,&#13;
ACT, OPCS, AFR, EXT, WBI, PREM-DEC, HDN, MGT, ESSD, and INF). Thirty nine&#13;
percent of the sponsors were higher than the Bank benchmark (PI, ACS, LEG, ISG, EAP-&#13;
SAR, ECA and HRS).&#13;
&#13;
Relevance to Bank's Mission&#13;
&#13;
4.32   In contrast to the course level ratings across sponsors for overall quality and&#13;
usefulness, we find that half the sponsors were rated above the bank benchmark in terms&#13;
of the relevance of their courses to the Bank's mission. The sponsors that were rated&#13;
above the Bank benchmark are: PI, ACS, LEG, EAP-SAR, LCR, HRS, OPCS, PREM-&#13;
DEC and HDN. Fifty percent of sponsors were rated below the Bank benchmark in terms&#13;
of relevance (ISG, ECA, ACT, EXT, WBI, MGT. AFR, ESSD, and INF).&#13;
&#13;
Overall Quality&#13;
&#13;
4.33   Again, with respect to overall quality, two sponsors receive below standard&#13;
ratings across all five categories: ESSD and INF. We use HLM analysis to determine&#13;
what causes these sponsors to be rated significantly below the others, and to explain how&#13;
quality can be improved based on activity features and participant characteristics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                    5. MODELING TRAINING QUALITY&#13;
&#13;
5.1     Some activities are more highly rated by participants than others, and both&#13;
activity features and participant characteristics could account for these differences in&#13;
ratings. In this chapter we estimate a series of models that (a) test whether low-rated&#13;
activities are a function of participant characteristics or activity features, and (b) provide&#13;
information on how to improve participants' experiences in the learning activity. More&#13;
generally, we seek to understand the determinants of overall satisfaction with training&#13;
quality as a function of both participant and course characteristics (see Figure 11). The&#13;
approach in this chapter builds on findings from past research (Chard and Arango 2003);&#13;
but utilizes a multi-level approach more suitable for these data.23 We describe the&#13;
variables and descriptive statistics below (also see Annex G).24&#13;
&#13;
                   Figure 11. Determinants of Perceived Training Quality&#13;
&#13;
                                 Activity Features&#13;
                                 Class size&#13;
                                 Activity Length&#13;
                                 WB designed activity&#13;
                                 Interactive learning&#13;
                                 Course topic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Participant Traits&#13;
                                                                      Motivation Work&#13;
                    Activity Ratings                                     Learning Plan&#13;
                    Content Quality                                          HQ staff&#13;
                Order of Presentation                                      Grade A-D&#13;
                 Quality of Materials&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Perceived Training Quality&#13;
     Composite score of quality, usefulness, increase in knowledge and&#13;
                                skills, applicability to job&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
23This approach avoids the biased estimation of standard errors which results from using ordinary least&#13;
squares approaches with unbalanced nested data. The data are weighted to reflect the actual distribution of&#13;
the courses delivered.&#13;
24We imputed missing data with the mean values at the participant level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                         VARIABLES&#13;
&#13;
Individual Ratings of Training Quality&#13;
&#13;
5.2     The dependent variable in our analysis, overall training quality, is a composite&#13;
measure based on four participant-reported assessments of the activity for its quality,&#13;
usefulness, effectiveness in increasing the participant's knowledge and skills, and&#13;
applicability to the participant job (questions 13, 14, 16, and 17 in Annex B). All items&#13;
had a seven point response option scale, which were recoded from zero (low quality) to&#13;
one (high quality). We combine these variables both because they are theoretically&#13;
measuring the same underlying dimension of overall perceived quality and because they&#13;
are statistically correlated (alpha=.89).&#13;
&#13;
5.3     It is important to note that although values for overall quality range between zero&#13;
and one, the data are strongly and positively skewed (mean=.81, std dev=.15). We tried&#13;
various types of transformations (i.e. natural log, squaring, cubing), none of which&#13;
mitigated the skewedness of the data; we therefore left it in its most readily interpretable&#13;
state. The reliability score of .668 indicates solid reliability in the outcome variable&#13;
(Raudenbush and Bryk 2002).25&#13;
&#13;
Participant Predictors&#13;
&#13;
5.4     We include four individual participant characteristics as predictors of overall&#13;
quality rating; all are "dummy" variables, where one indicates the participant has the&#13;
characteristic and zero indicates absence of the characteristic. These are:&#13;
&#13;
· Motivation Work: the participant enrolled in the activity to learn skills to enhance&#13;
    their work productivity. Fifty-nine percent of participants indicated work was their&#13;
    primary motivation for taking the course.&#13;
&#13;
· HQ staff: the participant is based in headquarters. Seventy-one percent of staff are&#13;
    located in Headquarters.&#13;
&#13;
· Administrative grade level (Grade AD): the participant is administrative staff in&#13;
    grade levels A through D; ACS staff represent one quarter of our sample.&#13;
&#13;
· Learning Plan: the participant registered the course in their learning plan; thirty-&#13;
    three percent of respondents reported that they attended the course as part of their&#13;
    learning plan.&#13;
&#13;
Activity Features&#13;
&#13;
5.5     Indicators of activity features were developed from participant "Level-1" survey&#13;
responses, a questionnaire completed by the activity task manager, and data in the&#13;
Learning Management System (LMS). We include eight activity features in our analysis:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
25Raudenbush, Stephen W. and Anthony S. Bryk. 2002. Heirarchical Linear Models: Applications and&#13;
Data Analysis Methods. Thousand Oaks: Sage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
· Sponsor: a dummy variable identifying the baseline comparison group of activities&#13;
    that were rated below the benchmarks at both the respondent and course levels (i.e.&#13;
    INF and ESSD).26 These activities represent twenty percent of our sample.&#13;
&#13;
· Course type: three dummy variables identifying each of three major types of content&#13;
    included as controls (professional/technical, Bank operations and behavioral).&#13;
&#13;
· Training content: the rating given by activity's participants for the subject matter&#13;
    and training content, based on a seven-point scale recoded between zero (very poor)&#13;
    and one (very good) (question 8 in Annex B). The mean of .80 (sd=.18) indicates that&#13;
    content is rated highly.&#13;
&#13;
· Presentation order: the rating given by the activity's participants for the logical&#13;
    sequence of the presentations, based on a seven-point scale recoded between zero&#13;
    (very poor) and one (very good) (question 9 in Annex B). The mean of .80 (sd=.17)&#13;
    indicates that presentation organization was assessed as good to very good, on&#13;
    average.&#13;
&#13;
· Course materials: the rating given by the activity's participants for the materials&#13;
    used in the course, based on a seven-point scale recoded between zero (very poor)&#13;
    and one (very good) (question 10 in Annex B). The mean of .77 (sd=.19) shows that&#13;
    the materials were perceived to be of good quality.&#13;
&#13;
· Class size(Totpart): a continuous variable measuring the total number of participants&#13;
    in the activity. Class size ranged from four to 105, with an average of 21 participants&#13;
    (sd=13.5).&#13;
&#13;
· Course duration (Ndays): a continuous variable indicating the length of the activity&#13;
    in days. Duration ranged from a minimum of one day to a maximum of eleven days,&#13;
    with the average duration around two days (mean is 1.8 with a standard deviation of&#13;
    1.5).&#13;
&#13;
· Designed by WB (WBdesign): a dummy variable where a one indicates that the&#13;
    activity is designed by the World Bank. Activity task managers reported that eighty-&#13;
    eight percent of activities were designed internally.&#13;
&#13;
· Interactive learning (Interactive): a dummy variable where one indicates that the&#13;
    activity used action-oriented learning approaches versus a solely traditional lecture&#13;
    format. Activity task managers reported that fifty-eight percent of activities used&#13;
    interactive learning.27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26While INF and ESSD received the lowest scores in our sample, their evaluations are relative to the&#13;
remainder of the sample, and overall, evaluations are skewed to the positive.&#13;
27Interactive Learning question: "Will the training approach primarily employ "Interactive " Learning?&#13;
(Interactive Learning is a process of learning and reflection that happens with the support of a group of&#13;
peers working together with real business problems with the intention of accomplishing tasks while&#13;
enhancing the learning of the group at the same time.)"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                       MULTILEVEL ANALYSIS&#13;
&#13;
5.6      Hierarchical Linear Modeling (HLM) is used to estimate the effects of participant&#13;
characteristics and activity features on overall quality ratings of activities.                    This&#13;
multilevel modeling technique estimates fixed and random effects, and seeks to explain&#13;
the apparent lower participant ratings given to activities of selected sponsors.&#13;
&#13;
5.7      First, we partition the variation in the dependent measure of activity quality into&#13;
components residing at the participant and activity level. This is accomplished by&#13;
estimating an unconditional two-level HLM analysis where the random error components&#13;
signal the relative influence of factors at both these levels on overall quality. We&#13;
calculated the Intra-Class Correlation (ICC) for the dependent variable based on the fully&#13;
unconditional model. The ICC of .16 [ICC=/+2= .00339/(.00339+.01819)] indicates&#13;
that 16 percent of the variance in training quality can be explained by activity level&#13;
differences. Second, we use HLM to examine activity features that can explain this&#13;
variance, in four models.&#13;
&#13;
Model One&#13;
&#13;
5.8      In our first model, we estimate a simple bivariate model to confirm that activities&#13;
offered by the baseline sponsors are indeed statistically significantly below other&#13;
evaluated activities. We predict overall training quality (participant ratings of: quality,&#13;
usefulness of training, perceived increases in knowledge and skills, and applicability to&#13;
job) as a function of sponsor. Equation 1 illustrates Hierarchical Model 128:&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Level-1&#13;
                               Y(Overall Training Quality)= 0 + 1(Sponsor) + r&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Level-2&#13;
                                            0=00+ 01(Sponsor) + u0&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   Eq. 1&#13;
&#13;
Model Two&#13;
&#13;
5.9      In a second model, we estimate a between group model where we predict training&#13;
quality not only from sponsor, but also participant characteristics. In other words, we test&#13;
whether the low scoring courses are rated poorer because the participants in these courses&#13;
are somehow different from participants in other activities. These characteristics are:&#13;
participation motivation to improve current work, HQ based staff (versus field staff),&#13;
ACS grade, and whether or not the activity was registered in participants' learning plans.&#13;
All participant variables are grand mean centered. Equation 2 illustrates our second&#13;
model:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28In this chapter, the terms "Level 1" and "Level 2" refers to participant and activity measures,&#13;
respectively, and should not be confused with "Level-1 Evaluations".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               Level-1&#13;
           Y(Overall Training Quality)= 0 + 1(Sponsor) + 2(Motivation work) + 3(HQ) +&#13;
                             4(gradeAD) + 5(Learning Plan) + r&#13;
&#13;
                                               Level-2&#13;
                                      0=00+ 01(Sponsor) + u0&#13;
                                                1=10&#13;
                                                2=20&#13;
                                                3=30&#13;
                                                4=40&#13;
                                                                                         Eq. 2&#13;
&#13;
Model Three&#13;
&#13;
5.10   In our third model, we test whether adding activity characteristics to the model&#13;
predicting course quality from participant characteristics helps to explain why the ratings&#13;
of activities of selected sponsors are rated lower and if the addition of these activity&#13;
features diminishes the effect of sponsor. In other words, we examine whether activity&#13;
features (class size, course length in days, activity design by World Bank, interactive&#13;
learning format, training content, materials and presentation organization) can explain the&#13;
variance in quality ratings better than the simpler model comprised of sponsor and&#13;
participant characteristics. Equation 3 illustrates our third model.&#13;
&#13;
                                               Level-1&#13;
         Y(Overall Training Quality)= 0 + 1(Motivation work)+ 2(HQ) + 3(gradeAD)&#13;
             + 4(Learning Plan) + 5(Content) + 6(Order) + 7(Material) + r&#13;
&#13;
                                               Level-2&#13;
          0=00+ 01(totpart) + 02(ndays) + 03(designWB) + 04(Interactive) + 05(Sponsor) +&#13;
                        06(P&amp;T) + 07(Bank Operations) + 08(Behavioral) + u0&#13;
                                                1=10&#13;
                                                2=20&#13;
                                                3=30&#13;
                                                4=40&#13;
                                5=50+ 51(totpart) + 52(ndays) + u5&#13;
                                6=60+ 61(totpart) + 62(ndays) + u6&#13;
                                7=70+ 71(totpart) + 72(ndays) + u7&#13;
                                                                                         Eq. 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.11   These equations predict overall quality as a between group hierarchical linear&#13;
model. Participant motivation (to enhance current work), staff status (HQ), grade level (A&#13;
through D) and learning plan are fixed, while individual ratings of content, material, and&#13;
order are free to vary at level one. Activity duration, class size, World Bank design,&#13;
interactive learning, sponsor, and training content (professional/technical, Bank&#13;
operations, behavioral) are included at level two. We also model the slopes for the key&#13;
instruction variables (content, material, order) as a function of activity features (i.e. class&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
size and activity duration).29 Our expectations for the impact of activity features are as&#13;
follows:&#13;
&#13;
    · Ratings of course features will significantly influence overall quality. As ratings&#13;
         of content, materials and presentation order become more positive, individual&#13;
         overall satisfaction and ratings of activity quality will also increase.&#13;
&#13;
    · Longer courses will increase ratings of training quality. Past research shows that&#13;
         as course duration increases, quality ratings become more positive.&#13;
&#13;
    · Larger class sizes will decrease overall quality ratings.                        Previous findings&#13;
         indicate that larger courses were rated less positively by participants.&#13;
&#13;
    · Courses designed by the World Bank will be rated higher in quality. Courses&#13;
         designed by the Bank will be perceived more positively by staff because Bank&#13;
         designed courses would be more relevant to staff.&#13;
&#13;
    · Courses utilizing interactive learning approaches will be perceived more&#13;
         favorably. Activities that use interactive learning such as small group exercises&#13;
         and interactive instructional approaches encouraging participation will be rated&#13;
         significantly higher than activities that use only traditional lecture approaches.&#13;
&#13;
    · Content type and sponsor are included as controls.&#13;
&#13;
Our expectations for participants' characteristics are:&#13;
&#13;
    · Participants who are motivated to attend learning activities to improve their work&#13;
         performance will rate courses more positively.&#13;
&#13;
    · Likewise, participants who register activities in their individual learning plans&#13;
         will rate the course more positively.&#13;
&#13;
    · Staff working in administrative positions will rate training they attend&#13;
         significantly higher in quality than professional level staff. This theory is based&#13;
         on past research which showed that administrative staff rate courses more&#13;
         positively than participants in higher level grades (Ouichi and Le Rouzic 2002).&#13;
&#13;
    · A variable for HQ versus field based staff is included as a control variable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
29We arrived at this model after trying various specifications (i.e. we tested whether gradeAD varied at the&#13;
course level in a within model; we re-centered ndays as grand centered in order to help make interpretation&#13;
of the intercept meaningful; and we estimated the model using only a between group model without&#13;
modeling the slopes). We found no effect for course development (training having been previously offered&#13;
2 or more times), course topic, nor participant affiliation with region/network/other.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Model Four&#13;
&#13;
5.12    In our fourth model, we present a general model of training quality. We remove&#13;
the sponsor variable from the equation and test whether the relationships found in Model&#13;
three are generalizable to all activities. Equation 4 illustrates Model four.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Level-1&#13;
           Y(Overall Training Quality)= 0 + 1(Motivation work) + 2(HQ) + 3(gradeAD) +&#13;
                  4(Learning Plan) + 5(Content) + 6(Order)+ 7(Material) + r&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Level-2&#13;
            0=00+ 01(totpart) + 02(ndays) + 03(designWB) + 04(Interactive) + 05(P&amp;T) +&#13;
                                 06(Bank Operations) + 07(Behavioral) + u0&#13;
                                                      1=10&#13;
                                                      2=20&#13;
                                                      3=30&#13;
                                                      4=40&#13;
                                    5=50+ 51(totpart) + 52(ndays) + u5&#13;
                                    6=60+ 61(totpart) + 62(ndays) + u6&#13;
                                    7=70+ 71(totpart) + 72(ndays) + u7&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     Eq. 4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               MULTILEVEL MODELING RESULTS&#13;
&#13;
5.13    Table 5 presents the HLM results for the four models. The first six columns&#13;
present the results for models one, two, and three, which successively build on each&#13;
other.30  The last two columns present our fourth and final model which explains&#13;
perceived training quality, more generally.&#13;
&#13;
5.14    Model one confirms the findings reported in the previous chapter that participants&#13;
in activities belonging to the baseline group of low rated sponsors gave statistically&#13;
significantly lower quality ratings (b=-.05, p&lt;.01).              Thus, we go on to examine why&#13;
these activities are rated lower.&#13;
&#13;
5.15    In Model two, we ask whether this is due to participant differences. Are staff who&#13;
are interested in these topics and who participate in related activities inherently different&#13;
from participants in other courses? Are they perhaps more critical of training? The results&#13;
from Model two indicate that this is not the case. While participant characteristics are&#13;
predictors of perceived training quality, they do not explain away the negative effect of&#13;
sponsor. In other words, even when we control for participant motivation, HQ based&#13;
status, grade level, and learning plan, a significant and negative impact from sponsor&#13;
remains (b=-.03, p&lt;.01). This could be due to unmeasured participant characteristics or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30Our analysis is based on questionnaires using the seven point scale and staff only (respondent N= 3980,&#13;
course N=309).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
could be a consequence of activity features. As we cannot investigate the former, we turn&#13;
to the latter.&#13;
&#13;
             Table 5. HLM Between-Group Model Predicting Training Quality&#13;
&#13;
                                  Model 1                  Model 2                  Model 3                   Model 4&#13;
&#13;
      Fixed Effects        Gamma       Reliability  Gamma       Reliability  Gamma        Reliability  Gamma       Reliability&#13;
                          Coefficient   estimate   Coefficient   estimate   Coefficient   estimate    Coefficient   estimate&#13;
      Intercept            0.8300**      .629      0.8246**       .599       0.8226**       .817      0.8210**       .818&#13;
      Sponsor              -0.0461**               -0.0329**                 -0.0140                      --&#13;
      Participant&#13;
      Motivation (work)                            0.0327**                  0.0254**                 0.0255**&#13;
&#13;
      Based in HQ                                   0.0146*                  0.0050                    0.0049&#13;
      Grade A ­D                                   0.0249**                  0.0112**                 0.0117**&#13;
      Learning Plan                                0.0220**                  0.0072*                   0.0073*&#13;
&#13;
      Total Participants                                                    -0.0015**                 -0.0015**&#13;
      Course Days                                                            0.0138**                 0.0144**&#13;
      Designed by WB                                                         0.0088                    0.0075&#13;
      Interactive&#13;
      Learning                                                               -0.0012                   -0.0022&#13;
&#13;
      Professional&#13;
      Technical                                                              -0.0129                   -0.0133&#13;
&#13;
      Bank Operations                                                        -0.010                    -0.0082&#13;
      Behavioral                                                             0.0131                    0.0157&#13;
&#13;
      Training Content                                                                      .224                     .224&#13;
      Intercept                                                              .3767**                  0.3762**&#13;
      Total Participants                                                     0.0045**                 0.0046**&#13;
      Course Days                                                            -.01401                   -0.0137&#13;
      Presentation&#13;
      Order                                                                                 .289                     .289&#13;
&#13;
      Intercept                                                              0.1944**                 0.1946**&#13;
      Total Participants                                                     -0.0017                   -0.0017&#13;
      Course Days                                                            0.0023                    0.0021&#13;
      Course Materials                                                                      .170                     .170&#13;
      Intercept                                                              0.1178**                 0.1178**&#13;
      Total Participants                                                     -0.0012                   -0.0012&#13;
      Course Days                                                            -0.0139                   -0.0139&#13;
&#13;
                           Standard                Standard                 Standard                  Standard&#13;
      Random Effect        deviation   Variance    deviation    Variance    deviation     Variance    deviation    Variance&#13;
      Mean quality          0.0567      0.0032      0.0523       0.0027      0.0548**      0.0030     0.0550**      0.0030&#13;
      Training Content                                                       0.1370**      0.0188     0.1371**      0.0188&#13;
      Presentation Order                                                     0.1756**      0.0308     0.1755**      0.0308&#13;
      Course materials                                                       0.0989        0.0098      0.0990       0.0098&#13;
      R                     .12336       .0153      .12239        .0150      0.01733       0.0051      0.0713       0.0051&#13;
    **p&lt;.01, *p&lt;.05, p&lt;.10;&#13;
                       &#13;
&#13;
    BOLD italics indicates grand mean centered; BOLD indicates group mean centered&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.16     The results from Model three show that activity features are in fact significant&#13;
predictors of training quality, and their inclusion in the model reduces to non-significance&#13;
the coefficient for the effect of sponsor. Five activity features -- training content,&#13;
presentation order, training materials, class size, and course duration -- explain&#13;
participants' ratings of training quality. Model four, the same in all respects to Model&#13;
three other than the non-inclusion of the sponsor category variable, shows the same&#13;
relationships. This suggests that all activities, not only those in the baseline category, can&#13;
improve their quality ratings by concentrating on enhancing the key aspects of training,&#13;
prominent in both Models three and four.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5.17      Because the findings for both models are consistent, we discuss the results with&#13;
respect to the coefficients reported in Model three.31 Overall, the reliability estimates in&#13;
the third column show that we can have reasonable confidence in our estimates for the&#13;
random variables (.82 for the intercept, .22 for content, .29 for order, and .17 for&#13;
materials). Our model explains 72 percent of the variance in the intercept and within&#13;
variance.32 The model results demonstrate the importance of five key activity features&#13;
and three participant characteristics.&#13;
&#13;
Activity features&#13;
&#13;
5.18      Four of the eight activity features discussed above were significant predictors of&#13;
participants' ratings of overall activity quality, and in some cases cross-level effects were&#13;
also found.&#13;
&#13;
Training Content&#13;
&#13;
5.19      Good training content significantly increased quality ratings by 38 percent (b=.38,&#13;
p&lt;.01). In activities where participant rating of training content was positive, individual&#13;
ratings of overall quality were also high. In examining the cross level effects however,&#13;
we find that the effect of training content is mediated by class size (b=.01, p&lt;01).&#13;
Content ratings are more important in larger classes.33 As class size increases&#13;
(average=21), the effect of subject matter becomes more prominent in overall quality&#13;
ratings. For example, increasing class size from average, by one standard deviation,&#13;
increases the importance of content ratings by 14 percent, thereby increasing the effect of&#13;
training content to 52 percent. This suggests that trainers need to pay even more attention&#13;
to content as their audiences increase. This is perhaps because larger courses do not lend&#13;
themselves as easily to other important aspects of learning such as class discussion.&#13;
Qualitative feedback suggests that respondents enjoy participating in class discussion in&#13;
smaller classes.34&#13;
&#13;
Presentation Order&#13;
&#13;
5.20      Likewise, presentation order being rated positively also increased perceived&#13;
quality ratings by 19 percent. In other words, activities in which presentation organization&#13;
is logical received significantly higher quality ratings. This indicates that paying closer&#13;
&#13;
31 Differences in the results of the two models are limited to few instances in the third or fourth decimal&#13;
place, which do not change the substantive interpretations.&#13;
32 The within model reduction in sigma squared is 72 percent. The random effect estimates for the&#13;
intercept (illustrated in the lower part of the table) that the adjusted variance for quality ratings is .003. This&#13;
is the amount of variance in quality ratings unaccounted for by the model, p&lt;.01, indicating that there is&#13;
still variance to be explained. The amount of within-group variance unaccounted for by the model is . 01. In&#13;
other words, after accounting for participant characteristics and assessments of course features, the estimate&#13;
of within group variance is .01.&#13;
33 We did not find any other cross-level effects between course features and course topic (i.e. P&amp;T, Bank&#13;
operations, Behavioral). We also tested whether the influence of training content, presentation order, and&#13;
course materials are mediated by course characteristics such as course length, interactive learning format&#13;
and activity topic.&#13;
34A summary of the qualitative analysis will be reported in a separate evaluation comparing the highest and&#13;
lowest rated activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
attention to the order in which content is presented is critical to successful learning&#13;
activities, as deemed by participants. For example, this perhaps means strict adherence to&#13;
the agenda and avoiding last minute schedule changes.&#13;
&#13;
Course Materials&#13;
&#13;
5.21    Activities where participants rated the course materials positively also received&#13;
higher ratings from participants, by 11 percent.&#13;
&#13;
Class Size&#13;
&#13;
5.22    Smaller classes received higher ratings for training quality. Increasing the average&#13;
total number of participants in an activity decreases quality ratings significantly (b=-.002,&#13;
p&lt;.01). For instance, increasing the average class size by one standard deviation from the&#13;
average of 21 to 35, decreases quality ratings by three percent. Further increasing the&#13;
class size to the maximum in our sample, 105, results in a 17 percent decrease in&#13;
perceived quality ratings.&#13;
&#13;
Course duration&#13;
&#13;
5.23    The data support our hypothesis that longer courses are perceived more positively.&#13;
On average, increasing course length by one day, increases quality ratings by one percent.&#13;
Increasing course length from average (nearly two days) to the maximum in our sample&#13;
(eleven days) increases quality ratings by nine percent.35 Again, however, since&#13;
increasing duration yields only a one percent increase per day in overall quality, it may be&#13;
cost-effective to retain shorter courses.&#13;
&#13;
Insignificant activity-level predictors&#13;
&#13;
5.24    Contrary to our expectations, we found no effects in the HLM model for the&#13;
following activity features: World Bank design, interactive learning, or type of course&#13;
(professional/technical, Bank operations, behavioral). That is, courses designed by Bank&#13;
staff, using interactive learning methods, or with specific training content were no more&#13;
or less positively rated than average.&#13;
&#13;
5.25    Perhaps the most counterintuitive finding is for interactive learning approaches in&#13;
staff training; there is no evidence in our analyses to support the theory that interactive&#13;
learning enhances adult learning. There are at least two reasons for this result. The first is&#13;
that, in fact, interactive learning methods are no more effective than didactic ones.&#13;
However, since a broad body of literature suggests that genuine interactive learning is&#13;
effective with adults, this is not an appealing explanation. Another explanation is that&#13;
there may be some social desirability bias in our interactive learning measure, which was&#13;
collected from the course administrators. Since "action learning" is encouraged at the&#13;
Bank, course administrators may over-report "interactive learning". We note that the&#13;
share of activities identified as using "interactive learning" is quite high in FY04: 54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
35We tested activity length for a quadratic relationship but did not find one.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
percent. We do not have confirmatory data on this measure from participants for staff&#13;
learning, but such data are available for WBI activities. Quizon, Chard and Lockheed&#13;
(2004)36 found that sixty-one percent of task managers reported that action learning was&#13;
utilized in their training events, but only thirty-three percent of participants indicated that&#13;
the activity included action learning exercises such as action plans. When a measure of&#13;
action learning that combined both staff and participant views was used, it was found to&#13;
be strongly associated with more positive ratings of the activity.&#13;
&#13;
Participant characteristics&#13;
&#13;
5.26     Our model also controls for various participant characteristics such as motivation,&#13;
grade level, staff status, and whether or not the activity was registered in participants'&#13;
learning plans. Staff located in Headquarters did not rate activities more or less positively&#13;
than did staff located in the field. However, participant's grade level, learning plan&#13;
status, and motivation for taking the course were significantly related to assessments of&#13;
training quality.&#13;
&#13;
ACS grade level&#13;
&#13;
5.27     Administrative staff rated training quality one percent higher on average than did&#13;
professional level staff (b=.01, p&lt;.01). We tested this for random effects and found no&#13;
significant differences by course type or sponsor category (see Annex F). The null&#13;
findings indicate that administrative staff are neither more, nor less likely to rate certain&#13;
types of courses more positively.&#13;
&#13;
Motivation for participation&#13;
&#13;
5.28     Participants' motivation for taking a course was also related to training quality.&#13;
We find that participants whose primary motivation was to enhance performance in their&#13;
current work program rated the courses more favorably by three percent, on average, than&#13;
participants with some other motivation for learning (i.e. professional growth/interest,&#13;
networking, or "other", b=.03, p&lt;.01).&#13;
&#13;
Learning plan&#13;
&#13;
5.29     Registration of the activity in participants' individual learning plans can be&#13;
considered another indicator of motivation. We found that participants who registered&#13;
their activities in their individual learning plans rated activities higher by one percent, on&#13;
average (b=.01, p&lt;.05).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
36Quizon, J. B.; C. L. Chard; and M. Lockheed. "The Effectiveness and Use in FY03 of WBI FY01-02&#13;
Activities: A Baseline Assessment in Five Countries." WBI Evaluation Studies, No, EG04-86, May 2004.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   6. CONCLUSIONS&#13;
&#13;
6.1     Overall, staff learning quality has improved significantly in FY04. On the whole,&#13;
the Bank has considerably increased the quality, usefulness, and relevance of its learning&#13;
programs in FY04. Participant ratings significantly increased from FY03 in three of five&#13;
key dimensions measuring the value of training: (a) overall quality (b) usefulness, and (c)&#13;
relevance to the Bank's mission. A comparison of various types of learning providers&#13;
showed specifically, that P&amp;T Networks and Other Networks markedly improved across&#13;
all three dimensions in FY04. Further, the Regions improved significantly in making&#13;
training more relevant to the Bank's mission.&#13;
&#13;
6.2     Conversely, there were no significant changes between fiscal years in the&#13;
remaining two dimensions of training value: (d) training applicability to job, and (e)&#13;
perceived increases in knowledge and skills. While participant ratings of both items&#13;
remained statistically the same in FY03 and FY04, in FY04 average training applicability&#13;
to job fell below the most recent ASTD benchmark.                      In particular, ratings of job&#13;
applicability and knowledge and skills were significantly lower among P&amp;T Networks&#13;
and Regions in FY04.&#13;
&#13;
ACTIVITY FEATURES EXPLAINING TRAINING QUALITY&#13;
&#13;
6.3     We analyzed the determinants of training quality in order to make more precise&#13;
recommendations for improving staff training. Our model results indicate that perceived&#13;
training quality is highly affected by instructional design and implementation: training&#13;
content, order of presentation and training materials. The higher the activity was rated on&#13;
these features, on average, the more positively participants rated the quality of the course&#13;
they attended. The effect of training content was stronger among activities with larger&#13;
class sizes.&#13;
&#13;
6.4     Two other course features were significantly related to perceived training quality:&#13;
course length and class size.          On average, we found that training was rated more&#13;
positively among participants in learning activities with greater than two days duration&#13;
and courses with fewer than 21 participants. These findings confirm results reported in&#13;
the annual review of staff learning for FY03.37&#13;
&#13;
6.5     In contrast to some of the literature on adult learning, we did not find any&#13;
evidence to support the claim that "action learning" enhances participant satisfaction with&#13;
training. That is, courses described by the course task manager as using interactive&#13;
learning techniques were not more highly rated by participants. This may be partially&#13;
due to social desirability bias and over-reporting of interactive learning. A comprehensive&#13;
summary of IEG evaluations of WBI client training shows that action learning is a&#13;
significant predictor of training effectiveness when the sources of information about&#13;
&#13;
37See Annex I for activity means for key determinants of activity quality by training sponsor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
action learning are course participants, rather than course task managers. Reported use of&#13;
action learning approaches was found to be significantly higher among task managers&#13;
than participants who recalled using action learning.&#13;
&#13;
PARTICIPANT VARIABLES RELATED TO TRAINING QUALITY&#13;
&#13;
6.6     Finally, we found that participant demographics and characteristics were related&#13;
to perceived training quality: (a) staff grade level; (b) motivation for taking the course;&#13;
and (c) learning plan status. ACS staff were more likely to rate courses higher in quality&#13;
than were higher level professional staff. This effect varied neither by course nor&#13;
learning provider category. Participants who reported their primary motivation for taking&#13;
the course as enhancing their performance in their current work program rated the&#13;
courses more positively than participants with some other motivation for learning (i.e.&#13;
professional growth/interest, networking, or "other".) Participants who registered their&#13;
activity in their individual learning plans rated training quality significantly higher than&#13;
their counterparts who did not report the activities as part of their learning plan. This&#13;
result also underscored findings from FY03.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         33&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                  ANNEX A: ACTIVITY QUESTIONNAIRE&#13;
&#13;
                                                 ··· -- Institute Evaluation Group -- ···&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Add a course to the Level 1 database&#13;
Event Title&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Task Manager(s) for learning event&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Learning Coordinator&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Learning Catalog Code&#13;
Format: LLLNNN-NN-NNN (L= letter ; N= number)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Event Dates and Times&#13;
&#13;
Start Date                                 Start Time:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
End Date                                   End Time:&#13;
&#13;
Activity Location (Building / Room)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Number of Days&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Number of participants expected to attend learning event&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Are at least half of the expected participants World Bank staff members?&#13;
&#13;
     Yes          No&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Would you like a separate evaluation of the instructor?&#13;
&#13;
     Yes          No&#13;
&#13;
If you answered "yes " to the optional instructor's evaluation, please provide the names of the instructors to be evaluated:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Order of Instructors by                     Name of instructor to be evaluated        Title of corresponding session&#13;
 appearance in the course&#13;
                       1&#13;
                       2&#13;
                       3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        (Please add rows as needed)&#13;
&#13;
Please select the sponsor(s) for this learning event&#13;
Regional Vice - Presidencies:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     AFR           EAP/SAR           ECA             LCR           MENA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           34&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Network Anchors:&#13;
&#13;
      ACS          ESSD           FSE        HDN       INF         ISG        OPCS         PREM/DEC&#13;
Other:&#13;
&#13;
      MGT SLC           EXT           PI      GSD       HRS          LEG         OED         ACT          WBI&#13;
&#13;
      Other, specify:&#13;
In which one of the following categories does the training content best fit?&#13;
&#13;
      Information &amp; Technology&#13;
&#13;
      Executive Management&#13;
&#13;
      Professional &amp; Technical&#13;
&#13;
      Trust Funds&#13;
&#13;
      Behavioral &amp; Social (interpersonal communication skills)&#13;
&#13;
      Bank Operations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Will the training approach primarily employ "Interactive " Learning? (Interactive Learning is a process of learning and reflection that&#13;
happens with the support of a group of peers working together with real business problems with the intention of accomplishing tasks while&#13;
enhancing the learning of the group at the same time.)&#13;
&#13;
      Yes          No&#13;
&#13;
How will this event be delivered?&#13;
&#13;
      Face to Face&#13;
&#13;
      Distance Learning&#13;
&#13;
      Combined (F2F and DL)&#13;
&#13;
Was this event designed by the World Bank?&#13;
&#13;
      Yes       No&#13;
&#13;
Will the event be facilitated by the World Bank?&#13;
&#13;
      Yes        No&#13;
&#13;
      Combined (Bank Staff and Outside Consultants)&#13;
Was this course designed especially for Managers?&#13;
&#13;
      Yes        No&#13;
&#13;
How many times has this event been delivered in the past?&#13;
&#13;
      First time this event will be delivered&#13;
&#13;
      Second time this event will be offered&#13;
&#13;
      Two or more times&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                 35&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                    ANNEX B: PARTICIPANT QUESTIONNAIRE&#13;
&#13;
                                   Level 1 Evaluation Questionnaire for Staff Learning&#13;
  Please assess the course to help to improve future training. To answer, please fill in the circle completely(    ). If you&#13;
  wish to change an answer, fully erase it or draw an     X  over the unwanted mark and fill in the circle indicating your&#13;
  preferred answer. Please choose only one answer per question.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Training Title:                                                              Training Dates:&#13;
&#13;
  1. What was your main reason for taking this training? (Fill only one circle.)&#13;
       To enhance performance in current/planned assignment&#13;
       To network and share information&#13;
       For professional interest and growth&#13;
       Other&#13;
&#13;
  2. Do you work for the World Bank?          ?    Yes, at HQ           ?   Yes, in the Field      ?    No If no, go to Q6.&#13;
&#13;
  3. For what part of the World Bank Group do you primarily work? (Fill only one circle.)&#13;
       Regional Vice-Presidencies          Network Anchors                   Other&#13;
       AFR             LCR                 ESSD             OPCS             DEC               IFC&#13;
       EAP             MENA                FSE              PREM             HRS               MIGA&#13;
       ECA             SAR                 HDN              PSD              LEG               EXT&#13;
                                           ISG              INF              WBI               Other&#13;
&#13;
  4. What is your grade level?&#13;
       GA-GD                          GE                             GG                             ETC / STC&#13;
&#13;
       ETT / STT                      GF                             GH or above                    Other&#13;
&#13;
  5. Was this training agreed upon in your Learning Plan (LP)?&#13;
  ? Yes                          ? No                            I don't have a LP              I don't know&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Using the scale on the right, please rate each question/statement below.        Not                                   Very&#13;
                                                                                 at all                                much&#13;
  6. To what extent did the training fulfill your learning needs?                         &#13;
  7. To what extent did the training achieve its announced objectives?                    &#13;
                                                                                 Very                                   Very&#13;
                                                                                 poor                Average            good&#13;
&#13;
  8. How would you rate the training content or subject matter?                           &#13;
&#13;
  9. How would you rate the order in which the content was presented?                     &#13;
&#13;
  10. How would you rate the materials used during the training?                          &#13;
                                                                                 Very                                   Very&#13;
                                                                                  low                Medium             high&#13;
&#13;
  11. How would you rate the overall quality of the training?                             &#13;
&#13;
  12. How would you rate the overall usefulness of the training?                          &#13;
  13. How would you rate the relevance of this training to the Bank's&#13;
      mission?                                                                            &#13;
&#13;
                                                                               Strongly                            Strongly&#13;
                                                                               Disagree              Neither          Agree&#13;
  14. My knowledge/skills increased as a result of this training.                         &#13;
  15. The knowledge/skills gained through this training are directly applicable&#13;
      to my job.                                                                          &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
36&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX C: COURSE AUDIENCE: DISTRIBUTION OF RESPONDENT&#13;
                              UNIT, BY ACTIVITY SPONSOR&#13;
&#13;
                                              P&amp;T NETWORKS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by                      Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by&#13;
                      ESSD                                                                 HDN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   100                                                              100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   80                                                               80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   60                                                               60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   40 32.5                                                          40&#13;
                                                                       25.8&#13;
          19.6                                                             17.5&#13;
   20         12.810.68.3                                           20         13.1 12.0&#13;
                         6.2                                                            8.9&#13;
                              4.9                                                           6.2&#13;
                                  1.4 1.2 0.6 0.6 0.5 0.5 0.3                                   4.1 4.1 3.42.4 0.7 0.70.3 0.3 0.3&#13;
     0                                                                0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Participant Unit                                                    Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by                      Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by&#13;
                        INF                                                            PREMDEC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   100                                                              100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   80                                                               80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   60                                                               60&#13;
      40.7&#13;
   40                                                               40&#13;
                                                                       23.721.9&#13;
          15.4&#13;
   20         11.2 9.1 7.1                                          20         11.1&#13;
                           4.6  4.1                                                7.8 7.8 7.1&#13;
                                    2.5  2.1 1.7 0.8                                          4.7 4.5&#13;
                                                     0.4 0.4                                         3.8 2.72.0 1.60.50.4 0.2 0.2&#13;
     0                                                                0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Participant Unit                                                   Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      37&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     OTHER NETWORKS&#13;
&#13;
  Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by                                  Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by&#13;
                             ACS                                                                          ISG&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    100                                                                           100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     80                                                                           80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     60                                                                           60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     40                                                                           40 27.4&#13;
&#13;
     20 16.516.514.410.17.2                                                       20&#13;
                           7.2                                                          14.08.8&#13;
                              5.0 5.0 5.0                                                      6.7&#13;
                                         3.62.9 2.2                                                5.34.64.6 4.2&#13;
                                                    0.7 0.7 0.7 0.7 0.7 0.7                                     3.53.2 2.5 2.5 2.52.5 2.5 1.81.8 1.40.7&#13;
&#13;
      0                                                                             0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Participant Unit                                                             Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored                                     Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored&#13;
                           by MGT                                                                     by OPCS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     100                                                                          100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     80                                                                           80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     60                                                                           60&#13;
&#13;
        34.9&#13;
     40                                                                           40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     20     12.010.88.4                                                           20 22.118.413.212.912.48.9&#13;
                        4.8 4.8 4.83.6 2.4 2.4 2.4 2.4                                                      5.3&#13;
                                                       1.2 1.2 1.2 1.2 1.2                                      1.1 1.1 1.1 1.1 0.8 0.5 0.5 0.3 0.3 0.3&#13;
       0                                                                            0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Participant Unit                                                             Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored&#13;
                            by PI&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     40 26.6&#13;
&#13;
     20     14.7&#13;
                6.2 6.2 5.6 5.6 5.1 5.1 5.13.4 3.4 2.8 2.82.3 2.3 2.3 0.6&#13;
       0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
38&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             REGIONS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by             Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by&#13;
                     AFR                                                   EAPSAR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   100                                                     100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   80                                                      80&#13;
       64.7&#13;
&#13;
   60                                                      60   50.0&#13;
                                                                        42.7&#13;
   40                                                      40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   20       11.8&#13;
                 7.8                                       20&#13;
                     5.9   2.9  2.0  2.0 1.0 1.0 1.0                            3.6        1.8    0.9    0.9&#13;
     0                                                       0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       Participant Unit                                        Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by             Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored&#13;
                    ECA                                                    by LCR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   100                                                     100&#13;
                                                               81.9&#13;
   80                                                      80&#13;
       64.7&#13;
&#13;
   60                                                      60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   40      26.9                                            40&#13;
&#13;
   20                                                      20        8.4&#13;
                 2.4 1.2   1.2  1.2  0.6 0.6 0.6 0.6                        3.6   1.2    1.2   1.2   1.2  1.2&#13;
     0                                                       0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Participant Unit                                         Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        39&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                   OTHERS&#13;
&#13;
 Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by                                Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by&#13;
                            ACT                                                                     EXT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     100                                                                       100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     80                                                                        80&#13;
&#13;
     60                                                                        60 49.7&#13;
&#13;
     40 30.5                                                                   40&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      18.2&#13;
     20    13.09.9 8.46.1 5.3                                                  20&#13;
                             5.3 3.83.12.32.3 2.3 1.5 1.5 1.5 1.5                         6.8&#13;
                                                                 0.8 0.8                      5.3 4.7 3.52.4 1.8 1.8 1.51.2 1.2 0.9 0.90.3&#13;
       0                                                                         0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Participant Unit                                                         Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by                               Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by&#13;
                            GSD                                                                     HRS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     100                                                                       100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     80                                                                        80&#13;
&#13;
     60      50.0                                                              60 52.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     40                                                                        40&#13;
                             25.0&#13;
&#13;
     20                                     12.5              12.5             20     10.2  8.6 6.3 4.7 4.7  3.9 3.9 1.6 1.6  0.8 0.8 0.8&#13;
       0                                                                         0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Part icipant Unit                                                        Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by                                Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored by&#13;
                            LEG                                                                     SEC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     100                                                                       100&#13;
            82.5&#13;
&#13;
     80                                                                        80&#13;
                                                                                  59.3&#13;
     60                                                                        60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     40                                                                        40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     20                                                                        20       13.6&#13;
                         5.3          5.3         5.3            1.8                          5.1  5.1  3.4  3.4  3.4   1.7 1.7   1.7  1.7&#13;
       0                                                                         0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Participant Unit                                                         Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
40&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Respondents by Unit in Courses Sponsored&#13;
                by WBI&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  100&#13;
       79.2&#13;
  80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  20           8.3        4.2       4.2    4.2&#13;
&#13;
    0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Participant Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  41&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 ANNEX D: DISTRIBUTION OF RESPONDENTS BY UNIT IN ACTIVITY&#13;
                                                                                        CONTENT TYPE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Respondents in BANK OPERATIONS courses                                                                            Respondents in BEHAVIORAL SOCIAL courses&#13;
&#13;
                             100                                                                                                               100&#13;
&#13;
                stn          80                                                                                        s                       80&#13;
&#13;
                   de                                                                                                   nt&#13;
                             60&#13;
                     onpseR  40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           % 20 18.216.215.110.38.46.0                                                                    denopseR 60          40&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  27.0&#13;
&#13;
                                                      5.33.83.63.2          2.52.31.7 1.30.8 0.7 0.50.10.1                % 20&#13;
                               0                                                                                                                      11.4 9.78.2 6.8 5.7 5.5 5.5 4.33.53.2 3.0 2.2 1.2 1.20.8 0.30.3 0.2&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Respondent's Unit                                                                                                 Respondent's Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Respondents in EXECUTIVEMANAGEMENT                                                        Respondents in INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY&#13;
                                                   courses                                                                                                            courses&#13;
&#13;
                            100                                                                                                                100&#13;
&#13;
    s&#13;
     nt                      80                                                                                                                80&#13;
&#13;
       de                    60                                                                                                                60&#13;
&#13;
         ponseR                                                                                                                   stnedno&#13;
                             40 34.4&#13;
                                                                                                                                               40&#13;
                                                                                                                                         espR      30.1&#13;
&#13;
                             20&#13;
               %                    13.1 8.2  6.6 6.6 6.64.9                                                                                   20&#13;
                                                            3.3 3.3 3.3           1.6 1.6 1.6 1.6 1.6 1.6                                    %        13.510.27.0 5.0 4.8 4.13.4  3.23.0 2.9 2.5 2.52.3 2.1 1.60.9 0.50.4&#13;
                              0                                                                                                                  0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Respondent's Unit                                                                                                  Respondent's Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            Respondents in PROFESSIONAL / TECHNICAL&#13;
                                                                                                        courses&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            100&#13;
&#13;
                                                               s&#13;
                                                                nt          80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            60&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  pondeseR  40&#13;
                                                                                24.2&#13;
                                                                                     15.8&#13;
                                                                            20&#13;
                                                                          %              8.9  8.1 8.0 6.4 6.25.44.53.32.3                      1.9 1.5 1.4 1.2 0.9  0.0 0.0 0.0&#13;
                                                                              0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          Respondent's Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
42&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
            ANNEX E: RATINGS FOR JOINTLY SPONSORED COURSES IN&#13;
                                                               FY04&#13;
&#13;
Note: For Columns 1 And 2,   (=Higher    Than Bank/ASTD Average,           )=Bank/ASTD       Average,*   =Below Bank/ASTD&#13;
&#13;
            Ratings of FY04, Q1-Q4, Learning Programs by Activity Sponsor (Respondent level),&#13;
                                       listed in order of overall aggregate index&#13;
                    Increase Knowledge                                                                  Relevance toThe     No. of&#13;
Joint Sponsors            And Skills38    Job Applicability39 Overall Quality40   Overall Usefulness*   Bank's Mission *  Respondents&#13;
&#13;
      ACT ISG                (                   (                    (                   (                   (               11&#13;
&#13;
    ECA OPCS                 (                   (                    (                   (                   (               34&#13;
&#13;
      LCR LEG                (                   (                    (                   (                   (               12&#13;
&#13;
   EAP-SAR PI                (                   )                    (                   (                   (               21&#13;
&#13;
      OED LCR                )                   (                    (                   (                   (               37&#13;
&#13;
  OPCS HRS PI                )                   (                    (                   (                   (               8&#13;
&#13;
 AFR PREM-DEC                )                   )                    (                   (                   (&#13;
  EAP-SAR LCR                                                                                                                 21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    ESSD EXT                 )                   )                    (                   (                   (               8&#13;
&#13;
    ESSD HDN                 )                   )                    (                   (                   (               15&#13;
&#13;
       EXT PI                )                   )                    (                   (                   (               58&#13;
&#13;
     MGT LEG                 )                   )                    (                   (                   (               21&#13;
&#13;
  PREM-DEC PI                )                   )                    (                   (                   (               4&#13;
&#13;
 PREM-DEC WBI                )                   )                    (                   (                   (               23&#13;
&#13;
    ESSD AFR                 )                   (                    (                   (                   *               11&#13;
&#13;
 INF PREM-DEC                )                   *                    (                   (                   (               37&#13;
&#13;
      PSD AFR                *                   )                    (                   (                   (               9&#13;
&#13;
     ESSD WBI                )                   )                    *                   (                   (               39&#13;
&#13;
  INF ESSD WBI               )                   )                    (                   *                   (               16&#13;
&#13;
      HDN AFR                *                   )                    *                   (                   (               18&#13;
&#13;
    OPCS HDN                 )                   )                    *                   *                   (               20&#13;
&#13;
      OED AFR                )                   )                    *                   *                   *               11&#13;
&#13;
 PSD PREM-DEC                )                   )                    *                   *                   *&#13;
        WBI                                                                                                                   6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    OPCS ACT                 )                   )                    *                   *                   *               8&#13;
&#13;
 AFR PREM-DEC                *                   *                    *                   *                   (               55&#13;
&#13;
  HDN WBI AFR                )                   *                    *                   *                   *               23&#13;
&#13;
 LCR PREM-DEC                *                   *                    *                   *                   *               18&#13;
&#13;
       HRS PI                *                   *                    *                   *                   *               39&#13;
&#13;
Average; For Columns 3, 4 And 5,    (   = Meets Or Exceeds Bank Benchmark,          *  = Does Not Meet Bank Benchmark.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      38The benchmark is the Bank average rating (4.20), statistically the same as the ASTD standard (4.21).&#13;
      39The benchmark is the Bank average rating (4.18), statistically the same as the ASTD standard (4.21).&#13;
      40The benchmark is 85% of respondents in a course gave ratings of 4 or 5.&#13;
                                                                                                                           43&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  ANNEX F: MEAN RATINGS OF ACTIVITY CHARACTERISTICS,&#13;
                         FY03-FY04 (1=LOW; 5=HIGH)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              4.14&#13;
        Material used&#13;
                                     4.10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        4.28&#13;
   Presentation Order&#13;
                                                                4.23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        4.28&#13;
              Content&#13;
                                                               4.23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      4.27&#13;
Announced Objectives&#13;
                                                          4.19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      4.18&#13;
  Learning Needs Met&#13;
                                       4.11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     4.00   4.05   4.10      4.15       4.20     4.25     4.30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          FY04    FY03&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
44&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                ANNEX G: VARIABLE DEFINITIONS&#13;
&#13;
 Variable Name                     Definition                                     Coding&#13;
&#13;
Overall Training Participant ratings of the training's        Higher scores indicate higher overall&#13;
Quality          applicability to job, quality, usefulness,   training quality, coded between zero&#13;
                 relevance to Bank's mission; and             and one.&#13;
                 perceived increase in knowledge and skills&#13;
&#13;
Bank Operations  Training content focuses on Bank             1 if Bank Operations; zero otherwise&#13;
(BO)             operational work&#13;
&#13;
Professional     Training content focuses on professional     1 if Professional Technical; zero&#13;
Technical (PT)   and technical topics (e.g. macro-            otherwise&#13;
                 economics)&#13;
&#13;
Behavioral       Training content type is behavioral and      1 if Behavioral Social; zero otherwise&#13;
Social           social (e.g. communication etc.)&#13;
(Behavioral)&#13;
&#13;
WBdesign         World Bank designed the course               1 if designed by WB; zero otherwise&#13;
&#13;
Total            Total participants in the course             Number of participants&#13;
Participants&#13;
(Totpart)&#13;
&#13;
Course Days      Course duration measured in days             Number of days in training&#13;
(ndays)&#13;
&#13;
Training Content Participant rating of training content       Higher scores indicate higher training&#13;
(Content)                                                     content quality&#13;
&#13;
Presentation     Participant rating of the order in which     Higher scores indicate better ratings of&#13;
Order            topics were presented                        the sequence in which the material was&#13;
(Order)                                                       presented&#13;
&#13;
Course Materials Participant rating of the course materials   Higher scores indicate higher ratings of&#13;
(Materials)                                                   course material&#13;
&#13;
Interactive      Interactive learning was used in course      1 if interactive learning was used; zero&#13;
Learning                                                      otherwise&#13;
(Interactive)&#13;
&#13;
ACS staff        Participant grade level A, B, C, or D        1 if participant was in grades A-D; zero&#13;
(Grade_AD)                                                    otherwise&#13;
&#13;
Headquarters     Participant based in headquarters (versus    1 if participant is based in&#13;
staff (HQ)       field)                                       headquarters; zero otherwise&#13;
&#13;
Participant      Participants' motivation for taking the      1 if motivation was current or planned&#13;
Motivation       course was to enhance performance in         work assignment; zero otherwise&#13;
(Motivation      current work load&#13;
Work)&#13;
&#13;
Learning Plan    Participants who registered the activity in  1 if participant reported that activity&#13;
(LearnPlan)      their individual learning plans              was registered in learning plan; zero&#13;
                                                              otherwise&#13;
&#13;
Baseline         Activities in the baseline sponsor category, 1 if activity is in baseline sponsor&#13;
Sponsor          rated below Bank benchmarks at both the      category; zero otherwise&#13;
(Sponsor)        respondent and course level (INF &amp; ESSD)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       45&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  ANNEX H: HLM BETWEEN-GROUP MODEL TESTING CROSS-&#13;
LEVEL EFFECTS BETWEEN GRADE LEVEL AND COURSE TOPICS&#13;
&#13;
                                                            Model 1&#13;
&#13;
                       Fixed Effects             Gamma              Reliability&#13;
                                                 Coefficient        estimate&#13;
              Intercept                          0.8246**            .841&#13;
              Sponsor                            -0.0151&#13;
              Participant Motivation (work)      .0248**&#13;
              Based in HQ                        .0056&#13;
              Grade A ­D                                             .195&#13;
              Intercept                          .0092&#13;
              Professional Technical             -.0024&#13;
              Bank Operations                    .0067&#13;
              Behavioral                         -.0026&#13;
              Sponsor                            -.0203&#13;
              Learning Plan                      .0081**&#13;
              Total Participants                 -.0012**&#13;
              Course Days                        .0120**&#13;
              Designed by WB                     .0083&#13;
              Interactive Learning               -.0006&#13;
              Professional Technical             -.0148&#13;
              Bank Operations                    -.0110&#13;
              Behavioral                         .0111&#13;
&#13;
              Training Content                   .3906**             .277&#13;
              Presentation Order                 .1908**             .299&#13;
              Course Materials                   .1181**             .149&#13;
&#13;
              Random Effect                      Standard deviation Variance&#13;
              Mean quality                       .0555**            .00309&#13;
              Grade A-D                          .0329**&#13;
              Training Content                   .1605*&#13;
              Presentation Order                 .1786*&#13;
              Course materials                   .0920*&#13;
                             R                   .07055             .00498&#13;
           **p&lt;.01, *p&lt;.05;&#13;
           bold italics indicates grand mean centered;&#13;
           bold indicates group mean centered&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
46&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX I: KEY DETERMINANTS OF ACTIVITY QUALITY, BY&#13;
                                   SPONSOR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Activity Means&#13;
&#13;
                                                                .&#13;
           Training   Presentation Order Materials UsedTotal No of      Number of Days&#13;
 Sponsor   Content                                     Participants&#13;
&#13;
ACS              4.18              4.27          4.18             14.36           1.91&#13;
&#13;
AFR              4.33              4.17          4.17             23.83           3.33&#13;
&#13;
EAP              4.63              4.50          4.63             19.75           5.00&#13;
&#13;
ECA              4.11              3.78          3.50             22.89           3.00&#13;
&#13;
ESS              4.14              3.83          3.79             26.14           1.26&#13;
&#13;
EXT              4.11              4.16          3.94             21.70           1.25&#13;
&#13;
GSD              4.00              4.00          4.00              9.00           3.00&#13;
&#13;
HDN              4.32              4.17          4.00             26.47           1.00&#13;
&#13;
HRS              4.33              4.00          4.11             16.56           2.33&#13;
&#13;
INF              4.17              4.25          4.36             28.42           1.17&#13;
&#13;
ISG              4.53              4.50          4.38              8.28           1.14&#13;
&#13;
LCR              4.50              4.50          4.25             19.75           3.40&#13;
&#13;
LEG              4.50              4.33          4.33             21.00           1.50&#13;
&#13;
MEN              4.00              4.00          4.00             19.00           5.00&#13;
&#13;
MGT              4.50              4.25          4.25             11.75           2.25&#13;
&#13;
PI               4.38              4.31          4.38             13.31           3.19&#13;
&#13;
PRE              4.38              4.28          4.03             27.13           1.91&#13;
&#13;
SEC              3.50              3.50          3.25             17.50           1.25&#13;
&#13;
WBI              3.00              3.00          3.50             15.50           1.50&#13;
&#13;
OPC              4.11              4.15          4.04             18.44           2.26&#13;
&#13;
ALL              4.25              4.17          4.11             20.77           1.85&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       47&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5546446">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/12/5546446/annual-review-world-bank-staff-learning-fy04
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/12/5546446/annual-review-world-bank-staff-learning-fy04</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/12/5546446/annual-review-world-bank-staff-learning-fy04</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/01/13/000090341_20050113141355/Rendered/INDEX/313190EG051104.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/01/13/000090341_20050113141355/Rendered/PDF/313190EG051104.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-01-13T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2004-12-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Annual review of World Bank staff learning FY04
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This report evaluates staff learning
            activities offered in FY04. Institute Evaluation Group
            (IEG)compiled level one evaluation questionnaires completed
            by 4,750 respondents in 317 staff learning activities. We
            examine the results of these surveys to monitor staff
            training and evaluate which factors can improve it. On the
            whole, training quality ratings increased markedly in FY04
            from FY03. There were significant increases in participant
            ratings in three of the five key dimensions of training
            quality: (a) relevance to the Bank's mission, (b)
            overall quality, and (c) usefulness of training; ratings of
            (d) course applicability to job, and (e) perceived increases
            in knowledge and skills (K&amp;S) remained statistically the
            same in the two fiscal years. However, it is important to
            note that applicability to job dropped below the American
            Society for Training and Development (ASTD) benchmark.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Annual review of World Bank staff learning FY04
        </docna>
        <display_title>Annual review of World Bank staff
            learning FY04</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2004/12/5546446/annual-review-world-bank-staff-learning-fy04</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Teaching and Learning,Girls Education,Educational Sciences,Poverty Monitoring &amp; Analysis,ICT Policy and Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Ling Chard, Cristina</author>
            <author>Arango, Diana J.</author>
            <author>Jha, Shreyasi</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20050113141355</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>WBI evaluation studies ; no. EG05-104</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            attention, class size, course materials,
            curriculum, data collection, Distance Learning, enrollment,
            Human Development, individual learning, instruction,
            instructors, Learning, learning activities, learning
            approach, learning needs, learning opportunities, Learning
            Outcomes, learning programs, MODELING, Motivation, papers,
            perception, training events, Training materials
        </keywd>
        <owner>Office of the Vice President (WBIVP)</owner>
        <repnb>31319</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>