<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                             Documentof&#13;
                                          The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
                                   FOR OFFICIAL USEONLY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      ReportNo. T-7642-PK&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                                ONA&#13;
&#13;
                            A PROPOSEDLOAN OFX 13,107,500,000&#13;
                                    (US$123 millionequivalent)&#13;
&#13;
                                                  TO&#13;
&#13;
                           THE ISLAMIC REPUBLICOF PAKISTAN&#13;
&#13;
                                                FORA&#13;
&#13;
TAUNSA BARRAGEEMERGENCY REHABILITATION&amp; MODERNIZATION&#13;
                                             PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       FEBRUARY 18,2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
AgricultureandRuralDevelopmentSector Unit&#13;
SouthAsia RegionalOffice&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricteddistribution and may be usedby recipientsonly inthe performanceof&#13;
their official duties. Its contentsmay not otherwisebe disclosedwithout World Bankauthorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           CURRENCYAND EQUIVALENTS&#13;
                               (as o f October 31,2004)&#13;
&#13;
                          Currency Unit = Pakistan Rupee (Rs)&#13;
                                Rs59.5 = US$1&#13;
                              US$0.017 = Rs 1&#13;
                           JPY 106.565 = US$ 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    July 1 - June 30&#13;
                                     FISCALYEAR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
CAS      Country Assistance Strategy             N S      NationalShopping&#13;
ECNEC    Executive Committee o f National        M&amp;E      Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
         Economic Council&#13;
EIA      Environmental Impact Assessment         NCB      National Competitive Bidding&#13;
EMP      Environmental Management Plan           NBP      National Bank o f Pakistan&#13;
EPD      Environmental Protection                O&amp;M      Operation &amp; Maintenance&#13;
         Department&#13;
EIRR     Economic Internal Rate o f Return       OMS      Operation, Maintenance &amp;&#13;
                                                          Surveillance&#13;
FD       Finance Department                      PC-1     Planning Commission Proforma 1&#13;
GOP      Govemment o f Pakistan                  P&amp;D      Planning and DevelopmentBoard&#13;
GOPunjab Govemment o f Punjab                    PMO      Project Management Office&#13;
GPN      General Procurement Notice              POE      Panel o f Experts&#13;
IBRD     IntemationalBank for                    PSC      Project Steering Committee&#13;
         Reconstruction &amp; Development&#13;
IA       Implementing Agency                     PWD      Punjab Wildlife Department&#13;
ICB      Intemational Competitive Bidding        RFP      Request for Proposal&#13;
IPD      Irrigation &amp; Power Department           SOE       Statement o f Expenditure&#13;
IRSA     Indus River SystemAuthority&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         MEASURES AND EQUIVALENTS&#13;
&#13;
                    11hectare&#13;
                      acre          -        0.404 hectares&#13;
                                    -&#13;
                                    -        2.47 acres&#13;
                    1 cubic meter =          35.31 cubic feet&#13;
                    1 kilometer     =        0.62 miles&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Vice President:              Praful C. Pate1&#13;
                     Country Director:               John W. Wall&#13;
              Sector ManagerDirector:                Adolfo Brizzi/&#13;
                                                     Constance A. Bernard&#13;
                    Task Team Leader:                Xiaokai Li&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            ..&#13;
                                            11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                               FOROFFICIAL USEONLY&#13;
                                                T-ABLEOFCONTENTS&#13;
                                                                                                                                                Page&#13;
              I BACKGROUNDANDSTRATEGY&#13;
               .                                                                                                                                  1&#13;
&#13;
              I1.   RATIONALE FOR BANK INVOLVEMENT                                            .............................................      2&#13;
                    Rationalefor Bank Involvement                 .......................................................................&#13;
                    Lessons Learned from other Bank-financedEmergencyProjects.....................                                               2&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 3&#13;
&#13;
              I11&#13;
                .   PROJECTDESCRIPTION                      ............................................................................&#13;
                    ProjectObjectives..............................................................................................              3&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 3&#13;
                    ProjectComponents ........................................................................................&#13;
                    Cost Estimatesand Financing...........................................................................                        3&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 4&#13;
&#13;
              IV.   PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
                    ImplementingAgency .......................................................................................&#13;
                                                                          ...............................................................        5&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  5&#13;
                    ProjectManagement Office ............................................................................                         5&#13;
                    ProcurementArrangements .............................................................................                         6&#13;
                    FinancialManagement and Disbursement ........................................................                                 6&#13;
                    Reportingand Monitoring.................................................................................                      7&#13;
&#13;
              V.    PROJECTJUSTIFICATION AND RISKS                                     ...................................................&#13;
                    ProjectJustification ..........................................................................................               7&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  7&#13;
                    Project Risks......................................................................................................           8&#13;
                    Project Sustainability.........................................................................................               8  .&#13;
&#13;
              VI.   ENVIRONMENTAL AND SOCIAL ASPECTS AND SAFEGUARDS                                                                        ......&#13;
                    Overview............................................................................................................          8&#13;
&#13;
                    Projects on InternationalWaterways .................................................................                          8&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  9&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  9&#13;
                    Social Impact .....................................................................................................&#13;
                    Dam Safety ........................................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 10&#13;
&#13;
              VI1.   LOAN CONDITIONS AND COVENANTS                                        .................................................&#13;
                     Effectiveness Conditions...................................................................................                 10&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 10&#13;
                     BoardConditions ..............................................................................................              10&#13;
                     Loan Covenants.................................................................................................             11&#13;
&#13;
              VI11.  READINESS FOR IMPLEMENTATION                                       ...................................................      11&#13;
                     Readiness for Implementation...........................................................................                     11&#13;
                     Compliancewith Bank Policies........................................................................                        11&#13;
&#13;
              APPENDICES&#13;
                    Appendix 1: Indus BasinBarragesand RehabilitationPriorities.......................                                           12&#13;
                    Appendix 2: ProjectDescriptionand Cost Estimates........................................                                     15&#13;
                    Appendix 3: Economic Evaluation....................................................................                          18&#13;
&#13;
                    Appendix 5: FinancialManagement and Disbursement....................................&#13;
                    Appendix 4: ProcurementCapacityAssessment andArrangements ................ 22&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 25&#13;
                    Appendix 6: Environmentaland Social Safeguards..........................................                                     28&#13;
                    Appendix 7: PerformanceMonitoring Indicators..............................................                                   30&#13;
                    Appendix 8: ProjectProcessingSchedule.........................................................                               31&#13;
               MAP IBRD 33568&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricted distribution and may be used by recipients only in&#13;
the performance of their official duties Its contents may not be otherwise disclosed&#13;
without World Bank authorization            .        .&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                          I.BACKGROUNDANDSTRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.       Agriculture i s the backbone o f Pakistan's economy and one o f the key engines of&#13;
economic growth. The sector contributes about 25% o f GDP, employs nearly 50% o f the&#13;
rural labor force, and is responsible, directly or indirectly, for over 60% o f exports.&#13;
Around 80% o f Pakistan's arable lands and 90% o f agricultural output depend on&#13;
irrigation. Over 18 million ha o f land in Pakistan are irrigated from the Indus River and&#13;
its tributaries.&#13;
&#13;
2.       Barrages in the Indus Basin are vital parts o f Pakistan's irrigation network&#13;
(Appendix 1). Their main purpose i s to, divert water from the rivers into canals serving&#13;
vast areas o f irrigated land. Some o f the newer barrages also divert water into link canals&#13;
that join the main rivers o f the IndusBasin, namely, the Indus, Jhelum, Chenab, Ravi and&#13;
Sutlej. Barrages also serve as road and rail bridges and crossings for oil, gas, and power&#13;
transmission lines. Many o f the older barrages built 50 to 100 years ago, in Punjab are in&#13;
need o f rehabilitation. Most o f the problems identified stemfrom design and construction&#13;
defects, aging and changes in hydrological conditions. Some o f them require urgent&#13;
remedial measures to avoid severe economic and social impacts on the lives o f millions&#13;
o f poor farm families through interruption of irrigation on millions o f acres o f irrigated&#13;
land. The newer barrages built as a part o f the Indus Basin Project in the 1960s are&#13;
reportedto be ingood condition.&#13;
&#13;
3.       The main problem encountered inthe older barrages i s erosion at the downstream&#13;
toe, due inpart to changes in river hydrology. Another problem i s "piping," that occurs&#13;
when a loss o f integrity inthe downstream floor causes a loss o f soil from the foundation.&#13;
Gates and hoists are also in most cases in need o f renovation. River training works&#13;
upstream o f the barrages also need some improvement. These problems are present in&#13;
varying degrees o f severity at all o f the older barrages.&#13;
&#13;
4.       The Taunsa Barrage on the River Indus, completed in 1958, has been identified as&#13;
the barrage with the highestpriority for rehabilitation (Appendix 1).The barrage diverts a&#13;
part o f the Indus flow to two large canal commands with an irrigated area o f 2 million&#13;
acres and to other large areas served by the Taunsa -Panjnad Link Canal. This link canal&#13;
was built in the 1960's to transfer water from the Industo areas served by two rivers, the&#13;
Ravi and the Sutlej that became controlled by India under the terms of the 1960 Indus&#13;
Waters Treaty.&#13;
&#13;
5.       At Taunsa, there is clear evidence o f distress, such as severe erosion of the&#13;
downstream floor and loss o f foundation material. In the event o f a major flood, the&#13;
downstream floor, that i s already damaged, could be underminedand this could cause a&#13;
failure o f the barrage at any time. The barrage would not then be able to maintain the&#13;
water at the level needed to supply the irrigation canals. Floods on the Indus occur&#13;
during the main season for crop irrigation. The flow inthe river would then be too high&#13;
to allow a temporary earth and rock fill dam to be built as a temporary closure.&#13;
Therefore, all irrigated crops would fail because the commanded area has very low&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rainfall. There i s no way o f telling when or how the Taunsa Barrage might fail. But the&#13;
owner o f the barrage and the consultants are o f the view that the weaknesses are so&#13;
serious that failure could conceivably occur in the near future. Therefore, the first option&#13;
poses an unacceptable risk to the livelihoods o f millions o f farm families in the area&#13;
served by the barrage.&#13;
&#13;
6.      The government strategy has been to employ consulting firms, experienced in&#13;
barrage design, to review the structural and hydraulic conditions o f six existing barrages&#13;
built between 1890 and 1958, to prioritize the rehabilitation and undertake rehabilitation&#13;
in the order o f urgency. The priority for rehabilitation depends on a number of factors&#13;
(Annex 1). First, i s the severity o f the current problems. Second, i s the extent to which&#13;
failure would cause agricultural and other economic and social losses. Third, i s the&#13;
difficulty that would be met in executing temporary measures to restore service. Failure&#13;
would involve collapse o f a number o f the 50-60 bays in a barrage; it would not result in&#13;
total collapse o f the whole structure. Therefore, the response to a failure would be to&#13;
build a temporary dam to close the breach. On the Indus, this would be more difficult&#13;
than on other rivers in the Indus Basin because the Indus has a high flow throughout the&#13;
year.The Taunsa and Jinnah Barrages on the Indus also suffer from a drop in the&#13;
downstream river levels due to a change in regime caused by sediment deposition in the&#13;
upstream dam at Tarbela. Ofthe two barrages, Taunsa has the most serious weaknesses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    11. RATIONALEFORBANKINVOLVEMENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Rationale for Bank Involvement&#13;
&#13;
7.      In view o f the severe conditions o f Taunsa Barrage proved by the in-depth&#13;
investigation and studies and review o f the independent panel o f experts, it was decided&#13;
to follow the Bank's emergency operations procedures (OP/BP 8.50), in response to the&#13;
government's request for urgent actions. Applying the emergency procedures, provides&#13;
both the government and the Bank the possibility to prepare and process the project to&#13;
meet the very tight schedule for awarding the main contract and starting preparatory&#13;
implementation work before the 2005 flood season, so that the main construction and&#13;
repair work could start immediately after the flood season ends. Consequently, time i s&#13;
gained in helping prevent a potentially prominent disastrous barrage failure. Bank&#13;
involvement would ensure timely and adequate financing that might not otherwise be&#13;
available to carry out an emergency project.&#13;
&#13;
8.      This is consistent with the current country assistance strategy for Pakistan that&#13;
emphasizes improvements in rural infrastructures for poverty reduction and provision o f&#13;
reliable and safe water for domestic and productive purposes. The Bank has a long&#13;
history o f operations in Pakistan that began with its support for the Indus Basin Waters&#13;
Treaty between Pakistan and India. The Bank had the leading role to secure finance and&#13;
manage the Indus Basin Project (IBP). The IBP implemented a vast system o f works to&#13;
transfer water from the western rivers o f the Basin to the areas inPakistan supplied by the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
eastern rivers whose waters were allocated to India. Since then the Bank has financed&#13;
numerous major water and power projects often inpartnership with other lenders.&#13;
&#13;
9.      The Bank's involvement will also help ensure that: (i) systematic approach i s&#13;
                                                                   a&#13;
adopted inthe design o f rehabilitationprojects for the Taunsa Barrage and other barrages;&#13;
(ii) environmentalandsocialconcernsareproperlyaddressed;(iii) projectworks&#13;
    any                                                                   the&#13;
and facilities are procured and constructed with good quality, within the budget, and on&#13;
schedule; and (iv) the operation and maintenance will be upgraded and strengthened as a&#13;
model for safe and sustainable use o f other Punjab barrages.&#13;
&#13;
10.     LessonsLearnedfrom other Bank-financedEmergencyProjects.                       The&#13;
project design draws on the lessons learned from emergency operations financed by the&#13;
Bank in and outside Pakistan, as highlighted in the project Implementation Reports and&#13;
OED's evaluation reports. These lessons include: (i)   emergency loans should be simple in&#13;
design and consistent with the Borrower's institutional capacity to prepare and implement&#13;
projects; (ii)emergency loans should have no policy refo'rms or similar conditions for&#13;
disbursement; (iii)the speed o f appraisal and implementation is critical to project&#13;
success; (iii) procurement needs to be flexible and procurement process should start&#13;
early, and retroactive financing can be very helpful to ensure an early project startup; and&#13;
(vi) strong government leadership and a properly staffed Project Management Office are&#13;
indispensable to effective project preparation and implementation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              111.   PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ProjectObjectives&#13;
&#13;
11.     The main objectives o f the Project are: (a) to take urgent steps to prevent the&#13;
failure o f the Taunsa Barrage which provides irrigation for two million acres and&#13;
drinkingwater to several million farmers inthe rural areas o f Southern Punjab; and (b) to&#13;
prepare for similar steps with respect to other existing barrages inPunjab. The objectives&#13;
will be achieved through: (i)    rehabilitating and strengthening the Taunsa Barrage and&#13;
associated structures; (ii) renovation and modernizationo f gates, hoists and operating and&#13;
control facilities;   (iii)improving operation and maintenance             capability;   and&#13;
(iv) rehabilitation design studies for other barrages inPunjab.&#13;
&#13;
ProjectComponents&#13;
&#13;
12.     The Project includes the following components (Appendix 2):&#13;
&#13;
ComponentA.       Rehabilitation and Strengthening Works&#13;
&#13;
The main works include: (a) a 4,300 feet long subsidiary weir located about 1,000 feet&#13;
downstream o f the barrage to raise the tail water level and ensure proper energy&#13;
dissipation; (b) repair o f the barrage floor by removal o f weak concrete and replacement&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
with a new layer o f concrete, and grouting to seal joints and fill voids inthe foundation;&#13;
(c) a silt excluder at the canal intake on the right bank; and (d) upgrading the internal&#13;
monitoring system o f the barrage structure. This will lead to a secure barrage structure&#13;
with effective energy dissipation and a functional monitoring and flow measurement&#13;
system'. The operating manual will be improved and brought up to date.&#13;
&#13;
Component B.            Renovation of Gates and Hoists and Strengthening 0 &amp; A4Facilities&#13;
&#13;
This involves: (i)        renovation o f the barrage gates and hoists and improvement in the&#13;
operating and control system for the barrage and canal head-works, including necessary&#13;
facilities to enhance the flow measurement in existence; and (ii)procurement o f&#13;
necessary equipment for operation and maintenance. This component will lead to&#13;
upgrading o f the operating facilities with higher level o f automation through remote&#13;
control and operation &amp; maintenance equipment.&#13;
&#13;
Component C.             Consulting Services and Implementation Support&#13;
&#13;
This component covers: (i)consulting services for construction supervision at Taunsa&#13;
Barrage; (ii)consulting services for preparation o f designs for other Punjab barrages;&#13;
(iii)maintainingaindependentpanelofexperts fortechnicaldesignandsafetyreview,&#13;
and construction quality enhancement; and (iv) incremental administration and operating&#13;
costs o f the Project Management Office (PMO) and the PSC Secretariat.&#13;
&#13;
The Project is expected to start inApril, 2005 and be completed by June 30, 2008.&#13;
&#13;
Cost Estimatesand Financing&#13;
&#13;
13.       The following is a summary o f the estimated project costs and financing&#13;
arrangement. More details are given in Appendix 2. Physical contingencies are 10% o f&#13;
the works and price contingencies are based on annual price escalation o f 3.9%. A Bank&#13;
Loan of US$123 million equivalent will finance 92% of the project cost. Retroactive&#13;
financing in an aggregate amount not exceeding the equivalent o f US$2 million, o f&#13;
eligible expenditures occurred before loan signing but after March 31,2004.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1         IRSA has installed gate opening and water level sensors at many of the barrages and canal headworks along&#13;
the Indus Rivers. The discharges are derived from the water level and gate opening data that are periodically calibrated&#13;
by actual flow measurements. The flow data is transmitted inreal time through satellite to several hubs and is expected&#13;
to be accessible soon through the intemet. The installation contractor is training IRSA staff inoperation o f the system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                      Component&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      1. Rehabilitation &amp; Strengthening Works    72.6   90     65.3     53.1    7.3&#13;
      2. Gates, Hoists and O$MEquipment          41.9   90     38.0     30.8    3.9&#13;
      3. ConsultingServices and Implementation   8.9    100     8.9     7.2      0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       on IBRDLoan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             IV. PROJECTIMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ImplementingAgency&#13;
&#13;
14.     The Irrigation and Power Department o f the Government o f Punjab (IPD) will be&#13;
the implementing agency. A Project Steering Committee (PSC) chaired by the Chairman&#13;
P&amp;D with the Secretaries o f IPD and Finance and Environmental Protection Departments&#13;
as its members, has been setup to provide policy guidance and inter-agency coordination&#13;
for the project. An independent Panel o f Experts (POE) composed o f experienced&#13;
international and national experts has been appointed.      The POE has already been&#13;
convened to review the feasibility study for the Taunsa barrage and will be convened&#13;
from time to time as needed during the course o f project implementation to advise the&#13;
IPD on technical and construction issues.&#13;
&#13;
Project Management Office&#13;
&#13;
15.     A Project Management Office (PMO), headed by a Project Director, has been set&#13;
up inIPD comprising the four units described below. Key specialists have beenrecruited&#13;
and the units have largely been staffed with qualified personnel. A Project Management&#13;
&amp; Procurement Unit will be responsible for the overall management of the project&#13;
implementation. It will manage the entire procurement process, monitor and evaluate&#13;
project progress and performance, liaise with the Bank and be responsible for preparing&#13;
annual programs and implementation reporting. An Engineering Unit will oversee the&#13;
work o f the consultants on design and construction supervision matters. A Financial&#13;
Management Unit will be responsible for all project-related financial management,&#13;
disbursement and financial management reporting. And, an Environmental Unit will&#13;
supervise compliance with the Environmental Management Plan. For contractual&#13;
purposes, the Project Director will serve as the Employer, and the supervising consultant&#13;
will serve as the Engineer for construction supervision. At the site, a Resident Engineer,&#13;
appointed by the consultant, with a team o f specialists and inspectors will supervise the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contractor. The head o f the Engineering Unit will spend about half o f his time at the site&#13;
to provide coordination between the PMO and the supervising consultant.&#13;
&#13;
ProcurementArrangements&#13;
&#13;
16.      All repairs to the barrage structure andthe construction o fthe subsidiary weir will&#13;
be executed under a single civil works contract. Renovation o f the gates and hoists will&#13;
be executed under another contract. Both contracts will be awarded to pre-qualified&#13;
bidders through ICB according to the Bank procurement guidelines. Works costing less&#13;
than US$2 million and US$lOO,OOO          per contract will be procured through National&#13;
Competitive Bidding and Shopping (Quotation) respectively. Office and field equipment&#13;
and vehicles for the PMO will be procured through shopping procedures. Consulting&#13;
services for detailed designs o f the other Punjab barrages will be procured through&#13;
competitive bidding procedures following the Bank Guidelines for Selection and&#13;
Employment o f Consultants by World Bank Borrowers, dated May 2004.&#13;
&#13;
FinancialManagementandDisbursement&#13;
&#13;
17.      The project works will be executed under two large works contracts that will be&#13;
unit price contracts. Disbursement to the contractors will be against contractors' claims&#13;
certified by the Resident Engineer and submitted to the PMO. Disbursement for&#13;
consultants will be against payment claims reviewed and verified by the PMO. A Special&#13;
Account o f US$7,500,000 will be established by the PMO for the IBRD Loan with the&#13;
National Bank o f Pakistan (NBP). The PMO will also establish a `Rupee Assignment&#13;
Account' with the National Bank o f Pakistan for government funds for the project.&#13;
&#13;
18       Financial management will be carried out by two professionally qualified staff o f&#13;
the PMO recruited on contracts, supported by the two seconded government accounting&#13;
personnel. A financial management manual would be prepared following the Bank's&#13;
financial management guidelines. The project shall adopt cash basis accounting for&#13;
financial reporting. However, it would be requiredto provide abridgednotes definingthe&#13;
liabilities it has accrued at each reporting period as well as the assets it has acquired for&#13;
internal management and project monitoring. The PMO shall render quarterly Financial&#13;
Monitoring Reports (FMRs) to the Bank, the IPD and its management within 45 days&#13;
after the end o f each quarter. The FMRs shall include statements such as: `sources and&#13;
uses of funds', `uses o f funds according to project categories and components', `special&#13;
accounts reconciliation' and `financial vs. physical progress'.&#13;
&#13;
19.       Annual external audit o f the project will be undertaken by the Auditor General o f&#13;
Pakistan under agreed terms o f reference (to be submitted to the DGAudit by the Finance&#13;
Department after clearing with the Bank), and the audited financial statements together&#13;
with the audit report shall be furnished to the Bank within six months o f the end o f each&#13;
fiscal year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Reporting and Monitoring&#13;
&#13;
20.      The format, contents and reporting frequency o f project progress and financial&#13;
statements have been discussed and agreed with the IPD. The project's financial and&#13;
progress reports, together with procurement and disbursement documents, will form the&#13;
basis for routine monitoring o f physical and financial progress. The PMO will carry out&#13;
quarterly implementation performance review and evaluation, the result o f which will be&#13;
furnished to the Bank for review within a month thereafter. A Mid-Term Review o f&#13;
project implementation will be undertakenby December 31,2006 and any changes to the&#13;
Project will be reviewed and agreed by the Bank. The PMO will be responsible, in&#13;
cooperation with the Resident Engineer, for monitoring the compliance o f Environmental&#13;
Management Plan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    V.      PROJECTJUSTIFICATIONAND RISKS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Project Justification&#13;
&#13;
21.      If Taunsa Barrage were to fail it would probably be during the summer flood&#13;
season. With the huge summer flow in the Indus it would than be impossible to build a&#13;
temporary dam to maintain the pool level and continue to serve the more than 2 million&#13;
acres o f irrigated land inthe summer and in the next dry season. The summer and winter&#13;
crops are almost entirely dependent on irrigation as the annual rainfall is about 150").&#13;
So a failure would mean huge agricultural losses estimated to be about $300 million&#13;
(Appendix 3).      In addition there would be the cost of temporary repairs to restore&#13;
irrigation service and then the cost o f full rehabilitation. The question i s when could this&#13;
failure happen? If it i s assumed to happen some years inthe future, the ERR i s arrived at&#13;
by treating the losses avoided as a benefit to be measured against the cost o f barrage&#13;
rehabilitation starting in2005. If,for example, the loss i s assumed to happen 5 years from&#13;
now, the EIRR is 42%, and if 10 years from now the EIRR would be 17%. Under the&#13;
scenario o f a 10% cost increase and 10% benefit decrease assuming failure ten years from&#13;
now the Project i s still sound economically.&#13;
&#13;
22.      The major benefits o f the Project stem from securing irrigation o f the cultivated&#13;
lands in the command areas o f over 2 million acres in the two canal commands o f&#13;
Muzaffargarh and Dera Ghazi Khan, and through the Taunsa-Panjnad Link Canal to&#13;
supplement water supply to Panjnad Headworks canals. Other benefits from the&#13;
rehabilitation o f the barrage include: (a) long-term and effective functioning o f the&#13;
critical oil and gas pipelines, and telephone lines; and (b) ensuring continued availability&#13;
o f vital rail and road links o f strategic importance between the Punjab and the Sindh and&#13;
Balochistan provinces.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ProjectRisks&#13;
&#13;
23.     Most o f the emergency projects financed by the Bank in the past have been to&#13;
assist restoration o f infrastructure after natural disasters or conflicts. Typically, such&#13;
projects have had to implement a wide variety o f infrastructure over large areas through a&#13;
number of institutions. Incontrast, this Project is confined to a single site and involves&#13;
clearly defined works that have been designed in detail. However, timely procurement&#13;
will be crucial in view o f the emergency nature o f the Project. Project implementation&#13;
may be delayed because o f lack o f counterpart funds and delays inprocurement. Inorder&#13;
to achieve speedy project implementation it has been agreed to finance a major&#13;
proportion o f the investment costs from the Bank Loan. The Government has established&#13;
a procurement and contract management unit together with engineering, environment and&#13;
financial management units in the PMO, to ensure adequate capacity inprocurement and&#13;
other key fields by recruiting experienced specialists in procurement and other fields on&#13;
fixed-term contracts at competitive salaries. The Project will finance the cost o f these&#13;
experts. Also a project launch workshop will be organized to train PMO and consultant&#13;
staff in project management and monitoring, especially on procurement, disbursement&#13;
and financial management.&#13;
&#13;
24.     During construction, there is a chance o f setbacks from high floods that could&#13;
under the worst circumstances breach cofferdam that protects the work area for the&#13;
subsidiary weir. The contractor's plans for cofferdam design and construction will be&#13;
closely reviewedby the supervision consultants and the POE.&#13;
&#13;
ProjectSustainability&#13;
&#13;
25.     Taunsa Barrage has been in service for more than 50 years, despite initial design&#13;
errors and construction defects. The proposed rehabilitation will eliminate possible&#13;
sources of failure and give the structure a long life. Instruments will be installed to&#13;
monitor the performance o f the barrage structures and its foundations. In addition, the&#13;
project will help strengthen operation and maintenance through staff training, upgrading&#13;
o f the 0 &amp; M Manual including safety management and preparedness planning, and&#13;
automation o f the gate control system. In addition, assurance was obtained from the&#13;
government at negotiations that sufficient funds would be made available by the&#13;
government for the 0 &amp; Mo f Taunsa Barrage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     VI. ENVIRONMENTAL AND SOCIAL ASPECTSAND SAFEGUARDS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overview&#13;
&#13;
26.     This project is processed as an environmental category B emergency intervention.&#13;
The applicable safeguard policies are: (i)Environmental Assessment (OP/BP/GP 4.0 1);&#13;
(ii) Habitats(OP/BP 4.04); (iii) ofDams(OP/BP4.37); and(iv)Projects&#13;
    Natural                                Safety&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
on International Waterways (OP/BP 7.50). The EINEMPwas cleared by the Bank before&#13;
Loan negotiations.&#13;
&#13;
27.     The key safeguard policy issues raised by the project are: (i)the possible&#13;
environmental and social impacts o f any upstream or downstream changes to the&#13;
hydrological regime once the rehabilitation is completed; and (ii)management o f&#13;
constructionphase environmental and social impacts.&#13;
&#13;
28.     The pond area upstream o f the Taunsa Barrage was designated a Ramsar site in&#13;
1996. N o significant environmental or social impacts are anticipated as a result o f the&#13;
rehabilitation o f the barrage, as water levels will remain within the current seasonal&#13;
ranges. A detailed EMP has been prepared to mitigate the possible construction phase&#13;
impacts, and environmental monitoring will be carried out by the PMO's environmental&#13;
unitincollaborationwith independent thirdparties.&#13;
&#13;
29.     Regarding dam safety, since the barrage is not a water impounding structure,&#13;
negligible incremental inundation damage would occur in the case o f failure. However,&#13;
given the severity o f the economic impacts that failure would cause, the task team&#13;
decided to make use o f the provisions o f OP 4.37 inthe preparation o f the project.&#13;
&#13;
30.     A public hearingto discuss the draft EIA was heldinDera Ghazi Khan on August&#13;
23, 2004. The EIA has been made publicly available at the office o f the District Officer&#13;
(Environmental) in Dera Ghazi Khan, in the Punjab Public Library, Lahore, and in the&#13;
InfoShop. The EIA has been approved by both the Punjab Environmental Protection&#13;
Department and the Punjab Wildlife Department. More detailed discussions are in&#13;
Appendix 6.&#13;
&#13;
Projects on International Waterways&#13;
&#13;
31.     Since the Project i s to be carried out on irrigation structure that diverts water from&#13;
the Indus River - an international waterway - OP 7.50 is triggered. However, the Project&#13;
i s essentially to rehabilitate an existing structure, and the Project works and activities are&#13;
not expected to exceed the original scheme, or change its nature, or so alter or expand its&#13;
scope or extent as to make it appear a new or different scheme. Giventhe nature o f these&#13;
works, the Project will not (a) adversely affect the quality or quantity o f water flows to&#13;
other riparians, or (b) adversely affect other riparians' water use. Also, the Project will not&#13;
cause interference with the waters o f any o f the rivers covered by the India-Pakistan&#13;
Indus Waters Treaty o f 1960 and will not affect the other riparian materially. Therefore,&#13;
the requirement o fnotification o f other riparians under OP 7.50 was waived.&#13;
&#13;
Dam Safety&#13;
&#13;
32.     Neither Taunsa nor any o f the other Punjab barrages for which rehabilitation&#13;
designs are to be prepared under the Project can be classified as a dam, Le. a water&#13;
impounding structure. However, given the severity o f the impacts that failure o f any o f&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the barrages would cause, the project team decided to make use o f the provisions o f OP&#13;
4.37 "Safety o f Dam' inthe preparationo f the project.&#13;
&#13;
33.     The implementing agency has appointed an independent panel o f experts (POE)&#13;
to review the design, implementation progress at critical stages, and advise on the long&#13;
term operation o f the rehabilitated works. The panel i s composed o f three experts, two&#13;
national and one international. A minimum o f three visits o f about a week each in the&#13;
duration o f the project will be organized.&#13;
&#13;
34.     The information provided by the Irrigation and Power Department (IPD) o f&#13;
GOPunjab indicates that Taunsa barrage needs urgent and major remedial measures. The&#13;
likelihood of failure o f some important components o f the structure, and the potential&#13;
consequences are such as to require emergency intervention. Other barrages are also in&#13;
need o f rehabilitation. An assessment o f priorities for rehabilitation i s presented in&#13;
Appendix 1.&#13;
&#13;
35.     An Emergency Preparedness Plan (EPP) will be included inthe OMS Manual of&#13;
the Barrage. The EPP will specify the actors and actions inrelation to the following chain&#13;
o f tasks: (a) detection and classification o f any potential problem at the barrage site;&#13;
(b) decision to notify and warn competent authorities; and (c) mobilization o f response&#13;
unitswhenneeded.&#13;
&#13;
Social Impacts&#13;
&#13;
36.     The primary purpose o f the Project i s to prevent failure o f Taunsa Barrage and&#13;
thus eliminate the possibility o f at least a year-long interruption inthe supply o f water to&#13;
more than two million people who depend on irrigation for their livelihood. N o&#13;
resettlement i s required for the rehabilitation o f the barrage or the contractor's facilities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     VII.     LOANCONDITIONS AND COVENANTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
EffectivenessConditions&#13;
&#13;
37.     Standard.&#13;
&#13;
Board Conditions&#13;
&#13;
38.     The conditions for Board include: (i)approval by GOP and Punjab o f the&#13;
negotiateddraft LoanAgreement and Project Agreement; (ii)          receipt o f the bidevaluation&#13;
report for the lStICB works contract by the Bank; (iii) confirmation o f the Project&#13;
                                                            GOP's&#13;
PC-1 approval by ECNEC; and (iv) evidence that the implementation o f agreed Financial&#13;
Management Action Planhas been completed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LoanCovenants&#13;
&#13;
39.    The mainlegal covenants are as follows:&#13;
&#13;
(i) PunjabwillmaintainaProjectSteeringCommittee(PSC), aPanelofExperts&#13;
(POE) and a Project Management Office (PMO) throughout Project implementation.&#13;
&#13;
(ii)   Punjab will each year prepare a detailed annual work plan, including a work&#13;
program and budget, for the Project.&#13;
&#13;
(iii)  Punjab will prepare an Operation, Maintenance and Surveillance (OMS) Manual ,&#13;
and, on the basis thereof, an Operation and Maintenance (O&amp;M) financing plan, all for&#13;
Taunsa Barrage.&#13;
&#13;
(iv)   Punjab will implement the Environment Management Plan (EMP), and make&#13;
suitable arrangements for keeping the same under constant monitoring, and will provide&#13;
the Bank with semi-annual Environmental Monitoring Reports.&#13;
&#13;
(v)    Punjab will fumishto the Bank quarterly Financial Monitoring Reports (FMRs)&#13;
as well as semi-annually progress reports inrespect o fthe Project, and, jointly with the&#13;
Bank, conduct a mid-term review o f the Project, all inaccordance with agreed indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       VIII. READINESSFORIMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Readinessfor Implementation&#13;
&#13;
40.    The engineering design documents for the first year's activities are complete and&#13;
ready for the start o f project implementation.&#13;
&#13;
41.    The annual work plan and procurement documents for the first year's activities&#13;
are complete and ready for the start o f project implementation.&#13;
&#13;
Compliancewith BankPolicies&#13;
&#13;
42.    This project complies with all applicable Bank policies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                 Appendix 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                IndusBasinBarragesandRehabilitationPriorities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IndusRiver Barrages&#13;
&#13;
Irrigation has been carried out for centuries in the Indus Basin. Until the advent o f&#13;
barrages, irrigation was through inundation canals that drew water from the rivers only&#13;
when water levels were high during the flood season (July to September). To overcome&#13;
this problem, a number ofbarrages were builtbetween 1875 and 1940to divert water into&#13;
the canals at all stages o f flow throughout the year. At the same time the new canals were&#13;
built and extended to create one o f the world's largest irrigation systems. After&#13;
Independence, Pakistan built several new barrages and then in 1960 the signing o f the&#13;
Indus Water Treaty led to the construction o f six new barrages to transfer water from the&#13;
western to the eastern rivers as parts o f the IndusBasin Project. The barrages o f the Indus&#13;
Basin are listed inTable 1.1.&#13;
&#13;
A typical barrage consists of a concrete weir divided into 40 to 60 bays, each 60 ft wide&#13;
controlled by 20 ft high gates. The total width o f a barrage between abutments can be&#13;
over 4,000 ft. A barrage forms a shallow reservoir with a pool level about 20 ft above the&#13;
river bed. The early structures were simple concrete weirs with steel flap gates that could&#13;
be raised or lowered as needed. These were followed by larger more durable structures.&#13;
Inthe Indus Basin, a barrage is a concrete structure founded on alluvial sands and silts.&#13;
Therefore, cut-off walls, usually several rows o f sheet piles, are needed to prevent&#13;
seepage through the foundation and to reduce uplift pressures under the downstream&#13;
floor.&#13;
&#13;
A barrage has also to be designedto pass safely a flood that inthe case o f most barrages&#13;
in the IndusBasin is on the order o f one million cubic feet per second. The crest of the&#13;
weir i s set a level that raises the upstream flood level by about 3 ft above the downstream&#13;
level (this i s called the afflux). Betweenthe crest and the horizontal downstream floor is a&#13;
sloping section called the glacis. The horizontal downstream floor i s protected at the toe&#13;
by concrete blocks, and heavy rock armor. A concrete apron on the upstream side ties&#13;
into the upstream sheet pile cutoff. The normal operating pool level upstream of a barrage&#13;
is usually about the maximum flood level in the absence o f a barrage Embankments&#13;
(marginal bunds) extend upstream o f the barrage to contain the pool. At the barrage, rock&#13;
protected guide banks prevent the river outflanking the barrage.&#13;
&#13;
Duringhighflows, a very large volume o f water falls through a height o f around 3-5 ft.&#13;
The floor below the glacis, known as the stilling basin, has to be set low enough so that a&#13;
standing wave, or hydraulic jump, forms just downstream o f the glacis.&#13;
&#13;
There are several problems that can threaten a barrage structure. There can be a loss o f&#13;
foundation material ifconstructionjoints inthe floor are not sealed; this can, inthe worst&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
case, cause one or more bays to collapse. A serious problem arises if the downstream&#13;
water level for the design flood i s lower than the level used in the designing the&#13;
downstream floor. This can happen where the level originally assumed was inerror (as in&#13;
the case o f Taunsa), or where changes in a river's sediment regime cause a drop in level&#13;
(retrogression).&#13;
&#13;
Priorities for Rehabilitation&#13;
&#13;
Of the structures listed in Table 1.1, Taunsa, Jinnah, Balloki, Suleimanki, and Islam&#13;
Barrages and the Khanki Weir have been found to have structural and hydraulic&#13;
problems. The priority depends to a large extent on the nature o f possible failure, and to&#13;
what extent temporary measures can be employed to restore a barrage's ability to meet&#13;
the full demands o f its related canals.&#13;
&#13;
As regards the Punjab Barrages, there is a strong casethat Taunsa and Jinnah should have&#13;
the highest priority. As explained below the consequences and chances o f damage to the&#13;
various barrages are quite different. In some cases temporary measures could restore&#13;
irrigation a few weeks after a failure, but at Taunsa and Jinnah the huge annual flow&#13;
would make temporary repairs impossible untilwell into the following dry season.&#13;
&#13;
Khanki on the Chenab is an old weir carrying "shutters." These are steel panels hinged at&#13;
the weir crest. Ifa piece o f the structure gets destroyed in a flood, a temporary fix after&#13;
the flood has passed would be a low embankment, or gabions, or some other way o f&#13;
pluggingthe hole. Inthe dry season, a more permanent fix could be made. Ifirrigation is&#13;
interrupted for a month in the summer, it would lower the crop yields but not cause the&#13;
whole crop to be lost on the one million acres o f the Lower Chenab command. The dry&#13;
season irrigation could be assured by a temporary closure while reconstruction proceeds.&#13;
&#13;
Suleimanki and Islam on the Sutlej is on a river with not much flow except during rare&#13;
floods. A failure o f a number o f bays could be handled as described above, but it would&#13;
be easier to do a temporary fix as most o f the time the Sutlej i s dry because India has full&#13;
use o f it. A wet season flood is less likely than on the Chenab. The barrage at Islam&#13;
actually failed during a major flood inthe early 1950s because o f retrogression caused by&#13;
upstream dams.&#13;
&#13;
Balloki on the Ravi: The situation at Balloki is very similar to Suleimanki and Islam.&#13;
&#13;
Jinnah and Taunsa on the Indus pass a huge flow every year, and sometimes a major&#13;
flood. Ifsome bays collapse due to downstream erosion, it could be a progressive failure.&#13;
It would also be very difficult to make a temporary fix in the summer or even in the&#13;
winter. The areas served have less than six inches o f rainfall so the agricultural impact&#13;
would be very serious. Taunsa barrage i s in emergency condition, in the sense that&#13;
continued safe operation cannot be predictedunder the circumstances.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                              Table 1.1 Indus Basin Barra-&#13;
&#13;
                                         Year of      I&#13;
                         River                          Area Served          LinkCanal&#13;
                                      Completion      1  (mil. acres)           Served&#13;
                                                                         ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1PUNJABBARRAGES&#13;
I     Jinnah             Indus   1        1946        1     1.912     I&#13;
      Chasma             Indus            1971                              Chasma-Jhelum   Part of IBP&#13;
      Taunsa             Indus            1958              2.225           Taunsa-Panjnad  Part of IBP&#13;
       Rasul             Jhelum  I        1967              1.518           Rasul-Qadirabad Part of IBP*&#13;
                         Chenab  I        1971              2.597            Marala Ravi    Out of IBP&#13;
I     Khanki             Chenab  I        1892        1     3.054        I&#13;
     Qadirabad                                                                              Partof IBP&#13;
&#13;
      Trimmu             Chenab           1938              1.462&#13;
                         Chenab           1932              1.590           Trimmu-Sidhnai  Part of IBP&#13;
&#13;
      Balloki             Ravi            1967              2.282              Balloki-&#13;
                                                                               Suleimanki&#13;
I     Sidhnai             Ravi   I        1965        I     1.766        I                  Part of IBP*&#13;
     Suleimanki          Sutlej           1926              2.529&#13;
                         Sutlej           1927                0.5           Sidhnai-Mailsi  Part of IBP&#13;
&#13;
   Mailsi Siphon         Sutlej           1965                                  Mailsi-&#13;
                                                                              Bahawalpur    Part of IBP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 SINDHBARRAGES&#13;
&#13;
                         Indus            1963               2.89&#13;
~&#13;
I&#13;
i     Sukkur             Indus   II       1932        II    7.544         1I&#13;
       Kotri             Indus   I        1956              2.805&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  * These barrages replaced weirs built inthe lgthcentury; IBP=Indus Basin Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                Appendix 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Project Descriptionand CostEstimates&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BasicFeaturesof TaunsaBarrage&#13;
&#13;
The Taunsa Barrage spans the River Indus about 60 miles from the city o f Multan inthe&#13;
southern part o f the Punjab. It has 64, 60 ft wide bays and has a length between&#13;
abutments o f 4,200 feet and was completed in 1958. The barrage diverts water to Dera&#13;
Ghazi Khan Canal on the right bank serving 1,285,000 acres o f irrigated land and the&#13;
Muzaffargarh Canal on the left bank serving 940,000 acres of irrigated land. It also&#13;
serves the Taunsa-Panjnad Link Canal built in 1966 to divert Indus water to the lands&#13;
formerly irrigated from the rivers Ravi and Sutlej. These rivers came under the control o f&#13;
India under the terms o f the 1959 Indus Water Treaty. In addition to the supply of&#13;
irrigation water, the canals bringdrinkingwater to millions o fpeople inan area where the&#13;
annual rainfall i s around six inches. The barrage also carries a road bridge, oil and gas&#13;
pipelines, and a power transmission line.&#13;
&#13;
Diagnosisof Problems&#13;
&#13;
A detailed inspection o f the barrage by the consultants and the barrage's operating and&#13;
maintenance staff has identified numerous structural weaknesses and an unstable&#13;
hydraulic situation on the downstream floor. Work on Taunsa Barrage began soon after&#13;
Pakistan's independence in 1947 when the new nation's financial resources were low and&#13;
construction funds were hardto come by. This ledto short cuts inquality to save money.&#13;
It is also now evident that the assumed level o fthe highflood tailwater level is lower than&#13;
assumed inthe design.&#13;
&#13;
These problems show up in several ways. Many o f the joints in the downstream floor&#13;
were not sealed. When the head across the barrage i s high inthe dry season, sand and silt&#13;
i s washed out by the high pressure under the floor. This piping o f the foundation could&#13;
eventually lead to collapse of parts of the floor. A one foot layer o f concrete was not&#13;
anchored to the underlying concrete and large areas have been ripped loose by high&#13;
velocity flow across the floor.&#13;
&#13;
The most serious threat to Taunsa Barrage has to do with deficiencies in hydraulic&#13;
design. The actual tail-water level is about three feet lower than the level assumed inthe&#13;
design, and therefore the hydraulic jump does not form in the stilling basin. This&#13;
contributes to the damage to the surface concrete o f the stilling basin. Also, many impact&#13;
blocks designed to help in energy dissipation have been dislodged. Inadequate energy&#13;
dissipation has also caused damage to the concrete blocks and flexible apron at&#13;
downstream end o f the floor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The barrage gates are in need o f renovation. A detailed inspection o f each gate by the&#13;
consultants shows that wear and tear on the gates, rollers and hoists is considerable.&#13;
Each o fthe 53 bays o f the barrage is controlled by 60ft wide vertical lift gates. There&#13;
are also 23 gates in the under sluices, canal head regulators, the fish ladder and the&#13;
navigation lock. Another operationalproblem concerns the excessive sediment inflow&#13;
to the Dera Ghazi Khan Canal on the right bank. This has been a problem for many years.&#13;
The IPD and its consultants believe the proposed silt excluder will help mitigate this&#13;
problem.&#13;
&#13;
Project Description&#13;
&#13;
Repair of the glacis and the stilling basinjloor: The entire one-foot skin o f concrete on&#13;
the glacis and stilling basin floor will be removed and replaced with a layer o f reinforced&#13;
concrete that will be anchored to the underlying concrete. The new layer o f concrete will&#13;
also include a new sill beam under the gates. Grouting o f the foundation will precede the&#13;
placing o f the new concrete skin. Several barrages in Pakistan have a silt excluder, a&#13;
device that is believed to reduce silt entry into off taking canals.&#13;
&#13;
Silt Excluder:      A silt excluder is a set o f tunnels in the barrage bays in front o f the&#13;
canal head. The theory is that the heavier sediments will flow through the tunnels and&#13;
only the lighter sediments will enter the canal. The plan is to build silt excluders in front&#13;
o f the DG Khan Canal at the same time as the floor i s repaired&#13;
&#13;
Construction of a Subsidiary Weir:       The main purpose o f the subsidiary weir i s to raise&#13;
the water level downstream o f the barrage by 6 ft. This will cause a stable jump to occur&#13;
on the downstream floor o f the barrage. The weir will have a stilling basin and protective&#13;
aprons designed to ensure energy dissipation for the weir itself.&#13;
&#13;
Alternatives to a concrete subsidiary weir were considered in detail by the consultants.&#13;
One was to build a weir at the end o f the existing downstream floor. Such a scheme&#13;
would involve the removal o f the massive concrete blocks and stone in and the creation&#13;
o f an entirely new concrete block and rock apron. It was found that much more favorable&#13;
conditions would exist downstream at the site now adopted. Another alternative would be&#13;
to form a subsidiary weir by a line o f gabions (rock-filled heavy wire baskets). But the&#13;
concern here was that even if costly protection was provided upstream and downstream&#13;
o f the gabions the durability could not be guaranteed. Also, the gabions could not bejust&#13;
dumped in fast flowing water and so a cofferdam would be needed as in the case o f the&#13;
subsidiary weir.&#13;
&#13;
Renovation of Gates and Appurtenances: The survey o f the gates and appurtenances has&#13;
shown that the gates themselves do not need replacement. The main items needed are&#13;
new rollers and conversion o f the hoists to powered, remote control operation. The skin&#13;
plates on the gates will be cleaned and painted. The operation o f the barrage and canal&#13;
head-works gates will be undertaken in a central control room, together with monitoring&#13;
instrument readings and flow measurement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ConsultingServices:     Consulting services include (a) construction supervision for the&#13;
Taunsa Barrage; (b) detailed designs for the rehabilitation o f other barrages o f Punjab, in&#13;
the Indus River Basin; (c) an independent panel o f experts for feasibility study, design,&#13;
safety review and construction quality assurance; (d) miscellaneous consultants for&#13;
project management, technical advisory services, monitoring and so on.&#13;
&#13;
Cost Estimates&#13;
&#13;
The Project is estimated to cost US$134 million (Table 2.1), including proposed Bank&#13;
financing of US$123 million and a Government share o fUS$ 11million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Table 2.1 COST ESTIMATE&#13;
                                                                   US$ million&#13;
            Component A&#13;
            SubsidiaryWeir:&#13;
            Cofferdam                                                      6.5&#13;
            Care of Water                                                  6.2&#13;
            Main Body of Sub Weir                                         38.0&#13;
            Other structures (incl. barragefish ladders&#13;
            upgrading)                                                     1.4&#13;
            Remodeling DG Khan Head Regulator                              0.2&#13;
            Repair of Barrage Floor                                        6.0&#13;
            Buildings &amp; Equipmentfor Engineer and Employer                 1.1&#13;
              Total ComponentA                                            59.5&#13;
&#13;
            Component B&#13;
            Gates for Subsidiary Weir                                      0.6&#13;
            Gates and Hoists                                              36.1&#13;
            O&amp;M Equipmentand Training                                      0.9&#13;
              Total Component B                                           37.6&#13;
&#13;
            Component C&#13;
            Consultantsfor Supervision                                     3.7&#13;
            Consultants for Other Barrages                                 2.5&#13;
            PMO staffing, operationand equipment                           1.9&#13;
              Total component C                                            8.2&#13;
&#13;
            TOTAL BASE COST                                              105.3&#13;
            PhysicalContingencies                                          9.5&#13;
            Price Contingencies                                            8.6&#13;
            InterestDuring Construction                                   10.3&#13;
            Front End Fee                                                  0.6&#13;
&#13;
            TOTAL COST                                                   134.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                Appendix 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Economic Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The condition o f Taunsa Barrage i s such that it could fail at any time. In the event o f a&#13;
major flood, the downstream floor, that is already damaged, could be undermined and&#13;
this would cause a part o fthe barrage to collapse. The flow inthe river would then be too&#13;
highto allow a temporary earth and rock fill dam to be built as a temporary closure. The&#13;
barrage would not then be able to maintain the water at the level needed to supply the&#13;
irrigation canals. If failure occurred for example in July, the main summer (khan) crop&#13;
o f cotton could not be irrigated any longer and the crop would fail because the&#13;
commanded area has very low rainfall. Ifthe barrage could not be put back in service in&#13;
time for the winter (rabi)crop, the farmers would be unableto grow a winter wheat crop.&#13;
&#13;
The economic benefit o f the barrage rehabilitation would be the avoided crop losses as&#13;
well as other losses due to interruption o f the oil and gas pipeline and other services.&#13;
The agricultural losses in the summer would be the area o f cotton in the DG Khan and&#13;
Muzaffagarh Canal Commands times the per acre value o f the crop. By July the farmers&#13;
will have invested in most o f the inputs, and in the absence o f barrage failure the crop&#13;
would continue to mature. The crop value to be taken as an agricultural loss would&#13;
therefore be the gross farm-gate value o f raw cotton less the remaining costs for water&#13;
management and harvesting. This i s estimated to be $260 per acre. The loss in the rabi&#13;
season would be the opportunity value o f the wheat crop that could not be planted&#13;
because o f the lack o f irrigation.  The net value o f a wheat crop would be about $40&#13;
per acre. The cropping pattern for the two canal commands is roughly 50% cotton and&#13;
50% wheat. The total agricultural loss would be about $300 million. It is assumed for&#13;
purposes o f this analysis that losses would be confined to one year (two crop seasons)&#13;
and that emergency arrangements at a cost o f $20 million could be made to restore&#13;
service to the two canal commands by the start of the next main irrigation season. After&#13;
that, the barrage would have to be rehabilitated at a cost o f over $100 million.&#13;
&#13;
The losses due to interruptions in the service o f the pipelines and the road have been&#13;
omitted inthis analysis on the assumption that temporary pipe and road bridges could be&#13;
built in a short time. The rate o f return on the investment in barrage rehabilitation&#13;
depends on when it i s assumed barrage failure takes place. If it occurs five years from&#13;
now the EIRR is 42%, and ten years from now 17%. A sensitivity analysis indicates that&#13;
even under the worst scenario, with 10% cost increase and 10% benefit reduction at the&#13;
same time, the EIRR assuming failure ten years from now is still above 12%, thus the&#13;
Project i s economically justified.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
              Table 3.1     Economic Evaluation&#13;
                      Crop Budgets (Acre)&#13;
&#13;
ProductionInputItems                       Cotton         Wheat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Yield-Kg                                            660      860&#13;
PriceJkg-Rs                                          27        11&#13;
Value o f By-product                                413      722&#13;
GrossValue                                       18226     10139&#13;
&#13;
Land Preparation                                   1373      761&#13;
&#13;
Seed Rate-kg                                           9       40&#13;
Pricehit-kg                                          20        13&#13;
Total-Rs.                                           176      526&#13;
&#13;
Fertilizer. K g                                      95        68&#13;
Unitrate-Rs.                                         24        24&#13;
Total-Rs.                                          2166      1632&#13;
&#13;
Sprays-No.                                             5        0&#13;
Unitrate-Rs.                                        293         0&#13;
Total-Rs.                                          1389         0&#13;
&#13;
Labor-days                                           65        43&#13;
Unit rate-Rs.                                       113       113&#13;
Total-Rs.                                          7345     4859&#13;
&#13;
ProductionCost                                   12449       7778&#13;
&#13;
Net Value of Production                            5777      2362&#13;
&#13;
Source: Taunsa BarrageRehabilitation,Feasibility Study NI&#13;
NESPAWAtkinsJuly 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                         Table 3.2      Economic Evaluation&#13;
                             Economic Price of Cotton&#13;
                                     (Export Parity)&#13;
&#13;
                      Price Typesand Conditions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Middling, 1-3/32Inch, CIF Europe/a&#13;
Current US$ per metric toda                                                     1542&#13;
Adjusted by factor o f .94 /b                                                   1453&#13;
Exchange rate /c                                                                   58&#13;
FOB Karachi, constant Rsper metric ton                                         84,259&#13;
Handling and Transport between port and market adjusted by SCF/d                -334&#13;
Ex-Ginnery Price o f Lint                                                      83,925&#13;
LintValue from 1ton of seedcotton @ 1/3                                        27975&#13;
Ginning, baling, etc. adjustedby SCF.                                           -857&#13;
&#13;
Handling and Transport between farm gate and mill adjusted by SCF.              -124&#13;
&#13;
Price at ginnery, per metric ton o f Seed Cotton                               26994&#13;
                            Price Rs.per Kg                                        27&#13;
&#13;
/a World Bank Commodity Price Data May, 2004.&#13;
/b For differences inquality and marketing; based on relationship between export&#13;
   unitprice andprices ofreference quality.&#13;
/c US$ 1= Rs.58 as on June 2004.&#13;
&#13;
Source: TaunsaBarrageRehabilitation,Feasibility Study NDC/NESPAWAtkinsJuly 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                        Table 3.3       Economic Evaluation&#13;
                             Economic Price of Wheat&#13;
                                  (Import Parity)&#13;
                          Price Typesand Conditions                             Amount&#13;
                                                                                 (RSJ&#13;
&#13;
Canadian No. 1WRS, in Store, St. Lawrence /a&#13;
Current US$ per metric toda                                                       148&#13;
Adjusted by factor o f 1.03 /b                                                    152&#13;
Freight and insurance                                                             30&#13;
CIF Karachi, constant US$per metric ton                                           182&#13;
Exchange rate /c                                                                  58.&#13;
CIF Karachi, constant Rs.per metric ton                                         10575&#13;
Handling and Transport between Port and market adjusted by SCF. /d               503&#13;
&#13;
Local market Price                                                              11077&#13;
                                                                                   -&#13;
Handling and Transport. Between farm gate and market adjusted by&#13;
SCF.                                                                             -124&#13;
&#13;
Farm gate price, constant Rs per Metric Ton.                                    10954&#13;
&#13;
                        Rs.per Kg                                                 11&#13;
/a World Bank Commodity Price Data May, 2004&#13;
/b For differences inquality and marketing; based on relationship between export&#13;
   unitprice andprices'ofreference quality.&#13;
/c US$ 1= Rs.58 as on June 2004.&#13;
/d Adjusted by SCF o f0.9.&#13;
&#13;
Source: Taunsa BarrageRehabilitation,FeasibilityStudy NDC/NESPAUAtkins July 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                          Appendix4&#13;
&#13;
           ProcurementCapacityAssessment andArrangements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ProcurementCapacityAssessment Summary&#13;
&#13;
Keeping in view the procurement capacity o f the department and the need to&#13;
expeditiously process all procurement throughout the process, a Project Management&#13;
Office (PMO) with a procurement and contract management unit has been set up.&#13;
Effective function o f PMO i s essential for meeting the milestones o f the procurement&#13;
plan o f the project. Hiring o f all key personnel o f PMO, particularly the procurement&#13;
personnel with prior Bank procurement experiences i s essential for meeting the tight&#13;
schedule. Minimumroutine organizational reshuffle o f the PMO staff would be expected&#13;
before the project startup.&#13;
&#13;
It is understood that PMO shall be the technical authority in awarding all Works and&#13;
Goods contracts. Authority o f Consultancy Contracts i s not vested in PMO and a high&#13;
level Consultants Selection Committee remains the evaluatiodapproving authority. This&#13;
may create a bottleneck in procurement o f consultancy services. However, IPD has&#13;
already obtained government approval o f single sourcing o f supervision consultancy o f&#13;
Taunsa Barrage (See detailed procurement assessment report inthe project files).&#13;
&#13;
To enhance the procurement capacity o f the implementing agency, a two-day&#13;
procurement training workshop i s planned in'December 2004 in Lahore, to be followed&#13;
bythe project Launch Workshop inthe first halfo f2005.&#13;
&#13;
ProcurementArrangements&#13;
&#13;
General&#13;
&#13;
Procurement o f goods and works to be financed under the Project shall be carried out in&#13;
accordance with the Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits&#13;
dated May 2004. Consultants Services financed under the project shall be procured in&#13;
accordance with Bank's Guidelines for Selection and Employment o f Consultants by&#13;
World Bank Borrowers dated May 2004 (except as noted below). The Bank's standard&#13;
biddingdocuments for procurement under International Competitive Bidding(ICB), will&#13;
be usedfor procurement o f Goods and Works under the Project. Domestic Preference as&#13;
defined in the Guidelines will be allowed for eligible domestic contractors and&#13;
domestically manufactured goods on ICB contracts.&#13;
&#13;
All expected procurement o f goods; works and consulting services have been listed inthe&#13;
Project's General Procurement Notice (GPN). The GPN has already been published in&#13;
the United Nations Development Business (UNDB) and will be updated annually.&#13;
Specific Procurement Notice (SPN) for the first ICB contract has been advertised in&#13;
UNDBandnational newspapers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CivilWorks&#13;
&#13;
All repairs to the barrage structure and the construction o f the subsidiary weir will be&#13;
executed under a single civil works contract, and renovation o f the gates and hoists will&#13;
be executed under another contract. Both contracts will be awarded to pre-qualified&#13;
bidders through ICB. Any other works contracts costing less than $2 million equivalent&#13;
per contract to an aggregate amount o f US$ 4 million shall be procured through NCB,&#13;
and works costing less than $100,000 per contract through shopping (quotation).&#13;
&#13;
Goods&#13;
&#13;
All vehicles and office equipment for the PMO and PSC Secretariat, at cost o f no more&#13;
than $200,000 equivalent per contract up to an aggregate amount o f $500,000, shall be&#13;
procured through national shopping procedures acceptable to the Bank. The O&amp;M&#13;
equipment will be procured as part o fthe ICB works contract for gate renovation.&#13;
&#13;
ConsultingServices&#13;
&#13;
Consulting services under the project include: (a) Taunsa Barrage construction&#13;
supervision; (b) detailed design for other Punjab barrages, (c) an independent Panel o f&#13;
Experts (POE); and (d) consultants employed by the PMO for project management and&#13;
technical advisory services, and monitoring, etc. Consulting services shall be procured in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's Guidelines for Selection and Employment o f Consultants by&#13;
World Bank Borrowers, dated May 2004. Selection methods include QCBS, CQ and&#13;
Least-Cost Selection for firm contracts, and individual consultants.&#13;
&#13;
ProcurementPlanning&#13;
&#13;
The procurement plan for the project prepared at appraisal andupdated on November 24,&#13;
2004 at the time of negotiations i s attached to the minutes o f negotiations for the Project.&#13;
Prior to the issuance o f any invitations to bid for contracts, the proposed procurement&#13;
plan for the Project shall be furnished to the Bank for review and approval, inaccordance&#13;
with the provisions o f paragraph 1 o f Appendix 1 to the relevant Bank Procurement&#13;
Guidelines. Such plan shall be updated every three months during the execution of the&#13;
Project, and each such updating shall be furnished to the Bank for its review and approval.&#13;
Procurement o f all goods, works and consultants' services shall be undertaken in&#13;
accordance with such procurement plan (as updated from time to time) as shall have been&#13;
approvedby the Bank, andwith the provisions o f said paragraph 1.&#13;
&#13;
ProcurementReviewby the Bank&#13;
&#13;
Except as the Bank shall otherwise determine by notice to the Borrower, the following&#13;
contracts shall be subject to Prior Review by the Bank: (a) each contract for goods, works&#13;
and services (other than consultants' services) procured on the basis o f International&#13;
Competitive Bidding, or National Competitive Bidding; (b) each contract for consultants'&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
services provided by a firm estimated to cost the equivalent of $100,000 or more, and all&#13;
single-source contracts irrespective o f value; and (c) the first contract for the employment&#13;
o f individual consultants, irrespective o f value, and thereafter each such contract&#13;
estimated to cost the equivalent o f $50,000 or more.&#13;
&#13;
     SummarvProcurementArrangementsfor the Project(amount inUS$ million)&#13;
&#13;
         Project Component                               Procurement Method                       Total&#13;
                                            ICB/a        NCB/b        lOthers/c  I NBF/d&#13;
Civil Works                                  114.5           0.0          0.0        0.0          114.5&#13;
                                            (103.5)         (0.0)        (0.0)       (0.0)      (103.5)&#13;
Goods                                         0.0            0.0          0.3        0.0           0.3&#13;
                                             (0.0)          (0.0)        (0.3)       (0.0)        (0.3)&#13;
Consulting Services and Training              0.0            0.0          6.3        0.0           6.3&#13;
                                             (0.0)         (0.0)         (6.3)       (0.0)        (6.3)&#13;
Incremental Administrative &amp;                  0.0            0.0          2.0         0.0          2.0&#13;
Operating Costs                              (0.0)          (0.0)        (2.0)       (0.0)        (2.0)&#13;
Interest During Construction                  0.0            0.0          10.3        0.0          10.3&#13;
                                             (0.0)          (0.0)        (10.3)      (0.0)        (10.3)&#13;
Front-end Fee                                 0.0            0.0          0.6         0.0          0.6&#13;
                                             (0.0)          (0.0)        (0.6)       (0.0)        (0.6)&#13;
             Total                           114.5           0.0          19.5        0.0         134.0&#13;
                                            (103.5)         (0.0)        (19.5)      (0.0)       (123.0)&#13;
la:&#13;
     floor repair, and renovation o f the barrage and canal intake gates.&#13;
ib: NationalCompetitive Bidding(NCB) for minor civilworks costing lessthan US$2million. Such&#13;
    works are unlikely to be needed and are not included inthe cost estimates.&#13;
I C Include: (i) shopping for goods (vehicles, equipment and materials) estimated to cost between&#13;
    US$25,000 and US$200,000 equivalent per contract up to an aggregate amount o f US$500,000;&#13;
    (ii) shopping (quotation) for minor works estimated to cost less than US$lOO,OOO per contract;&#13;
    (iii)incrementaladministrativeandoperatingcosts(PMO); (iv)procurementofconsultingservices&#13;
    according to the Bank's "Guidelines for Selection and Employment o f Consultants by World Bank&#13;
    Borrowers" dated May 2004; (v) interest during construction (Loan part); and (vi) front-end fee.&#13;
Id: NBF=Not Bank Financed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                               Appendix 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   FinancialManagementandDisbursement&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
InstitutionalArrangementsand Staffing&#13;
&#13;
A project management office (PMO), headed by a Project Director has been established&#13;
within the IPD to carry out the day-to-day management o f the Project. The PMO will&#13;
have a Financial Management Section staffed by two key qualified accounting personnel:&#13;
a Director (Finance) responsible for overall financial management o f the project&#13;
including reporting, and preparation o f annual financial statements for audit ; and a&#13;
financial management staff responsible for budget planning and execution reporting, and&#13;
for all disbursements for the project and management o f the Special Account and&#13;
associated withdrawal and replenishment activities, preparation o f the annual financial&#13;
statements for audit and submission thereof to the Bank. To support the PMO staff, the&#13;
Government o f the Punjab shall assign two full-time government accounting staff with&#13;
qualifications equivalent to Accounts Officers to manage and implement the book-&#13;
keeping o fthe project's financial transactions duringthe life o f the project.&#13;
&#13;
Disbursementsand SpecialAccount&#13;
&#13;
The Project will be executed under two large works contracts that will be unit-price&#13;
contracts. Disbursement to the contractors will be against contractors' claims verified by&#13;
the Resident Engineer and submittedto the PMO. Disbursement for consulting services&#13;
will be against payment claims reviewed and verified by the PMO. A Special Account&#13;
will be opened with the National Bank o f Pakistan (NBP) to finance all eligible&#13;
expenditures. All funds transferred by the Bank shall be routed through the State Bank o f&#13;
Pakistan (SBP) to the nominated account o f the project with the NBP. The Authorized&#13;
Allocation to the Special Account will be $7,500,000.&#13;
&#13;
To allow for uninterrupted flow o f funds to the project, a `rupee assignment account'&#13;
representing the counterpart funds will be opened at the NBP and managed under the&#13;
same auspices as the Special Account. The project will observe the provisions o f the&#13;
CGA instructions o f 25 November 2002 relating to the maintenance and operation o f          ,&#13;
revolving fund accounts opened for IDA/IBRD/ADB loandcredits. In addition to&#13;
disbursements through the Special Account, the project will be at liberty to use the option&#13;
o f `direct payments' from the credit proceeds to finance large payments to thirdparties.&#13;
&#13;
Withdrawal Applications for replenishing eligible expenditures drawn from the Special&#13;
Account will be supported by Statements o f Expenditures for: (a) Contracts for civil&#13;
works, goods and consulting firms estimated to cost less than US$lOO,OOO equivalent;&#13;
(b) Contracts for individual consultants estimated to cost less than US$50,000 equivalent;&#13;
and (c) the incremental operating costs o f the PMO.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 The total loan o f US$123 million equivalent will be disbursed over a period o f about four&#13;
 years with the projected disbursementschedule (unit:million US$ ).&#13;
&#13;
                               Table 5.1 ProjectedDisbursementSchedule&#13;
                           FY 2005-06                 FY2006-07                   FY 2007-08&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             1     I1    II    I 1    II     I      II    I&#13;
                                                          I    II      I        II      II     I     II&#13;
~     ~~&#13;
 Quarterly    11.0   5.3   14.2   18.3  15.2    6.3   10.5 12.6  12.6     2.6     4.3     4.3   3.4    2.6&#13;
 CumulativeI  11.0   16.3  30.5   48.8  64.0   170.3  80.7 93.3  105.8   1108.4   112.7   117.0I120.4  123.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Allocation o f the loan proceeds by disbursement category and percentage to be financed&#13;
 are shown inthe Table 5.2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Expenditure Category               Amount               Financing&#13;
                                            (Japanese Yen)            Percentage&#13;
           1. Works                         10,475,400,000                  90%&#13;
           2. Goods                             31,970,000                 100%&#13;
           3. Consultant Services &amp;            735,3 00,000                100%&#13;
           Training&#13;
           4. IncrementalAdmin. &amp;               170,510,000                100%&#13;
           Operating Costs&#13;
           5. Interest during               1,097,620,000                  100%&#13;
           Construction&#13;
           6. Front-endFee                      65,537,500                 100%&#13;
&#13;
          I7. Unallocated                      531.162.500&#13;
           TotalLoanFinancing             1 13,107,500,000      [                         1&#13;
&#13;
 Based on the level o f financial management preparedness for this project and the&#13;
 qualifications o f the personnel that will serve inthe FMunit, an initial overall FMrisk o f&#13;
 the project i s assessed as `Medium". The details o f the capacity assessment are on the&#13;
 project file.&#13;
&#13;
 ReportingandAuditing&#13;
&#13;
 The PMO will prepare quarterly Financial Monitoring Reports (FMRs) and submit to the&#13;
 Bank within 45 days o f the end o f each quarter. The formats o f these reports will closely&#13;
 follow the FARAHprinciples but will specifically include: `Sources and Uses o f Funds',&#13;
 Uses o f Funds according to Project Category and Component', `Reconciliation o f Special&#13;
 Accounts', Physical vs. Financial Progress Reports'. An inventory o f fixed assets&#13;
 acquired with project funds should also be prepared, updated, and made available to the&#13;
 PMO and the Bank at least on semi-annual basis. Internal auditing will be undertaken by&#13;
 the Finance Bureau o f the Punjab. The external audit o f the Project accounts will be done&#13;
 bythe Auditor-General ofPakistanthrough the DirectorateGeneral for Provincial Audit.&#13;
&#13;
 Since this i s a public sector development program project, the specific reporting&#13;
 requirements of the GoPakistan would not be compromised. The Financial Management&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    26&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section o f the PMO would need to prepare monthly expenditures of the project (made&#13;
through Special Account and Pak. Rupees Assignment Account) accounting to approved&#13;
heads o f account and report to the Accountant General o f Punjab for incorporation and&#13;
aggregation o f those expenditures in the GoPunjab civil accounts. The specific heads o f&#13;
account for the project's transactions would have to be pre-agreed with the Accountant&#13;
General, Punjab, and the codes should be derived from the New Chart o f Accounts that&#13;
the GoPunjab shall fully adopt as of FY 2005/06.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                              Appendix 6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       Environmental and Social Safeguards&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OperationPhaseImpactson TaunsaWildlife Sanctuary&#13;
&#13;
The pond and shore area behind Taunsa barrage, covering 6,567 ha was declared a Game&#13;
Sanctuary by the Government o f Pakistan in 1972. The Sanctuary was re-listed in April&#13;
1983, then in July 1988 and subsequently in March 1993. The area was re-notified as a&#13;
Wildlife Sanctuary in 2002.        In 1996 it was declared a wetland o f international&#13;
importance under the Ramsar Convention on Wetlands.           This Convention, signed in&#13;
Ramsar, Iran, in 1971, i s an intergovernmental treaty which provides the framework for&#13;
national action and international cooperation for the conservation and wise use o f&#13;
wetlands and their resources.&#13;
&#13;
The rare marbled teal (Marmaronetta angustirostris) is a regular passage migrant and a&#13;
winter visitor in small numbers to the Taunsa Wildlife Sanctuary. The rare Indus dolphin&#13;
(Platanista minor) and otter (Lutraperspicillata) are present at the site in small numbers,&#13;
and the endangered crocodile (Gavialis gangeticus) has been reported at the barrage. The&#13;
site forms an important wintering area for ducks and geese, a breeding area for several&#13;
species, notably the Lesser Whistling-Duck (Dendrocygna javanica), and a staging area&#13;
for cranes (Grus grus and Anthropoides Virgo) and shorebirds. Taunsa Barrage i s the&#13;
most important wintering area for the bar-headed goose in Pakistan. Over 24,000 water&#13;
birds were present at Taunsa in mid-January 1987. Mammals occurring at the site&#13;
include the Asiatic jackal (Canis aureus), jungle cat (Felis chaus), wild boar (Sus scrofa&#13;
cristatus) and hare (Lepus nigricollis). The hog deer (Axis porcinus) still occurs in the&#13;
area, although it has been heavily hunted.&#13;
&#13;
The question arises whether the rehabilitation o f the reservoir may cause changes in&#13;
reservoir operation that might affect the ecology o f the Sanctuary. Inorder to supply the&#13;
off-taking canals at their maximum capacity the pond level is normally about El. 447.5,&#13;
but sometimes it is as high as El. 448.5 because o f silt accumulation in the DG Khan&#13;
canal. The operating level can fall to as low as El. 443.0 in November, when the head&#13;
across the weir i s greatest. Each year for three weeks inJanuary the canals are closed and&#13;
the pool level drops to as low as El. 425.7. While rehabilitation o f the barrage provides&#13;
the possibility of operating the barrage at higher pond levels during winter, the EIA&#13;
indicates that the operational pond levels will remain within current seasonal ranges upon&#13;
completion o f rehabilitation, and that there will not be a significant ecological impact&#13;
from this. A baseline survey has been conducted and regular monitoring will be&#13;
undertaken duringproject implementation by the PMO in collaboration with independent&#13;
thirdparties.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ConstructionPhaseImpacts&#13;
&#13;
Temporary land acquisition:          Sufficient unused land i s available within the existing IPD&#13;
compound for storage and lay-down areas, so it will not be necessary to acquire land&#13;
temporarily for these purposes duringconstruction.&#13;
&#13;
Local Labor: An important opportunity for positive intervention will be the hiring of local labor&#13;
for construction activities, to the extent possible. This has been noted inthe EMP.&#13;
&#13;
Canal Closures: The IPD provided assurances that the duration and timing o f canal&#13;
closures duringthe constructionperiodwill remain the same as under the current regime.&#13;
&#13;
Access:       No new roads or road widening will be required to provide access during&#13;
construction. The approved EMP includes measures to control emissions and waste&#13;
duringthe roaduse.&#13;
&#13;
Vehicle Impacts:       The EMP includes measures to ensure that dust and other vehicular&#13;
emissions are minimized. The contractor will consult with local communities to develop&#13;
measures to minimize the disturbances and safety risks imposedby construction traffic.&#13;
&#13;
Safety and Health:        The contractor will be required to provide laborers with&#13;
appropriate safety equipment and training. The contractor will also adopt additional&#13;
measures to help prevent the spread o f sexually transmitted infections (STI) within the&#13;
host population and the temporary work force especially HIV/AIDS. The contractor will:&#13;
(i)employ a qualified organization to conduct an STI/HIV/AIDS awareness and&#13;
prevention campaign, reaching in particular the non-local labor and truck-drivers,&#13;
(ii) that condoms are available at laborcamps andtruck stops, and(iii)ensure&#13;
    ensure&#13;
access to acceptable and appropriate STI voluntary counseling and testing services.&#13;
&#13;
EnvironmentalManagementPlan&#13;
&#13;
Based on the assessment o f operation and construction phase impacts outlined above, the&#13;
EIA includes an EMP prepared insufficient detail to be incorporated in(i)          guidelines for&#13;
operation o f the barrage and (ii)bidding documents and the contracts for construction&#13;
under the Project. These include specific mitigation measures, with associated budgets,&#13;
timetables, and responsibilities for implementation and monitoring.&#13;
&#13;
Consultation&#13;
&#13;
The EIA has been made publicly available at the office o f the District Officer&#13;
(Environmental) inDera Ghazi Khan, and inthe Punjab Public Library, Lahore. A public&#13;
hearing to discuss the EIA was heldinDera Ghazi Khan on August 23,2004.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                   Appendix 7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       Performance Monitoring Indicators&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
InputIndicators:                                            Result-Targets&#13;
&#13;
1. Construction Supervision ConsultantsMobilized:           February 2005&#13;
2. Award of ICB Works Contract No. 1:                       March 2005&#13;
3. Consultants for Environmental Baseline SurveyAppointed:  April 2005&#13;
4. Start o f Cofferdam Construction:                        September 2005&#13;
5. Award of ICB Works Contract No. 2:                       October 2005&#13;
6. Consultants for Designs of Other Barrages Selected:      October 2005&#13;
7. Gates Renovation &amp; Installation Starts:                  January 2006&#13;
8. Numberof Panelof Experts Meetings Held:                  6-8times&#13;
9. Govemment Counterpart Funding provided:                  8% o ftotal costs&#13;
10. Adequate O&amp;M Funding for Taunsa Barrage:                As definedinthe&#13;
                                                            OMS Manual&#13;
&#13;
OutputIndicators:&#13;
&#13;
11. ICB Works Contract No. 1Completion:                     June 2008&#13;
12. ICB Works Contract No. 2 Completion:                    June 2008&#13;
13. Completion o fUpgrading OMS Manual for Taunsa Barrage:  December 2007&#13;
14.Number of Operating Staff Trained:                       20&#13;
15. Completion of Technical Designs for the Five Barrages:  October 2006&#13;
16.FinalProject Costs:                                      US$134 million&#13;
17.Project Completion Date:                                 June 30,2008&#13;
18. Barrage Monitoring SystemPerformance (actual):&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Outcome/ImpactIndicators(Actual):&#13;
&#13;
19. Number of Significant Safety Incidentsat Taunsa:&#13;
20. Pond Level Maintained Upstream o fthe Barrage:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                     Appendix 8&#13;
&#13;
                         Project Processing Schedule&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B. Teamcomposition&#13;
                Name                                Area of specialty&#13;
Xiaokai Li                            TTL, Senior Water Resources Specialist&#13;
Usman Qamar                           Senior Irrigation Specialist&#13;
Alessandro Palmieri                   Lead Dam Specialist&#13;
William Smith                         Consulting Engineer&#13;
Akhtar Hamid                          Lead Counsel&#13;
Paul Martin                           Senior Environmental/ Safeguard Specialist&#13;
Ali Awais                             Counsel&#13;
Tasnim Beg                            Financial Management Specialist&#13;
Uzma Sadaf                            Procurement Specialist&#13;
Anwar Ali Bhatti                      Disbursement Analyst&#13;
Ismaila Ceesay                        Senior FinancialManagement Specialist&#13;
Hasan Saqib                           Financial Management Specialist&#13;
Vaqar Zakaria                         Environmental Consultant&#13;
Altaf Iqbal                           Economist/Costs Consultant&#13;
Manuel Contiioch                      Senior Water Resources SDecialist&#13;
Lilac Thomas                          Program Analyst&#13;
Ghulam Ali                            Program Assistant&#13;
Arthur Walz                           Peer Reviewer -Engineering (consultant)&#13;
Chaohua Zhang                         Peer reviewer - Safeguards&#13;
Rita E. Cestti                        Peer reviewer - Economics&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Key Processes                      ResourceRequirement&#13;
Concept review                                           20,000&#13;
Amraisal                                                 200.000&#13;
Negotiation                                              30,000&#13;
Board Approval                                           20,000&#13;
Effectiveness                                            10,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5627753">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/02/5627753/pakistan-taunsa-barrage-emergency-rehabilitation-modernization-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/02/5627753/pakistan-taunsa-barrage-emergency-rehabilitation-modernization-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/02/5627753/pakistan-taunsa-barrage-emergency-rehabilitation-modernization-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/02/28/000090341_20050228093536/Rendered/INDEX/T7642.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/02/28/000090341_20050228093536/Rendered/PDF/T7642.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-02-28T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2005-02-18T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Pakistan - Taunsa Barrage Emergency
            Rehabilitation and Modernization Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objectives of the Taunsa Barrage
            Emergency Rehabilitation and Modernization Project for
            Pakistan are: (a) to take urgent steps to prevent the
            failure of the Taunsa Barrage which provides irrigation for
            two million acres and drinking water to several million
            farmers in the rural areas of Southern Punjab; and (b) to
            prepare for similar steps with respect to other existing
            barrages in Punjab. The objectives will be achieved through:
            (i) rehabilitating and strengthening the Taunsa Barrage and
            associated structures; (ii) renovation and modernization of
            gates, hoists and operating and control facilities; (iii)
            improving operation and maintenance capability; and (iv)
            rehabilitation design studies for other barrages in Punjab.
            The major benefits of the Project stem from securing
            irrigation of the cultivated lands in the command areas of
            over two million acres in the two canal commands of
            Muzaffargarh and Dera Ghazi Khan, and through the
            Taunsa-Panjnad Link Canal to supplement water supply to
            Panjnad Headworks canals. Other benefits from the
            rehabilitation of the barrage include: (a) long-term and
            effective functioning of the critical oil and gas pipelines,
            and telephone lines; and (b) ensuring continued availability
            of vital rail and road links of strategic importance between
            the Punjab and the Sindh and Balochistan provinces.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Pakistan - Taunsa Barrage Emergency
            Rehabilitation and Modernization Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Pakistan - Taunsa Barrage
            Emergency Rehabilitation and Modernization Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2005/02/5627753/pakistan-taunsa-barrage-emergency-rehabilitation-modernization-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>PK-Taunsa Barrages Emergency Rehabilitation
            And Modernization Proj -- P088994</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Water Supply and Systems,Engineering,Water Conservation,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Pakistan</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20050228093536</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <subsc>General agriculture, fishing and forestry sector,Irrigation and drainage,General water, sanitation and flood
            protection sector</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry,Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            afflux, aging, Agriculture, annual flow,
            annual rainfall, Barrages, Basin, bunds, canals, cofferdam,
            construction, covers, crop yields, crops, crossings,
            cultivated lands, Dam Safety, Dams, disasters, drinking
            water, dry season, Embankments, Employment, Engineering,
            engineering design, engines, Environmental Impact
            Assessment, Environmental Management, environmental
            monitoring, Environmental Protection, erosion, families,
            farmers, Floods, flow measurement, gas, hoists, hydraulic
            jump, hydrology, International Waterways, intervention,
            inundation, Irrigation, irrigation canals, irrigation
            systems, irrigation water, joints, ladders, Lessons Learned,
            measurements, natural disasters, Operation &amp;
            Maintenance, partnership, pipe, pipelines, pressure,
            programs, PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION, Project Management,
            project preparation, protective aprons, quality assurance,
            rainfall, REHABILITATION, riparian, River, River System,
            rivers, safe water, Safety, safety management, sand,
            sediment, sediment deposition, sediments, seepage, Silt,
            standing wave, structures, sustainable use, tributaries,
            velocity, water flows, water level, water levels, water
            management, water supply, water use, Waters, weirs, winter
            crops, winter wheat
        </keywd>
        <owner>Agriculture,Irrigation &amp; Nat Res (SASDA)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Specific Investment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T7642</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety of Dams</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Rivers Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Riparian Rights</ml:concept><ml:concept>PIM Diagnostic Tool</ml:concept><ml:concept>Project Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>EIA</ml:concept><ml:concept>EMMP</ml:concept><ml:concept>EMP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Barrages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydrology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Protection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dam Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oil and Gas Pipeline</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Project Cycle Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Impact Assessement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Management and Mitigation Plans</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Levees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Headworks</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Pakistan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>