<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>285&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           privatesector       P U B L I C        P O L I C Y     F O R       T H E&#13;
&#13;
   NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         NOTE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             2005&#13;
                                                                                                             The Future of Aid 2&#13;
                 MARCH&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Tim Harford and             The Big Push&#13;
                                                                                 Michael Klein&#13;
                                                                                                             Imagine that you are in 2030, reviewing the aid industry over the&#13;
                                                                                 Tim Harford&#13;
                                                                                                             past 25 years. This Note offers one possible scenario--responses of&#13;
                                                                                 (tharford@ifc.org) is an&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 economist at the World      the aid industry to falling numbers of people in absolute poverty and&#13;
                                                                                 Bank and International      to the growing ability of poor countries to borrow from the market.&#13;
                                                                                 Finance Corporation&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 (IFC). Michael Klein        A companion Note offers a second scenario. Organizations use&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 (mklein@worldbank.org)&#13;
                      PRESIDENCY                                                                             scenario planning to prepare for the very long term. Good scenarios&#13;
                                                                                 is chief economist at IFC&#13;
                                                                                                             are plausible stories about the future, recognizable in the trends of&#13;
                                VICE                                             and joint IFC­World&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Bank vice president for     today. The ideal scenario encourages thinking about possible&#13;
                                                                                 private sector development.&#13;
                                                                                                             responses. It is in this spirit that this scenario is offered.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 This Note is part of a&#13;
                                                                                                              Trends to 2005                                      type--from new donors such as China, Slovenia,&#13;
                                    DEVELOPMENT                                  series exploring trends&#13;
                                                                                                              It was clear by 2005 that three trends were shap-   and Thailand--but also of entirely new types--&#13;
                                                                                 in the aid industry,&#13;
                                                                                                              ing the aid industry. First, incomes had been ris-  agencies with different approaches to raising or&#13;
                                                                                 including patterns of aid&#13;
                                               SECTOR                                                         ing rapidly in many developing countries over       disbursing funds. These new types included the&#13;
                                                                                 flows, competition, and&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 the effectiveness of         the past few decades, especially in East Asia and   Millennium Challenge Corporation, distribut-&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 different types of aid.      India. Fewer countries were very poor.              ing most of its grants to countries meeting&#13;
                                                     PRIVATE                                                     Second, more developing countries were           objective standards, and the Global Fund to&#13;
                                                                                                              able to borrow from banks or bond markets at        Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis, and Malaria, focusing&#13;
                                                                                                              attractive terms. And much of the money flow-       on a tight group of cross-border problems. In&#13;
                                                                                                              ing to developing countries was no longer gov-      response to these three trends, the aid industry&#13;
                                                            GROUP&#13;
                                                                                                              ernment debt but private borrowing, equity and      emphasized "harmonization," the buzzword for&#13;
                                                                                                              foreign direct investment, and even remittances     trying to coordinate the efforts of different aid&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 BANK                                         from migrant workers.                               agencies.&#13;
                                                                                                                 Third, new players--official agencies and&#13;
                                                                                                              unofficial ones, usually called nongovernmen-       Reinventing the industry&#13;
                                                                                                              tal organizations (NGOs)--had been entering         Looking back from 2030, it is clear that these&#13;
                                                                     WORLD                                    the market for aid, a market that had seen a cen-   three trends would force the traditional model&#13;
                                                                                                              tury of entry by aid agencies and no exit. The      of foreign aid to change. The aid industry was&#13;
                                                                          THE                                 new entrants were not only of the traditional       steadily transformed from one dominated by a&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
T H E F U T U R E O F A I D 2 T H E B I G P U S H&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   few large agencies to one that was far more com-                                                well, could buy development. The technical&#13;
                                   petitive and far more subject to competition                                                    advicewasamuchquietersuccessstory.The1970s&#13;
                                   from such substitutes as bonds, loans from pri-                                                 and 1980s had seen widespread fiscal instability&#13;
                                   vate banks, and private giving.                                                                 and inflation; by 2005 these blights had been met&#13;
                                        Traditional development needs also were                                                    head-on and subdued by many developing coun-&#13;
                                   changing. Good-value loans to governments                                                       tries. Few people noticed, because as one problem&#13;
                                   were not in short supply: as spreads narrowed                                                   was solved the discussion would move on to the&#13;
                                   and credit ratings improved, most developing                                                    next, such as providing infrastructure or cutting&#13;
                                   countries became able to borrow commercially                                                    red tape. Finally, harmonization had become an&#13;
2&#13;
                                   at attractive terms (see Martin, Harford, and                                                   obsession of an increasingly competitive industry&#13;
                                   Klein forthcoming).                                                                             by 2005.&#13;
                                        As a result of these changes, more and more&#13;
                                   aid agencies were supplying fewer and smaller                                                   2010­20: drowning in the "common pool"&#13;
                                   poor countries. To some extent the industry was                                                 By 2010 the aid industry was attempting to kill&#13;
                                   becoming a victim of its own success: the share of                                              two birds with one stone: by delivering large&#13;
                                   the developing world's population living in                                                     grants through a "common pool" mechanism,&#13;
                                   extreme poverty had declined by nearly half in                                                  the Multilateral Fund for Development, it aimed&#13;
                                   just two decades. The population and economic                                                   to scale up the amount of aid delivered while also&#13;
                                   weight of very poor countries had also fallen: with                                             reducing the costs of a fragmented industry.&#13;
                                   China, India, and Indonesia too well-off to                                                        The rules of the fund, agreed to by donors in&#13;
                                   receive           subsidies               from             the         International            2009, were designed to maximize grants to directly&#13;
                                   Development Association (IDA), IDA recipients                                                   support recipient government budgets--and also&#13;
                                   generated less than 1 percent of world GDP in                                                   to make negotiations with multiple donors much&#13;
                                   2030, down from 5 percent in 1970 (figure 1).                                                   more efficient. Each developing country pre-&#13;
                                        In retrospect, the trajectory of the aid industry                                          sented a development strategy to donors, which&#13;
                                   was already clear by 2005: it was going to be large                                             could then decide to support the strategy, or not,&#13;
                                   grants, ever-more-sophisticated technical advice,                                               with grants made through the fund. The fund&#13;
                                   and harmonization. The grants were preceded by                                                  rules prohibited earmarking and specific condi-&#13;
                                   louder and louder calls for a "big push"--for                                                   tionality:eachdonorsimplyhadtodecidewhether&#13;
                                   example, in the U.K. government's proposal for                                                  ornottosupportthedevelopmentstrategyofeach&#13;
                                   an international financing facility and in the                                                  recipient. Donors unhappy with how the money&#13;
                                   much-cited report of the UN Millennium Project                                                  was spent simply gave less next year. Few donors&#13;
                                   (2005). With richer donors and fewer badly strug-                                               sent every penny of aid through the fund, but&#13;
                                   gling countries, the logic was that grants, if aimed                                            many sent substantial proportions.&#13;
                                                                                                                                      The common pool approach embodied high&#13;
                                                                                                                                   hopes (Kanbur and Sandler 1999), but difficulties&#13;
                                   Figure   Poor countries grow, IDA shrinks&#13;
                                                                                                                                   quickly became apparent. The strategy was rooted&#13;
                                   1         Percentage of global GDP produced                                                     in the conventional wisdom of the early 21st cen-&#13;
                                             by IDA countries&#13;
                                                                                                                                   tury: find a developing country with good policies&#13;
                                             8&#13;
                                                                                                                                   and institutions, send aid, and stand back. It&#13;
                                                                    China graduates&#13;
                                                                    Indonesia rejoins                                              worked well for middle-income countries with&#13;
                                                                                                                                   mature institutions. But many other countries&#13;
                                             4                                                        India graduates&#13;
                                                                                                                                   struggledtousetheaideffectively.Thetroublewas&#13;
                                                                                                                                   that policies and institutions are changed by large&#13;
                                                                   Indonesia graduates&#13;
                                                                                                                                   flowsofaid--whichisexactlywhatwashedoverthe&#13;
                                             0&#13;
                                              1960                   1980                 2000                 2020        2030    handful of the poorest countries that met the stan-&#13;
                                                                                                                                   dards set by donors. For such countries the aid&#13;
                                          Note: Scenarios are not forecasts. The scenario reflected here assumes that the income&#13;
                                          cutoff for IDA membership does not change and that countries grow at trends slightly     flows had effects similar to those of the well-known&#13;
                                          (0.33 percent annually) above historical rates.&#13;
                                          Source: Historical data from IDA and World Bank, World Development Indicators database;  "resource curse": manufacturing and agriculture&#13;
                                          authors' projections.                                                                    were squeezed by appreciating exchange rates&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(Foster and Keith 2003). More important, demo-       mercial providers needed to be accredited; aid&#13;
cratic institutions were compromised in the rush     agencies that delivered services needed to be rated&#13;
for control of the new money (see Djankov,           so that credit holders could direct their credits to&#13;
Montalvo, and Reynal-Querol 2004; and Knack          the most effective;1 recipients needed to be moni-&#13;
2000). Practitioners became disillusioned with the   tored to assure donors that they were deserving of&#13;
Multilateral Fund for Development, and some          service credits in the first place. Some donors,&#13;
began to comment blackly that promising reform-      skeptical of the credit scheme, used intensive eval-&#13;
ers had been drowned in the common pool.             uation to justify alternative approaches. A virtuous&#13;
                                                     spiral quickly developed: the service credit scheme&#13;
                                                                                                                                         3&#13;
2020­30: discovering discipline                      strengthened demands for better evaluation,&#13;
While the pool system did not deliver what had       while better evaluation bolstered the case for the&#13;
been hoped for, it represented an important          service credit scheme (figure 3).&#13;
step toward the aid system we enjoy today in              Once the service credit scheme was estab-&#13;
2030. Technical assistance was a case in point: by   lished, donors were able to experiment with new&#13;
forbidding grants for specified projects, the pool   ideas, giving credits directly to municipalities or&#13;
system prevented the old practice of providing       even small communities, secure in the knowl-&#13;
money bundled with technical assistance. But         edge that the system was more and more resistant&#13;
that weakness became a strength: by providing        to waste and abuse. Other donors, armed with the&#13;
cash rather than technical assistance, the pool      ratings of agencies, felt happy to fund those with&#13;
system left recipients free to buy their own assis-  a proven track record. But agencies with poor rat-&#13;
tance on the open market rather than accepting       ings lost funding and struggled to survive.&#13;
whatever ad hoc program was bolted onto a loan.           Some aid agencies specialized in service deliv-&#13;
A more professional and competitive market for       ery, competing with NGOs and private firms.&#13;
technical assistance emerged as a result.            Others became fund managers on behalf of&#13;
   The pool system's shortcomings also made it       donors; the best found that they were also able&#13;
clear what had been missing: trying to minimize      to act on behalf of foundations and charities.&#13;
the costs of chaotic competition was all very well,       An important side effect was the marginaliza-&#13;
but what about trying to maximize the benefits?      tion of political aid. Clearly outside the loop of&#13;
What was needed was a set of systems to impose       service credits, monitoring, and evaluation, aid&#13;
discipline on donors, service providers, and         that was driven by realpolitik became easy to dis-&#13;
recipients alike, making them accountable to         tinguish from aid that was benevolent. (In an early&#13;
one another.                                         initiative to isolate aid funds from political consid-&#13;
   The first step toward such discipline was a shift erations, the United States set up the Millennium&#13;
away from the pool as slush fund: rather than cash,  ChallengeCorporationin2002.Itsfundsweresup-&#13;
recipients received "service credits" that they used&#13;
to buy services from official aid agencies and&#13;
                                                             The official aid market in 2030&#13;
accreditedcommercialserviceproviders(figure2).         Figure&#13;
                                                     2&#13;
Thisservicecreditschemehelpedtoraisethegame&#13;
of aid agencies and encourage entry by infrastruc-                                 Cash                        Credits&#13;
                                                                    Donors                         Pool                    Recipients&#13;
ture providers, consultants, and many others. At&#13;
the same time it supplied aid in a form that was&#13;
harder for recipient countries to spend unwisely or&#13;
                                                                                                Commercial&#13;
corruptly, because service credits were redeemable&#13;
                                                                                                  service&#13;
only with recognized agencies and firms. The                                                    providers&#13;
scheme, which had seemed implausible when pro-&#13;
posed nearly 20 years earlier (Easterly 2002), was&#13;
                                                                                               Aid agencies&#13;
much easier to implement with the pool in place.&#13;
   Mostimportant,theservicecreditschemecried                     Independent                                              Independent&#13;
                                                                  evaluation                                               monitoring&#13;
out for better monitoring and evaluation--a de-&#13;
mand that could no longer be ignored. Com-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
T H E F U T U R E O F A I D 2 T H E   B I G P U S H&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       help them. But this is speculative. Looking for-&#13;
 FigureDeveloping discipline&#13;
                                                       ward to 2050, we can only conclude that if the last&#13;
3          Skeptics of                                 of the truly poor are to be helped, the aid indus-&#13;
                                  Evaluation helps&#13;
         credits demand           competition work     try will have to go through yet another revolution.&#13;
            evaluation&#13;
                                                                                                                          viewpoint&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Note&#13;
          Credit scheme          Competition fuels                                                                        is an open forum to&#13;
            kick-starts            demand for             1. An early example was the peer review process&#13;
                                                                                                                          encourage dissemination of&#13;
           competition              evaluation         launched in the Consultative Group to Assist the Poor&#13;
                                                                                                                          public policy innovations for&#13;
                                                       (CGAP), where donors reviewed and rated one another&#13;
                                                                                                                          private sector­led and&#13;
                                                       (http://www.cgap.org/projects/donor_peer_reviews.html).&#13;
                                                                                                                          market-based solutions for&#13;
posed to be disbursed according to objective cri-&#13;
                                                                                                                          development. The views&#13;
teria, and it was scrutinized to see whether it lived  References&#13;
                                                                                                                          published are those of the&#13;
up to this promise.) Political aid did not stop, but      Djankov, Simeon, Jose G. Montalvo, and Marta Reynal-            authors and should not be&#13;
it shrank--and benevolent aid burgeoned as pub-        Querol. 2004. "Determinants of Aid Effectiveness." World           attributed to the World&#13;
licsuspicionofforeignaidebbedinrichcountries.          Bank, Washington, D.C.                                             Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
&#13;
                                                          Easterly, William. 2002. "The Cartel of Good                    organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
&#13;
Struggling with the big issues in 2030                 Intentions." Foreign Policy (July­August): 40­49.                  the conclusions represent&#13;
&#13;
All this is not to say that the aid industry of 2030      Foster, Mick, and Andrew Keith. 2003. "The Case for             official policy of the World&#13;
&#13;
functions perfectly. While many problems have          Increased Aid: Report to the Department for International          Bank or of its Executive&#13;
&#13;
been solved or are being convincingly addressed,       Development." Overseas Development Institute, London.              Directors or the countries&#13;
&#13;
others seem intractable, even given the achieve-       http://www.odi.org.uk/PPPG/cape/seminars/may04papers/              they represent.&#13;
&#13;
ments of today's aid system.                           Foster_Case_for_Increased_Aid.pdf.&#13;
&#13;
    The problems are twofold. The first is to             Kanbur, Ravi, and Todd Sandler. 1999. "The Future of            To order additional copies&#13;
&#13;
address global dangers such as contagious diseases     Development Assistance: Common Pools and International             contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
&#13;
or global warming. The technical work of design-       PublicGoods."OverseasDevelopmentCouncil,Washington,                managing editor,&#13;
&#13;
ing solutions is not hard. What gets in the way is                                                                        Room F 4K-206,&#13;
                                                       D.C.&#13;
&#13;
politics. As the world gets richer, countries have                                                                        The World Bank,&#13;
                                                          Knack, Stephen. 2000. "Aid Dependence and the&#13;
                                                                                                                          1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
the luxury of taking an obstructive stance on one      Quality of Governance: A Cross-Country Empirical&#13;
                                                                                                                          Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
project or another. In 2005 religious and cultural     Analysis." Policy Research Working Paper 2396. World&#13;
&#13;
disputes were already undermining global coop-         Bank, Development Research Group, Washington, D.C.&#13;
                                                                                                                          Telephone:&#13;
eration on HIV/AIDS, though few people foresaw            Martin, Facundo, Tim Harford, and Michael Klein.&#13;
                                                                                                                          001 202 458 7281&#13;
that the disputes would worsen rather than ease.       Forthcoming. "The Demand for Aid." Viewpoint. World&#13;
                                                                                                                          Fax:&#13;
Policy on climate change was even more theologi-       Bank, Private Sector Development Vice Presidency,&#13;
                                                                                                                          001 202 522 3480&#13;
cal. That such value differences continue to be as     Washington, D.C.&#13;
                                                                                                                          Email:&#13;
important as ever is hardly a surprise.                   Rogerson,Andrew.2004."TheInternationalAidSystem&#13;
                                                                                                                          ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
    The second problem is to deal with failed          2005­2010: Forces For and Against Change." ODI Working&#13;
&#13;
states. Although they have been a hot topic for        Paper 235. Overseas Development Institute, London.&#13;
                                                                                                                          Produced by Grammarians,&#13;
more than three decades, the international com-        http://www.odi.org.uk/publications/web_papers/                     Inc.&#13;
munity has yet to formulate an effective response.     aid_system_rogerson.pdf.&#13;
&#13;
In many failed states entrepreneurs are scraping          UN Millennium Project. 2005. Investing in Development:          Printed on recycled paper&#13;
out a living by tapping into the laws and institu-     A Practical Plan to Achieve the Millennium Development Goals.&#13;
&#13;
tions of the outside world. But failed states simply   New York. http://unmp.forumone.com/.&#13;
&#13;
do not fit the strictures of the common pool. In&#13;
the past few years we have seen promising exper-&#13;
iments using private firms and NGOs to deliver&#13;
services while bypassing governments. The hope&#13;
is that these new approaches will help countries&#13;
reach a point where the official aid system can&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 T h i s N o t e i s a v a i l a b l e o n l i n e :&#13;
                                                                   h t t p : / / r r u . w o r l d b a n k . o r g / P u b l i c P o l i c y J o u r n a l&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5741910">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/03/5741910/future-aid-2-big-push
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/03/5741910/future-aid-2-big-push</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/03/5741910/future-aid-2-big-push</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/04/18/000112742_20050418121636/Rendered/INDEX/321250285Harford1Klein.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/04/18/000112742_20050418121636/Rendered/PDF/321250285Harford1Klein.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2005-03-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2005-04-18T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The future of aid 2 : the big push
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This note considers the future of aid
            from the perspective of the 2005-2030 time frame. It offers
            a possible scenario for the future, with responses of the
            aid industry to falling numbers of people in absolute
            poverty and to the growing ability of poor countries to
            borrow from the market. A companion note (report 32124)
            offers a second scenario. The notes were written in the
            spirit of plausible stories about the future to encourage
            thinking about possible responses.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The future of aid 2 : the big push
        </docna>
        <display_title>The future of aid 2 : the big push</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2005/03/5741910/future-aid-2-big-push</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Development Economics &amp; Aid Effectiveness,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Poverty Assessment,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Poverty Reduction,Health, Nutrition and Population,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Harford, Tim</author>
            <author>Klien, Michael</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000112742_20050418121636</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 285</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Poverty Reduction,Health, Nutrition and Population,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            agriculture, Aid, aid agencies, aid flows,
            banks, bonds, Cartel, communities, debt, democratic
            institutions, Development Assistance, Development Goals,
            Development Research, development strategy, exchange rates,
            extreme poverty, forecasts, GDP,  inflation, International
            Aid, International Development, laws, municipalities,
            negotiations, new entrants, peer review, Policy Research,
            private banks, PRIVATE SECTOR, Public Goods, PUBLIC POLICY,
            service delivery, service providers, Technical assistance,
            World Development Indicators
        </keywd>
        <owner>KM and Outreach-IFC (FPDKM)</owner>
        <repnb>32125</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cartels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Horizontal Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Fixing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tuberculosis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Malaria</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anticartel Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competitive Industries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>