<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>THE HANDWASHING HANDBOOK&#13;
&#13;
                  A guide for developing&#13;
 a hygiene promotion program to increase&#13;
                handwashing with soap&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                      The&#13;
            Handwashing&#13;
                Handbook&#13;
A guide for developing a hygiene promotion program&#13;
         to increase handwashing with soap&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                              TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
FOREWORD          5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
EXECUTIVE SUMMARY 7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
INTRODUCTION            8&#13;
Context and Purpose of This Handbook&#13;
The Leading Causes of Child Mortality&#13;
Handwashing with Soap: The Most Effective Vaccine Against Childhood Infections?&#13;
The Challenge of Handwashing Promotion&#13;
What's New about This Approach?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION 1       13&#13;
Laying the Foundation for&#13;
a National Handwashing Program&#13;
Getting Started: Is This the Right Place at the Right Time?&#13;
Conducting a Rapid Situation Analysis&#13;
Public-Private Partnerships&#13;
Making the Case for Handwashing&#13;
  Making the Case to Government&#13;
  Making the Case to Industry&#13;
  Making the Case to Financiers&#13;
  Financing Issues&#13;
Organization and Coordination&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION 2       21&#13;
Understanding the Consumer&#13;
The Marketing Approach&#13;
  Understanding Behavior&#13;
Designing and Implementing the Consumer Research&#13;
Managing and Supervising the Consumer Research&#13;
Analysis and Reporting of the Results&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2 The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SECTION 3       33&#13;
Program Implementation&#13;
Designing the Campaign&#13;
  Applying the Marketing Mix&#13;
Developing the Promotion&#13;
  Target Audiences and Segmentation&#13;
Agencies, Concepts, and Testing&#13;
Multiple Strategies for Behavior Change&#13;
  Public Relations and Advocacy&#13;
  The PR Plan&#13;
  The Media Mix&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION 4       43&#13;
Program Organization&#13;
The Partnership Mix&#13;
  A General Partnership Model&#13;
  The Business Plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CONCLUSION           49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
REFERENCES AND RESOURCES               51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TOOLS AND TERMS OF REFERENCE             53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS           76&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               The Handwashing Handbook 3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                       LIST OF TABLES AND FIGURES&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1:  Distribution of Global Child Deaths by Cause&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2:  The F-Diagram: Major Transmission Routes of Fecal-Oral Diseases&#13;
&#13;
Table 1:   Observed Rates of Handwashing with Soap Around the World&#13;
&#13;
Table 2:   SWOT Analysis Factors&#13;
&#13;
Table 3:   SWOT External Factors&#13;
&#13;
Box 1:     The Cost-Effectiveness of Handwashing Programs&#13;
&#13;
Box 2:     The Central American Initiative&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3:  Consumer Research Process&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4:  Drivers, Habits, and Environment in Behavior Change&#13;
&#13;
Box 3:     Cultural Beliefs Inhibiting Handwashing with Soap in Senegal&#13;
&#13;
Table 4:   Drivers, Habits, and Environments for Handwashing with Soap (Four Areas)&#13;
&#13;
Table 5:   Identifying Barriers and Drivers to Handwashing with Soap at Key Events&#13;
&#13;
Box 4:     Ghana Consumers Prefer Multipurpose, Long-Lasting Soaps at Economy Prices&#13;
&#13;
Figure 5:  How Mothers Communicate in Kerala, India: Monthly Contact Profile&#13;
&#13;
Box 5:     A Note on Schools&#13;
&#13;
Table 6:   Summary Design for Consumer Research&#13;
&#13;
Box 6:     Outline of Study Methods&#13;
&#13;
Box 7:     Key Points for Contracting Consumer Research&#13;
&#13;
Box 8:     Consumer Research: The Rational Bias&#13;
&#13;
Box 9:     The Perfect Brief&#13;
&#13;
Table 7:   Advantages and Disadvantages of Different Approaches to Communication&#13;
&#13;
Box 10:    A Lesson in Public Relations: Handwashing in Kerala, India&#13;
&#13;
Table 8:   The Ghana National Handwashing Initiative: Phase 1 Evaluation Results (in Percentages)&#13;
&#13;
Figure 6:  Monitoring and Evaluation: Program Activities and Impact&#13;
&#13;
Box 11:    Handwashing in Action: The Handwashing Partnership in Peru&#13;
&#13;
Box 12:    Private Sector Handwashing Activities&#13;
&#13;
Box 13:    Elements of the Business Plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4  The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                FOREWORD&#13;
&#13;
Hygiene is essential to the public health mission of reducing the transmission and consequences of disease. The sharp&#13;
decline in deaths from infectious diseases observed in wealthy countries last century could not have been achieved&#13;
without vastly improved public hygiene. Raising living standards allowed people to become more hygienic once clean&#13;
water was piped into their homes, and soap became cheap enough to put at every sink. Eventually, the collective efforts&#13;
of both the public health movement and private industry ensured that clean hands, clean homes, and clean lives,&#13;
became a social norm.&#13;
&#13;
Unfortunately, the story in poor countries could not be more different. By the end of the 20th century, two billion&#13;
people still had inadequate access to sanitation, and one billion were without enough clean water to drink. Efforts at&#13;
promoting effective hygiene have been piecemeal and ineffective. Though industry has succeeded in getting soap into&#13;
almost every home, it has not consistently promoted good hygiene or handwashing to accompany their products.&#13;
&#13;
This is a missed opportunity for public health. The two biggest killers of children in the developing world today are&#13;
diarrheal disease and respiratory tract infections. The simple act of washing hands with soap can cut diarrhea risk by&#13;
almost half, and respiratory tract infection by a third. This makes handwashing a better option for disease prevention&#13;
than any single vaccine.&#13;
&#13;
If developing countries are to achieve their 2015 millennium development targets for reductions in child mortality, this&#13;
unfinished agenda of the 20th century must be completed. Not only must water and sanitation become universal, but&#13;
so must the habit of handwashing with soap. This requires Ministries of Health, Education, and Water, in addition to&#13;
non-governmental organizations (NGOs) and community-based groups, to exploit every opportunity to promote&#13;
handwashing with soap.&#13;
&#13;
Moreover, private industry, which played such a large part in creating standards of good hygiene in rich countries, can do&#13;
the same as it expands its business in developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
Handwashing with soap can and must become commonplace in developing countries. To do this we have to:&#13;
&#13;
! Make sure everyone knows the importance of handwashing&#13;
&#13;
! Build alliances between the public and the private sectors&#13;
&#13;
! Mobilize the necessary resources and expertise&#13;
&#13;
! Use proven high-impact communications outreach to promote handwashing to a mass audience&#13;
&#13;
! Demonstrate that measurable changes in behavior can be achieved cost-effectively.&#13;
&#13;
In a noisy world of competing messages aimed at people from all directions, only the most effective,&#13;
best-designed campaigns will lead to behavior change. This handbook seeks to meet this challenge.&#13;
&#13;
It describes a new approach to handwashing promotion, building on the pioneering work of the&#13;
Public-Private Partnership for Handwashing with Soap. It explains how the latest thinking in industrial marketing can be&#13;
combined with the latest research in public health to provide powerful new insights to drive effective handwashing&#13;
campaigns. It offers lessons from national programs in Ghana, Peru, Senegal, and other countries. Early indicators&#13;
suggest that this may be the start of an exciting new field in public health in the 21st century.&#13;
&#13;
Several members of the Global Public-Private Partnership for Handwashing Initiative must be acknowledged for making&#13;
this handbook possible. We would especially like to thank Beth Scott, Val Curtis, and Jason Cardosi for compiling this&#13;
guide. We are grateful to Ali Diouf, Rocio Florez, and Nana Garbrah-Aidoo for providing country examples. Special&#13;
thanks go to Peter Kolsky, Mariam Claeson, Stéphane Legros, and Nancy Lee for their in-depth peer reviews. Valuable&#13;
contributions were also made by Steve Luby, Eckhard Kleinau, Suzanne Reiff, Camille Saade, Myriam Sidibe, Barbara&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           The Handwashing Handbook      5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Evans, Sandy Callier, Joana Godinho, Wendy Wakeman, Merri Weigner, and Henk Van Norden. The private sector&#13;
partners, Yuri Jain from Hindustan Lever, Diana Grina from Colgate-Palmolive, and Tim Long from Procter and Gamble,&#13;
provided expertise and technical advice. Finally, we would like to acknowledge the guidance and leadership provided by&#13;
the Task Team Leaders, Jennifer Sara and Param Iyer.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Jamal Saghir                                                                                         Jacques Baudouy&#13;
&#13;
Director, Energy and Water                                                   Director, Health, Nutrition and Population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6   The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                       EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
&#13;
Handwashing is one of the most effective means of preventing diarrheal diseases, along with safe stool disposal and safe and adequate&#13;
household water supply. Evidence suggests that improved handwashing can have a major impact on public health in any country and&#13;
significantly reduce the two leading causes of childhood mortality ­ diarrheal disease and acute respiratory infection. Because&#13;
handwashing with soap can prevent the transmission of a variety of pathogens, it may be more effective than any single vaccine or&#13;
hygiene behavior. Promoted broadly enough, handwashing with soap can be viewed as an essential do-it-yourself vaccine. Almost&#13;
every household in the world, regardless of economic status, has soap. Handwashing with soap at key times, however, is not widely&#13;
practiced. If the millennium development targets for reduction in child mortality are to be met, handwashing habits must be improved&#13;
along with access to safe water and sanitation.&#13;
The Global Public-Private Partnership for Handwashing has brought together various organizations and sectors to promote&#13;
handwashing with soap on a large scale. The partnership includes:&#13;
! governments who, by prioritizing hygiene, enable handwashing to move from piecemeal, village-by-village, efforts to national&#13;
programs;&#13;
! donor organizations who increasingly include handwashing in their water, sanitation, health, and education programs;&#13;
! the private sector which has brought state-of-the art marketing knowledge and techniques to the table;&#13;
! academic and scientific organizations who are contributing the latest behavior change theory and scientific evidence of the&#13;
effectiveness of handwashing; and&#13;
! non-governmental and community-based organizations who are aiming to integrate handwashing messages into their own&#13;
work programs.&#13;
The Handwashing Handbook lays out the experiences of this global partnership in a practical guide. While countries are still&#13;
optimizing and experimenting with approaches, it is important to disseminate what is currently known. This way others can begin&#13;
designing programs and contributing to the global body of knowledge and experience in the fight against child mortality. This guide&#13;
is for staff in governments and development organizations charged with carrying out handwashing programs. Decision makers in&#13;
ministries and funding agencies will also find assistance in this book for designing policies and programs to improve public health.&#13;
The approach to large-scale handwashing promotion covers the following components:&#13;
Laying the Foundation for a National Handwashing Program&#13;
To be successful, handwashing programs must address a recognized health need and have the support of key stakeholders.&#13;
Government, industry, and donors can all offer unique resources which are necessary to ensure the success of a large-scale&#13;
program. Conducting a situation assessment and, where needed, making the case for handwashing on topics ranging from cost-&#13;
effectiveness to health impact will give the handwashing program a solid foundation.&#13;
Understanding the Consumer&#13;
In order to change long-held habits related to behaviors such as handwashing, a firm understanding of the factors the drive and&#13;
facilitate behaviors in target consumers must be established. This means putting the needs of the target audience ­ primarily&#13;
mothers and caretakers of children under five years old as well as school-aged children ­ at the center and having their perspective&#13;
determine the nature and scope of all promotion activities. Carrying out consumer research provides a baseline for measurement&#13;
and understanding of the target audience by answering four broad questions: What are the risk practices? Who carries out the risk&#13;
practices? What drivers, habits, and/or environmental factors can change behavior? How do people communicate?&#13;
Program Implementation&#13;
The results of consumer research drive program implementation including which environmental factors related to handwashing&#13;
need to be addressed, what is the most appropriate and appealing way to promote handwashing, and what is best mix of&#13;
communication channels to reach the target audience. Implementation also includes the careful monitoring of the program and&#13;
periodic evaluation and adjustment.&#13;
Program Organization&#13;
When partners from different backgrounds and sectors are not accustomed to working together, establishing common aims and&#13;
trust takes time and effort. Placing a program coordinator in a trusted organization is an effective approach to steering diverse&#13;
partners towards a common objective.&#13;
Throughout the handbook, references, case study information, and tools are provided to support handwashing programs. Users&#13;
are encouraged to combine their creativity with existing knowledge in order to innovate and optimize approaches to large-scale&#13;
handwashing promotion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     The Handwashing Handbook      7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             INTRODUCTION&#13;
&#13;
Purpose of This Handbook&#13;
This handbook grows out of the experience of the Global Public-Private Partnership for Handwashing with Soap&#13;
(PPPHW) and its predecessor, the Central American Handwashing for Diarrheal Disease Prevention Program. These&#13;
efforts demonstrated that mass programs with public and private sector involvement can be successful in promoting&#13;
handwashing and reducing disease. With core support from the Bank Netherlands Water Partnership, the PPPHW has&#13;
brought together global public and private agencies to consolidate approaches while initiating large-scale handwashing&#13;
promotion in Ghana, Peru, Senegal, and Nepal.&#13;
&#13;
While much has been learned about handwashing promotion in recent years, especially in the areas of research and&#13;
program design, countries are still experimenting with, and optimizing approaches to implementation. It is important to&#13;
lay out what is known so that others can begin designing programs and contributing to a global body of knowledge and&#13;
experience in the fight against child mortality.&#13;
&#13;
This handbook is intended for staff in government and development organizations charged with carrying out handwashing&#13;
programs. Decision-makers in Ministries and funding agencies will also find assistance in designing policies and programs&#13;
to improve public health.&#13;
&#13;
Context&#13;
Handwashing is one of the most effective means of preventing diarrheal diseases, along with safe stool disposal and safe&#13;
and adequate household water supply. This handbook focuses entirely on handwashing and advocates for stand-alone&#13;
handwashing-with-soap programs.&#13;
&#13;
It is not the intention of this guide to detract from hygiene behaviors other than handwashing. On the contrary, each has&#13;
a place and should be addressed distinctly, carefully, and in the right context. However, it is axiomatic in communications&#13;
programs that messages have to be single and simple: economies of scale do not operate at the level of message&#13;
delivery. For example, conveying two messages in a single communication reduces the effectiveness of each by half.&#13;
Consequently, lumping the three key hygiene behaviors together is inadvisable.&#13;
&#13;
The handwashing promotion approach described in this book involves careful consumer research followed by&#13;
up-to-date marketing efforts. This approach adapts itself well to other health issues, and lessons learned from&#13;
carrying out a handwashing program could clearly be applied to other programs using similar technical and&#13;
institutional approaches.&#13;
&#13;
Current efforts to promote good hygiene, including handwashing, have not been sufficient to engender mass behavior&#13;
change. Many public health programs include improved hygiene among their objectives: in any country at any time,&#13;
one might find a diarrheal disease control program, a school health education program that includes hygiene, a water&#13;
supply and sanitation program that invests in raising hygiene awareness, and sporadic local-level hygiene education.&#13;
All these efforts share the weakness of treating hygiene as a side issue, rather than a central one. Sufficient resources&#13;
are lacking; imagination, human skills, and enthusiasm are not fully engaged; and the approaches may be outdated.&#13;
No one agency champions hygiene, and financing bodies do not see its importance. Objectives committed to paper&#13;
are never fully operationalized, resourced, evaluated, or monitored. Successes have largely been confined to individual&#13;
villages, achieved by approaches that cannot be scaled up countrywide. Worse, confusion reigns at the most basic&#13;
level as to what good hygiene is: different actors define it differently, and prejudice and local preference take&#13;
precedence over evidence.&#13;
&#13;
The approach outlined here aims to resolve all of these problems: it raises awareness, enhances political commitment&#13;
and resource allocation for hygiene, offers a route to a coordinated national program, combining them all under one&#13;
umbrella. It also uses high-profile and up-to-date methodologies to change the hygiene behavior which consistently&#13;
demonstrates the greatest potential impact on overall public health; handwashing with soap.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8     The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Just as every child has a right to vaccination, each should also have the right to protection from hand-&#13;
transmitted disease. This means simply washing hands with soap after using the toilet or cleaning a child and&#13;
before handling food.&#13;
&#13;
The Leading Causes of Child Mortality&#13;
The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that diarrhea and respiratory infections are responsible for two-&#13;
thirds of child deaths (figure 1). UNICEF estimates that diarrhea alone kills one child every 30 seconds. The vast&#13;
majority of child mortality occurs among the world's poorest populations in low- and middle-income countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Figure 1: Distribution of Global Child Deaths by Cause&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Measles&#13;
                          2%         Other&#13;
                                      13%                          Diarrheal&#13;
                          AIDS                                     Diseases&#13;
                          5%                                         35%&#13;
&#13;
                        Malaria&#13;
                          13%&#13;
&#13;
                                           Acute&#13;
                                         Respiratory&#13;
                                          Infections&#13;
                                            32%                             Source: WHO 2001&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Handwashing with Soap:&#13;
The Most Effective Vaccine against Childhood Infections?&#13;
Human feces are the main source of diarrheal pathogens. They are also the source of shigellosis, typhoid, cholera, all&#13;
other common endemic gastro-enteric infections, and some respiratory infections: just one gram of human feces can&#13;
contain 10 million viruses and one million bacteria. These pathogens are passed from an infected host to a new one via&#13;
various routes, as shown in figure 2. While the routes are numerous, they all emanate from one source: feces. While&#13;
secondary measures (food handling, water purification, and fly control) may have an impact, far more important are the&#13;
primary barriers ­ sanitation and handwashing ­ after fecal contact. These barriers prevent fecal pathogens from&#13;
reaching the domestic environment in the first place.&#13;
&#13;
Handwashing interrupts the transmission of disease agents and so can significantly reduce diarrhea and respiratory&#13;
infections, as well as skin infections and trachoma. A recent review (Curtis and Cairncross 2003) suggests that&#13;
handwashing with soap, particularly after contact with feces (post-defecation and after handling a child's stool), can&#13;
reduce diarrheal incidence by 42-47 percent, while ongoing work by Rabie et al. suggests a 30 percent reduction in&#13;
respiratory infections is possible through handwashing. This remains true even in areas that are highly fecally&#13;
contaminated and have poor sanitation. Another current study found that children under 15 years living in households&#13;
that received handwashing promotion and soap had half the diarrheal rates of children living in control neighborhoods&#13;
(Luby et al. 2004). Because handwashing can prevent the transmission of a variety of pathogens, it may be more&#13;
effective than any single vaccine. Promoted on a wide-enough scale, handwashing with soap could be thought of as&#13;
a `do-it-yourself' vaccine.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         The Handwashing Handbook    9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
         Figure 2: The F-Diagram: Major Transmission Routes of Fecal-Oral Diseases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Fields&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Fluids&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       New&#13;
             Feces                                                                   Foods                             Host&#13;
&#13;
                                         Flies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Fingers&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Source: Wagner and Lanois, 1958&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Feces are the source of diarrheal pathogens, microscopic `bugs.' As the figure shows, these bugs enter the environment&#13;
if not disposed of safely, and are then spread by the four F's: flies, on fingers, in fluids, and via surfaces, such as fields.&#13;
Cutting these routes of transmission is key to the prevention of diarrheal disease, but which of the many possible hygiene&#13;
practices would eliminate the most disease? Boiling or sterilizing water in the home would reduce diarrhea, but preventing&#13;
fecal pathogens from ever reaching household water is likely better and more cost-effective. Similarly, foods should&#13;
clearly be reheated carefully to kill any bugs that multiplied during storage, but preventing fecal pathogens from ever&#13;
reaching food is more effective.&#13;
&#13;
Two key actions isolate fecal material and prevent its reaching the environment and then the four F's. These actions are adequately&#13;
disposing of adult and child feces and handwashing with soap after touching feces. Such touching occurs after using a toilet or when&#13;
cleaning a child after defecation.&#13;
&#13;
Some respiratory tract infections, including the SARS-causing coronavirus, are also transmitted via the fecal-oral route or simply on&#13;
hands, so handwashing helps prevent these infections as well.&#13;
&#13;
How should hands be washed? The evidence suggests that soap ­ any soap ­ and water adequately remove microbe-containing&#13;
dirt from hands. Antibacterial soaps or other hand-sanitizing technologies have no additional advantage. Hands have to be fully&#13;
covered with soap and then rinsed off.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  10    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Challenge of Handwashing Promotion&#13;
If handwashing with soap is so important, why doesn't everyone do it?&#13;
&#13;
Table 1 suggests that worldwide rates of handwashing with soap are very low. While many wash their hands&#13;
with water, only a small percentage use soap at critical times.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Table 1: Observed Rates of Handwashing with Soap Around the World&#13;
&#13;
Setting                             Handwashing with Soap            Prevalence       Reference&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Kerala State, India                 After defecation                 34 percent       PPPHW&#13;
&#13;
                                    After cleaning up a child        35 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ghana                               After defecation                 3 percent        PPPHW&#13;
&#13;
                                    After cleaning up a child        3 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Peru                                After defecation                 6 percent        PPPHW&#13;
&#13;
                                    After cleaning up a child        30 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Senegal                             After defecation                 31 percent       PPPHW&#13;
&#13;
                                    After cleaning up a child        26 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Kolkata, India (slums)              After defecation                 16 percent       Sircar et al. 1996&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Kyrgyzstan (rural)                  After cleaning up a child        0 percent        Biran 1999&#13;
&#13;
                                    After using a toilet             18 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Nigeria (rural)                     After cleaning up a child        10 percent       Omotade et al. 1995&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Burkina Faso (urban)                After cleaning up a child        13 percent       Curtis et al. 2001&#13;
&#13;
                                    After using a toilet             1 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Brazil (childcare centers)          After cleaning up a child        16 percent       Barros et al. 1999&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Lima, Peru (shanty town)            After defecation                 12 percent       Gilman et al. 1993&#13;
                                    (soap use `rare')&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Northern England (peri-urban)       After cleaning up a child        47 percent       Curtis et al. 2003&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Note: All prevalences are observed, except Sircar et al., which used soap measurements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    The Handwashing Handbook 11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The cause of low handwashing rates is rarely a lack of soap. Soap is present in the vast majority of households worldwide,&#13;
but it is commonly used for bathing and laundry, not handwashing. Lack of water is usually not a problem either, as hands&#13;
can be effectively washed with little, or recycled, water. In studies around the world, the main reason given why rates&#13;
of handwashing with soap are so low is that it is simply not a habit.&#13;
&#13;
The challenge remains ­ to make handwashing with soap a habit and a social norm on a worldwide basis.&#13;
&#13;
What's New about This Approach?&#13;
This handbook outlines how handwashing behavior can be changed on a large or national scale by providing lessons from&#13;
industrial marketing approaches as well as from current public health thinking. Its core feature is a focus on the&#13;
potential handwasher as a consumer, who has many choices to make. With the handwasher as the focal point, this&#13;
handbook explains how to:&#13;
&#13;
! Research consumer needs to delve into handwashing habits, barriers and drivers of behavior change, and the best&#13;
ways to communicate to the target audience;&#13;
&#13;
! Design appropriate and appealing messages; and&#13;
&#13;
! Implement a promotion program that makes use of all suitable channels, including outreach workers,&#13;
citizen networks, special events, soap distributors, schools, and mass media.&#13;
&#13;
Section 1 of this handbook describes the foundations for a national handwashing program. Section 2 discusses how to&#13;
understand consumers so that the handwashing campaign can be designed around their reality. Section 3 explains how&#13;
new insights can become a campaign that is effective in changing handwashing behavior. Section 4 outlines the organization&#13;
of a handwashing program, providing information that spans the other stages; it is designed to be read in parallel with&#13;
previous sections. The annex provides examples of tools, such as study instrument and terms of reference.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
             SECTION 1&#13;
             Laying the&#13;
             Foundation&#13;
             for a National&#13;
             Handwashing&#13;
             Program&#13;
CURTIS&#13;
&#13;
      VAL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 The Handwashing Handbook 13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                            SECTION 1. Laying the Foundation&#13;
                          for a National Handwashing Program&#13;
&#13;
Getting Started: Is This the Right Place                      ! Firms are looking to enhance their profile and&#13;
at the Right Time?                                               corporate image.&#13;
A strong handwashing program can make a big&#13;
contribution to public health, but building that program      Donors and Other Partners&#13;
takes time, resources, effort, and commitment. To be          ! There are programs in health, water, sanitation, or&#13;
successful, handwashing programs must address                    hygiene within which handwashing could fit;&#13;
a recognized health need and have the support of&#13;
key stakeholders.                                             ! Donor organizations are looking to develop new&#13;
                                                                 models of partnership;&#13;
Conducting a Rapid Situation Analysis                         ! NGOs can integrate handwashing into existing&#13;
A situation analysis can determine whether a country             programs; and&#13;
has a supportive environment for a handwashing program&#13;
and whether champions exist or can be created in              ! Others, such as healthcare providers, water&#13;
government, among donors, and in the private sector.             companies, and religious and community groups, are&#13;
                                                                 looking to play a major role in public health.&#13;
The first determinant of success is a health need,&#13;
such as:                                                      The likelihood of a successful, large-scale, and timely&#13;
                                                              program will increase with the number of factors that&#13;
! Diarrheaandrespiratorytractinfectionsaresignificant         exist or can be created.&#13;
    causes of morbidity and mortality;&#13;
&#13;
! Rates of handwashing with soap at key junctures are         Public-Private Partnerships&#13;
    low, or at least suspected to be; or                      Because both the public and private sectors have an&#13;
                                                              interest in promoting handwashing, country programs&#13;
! Cholera,typhoid,orSARSisrecognizedasaproblem.               usually take the form of a public-private partnership&#13;
If a health need exists, assessing interest and capacity      (PPP). While the public sector can be wary of working&#13;
within key stakeholder groups will help determine the         with industry and the private sector skeptical that working&#13;
viability of an initiative and how it can best be organized.  with government would produce significant results, both&#13;
Typical groups and issues to consider include:                sectors stand to gain from cooperation.&#13;
&#13;
                                                              First, industry typically invests a significant portion of its&#13;
Government                                                    energiesintounderstandingtheconsumerinordertomake&#13;
! ThecountryhascommittedtomeetingtheMillennium                and promote appropriate products. Hygiene promotion&#13;
    Development Goals (MDGs) and has a Poverty                programs generally lack this expertise, which is not widely&#13;
    Reduction Strategy;                                       available in the public sector.&#13;
&#13;
! Water, sanitation, and hygiene are government               Secondly, industry has already brought soap for bathing&#13;
    priorities; and                                           and laundering into over 90 percent of households&#13;
                                                              worldwide, showing how successful it can be at making&#13;
! Potential champions exist in Ministries of Health,          soap and its accompanying behaviors almost ubiquitous. In&#13;
    Education, and Water.                                     developed countries, industry was instrumental in changing&#13;
                                                              domestic hygiene practices; it can do the same in poorer&#13;
Industry                                                      communities while benefiting from market expansion.&#13;
! A soap market exists;&#13;
                                                              The private sector stands to gain from a PPP, mostly&#13;
! There is room for growth in the soap and related            through market expansion. In addition, the benefits of&#13;
    industries (e.g., plastics companies producing water      being seen as contributing to social goals and of being at&#13;
    tanks), especially in poor market segments; and           the table with development partners and international&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
            experts can also be substantial. In addition, many soap      Where skepticism might deter private sector&#13;
            company executives are glad to be involved in efforts to     involvement, it may be advantageous to label a public-&#13;
            improve social well-being.                                   private partnership an `Alliance for Handwashing.'&#13;
&#13;
            In summary, the public sector gains from the marketing&#13;
            expertise and resources of industry. Teamed, both parties    Making the Case for Handwashing&#13;
            can produce public health campaigns that rival ­ or surpass  If a handwashing program is to succeed, advocates will&#13;
            ­ industrial marketing efforts.                              have to sell the idea to stakeholders, including&#13;
                                                                         government, industry, and potential funders. A SWOT&#13;
            Industry is already making efforts to promote handwashing    (strengths, weaknesses, opportunities, and threats)&#13;
            as part of ongoing marketing or social responsibility        analysis can determine which factors need to be&#13;
            programs. Colgate-Palmolive, Procter and Gamble, and         addressed when engaging these stakeholders. First, the&#13;
            Hindustan Lever have school-based programs in many           SWOT analysis looks at factors that can potentially be&#13;
            countries that educate children about handwashing (see       controlled by the stakeholders as potential partners in&#13;
            box 11 for details). Such companies may already be           the initiative (table 2).&#13;
            converts to the handwashing message and ready to&#13;
            participate in partnerships with the public sector. Issues   Second, external factors are assessed. These factors&#13;
            of branding and exclusive rights will often need to be       are outside the influence of the initiative but may&#13;
            discussed and agreed upon.                                   have a positive or negative impact on the target&#13;
                                                                         audiences. Table 3 will help an initiative develop a&#13;
            Other industries may be willing and able to contribute       list of external factors.&#13;
            resources, expertise, or in-kind contributions to PPPs.&#13;
            These sectors include the water industry, media              Third, stakeholders can be engaged in partnership in order&#13;
            companies, manufacturers of tanks and pipes, and             to address weaknesses, build strengths, recognize&#13;
            transport companies, etc. For example, in Ghana,             opportunities, and mitigate threats.&#13;
            Polytank, a plastics company that manufactures water&#13;
            storage tanks, intends to provide tanks to schools at cost   Making the Case to Government&#13;
            or lower. Companies that do not contribute directly          Key issues that will drive government interest are the&#13;
            might be encouraged to carry the handwashing message         scale of the health problem and links to targets such as&#13;
            on their products, such as on soap, handwashing buckets,     the MDGs, the economic costs of disease caused by not&#13;
            or toilet paper rolls. This increases the intensity of the   washing hands, links to poverty reduction, and costs of&#13;
            handwashing message in the environment.                      treatment and work time lost.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
REIFF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     SUZANNE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   The Handwashing Handbook     15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                     Table 2: SWOT Analysis Factors&#13;
&#13;
     Factors within Sphere of Control                   Strengths       Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
     Sources of funding&#13;
&#13;
     Experience&#13;
&#13;
     Expertise&#13;
&#13;
     Ability to reach and serve target audiences&#13;
&#13;
     Management and political support&#13;
&#13;
     Issue priority for the organization&#13;
&#13;
     Current alliances and partnerships&#13;
&#13;
     Others&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Table 3: SWOT External Factors&#13;
&#13;
     External Factors                                  Opportunities    Threats&#13;
&#13;
     Cultural forces (including trends and events&#13;
     that affect the country's values and norms)&#13;
&#13;
     Technological forces (noting the potential for&#13;
     new technologies that might be leveraged)&#13;
&#13;
     Demographic trends (relevant to the campaign)&#13;
&#13;
     Economic forces (that could impact success)&#13;
&#13;
     Political and legal forces (that may&#13;
     affect campaign efforts or target audiences)&#13;
&#13;
     External publics (groups outside the initiative&#13;
     and its alliances that could have an impact&#13;
     on the target audience or the plan)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16 The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Investigating these issues will produce the arguments to     As mentioned, industry can, and should, play a key role&#13;
convince decision-makers to support handwashing              in promoting handwashing in the countries where it is&#13;
programs. Good sources for information on disease rates      most needed. Attracting industry support has not always&#13;
include national community-based surveys, such as            proved as straightforward as expected. When economic&#13;
Demographic Health Surveys. (Health facility reporting       times are good, soap companies have some latitude in&#13;
is a poor data source because it fails to capture a          spending, but during downturns, all available resources&#13;
community's infectious disease rates.) The costs to society  tend to be targeted at brand support.&#13;
and to an economy of not washing hands can be estimated&#13;
by calculating the cost of (a) treatment for hand-borne      Because the current PPP model proscribes the use of&#13;
infections; (b) working days lost; and (c) deaths due to     branding in programs with public funding, industry's&#13;
diarrhea and respiratory infection. In addition, a national  interest is reduced.&#13;
program can save money by replacing piecemeal hygiene        The problem can be resolved on several fronts. High-&#13;
promotion activities with a broader, more cost-effective     level, headquarters commitment and support may be&#13;
approach (see box 1).                                        essential to ensure commitment of funds and technical&#13;
Water and sanitation programs are attractive to              resources at country level. Companies often ask for an&#13;
governments because they involve the purchase and            exclusive deal with the partnership in return for substantial&#13;
installation of hardware. It can be very difficult to make   support. It may be possible to unlock this source of&#13;
the case that some of this funding be diverted to what is    resources by splitting particular activities and allowing&#13;
seen as a `soft' issue, that of handwashing. Though some     branding within them. So, for example, in Ghana, Unilever&#13;
international organizations and governments are swinging     might support a schools program and PZ-Cussons a&#13;
towards increased investment in hygiene, acceptance is       maternity hospital bounty-pack scheme.&#13;
slow. Advocacy efforts as to the relative importance of&#13;
the software issues have to be made repeatedly and at        Making the Case to Financiers&#13;
every opportunity.                                           Though they technically work through governments,&#13;
                                                             external support agencies often have their own agendas&#13;
Making the Case to Industry                                  andusuallytheirownfundingcycles.Ashandwashingmoves&#13;
&#13;
Though industry likes to be a good citizen, what drives      up the international list of priorities, more and more&#13;
&#13;
country-level activities is profit. Industries invest time,  organizations are preparing to invest in handwashing&#13;
&#13;
expertise, and resources where they see a potential          promotion. To obtain donor support, it is important to&#13;
&#13;
profit. It is therefore vital to make estimates of           determinedonors'priorities,wheredecision-makingability&#13;
&#13;
potential growth in the whole soap market. For               lies, and the mechanisms for obtaining funding.&#13;
&#13;
example, one could estimate that each handwashing            Decision-making about the use of funds from bilateral&#13;
event uses 0.5 grams of soap; this factor can be             agencies, such as the Danish International Development&#13;
multiplied by the population of the target area, the         Agency (DANIDA) and the United Kingdom Department&#13;
average number of times a person would wash hands            for International Development (DFID), is increasingly&#13;
each day, and the number of days in the period being         devolved to the national level, and accessing them may&#13;
considered. The resulting estimate would show how            require lobbying at local, government, and international&#13;
much more soap could be sold to each individual. Note        levels. Multilateral agencies, such as the United Nations&#13;
that the soap brands that may benefit include laundry        Children's Fund (UNICEF), may have programs that can&#13;
bars and locally made soaps, not just toilet soaps or        support handwashing in parts of a country. Lastly,&#13;
special handwashing formulations.                            World Bank loans for water and sanitation may specify&#13;
                                                             expenditure on hygiene.&#13;
Other potential benefits to industry include being&#13;
able to extend or stretch existing brands, grow&#13;
existing handwashing brands, raise visibility, and           Financing Issues&#13;
improve political contacts. Businesses, both small and       Initially, funds are needed to cover the costs of a program&#13;
large, will also benefit from the market research and        start-up, which usually entails an individual and/or&#13;
international contact. Multinationals may see a wider        organization spearheading the initiative and acting as a&#13;
benefit of participating in a PPP, and involving the         coordinator. Funds are next needed for consumer&#13;
international headquarters can help drive country-           research and then to hire a communications agency. The&#13;
level investment.                                            agency needs a budget for mass media, direct consumer&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         The Handwashing Handbook     17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18 The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
contact, and government-based programs, so                     and donors have few existing budget lines for such&#13;
commitments for funding should be in place early.              nontraditional activities. However, it may be possible to&#13;
Fundraising is discussed as part of advocacy and public        tap into a government or agency desire to be seen as&#13;
relations efforts in sections 3 and 4.                         being proactive, especially when there is a perceived&#13;
                                                               threat to national health, such as a cholera outbreak or&#13;
Financing mass media activities has been particularly          natural disaster. Similarly, agencies may be more&#13;
challenging in several countries. The private sector has       forthcoming with support if they are offered visible credit&#13;
little spare cash not otherwise earmarked. Governments         on promotional materials.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Box 1: The Cost-Effectiveness of Handwashing Programs&#13;
&#13;
        Health projects rarely focus on handwashing to         policy makers are now, theoretically, able to&#13;
        improve value-for-money. However, there is             calculate and change some original assumptions on&#13;
        mounting international evidence that hygiene,          the effectiveness of the initiative. This can be&#13;
        sanitation, and health investment focused on           achieved by establishing control groups to isolate&#13;
        handwashing and other health promotion programs        the intervention and calculate disease reduction in&#13;
        are among the most cost-effective investments that     the intervention area.&#13;
        canbemadewithpublicandprivateresources.Esrey&#13;
        (1991), for instance, demonstrated that hygiene        The main results from the cost-benefit analysis&#13;
        promotion is often required for water supply and       indicate that both handwashing initiatives save costs&#13;
        sanitation projects to have an impact on health.       for their respective societies. The net present value&#13;
                                                               (NPV) of benefits for The Central American Project&#13;
        A recent handwashing cost-effectiveness study          is US$4.3 million in the base scenario with an&#13;
        developed a standardized methodology for               internal rate of return (IRR) of 226 percent. For&#13;
        performing an economic analysis of handwashing         the Peru initiative, the NPV of benefits represents&#13;
        interventions. First, a cost-effectiveness analysis    US$8.1 million, with an IRR of 533 percent.&#13;
        of handwashing initiatives is conducted to establish   Sensitivity analyses in both cases remain positive&#13;
        comparisons with the effectiveness of other            and confirm the cost savings of these projects.&#13;
        health-related projects and with projects in other&#13;
        sectors. A cost-benefit analysis of handwashing        The comparisons that are established reveal that&#13;
        initiatives is then prepared to compare their          handwashing initiatives do not represent greater&#13;
        impact in a broader context.                           burdens for Ministries of Health and that the&#13;
                                                               contribution of private partners is recommended&#13;
        This methodology found that the Central American       for mutual benefits. Promotion of the initiatives&#13;
        Handwashing Initiative (see box 2) is cost-effective,  and future participation of private actors is possible&#13;
        preventing diarrhea for less than US$10 per case       with an estimate of benefits for each partner with&#13;
        and averting a cost per DALY* of US$91.30. Even        respect to the investment. While the Central&#13;
        without the intervention, the presence of soap,        American initiative demonstrates that the presence&#13;
        water, and certain equipment in these countries is     of soap is almost universal, soap use still needs to&#13;
        generally high, so the economic analysis can discount  be improved, recommending an appropriate&#13;
        these costs, thereby lowering the private costs.       handwashing campaign that would incidentally&#13;
        The sensitivity analysis reveals that even             increase soap sales.&#13;
        considering a lower rate of reduction of diarrhea,&#13;
        the handwashing initiative remains cost-effective.     * DALY, Disability Adjusted Life Year, is the&#13;
                                                               quantitative indicator of burden of disease that&#13;
        Estimates made with this methodology for the           reflects the total amount of healthy life lost,&#13;
        Peruvian Handwashing initiative (see box 10) during    whether from premature mortality or some&#13;
        2003 show that preventing a case of diarrhea here      degree of disability during a period of time.&#13;
        also cost less than US$10, and the cost per DALY&#13;
        averted was US$122.70. With this evaluation,            Extracted from Cercone et al. 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           The Handwashing Handbook    19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   Box 2: The Central American Initiative&#13;
&#13;
       The Central American Handwashing Initiative was          ! Ten percent of mothers improved from an&#13;
       designed to reduce under-five morbidity and              `inadequate stage' of handwashing to either the&#13;
       mortality through a campaign to promote                  `intermediate' or `optimal' stage.&#13;
       handwashing with soap to prevent diarrhea.&#13;
       Carried out in five countries, the initiative consisted  ! A 10 percent decline in the number of mothers&#13;
       primarily of a PPP that included a number of public      who agreed with the inaccurate statement: "Most&#13;
       players and four private sector soap producers. The      times washing hands with water is sufficient."&#13;
       initiative promoted increased access to soap by&#13;
       distributing free samples, conducting promotional        ! A10percentincreaseinthenumberofmothers&#13;
       and educational events, and sponsoring media             who agreed with the statement: "When I don't&#13;
       activities to convey information on the link between     use soap, I feel that I am not clean."&#13;
       hygiene and diarrhea prevention.&#13;
                                                                Extrapolating from these and other findings and&#13;
       The public sector provided technical support and         from literature on the relationship between&#13;
       market research to soap companies, supported             handwashing and the prevalence of diarrhea, it was&#13;
       advertising agencies' involvement, and helped form&#13;
       a task force to coordinate and direct the efforts of     estimated that "over the course of the intervention&#13;
&#13;
       the various players. In the end, the greatest            there was a 4.5 percent reduction in diarrheal&#13;
&#13;
       contribution of the program may have been the            prevalence among children under five."&#13;
       model it presented for establishing how public           Source: Environmental Health Project (EHP), UNICEF/&#13;
       health goals can be compatible with business goals.      WES, United States Agency for International&#13;
       In Guatemala, where the work was most carefully          Development (USAID), and World Bank/WSP and&#13;
       documented, the initiative resulted in:                  WSSCC, May 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Organization and Coordination                                   or neutral party and provide drive; enthusiasm; skills in&#13;
If an assessment finds favorable conditions, a first meeting    marketing; and knowledge of public health, management,&#13;
or workshop with potential stakeholders will help to            and communications. The coordinator could be in a public&#13;
consolidate ideas and interest. The agenda might include        agency, a private sector body (such as the local soap&#13;
experts outlining the importance of handwashing; a              manufacturer's umbrella organization), an agency, or&#13;
sharing of initial visions and expectations of potential        NGO. In Central America a catalyst organization was&#13;
stakeholders; and the establishment of initial                  set up to bring together public and private partners and&#13;
commitments, partnership structures, and milestones.            eventually phased itself out (see box 2).&#13;
&#13;
When setting out the vision and leading the program, it         This section has outlined key aspects of starting a&#13;
helps to have a country coordinator or catalyst. This           program. Further details about management and structure&#13;
individual or organization should be viewed as a legitimate     can be found in section 4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 SECTION 2&#13;
Understanding&#13;
the Consumer&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        The Handwashing Handbook 21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                           SECTION 2&#13;
                                       Understanding the Consumer&#13;
&#13;
The Marketing Approach                                                         Understanding Behavior&#13;
Once a platform for developing the handwashing work                            Consumer needs are many and varied. They may include&#13;
has been established and consensus reached on                                  the desire to be respected, to be clean, to feel&#13;
moving forward, the focus then shifts to the potential                         comfortable and fresh, and to provide the best for their&#13;
handwashers, called "consumers" in marketing                                   families. While health may seem an obvious need from&#13;
terminology. The only way to change long-held habits                           the point of view of the health professional, it may not&#13;
related to behaviors such as handwashing is to have a                          be the overriding or constant concern of the consumer.&#13;
firm understanding of the factors that drive and                               Industry invests heavily in understanding consumers' lives,&#13;
&#13;
facilitate handwashing in target consumers. The                                desires, and the ways they communicate in order to&#13;
                                                                               develop and deliver appropriate products and promotional&#13;
marketing approach means putting the needs of the                              messages. To market handwashing successfully, the&#13;
target audiences at the center and having their                                following four questions about consumers must be&#13;
perspective determine the nature and scope of all                              answered:&#13;
promotion activities.&#13;
                                                                               ! What are the risk practices?&#13;
Satisfaction of desires is at the core of marketing.&#13;
According to Northwestern University Marketing                                 ! Who carries out risk practices?&#13;
&#13;
Professor and author Philip Kotler, "Marketing is satisfying                   ! What drivers, habits, and/or environment can change&#13;
needs and wants through an exchange process."                                      behavior?&#13;
Marketers thus offer the consumer something that they&#13;
want and that they are prepared to make sacrifices for,                        ! How do people communicate?&#13;
either through expenditure of money, time, or effort.                          The answers to these questions provide the key elements&#13;
The heart of the marketing task is thus to find out what                       of consumer research. The process combines the insight&#13;
consumers want and then to offer it to them in a way                           of experts in consumer behavior, health, and handwashing&#13;
that will make it most attractive.                                             with the intelligence provided by consumers (figure 2).1&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   Figure 3&#13;
                                                       Consumer Research&#13;
                             Who carries                           Process&#13;
                                out risk                                                                Target&#13;
&#13;
                              practices?                                                               audiences&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              What are                                                                  Target&#13;
                            handwashing                           Consumers'                          handwashing&#13;
                              practices?                             views                              practice&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              What can                                                                  Drives,&#13;
                                change                             Experts'                             habits,&#13;
                              behavior?                              views                            facilitators&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               How do&#13;
                                people                                                                Media mix&#13;
                           communicate?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1Tools (such as Structured Observations and Behavioral Trials), formats, and terms of reference (TORs)&#13;
referred to in this section can be found in the annex.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                         habit                                                     drivers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        environment&#13;
   &#13;
&#13;
                                Figure 4: Environment, Habits, and Drivers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1. Who carries out risk practices? Handwashing programs        frequent handwashing is clearly protective against&#13;
target those groups whose handwashing behavior can             respiratory illness as well.&#13;
have the largest impact on disease reduction: this is usually&#13;
the caretaker who provides the child's `hygiene                It is essential to have reliable data on actual rates of&#13;
environment.' In most settings the primary caretaker is        handwashing with soap in any particular setting in order&#13;
the mother of the young child; however, it is important        to determine the scale of the problem and set&#13;
to document who else participates ­ grandmothers,              quantitative improvement targets. Such baseline data&#13;
sisters, fathers in some societies, aunts, etc. School-age     also provides a point from which to measure change in&#13;
children may also form a target audience, not so much          handwashing habits over the life of a proposed program.&#13;
because they too may provide childcare, but because            Unfortunately, actual handwashing behavior is very hard&#13;
they are the caretakers of the future. Furthermore, they       to assess reliably. Handwashing habits are generally&#13;
are more susceptible to behavior change and the uptake         private and are `morally bound': people fear they will&#13;
of new healthy habits. They can also act as enthusiastic       be judged harshly if they admit to a weakness in their&#13;
handwashing advocates. Sometimes secondary target&#13;
audiences (neighbors, fathers in some societies, elder         hygiene practices. Asking people if they wash their&#13;
&#13;
children, extended family) will also be addressed because      hands with soap consistently results in overestimates&#13;
&#13;
of their influence on the primary audience. For example,       of actual behavior. For example, in Ghana 75 percent&#13;
&#13;
in some societies husbands decide how much to spend            of mothers claimed to wash hands with soap after toilet&#13;
&#13;
on soap or serve as the purchaser of these goods for           use when asked, but structured observation showed&#13;
&#13;
their household.                                               that only 3 percent did so. The only feasible and reliable&#13;
                                                               way to obtain a valid measure of handwashing practice&#13;
2. What are the risk practices? As noted, handwashing          is through direct observation, which requires a trained&#13;
after contact with feces is usually the best way to            observer spending several hours in the home, observing&#13;
reduce the risk of fecal-oral transmission of gastro-          and recording events of interest in someone's home.&#13;
enteric pathogens. However, because this practice is           Well-trained and supervised fieldworkers are required&#13;
unlikely to ever be universal and because sanitation           for consistent and reliable results.&#13;
may also be poor, it is also important to wash hands&#13;
with soap before contacting, eating, or feeding food.          3. What can change behavior? Three key forces are&#13;
This means that handwashing at three junctures is              involved in behavior change: drivers, habits, and the&#13;
critical: after using the toilet, after cleaning up a child    environment, which can facilitate or hinder behavior&#13;
who has defecated, and before handling food. While             change. As figure 4 illustrates, moving behaviors&#13;
the important junctures for handwashing to prevent             from one point to another requires one or more&#13;
respiratory infection have not been identified, more           of three things:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         The Handwashing Handbook     23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
! Lowering barriers in the environment so as to               While habits are often learned at an early age, there are&#13;
    facilitate change;                                        opportunities for change, especially at life-changing&#13;
                                                              events. A key event for mothers is the birth of a baby.&#13;
! Transforming old habits into new ones; and                  Many mothers report that hand hygiene did not become&#13;
! Finding drivers that can create new habits.                 important to them until a baby was born and that if&#13;
                                                              midwives or others involved with perinatal care&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4: Environment, Habits,                                recommended handwashing with soap, it would likely&#13;
&#13;
and Drivers                                                   take hold. Another life-changing event for many mothers&#13;
                                                              is moving to the husband's home after marriage and&#13;
Consumer research delves into the consumer psyche to          learning the habits of the new household.&#13;
identify the deep desires and motives that can drive&#13;
behavior change, determine the source of habits and           Habits are best documented using structured observations&#13;
investigatehowbesttointroducenewones,andtoexplore             (tool 2). Their origins can be explored through in-depth&#13;
the factors in the environment that hinder or facilitate      interviews and the process of taking on new habits&#13;
behavior change. These can be established using a variety     understood in behavior trials.&#13;
of tools, including behavior trials and in-depth interviews.&#13;
                                                              Drivers are innate and learned modules in the brain that&#13;
Environmental facilitators and barriers are factors that      motivate particular behaviors. They come in the form of&#13;
enable or hinder the act of handwashing with soap.            emotions and the feelings that people report when&#13;
Facilitators might include easy access to water and the       carrying out particular behaviors. Discovering drivers is&#13;
low cost of soap. Barriers might include prohibitively        key to successfully promoting handwashing.&#13;
expensive or unattractive soap, lack of handwashing&#13;
facilities, and strong cultural prohibitions against washing  As with risk practices, determining drivers can be difficult&#13;
on certain days. Box 4 outlines the importance of specific    because (1) they may be buried in the subconscious&#13;
attributes of soap in Ghana that make it acceptable           (Zaltman 2003); and (2) there may be perceptions of&#13;
for handwashing.                                              shame or embarrassment in reporting them, for example,&#13;
                                                              using soap to heighten sexual attractiveness. Zaltman&#13;
Quantitative surveys provide basic information about the      suggests that at much as 95 percent of human thought&#13;
environment, such as availability of soap, distance to        takes place in the subconscious.&#13;
water, and access to sanitation. In-depth interviewing&#13;
following behavior trials can also help reveal barriers and   In-depth qualitative research into consumer motivations&#13;
facilitators (see tool 1).                                    in many countries shows a recognizable pattern of drivers&#13;
                                                              of handwashing behavior, as seen in table 4. Mothers&#13;
Barriers need to be first understood and then addressed       tend to be driven to handwashing by pride, status, social&#13;
as the communications program is developed. For               acceptance, and disgust of smells and contamination. They&#13;
instance, if distance to clean water is a barrier, the        also regard handwashing as an act of nurturance, part of&#13;
communications program can point out that a small             loving and caring for children. Women often think that&#13;
amount or recycled water suffices. Further, while a           only visibly dirty or smelly hands are potential sources of&#13;
communications campaign may not be able to directly           ill health, and even then, explicit relationships between&#13;
address physical barriers such as lack of handwashing         dirty hands, diarrhea, and disease are rarely cited.&#13;
facilities in schools, public relations (PR) and advocacy&#13;
activities may convince those who can help reduce such        While there appear to be some general cross-cultural&#13;
barriers. Demand from primary target audiences ­              motivations for handwashing and wider hygiene behaviors,&#13;
mothers and children ­ might also encourage the               their nuances and how they play out will be specific to&#13;
installation of handwashing facilities where necessary.       particular countries, as will the relative importance of&#13;
                                                              each motivation. This is also true of different segments&#13;
Habits are ingrained and sustained behaviors, often           of target audiences. For example, nurturance is unlikely&#13;
developed in childhood. Research has shown that once          to be a strong motivator among school-age children.&#13;
people anywhere acquire ingrained and habitual behaviors,     Consequently, country-specific consumer research is&#13;
they are not easily lost. The task for handwashing            needed to guide an effective marketing campaign.&#13;
promotion is not to achieve a single handwashing event,       Table 5 provides a simple format for identifying and&#13;
but to instill a routine and sustained habit that happens     notating barriers and drivers, while box 3 illustrates&#13;
automatically with every contaminating event.                 mothers' reports of cultural norms influencing their soap&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24     The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                          use in Senegal (note that these barriers are perceived&#13;
   Box 3: Cultural Beliefs Inhibiting                     rather than real). The barriers and drivers for handwashing&#13;
 Handwashing with Soap in Senegal                         with soap may be different for different key handwashing&#13;
                                                          times. These can be captured in a format such as table 4.&#13;
Consumer research in Senegal captured examples&#13;
of handwashing with soap that are related to habits       Behavioral trials, where volunteer mothers (and/or school&#13;
and barriers.                                             children) are given soap and asked to use it to practice&#13;
                                                          handwashing with soap for seven to 10 days, are a good&#13;
Ancestral and Religious Beliefs                           way to begin understanding local handwashing&#13;
Although no longer widely believed, some Senegalese       motivations. Following a trial, mothers are interviewed&#13;
take a "`better safe than sorry approach" when it         in-depth about their experiences, what was easy, what&#13;
&#13;
comes to traditional handwashing behavior. Using          was hard, what was liked and disliked, etc. Focus&#13;
soap during ritual cleaning prior to praying at the       group discussions (FGDs) with mothers and/or school&#13;
mosque removes some of the purity of the spiritual        children can be used to supplement these trials to&#13;
&#13;
cleansing because the blessed water is not                better understand the social nuances of handwashing&#13;
compatible with soap.                                     and associated motivations, as well as favored&#13;
                                                          communication channels.&#13;
Some women, especially in rural areas, still adhere&#13;
to a practice of not washing a child under the age of     How do people communicate? Finally, research has to&#13;
one for fear of reduced life expectancy. They may         determine where the target audience obtains information;&#13;
also reduce soap use during pregnancy to avoid harm       the reach of different channels of communication, both&#13;
&#13;
to the unborn baby. Some women also believe that          traditional and modern; which channels are trusted and&#13;
handwashing with soap might reduce fertility.             believed; and the best language(s) to use. The potential&#13;
                                                          effectiveness of different channels will differ among the&#13;
Fatalism                                                  various segments of the target audiences.&#13;
&#13;
A more common barrier is an attitude that one             There are two main sources of information on channels&#13;
cannot escape one's destiny; thus, being poor is          of communication. The first source is existing data. In&#13;
predetermined and dirtiness is simply part                most countries, commercial entities have already collected&#13;
of poverty.                                               detailed profiles of consumption of mass media, possibly&#13;
                                                          even covering mothers' and children's listening and&#13;
&#13;
                 Table 4: Drivers, Habits, and Environments for Handwashing&#13;
                                          with Soap (Four Areas)&#13;
&#13;
                                       Ghana           Kerala, India         Senegal          Wirral, UK&#13;
&#13;
      Drivers                      Nurture a child     Disgust               Pride/status     Disgust&#13;
                                   Disgust of          Social                Disgust          Status/pride&#13;
                                     contamination      acceptance           Nurture          Nurture&#13;
                                   Social              Nurture               Seduction        Aesthetics&#13;
                                     acceptance         family&#13;
&#13;
      Habit                        New baby            Moving                Water only,      New baby&#13;
                                   Taught by            household             not soap,       Learned from&#13;
                                     mother            New baby               is the habit      midwife&#13;
&#13;
      Environment:                 Distance to         Men control           Local            Convenience&#13;
      Facilitators/barriers          public toilet      soap                  customs         Forgetting&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      The Handwashing Handbook     25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                             Table 5: Identifying Barriers and Drivers to&#13;
                                Handwashing with Soap at Key Events&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Target Behavior (for Mothers)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Wash Hands with              Wash Hands with Soap             Wash Hands&#13;
                          Soap After Using             After Cleaning up a Child        Before Handling Food&#13;
                          the Toilet                   Who Has Defecated&#13;
&#13;
       Barriers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Drivers/&#13;
       benefits&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Box 4: Ghana Consumers Prefer Multipurpose,&#13;
                                Long-Lasting Soaps at Economy Prices&#13;
  Women in Ghana were asked what features they               as they thought they were longer lasting.&#13;
  favored in a handwashing soap for research purposes.       Thepreferenceforhardsoapswassostrongthatmany&#13;
  In commenting on favored features for soap, they           stored soap in cold or sunny places to harden them&#13;
  cited a range of attributes ­ smell, cost, texture,        before use: "I cut it into pieces and put it on the floor&#13;
  and durability ­ and its capacity to be used for           of a veranda to dry and harden so that it will be&#13;
  many purposes.                                             long in use."&#13;
&#13;
   Smell was the most important attribute. Overall,          Liquid soaps, as well as being economical ­ only a little&#13;
  mild lemon/lime scents were most popular.                  is used each time hands are washed ­ are favored for&#13;
  However, soaps with stronger scents were favored           convenience "with soap in its hard state, you need to&#13;
  for use after defecation, while as little scent as         ask someone to pour water on your hands, but with&#13;
  possible was preferred before eating: women feared         this you don't need anyone's help."&#13;
  a strong scent would affect the enjoyment of eating.&#13;
  One said, "You will not have an appetite for food if       So strong was the desire for the more expensive liquid&#13;
  the soap lingers in it."                                   soaps that some women made their own from bar&#13;
                                                             soap: "I soaked it in water, mashed it, and poured it&#13;
   Cost: Overall, cheaper soaps were preferred, though       into an old feeding bottle."&#13;
   women were sometimes willing to pay more if&#13;
   the soap was larger or they thought it would              Multipurpose: Because it is associated with economy,&#13;
   last longer.                                              many women preferred laundry bar soaps that&#13;
                                                             could be used for a variety of purposes: "That is the&#13;
   Texture/durability: Associated with cost, women           only soap I buy, since I can use it to wash my things&#13;
   tended to prefer harder bar soaps or liquid varieties,    and have a bathing soap at the same time."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26  The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
viewing habits. Demographic and Health Surveys (DHS)&#13;
also collect this information. In Peru, media houses were             Box 5: A Note on Schools&#13;
a great source of data on coverage and listenership.&#13;
                                                              Because they provide a relatively easy and&#13;
When using existing data, however, it is important to         sustainable route to long-term behavior change,&#13;
complement it with primary research in order to learn         schools are a good focus of handwashing programs.&#13;
more about local channels of communication and to             Schools are a key environment, not just for learning&#13;
determine which communication networks, traditional           about handwashing, but for introducing the habit in&#13;
or modern, are most trusted and/or believed. People           practice, so it lasts. Children are often enthusiastic&#13;
can be skeptical of mass media, especially where there is     proponents of behavior change, and research&#13;
strong government control over them, and coverage             questions apply to school-age children, teachers, and&#13;
levels can be low among women. Thus, a second                 administrators as well as they do to other&#13;
information source is interviews with a representative        target audiences.&#13;
sample of the target audiences. Such interviews focus on&#13;
people's contact with different channels of                   In most countries, schools are the second places of&#13;
communication, be they word-of-mouth, traditional,            socialization after households. Children can spend&#13;
governmental, social organizations, mass media, etc.          up to eight hours a day for more than eight months&#13;
Figure 5 illustrates different channels for women in a        a year in schools and a substantial amount of time&#13;
village in Kerala, India.                                     with their peers. Consumer behavior literature&#13;
                                                              shows that children do not react to brands and&#13;
Qualitative research can help to map out channels of          brand communication in the same way as adults, so&#13;
communications from the mothers' perspective,                 a separate communications strategy is needed for&#13;
particularly concerning local communication channels          schools. The risk practices being carried out at school&#13;
(which may be missed in national data sets). It can explore   are also different than at home. Specific tools for&#13;
which channels are likely to be most influential and          researching school children's habits and motives are&#13;
credible for handwashing communications. For example,         in development, and some tips on researching&#13;
in Burkina Faso, it was found that though `griots'            school-age children are in tool 4.&#13;
(traditional praise singers) were good carriers of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      The Handwashing Handbook       27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 5: How Mothers Communicate in Kerala, India: Monthly Contact Profile&#13;
&#13;
             Development                                Local                                    Anganwaadis&#13;
            women &amp; child                             panchayats                                     96%&#13;
             program 51%                                1%&#13;
&#13;
            Integrated rural                 Primary              Middle                          Secondary&#13;
             dev. program                    school               school                            school&#13;
                  57%                         90%                  87%                               74%&#13;
&#13;
              Community                                                                              Adult&#13;
                TV 62%                                                                            education&#13;
                                                                                                 centre 58%&#13;
&#13;
              Community                                                                            Primary&#13;
              centre 40%                              Target                                        health&#13;
                                                      mother                                     centre 74%&#13;
&#13;
               Fair price                                                                        Health sub-&#13;
               shop 91%                                                                          centres 79%&#13;
&#13;
                 Recall                                                                             Private&#13;
               shop 67%                                                                          doctor 88%&#13;
                                               Bank 89%       Post office&#13;
                  Milk                                           89%                            Village health&#13;
              cooperative       NGOs 24%                                                          guide 38%&#13;
                  67%                                                     Traditional birth&#13;
                                                                           attendant 49%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Box 6: Outline of Study Methods&#13;
    Structured observations are direct observations of         observations. Focus group discussions (FDGs) involve&#13;
    the behavior of interest (handwashing with soap            asking small numbers of people to discuss a range&#13;
    and what communication channels most effectively           of topics relating to the behavior of interest. As&#13;
    transmit messages) by field workers recording what         the target audience includes mothers and children,&#13;
    they see using a standard format. This method can          each should be separately included in focus group&#13;
    be difficult, expensive, and intrusive, but provides       discussions. FGDs are probably best used to carry&#13;
    more valid measures of behavior than any other             out ranking exercises (ranking of daily activities,&#13;
    method. Observers arrive early in the morning, sit         most important things in life, soap use, soap types&#13;
    quietly where they can see the domestic behaviors          for handwashing, most effective communication&#13;
    of mothers and index children, and note, for               channels, etc.) to allow consensus to form on issues&#13;
    example, exactly what happens associated with a            likely to affect handwashing behaviors and to&#13;
    child defecation event. Behavior inevitably changes        determine the proportion of people taking&#13;
    as a result of the observation, but if mothers are         particular views.&#13;
    told the observers are recording domestic work or&#13;
    child health, they change handwashing behavior less.       Behavioral trials and in-depth interviews: In behavioral&#13;
    Field workers need careful training to standardize         trials volunteers, usually taken from FGD members,&#13;
    the approach and very careful support and                  are given soap and asked to use it regularly for&#13;
    supervision. Consumer interviews are standard              handwashing. The mother is visited several times&#13;
    quantitative interviews and are useful in profiling        to remind her. After seven to 10 days, she is&#13;
    target audiences and their environment.                    interviewed in depth with regard to her experiences&#13;
    Socioeconomic questions along with questions on            using soap: what she liked and disliked, what was&#13;
    water, sanitation, and handwashing facilities are          easy, what was hard, and what solutions she found&#13;
    asked, and observations are made on these issues.          to any problems. These trials can usefully be&#13;
    A standard set of questions about exposure to all          repeated after another seven to 10 days, as habits&#13;
    possible forms of communication is also asked. All         change. Such trials followed by in-depth interviews&#13;
    questions are structured and employ precoded               can reveal motives and barriers if done thoroughly.&#13;
    responses. Formats need careful pilot testing to           In-depth probing is essential to reach the ultimate&#13;
    adapt them to local conditions. Consumer                   cause of a behavior. To reach such cause, researchers&#13;
    interviews (CIs) are best carried out with child           repeat the question "Why?" until a subject cannot&#13;
    caregivers immediately after structured                    explain any further underlying cause.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28 The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                Table 6: Summary Design for Consumer Research&#13;
&#13;
Objective        Specific Questions                   Methods           Suggested Minimum&#13;
                 (Not Exhaustive)                                       Sample Size&#13;
&#13;
1. Who carries   1.1 What are the characteristics     Questionnaire     As below&#13;
out risk         of target audiences (socio-economic, interview&#13;
practices?       demographic, educational             As described&#13;
                 characteristics, etc.)               in text&#13;
&#13;
2. What are the  2.1 How much soap is used per        Structured        Representative sample&#13;
risk practices?  person on average?                   observation       in eight clusters, total&#13;
                 2.2 What is soap used for,                             400 households&#13;
                 by whom?&#13;
                 2.3 What types of soap are used&#13;
                 for what?&#13;
                 2.4 On what occasions and how&#13;
                 many times are hands washed?         Questionnaire     400 households&#13;
                 With/without soap?                   interviews after&#13;
                 2.5 Where is soap procured?          structured&#13;
                 2.6 Availability of handwashing      observation&#13;
                 facilities&#13;
                                                      FGDs on soap      5 FGDs&#13;
                                                      attributes&#13;
&#13;
3. What can      3.1 Why do those who currently (do Behavior trials     40 volunteer households&#13;
drive behavior   not) wash hands with soap do so?&#13;
change?          3.2 What are the perceived           In-depth          40 volunteer households&#13;
                 advantages and disadvantages         interviews after&#13;
                 of washing hands with soap?          behavior trials&#13;
                 3.3 What constrains soap use?&#13;
                 3.4 What factors facilitate/bar&#13;
                 soap use?&#13;
                 3.5 Context: Characterization of&#13;
                 locality: water sources, sanitation&#13;
                 provision&#13;
&#13;
4. How do        4.1 Reach of existing channels of    Questionnaire     400 caretakers of children&#13;
people           communication (e.g., mass            interviews,&#13;
communicate?     media, government channels,          available         Sub samples of 200 male&#13;
                 nongovernment channels,              national data     household members and&#13;
                 traditional channels)                                  200 school-age children&#13;
                 4.2 Appropriatencess of existing     In-depth          40 volunteer households&#13;
                 channels of communication            interviews        as above&#13;
&#13;
5. Schools       5.1 Existing habits                  Focus groups      20 schools&#13;
survey           5.2 Motivations                      with kids,&#13;
                 5.3 Barriers                         in-depth&#13;
                 5.4 Key players                      interviews with&#13;
                                                      key players&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         The Handwashing Handbook  29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                    Box 7: Key Points for Contracting Consumer Research&#13;
&#13;
   It should be made explicit from the outset and         field and make sure that field work is being carried&#13;
   re-iterated often that handwashing promotion           out to specification. Unannounced visits will&#13;
   programs are not traditional public health projects.   help ensure rigor in the field team.&#13;
   Rather, they are consumer-driven programs that&#13;
   need to determine deep consumer motivations            Qualitative work (e.g., in-depth interviews) cannot&#13;
&#13;
   for handwashing with soap. Simple interviews are       be carried out by field workers but must be&#13;
&#13;
   not enough. For example, the contractor must           executed in the field by qualified and well-trained&#13;
&#13;
   be told that when consumers are asked whether          anthropologists or psychologists. Support from&#13;
&#13;
   they have washed their hands, the answer is            the international PPP-health worker technical&#13;
&#13;
   invariably "yes." People often respond to              team may be needed to ensure effective,&#13;
&#13;
   questionnaires as if they were being tested or         quality research.&#13;
&#13;
   judged, so they tell the interviewer what they         All data, both quantitative and qualitative, are&#13;
   believe is the "right" answer.                         precious. Qualitative interviews should be recorded&#13;
&#13;
   A team with commercial consumer research               on tape, translated, and transcribed; carefully&#13;
&#13;
   experience is preferable to one that is accustomed     labeled and indexed with date, time, and&#13;
&#13;
   to working on public health programs.                  respondent details; and returned to the client&#13;
                                                          for safekeeping. Quantitative data should be&#13;
   Field workers need to speak local languages.           thoroughly cleaned and a copy of the data set given&#13;
                                                          to the client.&#13;
   Once recruited, agencies need detailed briefing and&#13;
   training to ensure that the right questions are asked  Data analysis and reporting should focus on the&#13;
   in adequate detail. For example, many handwashing      questions set out in the TOR. The analysis and&#13;
   studies find that consumers wash their hands           report should specifically answer the key questions:&#13;
   because they want to be "clean." However,&#13;
   this is not a useful finding. Understanding what       ! What are the characteristics of the target&#13;
&#13;
   "clean" means in this context and all its                  audiences?&#13;
&#13;
   ramifications ­ physical, psychological, and social ­  ! What are existing behaviors and habits?&#13;
   is more important.&#13;
                                                          ! What are the handwashing with soap drivers,&#13;
   The research agency must stay focused on the               habits, and environment?&#13;
   four questions and the specific information that&#13;
   is needed. The agency must probe to the                ! What are the main channels of communication&#13;
   bottom of each question and ensure that                    used by the target audiences?&#13;
   findings are sufficiently detailed to allow the&#13;
   development of a sophisticated, creative               When analyzing the data and writing the final&#13;
&#13;
   strategy to promote behavior change among the          report, the research agency must frame its work&#13;
&#13;
   target audience.                                       around the main research questions as presented&#13;
                                                          above. Using table 5 to summarize barriers and&#13;
   As with all contract work, the quality of work will    potential drivers is also recommended.&#13;
   only be as good as the client demands. The client&#13;
   has to understand all the issues in-depth, know        Depending on the team's level of experience, the&#13;
   exactly what is wanted, and keep the agency            client may need to set out all of the analysis that is&#13;
   focused on achieving this. Clients must visit the      required of the contractor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30 The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                              Box 8: Consumer Research: The Rational Bias&#13;
&#13;
       We know that behavior is a product of drivers or        disease." Standard health promotion programs tend&#13;
       motivations. They activate when the brain receives      to content themselves with such answers,&#13;
       signals from the environment (e.g., the sight of a      forgetting that there may be many more, and many&#13;
       juicy apple) or the body (e.g., low energy, hunger).    more powerful drivers of behavior change, than&#13;
       Many drivers can operate at once, and the brain         fear of disease.&#13;
       gives one or another priority for action. Actions that&#13;
       are easy (require the least expenditure of effort)      Even if a respondent knows her own motives, there&#13;
       will be favored over difficult ones. Actions that have  may be powerful social reasons for not admitting&#13;
       been done before, or are habitual, will be favored      to them: Who would admit they want to look&#13;
       over new, less familiar ones. Though it is often        attractive to the opposite sex or that they want&#13;
       assumed that communicating the health benefit of        high status in society?&#13;
       handwashing is enough to drive it, it is only one       Marketers know this and ensure that advertisements&#13;
       among many potential drivers and often not the          contain both what they call a functional message&#13;
       strongest, though people might attempt to&#13;
       rationalizeandexplaintheirbehaviorinhealthterms.        and an emotional one. They present a rational basis&#13;
                                                               for buying a product or changing a behavior, one&#13;
       Consumer research is made difficult by the              that the consumer can claim or persuade himself&#13;
       widespread tendency to rationalize and explain          or herself is the reason for doing so, but also a&#13;
       behavior in a way that makes an individual appear       deeper emotional reason that probably represents&#13;
       favorable to an interviewer. However, the basic         the actual driver of behavior change. A major toilet&#13;
       drivers of human behavior are subconscious. Some        paper brand in the United Kingdom gives a typical&#13;
       of them are felt, indirectly, as emotions. Faced by     example: its advertisements claim that it is a better&#13;
       an interviewer, a mother feels obliged to try to        brand than the others and uses a cute puppy to&#13;
       explain herself. She may feel as if she were in school  convey the idea. The fact is, the paper is no better&#13;
       again, trying to give the right answer in a test. She   than many other brands and is more expensive,&#13;
       may try to remember lessons about hygiene, germs,       but the consumer is lured to it through an&#13;
       and disease. Asked why she washes her hands, she        emotional response to the puppy (Buchholz and&#13;
       endeavors to give a rational explanation: "To avoid     Wordemann 2001).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
information, they were not seen as hygienic by the             (d) 5 FGDs with target mothers on soap attributes and&#13;
general population and were consequently inappropriate         communications;(e)40behaviortrialsfollowedbyin-depth&#13;
carriers of handwashing messages.                              interviews; and (f) a school study module.&#13;
&#13;
Designing and Implementing                                     Structured observations are costly. The number can be&#13;
the Consumer Research                                          reduced from 400 to about 200 if they are intended&#13;
&#13;
The objectives of the consumer research are to answer,         purely to inform the program and not to provide a baseline&#13;
&#13;
in a valid but concise way, the four questions above: Who      from which to measure changes. The higher number is&#13;
&#13;
carries out risk practices? What are the risk practices?       necessary and is typically sufficient to provide the&#13;
What can change behavior? And how do the target                statistical power to detect a significant change in behavior.&#13;
audiences communicate?                                         If the study is to develop a baseline, detailed calculations&#13;
                                                               must be made based on estimates of local handwashing&#13;
Table 6 presents a summary design for consumer research        rates and the expected impact of the program. The annex&#13;
for a country handwashing program. This design involves:       provides a formula and instructions on how to do this.&#13;
(a) 400 structured observations (SOs) of the behavior of&#13;
mothers; (b) 400 questionnaire-based interviews with the       These recommended quantities will provide a good&#13;
same mothers after the structured observation; (c) 200         overview of the country situation regarding handwashing&#13;
questionnaire-basedinterviewswithothertargetaudiences,         practices and factors inhibiting, enabling, and motivating&#13;
includingmaleheadsofhouseholdsandschool-agechildren;           handwashing with soap at key junctures, provided that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          The Handwashing Handbook       31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the methods table 6 calls for professionals to provide        Analysis and Reporting of the Results&#13;
cover with a full range of socioeconomic, geographical,       Once collected and cleaned, the data are analyzed by&#13;
and cultural backgrounds. The structured observations         the research agency. Data are used to answer the four&#13;
and questionnaire-based interviews provide a quantitative     main questions. Quantitative data are summarized in&#13;
snapshot of handwashing practices, socio-demographic          tables, and qualitative data are coded according to the&#13;
factors, and channels of communication. After analysis,       main themes: drivers; habits; and environment motives,&#13;
these data are reported as proportions and percentages.       barriers, and facilitators. Several rounds of analysis and&#13;
The focus groups and behavior trials use a different          reporting may be needed to develop a report that meets&#13;
approach: their aim is to probe a small number of             the needs of the program. Raw data and transcripts of&#13;
individuals at great depth concerning their drivers and       FGDs and in-depth interviews must also be provided, as&#13;
habits and the environment of handwashing. These data         transcripts, in particular, can provide excellent raw&#13;
are recorded as transcripts and present key insights into     material for the development of creative strategies.&#13;
the consumer's mindset in their domestic context. The&#13;
methods are detailed below.                                   It is essential that the steering or consultative committee&#13;
                                                              includes people who can critically review the reports.&#13;
Studies typically take two months of fieldwork with a         Experts recommend reviewing the quantitative report,&#13;
team of eight to 14 people, cover the whole target area/      by, minimally, checking that the data set is clean and&#13;
country, and may cost on the order of US$20,000-80,000.       that a re-analysis of some of the descriptive and cross-&#13;
                                                              tabulated variables finds the same results as the agency.&#13;
Managing and Supervising                                      With the qualitative data it is essential to read some of&#13;
the Consumer Research                                         the raw transcripts and develop a feel for what people&#13;
&#13;
The agency chosen to perform the research needs a             are saying. Interpretations can vary from person to person,&#13;
&#13;
background in consumer research and must demonstrate          so it is also possible that the research agency will miss&#13;
&#13;
its ability to achieve a nationally representative sample     some important nuances. In both qualitative and&#13;
                                                              quantitative research, it is not uncommon for marketers&#13;
and manage qualitative data. The study will be much           themselves to re-run the analyses using the data provided&#13;
improved with inputs from private sector marketing and/       by the market research agencies.&#13;
or international handwashing experts to help brief and&#13;
train the consumer research team; support the qualitative     Qualitative research and analysis is difficult to do well, so&#13;
work, if experience in this is lacking; and analyze results.  it is essential that it be reviewed closely.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                     SECTION 3&#13;
                      Program&#13;
                    Implementation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-SA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   STUBBS/WSP&#13;
&#13;
             GUY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 The Handwashing Handbook 33&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   SECTION 3&#13;
                                      Program Implementation&#13;
&#13;
Designing the Campaign                                       needs of each segment of the target audience. Each&#13;
With a partnership framework and research results,           segment will require different marketing strategies.&#13;
planning for the handwashing with soap campaign can          Primary target segments in handwashing programs include&#13;
begin. The results of the research should provide all the    (a) mothers of children under five years; (b) other&#13;
information needed: the key practices to target; who         caretakers of children under five years; and (c) school-&#13;
the target audiences are; what the barriers, habits, and     age children at school and in other settings.&#13;
environment are; and details about appropriate channels&#13;
of communication. Experienced soap industry marketing        Further segmentation might divide those not washing&#13;
professionals can provide expertise and assist with all the  their hands at all (likely late adopters, likely less inclined&#13;
activities described in this section.                        to develop the habit of handwashing with soap) from&#13;
                                                             those already washing their hands, but with water alone&#13;
&#13;
Applying the Marketing Mix                                   (likely early adopters, more ready to respond to&#13;
                                                             handwashing messages). In some cases it might be&#13;
The marketing mix, often presented as the Four P's ­         necessary to segment the target audience according to&#13;
Product, Price, Place, and Promotion ­ provides a            ethnic or religious group. Other segments might include&#13;
framework for how to design a comprehensive                  rural and urban target audiences. Regardless of how&#13;
handwashing program.                                         audiences are segmented, it is important to ensure that&#13;
Product refers to the tangible good or service that can      messages are appropriate to all groups.&#13;
facilitate behavior change; it can include environmental     There are also secondary target segments, audiences that&#13;
changes or aids. Handwashing-related products include        can be expected to support and influence behavior change&#13;
soap, water and water dispensers, and basins.                among the primary group. These might include (a) fathers&#13;
Price refers to monetary and nonmonetary incentives,         of children under five years; (b) mothers-in-law;&#13;
such as the cost of soap and water and the time needed       (c) teachers; and (d) healthcare workers.&#13;
&#13;
to wash hands.                                               A third segment may be the target of an advocacy/public&#13;
&#13;
Place refers to the distribution of products and             relations campaign in support of the program. This&#13;
&#13;
conveniences, such as distance to a water source and         includes `upstream' stakeholders who can assist in&#13;
&#13;
availability of soap.                                        garnering political commitment. They may also be able&#13;
                                                             to help in such areas as installing handwashing facilities in&#13;
Promotion refers to persuasive communication and             schools or public toilets and by adding handwashing to&#13;
includes key messages, media channels, and                   their own programs. Such stakeholders may include (a)&#13;
environmental prompts.                                       industry; (b) government; (c) the media; and (d)&#13;
                                                             development organizations (international agencies,&#13;
While this document largely concerns the fourth P,           bilaterals, NGOs, community-based organizations).&#13;
promotion, a country program may also aim to influence&#13;
product solutions (e.g., making water dispensers available   Other examples of upstream targeting include lobbying&#13;
in schools), pricing (e.g., lobbying a government to reduce  governments to reduce import duties on soap ingredients.&#13;
&#13;
a sales tax on soap), and place (e.g., lobbying for tap      In addition, working with development organizations to&#13;
&#13;
connections and soap dispensers in schools).                 plan infrastructure projects in coordination with hygiene&#13;
                                                             promotion can ensure the placement of handwashing-&#13;
&#13;
Developing the Promotion                                     related products, such as water points.&#13;
&#13;
Target Audiences and Segmentation                            Agencies, Concepts, and Testing&#13;
Segmentation refers to the process of dividing the target    Methodical and thorough planning is the key to a successful&#13;
audiences into groups with similar behaviors and needs.      campaign, and the use of a professional communications&#13;
Segmentation is done so that promoters can address the       agency is essential. Good agencies are skilled at turning&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
34     The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
consumer insights into effective behavior change              3. What is the single-minded proposition, our unique&#13;
programs. However, the results are only as good as the             selling point? That is, What is the single focus, the&#13;
brief (described below).                                           one benefit we want to communicate to the target&#13;
                                                                   audience? (This benefit must be believable.)&#13;
Communication agencies are responsible for turning the&#13;
objectives and insights of marketers into comprehensive       4. Execution       task,    including   the    tone     that&#13;
communications campaigns. They begin this process                  communications should take.&#13;
through a `creative brief,' a document designed to outline&#13;
the scope of the work they are expected to undertake.         Consumer research has provided the key elements for&#13;
The brief should be presented to the communications           the brief, notably: (a) target audience profiles; (b) current&#13;
team with time for discussion and idea generation. It         habits; (c) drivers, barriers, and the environment; and&#13;
should be as clear and succinct as possible and typically     (d) a map of channels of communication.&#13;
contain four key elements:                                    The final brief is negotiated between agency and client.&#13;
1. The business task.                                         Lintas Ghana Ltd has provided guidance on the `The&#13;
                                                              Perfect Brief' (see box 9). Alongside the brief, the client&#13;
2. The communication task: (a) Who is the target              should provide a full report of the consumer research,&#13;
   audience?; (b) What do they do/think now?; and             including verbatim transcripts of interviews and focus&#13;
   (c) What do we want them to do/think?                      groups and plenty of nuggets of insights gleaned from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         The Senegal Creative Strategy&#13;
&#13;
                             ADULTS                                               CHILDREN&#13;
       Objectives:                                            Objectives:&#13;
       !To adapt the behavior of washing hands with           !Toadaptthebehaviorofwashinghandswithsoap&#13;
       soap after the toilets, after having changed a child,  before eating and after using the toilet&#13;
       before eating, and before feeding a child cooking      !Convey this example to others&#13;
       !To transfer this behaviors to children and close&#13;
       contacts&#13;
&#13;
       Target Audience: Mothers and guardians of              Target Audience: Children 6-12 years old&#13;
       children under five years of age&#13;
&#13;
       Benefits:                                              Benefits:&#13;
       !attractiveness, cleanliness, to smell good, and to    !coolness and being accepted by the group&#13;
       be in good health                                      !feel good (physically and mentally)&#13;
       !to avoid the disease, dirtiness, bad smells, and&#13;
       shame&#13;
&#13;
       Tone: jovial and positive                              Tone: cool, `in', encouraging&#13;
&#13;
       Desired reaction:                                      Desired reaction:&#13;
       For the well-being of myself and my family, I wash     I wash my hands with the soap, and I have a good&#13;
       my hands with soap                                     sense of myself and it is cool.&#13;
                                                              If I do not wash my hands with the soap I will not&#13;
                                                              fit in with my peers&#13;
&#13;
       Sources:                                               Sources:&#13;
       !Consumer research carried out in Senegal at the       !Structured observations in primary schools in&#13;
       end of 2003                                            Dakar&#13;
       !Experiencesfromhandwashingprogramsinother             !Experiencesfromhandwashingprogramsinother&#13;
       countries                                              countries&#13;
                                                              !Consistency with adult strategy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          The Handwashing Handbook      35&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 Box 9: The Perfect Brief&#13;
&#13;
       During preparation of the Ghana Handwashing               Team Leader&#13;
       Initiative, the advertising agency Lintas was selected    ! The most experienced marketer on the team&#13;
       to design the campaign materials. It soon became          ! The driver&#13;
       clear to the client, Ghana's handwashing                  ! Empowered to make decisions on behalf of the&#13;
       initiative steering committee, that the successful        rest of the team&#13;
       development of the materials was due to the well-         ! In from the start, there at every milestone,&#13;
       designed creative brief. Lintas-Ghana shared its          and there to make the final decision&#13;
       guidelines for designing The Perfect Brief during a       ! Not a gatekeeper but an initiator&#13;
       global handwashing technical workshop in 2003.&#13;
                                                                 Content&#13;
       The Purpose of a Brief                                    ! Simple: one page; no jargon&#13;
       ! To create good advertising                              ! Objective&#13;
       ! Create/communicateacommonunderstanding                  ! Who are we talking to?&#13;
       of the task                                               ! What do they think now? What is their need?&#13;
       ! Inspire                                                 ! What       do we want them to think?&#13;
       ! Develop a tool for measuring the results                A single-minded proposition that it's important to&#13;
                                                                 the target's life&#13;
       Client/Agency Relationship                                ! Why should they believe us?&#13;
       Preparing the brief is a team process that includes:      ! Executional guidelines/requirements&#13;
       ! Collaborating with the agency&#13;
       ! Receiving a draft document early on, then re-           The Briefing Session&#13;
       working it                                                ! Present the brief face-to-face with the&#13;
       ! Getting sign-off from all stakeholders                  creative team&#13;
       ! An effective team (small, consistent)                   ! Be creative, make it an interesting and&#13;
       ! Defining roles and empowering a leader                  memorable experience&#13;
       ! Creating a shared vision                                ! Be flexible in the face of concerns voiced&#13;
       ! Effective, enjoyable meetings with clear,               by the team&#13;
       commonly understood objectives                            ! Make it fun&#13;
&#13;
       Risk versus Safety                                        Evaluating Advertising&#13;
       ! "If you don't get noticed, you don't get                ! Measure against brief: Does it say it? Did it&#13;
       anything": Bill Bernbach, legendary copywriter and        communicate?&#13;
       founder of DDB Worldwide                                  ! Does it have a single idea that links all the&#13;
       ! Anodyne, unoriginal, and uninteresting                  executions across media?&#13;
       advertising is ineffective                                ! Is it surprising?&#13;
       ! Advertising that stands out carries risk                ! Is it interesting?&#13;
       ! A small, well-led team has the courage to face/         ! Is it memorable?&#13;
       manage that risk and create communications that&#13;
       are surprising, interesting, and memorable                An imperfect brief&#13;
                                                                 ! A verbal brief (it isn't worth the paper it isn't&#13;
       Planning and Research                                     written on)&#13;
       Know what you want to achieve                             ! Is full of jargon, acronyms, and options&#13;
       ! Change of mind                                          ! Is unclear on budget or timing (that is, ASAP)&#13;
       ! Behavior change                                         ! Is non-negotiable&#13;
       ! Quantify (how many, by when)                            ! Asks for miracles, that is, overambitious&#13;
       ! Pinpoint, then know the target ­ demographic            objectives despite logistical barriers&#13;
       and psychographic ­ relevant, insight, golden             ! Hasadouble-barreledsingle-mindedproposition&#13;
       nugget, drivers, barriers. How they find information&#13;
       they trust&#13;
       ! Communication strategy                                  Source: Colin Charles, Lintas Ghana (August, 2003)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the research. This will contribute to the agency's               the creative process is iterative with regular agency-client&#13;
understanding of the behavior of interest, target                meetings. It is important to be as clear and directional as&#13;
audiences, and communication channels.                           possible throughout this process. Industry's experience is&#13;
                                                                 invaluable, so it is essential that private sector expertise is&#13;
Followinginitialbriefingmeetings,theagencyaccountmanager         used throughout development of the communications&#13;
will produce internal briefs for the creative team. Thereafter,  strategy. A core team familiar with all aspects of the research&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
36    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   Table 7: Advantages and Disadvantages&#13;
                                 of Different Approaches to Communication&#13;
&#13;
         Approach          Description                     Advantage                        Disadvantage&#13;
&#13;
         Mass media        Messages crafted to be          Low cost per capita,             Needs high saturation&#13;
                           transmitted through an          can be highly                    (6+contacts) to affect&#13;
                           optimized mix of radio,         memorable, can raise             behavior change&#13;
                           TV, billboard, and              the political profile of&#13;
                           other channels                  handwashing, easy to             Audience cannot interact&#13;
                                                           monitor                          Difficult to fund&#13;
&#13;
         Direct            Events organized by             Good audience                    High cost per capita&#13;
         consumer          professional event              interaction, high                Uncertainty about&#13;
         contact           management agencies,            impact, memorable                impact and optimal&#13;
                           held in schools, public                                          size of audience&#13;
                           places, community groups&#13;
&#13;
         Public            Using the ability of            Potentially highly               Hard to control&#13;
         channels          government agencies to          sustainable, if                  Low staff motivation&#13;
                           deliver handwashing             handwashing                      Contact with target&#13;
                           messages through                promotion becomes                audiences may be&#13;
                           schools and health              part of curriculum,              infrequent, resulting in&#13;
                           centers                         job description of health        low coverage&#13;
                                                           agent, promoted at ante-         Low ability to monitor&#13;
                                                           and post-natal contact           activities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and the approach should be maintained throughout this              include television, radio, and billboard advertising. Direct&#13;
process, which often takes several months.                         contact with consumers includes activities carried out by&#13;
&#13;
First, the results of the research are used to develop a           event management organizations and existing&#13;
&#13;
number of platforms or concepts. These are developed               organizations, such as local government, schools, health&#13;
&#13;
and tested by an independent research agency in order to           authorities, NGOs, commercial retail outlets, churches,&#13;
&#13;
determine which message direction is most likely to drive          mosques, etc. The more appropriate the mix of&#13;
&#13;
behavior change. The most promising concepts are then              communication channels to the local situation, the more&#13;
&#13;
further developed into miniature stories for TV and radio          effective the campaign will be.&#13;
ads and into outline poster designs. The advertising stories&#13;
are illustrated in drawn storyboards, which are also then          Mass communications (TV, radio, billboards): When channels&#13;
&#13;
testedwithtargetaudiencesforbelievability,attractiveness,          such as TV, radio, the Internet, billboards, leaflets, and&#13;
&#13;
and potential behavior change power, again by an                   posters are employed, they can reach large audiences at&#13;
&#13;
independent research agency. The processes for testing             a low cost per capita. They may thus appear cost-&#13;
&#13;
concepts and storyboards are similar, as outlined in box 7.        effective. However, the downside is that mass media&#13;
                                                                   contacts are thought to be less effective in achieving&#13;
It is essential that time is allowed in the creative process       behavior change than group or individual contact due to&#13;
for the testing and retesting of concepts; storyboards;            the lack of opportunity for audience interaction.&#13;
and, ideally, draft advertisements, as it is this fine-tuning      Direct consumer contact: Public meetings, street theater,&#13;
that will maximize the campaign's success.                         mobilecinema,andotherspecialeventsrunbyprofessional&#13;
                                                                   direct consumer contact (DCC) organizations, as well as&#13;
Multiple Strategies for Behavior Change                            educational sessions in schools and health facilities, can&#13;
Handwashing programs rely on a variety of communication            reach large numbers of people, if enough events are held.&#13;
channels such as mass media and direct consumer contact            The effectiveness of this approach has not been greatly&#13;
activities. As described in table 7, mass media might              studied, and group health education has had uncertain&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               The Handwashing Handbook     37&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
effects on behavior. However, industry believes that while   Public Relations and Advocacy&#13;
DCC is much more costly per person reached than mass         Whilethemassmediaanddirectconsumercontactactivities&#13;
media, in the longer term its power to change behavior is    seek to change handwashing behavior in mothers and&#13;
greater due to the greater intensity of the communication    children, public relations and advocacy aim to create and&#13;
and opportunity for audience interaction.                    maintain support for these efforts from the broader&#13;
                                                             stakeholder groups ­ the third target audience mentioned&#13;
Government and partner agency communication: In an ideal     above in `Target Audiences and Segmentation.' If used to&#13;
world, all government health employees, hygiene staff,       its full potential, PR can be a powerful marketing tool that&#13;
school teachers, and outreach workers would introduce        develops and maintains interest, anticipates and deals with&#13;
handwashing at every contact opportunity with target&#13;
audiences.However,suchemployeeshaveotherpriorities,          negativepublicity,andhelpsmaximizethecampaign'simpact.&#13;
&#13;
and special strategies will be needed if handwashing is to   Handwashing programs need concerted initial advocacy&#13;
become their priority. The key to the success of these       to bring all key stakeholders on board, but advocacy is&#13;
communications is the creation of a cadre of motivated,      not a one-time activity. During early stages of a program,&#13;
well-trained agents. This is as difficult to achieve in      it may be helpful to have international experts visit to&#13;
handwashing efforts as in any public health program.         raise the profile of handwashing and add credibility: not&#13;
However, efforts to include handwashing promotion in the     everyone may see what a serious issue handwashing is.&#13;
job descriptions of teachers and health workers may be       Advocacy is also needed throughout the life of the program&#13;
one route to long-term sustainability. A mass media          to keep stakeholders on board and to brief new partners&#13;
campaign may help motivate government employees to           experiencing staff turnover. The leading targets for&#13;
take on the handwashing message. Particular events in        advocacy are key decision-makers as identified in the&#13;
health facilities, such as the distribution of free soap in  stakeholder analysis. Often, it makes sense to target the&#13;
`bounty packs' for new mothers, also enhance health          highest possible level: Prime Ministers and Ministers as&#13;
worker motivation and provide stimuli for mothers to take    well as chief executives and country representatives.&#13;
on new behaviors for the good of their infants.              It may also be vital to identify potential dissenters and&#13;
The use of commitments can increase the likelihood of        to keep them well informed and in the loop.&#13;
behaviorchange.Clinicscanbeencouragedtogivemothers           Misunderstandings about the nature of the program can&#13;
&#13;
a `certificate' honoring their commitment to wash their      lead to bad press, which can seriously damage or even&#13;
&#13;
hands with soap at key junctures.These certificates could    sink handwashing programs (see box 10).&#13;
&#13;
also be distributed to mothers and children at community     PR targets stakeholder groups that can leverage publicity,&#13;
events (see `Direct consumer contact,' above) and to         funds, and expertise. Such groups include:&#13;
children through schools. Rewarding people as they&#13;
continuetopracticeanewbehavior,evenwithsmalltokens           ! The press, which develops news and features that&#13;
such as stickers or badges, or simple praise, can also be    highlight research findings, campaign events, and&#13;
important in moving people from a one-time trial of          accomplishments,andreinforcekeyhandwashingmessages;&#13;
handwashing with soap to developing the habit.               ! Government agents, who lobby officials to support&#13;
School children could have monthly hygiene prizes, while     and promote the program within their institutions and&#13;
clinics might reward new mothers for continuing to wash      budgets and to improve the operating environment;&#13;
their hands as their baby grows.&#13;
                                                             ! The private sector, which engages the soap industry&#13;
Product labeling: Ensuring that the handwashing message is   and other private sector entities to provide expertise&#13;
carriedonhandwashing-relatedproductscanprovideagood          and financial support for the design and execution of the&#13;
prompt/reminder to wash hands with soap at key times.        handwashing campaign or to carry handwashing messages&#13;
Foodcompaniescouldbeencouragedtocarrythemessage              and logos on their products to remind people to wash&#13;
orlogoonfooditemstoremindpeopletowashhandsbefore             hands at key junctures; and&#13;
eating or preparing foods, while soap companies could put&#13;
the message on soap packaging. For example, one soap         ! Support agencies, which create interest and&#13;
company in Ghana intends to introduce a new in packaging     commitment in the development community to set&#13;
that has the same colors as images from handwashing          up financial support, networking, technical assistance,&#13;
campaign. This need not involve additional cost but may      and the inclusion of handwashing messages in programs&#13;
require advocacy and PR (see below).                         and projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
38    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The PR Plan                                                 handwashing facilities in schools? Like all areas of the&#13;
The purpose of PR is to create and maintain awareness       handwashing initiative, local knowledge of each&#13;
and support. This is accomplished through various tools,    stakeholder group is essential when developing&#13;
such as press releases, speeches/presentations, and         appropriate messages.&#13;
events. Key points when planning a PR campaign are:&#13;
                                                            Encourage networking among target audiences: Put&#13;
Know the target audience: What type of stories will the     different organizations in touch with each other.&#13;
media be likely to print? What are the favored media        Independent support will leverage the handwashing&#13;
outlets and venues used by specific stakeholders? What      messages, increase credibility, and stimulate&#13;
are the current `hot' issues with stakeholders that could   problem solving.&#13;
be exploited or could potentially detract from&#13;
handwashing? Who can address handwashing barriers           Start early: PR is the first mass communications step of a&#13;
raised in the research, such as high import tariffs on raw  handwashing initiative. Many of the informal stages of&#13;
materials that lead to high soap prices or lack of          partnership formation will form the basis of the PR plan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Box 10: A Lesson in Public Relations: Handwashing in Kerala, India&#13;
&#13;
      As part of the Global Handwashing Partnership, a      Better media management: The only response&#13;
      handwashing program was started in Kerala, India,     to press criticism was an official, lukewarm&#13;
      in early 2001. Facilitated by the World Bank and      statement that came six months too late. Regular&#13;
      the Water and Sanitation Program, the government      briefings and updates could have helped build&#13;
      of Kerala partnered with the Indian Soap and          media support.&#13;
      Toiletries Manufacturers' Association (ISTMA) to&#13;
      develop a handwashing promotion program across        Better informed stakeholders: Not all key&#13;
      the state. Hindustan Lever Limited, the largest       stakeholders felt included, as the program was&#13;
      privatesoapmanufacturerinIndiaandakeymember           designed and business plan developed.&#13;
      of ISTMA, played an active role in developing the&#13;
      public-private partnership. UNICEF, the London        Small business involvement: Though local and small&#13;
      School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine (LSHTM),        soap companies were involved and participated,&#13;
      and a number of NGOs were also involved.              this was not widely known and led to the perception&#13;
                                                            that multinationals would take over the market.&#13;
      As the handwashing program design and business&#13;
      plan began to receive public attention,               Better informed stakeholders: A perception&#13;
      environmental and anti-globalization activists began  developed that the campaign was designed to sell&#13;
      criticizing the program through the print media.      only one company's soaps and that the whole&#13;
      They were soon joined by other high-profile groups,   initiative was being driven by one donor. In reality,&#13;
      including doctors, local newspapers, and opposition   the campaign was not promoting any particular firm&#13;
      politicians. The main points of criticism were:       or brand, and more than one internationally&#13;
      (a) the choice of Kerala for the program in view of   recognized organization was highly involved.&#13;
      its already high human development indicators;&#13;
      (b) unclear linkage between handwashing and health    At the same time a politician claimed it would&#13;
      improvement; (c) the potential adverse effect on      be better for the government to spend money&#13;
      the indigenous and local soap industry by increasing  on providing safe water and sanitation&#13;
      the market share of multinational soap companies;     infrastructure rather than handwashing. This&#13;
      and (d) the suggestion that the state government      argument was buttressed by the assertion that&#13;
      was capitulating to World Bank pressure. In the       safe water and sanitation initiatives are "tangible&#13;
      face of mounting media attacks and after a long       and based on hardware," while a communication-&#13;
      period of inaction, the state cabinet decided to      based initiative like handwashing is "largely&#13;
      abandon the program in August 2003.                   ephemeral, intangible, and therefore prone to&#13;
      Could the problems in Kerala have been avoided        wastage and misuse." Even doctors were skeptical&#13;
      or handled better? The ideal combination of an        about the health benefits of handwashing with soap.&#13;
      interested donor, an interested soap company, and     Information of the benefits of handwashing and the&#13;
      initial demand from the government for a              monitoring and evaluation frameworks could have&#13;
      handwashing program evaporated under                  been regularly disseminated to policy makers,&#13;
      widespread media criticism. A PR plan could have      constituents, and health professionals with forums&#13;
      contributed to:                                       encouraging the exchange of views.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         The Handwashing Handbook  39&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Initially, PR can convey the importance of handwashing         Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
with soap. With research results in hand, PR can highlight     The object of monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;E) is to&#13;
country-specific handwashing needs.                            ascertain the extent and effectiveness of the program.&#13;
                                                               Monitoring serves to diagnose and help fix problems during&#13;
Align the PR plan with broader communications efforts: As&#13;
the communications strategy is developed, PR activities        program execution. Evaluation is the process of&#13;
&#13;
will need to align with the mass media and direct              measuring outcomes both during and after the&#13;
&#13;
consumer contact campaigns. This will improve impact           intervention, to determine how successful the program&#13;
&#13;
through message clarity, timing, and campaign identity         is, or was. M&amp;E involves three broad steps: a baseline&#13;
&#13;
(logos, colors, etc.). In short, PR should fit with the        survey, ongoing monitoring of program activities, and a&#13;
&#13;
communications brief, whether or not professional PR           post-intervention survey.&#13;
&#13;
expertise is engaged.                                          In industry it is standard to run a communications program&#13;
                                                               in six-month phases, with three-month gaps between&#13;
The Media Mix                                                  each phase to review and adapt content. This enables&#13;
Modeling the impact of different communications routes         evaluation of the reach of the message, its content, and&#13;
on target audiences is the next step. With finite              the target audience's understanding and interpretation&#13;
resources it is essential to work out which mix of             of it. The media mix is revised to give better coverage of&#13;
communications channels will be most cost-effective. This      target audiences, to reflect what channels reach people,&#13;
is a science well understood by industry. Models of media      and which channels are most influential. Interim&#13;
consumption and contact patterns in the target                 evaluations can gauge the degree of saturation of the&#13;
populations are built by professionals. The capacity of        message and provide the information for minor or&#13;
TV, radio, and other channels to reach the whole target        complete revision, if needed. However, in early stages&#13;
audience is calculated. Assumptions are then made about        one cannot expect to detect significant behavior change&#13;
&#13;
the costs and effectiveness of different channels,             and must rely more on qualitative assessment of people's&#13;
&#13;
and finally a mix of channels is selected to maximize          understanding and appreciation of the messages and&#13;
&#13;
cost-effectiveness.                                            indicators of the propensity to change behavior.&#13;
&#13;
When designing the communications strategy and                 Baseline Survey&#13;
apportioning       budgets      to   various     different     Initially, the team needs to understand local handwashing&#13;
communications channels, it is essential to ensure that        practices and local determinants of regular handwashing&#13;
all are utilizing the same promotional messages and            with soap. A single baseline survey, which can be carried&#13;
materials as used in the mass media channels. Hence,           out along with the consumer research, can provide both,&#13;
before designing the direct consumer contact and               with advanced planning by the initiation team. Marketing&#13;
district-level programs, it is essential that mass media       companies tend to choose convenient populations to&#13;
messages are finalized.                                        explore attitudes and motivation. A baseline survey to&#13;
                                                               assess the impact of a program, however, requires a&#13;
This does not, however, mean that the same company             carefully drawn representative sample. Having the people&#13;
should be used for every communications approach.              conducting the baseline evaluation and the handwashing&#13;
Agencies that specialize in both advertising and direct        determinants investigation work in a single team or at&#13;
consumer contact will have to be recruited.                    least closely enough together is economical, as they would&#13;
&#13;
Finally, there are many activities that could promote          identify and work with the same population. In addition,&#13;
&#13;
handwashing in any country. However, since resources           their results would have more explanatory force, because&#13;
&#13;
and management time are limited, each activity must be         a sophisticated understanding of people's motivations can&#13;
&#13;
justified in terms of the time and resources it would take     be directly linked with their handwashing behavior.&#13;
&#13;
away from other efforts. Many small agencies may wish          The handwashing baseline survey should be conducted&#13;
to be involved, for example, but may take far more time        among a random sample of people who are the target of&#13;
to bring on board and convince of strategies than their        the handwashing promotion program. Thus, when the&#13;
likely impact would warrant. Strategic planning is essential:  baseline survey is commissioned, the handwashing&#13;
for each activity, managers have to decide how much            promotion team needs to be clear on who comprises&#13;
they can expect in terms of impact and concentrate on          the campaign's target audience. For example, is the&#13;
those with expected high returns.                              campaign a national campaign striving to reach all&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
40     The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
households or is it focused primarily on urban, rural, or      the link between health and handwashing or demand&#13;
low-income households? Once the campaign target has            direct measurement of health impact.&#13;
been identified, a strategy is developed to identify a&#13;
random sample of persons within the target audience. A         Monitoring&#13;
cluster-randomized design, similar to an immunization          The second requirement for evaluating a handwashing&#13;
coverage survey, where communities are randomly                promotion program is an ongoing process to monitor the&#13;
selected with the probability of selection proportional to     implementation of planned activities and ensure that&#13;
the population, is generally the most efficient and practical  messages are reaching their target audiences.&#13;
approach. The survey team visits 30 randomly selected&#13;
communities and evaluates 10-30 households in each.            Information from a well-designed monitoring system can&#13;
                                                               serve to reorient programs and make them effective. As&#13;
The primary indicators for the baseline survey include:        with any large-scale program, managers need to set up&#13;
! The presence of soap in the home, presence of&#13;
hand soap in the home;                                         systems to follow the progress of activities and gather&#13;
                                                               data on achievements. Such information can be&#13;
! The presence of a handwashing station (that is,              supplemented with periodic random sample surveys to&#13;
a place where water and soap are readily available             document the reach of the program via the different&#13;
for handwashing);                                              channels of communication. In essence, a simple survey,&#13;
                                                               representative of the target audiences, documents how&#13;
! Structured observations of handwashing behavior              much contact each actor has had with the program.&#13;
at key times, specifically recording the proportion of         Audiences report their recall of contact and content and&#13;
family members who wash their hands with soap before&#13;
preparing, eating, or giving food; after defecation; and       indicate if this has led to any changes in belief or behavior.&#13;
&#13;
after cleaning up a feces-soiled infant; and                   (As mentioned, this does not prove behavior change, but&#13;
                                                               is a general indicator of progress in the right direction.)&#13;
! Diarrhea occurrence among each family member                 Qualitative work concerning how well the audience is&#13;
in the last 24 hours, which may need to be measured in         reacting to the media presented can provide insight to&#13;
countries where key stakeholders are unconvinced of            reorient programs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Table 8: The Ghana National Handwashing Initiative:&#13;
                               Phase 1 Evaluation Results (in Percentages)&#13;
&#13;
         Women&#13;
&#13;
         Handwashing with                 Reporting HW           Reporting HW                      Change in&#13;
         Soap Juncture                    before Campaign        since Campaign                    Reporting&#13;
&#13;
         After defecation                 76                     89                                +13&#13;
&#13;
         Before eating                    14                     55                                +41&#13;
&#13;
         Before feeding a baby            6                      25                                +19&#13;
&#13;
         Before preparing food            11                     26                                +15&#13;
&#13;
         After eating                     53                     31                                -22&#13;
&#13;
         Children&#13;
&#13;
         After defecation                 76                     89                                +13&#13;
&#13;
         Before eating                    14                     76                                +62&#13;
&#13;
         After eating                     61                     41                                -20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            The Handwashing Handbook      41&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
               Figure 6: Monitoring and Evaluation: Program Activities and Impact&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Resources&#13;
                                          mobilized&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Resources and                                          Program&#13;
                                    management deployed                                                                                         Input:&#13;
                                        and effective&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     activity                                         costs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Program&#13;
                                       actors deployed&#13;
                                        and effective&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Promotional                                    Products/&#13;
              activities take                                components&#13;
                  place                                        sourced&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Facilitating&#13;
                                        environment&#13;
                                           created                                                                   Delivery&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Target audiences                                 Products in                                                        Output:&#13;
            receive messages                                    place&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        benefits&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       change                Behavior&#13;
&#13;
             Target audiences                                Products used&#13;
             act on messages                                  effectively&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Health impact                                         Health&#13;
                                          accrued                                     improves&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Evaluation                                                   requires special epidemiological expertise. The&#13;
Final evaluation compares handwashing behavior with the      prevalence of diarrhea is highly variable, so two one-&#13;
baseline in order to determine the outcomes and impact of    day measurements years apart in two populations of&#13;
the program. During evaluation, a new random sample is       300-900 households is insufficient to demonstrate a&#13;
drawnfromthetargetpopulation.Thirtynewcommunities            direct effect attributable to the handwashing promotion&#13;
are identified, and 10-30 households approached in each.     program. However, these data can be used to model&#13;
The same instrument that was used to collect the baseline    the prevalence of diarrhea and its association with&#13;
data is administered to collect the post-intervention data.  observed handwashing practices. This can then be used&#13;
The in-depth determinants of handwashing behavior            to model the impact of the improved handwashing on&#13;
investigation do not need to be repeated. The data from      diarrhea. However, since the impact on improved&#13;
thefinalsurveyareanalyzedandcomparedtothefirstsurvey&#13;
to assess changes in behavior (see table 8).                 handwashing behaviors on disease is known, it usually&#13;
                                                             suffices to look for impact on behavior as proof that&#13;
Detailed program evaluation, including the final             the program is achieving its objectives. Health impact&#13;
outcome, health impact, is expensive to do well and          can then be extrapolated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
42    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    SECTION 4&#13;
Program Organization&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      The Handwashing Handbook 43&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  SECTION 4&#13;
                                       Program Organization&#13;
&#13;
The Partnership Mix                                           produce public health campaigns that rival, or surpass,&#13;
Putting together a country team with the commitment,          industrial marketing efforts.&#13;
resources, and skills to set up, support, and run a national&#13;
handwashing program takes time and effort. When               A General Partnership Model&#13;
partners from different backgrounds are not accustomed        The experience of previous handwashing campaigns in&#13;
to working together, it takes time to build common aims       Central America, Ghana, Nepal, and Senegal suggests&#13;
and mutual trust.                                             that a coordinator-committee model for PPPs is&#13;
Public-private partnerships (PPPs) provide an effective       an effective way of managing a program with a diverse&#13;
model for handwashing programs because they combine           group of partners.&#13;
the health objectives of the public sector with the           The coordinator: The coordinator manages day-to-day&#13;
marketing expertise of the private sector. As noted, the      operations, keeps stakeholders engaged and informed,&#13;
private sector stands to gain from joining such a             and ensures that the whole initiative is moving towards&#13;
partnership primarily through market expansion, by being      its objectives. The coordinator is responsible for&#13;
seen as contributing to social goals, and by networking       developing and fulfilling the project business plan through&#13;
with development partners and international experts.&#13;
The public sector gains from the marketing expertise          the engagement of partners and resources. A sample&#13;
&#13;
and resources of industry. They are thereby able to           TOR, contained in the annex, outlines a coordinator's&#13;
                                                              duties, qualifications, and skills.&#13;
&#13;
                                                              The steering committee: The key stakeholders that provide&#13;
                                                              resources ­ technical, financial, and management support&#13;
                                                              ­ make up the steering committee. They communicate&#13;
                                                              with each other and the coordinator regularly and take&#13;
                                                              the lead on specific business plan components. The&#13;
                                                              benefits of having many members must be weighed against&#13;
                                                              the transaction costs, which rise geometrically with every&#13;
                                                              additional member.&#13;
&#13;
                                                              The consultative committee: The consultative committee&#13;
                                                              comprises stakeholders who have a specific interest in&#13;
                                                              the program but do not expect to be engaged on a daily&#13;
                                                              basis. Its members might be asked for occasional feedback&#13;
                                                              and approval on specific issues. This committee may&#13;
                                                              include government officials, members of the press,&#13;
                                                              community groups, the wider scientific community, and&#13;
                                                              senior institutional managers. They may also represent&#13;
                                                              organizations, such as regional or nongovernmental&#13;
                                                              organizations, that will be extending the campaign to&#13;
                                                              specific geographical areas.&#13;
&#13;
                                                              Meeting formally or informally, the consultative committee&#13;
                                                              helps     the   coordinator      organize   stakeholders&#13;
                                                              at the appropriate level of inter-action and helps keep&#13;
                                                              stakeholders engaged and enthused. Subgroups&#13;
                                                              oncommunications,consumerresearch,andthepressmay&#13;
                                                              be useful.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
44   The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   Box 11: Handwashing in Action:&#13;
                               The Handwashing Partnership in Peru&#13;
&#13;
Identifying the right partners, building a relationship  with new members joining from the private sector:&#13;
of trust, and then maintaining their involvement         Radio Programas del Perú, a national radio&#13;
and willingness to compromise at high levels, are        broadcaster engaged in social responsibility, and the&#13;
probably the most challenging, frustrating, and at       international NGO CARE with experience in&#13;
the same time rewarding tasks the coordinator must       handwashing promotion in rural areas. Their&#13;
achieve and sustain during the initiative. Once the      professionals participated in and followed closely the&#13;
PPP is believed to be solid, a coordinator must          planning process and activities that concluded in a&#13;
never rest on his/her success, because there is          business plan at the end of the first year.&#13;
always the risk that a pending threat may affect&#13;
or interrupt the consolidated equilibrium                Other private partners, such as Colgate-Palmolive&#13;
&#13;
among partners.                                          and Alicorp (the leading national producer of&#13;
                                                         laundry soap), members of a broader body, and&#13;
Peru's initiative started on the right footing.          the consultative committee were key members&#13;
A mission of the Global Committee visited Peru           in the communication task force, organized to&#13;
at the end of 2003 to identify opportunities for         draw the communication program structure of the&#13;
the implementation of a handwashing initiative           business plan.&#13;
there. Public and private institutions were invited&#13;
to evaluate the project and showed interest from         Slowing pace: The beginning of the implementation&#13;
&#13;
the beginning.                                           phase was marked by uncertainty. Financial sources&#13;
                                                         previously identified as strong possibilities fell&#13;
The mission planted a seed, and a few months later,      through, forcing the initiative to move more slowly,&#13;
the Ministry of Health, the Swiss Development            and momentum was lost.&#13;
Cooperation, the Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
of the World Bank, and USAID, joined the                 Changes took place within almost every&#13;
handwashing steering committee with a                    institutional member of the executive committee.&#13;
well-defined agenda for the first year                   Partners' roles were not fully understood by&#13;
of operations.                                           incoming members: Should the initiative be made&#13;
                                                         public? What responsibilities should executive&#13;
Steering committee meetings were held regularly,         committee members assume once funding&#13;
and building a strong partnership became a priority.     was received?&#13;
Close to 20 institutions were identified and&#13;
visited with two objectives in mind: to provide          A window of opportunity opened when USAID&#13;
handwashing information by way of a motivated            decided to fund the first activity of the&#13;
and persuasive speech and to gather quality              implementation phase: the creative process, which&#13;
information about the partner-to-be: its profile;        brought with it the opportunity to rebuild the&#13;
its institutional objectives; the assets it would bring  executive committee around a well-defined action&#13;
to the partnership; and its potential for providing      plan. The process had to start again.&#13;
professional advise and clout, for bringing along new&#13;
partners, and for becoming financial partners            The ability to communicate and build trust among&#13;
at some point.                                           a wide variety of institutions; the capacity to&#13;
                                                         promote partners' participation and commitment,&#13;
Steering committee members&#13;
in Peru participate in a global                          strengthening their ownership rights over the&#13;
&#13;
technical workshop                                       initiative; to know when to push and when to stop;&#13;
                                                         to be alert for changes and able to discover&#13;
The first year: The steering committee evolved           opportunities and manage risk as they appear, are&#13;
into a sound, well-defined executive committee,          all necessary tools for a coordinator.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     The Handwashing Handbook   45&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                        Box 12: Private Sector Handwashing Activities&#13;
&#13;
   The private sector engages worldwide in               handwashing among children. Handwashing has&#13;
   handwashing promotion and educational activities      been demonstrated to have a significant&#13;
   that can link and coordinate with country             impact in helping to reduce diarrhea and&#13;
   handwashing initiatives to leverage program scope     infectious diseases. The program operates as&#13;
   and help to ensure sustainability by tying            a partnership, with Safeguard providing&#13;
   handwashing messages to expanding soap brands.        expertise and materials while counting on its&#13;
   These excerpts from the promotional material of       media, government institutions, and education&#13;
   three large soap producers illustrate private sector  partners to reach people. Nationally known&#13;
   approaches to handwashing activities.                 newscaster Lolita Ayala, who has a foundation&#13;
   Colgate-Palmolive: Clean Hands, Good Health           for underprivileged children, endorses the&#13;
                                                         overall campaign.&#13;
   Health experts recommend handwashing as a key&#13;
   tool in protecting the public health. It's a          Safeguard donates a portion of sales to the&#13;
   mainstay in infection control. Yet surprisingly,      Solo por Ayudar Fund. The campaign employs&#13;
   promotion of handwashing to the general public        these partners:&#13;
   is not always visible. Research on habits of the&#13;
   general public reveals a gap between practice         ! Mexico's Institute of Social Security, which is&#13;
&#13;
   and the ideal. This is true in industrialized and     using its infrastructure to distribute materials on&#13;
   developing nations as well. To address the need       handwashing. The goal of this segment is to reach&#13;
   for handwashing promotion and education,              more than two million rural residents during the&#13;
   Colgate-Palmolive launched a global education         first 12 months. If Safeguard can reach this goal&#13;
   initiative, Clean Hands, Good HealthSM. The           with good results, it plans to expand the program&#13;
   initiative began in 1998 with a poster campaign       to reach 11 million people.&#13;
   entitled Lather Up for Good HealthTM, designed&#13;
   to promote and raise awareness of proper              ! More than 2,000 Mexican radio stations, which&#13;
&#13;
   handwashing through outreach to U.S. public           have been running information on handwashing.&#13;
   health professionals and the community at large.&#13;
   In 2000 the program was expanded with the             ! Mexico City's Children's Museum is featuring&#13;
&#13;
   introduction of a school education program            an interactive computer game about bacteria that&#13;
&#13;
   designed to help educators teach school-age           children can use at its main site and also in its&#13;
&#13;
   children in an engaging way. Since its U.S. launch,   traveling show.&#13;
&#13;
   millions of children have been reached in the         ! A puppet show promoting good hygiene to&#13;
   U.S., Asia, Latin America, and Africa. The            more than 80 percent of first-grade students&#13;
   program consists of both a structured school          in three cities, as well as in Merida's most&#13;
   curriculum as well as community programs.             popular plaza.&#13;
   Children, parents, educators, and health&#13;
   professionals work together to make                   Unilever: Lifebuoy Swasthya Chetna&#13;
   handwashing an important component of hygiene         (Awakening to One's Health)&#13;
   education and practice. Studies show that young&#13;
   children exposed to the curriculum can easily         This program was borne out of a need for&#13;
   grasp the how and why to wash, making it a great      personal hygiene practices like using soap&#13;
   companion in teaching self-protection.                everyday for handwashing as well as bathing in&#13;
                                                         India. It's a campaign in multiple phases and&#13;
   Procter &amp; Gamble:                                     touches every member of the community ­&#13;
   Mexico Handwashing Program                            children, parents, influencers, and young mothers&#13;
   Mexico's Safeguard bar soap has been running          ­ at all possible places of interaction, with every&#13;
   a multi-element campaign to promote                   possible media.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
46 The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   Lifebuoy Partnership&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       The program uses an innovative tool, the `Glow           The campaign is now in its third year, and the&#13;
       Germ demo,' to demolish the myth, `Visible clean         response has been very encouraging. Villagers speak&#13;
       is safe clean' and demonstrate `Water is not             very highly of it and consider it to be their campaign.&#13;
       enough.' Apart from this, stories, skits, quizzes,       Lifebuoy Swasthya Chetna is currently covering&#13;
       rallies, health checkup camps, posters,                  close to 18,000 villages across eight states, in&#13;
       newsletters, and stencils are used to deliver            keeping with the vision of contacting&#13;
       the message.                                             100 million people by the end of 2005.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Business Plan                                               The first draft outlines the vision for the&#13;
Setting up a handwashing partnership is an iterative and,       partnership. Updated versions will reflect the&#13;
in many cases, entrepreneurial process. While a general         participation of new partners and the completion&#13;
vision can be set out early on, objectives become more          of components, such as consumer research and the&#13;
detailed and activities crystallize as the project progresses.  communications strategy.&#13;
Holding this process together is the business plan&#13;
(box 13), which provides potential stakeholders with the        Business plans are usually limited to about 15 pages&#13;
justification for contributing and shows them where             with a one-or two-page executive summary.&#13;
resources are needed.                                           Interested parties can be invited to review more&#13;
                                                                detailed documents, such as consumer research&#13;
The business plan evolves with the initiative. As               results or the communications strategy. The business&#13;
the partnership grows, the business plan will help              plan should be drafted in a simple attractive format&#13;
participants consolidate ideas and reach consensus.             that is easily disseminated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            The Handwashing Handbook    47&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                Box 13: Elements of the Business Plan&#13;
&#13;
   This outline provides a starting point for a             The communications strategy summarizes the&#13;
   business plan that captures and promotes a               communications strategy, setting out precise,&#13;
   handwashing program.                                     measurable objectives, for example: "Double the&#13;
                                                            rates of handwashing with soap among mothers of&#13;
   Executive summary: A one- to two-page summary            children under five after using the toilet or cleaning&#13;
   of the business plan, usually written last.              up a child" or "Fifty percent of new mothers in&#13;
   Vision, needs statement, and brief initiative            the country will receive a free bar of soap and&#13;
   description: These brief documents answer such           instruction on the importance of handwashing." It&#13;
   questions as: What will the project achieve? What        sets out strategy, approaches, and the main&#13;
   needs will it fulfill? Who are the partners?             elements of the communications plan.&#13;
&#13;
   Sector summary: This document summarizes current         The communications campaign describes&#13;
   and projected development flows into the country         mass media, direct consumer contact, govern-&#13;
   that could be used for handwashing campaigns:            ment programs, public relations, and any&#13;
   MDGs and Poverty Reduction Strategies ­                  other components.&#13;
   sanitation and child mortality, etc. ­ show numbers      Monitoring and evaluation describes the M&amp;E&#13;
   and trends. Is this a growing area? It also describes    strategy:Whatdatawillbecollected,how,andwhen?&#13;
   the country's soap market: Who are the players&#13;
   by sales revenue and volume? What are the trends?        Management structure of the PPP: This is a record&#13;
                                                            of existing and desired committees and their&#13;
   Analysis of health burden and cost of disease            responsibilities, who will coordinate and what the&#13;
   What handwashing with soap can do: This document         coordination tasks will be, and a justification of the&#13;
   is a summary of the scientific evidence for the          choice of participants.&#13;
   importance of handwashing, its feasibility, and&#13;
   effectiveness. It forecasts the likely impact of the     Timing and milestones indicates the amount to be&#13;
&#13;
   partnership on health and the economy.                   funded and accomplishments to be completed by&#13;
                                                            stipulated dates. Financial position and funding&#13;
   Handwashing in country X provides consumer               needs show operating costs by component and&#13;
   research results and a summary of needed                 activity and includes sources of financing. It also&#13;
   behavior change.                                         provides secured and needed support.&#13;
&#13;
      Component                            Description  Time Line    Estimated Cost or `in       Source of&#13;
                                                                     Kind' if Support is         Funds (if&#13;
                                                                     Secured and Amount          Secured)&#13;
&#13;
      1. Situation assessment and&#13;
      initial consensus&#13;
&#13;
      2. Program establishment&#13;
&#13;
      3. Consumer research&#13;
&#13;
      4. Strategy development&#13;
&#13;
      5. Materials development&#13;
      and testing&#13;
&#13;
      6. Campaign implementation&#13;
&#13;
      7. Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
48 The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                    Conclusion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-SA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   STUBBS/WSP&#13;
&#13;
             GUY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      The Handwashing Handbook 49&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  Conclusion&#13;
&#13;
This handbook outlines an approach to the promotion of      sector. However, for handwashing to be widely accepted&#13;
handwashing with soap, an approach that will continue       and sustained, such programs also need ownership in&#13;
to develop.                                                 Ministries of Health and of Education.&#13;
&#13;
Many issues remain to be resolved. More work, for           Greater evidence on the importance of handwashing to&#13;
example, is needed to demonstrate cost-effectiveness.       public health will also help improve acceptance. In&#13;
In addition, public-private partnerships can be slow to     particular, rigorous trials of the impact of handwashing&#13;
build and be even slower to show results. This is not       on infectious disease are needed. The evidence for the&#13;
surprising, since communication between groups with         impact on acute respiratory infections, specifically, is still&#13;
different traditions, aims, and ways of doing business are  weak and needs more investigation. In addition more&#13;
difficult. Furthermore, personnel changes frequently        research on comparing the effectiveness of different&#13;
require that bridge building be repeated, as the Peru       approaches to generating behavior change will help&#13;
example shows. Nevertheless, as handwashing with soap       optimize implementation.&#13;
programs demonstrate their effectiveness, and&#13;
documentation of experiences is applied, momentum and       Available evidence is sufficient to enable public health to&#13;
&#13;
efficiencies will grow and stimulating partnerships         act on issues that, on balances of probability, look the&#13;
&#13;
should become easier.                                       most promising. From this perspective, making&#13;
                                                            handwashing with soap ubiquitous is a key challenge for&#13;
Anther key issue PPPs face is that hygiene does not have    public health in the 21st century. Government, industry,&#13;
a single institutional home. In the many programs, such     support agencies, and academia all have important&#13;
as Ghana, funding came from the water and sanitation        roles to play.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
50    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                 References&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
AMERICA&#13;
&#13;
       TIN&#13;
          -LA&#13;
&#13;
             WSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               The Handwashing Handbook 51&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             References and Resources&#13;
Burros A, D. Ross, W. Fonscea, L. Williams, and D. Moreira-                   Favin, M. 2004.ActivityReport143: PromotingHygieneBehaviorChange&#13;
Filho. 1999. Preventing acute respiratory infections and diarrhoea in         within C-IMCI: The Peru and Nicaragua Experience. Washington, D.C.:&#13;
child day care centres. Acta Paediatrica 88(10): 1113­18.                     EnvironmentalHealthProject OHIDN/BGH/USAID.www.ehproject.org.&#13;
Bateman, M., Bendehmane, D., and Saade, C. 2001. The Story of a               Favin M., Naimoli G., and Sherburne L. 2004. Joint Publication 7:&#13;
Successful Public-Private Partnership in Central America, Handwashing for     Improving Health Through Behavior Change: A Process Guide on Hygiene&#13;
Diarrheal Disease Prevention. Arlington, VA.: BASICS II, UNICEF, World        Promotion. Washington, D.C.: PAHO, PLAN and EHP OHIDN/BGH/&#13;
Bank and EHP OHIDN/BGH/USAID. www.ehproject.org.                              USAID. www.ehproject.org.&#13;
Bateman M., Jahan R., Brahman S., Zeitlyn S., and Laston S. Joint             Gilman R.H., G.S. Marquis, G. Ventura et al. 1993. Water cost and&#13;
Publication 4: Prevention of Diarrhea through Improving Hygiene Behaviors:    availability: Key determinants of family hygiene in a Peruvian shantytown.&#13;
The Sanitation and Family Education (SAFE) Pilot Project Experience. CARE,    American Journal of Public Health 83 (1): 1554-58.&#13;
ICDDR,B and EHP (OHIDN/BGH/USAID). Reprinted in 2002.&#13;
www.ehproject.org.                                                            Hoque, B.A. 2003. Handwashing Practices and Challenges in&#13;
                                                                              Bangladesh. International Journal of Environmental Health Research, 13&#13;
Biran, A. 1999. What form could a DFID-funded Hygiene Promotion               Supplement 1: 81-87.&#13;
ProgrammeTakeinOrdertoSupportandHelpEnsureMaximumHealth&#13;
Benefits from Proposed Improvements to Water Supply Systems in                Jones,G.,Steketee,R.W.,Black,R.E.,Bhutta,Z.A.,Morris,S.S.and&#13;
Northern Kyrgystan? MSc Thesis for LSHTM.                                     theBellagioChildSurvivalStudyGroup.2003.HowManyChildDeaths&#13;
                                                                              Can We Prevent This Year?" Lancet, 362: 65-71.&#13;
BuchholzandWordemann.2001.WhatMakesWinningBrandsDifferent:&#13;
The Hidden Method behind the World's Most Successful Brands. Wiley &amp;          Kolesor, R., Kleinau, E., Torres, M.P., Gil, C., de la Cruz, V. and&#13;
Sons, Chichester.                                                             Post, M. Combining Hygiene Behavior Change with Water and Sanitation:&#13;
                                                                              Monitoring Progress in Hato Mayor, Dominican Republic. Washington, D.C.:&#13;
Cairncross, S. and Shordt, K. "It Does Last! Some Findings from the           Environmental Health Project OHIDN/BGH/USAID, 2003.&#13;
Multi-City Study of Hygiene Sustainability." Waterlines 22 (3): 4-7.          www.ehproject.org.&#13;
Cercone, James A. et al. 2004. Handwashing as a cost-effective&#13;
approach to improving health: A framework for the economic analysis           Luby, S. P., M. Agboatwalla, J. Painter, A. Altaf, W.L. Billhimer, and&#13;
&#13;
of handwashing projects: Case study of Central America and Peru.              R.M. Hoekstra. 2004. Effect of intensive handwashing promotion on&#13;
                                                                              childhood diarrhea in high-risk communities in Pakistan: A randomized&#13;
Curtis V., B. Kanki, S. Cousens et al. 2001. Evidence for behaviour           controlled trial. Journal of the American Medical Association 291: 2547-54.&#13;
changefollowingahygienepromotionprogrammeinWestAfrica.Bulletin&#13;
of the World Health Organization 79 (6): 518-26.                              McGahey, C. and Rosensweig, F. 2002. Hygiene Improvement&#13;
                                                                              Framework. Washington, D.C.: Water Supply and Sanitation Collaborative&#13;
Curtis V., A. Biran, Deverell K., C. Hughes, K. Bellamy, and                  Council (WSSCC) and EHP OHIDN/BGH/USAID. www.ehproject.org.&#13;
B. Drasar. 2003. Hygiene in the home: Relating bugs and behaviour.&#13;
Social Science and Medicine 57 (4): 657-72.                                   Omotade, O.O., C.M. Kayode, A.A. Adeyemo, and O. Oladepo.&#13;
                                                                              1995. Observations on handwashing practices of mothers and&#13;
Curtis V. and Cairncross. 2003.Water, Sanitation &amp; Hygiene at Kyoto.          environmental conditions in Ona-Ara Local Government Area of Oyo&#13;
British Medical Journal 327: 3-4                                              State, Nigeria. Journal of Diarrhoeal Disease Research 13 (4): 224-28.&#13;
Curtis V. and Cairncross. 2003. Effect of washing hands with soap on          PRISM and EHP. 2004. Joint Publication 11E: Behavioral Study of&#13;
diarrhoeariskinthecommunity:asystematicreviewTheLancet Infectious             Handwashing with Soap in Peri-urban and Rural Areas of Peru. Washington,&#13;
Diseases 2003; 3: 275-81                                                      D.C.: EHP OHIDN/BGH/USAID. www.ehproject.org&#13;
Delafield, S. 2004. Activity Report 128: Planning Tools for the Nepal&#13;
Public-Private Partnership for Handwashing Initiative. Environmental Health   Rai, R., Khanal, S., and Wicken, P. 2004. Hygiene Behavior Can Be&#13;
&#13;
Project OHIDN/BGH/USAID. www.ehproject.org.                                   Sustained, A Report on the Nepal Country Findings of a Multi-Country Study&#13;
                                                                              on Sustaining Changes in Hygiene Behavior. NEWAH.&#13;
EHP. 2004.StrategicReport8:AssessingHygieneImprovement:Guidelines&#13;
for Household and Community Levels. Environmental Health Project              Simpson,Mayling,Sawyer,Ron,andClarke,Lucy.1997. Participatory&#13;
OHIDN/BGH/USAID, 2004. www.ehproject.org.                                     Hygiene and Sanitation Transformation (PHAST): A New Approach to Working&#13;
                                                                              with Communities. WHO, EOS/96.11; reprinted 2002. www.WHO.org.&#13;
EHP,UNICEF,WB/WSP,WSSCC,andUSAID.2004.JointPublication&#13;
8: The Hygiene Improvement Framework: A Comprehensive Approach to             Sircar B.K., P.G. Sengupta, S.K. Mondal et al. 1996. Effect of&#13;
Preventing Childhood Diarrhea. Washington, D.C.: UNICEF, WB/WSP,              handwashing on the incidence of diarrhoea in a Calcutta slum. In Journal&#13;
WSSCC, and EHP OHIDN/BGH/USAID. www.ehproject.org.                            of Diarrhoeal Diseases Research 5 (20): 114.&#13;
&#13;
EHP, UNICEF, WSSCC and USAID. 2004. Joint Publication 13                      UNICEF/WES, USAID, World Bank/WSP, WSSCC. 2004. Joint&#13;
(Adapted from EHP Joint Publication 8): Preventing Childhood Diarrhea         Publication8,TheHygieneImprovementFramework:AComprehensive&#13;
Through Hygiene Improvement. Washington, D.C.: EHP OHIDN/BGH/                 Approach for Preventing Childhood Diarrhea.&#13;
USAID. www.ehproject.org.&#13;
                                                                              Wood S., Sawyer R., Simpson-Hebert M. 2002. PHAST step-by-&#13;
EHP. Behavior Change Lessons Learned. Washington, D.C.: EHP Office            step guide: a participatory approach for the control of diarrhoeal disease.&#13;
of Health, Infections Diseases and Nutrition, Bureau for Global Health,       Geneva,WorldHealthOrganization(unpublisheddocumentWHO/EOS/&#13;
U.S.AgencyforInternationalDevelopment(OHIDN/BGH/USAID),1999.                  98.3). www.WHO.org.&#13;
www.ehproject.org.&#13;
Esrey S.A., J.B. Potash, L. Roberts, and C. Shiff. 1991. Effects of           Zaltman, J. 2003. How Customers Think: Essential Insights into the Mind&#13;
&#13;
improved water supply and sanitation on ascariasis, diarrhoea,                of the Market. Harvard Business School Press.&#13;
&#13;
dracunculiasis, hookworm infection, schistosomiasis, and trachoma.            World Bank, EHP, WSP: Handwashing Consumer Research Reports:&#13;
Bulletin of the World Health Organization 69 (5): 609-21                      Ghana, Peru, Senegal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
52      The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                   Tools and&#13;
                   Terms of Reference&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
AMERICA&#13;
&#13;
       TIN&#13;
          -LA&#13;
&#13;
             WSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         The Handwashing Handbook 53&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                 Tools and Terms of Reference&#13;
&#13;
Tool 1: Behavioral Trials and In-depth                          In the course of the interview you are to probe into the&#13;
Interviewing                                                    reasons, likes, and dislikes for each separate handwashing&#13;
Information and Instructions for Fieldworkers                   occasion, noting whether soap is used or not and why. It&#13;
                                                                is just as important to learn from those women who did&#13;
What Is a Behavioral Trial?                                     not use the soap given to them as those who experienced&#13;
A behavioral trial introduces a behavior to individuals and     positive experiences. Often informants will refer to&#13;
assesses their experiences with trying to carry out that        subjective concepts such as cleanliness and dirtiness. It is&#13;
behavior over a period of seven to 14 days. It gives insight    important that you probe into what people mean by such&#13;
into how easily that new behavior is adopted, things that       terms and how they are indicated, noting especially what&#13;
facilitated its practice, and those that hindered it. In this   sensory cues (touch, sight, smell, etc.) are involved.&#13;
case a soap is given to each participant, who is asked to       The Post-Experience Interview&#13;
use this soap ONLY for handwashing with soap, focusing&#13;
particularly on handwashing after contact with feces (after     ! Last week I left a soap with you and asked you to use&#13;
defecation, after wiping a child's behind, and after            it specifically for handwashing, did you use it?&#13;
disposing of stools), and before feeding a child. After a&#13;
period of time an interviewer visits each woman and             ! ASK TO SEE THE SOAP AND NOTE HOW MUCH&#13;
&#13;
carries out an in-depth interview with her to learn about       THE PRODUCT APPEARS TO BE USED AND WHERE&#13;
&#13;
her experiences between the two visits.                         IT WAS KEPT: RECORD ITS CONDITION:&#13;
                                                                _________________________________________________________________________&#13;
The key practice we are interested is handwashing with          _________________________________________________________________________&#13;
soap, what motivates women to carry out this behavior,          WHERE SOAP WAS KEPT:_____________________&#13;
and what hinders them. In particular, we are interested&#13;
in handwashing WITH SOAP after defecation, after                _________________________________________________________________________&#13;
&#13;
wiping a child's behind, after disposing of a child's stools,   ! Before we begin, may I get some basic&#13;
and before feeding a child.                                     sociodemographic information from you?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                How old are you?&#13;
                Under 24 = 1                25-30 = 2&#13;
                31-35 = 3                   36-40 = 4&#13;
                41+ = 5&#13;
&#13;
                Where do you live?&#13;
                Place Name: ______________________&#13;
                Place Type: Urban = 1       Peri-urban = 2    Rural = 3&#13;
&#13;
                What is the highest level of education you have attained?&#13;
&#13;
                What is your occupation?&#13;
&#13;
                What is your husband's occupation?&#13;
&#13;
                Does your husband work at home or away?&#13;
                Home = 1 Away = 2&#13;
&#13;
                How many children do you have?&#13;
                One = 1       Two = 2       Three = 3, etc.&#13;
&#13;
                How many of these are under five years?&#13;
                One = 1       Two = 2       Three = 3 etc.&#13;
                IF NO CHILD IS UNDER FIVE YEARS, TERMINATE INTERVIEW.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
54     The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
           How old is your youngest child?&#13;
           0-6 months = 1      7-12 months = 2&#13;
           1-2 years = 3       3-5 years = 4&#13;
&#13;
           Have you moved to work or live in another town/city in the past&#13;
           12 months? Yes = 1          No = 2&#13;
           Place:_____________________________&#13;
&#13;
           Where do you defecate?&#13;
           WC = 1       Private ordinary pit = 2   Private VIP = 3&#13;
           Private pour-flush = 4      Public = 5  Bush = 6&#13;
           Other = 7 _______________________&#13;
&#13;
           Where do your children defecate?&#13;
           Pottie = 1 Wrapper = 2            Floor = 3    As above = 4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Now conduct the interview covering the topics below:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
General Soap              Before being given this soap, for what did you use the soap and why?&#13;
Experiences               Usual handwash occasions and reasons.&#13;
                          IF THEY MENTION DIRT OR CLEANLINESS, ASK THEM WHAT THEY MEAN&#13;
(Each time a                  AND HOW THEY CAN TELL IF SOMETHING IS CLEAN OR DIRTY (I.E.,&#13;
handwashing is                CAN YOU BE DIRTY EVEN IF YOU CANNOT SEE, SMELL OR TOUCH&#13;
mentioned, clarify            THE DIRT?).&#13;
whether soap is used      Water source for handwashing.&#13;
or not and why hands      Any shortages in water supply?&#13;
are washed with or        Does this affect handwash practice?&#13;
without soap.)            Is soap ever used for handwashing? If so, when and why? What cues drive the use of&#13;
                              soap? If not, then why is soap not used?&#13;
                          Type of soap: Toilet or multipurpose. REASONS.&#13;
                          Soap source and storage.&#13;
                          Availability of soap.&#13;
                          What happens when soap is unavailable?&#13;
                          How do women feel when soap is not available, how do they get over this?&#13;
                          Key benefits to using soap for handwashing AT EACH JUNCTURE.&#13;
                          Key dislikes/problems associated with handwashing with soap.&#13;
                          Most important times to wash hands with AND without soap. Reasons.&#13;
                          Other uses of soap and reasons.&#13;
&#13;
Soap Usage                Was the soap given to the woman used?&#13;
                          What was it used for and where was it kept? (Get woman to show you, if she hasn't&#13;
                              already. Note soap condition and place of storage.)&#13;
&#13;
Non-Soap Users/           Why was the soap not used?&#13;
Little Use                Are these reasons general or specific to the brand given?&#13;
                          What would have aided/encouraged soap use?&#13;
                          Was a different soap used for handwashing? IF ANSWER IS YES, CARRY ON AS BELOW,&#13;
                              IF NOT TERMINATE INTERVIEW.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    The Handwashing Handbook 55&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  Soap Users                   If not already answered, for what purpose was the soap used for and why? PAY&#13;
                                   PARTICULAR ATTENTION TO HANDWASHING WITH SOAP. BE SURE&#13;
                                   TO NOTE THE REASONS FOR EACH SEPARATE HANDWASH&#13;
                                   INCIDENCE (THE REASONS ARE LIKELY TO BE DIFFERENT).&#13;
                               Did other people in the household use the soap, if so which members, for what purpose&#13;
                                   and why?&#13;
&#13;
  Soap Use Experiences         Likes and dislikes about the soap given.&#13;
                               Feeling after handwashing with soap ­ at each juncture.&#13;
                               Differences between using soap and water alone ­ at each juncture.&#13;
                               Difficulties associated with handwashing with soap.&#13;
                               How difficulties were overcome.&#13;
                               Was handwashing with soap ever forgotten, if so why and what was done to remember.&#13;
                               Best things about handwashing with soap.&#13;
                               Worst things about handwashing with soap.&#13;
                               Benefits of handwashing with soap, both absolutely and as compared to&#13;
                                   using water alone.&#13;
&#13;
  Soap Attributes              If a person has not been asked about likes and dislikes of soap in above section ask now.&#13;
                               Was soap given a good one, or is there one on the market that is better. If so, which one&#13;
                                   and why?&#13;
                               Most important attributes of a soap for handwashing. (Probes: cost, smell, color,&#13;
                                   multipurpose, skin care, size, lather, etc.) Reasons.&#13;
&#13;
  FINAL                        Having experienced handwashing with soap does the participant think it is good?&#13;
                               Will she continue to handwashing with soap once this bar has finished?&#13;
                               Will she continue to buy soap? From where, which one?&#13;
                               What will she use it for?&#13;
                               How would she persuade someone else to take up the habit of handwashing with soap?&#13;
                               Ask "If I returned in a month, or a year, would I still find you washing your hands with&#13;
                                   soap?" And "At what junctures would you be washing your hands with soap?"&#13;
&#13;
                               THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR TAKING THE TIME TO TALK TO ME, I HAVE&#13;
                                   LEARNED A LOT FROM YOU. OUR CHAT HAS BEEN VERY INTERESTING.&#13;
                                   DO YOU HAVE ANY FINAL COMMENTS?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tool 2: Structured Observations                                  Instructions&#13;
Format to be Adapted for Behavior Study and Baseline for M&amp;E     Arrive five minutes before start of observation time&#13;
                                                                 (05.55).&#13;
Objectives: to Determine:&#13;
! The proportion of times mothers wash hands with                Greet politely and ask for a seat in the yard. Place the&#13;
soap (WHWS) after using the toilet.                              seat where you can observe domestic activity.&#13;
! The proportion of times mothers WHWS after&#13;
cleaning up a child.                                             Sit quietly and keep conversation to the absolute&#13;
! The proportion of times mothers WHWS before                    minimum.&#13;
feeding a child.                                                 When an event of interest occurs, watch closely what&#13;
! The proportion of times school-age children WHWS               happens, then fill in the relevant section of the form.&#13;
after the toilet at home.&#13;
! The proportion of times school-age children WHWS               After completing the observation period, move on to&#13;
before eating at home.                                           the survey form (questionnaire).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
56   The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Before leaving, check that an answer&#13;
has been filled in to every question.&#13;
This will prevent your having to come&#13;
back again.&#13;
&#13;
Always use a blue biro. Any other&#13;
colors or writing instruments will&#13;
be refused.&#13;
&#13;
Put a ring round the correct response.&#13;
If you make a mistake, cross it through&#13;
once and ring the correct response.&#13;
&#13;
Only one response is allowed for&#13;
each question.&#13;
&#13;
Only supervisors can fill in 9 or 99.&#13;
&#13;
Notes&#13;
Format designed for analysis with&#13;
EPIINFO: 5-letter codes are unique&#13;
identifiers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Structured Observation of Childcare Practices&#13;
Section 1. Identification&#13;
&#13;
   1.1     Identification number of mother                                IDMOT&#13;
           |__|__|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
   1.2     Identification number of observer                              IDOBS&#13;
           |__|__|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
   1.3     Name                                                           NMEMO&#13;
&#13;
   1.4     Address                                                        ADDMO&#13;
&#13;
   1.5     Name of the index child &lt;5                                     NMECH&#13;
&#13;
   1.6     Sex of the child                      M=1   F=2         9.     SEXCH&#13;
&#13;
   1.7     Date of visit                                                  DAVIS&#13;
           |__|__|.|__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
   1.8     Arrival time                                                   ARRTI&#13;
           |__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
   1.9     Observation start time                                         STATI&#13;
           |__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
   1.10    Observation complete time                                      FINTI&#13;
           |__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       The Handwashing Handbook 57&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section 2. Index Child Defecation&#13;
&#13;
 2.1    Did the index child defecate while you were present?&#13;
        Yes, I saw = 1     Yes, I'm sure s/he did = 2 No s/he didn't = 3                        9   ICDEF&#13;
&#13;
        ONLY FILL IN THE NEXT SECTION IF THE INDEX CHILD DEFECATED&#13;
&#13;
 2.2    What time did the child defecate?                                                           TIDEF&#13;
        |__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
 2.3    Where did the child defecate (first time)?&#13;
        In a nappy/pants/wrapper = 1      On the ground/floor in the yard/house = 2&#13;
        In a potty = 3    On the ground outside the compound = 4&#13;
        On a paper = 5        In the toilet = 6&#13;
        Other (write in) = 7.......................................................             9   WHDEF&#13;
&#13;
 2.4    Did someone clean the child's bottom?&#13;
        Nobody = 1 Mother = 2           Sister = 3     Grandmother = 4              Other = 5    9  CLBOT&#13;
&#13;
 2.5    Did someone clear up the child's stools straightaway?&#13;
        No = 1      Mother = 2       Sister = 3        Grandmother = 4            Other = 5      9  CLST1&#13;
&#13;
 2.6    Immediately after completing stool contact, did the person . . .&#13;
        Carry on as before = 1            Rinse one hand with water = 2&#13;
        Rinse both hands with water = 3          Wash one hand with soap = 4&#13;
        Wash both hands with soap = 5       Rinse hands in soapy water = 6&#13;
        Take a bath = 7      Unable to see = 8                                                   9  ICWH1&#13;
&#13;
        If 2.4 and 2.5 were different, for the second person fill in:&#13;
&#13;
 2.7    Immediately after completing stool contact did the second person . . .&#13;
        Carry on as before = 1            Rinse one hand with water = 2&#13;
        Rinse both hands with water = 3          Wash one hand with soap = 4&#13;
        Wash both hands with soap = 5       Rinse hands in soapy water = 6&#13;
        Take a bath =7      No second person/Unable to see = 8                                   9  ICWH2&#13;
&#13;
 2.8    Did someone clear up the child's stools later on?&#13;
        No = 1      Mother = 2       Sister = 3        Grandmother = 4            Other = 5      9  CLST2&#13;
&#13;
 2.9    Immediately after clearing up stools did the person . . .&#13;
        Carry on as before = 1            Rinse one hand with water = 2&#13;
        Rinse both hands with water = 3          Wash one hand with soap = 4&#13;
        Wash both hands with soap = 5       Rinse hands in soapy water = 6&#13;
        Take a bath = 7      Unable to see = 8                                                   9  ICWH3&#13;
&#13;
 2.10   Where did water for handwashing (first person) come from?&#13;
        Hands not washed = 1       From a container in the compound = 2&#13;
        Laundry water = 3 A tap = 4         Unable to see = 5                                   9   ICWAT&#13;
&#13;
 2.11   Where did soap for handwashing come from?&#13;
        Soap not used =1 Soap kept near water source = 2&#13;
        Soap distant from water source = 3 Unable to see = 4                                    9   ICSOA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
58  The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 2.12   What brand of soap was used?&#13;
        Soap not used = 01      Duck = 02 Imperial Leather = 03             Sunlight = 04&#13;
        Canoe = 05            Rexona = 06               Lifebuoy = 07         Key = 08&#13;
        Medimix = 09           Geisha = 10           Sweetie = 11               Johnson's&#13;
        Baby = 12               Ayu = 13                   Safeguard = 14       Sa = 15&#13;
        CB = 16                        Guardian = 17               Harmony= 18&#13;
        Village Fresh liquid = 19           Tempo = 20                Fa = 21&#13;
        Premier =2 2 Lux = 23 ..... List&#13;
        Soap powder = 64&#13;
        Unidentified liquid soap = 65                   Unidentified brown soap = 66&#13;
        Unidentified colored soap = 67                      Unidentified local soap = 68             9      ICBRD&#13;
        Other = 77 Specify___________________&#13;
        Unable to see = 88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Section 3. Feeding Index Child&#13;
&#13;
 3.1    Did a carer feed the index child during the observation period?&#13;
        Yes, I'm sure = 1 Yes, I think so = 2 No = 3                                                9       ICFED&#13;
&#13;
        ONLY FILL IN THE QUESTIONS BELOW IF THE INDEX CHILD WAS FED&#13;
&#13;
 3.2    For the first item of food or meal, who fed the child?&#13;
        Mother = 1       Sister = 2    Grandmother = 3&#13;
        Other = 4...........................................                                        9       ICWFD&#13;
&#13;
 3.3    What was the food and how was it served?&#13;
        `Meal' food served with an implement = 1 `Meal' food served with hands = 2&#13;
        Liquid food served with an implement = 3 Liquid food served with hands = 4&#13;
        Snack food served with an implement = 5         Snack food served with hands = 6            9       ICFOO&#13;
&#13;
 3.3    Immediately before feeding did the person . . .&#13;
        Not wash hands = 1            Rinse one hand with water = 2&#13;
        Rinse both hands with water = 3           Wash one hand with soap = 4&#13;
        Wash both hands with soap = 5       Rinse hands in soapy water = 6&#13;
        Take a bath = 7        Unable to see = 8                                                    9       ICFWH&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         The Handwashing Handbook 59&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section 4. Mother's Defecation&#13;
&#13;
 4.1    Did mother go for defecation/toilet during the observation period?&#13;
        Yes, I'm sure = 1 Yes, I think so = 2 No = 3                                       9  MODEF&#13;
&#13;
        ONLY FILL IN THESE QUESTIONS IF THE MOTHER WENT FOR DEFECATION&#13;
&#13;
 4.2    Where did mother go for toilet?&#13;
        To a public toilet = 1      To a toilet outside the compound = 2&#13;
        To a toilet in the compound = 3           To a toilet inside her house = 4&#13;
        To the bush = 5                 Used a paper = 6           Not sure = 7            9  MOWHE&#13;
&#13;
 4.3    Immediately after completion, did she . . .&#13;
        Carry on as before = 1           Rinse one hand with water = 2&#13;
        Rinse both hands with water = 3          Wash one hand with soap = 4&#13;
        Wash both hands with soap = 5       Rinse hands in soapy water = 6&#13;
        Take a bath = 7       Unable to see = 8                                            9  MOWHS&#13;
&#13;
 4.4    Where did water for handwashing come from?&#13;
        Hands not washed = 1       From a container in the compound = 2&#13;
        A tap = 3      Unable to see = 4                                                   9  MOWAT&#13;
&#13;
 4.5    Where did soap for handwashing come from?&#13;
        Soap not used = 1 Soap kept near water source = 2&#13;
        Soap distant from water source = 3 Unable to see = 4                               9  MOSOA&#13;
&#13;
 4.6    What make of soap was used?&#13;
        Soap not used = 01      Duck = 02       Imperial Leather = 03     Sunlight = 04&#13;
        Canoe = 05            Rexona = 06             Lifebuoy = 07       Key = 08&#13;
        Medimix = 09          Geisha = 10 Sweetie = 11             Johnson's Baby = 12&#13;
        Ayu = 13          Safeguard = 14 Sa = 15                     CB = 16&#13;
        Guardian = 17            Harmony = 18        Village fresh liquid = 19             99&#13;
        Tempo = 20             Fa = 21                    Premier = 22 Lux = 23 .....&#13;
        List&#13;
        Soap Powder = 64&#13;
        Unidentified liquid soap = 65                   Unidentified brown soap = 66&#13;
        Unidentified coloured soap =67                   Unidentified local soap = 68&#13;
        Other = 77 Specify                                                                    MOBRD&#13;
        ________________________________________________&#13;
        Unable to see = 88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
60  The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section 5. School-Age Child Defecation&#13;
&#13;
RECORD FIRST SCHOOL-AGE CHILD SEEN&#13;
&#13;
 5.1    Did you see a school-age child going for defecation during the observation period?&#13;
        Yes, I'm sure = 1 Yes, I think so = 2 No = 3                                            9       SCDEF&#13;
&#13;
        ONLY FILL IN THESE QUESTIONS IF YOU SEE A SCHOOL-AGE CHILD GO FOR DEFECATION&#13;
&#13;
 5.2    Where did the child go for defecation?&#13;
        To a public toilet = 1     To a toilet outside the compound = 2&#13;
        To a toilet in the compound = 3          To a toilet inside his/her house = 4&#13;
        To the bush = 5                 Used a paper = 6          Not sure = 7                          SCWHE&#13;
&#13;
 5.3    Immediately after completion, did the child&#13;
        Carry on as before = 1          Rinse one hand with water = 2&#13;
        Rinse both hands with water = 3          Wash one hand with soap = 4&#13;
        Wash both hands with soap = 5      Rinse hands in soapy water = 6&#13;
        Take a bath = 7       Unable to see = 8                                                  9      SCWHS&#13;
&#13;
 5.4    Where did water for handwashing come from?&#13;
        Hands not washed = 1      From a container in the compound = 2&#13;
        Under a tap = 3      Unable to see = 4                                                   9      SCWAT&#13;
&#13;
 5.5    Where did soap for handwashing come from?&#13;
        Soap not used = 1 Soap kept near water source = 2&#13;
        Soap distant from water source = 3 Unable to see = 4                                     9      SCSOA&#13;
&#13;
 5.6    What make of soap was used?&#13;
        Key = 01 Duck = 02 Imperial leather = 03....List brands&#13;
        Unidentified brown soap = 66&#13;
        Unidentified colored soap = 67&#13;
        Unidentified local soap = 68&#13;
        Unable to see = 88                                                                       99     SCBRD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Section 6. School-age Child Seen Eating&#13;
NOTE: RECORD FIRST SCHOOL-AGE CHILD SEEN&#13;
EATING, MAY BE DIFFERENT FROM SECTION 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 6.1    Did you see a school-age child eating during the observation period?&#13;
        Yes = 1          No = 2                                                                  9      SCEAT&#13;
&#13;
        ONLY FILL IN THESE QUESTIONS IF YOU SEE A SCHOOL-AGE CHILD EATING&#13;
&#13;
 6.2    Immediately before eating did the person&#13;
        Not wash hands = 1            Rinse one hand with water = 2&#13;
        Rinse both hands with water = 3          Wash one hand with soap = 4&#13;
        Wash both hands with soap = 5      Rinse hands in soapy water = 6&#13;
        Take a bath = 7       Unable to see = 8                                                  9      SCEWH&#13;
&#13;
 6.3    What was the food and how was it eaten?&#13;
        `Meal' food eaten with an implement = 1 `Meal' food eaten with hands = 2&#13;
        Liquid food eaten with an implement = 3 Liquid food eaten with hands = 4&#13;
        Snack food eaten with an implement = 5 Snack food eaten with hands = 6                   9      SCFOO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     The Handwashing Handbook 61&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Structured Observation                                          Instructions&#13;
at Public Toilet                                                Arrive at 05.55.&#13;
Objective 1: Record total number of users and total&#13;
number of users who wash hands with soap.                       Sit in a place where you can see people entering and&#13;
                                                                leaving and where you can see handwashing, if any.&#13;
Objective 2: Record conditions in public toilets.&#13;
                                                                Carry out the observations.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                At 09.00 use the toilet and then fill out section 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Section 1. Identification&#13;
&#13;
 1.1        Identification number of toilet                                                                   IDTOI&#13;
            |__|__|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
 1.2        Identification number of observer                                                                 IDOBS&#13;
            |__|__|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
 1.3        Name of toilet                                                                                    NMEMO&#13;
&#13;
 1.4        Address                                                                                           ADDMO&#13;
&#13;
 1.5        Date of visit                                                                                     DAVIS&#13;
            |__|__|.|__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
 1.6        Arrival time                                                                                      ARRTI&#13;
            |__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
 1.7        Observation start time                                                                            STATI&#13;
            |__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
 1.8        Observation complete time                                                                         FINTI&#13;
            |__|__|.|__|__|&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Section 2. Public Toilet Conditions&#13;
Note: After completing observation, ask to use the toilet       Questions refer to the main part of the toilets used by&#13;
and fill in this section.                                       the general public.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 2.1        How many male cubicles does the toilet have?                                                       TCUBM&#13;
            01 02 03 04 05 06 07 08 09 10&#13;
            11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20                                                              99&#13;
&#13;
 2.2        How many female cubicles does the toilet have?                                                     TCUBF&#13;
            01 02 03 04 05 06 07 08 09 10&#13;
            11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20&#13;
            (If no M&amp;F, fill in just 2.1)                                                              99&#13;
            Is there a separate facility for VIPs?&#13;
            Yes = 1 No = 2&#13;
&#13;
 2.3        What is the price of using the toilet for an adult?&#13;
            |__|__|__|__| Cedis&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
62   The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2.3  What is the price of using the toilet for an adult?&#13;
     |__|__|__|__| Cedis&#13;
&#13;
2.4  What is the price of using the toilet for a child?&#13;
     |__|__|__|__| Cedis&#13;
&#13;
2.5  What is the additional cost of toilet paper?&#13;
     |__|__|__|__| Cedis&#13;
&#13;
2.6  What is the additional cost of washing hands?&#13;
     ||__|__|__|__| Cedis&#13;
&#13;
2.7  What is the condition of the superstructure?&#13;
     Overall, well maintained, roofed, recently painted = 1&#13;
     Reasonable, some cracks, painted but not recently = 2&#13;
     Tatty, dilapidated = 3                                                                            9&#13;
&#13;
2.8  What is the condition of the floors?&#13;
     Solid and very clean = 1&#13;
     Cracking, unswept = 2&#13;
     Dilapidated and dirty = 3                                                                         9&#13;
&#13;
2.9  What is the condition of the cubicles?&#13;
     Solid and very clean = 1&#13;
     Cracking, unswept = 2&#13;
     Dilapidated and dirty = 3                                                                         9&#13;
&#13;
2.10 What is the condition below ground?&#13;
     Sewer connection/septic tank (WCs) = 1&#13;
     Pit, not full = 2&#13;
     Pit, visibly nearly full = 3&#13;
     Pit full = 4&#13;
     Pit overflowing = 5                                                                               9&#13;
&#13;
2.11 Subjectively, how did you find using the toilet?&#13;
     Extremely smelly and disgusting = 1&#13;
     Smelly and disgusting = 2&#13;
     Reasonable = 3&#13;
     Very clean and free of smell = 4                                                                  9&#13;
&#13;
2.12 Any other remarks (insects, flies, dangerous structure, feces on ground, etc.)&#13;
&#13;
2.13 Is there some means of washing hands inside the toilet building?&#13;
     Yes = 1 No = 2&#13;
&#13;
2.14 Is there some means of washing hands immediately on exit&#13;
     from the toilet building?       Yes = 1 No = 2&#13;
&#13;
     If no to 2.13 and 2.14 skip to Q&#13;
&#13;
2.15 Source of water for handwashing&#13;
     None = 1 Basin with tap water (functioning) = 2&#13;
     Handwashing stand with water = 3 Bowl or container to put hands in = 4&#13;
     Container of water, water given to clients = 5&#13;
     Other.... Describe = 6.................................................................           9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            The Handwashing Handbook 63&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  2.16  Is soap available for handwashing?&#13;
        Yes = 1     No = 2&#13;
&#13;
  2.17  What sort of soap is available?&#13;
        What make of soap was used?&#13;
        Soap not used = 01       Duck = 02     Imperial Leather = 03            Sunlight = 04&#13;
        Canoe = 05             Rexona = 06              Lifebuoy = 07           Key = 08&#13;
        Medimix = 09           Geisha = 10 Sweetie = 11                   Johnson's Baby = 12&#13;
        Ayu = 13                Safeguard = 14 Sa = 15                          CB = 16&#13;
        Guardian = 17             Harmony = 18       Village fresh liquid = 19&#13;
        Tempo = 20          Fa = 21     Premier = 22 Lux = 23 .....                   List&#13;
        Soap Powder = 64&#13;
        Unidentified liquid soap = 65                      Unidentified brown soap = 66&#13;
        Unidentified coloured soap = 67                    Unidentified local soap = 68&#13;
        Other = 77 Specify....................................................................&#13;
        Unable to see = 88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
64  The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section 2. Observation Of Clients Leaving Facility           It is very important that you record all people leaving.&#13;
Instructions: Complete for all people leaving. If you miss   (WH = washed hands; WHWW = washed hands with&#13;
whether they washed their hands, indicate "didn't see."      water; WHWS = washed hands with soap).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Person                                                  Tick One                                    Office Use&#13;
&#13;
              Exit time        Didn't WH           WHWW           WHWS            Didn't see&#13;
&#13;
  1&#13;
&#13;
  2&#13;
&#13;
  3&#13;
&#13;
  4&#13;
&#13;
  5&#13;
&#13;
  6&#13;
&#13;
  7&#13;
&#13;
  8&#13;
&#13;
  9&#13;
&#13;
  10&#13;
&#13;
  11&#13;
&#13;
  12&#13;
&#13;
  13&#13;
&#13;
  14&#13;
&#13;
  15&#13;
&#13;
  16&#13;
&#13;
  17&#13;
&#13;
  18&#13;
&#13;
  19&#13;
&#13;
  20&#13;
&#13;
  21&#13;
&#13;
  22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      The Handwashing Handbook    65&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Tool 3: Focus Groups                                           Begin with a round of introductions. Each woman should&#13;
                                                               introduce herself (she may use an alias), what her&#13;
Handwash Behavior Study Instruments                            occupation is, what her husband's occupation is, how many&#13;
Focus Group Discussion Guide                                   children she has, and how old they are.&#13;
&#13;
Instructions for Fieldworkers:                                 We are going to focus the discussion on a series of&#13;
The key practice we are interested is handwashing              exercises to encourage group interactions: the basic&#13;
with soap, what motivates women to carry out this              content of each exercise is described below.&#13;
behavior and what hinders them. In particular we&#13;
are interested in handwashing with soap after                  The Exercises&#13;
defecation, after wiping a child's behind, after               1. Daily Activities/Life Values&#13;
disposing of a child's stools, and before feeding a child.     ! Ask each woman to outline what they do each day,&#13;
&#13;
In the course of the focus group, you are to probe into        noting the key activities on separate pieces of paper.&#13;
&#13;
reasons, likes, and dislikes for each separate handwashing     ! Wheneachwomanhassummarizedherday,askthem&#13;
occasion, noting whether soap is used or not and why. It       to rank these activities in order of their importance and&#13;
can be difficult in transcripts to distinguish whether people  the satisfaction and enjoyment each activity provides.&#13;
are talking about bathing, handwashing with water alone,       They may shuffle the pieces of paper around, as this&#13;
or handwashing with soap. It is therefore important that       helps the thought processes and discussion.&#13;
you are make clear which of these the participant is&#13;
talking about on each occasion. While women's bathing          ! Askthewomentoexplainthereasonsfortheranking&#13;
behaviors can be interesting and inform us about               they have chosen.&#13;
motivations for more general hygiene behaviors, the focus&#13;
of interviews should always be handwashing with soap.          2. Soap Use Ranking&#13;
                                                               ! Ask each woman to note what she uses soap for,&#13;
Often informants will refer to subjective concepts such        noting each use on a separate piece of paper.&#13;
as cleanliness and dirtiness. It is important that you&#13;
probe into what people mean by such terms and how              ! When each woman has summarized the main uses of&#13;
&#13;
they are indicated, noting especially what sensory cues        soap, ask them to rank these in order of importance,&#13;
&#13;
(touch, sight, smell, etc.) are involved. Often habit will     discussing while they do this and the reasons for the order&#13;
&#13;
be mentioned, or women will not be sure as to why              they are choosing.&#13;
&#13;
they hand wash with soap: try to probe into when they          3. Handwash Junctures Ranking&#13;
started the practice, who taught them, why and when.           ! Ask the women when they wash their hands, noting&#13;
Whenever someone gives a reason for a behavior,                each handwashing occasion on a separate piece of paper.&#13;
especially handwashing with soap try to probe as deeply        For each juncture ask whether soap is used and note this&#13;
as possible, often the original answer is a means to           on the appropriate piece of paper.&#13;
achieving a higher goal, and we want to know what this&#13;
final goal is. What are the most important benefits of         ! Lay the pieces of paper out in two categories: with&#13;
hand washing with soap?                                        and without soap.&#13;
&#13;
In focus group discussions it is common that certain           ! For each category ask women which junctures are&#13;
participants dominate, while others keep quiet. We want        most important for handwashing and why handwashing&#13;
to hear everyone's views, so try to encourage everyone to      is practiced.&#13;
contribute. It is also important to allow women to guide       ! In the case of water only, ask why soap is not used.&#13;
the shape of exercises and discussion themselves. While&#13;
youareafacilitator,youmustnottakeovertoomuch:Women             ! In the case of with soap, ask why soap is used.&#13;
should feel in control of what they are doing/discussing.      ! Note ­ in discussion of reasons for handwashing (both&#13;
                                                               with and without soap), deep probing is necessary to&#13;
The Discussion                                                 understand what cues are most important. Terms such as&#13;
Before beginning, explain to women that there are no           cleanliness and dirtiness are not reasons in themselves: How&#13;
right or wrong answers and that you just want to learn         is the reason to wash hands perceived? Sensory cues, feelings&#13;
from them and hear what they think.                            of contamination, other people watching, protect child, etc.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
66    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4. Personification Exercise                               ! Which ads have they seen/heard and liked lately?&#13;
! Ask women to describe the profile of the following      Why did they like them? Do they make them want to&#13;
two people:                                               buy the products?&#13;
1. A person who washes their hands with soap regularly.&#13;
&#13;
2. A person who never washes their hands with soap.       Tool 4: Tips on Researching&#13;
                                                          School-Aged Children&#13;
   Probes: Appearance, hobbies, music preference,         School toilets are not just used for practical issues of&#13;
   educational level, position in society, condition of   hygiene. Adolescent girls may meet to apply make up,&#13;
   compound, what people think of them, etc.              discuss boys, and make plans for after school, and boys&#13;
                                                          may smoke a cigarette. Children may have different&#13;
! What do women feel about the two people they            motivators for using the toilets, mainly to gossip and to&#13;
have described?                                           have some private time with their friends, far from the&#13;
5. Concepts Ranking                                       watchful eye of the teachers. Children may be reluctant&#13;
! Read out each concept (social acceptance, status,       to wash their hands in school, because being a good&#13;
health, nurture/children, cleaniliness/contamination,     student is associated with having chalk all over your hands.&#13;
thrift) to the group one at a time.                       Another very important feature of schools is the fact&#13;
                                                          that children do not want to lose one minute of play&#13;
! After each concept ask the women to discuss how         with their friends. These aspects need to be kept in&#13;
they feel about that concept and its importance to them.  mind when researching kids.&#13;
&#13;
! Wheneachconcepthasbeendiscussed,presenteach&#13;
one on a separate piece of paper and ask the women to     Tips:&#13;
rank them in order of:                                    1. Segmentation: Think like a Child. Children have&#13;
                                                          their own agendas that are important to them. While&#13;
        ! Importance                                      the onset of puberty for a 12-year-old, adolescent girl&#13;
        ! Relevance                                       may be a motivation towards hygiene, a six-year-old boy's&#13;
        ! Interest                                        playful nature may need a different appeal. If segmentation&#13;
        ! Disgust                                         of different age groups is not appropriately done,&#13;
                                                          promotion is unlikely to be effective.&#13;
! Ask them to explain their reasons for each ranking.&#13;
                                                          2. Be creative. The conventional methods of focus&#13;
! Finallyaskthemwhichconceptaffectsthemthemost            groups and questionnaires may never find the truth. For&#13;
and which concept they think would be most useful in      children under the age of 10, interviews should if possible&#13;
trying to persuade someone to adopt a new habit such      be based on observation and play. Research methods that&#13;
as handwashing with soap before `Name a Juncture.'        include stimuli (video clips, drawing, photography, local&#13;
6. Communication Channels                                 games) generate more insight. Knowing all the local songs&#13;
! Ask women what their main sources of information        and games that are in fashion is very helpful.&#13;
are for:                                                  3. Children evolve in groups. Children love being in&#13;
        ! Local                                           groups and do not like time away from their playmates.&#13;
                                                          Research methods that include play groups and friendship&#13;
        ! National                                        pairs (interviewing two friends at the same time) can&#13;
        ! International news                              facilitate finding useful insights. Questions can be&#13;
                                                          redirected so that the children talk to each other.&#13;
        ! Health issues&#13;
                                                          4. Separate adults and children. In schools there are&#13;
! How often do they have contact with each of             risk practices carried out by adults (teachers and head&#13;
these channels?                                           teachers) that children know and may be scared to report&#13;
&#13;
! Which of these channels do they like the most? Why?     during research carried out in the school settings (for&#13;
                                                          example, teachers may systematically take the soap&#13;
! Which of these channels are most credible/do they       home). Different research methods will be needed to&#13;
believe or trust the most?                                gather insights from different groups. The school&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     The Handwashing Handbook      67&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
watchman in certain contexts is highly respected and is        Terms of Reference 1: Consumer Research&#13;
an important figure amongst children.                          1. Background&#13;
                                                               Diarrhea kills about two million children every year.&#13;
5. Children can be the lead researchers. Children              Human excreta is the source of most diarrheal pathogens&#13;
can play a role as the senior researchers carrying out the     and probably the most important moments at which hands&#13;
research on their peer groups. They are likely to              should be washed with soap are after contact with human&#13;
distinguish the differences between the truth and fantasy.     excreta and before handling food. A recent review of all&#13;
The spirit of competition often motivates children to          the available evidence suggests that handwashing with&#13;
express themselves. Organizing a competition to get            soap could reduce diarrhea incidence by 42-46 percent&#13;
children to express their frustrations about the poor          and save at least one million lives worldwide.&#13;
hygiene in their schools and then identify some of the&#13;
key features that keep reappearing. Try asking children        The World Bank and the Water and Sanitation&#13;
the same thing in different ways in order to find the          Program (WSP), the London School of Hygiene &amp;&#13;
truth; for example, ask them to draw, write, come up           Tropical Medicine (LSHTM), the Academy for&#13;
with words, and create comics and collages.                    Educational Development, and the private sector, in&#13;
                                                               collaboration with USAID, UNICEF, and the Bank-&#13;
6. Start with the head teacher. The head teacher               Netherlands Water Partnership are implementing a&#13;
sets the tone for his or her school and decides if hygiene     global initiative aimed at promoting the use of&#13;
is going to be an important subject. Interviewing the head     handwashing with soap in developing countries.&#13;
teacher and then providing him or her with the study           Partnerships were established in two pilot locations in&#13;
report will ensure that you have the educational               2001: Ghana and Kerala, India. During FY03, the&#13;
authorities' blessing.                                         initiative will expand in at least two additional countries.&#13;
7. Identify `Leaders of the Pack.' Leaders of the pack         In [country], the [country lead agency], the Water and&#13;
or opinion leaders are key in school settings. Children&#13;
model themselves after a few leaders in the school. To         Sanitation Program (WSP), and the World Bank in&#13;
&#13;
know what is cool, what is in, and how best to address         collaboration with other public and private partners,&#13;
&#13;
the other kids, identifying these opinion leaders is crucial.  proposes to develop a Public-Private Partnership&#13;
&#13;
Teachers may know who they are. Consider training              Handwashing Initiative (PPPHW) with the overall&#13;
&#13;
identified leaders to run your focus groups.                   objective of improving the health of populations at risk&#13;
                                                               of diarrhea through a public-private partnership promoting&#13;
                                                               handwashing with soap.&#13;
Things to avoid:&#13;
1. Taking up recess time with questionnaires.                  Note: this document concerns formative research only.&#13;
Children love their recess time. If you take it, their         Separate monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;E) studies will&#13;
answers will not be much use, as kids will rush though so      be executed for the purposes of documenting the impact&#13;
as to get out and meet their friends. If you plan to carry     of the program.&#13;
out research during that time, make sure it is a group&#13;
activity and that the children enjoy it.                       2. Rationale for handwashing in [country]&#13;
                                                               The rationale for proposing such an initiative in the&#13;
2. Making children feel younger than they are. If              country is:&#13;
there is one thing that children dislike, it is being made&#13;
to feel younger than they are. Children hate to be             Diarrheal diseases are one of the most important causes&#13;
&#13;
babied. Knowing what is acceptable to each age group           of morbidity and morbidity in [country] in children under&#13;
&#13;
is crucial.                                                    five years old (source).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3. Breaking the confidence vow. Researching children           Reliable data on handwashing with soap after using a toilet&#13;
&#13;
is no different from adults in respect to keeping              or after cleaning up a child are [not available] in [country].&#13;
&#13;
information in confidence. Children expect it.                 However,...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4. Taking what children say for granted. The key               Informal discussions with community women and men&#13;
&#13;
to research with children is to investigate what they would    revealed that...&#13;
&#13;
not say. Children have a clear idea of what they think a       It is now recognized that handwashing is a much more cost-&#13;
researcher wants to hear.                                      effective means of lowering diarrheal incidence than the more&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
68    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
costly infrastructure building programs (that is, water and       A methodology for formative research techniques is explained&#13;
sanitation). Nevertheless, hygiene promotion initiatives in       in the booklets `Happy, Healthy and Hygienic' (UNICEF/&#13;
the country have in the past focused on the provision of          LSHTM 1998).&#13;
water and sanitation facilities, good storage methods, and&#13;
water treatment but not on handwashing. Little is therefore       5. Responsibilities of the contracted agency&#13;
known about the availability, affordability, and desirability of  The agency will be responsible for the following:&#13;
soap, especially for use after contact with excreta in rural      Detailed study design in collaboration with [lead agency]&#13;
and semi-urban areas. There is a need to make a connection        (that is, the client) and their technical advisors.&#13;
between hygiene promotion/provision of water and sanitation&#13;
facilities on one hand and the production and distribution of     Set up and manage the study.&#13;
affordable soap on the other. Industry stands to gain by&#13;
selling more soap through an expansion of their market into       Logistics arrangements, that is, travel, accommodation,&#13;
&#13;
more households and by better market penetration towards          allowances, communications, and stationery.&#13;
&#13;
poorer households. Public agencies stand to gain by involving     Quality Assurance.&#13;
soap manufacturers in their programs aimed at improving&#13;
the quality of life by reducing morbidity related to improper     Analysis of the results.&#13;
hygiene practices. [to update/drop as required]&#13;
                                                                  Production of a final report in 10 copies&#13;
3. Objectives of the assignment&#13;
This formative research will enable the partners to               It is the responsibility of the agency to recruit, train, and&#13;
&#13;
design an appropriate handwashing campaign.                       supervise a suitable team of field workers.&#13;
&#13;
Therefore, the main objective of this research is to              The Global Partnership will provide technical support to&#13;
develop the insights needed to design an effective                the agency at key stages of the assignment, which may&#13;
communication program to promote handwashing                      include: the appraisal of technical submissions; review of&#13;
with soap.                                                        proposed detailed study designs and guidance from prior&#13;
                                                                  experience; assistance with the training of field workers&#13;
The specific objectives of the assignment are:                    during piloting of instruments, fine tuning and finalizing of&#13;
                                                                  proposal;monitoringofthequalitycontrolsystemtoevaluate&#13;
to record current handwashing practices and their                 progressandrefocusifnecessary;reviewoffirstdraftreport&#13;
context;                                                          and recommendations for production of the final report.&#13;
&#13;
to understand what drives and facilitates handwashing in          6. Qualifications and selection of the contracted&#13;
communities;                                                      agency&#13;
                                                                  The contracted agency will be a professional consumer&#13;
to identify target audiences; and                                 or market research organization with track record of at&#13;
                                                                  least five years of consumer studies in [country and/or&#13;
to document current channels of communication.                    region].The team will need to demonstrate their&#13;
                                                                  members' experience both in quantitative and qualitative&#13;
4. Methods                                                        research techniques. Commercial/industry sector&#13;
The study requires the employment of both                         experience is essential.&#13;
quantitative and qualitative research techniques and&#13;
may include focus group discussions, behavior trials,             The qualifications of the proposed study team will make up&#13;
structured interviews, and structured observations for            a part of the submission and should be as follows:&#13;
data collection (as set out in the table in section B of          One statistician and one social scientist or anthropologist&#13;
the annex), as well as the compilation of available               with:&#13;
routine data.&#13;
                                                                  Track record on qualitative and quantitative surveys;&#13;
Detailed study designs will be proposed by the contracted&#13;
agency and finalized in collaboration with the technical          Familiarity with industry;&#13;
advisor (that is, the lead agency's consultant recruited for      Experience in cleaning products; and&#13;
the program) and with the technical support of&#13;
the partnership.                                                  Knowledge of the local language.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               The Handwashing Handbook      69&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Field workers should:                                        summary document suitable for posting on websites.&#13;
&#13;
have at least one year of experience of field work;          A presentation of results at stakeholder workshop.&#13;
&#13;
be female; and                                               The main report will include the following chapters:&#13;
&#13;
be fluent in local languages (as appropriate).               I. Approach&#13;
&#13;
The firm will provide a detailed plan for the management     II. Methods&#13;
and quality assurance of the study and justify the&#13;
proposed staffing.                                           III. Implementation schedule&#13;
&#13;
7. Final products                                            IV. Results set out using the framework of table in&#13;
The final products include:                                  section A of the annex&#13;
&#13;
Cleaned and fully referenced electronic data sets in an      V. Conclusion and recommendations&#13;
agreed format with copies of the original data               The report will contain graphics when needed.&#13;
collection forms.                                            Annexes will contain all relevant background&#13;
Full transcripts of all in-depth interviews and focus group  information for the study that is not necessary in the&#13;
discussions in an electronic format.                         body of the report.&#13;
&#13;
A 50-page document in 10 copies with detailed findings.      8. Time schedule&#13;
                                                             It is expected that the work will last about 13 weeks&#13;
An eight-page illustrated summary document suitable for      from appointment to final report. The schedule for each&#13;
general consumption and an electronic version of the         phase is set out in the table below:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Activity                                                   When&#13;
&#13;
  Set up and training                                        Week 1&#13;
&#13;
  Inception report with refined methodology&#13;
  and pretested materials                                    Week 2&#13;
&#13;
  Field survey                                               Week 3 to 10&#13;
&#13;
  Analysis                                                   Week 10&#13;
&#13;
  Draft report and stakeholder workshop                      Week 11&#13;
&#13;
  Final report                                               Week 14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
70    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section A: Framework of variables and data&#13;
collection techniques&#13;
&#13;
The following sets out the framework for the formative&#13;
research on handwashing and is intended as guidance for&#13;
the agency in designing and conducting the research.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Issues                                         Data Source/Method            Notes&#13;
&#13;
  1. What are current handwashing practices?&#13;
&#13;
  1.1 What are the handwashing practices of      Quantitative representative   Note 1: Refer to M&amp;E&#13;
  child caregivers (at key junctures)?           sample on handwashing         framework.&#13;
  1.2 What are handwashing practices of          practices using               Note 2: The specific occasions&#13;
  other family members (at key junctures)?       Structured Observation        for handwashing to be recorded&#13;
  1.3 What soap (laundry versus beauty soap)                                   depend on the exact objectives&#13;
  or other agent is being used?                                                of the handwashing program.&#13;
  1.4 What is the source of water?                                             Note 3: Structured observation&#13;
  1.5 What is the immediate placing of soap?                                   needs to be designed to capture&#13;
                                                                               all handwashing events at key&#13;
  1.6 How do people dry their hands after                                      junctures.&#13;
  washing?&#13;
&#13;
  2. What drives and facilitates handwashing?&#13;
&#13;
  2.1 Drivers                                    Behavior trials               Note 4: A driver is a psycho-social&#13;
  What motivate domestic hygiene, bathing                                      motivator or inhibitor for&#13;
  and handwashing with soap?                     In-depth interviews including&#13;
                                                 with school kids (about 12    hygiene behaviors and can be&#13;
  After what is handwashing practiced? ­         years old)                    either positive or negative.&#13;
  With/without soap?&#13;
                                                 Focus group discussions       Note 5: When noting drivers for&#13;
  Specific cues and occasions for people to      (FGDs)                        hygiene behaviors it is necessary&#13;
  wash their hands.                                                            to note motivators for ­ general&#13;
  Reasons for not using soap at key                                            hygiene, bathing, handwashing&#13;
  handwashing junctures? that is, psycho-                                      (without soap) and handwashing&#13;
  social inhibitors to soap use ­ cost, smell,                                 with soap separately, paying&#13;
  drying of skin...                                                            particular attention to&#13;
  How and when was handwashing learnt?                                         handwashing with soap.&#13;
  Who taught it?                                                               Note 6: Probe meaning of `clean'&#13;
  What are the attributes of a good                                            and `dirty' ­ are these defined&#13;
  handwashing soap?                                                            visually, by feel, smell, or&#13;
  Brand ranking of both soaps and their                                        concepts of moral purity?&#13;
  attributes for handwashing (ask why ranked                                   The environment refers to the&#13;
  like this) and of handwashing practices.                                     external conditions that facilitate&#13;
  Ranking of hypothesized drivers/concepts                                     or hinder handwashing with&#13;
  (status, nurture, disgust, aesthetics,                                       soap. See the annexed note on&#13;
  attractiveness).                                                             Handwashing Motivation&#13;
  Images/beliefs concerning cleanliness/                                       (Annex 3).&#13;
  dirtiness, healthy/non-healthy person,                                       Training on handwashing&#13;
  hygienic/non-hygienic...                                                     motivation and concept&#13;
  Rules for soap use within the household.                                     ranking needed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   The Handwashing Handbook      71&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  2.2 Environment                                Household survey&#13;
  Water supply: Where, Type, Access (cost,       Structured observations&#13;
  distance, who), Storage.                       In-depth interviews&#13;
  Sanitation facilities: Where, Type and         FGDs&#13;
  Access (including for children), Presence of&#13;
  fecal material in the yard?&#13;
  Handwashing facilities: What is it? (probe)&#13;
  Where is it?/availability ­ Distance from&#13;
  toilet, Storage place of soap, State, Access.&#13;
&#13;
  3. Who are the target audiences?&#13;
&#13;
  3.1 Who buys the soap?                         FGDs&#13;
  3.2 Who decides about soap buying?             In-depth interviews&#13;
  3.3 Who influences the buyers and              Household survey&#13;
  decision makers?&#13;
&#13;
  4. How do target audiences communicate?&#13;
  Exposure and reach of all channels of&#13;
  communication including modern and&#13;
  traditional.&#13;
&#13;
  4.1 Time spent and media consumption           Household survey          Note 7: Allow costs of&#13;
  moments (quantitative data).                   FGDs/In-depth interviews  consulting commercial databases.&#13;
                                                 (IDIs)&#13;
                                                 Commercially available&#13;
                                                 media data&#13;
&#13;
  4.2 Reach of all traditional channels of       Households surveys        Note 8. Traditional channels may&#13;
  information?                                   FGDs/IDIs                 include churches, social&#13;
&#13;
  4.3 Reach of government channels of                                      organizations, women's groups,&#13;
&#13;
  communication?                                                           markets, local events, etc.&#13;
                                                                           Government channels include&#13;
  4.4 What programs do they like and why?                                  contact with health services&#13;
  What do they remember? (qualitative data)                                (e.g., vaccination coverage,&#13;
  4.5 Which adverts do they know and like,                                 maternity and post-natal care),&#13;
  and why?                                                                 schools, agricultural extension,&#13;
  4.6 Which communication channels do they                                 local authorities, etc.&#13;
  find the most credible?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
72   The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section B: Definitions of Research Tools                       Disgust: An instinct to avoid and remove anything&#13;
                                                               disgusting, which includes sensory cues (olfactory,&#13;
Household Survey: Designed for a representative                tactile, visual: such as the sight of stains, feeling of&#13;
sample of mothers/care givers and children under five.         stickiness on hands, bad smells, or a feeling of&#13;
In-depth Interview: Qualitative one-to-one interview           contamination, both actual or imagined). It is important&#13;
with fully recorded transcript using a discussion guide.       to know which of these cues plays the greatest role in&#13;
                                                               the disgust instinct in order to direct handwashing&#13;
Behavior Trials: Volunteers asked to adopt handwashing         promotional messages. There appears to be a strong&#13;
with soap over a two-week period and then interviewed.         correlation between the objects of disgust and the&#13;
                                                               sources of infection and disease faced by our ancestors,&#13;
Structured Observation: Systematic technique for               thus the disgust instinct may be closely linked,&#13;
observing and recording particular practices in order to       according to Curtis (2001) to:&#13;
quantify them directly and monitor the impact of the&#13;
program. It requires careful planning, detailed piloting,      Health: Consumers often explain handwashing as a desire&#13;
training, follow-up and quality control.                       to avoid germs and disease. However, the usefulness of&#13;
                                                               this explanation in behavior change programs is not clear&#13;
Checklist Observation: A list of all behaviors putting         (see note). Often concepts of good health are linked to&#13;
children at risk of diarrhea. The list should note behaviors   the nurture instinct and the desire to protect one's&#13;
(who, what, when, where) observed in the household.            children from disease.&#13;
Results are used to design study instruments.&#13;
                                                               Note that the underlying motivator may be more to&#13;
Focus Group Discussions: Interviews with small                 create an ordered, balanced life that leads to success&#13;
groups of relatively homogeneous people asked to reflect       and well-being, rather than behavior calculated from an&#13;
on the interviewers' questions, provide their own              intellectual understanding of the mechanisms by which&#13;
comments, listen to what the rest of the group has to          particular microbes cause specific diseases. Germs are&#13;
say and react to their observations. It requires a skillful    also thought of as invisible beasties that are disgusting&#13;
facilitator guiding the discussion, cross-checking each        and so need removal.&#13;
participant's comments, and ensuring an even&#13;
participation from all members.                                Negative drivers include laziness, a desire to do something&#13;
                                                               else that conflicts with handwashing, a wish to avoid soap&#13;
Note: All instruments should be translated, back               because of the perfume, beliefs surrounding links between&#13;
translated, piloted, and tested.                               sensory cues, and the presence of `germs' and disease-&#13;
Reference: `Happy, Healthy and Hygienic' (UNICEF/LSHTM         carrying agents.&#13;
1998).                                                         Habits are behavioral routines that are laid down often&#13;
Section C: Note on Handwashing Motivation                      early in life and are semi-automatic. The external&#13;
                                                               environment can facilitate or hinder handwashing. For&#13;
Previous research suggests that handwashing behavior is        example, where soap and water are readily available,&#13;
motivated by psychological drivers, habits, and the            handwashing with soap is more likely, whereas if the toilet&#13;
environment (Curtis 2001). Drives can be both positive         is situated far from the house and handwashing facilities,&#13;
and negative.                                                  handwashing after the toilet may be less likely.&#13;
&#13;
Positive drivers usually include:                              1. Curtis, V.A., S. Cairncross, and R. Yonli. 2000.&#13;
Nurture: The desire to care for children. This is often        Domestic hygiene and diarrhea, pinpointing the problem.&#13;
related to health, as outlined below.                          Tropical Medicine and International Health 5(1): 22-32.&#13;
Status: A wish to appear clean for the sake of social         2. Curtis, V. 200l. Hygiene: how myths monsters and&#13;
status and dignity.                                           mothers-in-law can promote behavior change. Journal of&#13;
Aesthetics: A desire to look and smell good, to be             Infection 43: 75-79.&#13;
attractive to others, and please oneself.                      3. Curtis, V., and A. Biran. 2001. Dirt, disgust and&#13;
(Note: These last two drivers in particular can be             disease-Is hygiene in our genes? Perspectives in Biology &amp;&#13;
considered as linked.)                                         Medicine v.1: 17-31.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          The Handwashing Handbook      73&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4. Luby, S.P., M. Agboatwalla, J. Painter et al. 2004.          of soap, especially for use after contact with excreta, in&#13;
Effect of intensive handwashing promotion on childhood          rural and semi-urban areas. There is a need to make a&#13;
diarrhea in high-risk communities in Pakistan, a                connection between hygiene education/provision of water&#13;
randomized controlled trial. Journal of the American Medical    and sanitation facilities on one hand and the production&#13;
Association 291(21): 2547-54.                                   and distribution of affordable soap on the other. Industry&#13;
                                                                stands to gain by selling more soap through an expansion&#13;
Terms of Reference 2:                                           of their market into more households and by better&#13;
Handwashing Coordinator                                         market penetration towards poorer households. Public&#13;
Public-Private Partnership Handwashing                          agencies stand to gain by involving soap manufacturers in&#13;
Coordinator in Peru                                             their programs aimed at improving the quality of life by&#13;
                                                                reducing morbidity related to improper hygiene practices.&#13;
Terms of Reference&#13;
                                                                2. Objectives of the Consultancy&#13;
1. Background&#13;
                                                                To assist DIGESA, WSP, and the partners in establishing&#13;
The Government of Peru, with support from the Water             an effective public-private partnership for a successful&#13;
and Sanitation Program (WSP) and others, is initiating a        handwashing initiative. The coordinator will be expected&#13;
new intervention to promote handwashing with soap               to co-ordinate all activities of the partnership and manage&#13;
under a public-private partnership (PPP) with the               the planning and implementation of agreed activities&#13;
objective of reducing diarrhea morbidity among children         during the initial phase of the process. The end result of&#13;
below age five. A documented PPP experience in Central          this first phase is the submission of an approved business&#13;
America has demonstrated the positive impact on                 plan and communications strategy.&#13;
handwashing behavior and on the incidence of diarrhea.&#13;
The World Bank, WSP, UNICEF, and USAID at the global            3. Scope of Services&#13;
level have formed with the three major soap producers           The consultant will perform the following services:&#13;
a Global Initiative for PPP in Handwashing. Two pilots in&#13;
Kerala, India, and Ghana are implementing a local PPP.          ! Promote effective partnership relations between the&#13;
Peru is another candidate for expanding this PPP                private, public, NGOs, and external agencies on the&#13;
handwashing initiative. A local coordinator for this new,       handwashing initiative, with a special focus on establishing&#13;
promising activity is needed.                                   credibility and mobilizing technical input from the&#13;
                                                                private sector.&#13;
Rationale for a Handwashing Initiative:&#13;
                                                                ! Liaise with the global team to obtain information and&#13;
! Diarrheal diseases kill two to three million children         expertise of the global and other country initiatives.&#13;
globally every year, are the third most important cause&#13;
of morbidity and morbidity in Peru and account for              ! Conduct a background study on existing hygiene&#13;
35 percent morbidity in children under five years old.          studies and reports on hygiene promotion (particularly&#13;
                                                                handwashing practices) programs in Peru.&#13;
! Most diarrheal diseases are caused by fecal-oral&#13;
contamination.                                                  ! Collectadditionalinformationonthemarketsituation,&#13;
                                                                with particular reference to the poorer segments of&#13;
! Diarrhea can be prevented by stopping excreta from            the population.&#13;
reaching the environment through proper sanitation and&#13;
handwashing.                                                    ! Identify potential research firms and co-ordinate the&#13;
                                                                planning, consultant recruitment, and implementation of&#13;
! Handwashing with soap alone could reduce reported             the consumer study.&#13;
cases of diarrhea by 35 percent.&#13;
                                                                ! Complement the situation analysis by integrating&#13;
Reliable data on handwashing with soap after using a toilet     the results of the three studies (background, market,&#13;
or after cleaning up a child is not available in Peru. Hygiene  and business).&#13;
promotion initiatives have focused on the provision of&#13;
water and sanitation facilities, good storage methods and       ! Develop a draft business plan and communications&#13;
water treatment but not on handwashing, so little is            strategy as an iterative process, seeking input from&#13;
known about the availability, affordability, and desirability   the partners.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
74    The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
! Raise funds to cover activities of the business plan.    to the relevant network of contacts and provide&#13;
                                                           continuous backstopping to strengthen inter-agency&#13;
! Solicit comments and submit final approved plan          relationship building.&#13;
and budget.&#13;
                                                           7. Reporting&#13;
4. Approach&#13;
                                                           The consultant shall report to the WSP Country Program&#13;
The consultant will work closely with key WSP and          Coordinator and work closely with the Director of&#13;
DIGESA staff and other partners to build consensus on      DIGESA and his staff. All reports should be copied to&#13;
the direction and scope of the PPPH Initiative through     DIGESA. The consultant will submit brief monthly&#13;
participatory arrangements. Initially the consultant will  progress reports and the following month's workplan.&#13;
build trust with the stakeholders by embarking on one&#13;
to one contacts. Appropriate strategies have to be         8. Level of Effort and Duration of Assignment&#13;
adopted to generate and sustain the interests of all&#13;
stakeholders in the PPH Initiative.                        The consultant shall initially be engaged for six months&#13;
                                                           of work over a 10-month to completed the first phase of&#13;
5. Output                                                  the PPP process. The assignment could be extended to&#13;
                                                           the next phase of work based on performance and&#13;
The consultant is expected to:                             funding availability.&#13;
! Deliver a situation report on the soap market and        9. Qualification&#13;
hygiene promotion programs targed to the poor,&#13;
conducted by private, NGO, and public sectors in Peru;     The consultant shall have a solid experience working in&#13;
                                                           the private sector in the area of marketing and /or business&#13;
! Organize meetings and coordinate PPPH Steering           developmentpreferablywithfast-movingconsumergoods.&#13;
Committee (formation will be the responsibility of WSP     The consultant should have proven expertise in developing&#13;
and DIGESA);                                               marketing plans and communication strategies aimed at&#13;
&#13;
! Provide oversight to ensure the quality of the           behavioral change. Familiarity in dealing with market&#13;
&#13;
consumer study;                                            research and communication agencies is a must.&#13;
                                                           Additionally, the consultant should have excellent inter-&#13;
! Deliver a draft business plan; and                       personal skills and ability to work with all partners in order&#13;
                                                           to act as an effective catalyst. It would be extremely&#13;
! Deliver a final business plan that considers partner     advantageousfortheconsultanttobeconversantinEnglish.&#13;
comments and commitments.&#13;
                                                           10. Selection process&#13;
6. Client Input&#13;
                                                           Short-listed consultants who meet the qualifications&#13;
WSP will provide the consultant with office space and      criteria will be invited to an interview with WSP and&#13;
the necessary communication tools to perform the job.      DIGESA staff. The final selection will be based on the&#13;
The consultant is expected to provide their own            consultant's qualifications, the proposed approach to the&#13;
computer. WSP and DIGESA will introduce the consultant     work, and the financial proposal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        The Handwashing Handbook      75&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
&#13;
    BASICS             Basic Support for Child Survival Project&#13;
    CI                 Consumer interviews&#13;
    DALY               Disability Adjusted Life Year&#13;
    DANIDA             Danish International Development Agency&#13;
    DCC                Direct consumer contact&#13;
    DFID               United Kingdom Department for International Development&#13;
    DHS                Demographic and Health Surveys&#13;
    EHP                Environmental Health Project&#13;
    FGD                Focus group discussion&#13;
    IRR                Internal rate of return&#13;
    ISTMA              Indian Soap and Toiletries Manufacturers' Association&#13;
    LSHTM              London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine&#13;
    MDG                Millennium Development Goals&#13;
    M&amp;E                Monitoring and evaluation&#13;
    NGO                Non-governmental organizations&#13;
    NPV                Net present value&#13;
    PPP                Public-private partnership&#13;
    PPPHW              Public-Private Partnership Handwashing Initiative&#13;
    PR                 Public relations&#13;
    SDC                 Swiss Development Cooperation&#13;
    SO                 Structured observations&#13;
    TOR                Terms of reference&#13;
    UNICEF             United Nations Children's Fund&#13;
    UNICEF/WES         United Nations Children's Fund/Water and Environmental Sanitation&#13;
    USAID              United States Agency for International Development&#13;
    WES                Water, environment and sanitation&#13;
    WSP                Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
    WSSCC              Water Supply &amp; Sanitation Collaborative Council&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
76 The Handwashing Handbook&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
© The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433, USA&#13;
www.worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions in this paper are entirely those of the author(s) and should not&#13;
be attributed in any manner to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to members of its Board of&#13;
Executive Directors or the countries they represent. The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy of the&#13;
data included in this document and accepts no responsibility for any consequences of their use.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington DC, 20433&#13;
USA&#13;
Ph: +1 202 473-1000&#13;
email: feedback@worldbank.org&#13;
www.worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Task Team Leaders&#13;
Parameswaran Iyer, Jennifer Sara&#13;
&#13;
Chief Contributors&#13;
Valerie Curtis, Beth Scott, Jason Cardosi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Global Public Private Partnership for Handwashing&#13;
www.globalhandwashing.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Production&#13;
Vandana Mehra&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Created by Write Media and printed at&#13;
PS Press Services Pvt. Ltd.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5794173">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/01/5794173/handwashing-handbook-guide-developing-hygiene-promotion-program-increase-handwashing-soap
        </url>
        <availablein>French,Spanish,Swahili,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="000090341_20060929090241" node_id="5794173"/>
            <available_in lang="Spanish" entityid="000090341_20061002134135" node_id="5794173"/>
            <available_in lang="Swahili" entityid="000333038_20080320065956" node_id="5794173"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/01/5794173/handwashing-handbook-guide-developing-hygiene-promotion-program-increase-handwashing-soap</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/01/5794173/handwashing-handbook-guide-developing-hygiene-promotion-program-increase-handwashing-soap</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/05/11/000090341_20050511141605/Rendered/INDEX/323020Handwashing1handbook02005.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/05/11/000090341_20050511141605/Rendered/PDF/323020Handwashing1handbook02005.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-05-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2005-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The handwashing handbook: a guide for
            developing a hygiene promotion program to increase
            handwashing with soap
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This handbook grows out of the
            experience of the Global Public-Private Partnership for
            Handwashing with Soap (PPPHW) and its predecessor, the
            Central American Handwashing for Diarrheal Disease
            Prevention Program. These efforts demonstrated that mass
            programs with public and private sector involvement can be
            successful in promoting handwashing and reducing disease.
            With core support from the Bank Netherlands Water
            Partnership, the PPPHW has brought together global public
            and private agencies to consolidate approaches while
            initiating large-scale handwashing promotion in Ghana, Peru,
            Senegal, and Nepal. While much has been learned about
            handwashing promotion in recent years, especially in the
            areas of research and program design, countries are still
            experimenting with, and optimizing approaches to
            implementation. It is important to lay out what is known so
            that others can begin designing programs and contributing to
            a global body of knowledge and experience in the fight
            against child mortality. This handbook is intended for staff
            in government and development organizations charged with
            carrying out handwashing programs. Decision-makers in
            Ministries and funding agencies will also find assistance in
            designing policies and programs to improve public health.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The handwashing handbook: a guide for
            developing a hygiene promotion program to increase
            handwashing with soap
        </docna>
        <display_title>The handwashing handbook: a guide
            for developing a hygiene promotion program to increase
            handwashing with soap</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2005/01/5794173/handwashing-handbook-guide-developing-hygiene-promotion-program-increase-handwashing-soap</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Early Child and Children's Health,Water and Industry,Water and Human Health,Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20050511141605</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            advertising, aged, communities, conveying,
            diarrheal diseases, Education, Environmental Health,
            equipment, families, fathers, HANDWASHING, Health, health
            education, health promotion, hygiene, hygiene behavior,
            hygiene education, hygiene practices, hygiene promotion,
            infectious diseases, international organizations,
            intervention, laundry, Malaria, Marketing, mass media,
            Measles, Media, morbidity, Mortality, Mothers, new
            technologies, NGOs, Nutrition, Partnership, Private Sector,
            public health, public sector, recycled, resource allocation,
            safe water, sanitation, school health, Schools, vaccination,
            water, water supply, workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <repnb>32302</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Le manuel de l'initiative de lavage
            des mains: guide de preparation d'un programme de
            promotion du lavage des mains au savon
            Manual del lavado de manos: guia para
            desarrollar un programa de promocion de la higiene destinado
            a extender la practica del lavado de manos con jabon
            Kijitabu cha jinsi ya kunawa mikono :
            mwongozo wa kuandaa programu ya kuhamasisha usafi ili
            kuongeza mwamko wa watu kuhusu unawaji mikono kwa sabuni
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vaccines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Handwashing Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Immunizations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>