<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                        Field note                                                     31239&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    UNDP­                Improving User Participation to increase Project Effectiveness&#13;
                    World Bank&#13;
                    Water and           Community Action Planning&#13;
                    Sanitation&#13;
                    Program              in an Adaptive Project&#13;
                    South Asia&#13;
                    Region               NWFP Community Infrastructure Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        LEARNING FROM&#13;
        IMPLEMENTATION                   The Community Infrastructure Project (CIP) is an innovative project. It attempts&#13;
                                         to be responsive to communities' expressed desire to improve their lives through&#13;
This Field Note is about the lessons     access to better infrastructure and to test the recipient's willingness to contribute&#13;
learned, both successes and              substantially to the costs of providing and&#13;
challenges, in the Community             maintaining the facilities chosen. An&#13;
Infrastructure Project (CIP), currently  important milestone in the community&#13;
being implemented in 55 rural and        mobilization process is the preparation of&#13;
urban communities in the Northwest       the Community Action Plan (CAP).&#13;
Frontier Province of Pakistan. This&#13;
note also provides insights into how     The quality of social mobilization and&#13;
the community action planning (CAP)      community involvement is essential for the&#13;
process was diagnosed and improved       success of community based projects.&#13;
through the use of Process Monitoring.   Facilities provided must be based on&#13;
                                         informed choice, represent community&#13;
                                         demand and capacity to operate and&#13;
   NWFP ­ CIP PAKISTAN                   maintain completed facilities, and their&#13;
                                         collective willingness to contribute financially.&#13;
&#13;
 Started: 1995                           How do we know if the so-called community planning process in projects does&#13;
 Government Agency:                      this? Project management, being isolated from actual field realities, is often&#13;
                                         unable to directly assess the quality and impact of social mobilization. There&#13;
 Local Government, Elections and         is a tendency for management to focus on the completion of pre-defined "steps"&#13;
 Rural Development Department            in the mobilization process and the achievement of physical targets and&#13;
 (LGE&amp;RD)                                deadlines.&#13;
 Supported By:&#13;
                                         There is therefore a need for a way to assess the quality and results from the&#13;
 GoNWFP, IDA (loan), SDC (grant),        community mobilization process in a way which allows project management&#13;
 UNICEF (grant)                          to make timely and appropriate decisions to improve or expand the process.&#13;
 Main Activities: (loan funded)          Process Monitoring is one such tool.&#13;
&#13;
 Infrastructure upgrading for 55 rural&#13;
 and urban low income communities&#13;
 of over 3,000 population&#13;
&#13;
 Infrastructure Provided:&#13;
&#13;
 Water supply, sanitation/drainage,&#13;
 access roads, solid waste&#13;
 management, community facilities&#13;
&#13;
 Population to be Served : 421,000&#13;
&#13;
 Community Contributes:&#13;
&#13;
 20% of cost of community works&#13;
&#13;
 Other activities (grant funded):&#13;
&#13;
 Community Development,&#13;
 Mobilization, Health and Hygiene,&#13;
 Women and Children, Process&#13;
 Monitoring&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Process Monitoring (PM) is a way to collect relevant            and operation of the infrastructure to be provided.&#13;
qualitative and quantitative information about the effec-       During the technical survey work in the community, women&#13;
tiveness of key project processes as seen by the actual         felt excluded from decisions on the location, type, design&#13;
participants in the process. This often means community         and operation of the infrastructure to be provided.&#13;
members and representatives and project field workers,          Also, block representatives, who were important in collecting&#13;
actors whose voices are otherwise not often heard by project    data about the community and its preferences, were not&#13;
management. PM helps bridge the gap between project             chosen "democratically", but were directly appointed by&#13;
management's perspective and realities on the ground.           influential persons, known as a "contact group". They were&#13;
                                                                not adequately prepared for their role in data collection&#13;
PM Looks at Community Action                                    and informing the community about the project, and were&#13;
&#13;
Planning                                                        not motivated or able to spend the time necessary to do&#13;
                                                                effective community mobilization.&#13;
&#13;
The high drop-out rate of communities identified for            Information Overload&#13;
participating in the Project was identified as an important&#13;
issue by the Project. The PM Team was asked to explore&#13;
possible reasons for this and report to project management.     Initially, the CAP was a laborious and time consuming&#13;
As a critical project process, and as a main factor in ensuring process, focusing on data collection, and often involving&#13;
the community's readiness for participating in the project,     poorly trained community members&#13;
community mobilization was also examined through PM.            who were either unwilling or unable&#13;
The preparation of the CAP, an important milestone in the       to carry out their tasks effectively.&#13;
community mobilization process, was assessed. Field visits,&#13;
participant observation, structured discussions and meetings    It was also found that the project's&#13;
with project management were used to gather information         own social organizers were&#13;
about the entire CAP process. The CAP is a formal               overloaded with data collection and&#13;
document containing an agreement between the community          processing tasks, which occupied&#13;
and the Project.                                                up to three-fourths of their time and&#13;
                                                                left little time for actual work in the&#13;
                                                                community.&#13;
&#13;
  Issues Identified                                             Data collection for the Community&#13;
                                                                Self-Survey (CSS) was done through&#13;
  Several important issues were identified through PM&#13;
                                                                structured interviews with the heads of all households in&#13;
  through Participants Observation. Among the most&#13;
                                                                the community. Besides providing information from a mostly&#13;
  important are:&#13;
                                                                male group, this process resulted in large quantities of&#13;
                                                                data which were processed up to three times; at household&#13;
                                                                level, block level and at the project office. This cumbersome&#13;
Lack of Representativeness                                      task occupied the majority of the Social Organizer's time.&#13;
&#13;
The community's needs were identified using structured          The PM Team suggested rationalizing data collection and&#13;
questionnaires administered to                                  processing through using the Project's computerized MIS&#13;
heads of all households (usually                                to store and retrieve household data.&#13;
males) in the community. This&#13;
process to a large extent excluded                              In addition, it was found that much of the information&#13;
women (representing half of the                                 collected was not needed at this stage of the Project, and&#13;
intended beneficiaries).                                        could either be omitted or deferred to a later stage in the&#13;
                                                                project. This would release the valuable time of field staff&#13;
In addition, the women's committee                              which could be better used on working directly with informing&#13;
was formed as part of the men's                                 and mobilizing communities.&#13;
community based organization,&#13;
which conflicted with the socio-                                Thus, an unrepresentative community consultation process,&#13;
cultural norms prevailing in the                                often conducted by overloaded or misallocated project staff&#13;
Northwest Frontier Province. The                                or poorly trained community members, and which did not&#13;
Project also required female                                    capture the real demand of the community as a whole,&#13;
committee members to have a minimum of a high school            resulted in both a frustrated, demotivated staff and&#13;
education, which effectively excluded all but young girls.      community. This also increased the chances of lack of&#13;
Since young girls have restricted mobility and social status,   ownership at a later stage due to a "mismatch" between&#13;
they were not effective in representing the "voice" of all      true community preferences and those identified by a&#13;
the community's women.                                          community action planning process with serious&#13;
                                                                shortcomings and built-in biases.&#13;
During the technical survey work in the community. Women&#13;
felt excluded from decisions on the location, type, design&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Lack of Coordination between Social&#13;
&amp; Technical Processes&#13;
&#13;
PM also found that the technical survey team only started&#13;
its work after the official signing of the CAP between the&#13;
community and the Project. The technical survey, done by&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  CBO&#13;
external consultants, could take up to one month, and did                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            conducted                                                                                                                                                               format                                                                                                                    BRs&#13;
                                                                                                                            held                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     by&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          &amp;                                                                          formats&#13;
not adequately involve project staff or the community.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             CSS&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                community&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      on                                                                                                                   SOs                                                                              CSR                                                                                           formulated                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       community&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                         the                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  campaign                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 selected&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                community                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     of                                                                               on                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   by&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            by                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               contacted                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              held                                                                                                        elected                                                                  held&#13;
The PM Team saw that project efficiency could be improved                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  held&#13;
                                                                                                                INDICATORS&#13;
                                                                                                                                         with                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  design&#13;
through closer coordination between the technical survey,                                                                                                                                                                                                                        conducted                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             ficials&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                              selected                                                                                                                                        Estimate                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       meeting&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               training                                               awareness                                                                       Agencies                                                                          consolidated                               reviewed                                                                     meeting                                                                          compiled                               meeting                                                     constitution                                              of                     notified                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         approved&#13;
&#13;
the CSS and the CAP process. Information generated by                                                                                        Meeting                                                                  BRs                                                                 Survey                                                                      Cost                             BRs                                                     H&amp;H                                                                            Line                                                                                  Data                                   Data                                                                        Joint                                                                             Data                                  Mass                                                             CBO                                             CBO                          CBO                                    Mass                                                                                                             Preferred                                  CAP                                           CAP&#13;
&#13;
the CSS and the CAP could be made available to the&#13;
technical survey team, who could start working earlier,                                                                                             1.                                                                   2.                                                                     3.                                                                        4.                              1.                                                      2.                                                                              3.                                                                                    4.                                     1.                                                                           2.                                                                               3.                                    1.                                                              2.                                              3.                           4.                                      1.                                                                                                                    2.                                   3.                                            4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
before the signing of the CAP. Likewise, information&#13;
generated through the technical survey could be used in&#13;
the preparation of the CAP. Thus, these previously divergent&#13;
processes could now mutually benefit each other.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Completing the Loop&#13;
&#13;
These important issues were discussed between project&#13;
management and the PM Team through a series of&#13;
discussions and meetings. It was emphasized that&#13;
addressing these issues in a timely and effective manner&#13;
would result in a more efficient use of the Project's resources,&#13;
both time, staff and costs. The relevance and importance&#13;
                                                                 Plan&#13;
of PM in identifying important problems and solutions which                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       material&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              BR&#13;
&#13;
the Project could not otherwise address were beginning to                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           agencies&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            SOs                               with&#13;
&#13;
be realized by project management.                                   Action                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 line&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          construction&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  findings&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                other&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      local                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      Organizer&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          and                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             CAP&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      Demarcation                                                                        BR                                                                                for                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       from                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   (rough)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          Social                                                                             data&#13;
Convincing Project Management                                              Community                                                                             Block                                                                                                                                                        survey                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            by&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       wareness                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              formulate                                             estimate&#13;
                                                                                    in                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         A&#13;
                                                                                                        ACTIVITY                                                      and                                                                                                                                                           and                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           data                                                                           survey                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               to&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         construction                                                                                                                                                                                                  of                                                                                             CBO                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  cost                                                      approval&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     for                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 of                                                                                                                                                                                             CBO                                                    &amp;                                                                                      Plan&#13;
This was perhaps the hardest task of all. At the beginning,                                                                                                                                                                                Representatives&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       Survey                                                               regarding                                                                           (H&amp;H)&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          data                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             of                                                                                                                and                          ork&#13;
project management was not very familiar with participatory                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              review&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        rates                                                 of                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  CBO                                                                                                                                                                                                        W&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   CBO&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                         Orientation                                                                      Block                                                                                                                                                      BRs                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        design&#13;
                                                                                      involved                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        consolidated                                                                             the                                                                                                                                                   Guidelines                                                                      of                                                                                                                                                                                                       on&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      of                                                                                                                                             CBO&#13;
methodologies for working with communities and the role                                                                                                                                                                                                        of&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        to                                                                           Hygiene&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            Cost                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  of                                                                                                                                                                       regulations                                                                                                  of                                                                                   meeting                                                  and&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            &amp;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      &amp;                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         preparation&#13;
of process monitoring in improving project effectiveness.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    prevailing&#13;
                                                                                              Steps                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       raining&#13;
Eventually, though, project management did accept some                                                                                                                              Community                                                                    Selection                                                                   Reconnaissance                     Rough                                            T                                                                           Health                                                                                    Get                                      Consolidation                                                       Review                                                                        Discussing                                            Objectives                                     Rules                                                   Operational                                Election                     Notification                                                 General                                              Options                                                           CAP                  Agreement&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
of the recommendations of the PM Team on ways to reduce&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             1.                                                                           2.                                                                               3.                        4.                                           1.                                                                               2.                                                                                     3.                                                 4.                                                           1.                                                                                2.                                                    1.                                        2.                                                            3.                                      4.                               5.                                                      1.                                                   2.                                                            3.                         4.&#13;
the time taken to complete the CAP and the large amount&#13;
of sometimes unnecessary data collected at the initial&#13;
phases of the project. Decisions were taken to at least test&#13;
more participatory and consultative methods in working&#13;
with communities, and for the first time women were&#13;
addressed directly in the community mobilization process&#13;
through preparing a separate CAP for women.&#13;
&#13;
These changes resulted in an increase in the effectiveness&#13;
of the CAP process, as indicated by improved staff&#13;
performance and better contacts between community and&#13;
Project.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    Survey&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               of&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          Self&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           Formation                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  (3-6&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              Formation&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              Formulation&#13;
                                                                                                    STEP                                                                                                                                                                     (1-3                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               (1-3                                                                                                                                                        (1-2                                                                                                                                                                                                                 (1-2&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    Block                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 (CS                                                                                                                                                                                                    Review                                                                                                                                                                                CBO                                                                                                                                                                                               CAP&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              Community&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Future?&#13;
&#13;
Gradually, a change in the status of PM is noticeable. Project Management has begun to realize the&#13;
potential value of PM in improving the way the Project works. As a result of the clear and convincing&#13;
information through PM, CIP has changed its ways of doing things in some important areas. Project&#13;
management is now requesting the PM Team to look at other "problematic" areas of the Project. Initial&#13;
skepticism is slowly giving way to acceptance, and, in some cases, even to appreciation. In the case of&#13;
CIP, it appears that PM is playing an important role&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
For further information contact:&#13;
&#13;
UNDP ­ World Bank Water &amp; Sanitation Program ­ South Asia&#13;
World Bank, 20-A Shahrah-e-Jumhuriat, G-5/1, Islamabad, Pakistan ­ Tel +92-51-819781­6 Fax 824807/826362&#13;
Email: sansar@worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Community Infrastructure Project (CIP) Project Management Unit (PMU)&#13;
3rd Floor, Commercial Plaza, Phase V, Hayatabad, Peshawar NWFP, Pakistan ­ Tel: 9291-818540-2, 815542&#13;
Fax: 9291-818543&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5805399">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/01/5805399/improving-user-participation-increase-project-effectiveness-community-action-planning-adaptive-project-nwfp-community-infrastructure-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/01/5805399/improving-user-participation-increase-project-effectiveness-community-action-planning-adaptive-project-nwfp-community-infrastructure-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/01/5805399/improving-user-participation-increase-project-effectiveness-community-action-planning-adaptive-project-nwfp-community-infrastructure-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/05/17/000090341_20050517102131/Rendered/INDEX/312390PAPER0sa1cap1nwfp.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/05/17/000090341_20050517102131/Rendered/PDF/312390PAPER0sa1cap1nwfp.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2005-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2005-05-17T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Improving user participation to increase
            project effectiveness: community action planning in an
            adaptive project - NWFP community infrastructure project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The high drop-out rate of communities
            identified for participating in the Project was identified
            as an important issue by the Project. The PM Team was asked
            to explore possible reasons for this and report to project
            management. As a critical project process, and as a main
            factor in ensuring the community's readiness for
            participating in the project, community mobilization was
            also examined through PM. The preparation of the CAP, an
            important milestone in the community mobilization process,
            was assessed. Field visits, participant observation,
            structured discussions and meetings with project management
            were used to gather information about the entire CAP
            process. The CAP is a formal document containing an
            agreement between the community and the Project.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Improving user participation to increase
            project effectiveness: community action planning in an
            adaptive project - NWFP community infrastructure project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Improving user participation to
            increase project effectiveness: community action planning in
            an adaptive project - NWFP community infrastructure project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2005/01/5805399/improving-user-participation-increase-project-effectiveness-community-action-planning-adaptive-project-nwfp-community-infrastructure-project</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Governance Indicators,Community Development and Empowerment,Civil Society,Social Capital</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Governance,Social Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20050517102131</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program ; field note</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Governance,Social Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            communities, community action, community
            action planning, community based organization, community
            consultation, community demand, Community Development,
            community facilities, Community Infrastructure, community
            involvement, community members, community mobilization,
            community planning, consultation process, data collection,
            Field visits, field workers, income, Infrastructure
            upgrading, intended beneficiaries, interviews, LEARNING,
            lessons learned, Local Government, participant observation,
            PMU, preparation, Process Monitoring, Project management,
            Project Management Unit, Rural Development, social status,
            User Participation
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <repnb>31239</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>AGIs (Actionable Governance Indicators)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Measures of Government Effectiveness, Capacity, Authority, Legitimacy, Legal Framework, Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measures and Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>