<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                Documentof&#13;
                                              The WorldBank&#13;
                                        FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  ReportNo: T7657-WBZ&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            TECHNICAL ANNEX FORA PROPOSEDGRANT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            OFUS$20 MILLION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      TO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           WEST BANK&amp; GAZA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    FORA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                GAZA EMERGENCY WATER PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                May 16,2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Finance, Private Sector and Infrastructure&#13;
MiddleEast andNorthAfrica&#13;
This document has a restricteddistribution and may be used by recipients only in the performanceof their&#13;
official duties. Its contents may not otherwisebe disclosedwithout World Bank authorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                 CURRENCYEQUIVALENTS&#13;
                (Exchange rate as o fMarch 2005)&#13;
          Currency Unit:NewIsraeli Sheqalim (NIS)&#13;
           US$l.OO =NIS 4.37 (as ofMay 11,2005)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    WEIGHTSAND MEASURES&#13;
            1 meter (m)           --        3.281 feet (ft)&#13;
      1kilometer (km)             -         0.621 miles (mi)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            FISCAL YEAR&#13;
                      January 1to December 31&#13;
&#13;
               ABBREV UTIONSAND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
COIF         Capital and Operating InvestmentFund&#13;
CMWU         Coastal Municipalities Water Utility&#13;
CQ           Consultant Qualification&#13;
CTB          Central Tender Board&#13;
EC           EuropeanCommission&#13;
EIA          Environmental Impact Assessment&#13;
EIB          EuropeanInvestmentBank&#13;
EMP          Environmental Management Plan&#13;
ERSP         EmergencyResponseProgram&#13;
EWOC         EmergencyWater OperationsCenter&#13;
FM           FinancialManagement&#13;
FMR          FinancialManagement Report&#13;
FY           Fiscal Year&#13;
GEWP         Gaza Emergency Water Project&#13;
GPN          GeneralProcurement Notice&#13;
GO1          Governmentof Israel&#13;
ICB          International Competitive Bidding&#13;
IDA          IntemationalDevelopment Association&#13;
JWC          Joint Water Committee&#13;
LCBS         Least Cost BasedSelection&#13;
MC           Management Contract&#13;
M C M        Million Cubic Meters&#13;
MOF          Ministry of Finance&#13;
NCB          National Competitive Bidding&#13;
NGEST        Northem GazaEmergency Sewage TreatmentProject&#13;
NGO          Non-Governmental Organization&#13;
NPV          Net PresentValue&#13;
PA           PalestinianAuthority&#13;
PIP          Project Implementation Plan&#13;
PLO          PalestineLiberationOrganization&#13;
PMU          Project Management Unit&#13;
PSC          Project Steering Committee&#13;
PWA          PalestinianWater Authority&#13;
QCBS         Quality and Cost Based Selection&#13;
SAWSIP       SouthernArea and Sanitation Improvement Project&#13;
SOE          Statementof Expenditures&#13;
USAID        United StatesAgency for InternationalDevelopment&#13;
WBG          West Bank and Gaza&#13;
WHO          World Health Organization&#13;
WSSP         Water and Sanitation Services Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Country Director:                  Nigel Roberts&#13;
      Sector Director:                   Hossein Razavi&#13;
      Sector Manager:                    Jonathan Walters&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                      GAZA EMERGENCYWATER PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                                          TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Table of Contents&#13;
SECTIONA COUNTRY AND SECTOR BACKGROUND&#13;
            .                                                                                ................................................................................        1&#13;
&#13;
 INTRODUCTION   .........................................................................................................................................................            1&#13;
 THEWATERANDWASTEWATER                     SECTOR.................................................................................................................                   2&#13;
 PROGRESSACHIEVEDINGAZAUNDERTHE WSSP                                    ................................................................................................... 4&#13;
 ISSUESADDRESSEDGAZA....................................................................................................... 5&#13;
         REMAINING TO BE                             IN&#13;
&#13;
SECTIONB BANK RESPONSEAND STRATEGY&#13;
            .                                                                   ............................................................................................         6&#13;
&#13;
 RATIONALE    FORBANKINVOLVEMENT                    ..................................................................................................................... 7&#13;
 LESSONS LEARNED      FROMSIMILAR OPERATIONS AND UTILIZED INPROJECTDESIGN                                                         ...............................................    9&#13;
SECTIONC THE PROJECT&#13;
            .                          ................................................................................................................................             11&#13;
 PROJECT   OBJECTIVES.............................................................................................................................................                  11&#13;
 PROJECT   COMPONENTS      ...........................................................................................................................................              11&#13;
 KEY PERFORMANCEINDICATORS                  ...........................................................................................................................              13&#13;
 ENVIRONMENTAL     ASPECTS         ....................................................................................................................................              13&#13;
 SOCIALASPECTS    ....................................................................................................................................................               14&#13;
SECTIOND INSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTSAND PROJECTIMPLEMENTATION&#13;
            .                                                                                                                                                  .................... 15&#13;
&#13;
 INSTITUTIONAL  AND IMPLEMENTATION                    ARRANGEMENTS:                 ......................................................................................           15&#13;
 PROJECTIMPLEMENTATION             PLAN     ...........................................................................................................................              16&#13;
 FINANCIALMANAGEMENT              .....................................................................................................................................              17&#13;
&#13;
SECTIONE FINANCIAL AND ECONOMIC JUSTIFICATION&#13;
            .                                                                                           ....................................................................         17&#13;
SECTIONF: SUSTAINABILITY, RISKS AND BENEFITS                                                  .............................................................................          18&#13;
SECTIONG GRANT CONDITIONSAND COVENANTS&#13;
            .                                                                               ...............................................................................         22&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
ANNEX 1: RESULTSFRAMEWORKAND MONITORING                                                         ...........................................................................         23&#13;
ANNEX 2: DETAILED DESCRIPTIONOFPROJECTCOMPONENTS                                                                       .......................................................      36&#13;
ANNEX 3: PROJECTCOSTSAND FINANCING                                         ..............................................................................................            42&#13;
ANNEX 4: FINANCIALMANAGEMENT AND DISBURSEMENT ARRANGEMENTS                                                                                          .............................    43&#13;
ANNEX 5: PROCUREMENTARRANGEMENTS                                             .............................................................................................           47&#13;
ANNEX 6: ENVIRONMENTAL AND SOCIAL ASSESSMENTS                                                           ....................................................................         51&#13;
ANNEX 7: FINANCIALANALYSIS                         ....................................................................................................................              56&#13;
ANNEX 8: PROJECTPREPARATIONAND SUPERVISION                                                        .........................................................................          63&#13;
ANNEX 9: DOCUMENTSONPROJECTFILES                                          ...............................................................................................            64&#13;
ANNEX 10: STATEMENTOF LOANSAND CREDITS                                                  ...................................................................................          65&#13;
ANNEX 11: COUNTRY AT A GLANCE                              .............................................................................................................             66&#13;
MAP IBRD 33512   ......................................................................................................................................................              66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                ...&#13;
                                                                               -111-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                           WEST BANKAND GAZA&#13;
&#13;
                                 GAZA EMERGENCYWATER PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                             TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTIONA. COUNTRYAND SECTORBACKGROUND&#13;
&#13;
Introduction&#13;
&#13;
1.       The proposed Gaza Emergency Water Project (GEWP) is the fifthina series ofwater and&#13;
sanitation projects supported by the Bank in the West Bank and Gaza (WBG) since the&#13;
beginning o f the peace process in October 1993. It follows up on two recently approved&#13;
projects: the Northern Gaza Emergency Sewage Treatment Project (NGEST, US$7.8 million,&#13;
FY05) andthe Emergency Water Project (US$12.5 million, FY04). The former seeks to address&#13;
critical sewage treatment and disposal problems in northern Gaza, while the latter seeks to&#13;
address urgent water supply problems inthe southern area ofthe West Bank.&#13;
&#13;
2.        More importantly, though, the proposedproject (GEWP) seeks to consolidate and sustain&#13;
the very successful achievements of the earlier Bank-supported Gaza Water and Sanitation&#13;
Services Project (WSSP, TF026056, US$31 million, FY97),' which helped rehabilitate the&#13;
networks and systems in Gaza, and improve water and wastewater services delivery through a&#13;
private Management Contract (MC) Operator, as well as lay the foundation for the functional&#13;
establishment of a Coastal Municipalities Water Utility (CMWU).                             While GEWP seeks to&#13;
continue the initiatives of the WSSP, it has been developed in a significantly different and&#13;
considerably more difficult context than its predecessor-a                  context of very deep political, social,&#13;
economic, and institutional crisis which has enveloped WBG since September 2000-the&#13;
beginning o f the second Palestinian Intifada.2 The proposed project has been shaped to a&#13;
considerable extent by this crisis, one that only now seems to be beginning to abate.&#13;
&#13;
The Crisis&#13;
&#13;
3.        The ensuing cycle o f violence and counter-violence on both sides took the lives of more&#13;
than 3,100 Palestinians and about 980 Israelis.                    During the first two years of the crisis,&#13;
Palestinian economic and social indicators fell dramatically: real gross national disposable&#13;
income per capita declined by 29 percent between 1999 and 2003, while overall gross national&#13;
income losses reached US$5.2 billion - equal to almost one year of pre-Intifada Palestinian&#13;
national income. Physical damage was estimated at more than US$1.7 billion at replacement&#13;
cost; capital stock declined by about 20 percent; total investment fell from about US$1.45 billion&#13;
in 1999 to as little as US$500-550 million in2002. Per capita real income at the end of 2002&#13;
was only about half of what it had been three years earlier; the share of the population living in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.   See Implementation Completion Report No. 26156, dated June 26, 2003.&#13;
2.   This sectionrelies on The Trust Fundfor Gaza and the WestBank: Status, Strategy, and Requestfor Replenishment, Report&#13;
No: 27094-62, November 5,2003, and Twenty-Seven Months-Intfada, Closures and Palestinian Economic Crisis, World Bank,&#13;
May 2003.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           -1-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
poverty - defined as those consuming less thanUS$2.1 of goods and services per day3-tripled,&#13;
to about 60 percent of the population; the health status of the Palestinian population declined;&#13;
and real per capita food consumption dropped by up to a quarter when comparedto 1998 levels.&#13;
The crisis not only devastated the Palestinian economy and society, but it also placed the&#13;
PalestinianAuthority's (PA's) finances under severe pressure, making it extremelydifficult for it&#13;
to meet its basic domestic commitments.&#13;
&#13;
4.        Since 2003, the crisis has eased somewhat. However, there i s as yet little sign of&#13;
sustainable economic recovery, with incomes and employment yet to returnto pre-2000 level^.^&#13;
On the political front, however, there are currently some positive signs.&#13;
&#13;
The Water andWastewater Sector&#13;
&#13;
5.        The sector has come a longway since 1995:&#13;
&#13;
    8     A capablenational institution, the PalestinianWater Authority (PWA), has beenfounded&#13;
&#13;
    8     The foundations for policy and operational coordination with Israel have been&#13;
          established;&#13;
&#13;
    8     Several existing municipal distribution networks have been rehabilitated, new networks&#13;
          developed, and supplies improved;&#13;
          Several new water wells have been drilled and many rehabilitated -particularly                            inthe&#13;
          West Bank;&#13;
&#13;
     8    Backbone primary networks of bulk-water carriers are under construction in the West&#13;
          Bank andready to be launched inGaza.&#13;
&#13;
     8    In Gaza, not only have municipal networks and systems been significantly upgraded&#13;
          under an internationally-recruited management contractor, effective managerial and&#13;
          operational systems have also beenestablished;&#13;
&#13;
     8    A new water law rationalizing the sector has beenpassed;&#13;
&#13;
     8    Several studies have beenundertakento evaluate resource availability and quality, supply&#13;
          and demand, well and network conditions, tariffs, technical and financial management,&#13;
          and institutional options;&#13;
          A coherentnational policy has beenlaidout andanational plandeveloped; and&#13;
&#13;
     8    The CMWU is being establishedin Gaza, inan attempt to consolidate the existing small&#13;
          and inefficient municipalwater departments into a more efficiently operating and service&#13;
          delivery unit.&#13;
&#13;
6.        However, the crisis has taken a heavy toll on the sector, particularly on the West Bank,&#13;
whichsuffered significantly from intemal closures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.   The US$2.1 povertyline is basedon what is consideredto be the minimum acceptable levelof expenditures(food andnon-&#13;
food) per capitainabenchmarkhouseholdconsistingof two adults andfour children(National Commissionfor Poverty&#13;
Alleviation, PalestinePoverty Report 1998).&#13;
4.   See "Four Years -Intifada, Crisis and Palestinian Economic Crisis", World Bank, October 2004 for the most recent&#13;
assessment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            -2-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Impactof Crisison the Sector&#13;
&#13;
7.       An estimated US$900 million in overall infrastructure sector damage was inflicted on&#13;
WBG between September 2000 and July 2003. The water and wastewater sector accounted for&#13;
about US$140 million, or about 25 percent o f the total cost o f damage. Most o f the damage&#13;
involved the breakage o f supply lines and the destruction o f water pumps and installations. As&#13;
the crisis deepened, the P W A and municipalities were unable to collect fees from an increasingly&#13;
impoverished citizenry. Supplies and spare parts depleted, and access to networks to undertake&#13;
essential maintenance and repairs was curtailed by extensive Israeli military blockades, closures&#13;
and curfews. As a result, many waterlines and sewers have gone un-repaired for lengthyperiods&#13;
of time, and inmany municipalities the streets have been strewn with garbage. The challenge to&#13;
public healthis obvious.&#13;
&#13;
8.       Inaddition, the crisis weakened the ability o f both PWA and the municipalities to meet&#13;
their financial commitments to the Israeli Water Corporation(Mekhorot) for supplies provided-&#13;
leading to a considerable build up o f arrears that the PA in the end had to settle with the&#13;
Government o f Israel (GOI).            Finally, with the crisis, the damage sustained to plant and&#13;
equipment severely retarded PWA's and the municipalities' ability to implement their originally&#13;
planned development and institutional reform programs. This was mainly due to the physical&#13;
risks and movement restrictions on workers, contractors and consultants. The risks to life and&#13;
limb and the cost and difficulties o f doing business reduced the willingness o f management&#13;
contractors (agents) and potential investors to participate inthe management and development o f&#13;
the sector, negatively impacting progress inpreparing new projects, including GEWP.&#13;
&#13;
PWA Response&#13;
&#13;
9.        Recognizing the heightened threat to public health, the increased economic burden on&#13;
households, and the financial and operational constraints on municipalities and villages, the&#13;
PWA established the Emergency Water Operations Center (EWOC) in April 2002. This was&#13;
done in close consultation with and strong support from the donor and NGO community.&#13;
EWOC's mandate was largely limitedto the West Bank, partly because the problems there were&#13;
more widespread and severe, and because o f the capacity already built up in Gaza by P W A and&#13;
the municipalities under the WSSP and other donor supported projects. The purpose o f the&#13;
EWOC was (and still is) to assist in responding to the growing humanitarian crisis through the&#13;
prompt restoration o f basic water and sanitation services in the West Bank. EWOC has&#13;
functioned very well to date. In the first six months o f operation, it disbursed about US$1.15&#13;
million for emergency repair works, managing to get the most severely damaged systems back&#13;
up and running and delivering emergency supplies (including bottled water) and spares. An&#13;
additional US$4.4 million has recently been made available to EWOC by donors for continuing&#13;
emergency work.          The focus is now on restocking o f supplies, helping to improve local&#13;
preparedness, and moving beyond mere crisis management to help relieve social and economic&#13;
hardship inthe most affected areas.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.   It shouldbenotedthat the PWA's response includedthetwo Bank-supportedprojects:the West BankEmergencyWater&#13;
Project(WBEWP), andtheNorthernGaza SewageTreatment Project(NGEST), both identified above.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         -3-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CurrentSectorIssues&#13;
&#13;
10.     Despite considerable efforts and many praiseworthy achievements, the structure and&#13;
performance of the water supply and delivery system as a whole has not yet changed&#13;
significantly:&#13;
&#13;
    Water production and consumption at 105 and 65 liters per capita per day respectively,&#13;
    remains low, well below regional comparators and Israel, and critical water resources are&#13;
    still almost totally under GO1control.&#13;
    Palestinian supply and demandinthe West Bank i s highly constrainedby Israeliactions.&#13;
    Supply in Gaza, while somewhat less constrained than in the West Bank, is o f highly&#13;
    variable quality (high salinity and nitrate contents). The Gaza aquifer remains degraded and&#13;
    at risk o f irreversible damage.&#13;
    Adequate wastewater treatment and disposal are still lacking, and the potential for&#13;
    wastewater reuse is not effectively exploited.&#13;
    Adequate transmission networks and systemshave yet to be developed.&#13;
    While the new law and the proposed institutionalreforms have achieved extremely positive&#13;
    developments, they have yet to be fully implemented.&#13;
    The institutionalframework, while greatly improved, still needs further rationalization;&#13;
    Distribution institutions and systems are still inefficient, and in need of major reform and&#13;
    rehabilitation, andwater lossesare unacceptably high.&#13;
    Tariffs generally do not reflect the cost of operations or maintenance, much less&#13;
    development needs.&#13;
    Finally, the initiative to establish CMWUneeds to be consolidated.&#13;
&#13;
11.     Insummary, while there has beenconsiderable progressinthe sector, an achievement of&#13;
which the PWA can bejustly proud, there is still a long and difficult road ahead-one made even&#13;
more difficult by the crisis.&#13;
&#13;
ProgressAchievedinGaza underthe WSSP&#13;
&#13;
12.     Significant progress was achieved in Gaza under WSSP, the immediate predecessor of&#13;
GEWP. For example:&#13;
&#13;
(a) Physical Indicators&#13;
    Improved water quality: almost 100 percent of the waterin the network is now disinfected.&#13;
    This i s up from about 50 percent in 1996.&#13;
&#13;
m   Over 1,200 kmof pipewas surveyed for leaks.&#13;
     17,000 illegal connections were identified, and 8,400 converted to legal status.&#13;
    Over 26,000 service connections have beenreplaced.&#13;
    20,000 meters were repaired, and a total o f over 40,000 replaced.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -4-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
     Accounted for water improved from 50% to 72%.&#13;
&#13;
(b) Institutional Indicators&#13;
     The basis for a regional utility (CMWU) was laid, replacing the numerous weak and&#13;
     fragmented municipal departments.&#13;
     Computerized administrative systems were developed.&#13;
     A computerizedcustomer service system was installed.&#13;
     Management training programs were instituted.&#13;
     A public informationprogramwas developed andimplemented.&#13;
     A regional association o fwater sector personnel was established.&#13;
&#13;
13.     There were several other important achievements duringthe years prior to the crisis. For&#13;
example, revenue collection increased from NIS17 million in 1996 to NIS33 million in 1999.&#13;
However, this and many o fthe positive financial trends were reversed as the economic impact of&#13;
the Intifada took hold, and several issues remainto be addressed.&#13;
&#13;
Issues Remainingto beAddressedinGaza&#13;
&#13;
14.     Despite the progress achieved under WSSP, several issues remain to be addressed. For&#13;
example: the drinking water supply in the Gaza Strip is still o f insufficient quality and is&#13;
intermittent, with intemptions of supplies sometimes lasting for several days. Although about&#13;
98% o f households are connected to the drinking water supply network, households increasingly&#13;
have to rely on water delivered by tankers or on bottled water, both delivered at a comparatively&#13;
high cost. The salinity, and especially the nitrate content, of drinking water exceeds the World&#13;
Health Organization (WHO) norms. Wastewater treatment is also most inadequate--existing           '&#13;
treatment plants are overloaded, andtreated effluent and sludge are disposed o f inadequately. In&#13;
addition, the already heavily overexploited groundwater is being contaminated by leakage from&#13;
cesspools as well as by residues from fertilizers. About 140 million cubic meters (MCM) per&#13;
year are being abstracted while the natural safe yield i s only about 60 M C M per year. Return&#13;
flows are 50 M C M per year, leading to increasing seawater intrusion into the aquifer inthe order&#13;
o f 30 M C M per year. Furthermore, as the population increases -mainly due to high natural&#13;
growth - and the per capita water consumption rises, the demand for water will inevitably&#13;
increase. This will place even more stress on the resource, supply anddelivery systems.&#13;
&#13;
15.     The main obstacle for improved service delivery is o f an institutional nature. Untilthe&#13;
establishment o f CMWU, water and sanitation service delivery inthe Gaza Strip was fragmented&#13;
between 25 municipal and village councils, whose managerial capacity i s weak andwhose tariffs&#13;
still barely cover operation and maintenance costs.      To make matters worse, municipalities&#13;
frequentlydiverted water revenues to subsidize other municipal services. The water networks o f&#13;
most municipalities were physically separate from one another, making it impossible to&#13;
distribute to all municipalities urgently needed bulk water that would come either from future&#13;
desalination or from imports.&#13;
&#13;
16.     In order to operate and to finance the expensive infrastructure needed to improve the&#13;
supply and distribution system in Gaza, there are three prerequisites: (i) the establishment o f a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -5-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
single water utility with financial autonomy for the whole of Gaza; (ii)                         renewed and enhanced&#13;
private sector participation; and (iii) introduction of a cost recovery mechanismconsisting of&#13;
                                                   the&#13;
an effective metering and billing systemalong with adequatetariffs. Additionally, the capacities&#13;
o f newly established CMWU as well as that of the PWA need to be strengthened. Inparticular,&#13;
CMWU, which will be the owner of the assets, would be responsible for setting and monitoring&#13;
key objectives interms of service delivery, and hence needs to be fully operationalized. PWA,&#13;
for its part, needs to be strengthened to enable it to focus effectively on regulating the sector,&#13;
including environmental aspects such as groundwater quality, groundwater abstraction, and&#13;
wastewater quality and discharge and selected economic aspects such as adherence to national&#13;
water tariff guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION B. BANKRESPONSEAND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
17.      Bank assistance during the crisis (i.e., from late 2000 to the present) constitutesthe third&#13;
phase of Bank intervention6 and features a balance between maintaining medium-term&#13;
developmental activity where feasible and providing emergency assistance designed to sustain&#13;
Palestinian institutions and mitigate poverty. Inresponseto economic hardshipand fiscal crisis,&#13;
the Bank has placed increasing emphasis on fast-disbursing operations, with US$89.1 million&#13;
committed to various emergency projects since the beginning o f the Intifada.7                                       Initially,&#13;
consistent with the Bank's emergency support during periods of closure inthe 2000s, priority has&#13;
been given to job creation (the Emergency Response Program, FYOI). The scale of job losses&#13;
renderedsuch efforts marginal intheir overall impact, however, from 2001 onwards the Bank's&#13;
emergency strategy shifted towards sustaining basic services, largely through operating cost&#13;
support.* An additional element in the Bank's emergency response was a reallocation of&#13;
US$10.3 million from six Credits into public infi-astructure repair. The Board approved this&#13;
reallocation inAugust 2002.'&#13;
&#13;
18.      Inthe last two years, the keyobjective ofthe Bank's strategy andprogramwas to balance&#13;
efforts to managethe emergency with a continued focus on a medium-termdevelopment agenda.&#13;
This objective built on the bi-focal strategy espoused inthe Bank's two Economic Assessments,&#13;
which are reflected in the ongoing Palestinian Social and Economic Stabilization Plan 2004-5.&#13;
The strategy aims at continuing to lay the institutional foundation for statehood through&#13;
knowledge-basedanalytical and policy work, and operations that encourage the development of&#13;
sound governance institutions at the central and sector levels; and, in the context o f the current&#13;
&#13;
6.   See The Trust Fundfor Gaza and the WestBank: Status, Strategy, and Requestfor Replenishment, ReportNo: 27094-62,&#13;
November 5, 2003. The first phase(1994-96) focusedon emergencyrehabilitation of infrastructureandbasic services. The&#13;
second(1997-2000) saw the beginningof stabilizationand institutionalreform.&#13;
7.   These are Emergency Response Program (ERP), which financedover 200 labor-intensivemicro-projects,two Emergency&#13;
Services Support Projects (Iand   Io,which  provideoperatingcost support to the main social service ministries(Education,&#13;
Health, and SocialAffairs), the Emergency Municipal Services Rehabilitation Project, which helpsmunicipalitiessustainbasic&#13;
services(solid waste, electricity, water &amp; sanitation) as well as strengthenbudgetandplanningprocesses, the Emergency Water&#13;
Project, which alleviates severe water shortagein the southern West Bank and the Northern Gaza Emergency Sewage Treatment&#13;
Project.&#13;
8.   Annex 1 in Twenty-Seven Months-Intifada, Closure and PalestinianEconomic CrisisAn Assessment features acomparison&#13;
of welfare instruments -- food, cash schemes, job creation, budget support  -- andconcludesthat budget supportto the PA and&#13;
municipalitieshas greaterimpactfrom the macro-economicandwelfare perspectivesthan employment generationactivitiesas&#13;
implementedthus far.&#13;
9.   The six projectsbeingthe Municipal InfrastructureDevelopmentProjectsI&amp; 11,the EducationAction Project, the&#13;
Bethlehem2000 Project, the GazaIndustrialEstateProjectandthe Solid Waste and EnvironmentalManagementProject.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 -6-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
crisis, continue providing analytical andprogrammatic leadershipto the collective donor effort to&#13;
cope with the emergency, while initiating multi-donor operations to support the delivery of&#13;
essential services andthe maintenancehecovery of private sector activity.&#13;
&#13;
19.       The proposed project (GEWP) is a key part o f the lending program proposed to the&#13;
Board. It aims to address specific, highpriority issues inthe water and wastewater sub-sector in&#13;
Gaza, and supports the Bank's already widely respected leadership inthe collective donor effort&#13;
to find effective ways to assist with the most negative social and economic consequences of the&#13;
crisis in WBG. In addition, the technical assistance to be given to PWA under the project will&#13;
helpensure more effective managementandregulatory oversight ofthe sector.&#13;
&#13;
20.       Finally, and importantly, it should be noted that significant changes in Bank strategy and&#13;
policy changes are afoot. Following upon GOI's decision in 2004 to withdraw from Gaza and&#13;
areas of the northern West Bank," the Bank was asked by the donor community to explore the&#13;
options for sustained recovery inGaza, and WBG as a whole. After a number of recent studies a&#13;
new Bank and donor strategy and policy options have started to emerge." Reinforcingthis has&#13;
been the election of the new Palestinian President and the very recent formation o f a new&#13;
Palestinian govemment (February 2005). However, it i s too early to say where these nascent&#13;
changes will lead, ifanywhere.12&#13;
&#13;
Rationale for Bank Involvement&#13;
&#13;
21.       There are two basic reasons for Bank involvement: one i s based on successful Bank&#13;
leadership and track record o f positive results inthe water sector in Gaza, and WBG in general,&#13;
followed by the need to follow through on reform initiatives that were started; and the other is&#13;
basedmore broadly onthe Bank's role and experience with emergency operations.&#13;
&#13;
22.       Leadership and Staying the Course: As indicated above, the Bank has played a leading,&#13;
innovative and successful role in initiating change in the water sector in Gaza under WSSP.&#13;
Among the initiatives was the introduction of a private sector Operator under a performance-&#13;
based Management Contract (MC) to operate and manage water and wastewater services&#13;
throughout Gaza.             This proved to be an example of best practice not only in Gaza, but&#13;
worldwide, and has attracted considerable additional donor support for the sector.&#13;
&#13;
23.       The regional sector staff envisaged a follow-on project, since it was acknowledged that&#13;
the task of entirely transforming the sector could not be accomplished in a single project. The&#13;
plan was to lay the foundation for a CMWU, which was achieved under the WSSP, and to&#13;
deepen the level of private sector participationinthe follow-on project, possibly to the stage of a&#13;
concession agreement, considerably advancing sector development in Gaza and setting a model&#13;
for entire WBG. For reasons largely related to the crisis, the latter has proved impossible&#13;
because the physical and financial risks have become too high. Despite this setback which has&#13;
considerably delayed the preparation of the proposed new project, PWA and the Bank have&#13;
managedto maintain private sector interest incontinuing to build capacity in Gaza, culminating&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10. GOI, ModzjiedDisengagementPlan, June 6,2004.&#13;
11. See "Stagnation or Revival, Israeli Disengagement and PalestinianEconomic Prospects" World Bank; December 2004.&#13;
12. It should also be notedthat the PA hasjust announcedPalestinian MediumTerm Development Plan 2005-2007 (PMTDP),&#13;
lay out their plans for the future. This plan is currently beingreviewed by the Bank and donors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 -7-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
in a successful international competitive bidding, evaluation and subsequently signing of a&#13;
performance-based M C in April 2005. This augurs well for the development of the sector in&#13;
Gaza, as shown above to be still inneed of considerableassistance.&#13;
&#13;
24.       Emergency Experience: The Bank has had considerable global experience in designing&#13;
andimplementingoperations inresponseto natural disasters andemergenciesarising inconflict-&#13;
affected settings. Also, developing countries are becoming increasingly aware o fthe needto put&#13;
in place measures to prevent or reduce risks arising from crises. Thus, the number of Bank-&#13;
supported emergency recovery projects has increased in the past ten years, and the Bank has&#13;
come a long way in its own understandingof how to operationalize sustainable interventions in&#13;
emergency situations. InWBG, specifically, the Bank is often relied upon by the PA and donors&#13;
to lead such efforts, andhas done so successfully. For example:&#13;
&#13;
     The first three operations implementedby the Bank inWBG13were all of emergency nature&#13;
     and benefitedfrom simplicity o f design and speed of preparation, while contributing toward&#13;
     the establishment of Palestinian implementation capacity, givenits absence at the outset.&#13;
     The Bank has already demonstrated an ability to respond rapidly and effectively to the&#13;
     current crisis in WBG through its US$12 million contribution to the Emergency Response&#13;
     Program,14launched in December 2000 - only two months after the start of the second&#13;
     Intifada - in which the Bank and five other donors provided over US$37 million to create&#13;
     temporary employment opportunities throughsmall-scale infrastructure micro-projects.&#13;
     The Bank's ability to mobilize resources and contribute by providing a framework for other&#13;
     donor assistance is illustrated by the Emergency Services SupportProjects I h II;TF050473;&#13;
     US$20 million, FY02 followed by US$40 million, FY03), which has mobilized over US$55&#13;
     million inadditional donor co-financing.&#13;
      The Emergency Municipal Services Rehabilitation Project (TF050956; US$20 million,&#13;
     FY03), prepared in close coordination with the European Commission and the Government&#13;
     of Belgium, among others, will leverage over US$37 million in parallel financing at its&#13;
      inception. Additional donor co-financing is expectedto follow once the proposed Municipal&#13;
     Fund is established.l5&#13;
      The Emergency Water Project (TF052627 GZ; US$12.5 million; FY04), prepared in close&#13;
      coordination with PWA, USAID andthe Government of France, will relieve the severe water&#13;
      shortage in the villages of the southern West Bank. Emergency Water is expected to&#13;
     leverage some US$70 million equivalentindonor fundingfor the area.&#13;
      The recent Northern Gaza Sewage Treatment Project (TF054208; US$7.8 million; FY05),&#13;
     preparedin close coordination with Government of Sweden, will address the long festering&#13;
      environmental, public health and safety probleminnorthern Gaza.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
13. Emergency Rehabilitation Project I and II(November 1994and May 1996respectively)and the Education and Health&#13;
Rehabilitation Project (February 1998).&#13;
14. The Bank channeleda contributionto the Emergency Response Program (P073538) of US$12 million throughthe Bank-&#13;
administeredHolstFundandleverageda further US$25 million injoint co-financingthroughthe PEACE Facility in support of&#13;
emergencyjob creationthrough infrastructuremicro-projects.&#13;
15.  EMRSPis amunicipal instrument, anddoes notaddress deeper supply anddistributionproblems inthe water sector-at least, not inthe&#13;
short run.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               -8-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    The Bank's Country Office has a comparative advantage by virtue of its highly skilled and&#13;
    experienced national and international staff that can effectively administer and supervise&#13;
    emergency programs inthe WBG.&#13;
    Through its various water and wastewater studies and projects in WBG over the last eight&#13;
    years, the Bank has gained a deep knowledge and understanding o f the sector and&#13;
    demonstrated considerable practical and intellectual leadership. It has also built a strong&#13;
    relationship with PWA andother key donors inthe sector. Thus, PWA anddonors expect the&#13;
    Bankto play a leadingrole intimes such as these.&#13;
    The Bank's comparative advantage and global experience, has been instrumental in&#13;
    implementing innovative institutional reforms in the sector pioneered under the Water and&#13;
     Sanitation Services Project (TF026056; US$31 million followed by an additional US$6&#13;
    million as a supplemental credit; FY97) and the Southern Area and Sanitation Improvement&#13;
    Project (TF022443 -US$21 million, FY00).16&#13;
    Finally, based on its successful initiatives in Gaza (noted repeatedly above) the Bank has&#13;
    been specifically asked by the PA, including PWA, to take the lead in this very urgent and&#13;
     sensitive project.&#13;
&#13;
LessonsLearnedfrom Similar OperationsandUtilizedinProjectDesign&#13;
&#13;
25.       Two sets o f lessons have been learned and incorporated in the project's design. Those&#13;
specific to the successful M C under the WSSP andthe unsuccessful biddingprocess for an eight-&#13;
year operating lease; and more general ones based on overall program experience.&#13;
&#13;
26.       Specific WSSP Lessons: The lessons specifically noted in the WSSP Implementation&#13;
Completion Report (Report No. 26156) were as follows:&#13;
&#13;
Borrower commitment and ownership:&#13;
&#13;
     Borrower's strong commitment for development o f the sector through the Project was a key&#13;
     factor that not only helped formulate the Project concept/design, but also facilitated its&#13;
     implementation at every successive stage.&#13;
     The strong ownership that the Project enjoyed i s amply demonstrated through the&#13;
     introduction o f the private Operator which ultimately caused a significant turn around inthe&#13;
     sector's overall performance through a "public-private partnership" that was based on mutual&#13;
     trust and confidence. This created an enabling environment for other donors to step-in, and&#13;
     provided much neededfinancing for the sector's further development.&#13;
     The consolidation o f the municipalities' water departments through the creation o f the&#13;
     C M W U as the sole entity responsible for the provision o f water supply and wastewater&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16. The key institutionalreformcomponent of SAWSIP was restructuredrecently inresponse the terminationofthe contract&#13;
with the intemationaloperator on groundsofforce majeure. Both actions were directly due to the current crisis. Giventhe&#13;
circumstances, it is highly unlikely that the strategicobjectivesfor the creationof the southem water utility canbecome a reality&#13;
inthe short-term. Duringthisperiodof instability,the focus will beplacedin addressingthe pressingneedsto supply additional&#13;
water while pursuingthe modestobjectiveof establishingjoint service councils, which would be astepping-stonefor the creation&#13;
ofthe future southemutility.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 -9-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   disposal systems demonstrates the commitment o f the Borrower inthe implementation o f its&#13;
   stated strategy for the sector.&#13;
&#13;
27.    Independent auditing necessary to build trust and certijj the annual performance&#13;
incentivefee.    In Gaza, where no regulatory capacity existed before the management contract&#13;
went into effect, the contracting o f an independent reputable auditing firm proved to be essential&#13;
inbuildingtrust between the public and private parties involved. The auditor was incharge of&#13;
performing an annual audit o fthe Operator's technical and financial performance, andcalculating&#13;
the incentive fee. Based on their audit work, each year the auditors provided a "comfort letter,"&#13;
which formed the basis o fpayment o fthe annual performance incentive fee.&#13;
&#13;
28.    Management Contract&#13;
&#13;
   Providing higher degrees o f management responsibility to the Operator can expedite system&#13;
   improvements.&#13;
   As successful as the Operator was in meeting the requirements under its direct authority,&#13;
   local authorities were not always committed to supporting these improvements (e.g.,&#13;
   conversion o f illegal connections).&#13;
   Despite the overall success o f the contract, the Operator was not able to consolidate the&#13;
    receivables o f all the municipality water departments. Thus, the initial financial position o f&#13;
   the newly created C M W U could be undermined by this unclear receivables position and&#13;
    implementation o f a clear actionplanto reduce them may be difficult. The new M C has paid&#13;
    particular attentionto reducing these receivables.&#13;
    Some o f the key features that enabled a successful implementation o f the M C include:&#13;
    (i)well-defined roles o f the P W A and the Operator (parties o f the contract); (ii)clear&#13;
    allocation o f risks between the PWA and the Operator; (iii)  achievable performance targets;&#13;
    and (iv) a clear linkage between incentive fees andperformance.&#13;
&#13;
29.     Overall: The experience in Gaza suggests that MCs are likely to be the most effective&#13;
form o fprivate participation under the following conditions:&#13;
&#13;
     The primary objective is to rapidly enhance the technical capacity and efficiency o f services.&#13;
     Government faces obstacles in committing to a long-term arrangement for private&#13;
     participation, or in attracting private sector investment that i s willing to bear commercial&#13;
     and/or political risks.&#13;
     Tariffs are too low to support a sustainable long-term arrangement for private participation.&#13;
     Government faces difficulties in securing agreements to allow the long-term involvement o f&#13;
     the private sector, due to an inappropriate/absence o f any regulatory framework. Putting in&#13;
     place a short-term M C allows the authorities to focus on adopting an appropriate strategy,&#13;
     creating a proper regulatory framework, adjust tariffs and subsidies; thus creating an&#13;
     environment that has the proper conditions for private sector participation and risk taking.&#13;
&#13;
30.     General Program Lessons:          Important lessons have been learned from the recent&#13;
emergency operations in WBG supported by the Bank. These relate to decentralization o f&#13;
project preparation and implementation. The latter greatly facilitates implementation at a time&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -10-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
when central systems are unable to function effectively because of the security situation. In&#13;
addition, the following has been learned:&#13;
&#13;
    The water and wastewater sector is one of the few in which dialogue and reasonable&#13;
    working relationships still persist among the professionals on the Palestinian and Israeli&#13;
    sides, and where consistent donor involvement has also facilitated the dialogue betweenthe&#13;
    Palestinian and Israeli parties. There appears to be a higher-level consensus that issues&#13;
    related to the management o f scarce water resources, and the health risks attached to a&#13;
    breakdown inwater and sanitation systems are too important to be left to the vagaries of the&#13;
    current crisis.&#13;
&#13;
    Consultative mechanisms such as the Joint Water Committee (JWC) bring together Israeli&#13;
    and Palestinian professionals (including the military) periodically to discuss sector issues.&#13;
    These mechanisms are working and have proved effective in sorting out many problems.&#13;
    For example, upon consultation in a number of cases including the ongoing SAWSIP and&#13;
    EWP, Israeli military authorities have given special permits to a number o f contractors and&#13;
    consultantsinorder to facilitate the movement o f construction equipment and workers.&#13;
&#13;
    The situation favors the operation of international contractors, who are able to expedite the&#13;
    process of obtaining the necessarypermits and clearances. However, there i s a highrisk that&#13;
    key expatriate staff may depart quickly when serious conflicts materialize.&#13;
&#13;
    Existing consultative mechanisms must be utilized effectively, and project design,&#13;
    management and procurement strategies must exploit, or at least take heed o f the factors that&#13;
    foster success inthe current context.&#13;
&#13;
    Finally, realistic contingency plans must be developed to deal with the various crises and&#13;
    blockagesthat may arise.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION C. THEPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
ProjectObjectives&#13;
&#13;
31.    The primary objectives of the proposedproject are to improve the provision of adequate&#13;
water and wastewater services in Gaza, and to functionally establish the Coastal Municipalities&#13;
Water Utility as an autonomous well-runmodern utility. Inaddition, the project has a secondary&#13;
objective to strengthenPWA's capacity to assume sector regulatory functions.&#13;
&#13;
ProjectComponents&#13;
&#13;
32.    The project would pursuethe above objectives through the following components:&#13;
&#13;
   a.     Performance-based Management Contract Comoonent (US$8.6 million).                  This&#13;
   component would finance the fixed fees for key staff of the Operator to supply services and&#13;
   management of operations required by the MC. This component would also finance the&#13;
   annual performance incentive fees based on the attainment o f specific performance targets&#13;
   built into the MC.       This payment will depend on the extent o f the achievement of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              -11-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   performance targets specified in the M C and will be determined by the application of a&#13;
   performance factor (composite score) to the maximum annual performance incentive fee of&#13;
   US$SOO,OOO.     The agreed term of the M C is 3 years with a provision for a four-year&#13;
   extension.    The M C was tendered competitively following the Bank's procurement&#13;
   guidelines. The mainperformancetargets for the managementcontract are clusteredaround:&#13;
&#13;
                  Structuring the newly established utility by proposing its organization&#13;
                  structure, staffing plan, payroll system, human resource management,&#13;
                  strengtheningthe capital investment andplanning systems.&#13;
&#13;
                  Improving water quantity by reducing water losses and increasing the supply&#13;
                  capacity.&#13;
&#13;
                  Improving water quality via the maintenance and upgrade o f the existing&#13;
                  disinfection program including improving the performance of the existing&#13;
                  wastewater works.&#13;
&#13;
                  Improvingthe management systems of the water andwastewater services with&#13;
                  emphasis on operation and maintenance systems, financial management,&#13;
                  customer services, billing and collection, humanresourcesdevelopment.&#13;
&#13;
   b.    CaDital and Operatinrr Investment Fund Component (US$12.0 million).                 This&#13;
   component would finance the purchase o f materials, supplies and equipment essential for&#13;
   operations and maintenance o f water and wastewater systems for which collected revenues&#13;
   are unable to cover. This fund i s under the control o f the Operator; however, the CMWU&#13;
   Board will approve annual procurement plans prepared by the Operator in accordance with&#13;
   Bank Procurement Guidelines. This would reduce procurement concerns, and provide the&#13;
   Operator with funds to direct the achievement of the performance standards set in the&#13;
   managementcontract.&#13;
&#13;
   c.    Institutional Reform and Capacitv Building Component (US$2.3 million). This&#13;
   component would focus on completing a list of activities considered the cornerstones for&#13;
   building the utility. The list o f such activities constitutes the short- to medium-termagenda&#13;
   for functionally establishing the CMWU. This component would fund the existing Project&#13;
   Management Unit (PMU) to continue its supervisory functions o f the M C Operator. In&#13;
   addition, funding is included for key capacity building tasks for PWA targeted at enabling a&#13;
   more effective regulatory framework to be inplace. These tasks build on and complement&#13;
   the ongoing larger institutional capacity building program funded the Nonvegian-&#13;
   Netherlands program.&#13;
&#13;
33.    A summary of the proposed components, estimated costs and tentative financing is&#13;
presented inthe table below. Further details are presented inAnnex 2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -12-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                Table 1: ProjectComponentsand Costs&#13;
&#13;
                                            EstimatedCost (including  Amount&#13;
Project Phase/Component                     contingencies and taxes)                      Total&#13;
                                                   (US%m)&#13;
&#13;
 1. PrivateSector Operator(Management&#13;
    Contract)&#13;
     1.1 FixedFee                                     6.2                    I  6.2   I     27%&#13;
     1.2 IncentiveBonus                               2.4                       2.4         10%&#13;
                                   Subtotal           8.6                       8.6         37%&#13;
&#13;
2. Capitaland OperatingInvestmentFund                12.0                2.9    9.1         52%&#13;
&#13;
 3. InstitutionalReformandCapacity Building&#13;
    3.1 For CMWU                                      1.2                       1.2         6%&#13;
    3.2 ForPWA                                        0.4                       0.4         2%&#13;
    3.3 Technicalandfinancialaudits                   0.7&#13;
                                   Subtotal           2.3&#13;
Total Cost                                          22.90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
34.       The project cost o f US$22.9 millionequivalent will be financed through a US$20 million&#13;
(87%) grant from the Bank-administered Trust Fund for Gaza and the West Bank and budget&#13;
allocations o f US$2.9 million (13%) from the P A inlieu o ftaxes.&#13;
&#13;
35.       Like the WSSP, the proposed project is part o f a larger donor investment program to&#13;
improve water and sanitation services in the Gaza Strip. The program includes substantial&#13;
investments in the in the sewerage network; wastewater treatment plants; and in a bulk water&#13;
supply network connecting the various municipalities in the Gaza Strip. These investments,&#13;
totaling about US$320 million for 2005-2008, will be financed by soft loans and grants from&#13;
various donors.&#13;
&#13;
KeyPerformanceIndicators&#13;
&#13;
36.       To measure progress towards achieving the development objectives, Annex 1presents the&#13;
key performance indicators for the project. The M C also establishes a set o f annual performance&#13;
targets to be achieved during project implementation. The extent o f progress towards achieving&#13;
those performance targets by the M C Operator is directly related to the amount o f performance&#13;
incentive compensation paid to the Operator each year. Annex 1, also includes performance&#13;
targets prescribed inthe MC.&#13;
&#13;
EnvironmentalAspects&#13;
&#13;
37.       The proposed project would contribute to improving the environment through improved&#13;
management o f existing water and sanitation facilities, increased expenditure on essential&#13;
operations and maintenance, and a capital investment program to expand and improve water and&#13;
sanitation infrastructure. Currently there are no known project proposals whose implementation&#13;
would require land acquisition or result ininvoluntary resettlement. No known archaeological or&#13;
historical sites would be affected by rehabilitation sub-projects, nor does the operating&#13;
investment component o f the project raise any international water issues. The capital investment&#13;
activities to be supported comprise rehabilitation, upgrading and extension o f piped water supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     -13-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
and sewerage services inurbanareas andwater supply improvements inrural areas. The project&#13;
does not include new wastewater treatment facilities.        The project does not include any&#13;
component with major environmental impact and will result in significant improvement in&#13;
environmental quality through improved water and sanitation services.&#13;
&#13;
38.     The environmental impact will be mitigated by improved operations and maintenance o f&#13;
water and sewerage services, which will improve the efficiency o f water use and reduce the need&#13;
for tapping new resources.      Substantial past and future investments by other donors have&#13;
provided adequate wastewater collection systems to accommodate increased discharges resulting&#13;
from this project. Management will be improved by the Operator but treatment, which is&#13;
inadequate, will not be directly increased. However, there are plans to build several wastewater&#13;
treatment plants (funded by donors) to treat the collected sewage and reuse the treated effluent.&#13;
&#13;
39.     The proposed project has been classified under the environmental category "By' in&#13;
accordance with the World Bank's Operational Policy 4.01 on Environmental Assessments&#13;
Accordingly, an Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) and Environmental Mitigation and&#13;
Management Plan (EMP) were completed inMarch2001 as part o fthe Project preparation. Both&#13;
the EIA and EMP remain germane to the planned project, and are available on file within the&#13;
World Bank's Infoshop. Key findings on environmental issues are described inAnnex 6.&#13;
&#13;
SocialAspects&#13;
&#13;
40.     The social assessment findings (Annex 6) showed that most consumers were deeply&#13;
concerned about inadequate water quality and poor regularity/predictability o f supply, and&#13;
improvements in both would bring major public benefits. Given the high risk context o f the&#13;
project, and the need to raise water revenues to viable levels, the main social development&#13;
outcome should be to enhance confidence and trust (or least to take measures to prevent&#13;
deterioration o f trust which would otherwise risk project outcomes). This should be done at two&#13;
levels: to enhance trust between the individual consumer and the service provider, and to ensure&#13;
public trust in the institutional arrangements for the sector.    Subsidiary social development&#13;
outcomes would be adequate safety nets for the very poor and improvement in customer&#13;
behavior inrelation to water.&#13;
&#13;
41.     Implementation therefore requires attention not only to enhancing and improving&#13;
customer satisfaction, but to measuring it objectively, communicating progress regularly, and&#13;
establishing mechanisms o f consultation, handling o f complaints, and a transparent and&#13;
accountable regulatory environment.     Three actions are indicated, which have been included&#13;
amongthe service responsibilities o fthe M C Operator :&#13;
&#13;
    a. Regularconsumer surveys are a useful tool to assess the extent o f consumer satisfaction&#13;
        and o f trust between consumers and service providers. Some o f the issues that could be&#13;
        covered by such surveys are consumer confidence in metering and billing; service time&#13;
        response to complaints and queries including billing; and the reliability o f supply.&#13;
&#13;
    b. Broad-based public informationcampaign should be conducted, including the media.&#13;
        The campaign should go well beyond explaining the need to save water, which has been&#13;
        the main or even unique activity in some awareness campaigns in other countries. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               -14-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        campaign should explain the role o f the private sector Operator; the role given to&#13;
        consumers inmonitoringthe Operator through regular surveys, consumer committees and&#13;
        their board representative; special measures to be introduced to protect the needy; the&#13;
        functioning of the complaints process; the need to increase tariffs in order to provide&#13;
        improved services, in particular improved water quality through desalination and piped&#13;
        sewerage; indicating what the project can and cannot do, at least in the short term,&#13;
        pendingmajor capital investments.&#13;
&#13;
    c. Targeted Support Payments to the Poor: Currently, municipalities exempt some&#13;
        consumers from paying their water bills or forgive the accumulated arrears on water bills,&#13;
        presumably on the basis of social need. However, the current practice may not be well&#13;
        targeted to the poor, since these exemptions are apparently often granted as favors to&#13;
        relatives and friends. The newly approved by-lawsfor the CMWU do not allow for such&#13;
        mechanism to continue. The Operator i s askedto proposea more targeted system.&#13;
&#13;
42.     A possible fourth action would be the formation of consumer committees in each&#13;
municipality or group of municipalities. These committees could serve as an interface between&#13;
the utility and the consumers, holding public meetings, providing feedback to the Operator and&#13;
CMWU on consumer priorities and concerns, and having the right to accede to information from&#13;
the Operator, thus increasingtransparency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTIOND. INSTITUTIONALARRANGEMENTS            AND PROJECTIMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
Institutional and implementation arrangements:&#13;
&#13;
43.     Implementation period The M C will be implemented over 36 months starting July 1,&#13;
2005, through June 30, 2008. The project also includes a provision for retro-active financing&#13;
from May 1,2005.&#13;
&#13;
44.     The CMWU will be the executing agency, which is vested with the responsibility for&#13;
owing all water and wastewater assets and providing and managing water and wastewater&#13;
services in all Gaza governorates. The decree establishing the CMWU and the national Water&#13;
Law No. 3 of 2002 allow the CMWU to delegate part of their responsibilities to others. The&#13;
decision to contract with an experienced private sector water utility company to operate these&#13;
services in Gaza was taken by the CMWU Board and endorsed by PWA and the Ministry o f&#13;
Local Government because of the needs for substantial and rapid improvements in service&#13;
delivery.&#13;
&#13;
45.     Project Coordination:&#13;
&#13;
    a. The CMWU through its Boardo f Directors and with the assistance of the PMU will have&#13;
        overall responsibility for project execution, except for a small technical assistance&#13;
        program to build regulatory capacity within PWA. This small program will be directly&#13;
        managedby PWA.&#13;
&#13;
    b. The PMUwithin the CMWU is headed by a Project Director who reports directly to the&#13;
        CMWU Board. The PMU will be responsible for following day-to-day project activities,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              -15-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       coordinating with the Operator, and monitoring performance indicators during the&#13;
       implementation period. The PMU will also liaise with other government entities such as&#13;
       PWA and the Ministry o f Local Governments to ensure effective implementation of the&#13;
       project.&#13;
&#13;
   c. The Operator will be responsible for managing water and wastewater services in the&#13;
       Service Area under a 3-year performance-based management contract. Ownership of the&#13;
       underlying assets and authority for setting tariffs will remain with the Government. The&#13;
       Operator, as part o f the "Service Obligations" called for by the MC, will have&#13;
       responsibility, on behalf of CMWU, to manage the Capital and Operating Investment&#13;
       Fund (COIF), to procure goods, works and services inaccordancewith the World Bank&#13;
       ProcurementGuidelinesandto enter into contractswith third parties.&#13;
&#13;
   d. In the absence of an effective regulatory mechanisms to regulate the CMWU and until&#13;
       PWA assumes that role effectively, a Project Steering Committee (PSC) chaired by PWA&#13;
       and includes high-level representatives from the Ministries of Finance, Local&#13;
       Government, Public Works and Planning and the Environmental Quality Control&#13;
       Authority will be responsible for providing overall project oversight and policy guidance&#13;
       including reviewing the quarterly progress reports and the annual procurement plan for&#13;
       the use of the COIF as preparedby the Operator.&#13;
&#13;
   e. The Operator's activities will be subject to periodic independent technical and financial&#13;
        audits to monitor performance and determine the amount of performance incentive&#13;
        compensationas prescribedby the MC.&#13;
&#13;
   f. Other works will be carried out underparallel programs by other donors. The CMWU,&#13;
       through the PMU, will ensure coordination of all programs. The M C Operator, who is&#13;
        contractually responsible for operating and maintaining the water supply (and sewerage)&#13;
        system, will accordingly have a special role. This role i s defined in the management&#13;
        contract, which specifies the arrangements for coordination and consultation betweenthe&#13;
        Operator and CMWU with respectto the capital investment program.&#13;
&#13;
ProjectImplementationPlan&#13;
&#13;
46.     A draft Project Implementation Plan (PIP) as preparedby the PMUwas discussedduring&#13;
project appraisal. It was agreed that the final PIP should be submitted before the start of M C to&#13;
provide the operator adequate opportunity to contribute to it. The PIP expands on important&#13;
implementation arrangements, and i s seen by PMU as a flexible implementation tool that would&#13;
be reviewed periodically and adjusted when warranted. The PIP describes the CMWU as the&#13;
focal point that is fully accountablefor Project oversight and coordination. Staffing andkey staff&#13;
positions within the PMU are described in the PIP, which also includes the role of the other&#13;
participants (various ministries and donors), and the coordination mechanisms betweenthe key&#13;
stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
47.     There will be a Project Launch Workshop within one month of effectiveness.&#13;
Supervision missions would take place according to Project requirements. The Project mid-term&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -16-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
review is tentatively scheduled for June 2006. The penultimate supervision mission would be&#13;
usedto launchthe preparation ofthe Implementation Completion Report.&#13;
&#13;
Financial Management&#13;
&#13;
48.     Project financial management (FM) responsibilities will be entrusted to the PMU. The&#13;
PMU was originally part of the PWA and was establishedunder the on-going Emergency Water&#13;
Project (P065921). The decision to utilize the PMU to undertake the financial management&#13;
responsibilities o fthe project is due to the fact that the Operator as part of its responsibilities will&#13;
build adequate finance department at the CMWU. This finance department, when established,&#13;
will be supported by the PMU and will be trained on project financial management and&#13;
reporting. The PMU has in place: an adequate computerized financial management system&#13;
(BISAN), documented financial managementprocedures, and employs qualified financial staff;&#13;
italsohashadapositive 7 year track recordwithBankandother donor fundedprojects.&#13;
&#13;
49.     The existing PMUhas beencompetently managing the Emergency Water Project and the&#13;
previous WSSP. For example, project accountswere continuously maintained up-to-date and all&#13;
Financial Management Reports (FMRs) as well as annual audit reports were received in time&#13;
with clean audit opinion from a qualified auditor. For this Project, the PMU will maintain a full&#13;
set of project accounts, generate quarterly FMRs, and prepare project annual financial&#13;
statements. The project financial statements will be audited annually by a qualified auditor&#13;
acceptable to the International Development Association (IDA). The audit report will be&#13;
           '&#13;
submitted to IDA within six months after year-end. Project Disbursement will use traditional&#13;
disbursement methods including the use of Special Account, Statement of Expenditures (SOE),&#13;
full documentation, and direct payments. Incompliance with the Palestinian laws, the Project's&#13;
SpecialAccount will be establishedunder the Central Treasury Account inthe name of CMWU.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTIONE. FINANCIALAND ECONOMIC              JUSTIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
50.     The management contract financed by the project will generate financial benefits to the&#13;
water andwastewater sector inGazathrough increase inthe revenue collection ratio, as well as a&#13;
decrease in unaccounted-for-water, while ensuring appropriate levels of maintenance o f the&#13;
network.&#13;
&#13;
51.     Other benefits range from the provision of additional water supply capacity to better&#13;
satisfy the targeted population, to securing water supply and protecting water quality at a lower&#13;
cost. The project will increase water supply to households throughout Gaza, particularly lower&#13;
income ones, which will increase their welfare (the consumer surplus) and the revenues for the&#13;
utility. The institutional component of the project will provide different benefits; including&#13;
improving the finances of the CMWU, its management, and will result in reduced operating&#13;
costs. Other benefits include improved skills from capacity building and training inthe different&#13;
operation andmanagementfunctions.&#13;
&#13;
52.     Inthe absence of consolidated auditedfinancial statements for the CMWU, the financial&#13;
analysis was carried out based solely on pro-forma consolidated special purpose income&#13;
statements prepared by PWA with data collected from all municipalities. Given the limited&#13;
availability of financial information, this analysis i s simple and limitedto showing the projected&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   -17-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
impact o f "with and without" management contract scenarios on the service area. The detailed&#13;
analysis is presented inAnnex 7.&#13;
&#13;
53.     Based on the pro-forma consolidated income statements prepared by PWA, the&#13;
municipalities are incurring net losses mainly due to a weak billing and equally weak revenue&#13;
collection systems. At present, maintenance expenditures have been kept to a minimum, given&#13;
the inability o f the municipalities to financially cope with the costs o f appropriately maintaining&#13;
their water and wastewater systems.&#13;
&#13;
54.     The analysis uses a cost-benefit structure, estimating the future financial performance o f&#13;
the municipalities with or without the project, as well as the net present value (NPV) infinancial&#13;
terms for the duration o f the management contract (including the optional 4 years extension).&#13;
The analysis shows that the NPV of the operating surplus with the management contract scenario&#13;
is positive at NIS4.4 million (US$1 million), while the NPV o f the operating deficit without the&#13;
management contract scenario is at NIS40 million (US$9.4 million).&#13;
&#13;
55.     During project implementation, as the CMWU is strengthened and becomes capable o f&#13;
producing appropriate financial statements, a more elaborate analysis should be carried out to&#13;
model its future financial performance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION F: SUSTAINABILITY, RISKSAND BENEFITS&#13;
&#13;
56.     Project sustainability will depend upon the following factors:&#13;
&#13;
    a. establishing a well functioning autonomous modern utility with continued engagement o f&#13;
        the private sector management beyondthe 3 years;&#13;
&#13;
    b. assuring that the Operator will have adequate financial resources to carry out his&#13;
        mandate;&#13;
&#13;
    c. there being adequate supplies o fbulk water; and&#13;
&#13;
    d. the Operator needs to work within a flexible legal environment (labor and procurement&#13;
        regulations, constructionpermits, etc.).&#13;
&#13;
57.     Associated with the factors above are an array o f risks which the following features inthe&#13;
project designhave triedto mitigate:&#13;
&#13;
    a. The C M W U i s legally formed and the Board o f Directors was elected by the General&#13;
        Assembly (all the shareholder municipalities) and a Chairman was selected. The legal&#13;
        registration o f the C M W U and the approval o f its Bylaws were completed early 2005.&#13;
        The CMWU is expected to be the proper vehicle to carry the water and wastewater&#13;
        services in Gaza in a sustainable manner. The new national Water Law and the C M W U&#13;
        Bylaws give the utility a large degree o f financial and operational autonomy to runitself.&#13;
&#13;
    b. The M C puts at the disposal o f the Operator a COIF to be used to achieve the&#13;
        performance targets thus ensuring that the collected revenue stream would cover the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  -18-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       CMWU staff salaries and a percentageof the operational and maintenance costs. As the&#13;
       Operator improves operational efficiency, it is anticipated that revenue collections will be&#13;
       sufficient to cover all working capital needs by the thirdyear of the MC.&#13;
&#13;
   c. To reduce some o f the constraints on water supply, the PA and GO1have agreed for the&#13;
       latter would supply Gaza with 10 million cubic meters annually with of fresh water.&#13;
       Moreover, the M C allows the Operator to dig additional wells ifthe need arise.&#13;
&#13;
   d. The M C contract allows the Operator certain flexibility with respect to procurement&#13;
       planning and execution. Assurances were sought from the PA that the new Central&#13;
       Tender Board (CTB) would not slow down the procurement process prescribed in the&#13;
       MC. Also assurances were sought from the CMWU, PWA and the Ministry of Local&#13;
       Government would exert all efforts to assistthe Operator ingetting the necessarypermits.&#13;
&#13;
   e. The Operator with the assistance of the PMU will also be encouragedto utilize existing&#13;
       coordination mechanisms with GO1to ensure the smooth passage of goods and supplies&#13;
       to Gaza.&#13;
&#13;
Financial Management Risk&#13;
&#13;
58.    The overall FMrisk is rated Moderate. The lack of a finance department initially at the&#13;
CMWU is a major risk factor. However, the inclusion of establishing such a department in the&#13;
M C mitigates this risk. Also, the PMU i s already well-established and has been using a financial&#13;
management system acceptable to the Bank. The process of establishing an adequate finance&#13;
department within CMWU will be closely monitored by the project team as part of project&#13;
supervision.&#13;
&#13;
Critical Risks&#13;
&#13;
59.    There are several risks related to implementing a project inWBG, not all o f which can be&#13;
addressed at this point. Risk factors include: (a) non-performance o f the Operator either as a&#13;
result of (i)poor selection; or (ii)lack of cooperation between municipalities and village&#13;
councils; (b) lack o f counterpart funds, Le., revenues to pay for CMWU staff salaries and other&#13;
operation and maintenance expenditures, and (c) the potential for political instability, that could&#13;
have several negative implications:         (i)access obstruction due to border closure,&#13;
(ii)&#13;
   administrative difficulties to implement the service improvement program by the Operator;&#13;
and (iii)foreign exchange restrictions that could hamper imports necessary to achieve&#13;
performance targets, and investments to improve and expand water and wastewater services&#13;
These risks and others are addressed below:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -19-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                       Risks                        Risk    Risk MinimizationMeasure&#13;
                                                    Rating&#13;
 1. Non-performance o fthe Private Operator          N      Close and continuous supervision o fthe operator staff.&#13;
    either as result o f unavailability o f&#13;
    necessary skills and experienced staff to               Operator was selectedby a rigorous competitive bidding&#13;
    manage the project, or lack o f cooperation             process inaccordance with the World Bank Guidelines&#13;
    o f local government, C M W U and PWA                   andwill work according to defined quantified&#13;
                                                            performance target and will be compensated partly by&#13;
                                                            fixed fee inaddition to a ceiled performance incentive&#13;
                                                            fee.&#13;
 2. Lack o f sufficient revenues to pay for the       S     Preliminary financial analysis has shown that current&#13;
    CMWU Operating Staff, maintenance and                   tariffs, combined with increased sector efficiency,&#13;
    other costs related to the management                   brought about bythe Operator, will significantly improve&#13;
    contract Operator                                       the financial performance at the end o f the three years.&#13;
 3. Lack o f counterpart funds from MOFto            M      Activities selected for financing by MOF underthe COIF&#13;
    finance activities under the COIF                       are limitedto goods, and are inaccordance with MOF's&#13;
                                                            expressedpreference for financing these items. MOF has&#13;
                                                            agreed to add a line itemon its annual budget for&#13;
                                                            channeling o f counterpart funds to CMWU.&#13;
 4. Potential for political instability, that could   S     All projects inWBG face political risks. The Peace&#13;
    have several negative implications: (i)                 Processhas developed momentum and passedsignificant&#13;
    access obstruction due to border closure,               milestones, includingPalestinian self-rule inGaza and&#13;
    (ii) administrative difficulties to implement           parts o fthe West Bank; nevertheless, disruptions due to&#13;
    the services bythe Operator; and (iii)                  political events can be expected from time to time and&#13;
    foreign exchange restrictions that could                could delay implementation. The latest efforts by the&#13;
    hamper imports necessaryto achieve                      Israelis, Palestinians andthe intemational community&#13;
    performance targets, and investmentsto                  look promising.&#13;
    improve and expand water and wastewater&#13;
    services&#13;
 5. Operator's contract is finished after 3 yrs,     M      Allow extension o f the MC, havingthe Operator&#13;
    butPA not able to move forward to amore                 concentrate on financial buildingmeasures and&#13;
    substantive private sector involvement                  performance targets. Special attention is giventowards&#13;
                                                            the strengthening o fthe CMWU as a fully functioning&#13;
                                                            Utility.&#13;
 6. Administrative difficulties to procure           M      The M C includes provision that management and&#13;
    goods and works necessary to implement                  procurement o f goods, works and services underthe&#13;
    rehabilitation investment and service                   COIF would be the responsibility o f the Operator on&#13;
    improvement under the COIF bythe                        behalfo f CMWU.&#13;
    Operator to improve service&#13;
 7. Lack o f agreement on a program of cost           S     Analysis and discussion will be carried out. But water&#13;
    recovery and time frame for pricing reform              pricing proposals may enable pricing issuesto be&#13;
    between                                                 addressed instages&#13;
 8. Delay inproject implementation. Permits          M      Close follow up o f Project Management TeadCMWU of&#13;
    not issued for Investment Projects                      project implementation. Early application o f permits.&#13;
 9. Interference by the newly created CTB             S     The role o f the CTB will be limited, through the Project&#13;
    with the procurement responsibilitiesby                 Steering Committee, to reviewing the annual&#13;
    the M C Operator                                        Procurement Plans on which the M C Operator's work&#13;
                                                            will be based.&#13;
&#13;
I                            OverallRisk Rating      M&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        -20-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Possible Controversial Aspects           --&#13;
                  Risks                  Type of   Risk           RiskMinimizationMeasure&#13;
                                           Risk    Rating&#13;
 1. Costrecovery andtariff restructuring   G         S     A tariff study hasbeencompletedwith&#13;
   may not be able to be implemented                       recommendationson a policy of full cost&#13;
                                                           recoveryand tariffreform.&#13;
                                                            Implementationofnew tariff structure is&#13;
                                                            implicitly tied to improvement inthe&#13;
                                                            economic conditions. The current&#13;
                                                            outlook for improved economy is&#13;
                                                            cautious.&#13;
2. PoliticalOpposition to aprivate         G/S       M      Beneficiary municipalities have accepted&#13;
    Operator                                               to share inthe CMWUand signeda&#13;
                                                            MOUto appointprivate Operator to&#13;
                                                           manage this newly establishedutility.&#13;
                                                            However, recent municipal elections in&#13;
                                                            Gazahave brought innew mayorswho&#13;
                                                            maynotbe entirely sold onthe ideaofthe&#13;
                                                            private operator. The new clan ofmayors&#13;
                                                            will have to be introducedto the concept&#13;
                                                            and advantages ofthe MC.&#13;
3. Operator and OperatingStaff             M         M      All municipal water andwastewater staff&#13;
    relationship                                            will be transferredto the CMWU, which&#13;
                                                            is 100% ownedby the sharing&#13;
                                                            municipalities. The staff will be seconded&#13;
                                                            to the Operator for the life ofthe MC.&#13;
'meofRisk-S (Social) G (Governance) h ManagementCapac      Y)&#13;
RiskRating-S (SubstantialRisk) M(Modc    Risk)N(Negligible or Low Risk)&#13;
&#13;
Benefits&#13;
&#13;
    .&#13;
60.      The main benefits from this project are as follows:&#13;
&#13;
    .....Improved efficiency o f the distribution system through leakage management and network&#13;
         rehabilitation.&#13;
         Improved operational and distribution efficiency will result in higher revenue generation&#13;
         and greater cost recovery.&#13;
         Improved water quality and more regular supply to customers with fewer breaks in&#13;
         service.&#13;
         Improvedwastewater collection and treatment efficiency.&#13;
         Enhancedprivate sector participation inthe delivery o f water andwastewater services.&#13;
&#13;
         Improved planning, project design, procurement and implementation through the&#13;
         functional establishment o fthe CMWU.&#13;
&#13;
61.      Target Population: the entire population of Gaza is within the service areas under the&#13;
project (estimated at around 1.2 million) will benefit from this project. Low income households&#13;
especially will benefit from access to reliable piped water supplies at much lower prices than&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -21-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
charged by vendors. These households will also experience health and environmental benefits&#13;
from improved access to water andwastewater services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION G. GRANTCONDITIONS AND COVENANTS&#13;
&#13;
62.   The following points havebeenagreedas conditions ofeffectiveness:&#13;
&#13;
    Conclusion o f a Subsidiary Agreement betweenthe PalestineLiberationOrganization (PLO)&#13;
    andthe PA satisfactory to IDA.&#13;
    Submission to IDA o f a legal opinion that the Trust Fund Grant Agreement has been duly&#13;
    authorized or ratified by the Recipient and is legally binding upon the Recipient in&#13;
    accordance with its terms. The legal opinion shall also state that the Subsidiary Agreement&#13;
    has been duly authorized or ratified by, and executed and delivered on behalf of, the parties&#13;
    thereto, and i s legally bindinguponthem, inaccordance with its terms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              -22-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                              ANNEX 1: RESULTSFRAMEWORKMONITORING         AND&#13;
&#13;
                                                 Results Framework&#13;
&#13;
              PDO                               Outcome Indicators                       Use of Outcome Information&#13;
&#13;
Improving the provision of      Services consistently meetingstandards: Drinking        Planningfor future investment&#13;
adequatewater andwastewater     water deliverymeetsthe quality andquantity standards    needs andpriorities inthe water&#13;
services inGaza.                Wastewatercollectionanddisposal servicesmeetsthe         andwastewater sectors.&#13;
                                standards&#13;
Functionallyestablishingthe                                                              Improvedenforcement ofthe&#13;
CoastalMunicipal Water          CMWU fully functionaland operational: Sets clear         environmentalregulationofthe&#13;
Utility (CMWU) as an            objectives andmonitorsthe performanceof its services     CMWU.&#13;
independentmodernutility.       throughactionplanson investmentneedsandpriorities.&#13;
&#13;
Strengtheningthe capacityof     Capacity of PWA strengthened: PWA monitorswater&#13;
the PalestinianWater Authority  abstraction,groundwaterand wastewaterqualitieson a&#13;
(PWA) to assume its sector      regularandcomprehensivebasisand publishesperiodic&#13;
regulatoryrole.                 reports about compliance with adoptedstandards.&#13;
&#13;
    Intermediate Results             Results Indicators for Each Component                Use of Results Monitoring&#13;
   (one per Component)&#13;
&#13;
Components 1and 2:''            The amount ofthe annualperformanceincentive              Action planpreparedto pay&#13;
Performance-based               compensation(PIC) paidto the Operator isusedas a         incentives&#13;
Management Contract and         proxyto measurethe success ofthe Operator in             The Auditor andCMWUreports&#13;
associated Capital and          achievingthe MC performancetargets. The PIC              enablethe CMWU Board, PWA&#13;
Operating Investment Fund       determinationincorporatesthe following 6 key&#13;
                                performancetargets:                                      andthe customersto monitor the&#13;
Core operationaldepartments        - Water wells operationaltime                         utility operations.&#13;
ofthe utility are established,       Water andwastewater samples meetingthe agreed       Preventiveand corrective&#13;
                                   ~&#13;
staffedwith requiredskills, and                                                          programsare preparedand&#13;
are functioningeffectively.        -standards of&#13;
                                     Volume     water billed to volumeof water           followed accordingto actionplan.&#13;
Adequate water supplyand           producedfrom all availablesources&#13;
sanitationinvestmentsare           - Numberof   hours all customersreceivewater each&#13;
implemented inGaza as per&#13;
annualProcurementPlans.            -day&#13;
                                     Wastewatereffluent quality meetsagreedstandards&#13;
                                   - Improvementsto annualgross revenuecollection.&#13;
&#13;
Component 3: Technical          PWA and CMWU issues Quarterly Monitoring and             Use Reports prepared by the&#13;
Assistance                      Evaluation reports                                       PWA and CMWU will:-&#13;
Institutionalandoperational     PWA monitorsenvironmentaland economicregulations         Enable sector stakeholdersto&#13;
performanceof PWA and           andtheir complianceto standards, as well as quality of   monitor the sector's performance&#13;
CMWU are improvedthrough        drinking water andwastewater effluent quality and        and its impact inthe environment.&#13;
targetedtechnicalassistance     disposal.&#13;
and performance-related                                                                  PWA's plans for mitigating&#13;
measurement.                    CMWU's Boardableto effectively oversee the               measures, andfor improvementin&#13;
 -    PMUmonitorsMC             company's operations and effectively interfaces with the adoptionlamendmentsand&#13;
      progress.                 sector's regulator(PWA).                                 enforcementof regulations.&#13;
 --   CMWU boardtrained&#13;
      PWA startedits sector&#13;
      regulatoryfunctions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 l7Components 1 and2 are designedto complementeachother andwill beimplementedbytheMCOperator.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            -23-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      3&#13;
      h 2         0&#13;
         m    2   2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ry&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
      0&#13;
      h  2        0&#13;
         m         13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
h&#13;
&amp;&#13;
&#13;
      0&#13;
      m  m&#13;
         2         0&#13;
          I 1303&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
d -    d&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                        I&#13;
 SERVICES                                                                  THREE      YEARLY TARGET&#13;
 APPENDIX         DESCRLeT1oNOF         PERFORMANCE STANDARD               YEAR&#13;
 SECTION#             SERVICE                                             TARGET YEAR 1I YEAR2  IYEAR3&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.1         InitialTransitionPlan&#13;
&#13;
SA 3,1(2)(~)'    Develop Initial         Quality OperatingStandard        100%   100%&#13;
               Transition Plan&#13;
                                         No later than 30 days after the&#13;
                                       ,Starting Date&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.2         BaseYear DataReport&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.2'          DevelopBaseYear         Quality OperatingStandard        100%&#13;
               Data Report&#13;
                                         No later than90 days after the&#13;
                                        Starting Date&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.3         ManagementInformationSystem Plan&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.3(1)'      * Preparea               Quality OperatingStandard        100%    100%&#13;
                Management&#13;
                InformationSystem        Nolater than 180days after the&#13;
                Plan                    StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.5(1)*        DevelopEmergency       Quality OperatingStandard        100%    100%&#13;
                ResponsePlan&#13;
                                         No later than 180days after the&#13;
                                        Starting Date&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.6          StaffTraining andDevelopmentProgram&#13;
&#13;
~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.6( l)(a)     Carry Out askills      Quality OperatingStandard&#13;
                assessmentof the&#13;
                operations staff         No later than 60 days after the&#13;
                                        StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.6(1)@)       Develop a Staff         Quality OperatingStandard       100%&#13;
                Training and&#13;
                DevelopmentProgram      * No later than 180days after the&#13;
                                        StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
SA3.7           Water andWastewaterSamplingandMonitoringProgram&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.7( 1)        Developa Water and    * Quality OperatingStandard       100%    100%&#13;
                WastewaterSampling&#13;
                and Monitoring          * In accordancewith the sampling&#13;
                Program                 requirements for water set out in&#13;
                                        Attachment 1 to the Performance&#13;
                                        Standards Appendix&#13;
&#13;
                                        * No later than 60 days after the&#13;
                                        StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
                                                     -27-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 SERVICES                                                                   THREE        YEARLYTARGET&#13;
 APPENDIX                       OF      PERFORMANCE STANDARD                YEAR&#13;
 SECTION#            SERVICE                                               TARGET   YEAR1   YEAR2  YEAR3&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.8        Equitable Distribution Plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.8'        Develop an Equitable      The average number of hours in    100%     IOOYO&#13;
              Distribution Plan         a day when water is supplied to&#13;
                                        all Customers at apressureof&#13;
                                        200 !&amp;a or more shall be equal to&#13;
                                        or greater than the average&#13;
                                        number of hours ina day when&#13;
                                        water was supplied to all&#13;
                                        Customers at a pressureof 200&#13;
                                        kea or more in the BaseYear&#13;
&#13;
                                         Quality Operating Standard&#13;
&#13;
                                         No later than 180days after the&#13;
                                        Starting Date&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.9        Safety PlanandReport&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.9(1)*     Conduct physical                                                     100%&#13;
              inspection o fthe&#13;
              Facilities                 No later than 30 days after the&#13;
                                        Starting Date&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.9(2)      Prepare Safety Plan       Quality OperatingStandard         100%     100%&#13;
              and Report&#13;
                                         No later than 60 days after the&#13;
                                        Starting Date&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.9(4) '    Providesecurity          * Quality OperatingStandard        100%     100%&#13;
              measures for the&#13;
              Facilities                  No later than 60 days after the&#13;
                                        Starting Date&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.9(5)      Develop                  9 Quality OperatingStandard        100%     30%     60%    100%&#13;
              Occupational Health&#13;
              and Safety Program          No later than 90 days after the&#13;
                                        Starting Date&#13;
                             .     -                                      I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA3.10(1)*     Develop an Industrial    * Quality Operating Standard       100%     0%      50%    100%&#13;
              Discharge Program&#13;
                                          No later than 90 days after the&#13;
                                        Starting Date&#13;
            I                         I                                   I        I       I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          The MaintenanceManagement&#13;
                                        Program shall establish&#13;
                                        maintenance schedules and&#13;
                                        programs that are consistent with&#13;
                                        manufacturers' recommendations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          -28-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 SERVICES                                                                    THREE      YEARLY TARGET&#13;
 APPENDIX                          OF  PERFORMANCE STANDARD                  YEAR&#13;
 SECTION#               SERVICE                                             TARGET  YEAR1  YEAR2   YEAR3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.12'          Developthe             QualityOperatingStandard           100%    100%&#13;
                 FinancialManagement&#13;
                 and CustomerServices    No later than 180days after the&#13;
                 Information Systems   StartingDate&#13;
                 Plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  I&#13;
SA 3.14(1)        Developthe Public      QualityOperatingStandard           100%    100%&#13;
                 EducationProgram&#13;
                                         No later thanthe last day of the&#13;
                                       first ContractYear&#13;
                I                     I                                    I       I      I       I&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.1&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.15(1) '      Developan Energy       Quality OperatingStandard          100%    100%&#13;
                 ManagementPlan&#13;
                                         No later than90 days after the&#13;
                                       StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.16(1)        Developthe             Quality OperatingStandard          100%    100%&#13;
                 Customer Service Plan&#13;
                                         No later than240 days after the&#13;
                                       StartingDate                        I       /       /       I&#13;
SA 3.16(2)'       Establishcustomer    * Quality OperatingStandard          100%    40%     100%&#13;
                 service centre and&#13;
                 computerisedsystem      No later than 240 days after the&#13;
                 for treatingCustomer  StartingDate&#13;
                 complaints&#13;
                1                     I                                    I       I      I       I&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.17&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.17'          Developthe             Quality OperatingStandard          100%    100%&#13;
                 Customer Service&#13;
                 Training Program        No later than the last day of the&#13;
                                       first ContractYear&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        -29-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  SERVICES                                                                   THREE       YEARLY TARGET&#13;
  APPENDIX      DESCRIPT1oN OF           PERFORMANCE STANDARD                YEAR&#13;
  SECTION#             SERVICE                                              TARGET   YEAR1   YEAR2   YEAR3&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.18        StandardOperating Procedures&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 3.18(1)      Prepare Standard          Quality OperatingStandard         100%&#13;
               OperatingProcedures&#13;
                                          No later than 180 days after the&#13;
                                        StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA3.18(4)       Provide training re:      Quality OperatingStandard         100%&#13;
               StandardOperating&#13;
               Procedures                 Operator shallcompletetraining&#13;
                                        for all Operations Staffno later&#13;
                                        than 90 days after the preparation&#13;
                                        or updatingofthe Standard&#13;
                                        OperatingProcedures&#13;
              I                        I                                                   I       I&#13;
&#13;
SA3.19&#13;
&#13;
                                       I&#13;
SA!.19(1) and   Prepare Operations      * Quality OperatingStandard         100%     100%&#13;
(2)            and Maintenance&#13;
               Manuals for all            No later than 180days after the&#13;
               Facilities, vehicles and StartingDate&#13;
               equipment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA3.19(5)'      Provide training re:      Quality OperatingStandard&#13;
               Operations &amp;&#13;
               MaintenanceManuals        9Operator shallcompletetraining&#13;
                                         for all Operations Staffno later&#13;
                                        than 90 days after the preparation&#13;
                                        or updatingof the Operations and&#13;
                                        MaintenanceManuals&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         n180days after the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    I      I       I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       I                                            I      I       I&#13;
SA4.1.          Procuregoods, works       Inaccordancewith the Capital      100%     30%     60%     100%&#13;
               and services under the   andOperatingInvestmentFund&#13;
               Capital and Operating    Appendix&#13;
               InvestmentFund&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Operate and maintain      Quality OperatingStandard         100%     100%    100%    100%&#13;
               raw water sources and&#13;
               protect wellheads and      The percentageof wellheads&#13;
               wellfields               andwell fields at which wellhead   I        I       l       l&#13;
              I                        Iana well rieiaprotection&#13;
                                            .    . . e . .  . .            I        I      I        I&#13;
&#13;
                                        measures are developed and fully&#13;
                                        implemented&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          -30-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 SERVICES                                                                 THREE          YEARLY TARGET&#13;
 APPENDIX       DESC"oN          OF   PERFORMANCE STANDARD                 YEAR&#13;
 SECTION#            SERVICE                                             TARGET    YEAR1    YEAR2    YEAR3&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.1.2       PumpingandTreatment of Water&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.1.2(f)     Chlorinatewater        The percentageo fwater            100%              100%      00%&#13;
                                     samples, taken inaccordancewith     innually&#13;
                                     the Water andWastewater&#13;
                                     Samplingand Monitoring              Vo less&#13;
                                     Program, that havea minimum         han98% in&#13;
                                      chlorine residualof 0.02 mgk       my period&#13;
                                      anda maximumchlorineresidual      if48 hours&#13;
                                     of0.5 mg/L&#13;
&#13;
                                       QualityOperatingStandard&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.1.2(i) *   Manageandabstract    - Inaccordancewithwell licences     100%      100%     100%    100%&#13;
               water from any raw    andregulatoryrequirements&#13;
               water sources          underApplicable Law&#13;
&#13;
                Managedesalination     Inaccordancewith the existing     100%      100%     100%    100%&#13;
               processes              operations andmaintenance&#13;
                                      manuals for the desalination&#13;
                                      facility as updatedinpreparation&#13;
                                     ofthe Operations and&#13;
                                      MaintenanceManuals.&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.1.3       Storage, SupplyandDi! ibu                o Custom&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.1.3(c)     Monitor water supply   The totalvolume ofwater billed    75%       70%      73%      75%&#13;
               anddistribution        to Customersas a percentageof&#13;
               systems for leaks and  the total of the volume ofwater&#13;
               water pressure         where the total volume of water&#13;
               measurement            equals,&#13;
&#13;
                                      (a) water producedat&#13;
                                           groundwater sources, as&#13;
                                           measuredby the water&#13;
                                           meters at the wellheads; plus&#13;
&#13;
                                      (b) water receivedinbulk supply&#13;
                                           fromMekeroth,as measured&#13;
                                           by the CMWU's bulk water&#13;
                                           meter; plus&#13;
&#13;
                                      (c) water suppliedby the&#13;
                                           desalinationplant, as&#13;
                                           measuredby the desalination&#13;
                                           plant's bulk water meter&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.1.3(d)     Monitor andmaintain    The averagenumberofhours          10hours   6 hours  8 hours  10hours&#13;
               the availabilityofthe  each day in a ContractYear when    per day   per day  per day  Per &amp;Y&#13;
               supply ofwater         all Customers receive water at a&#13;
                                      minimumpressureof200 kPa&#13;
                                      anda maximumpressureo f600&#13;
                                      kPaas measuredat monitoring&#13;
                                      pointsdeterminedby the&#13;
                                      EquitableDistributionPlan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       -31-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                          YEARLYTAR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.1.3(e)(i)    Carry out all new      The installationo fnew service      100%     00%    100%  100%&#13;
                water service           connections shall be completed&#13;
                connections.            no later than 7 days after the&#13;
                                        Customer submits a complete,&#13;
                                        and CMWU approved,&#13;
                                        application for a new service&#13;
                                        connection&#13;
&#13;
                                         The pipe o f the service&#13;
                                        connection shall have a diameter&#13;
                                        greater than or equal to 20 mm&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.1.30)        Carry out water main    Quality OperatingStandard          100%            100%&#13;
                flushing                                                                    I&#13;
                                          Flushing shall be camed out for           )%&#13;
                                        all water mains once every two&#13;
                                        Contract Years&#13;
&#13;
                  Carry out water main   Quality OperatingStandard           100%    3%      0%    100%&#13;
                swabbing&#13;
                                          Swabbingshall be canied out&#13;
                                        for all water mains two times&#13;
                                        duringthe term o fthe Contract,&#13;
                                        with the first swabbing to be&#13;
                                        carriedout no later than the end&#13;
                                        o fthe second Contract Year and&#13;
                                        the second swabbing to be carried&#13;
                                        out duringthe last ContractYear&#13;
&#13;
SA&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.2(a)(i)      Carry out all new       All new service connections        100%    100%    100%   100%&#13;
                service connections.    shall be completed no later than 7&#13;
                                        days after the Customer submits a&#13;
                                        complete, and C M W U approved&#13;
                                        application, for a new service&#13;
                                        connection, including CMWU&#13;
                                        approval&#13;
                                                                                     ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          The pipe ofthe service&#13;
                                        connectionshall have a diameter&#13;
                                        greater than or equal to 100 mm&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.2(c)         Monitor for and         The percentage o f flow            86%     80%     83%    86%&#13;
                respondto reports o f   blockage complaints where the&#13;
                flow blockages          response time is less than 2 hours&#13;
                                        after the Operator receives and&#13;
                                        logs the first Customer report o f a&#13;
                                        flow blockage&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.2(g)         Manage, operate and     The percentage for measuring       97%      97%    97%    97%&#13;
                maintain wastewater     wastewater effluent quality, as          L&#13;
                treatment facilities    calculated by the formula set out&#13;
                                        inAttachment 2 to this&#13;
                                        Performance Standards Chart,&#13;
                                        shall not be less than 97 percent&#13;
&#13;
SA 5.2(i) *       Carry out septic tank * No later than one day after a      100%     100%   100%   100%&#13;
                evacuations             Customer request for a septic tank&#13;
                                        evacuation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         -32-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 SA 5.2(1) *      Carry out close-          *The inspectionshall be carried      100%    100%  100%&#13;
                 circuit inspectionsof      out no later than the endof the&#13;
                 the stomwater and          secondContract Year on all&#13;
                 wastewater Facilities      sewers havingadiameter of at&#13;
                                            least 200 mm&#13;
&#13;
 SA 6.1          GeneralMaintenanceServices&#13;
               I                         I&#13;
 SA 6.1.          Cany out all                Inaccordancewith the&#13;
                 corrective and             MaintenanceManagement&#13;
                 preventive                 Program&#13;
                 maintenance programs&#13;
                 for Facilities, vehicles&#13;
                 and equipment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 SA7.1. [(a) *    Prepareand update           Quality OperatingStandard&#13;
                 Facilities Data Base&#13;
                                              No later thanthe last day of the&#13;
                                            first Contract Year&#13;
&#13;
 SA7.1,1@)        PrepareInitial              Quality OperatingStandard&#13;
                 Condition Survey&#13;
                                            * No later than 90 days after the&#13;
                                            Facilities DataBaseis finalised&#13;
&#13;
 SA7.l.l(~)       Complete physical           Quality OperatingStandard&#13;
                 inspectionofthe&#13;
                 Facilities                   No later,than 60 days after the&#13;
                                            StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 SA 7.1.2~)*      Prepare Final               Quality Operating Standard         100%    0%    0%      100%&#13;
                 Condition Survey&#13;
                                              No later than the last day of the&#13;
                                            seventhContract Year&#13;
&#13;
 SA7.1.2(2)        Preparearemediation        Quality OperatingStandard          100%    0%    0%      100%&#13;
                 plan&#13;
                                              No later than 60 days after the&#13;
                                            Final ConditionSurvey is&#13;
                                            finalised&#13;
&#13;
                                           1&#13;
 SA 7.2          FinalTransitionPlan&#13;
I                                                                                                    I&#13;
                I                         I                                     I       I             I&#13;
 SA 7.2(1) *       Develop Final              Quality Operating Standard&#13;
                 Transition Plan                                                                 O%    loo%&#13;
                                              N o later thanone year prior to&#13;
                                            the EndDate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 SA 7.3.2(2)       Procure items from         Inaccordancewith the Capital       100%    30%     60%   100%&#13;
                 the Capital and            and OperatingInvestmentFund&#13;
                 OperatingInvestment        Appendix&#13;
                 Fund&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              -33-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                   DESCRIPT1oNoF                                              THREE        YEARLY TARGET&#13;
                       SERVICE         PERFORMANCE STANDARD                   YEAR   -&#13;
                                                                             TARGET   YEAR1   YEAR2&#13;
                                                                                              I       YEAR3&#13;
&#13;
                Billings andCollection&#13;
&#13;
                  Collect amounts due   Percentageof gross collected         75%      5%&#13;
                to the CMWU            revenues,Revenue Collection&#13;
                                       Efficiency.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The RevenueCollection&#13;
                                       Efficiency is calculatedin&#13;
                                       accordancewith Attachment 3 to&#13;
                                       the PerformanceStandards&#13;
                                       Appendix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 8.I.1(2)(b)    Develop collection    Quality OperatingStandard            100%     100%&#13;
                procedures                                                                    --r&#13;
                                        No later than 30 days after the&#13;
                                       StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 8.1.1(2)(c)*   Identifyandrecord     Inaccordancewithcollection           100%     100%    00%     100%&#13;
                outstandingaccounts    proceduresdevelopedby the&#13;
                andtake collection     Operatoras approvedby the&#13;
                measures               CMWU                                                   I&#13;
SA 8.1.2&#13;
                                      I                                    I&#13;
SA 8.1.2(d)       Develop three-year    Quality OperatingStandard            100%     100%&#13;
                programfor the                                                                -7-&#13;
                calibrationof the        No laterthan 180days after the&#13;
                Customermeterstock     StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 8.1.2(g) *     Developprogramto       Quality OperatingStandard           100%     100%&#13;
                estimateconsumption&#13;
                                         No later than 180 davs after the&#13;
                                         .. ..........     __&#13;
                                                             2 ------- ----&#13;
                                       StartingDate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 8.1.2(1)*     * Carry out routine   * Quality'OperatingStandard           30,000   10,000  10,000  30,000&#13;
                replacementof meters&#13;
                                         The Operator shall repair or&#13;
                                       replace at least 10,000 Customer&#13;
                                       meters during eachContractYear&#13;
                                      I                                     I&#13;
&#13;
                      merService Program&#13;
                                                                                              I&#13;
SA!. 1.3@) and    Receiveandhandle       Quality OperatingStandard           100%     80%     90%     100%&#13;
(c)             Customercomplaints,&#13;
                inquiries andrequests    The percentageof Customer&#13;
                                       queries, complaints andresponses&#13;
                                       that mustberesolvedno later&#13;
                                       than 15 days after the query,&#13;
                                       complaint or requestis first&#13;
                                       loggedby the Operator&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              I&#13;
SA?.l(l) and       SubmitQuarterly       Quality OperatingStandard           100%     100%    100%    100%&#13;
(2)             Reports&#13;
                                         No later than 15days after the&#13;
                                       endo f each90 day period&#13;
                                       (quarter) in a Contract Year&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        -34-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 SERVICES                                                         THREE     YEARLY TARGET&#13;
 APPENDIX  DESCRIPT1oNoF PERFORMANCE STANDARD                     YEAR&#13;
 SECTION#      SERVICE                                           TARGET YEAR^  "2      YEAR^&#13;
&#13;
SA9.2      Annual Report&#13;
                            ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SA 9.2'    Submit annualreport   QualityOperatingStandard        100%   100%   100%    100%&#13;
&#13;
                                 No laterthan 30 days after the&#13;
                                end of eachContractYear&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               -35-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                 ANNEX 2: DETAILEDDESCRIPTIONPROJECTCOMPONENTS&#13;
                                                      OF&#13;
&#13;
The proposed project has three main components:&#13;
&#13;
       1)   Employment o f a Private Sector Operator under a Management Contract (MC)&#13;
            which includes a fixed fee plus a performance-based incentive fee (US$8.6&#13;
            million, or 37% o ftotalproject costs);&#13;
&#13;
      2)    A Capital and Operating Investment Fund (US$12 million, or 52% of total&#13;
            project costs); and&#13;
&#13;
       3)   Support for Institutional Reform and Capacity Building, including support to&#13;
            fully establish the CMWU as well as to strengthen the PWA inits function as&#13;
            sector regulator (US$2.3 million, or 11%o ftotal project costs).&#13;
&#13;
Component 1. Employmentof a PrivateSector Operatingunder a Management&#13;
                  Contract(US$8.6 millionequivalent,37% oftotalprojectcosts)&#13;
&#13;
This component includes support for the employment o f a Private Sector Operator under a MC,&#13;
competitively bid under Bank procurement guidelines. In general, the Operator will ensure the&#13;
functional establishment o f the C M W U in Gaza, improved management o f the water and&#13;
wastewater systems, as well as an improvement in the operation and quality o f water and&#13;
wastewater services inGaza. For the provision o f these services, the Operator will be paid a fixed&#13;
management fee o f US$6.2 million and a performance-based incentive fee with a ceiling o f&#13;
US$2.4 million.&#13;
&#13;
The Management Fee: The management fixed fee will be paid to the Operator to provide for&#13;
mobilization and operating costs during the period o f the contract and finance the necessary staff&#13;
to implementthe service improvement program.&#13;
&#13;
The Incentive Fee: The incentive fee will depend on the achievement o f the performance targets&#13;
specified inthe MC. The maximum amount that can be paid as an incentive fee for meeting the&#13;
specified performance targets over the duration o f the contract has been fixed at US$2.4 million,&#13;
i.e., an annual maximum o fUS$O.8 million.&#13;
&#13;
The details of the above arrangements are speciJiedin the Manaaement Contract, which already&#13;
has been competitively tenderedand signedwith the lowest evaluated bidder.&#13;
&#13;
Main Tasksof the Operator&#13;
&#13;
The Operator will assume full responsibility for the management, operation and maintenance of&#13;
water and wastewater services in Gaza, including management o f seconded personnel and&#13;
associated wages, salaries and benefits, and administrative facilities and services necessary to&#13;
oversee the management and direct operations o f the various water and wastewater systems,&#13;
including source withdrawal, treatment, pumping, and distribution systems, wastewater&#13;
collection, pumping, treatment and disposal. More specifically, the Operator will:&#13;
&#13;
     1. Manage the process o f transition from a collection o f separate municipal water and&#13;
         wastewater systems in the service area to a single water and wastewater utility. This&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -36-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    would entail a review of the status of the transition and restructuring process, and the&#13;
    preparation of an action plan with respect to any transition activities that remain to be&#13;
    completed.&#13;
&#13;
2. Manage this transition andrestructuring process, assist CMWU inliaisingwith municipal&#13;
    authorities and ensuring that:     (i)all CMWU's revenuesare allocated to CMWU's&#13;
    accounts, (ii)  operations staff is paid appropriately, and (iii) existing continuity o f&#13;
                                                                    the&#13;
    water andwastewater servicesto customers is maintained.&#13;
&#13;
3. As part o f the transition process, develop a human resources plan for the integration of&#13;
    the municipal workforce into CMWU, and aplanfor the consolidation and rationalization&#13;
    of facilities and inventories, as well as a number of functions, such as administration,&#13;
    financial, operations, maintenance, repair andrehabilitation.&#13;
&#13;
4. Manage the operation o f water facilities, including water resources, pumping, treatment,&#13;
    storage, supply and distribution of water to customers, including developing,&#13;
    implementing and managing a comprehensive maintenance management program for&#13;
    these facilities.&#13;
&#13;
5. Manage the operation o f wastewater and storm water facilities, including all waste and&#13;
    storm water sewers and collectors, the pumping and transportation of raw sewage to the&#13;
    treatment plants, as well as the treatment and disposal of treated effluent. The Operator&#13;
    will develop and manage a comprehensive maintenance management program for these&#13;
    facilities.&#13;
&#13;
6. Plan and manage the implementation of programs to be carried out under the Capital and&#13;
    Operating Investment Fund.&#13;
&#13;
7. Develop and manage capacity building programs to train and advance the skills of&#13;
    CMWU personnel. The Operator will carry out a skills assessment of the operations&#13;
    staff, and based on that develop and implement a comprehensive training program that&#13;
    includes a review as well as recommendations for future development of existing in-&#13;
    house and external training capacity andfacilities.&#13;
&#13;
8. Carry out all management, financial and administrative responsibilities related to the&#13;
    CMWU, as well as manage all billings collections, customer relations and service&#13;
    functions related to the customers inthe service area.&#13;
&#13;
9. Provide ongoing assistance and advice to the CMWU on all matters related to the&#13;
    CMWU, the services, and any requests for information or advice from the PWA or&#13;
    citizen committees with respect to the CMWU, its facilities or services offered.&#13;
&#13;
10. Prepare the associated reports with appropriate analysis and action plans for the&#13;
    management and implementation of the above-mentioned activities. (These reports are&#13;
    specified indetail inthe Services - Appendix 3 of the Management Contract )&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            -37-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Component2. CapitalandOperatingInvestmentFund(US$12.0 million&#13;
                     equivalent,52% of totalprojectcosts)&#13;
&#13;
This Fundwill provide financing for the purchase o f materials, supplies and equipment that are&#13;
required to rehabilitate the water and wastewater infrastructure in the service area, and to&#13;
enhance the efficient operation, maintenance and administration o f the water and wastewater&#13;
systems in the service area. In order to provide the Operator with the flexibility to direct the&#13;
achievements of performance standards and reduce procurement concerns, the Fund is&#13;
considered to be under the control of the Operator, subject to the approval o f an annual&#13;
procurement plan. Some activities have already been identified for financing under this Fund, as&#13;
follows:&#13;
&#13;
Summary:&#13;
&#13;
    Item   Description                                                                    FinancingRequired&#13;
                                                                                               (US$m)&#13;
&#13;
    1.      Repairandrehabilitationofreservoirs                                                 $0.94&#13;
    11.&#13;
    ...     Correctionofsafety deficiencies                                                     $0.12&#13;
    111.    Replacementof existingwells, drilling of new wells                                  $1.17&#13;
    iv.     Replacementof water mainsor sewer piping                                            $2.57&#13;
    V.     Purchaseof GIS                                                                       $0.60&#13;
    vi.     Replacementof water andwastewater connections                                       $1.46&#13;
    vii.   Effluent disposalandre-use facilities                                                $0.76&#13;
    v111.&#13;
      ...  Repairandreplacementof water meters                                                  $0.94&#13;
    ix.     Repair, maintenanceand replacement ofelectromechanical equipment                    $0.70&#13;
            Supplyof chemicalsanddosingpumps for water andwastewatertreatment and&#13;
    X.      disinfection                                                                        $1.00&#13;
&#13;
    xi.     Purchasesystems hardwareandsoftware                                                 $0.59&#13;
&#13;
    xii.    Incrementalcosts, includingfuel andelectricity, for the water andwastewater&#13;
            facilities                                                                          $0.40&#13;
&#13;
    xiii. . Capacity building programincludingtraining sessions locally andoverseascosts&#13;
            andtravel allowances                                                                $0.15&#13;
&#13;
    xiv.    Constructionnew administrativefacilities                                            $0.60&#13;
            TOTAL                                                                               s12.00&#13;
&#13;
The Operator will review these activities andmake changes as appropriate incoordination with&#13;
PWA.&#13;
&#13;
Summary Description of Activities IdentiJiedfor Financing under Fund&#13;
&#13;
Repair and rehabilitation of reservoirs: A survey o f reservoirs carried out by PWA and financed&#13;
by the European Investment Bank (EIB) recommended that 20 existing reservoirs be&#13;
rehabilitated. EIB financed the rehabilitation o f 10 reservoirs, and the project will finance the&#13;
rehabilitation of the remaining 10.&#13;
&#13;
Correction of safety dejkiencies: For the past 20 years, very little has been done in Gaza to&#13;
ensure safety of workers and the overall population. The financing covers the purchase of&#13;
equipment andtraining requiredto ensure employee and facilities' safety.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          -38-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Replacement of existing wells, drilling of new wells: This activity i s needed to address the&#13;
deteriorating quality o f the water being provided by existing wells, due to increasing levels o f&#13;
salinity and nitrate concentration which exceeds the WHO standards.              The work includes&#13;
development and implementationo f well field protectionmeasures.&#13;
&#13;
Replacement water mains or sewer piping: PWA has identified the critical main transmission&#13;
lines and collectors that needto be replaced. The replacement is expected to yield improvements&#13;
inthe quality ofwater suppliedaswell as network efficiency.&#13;
&#13;
Purchase of GIs: The purchase o f these systems is recommended to enable the Operator to&#13;
control the network from a remote location and quickly identify leakage and network efficiency&#13;
issues. Given the movement restrictions currently in place and the difficulty o f movement, this&#13;
system becomes even more critical.&#13;
&#13;
Replacement of water and wastewater connections: This activity involves regular maintenance&#13;
work to replace old connections and add new customers.&#13;
&#13;
,?fluent disposal and re-usefacilities: The use o f the treated effluent as non-conventional water&#13;
resource is recommended in order to release stress on the potable water resources. This activity&#13;
entails the preparationo f the required facilities for effluent storage and transfer to the location o f&#13;
re-use and/or disposal.&#13;
&#13;
Repair and replacement of water meters: The repair and replacement o f meters represent&#13;
substantial investments and are essential to improving network efficiency, reducing losses, and&#13;
increasing water availability to consumers. District meters, with pressure gauges, are important&#13;
to improving network pressure, and are needed to finalize the metering o f network districts inthe&#13;
Gaza Strip. In addition, calibration and replacement o f 30,000 customer meters will be carried&#13;
out duringthe project implementation.&#13;
&#13;
Repair, maintenance and replacement of electromechanical equipment: The financing under this&#13;
category will cover the emergency replacement needs and the implementation o f a preventive&#13;
maintenance program for facilities, equipment and vehicles, which will result in an overall&#13;
improvement o f system efficiency.&#13;
&#13;
Supply of chemicals and dosing pumps for water and wastewater treatment and disinfection:&#13;
This will enable the supply o fvarious chemicals and dosing pumpsrequired to operate water and&#13;
wastewater facilities. Currently, chlorine i s used as a disinfectant and other chemicals are used&#13;
to operate small scale desalinationplants.&#13;
&#13;
Purchase systems hardware and software:          As the C M W U is being functionally established,&#13;
there will be a need to implement various computerized systems such as inventory control,&#13;
customer services, billing and collections, financial management, etc.          This component will&#13;
cover bothhardware and software costs.&#13;
&#13;
Incremental costs, including fuel and electricity, for the water and wastewater facilities:&#13;
Currently, municipalities do not pay for 100 percent o f their electricity and fuel bills. Once they&#13;
are integrated within the CMWU, this will create an initial deficit that needs to be compensated&#13;
for inorder for the utility to operate ina sustainable manner.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -39-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Capacity buildingprogram including training sessions locally and overseas: Staff training i s an&#13;
essential element for the good performance o f the utility. The Operator will be responsible,&#13;
through the MC, to carry out a comprehensive training program in order to build sustainable&#13;
humancapacity withinthe utility. The program will include training plumbersand electricians,&#13;
material for computer training, training sessions abroad for key staff, professionaltrainers, etc.&#13;
&#13;
Construction new administrative facilities: One o f the objectives o f the project is to fully&#13;
operationalize the C M W U through the merger o f the water departments o f all Gaza&#13;
municipalities and village councils. This activity entails the construction o f facilities required to&#13;
accommodate the C M W U andits staff.&#13;
&#13;
Component3. Support for Institutional Reform and Capacity Building Technical&#13;
                 Assistance/Advisory Services for CMWU and PWA (US$2.3 million&#13;
                 equivalent, 11% of totalprojectcosts)&#13;
&#13;
This component provides support for building the capacity o f i)the CMWU (including PMU)&#13;
and ii)PWA. It is divided into packages as shown below.&#13;
&#13;
Capacity Building for CMWU (US$O.l million): This package will enable the C M W U to&#13;
effectively implement its business plan, and to work under the regulatory environment o f the&#13;
PWA. The subcomponents include:&#13;
&#13;
i. buildingtheCMWUBoard'scapacitytoprovideoversighttotheorganization;&#13;
&#13;
ii. buildingthe capacity of the CMWU to manage and implement its capital investment&#13;
    program and strengthen its legal capabilities.&#13;
&#13;
iii.preparingbiddingdocuments deemed necessary to enable the CMWUto carry out its&#13;
    responsibilities at the end o fthis MC.&#13;
&#13;
iv. buildingcapacity o fthe CMWUto interface effectively with PWA, the sector regulator&#13;
&#13;
Capacity Buildingfor PMU (US$l.l million): This package will help the C M W U to finance the&#13;
project management unit (PMU).          This unit is expected to mainly oversee the day to day&#13;
implementation o f the M C and to facilitate its implementation. The PMU will be composed o f a&#13;
multidisciplinary team including the expertise in water and wastewater engineering, financial&#13;
management, procurement, site supervisionandproject management.&#13;
&#13;
Employment of Auditor (US$O.7 million): This package will cover the expenses o f a neutral&#13;
independent auditor who will perform a technical audit on all services carried out by the&#13;
Operator. The auditor i s expected to report on the achievements o f the Operator against the&#13;
services and performances requiredto be achieved inaccordance with the MC. The audit will be&#13;
performed semi-annually while incentives will be paid and settled annually.               Besides the&#13;
technical audit, a financial audit needs to be performed annually to audit the accounts o f the&#13;
C M W U inrelation to the implementation o fthe MC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -40-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Capacity Buildingfor PWA (US$0.4 million): This package focuses on five priority tasks for&#13;
PWA to develop specific capacity clustered around regulation of water abstraction, pollution&#13;
control and improved management o f water resources and service delivery to customers in the&#13;
West Bank and Gaza inan efficient and effective manner. These tasks build on and complement&#13;
the ongoing and more comprehensive Institutional Capacity Building Program funded by the&#13;
Governments o f Norway and the Netherlands. The objective ofthis Program is to develop PWA&#13;
into a strong and effective regulator of the water sector, and as such to contribute to the long-&#13;
term sustainable development ofthe sector.&#13;
&#13;
The proposed capacity building measures under this project fall under the following broad&#13;
headings:&#13;
&#13;
i. DevelopmentoftoolstohelpPWAundertakeenvironmental,economicanddrinkingwater&#13;
    quality regulations. This is in particular related to the set up of the licensing scheme,&#13;
    empowering tariff reforms and price review and initiate the practices in drinking water&#13;
    quality inspection and the monitoring o f wastewater treatment and disposal practices from&#13;
    bothenvironmentaland health perspectives.&#13;
&#13;
ii.BuildingorganizationalstrengthwithinPWAthroughtrainingandprovisionofadvisors.&#13;
&#13;
iii.IdentificationofoptimalindustrystructureintheWBG.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              -41-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                               ANNEX3: PROJECT            COSTSANDFINANCING&#13;
                              (US$millions including taxes and contingencies)"&#13;
&#13;
  ProiectComDonent                                                     I Totalcost I      Financine       I&#13;
                                                                                    GovernmentI  TF Grant&#13;
  COMPONENT 1      -Performance-basedManagementContract                                       I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   TOTAL PROJECT COST                                                          22.90       2.90       20.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
l8Physicalandpricecontingenciesare appliedtoactivitiesfinancedunderitemc aboveandareintheorderofapproximately&#13;
15% of basecost for respectiveactivities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        -42-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
         ANNEX 4: FINANCIALMANAGEMENT              ANDDISBURSEMENT      ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
Project financial management (FM) responsibilities will be entrusted with the PMU that will&#13;
report initially to the C M W U Board until the organizational structure o f the C M W U is&#13;
functionally established by the M C Operator. The P M U will build on core competencies inthe&#13;
current project management unit which was set up withinthe P W A and built up and maintained&#13;
since 1997 and is currently implementing the Gaza portion o f the Southern Area Water and&#13;
Sanitation Improvement Project (SAWSIP). The decision to move the existing PMU from P W A&#13;
to the C M W U and utilize it to undertake the financial management responsibilities for this&#13;
project is due to the fact that management contract Operator, as part o f its performance&#13;
obligations, will build adequate finance department at the CMWU. This finance department,&#13;
when established, will be supported by the PMU and will be trained on project financial&#13;
management and reporting.       The P M U has in place an adequate computerized financial&#13;
management system, documented financial management procedures and employs qualified&#13;
financial staff.&#13;
&#13;
TheFMSystem at PWA&#13;
&#13;
The FM system at PWA was established under the WSSP and was subsequently re-assessed and&#13;
strengthened under the on-going SAWSIP. Most weaknesses identified in the assessment were&#13;
properly addressed by PWA. Accordingly, the PWA has in place an acceptable FM system&#13;
including accounting,    internal control, record management system, and external audit&#13;
arrangements.    Internal auditing and reporting at project and corporate levels are still to be&#13;
strengthened. In general, the FM system is capable o f meeting the operational and information&#13;
needs o f the PWA. For the project purpose, the PMU establishedfor the first Gaza project will&#13;
be relocated to the CMWU and take charge o f the project implementation including financial&#13;
management.&#13;
&#13;
The FMSystem at the PMU&#13;
&#13;
The PMU has inplace and adequate FM system acceptable to IDA including proper segregation&#13;
of duties under formal organization structure anddetailed FMpolicies andprocedures. Accounts&#13;
are computerized and are carried on accrual basis as required by international accounting&#13;
standards. The P M U employs a qualified FM Manager who is supported by qualified staff,&#13;
Also, the Coastal Water Utility will designate a finance officer to be part o fthe PMU.&#13;
&#13;
RiskAssessment&#13;
&#13;
The inherent risk i s considered substantial due to the new establishment of the C M W U and&#13;
accordingly lack of well-established finance department.          The control risk is considered&#13;
moderate since the PMU, with all its expertise and established experience with monitoring&#13;
private Operators, will be relocated to the utility to implement the project. The project risks are&#13;
as follow:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -43-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   I Inherent          S    1 As of now, the utility i s not yet operational and thus no finance&#13;
     Risk                     department is inplace.&#13;
&#13;
     Control          M       The PMU, to be relocatedfrom the PWA to report to the Board&#13;
     Risk                     of the CMWUto monitor the M C Operator. Payment final&#13;
                              authorization will remainwith the CMWU Board.&#13;
     Detection        M       The PMU, with its proper structure, will beresponsible for all&#13;
     Risk                     financial managementaspects. This would abatethe risk in&#13;
                              detecting errors and irregularities in atimely manner.&#13;
     Overall           S      The PMUwill undertake FMresponsibilities, while final&#13;
     Risk                     authorization to pay rests with the CMWU. CMWU does not&#13;
                              have yet a finance department. However, the M C Operator will&#13;
                              be responsible to establish finance department inaccordance&#13;
                              with international codes o fpracticefor utilities.&#13;
   H:High              S: Substantial           M:Moderate&#13;
&#13;
Mainfinancial managementrisks are:&#13;
&#13;
   Lack o f a finance departmentat the CMWU&#13;
&#13;
   Lack o f cooperation between different stakeholders; CMWU management, PMU, CM, and&#13;
    PWA&#13;
&#13;
These risks are mitigated by clearly describing the roles and responsibilities o f the involved&#13;
parties in the clauses of the MC, the CMWU by-laws and the Water Law. However, the&#13;
multilateral involvement to the project remains an issue.&#13;
&#13;
Project Accounting and Records Management&#13;
&#13;
Project accounts will be maintained on accrual basis following international accounting&#13;
standards by the PMU. Project annual financial statements consisting of: project balance sheet;&#13;
statement of resources of funds andtheir uses; and, summary of expenditures by activity reports&#13;
will bepreparedon accrual basisby the PMUandreviewed andapproved bythe CMWU Board.&#13;
Upon project completion all records will be kept at for at least one year after the submission of&#13;
the last audit report to IDA. The PMU will assist the utility's finance department on project&#13;
financial management.&#13;
&#13;
Auditing&#13;
&#13;
The project financial statements will be annually audited by qualified independent auditor&#13;
acceptable to IDA under terms of reference acceptable to IDA. The audit will be conducted in&#13;
accordance with international standards on auditing and will cover financing provided by all&#13;
sources. The audit report would be submittedto IDA within six months of year end.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   -44-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FinancialMonitoringReports(FMR)&#13;
&#13;
The PMUwill prepare quarterly FMRwhich consist o fthe following:&#13;
&#13;
(i)    statement o f cash receipt and expenditures for the period and cumulatively along with&#13;
       explanations o f significant variances between budgeted and actual amounts, and cash&#13;
       balances of the project;&#13;
&#13;
(ii)   statement on procurement of goods and works below the stated prior review threshold;&#13;
       and,&#13;
&#13;
(iii)  physical progress containing actual progress on project implementation.&#13;
&#13;
The format and contents o f the FMR have been agreed to during negotiation. The P M U and&#13;
C M W U will be responsible for reviewing and submission the FMR to IDA within 45 days after&#13;
eachquarter-end.&#13;
&#13;
Flow of Funds&#13;
&#13;
IDA funds will be channeled through a Special Account (SA) to be established underthe Central&#13;
Treasury Account inthe name o f C M W U for the project. To simplify the disbursement process,&#13;
the Ministry of Finance will allow the PMU to withdraw funds directly from the SA, thus the&#13;
P M U will be the sole signatory on the payments made from the SA.            The PMU will be&#13;
responsible for preparingand signing the Withdrawal Applications and have them co-signed by&#13;
the Ministry o f Finance within five business days.      The Ministry o f Finance will review&#13;
supporting documents of Withdrawal Applications on ex-post basis except for the last&#13;
Withdrawal Application which would be made on ex-ante basis.&#13;
&#13;
Disbursement&#13;
&#13;
Disbursements will be based on transactional disbursement methods including replenishments to&#13;
the SA and reimbursements with full documentation or statements o f expenditure (SOE)&#13;
procedure, direct payments, and special commitments issued against letters o f credit will be&#13;
followed under the project. The limits o f expenditures amounts that can be claimed under SOE&#13;
are (i) costing less than US$200,000 per contract, (ii) costing less than US$200,000&#13;
      goods                                                  works&#13;
per contract, (iii)consulting firms costing less than US$lOO,OOO per contract and individual&#13;
consultants costing less than US$50,000 per contract, (iv) training expenses, and (v) incremental&#13;
operating expenses.&#13;
&#13;
VAT Control&#13;
&#13;
The Country Financing Parameters for the West Bank and Gaza call for financing o f Value&#13;
Added Tax and other reasonable taxes.        Accordingly the grant will cover contract prices&#13;
including taxes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              -45-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Supervision&#13;
&#13;
Due to the risk embedded in the project, the project will be allocated between 2-3 weeks of&#13;
financial management supervision resources.       Financial management supervision will be&#13;
conducted in accordance with the IDA guidelines and procedures by financial management&#13;
specialist, financial management analyst and disbursement officer. The project will be visited&#13;
approximately quarterly.    Financial management supervision mission reports will be made,&#13;
through the project team leader, available to other stakeholders. Findings will be followed up&#13;
withthe PMU, C M W , PSCandthe International Relations Department at MOF.&#13;
&#13;
Role of the Operator&#13;
&#13;
The M C Operator is required under its contract (Section 3.3, Services Appendix of the&#13;
Management Contract) to establish a complete financial management systemwithin the CMWU&#13;
by functionally creating a Finance Departmentwith adequate financial managementcontrols and&#13;
information system as well as billing and collection system. The PMU will assist the Finance&#13;
Department on project financial management. IDA will follow up on establishing the Finance&#13;
Departmentbythe Operator as partof its supervision.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              -46-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           ANNEX5: PROCUREMENTARRANGEMENTS&#13;
A.      General&#13;
&#13;
Procurement for the proposed project would be carried out inaccordance with the World Bank's&#13;
"Guidelines: Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" dated May 2004; and&#13;
"Guidelines: Selection and Employment o f Consultants by World Bank Borrowers" dated May&#13;
2004, and the provisions stipulated in the Grant Agreement. The general description o f various&#13;
items under different expenditure category is described below. For each contract to be financed&#13;
by the Grant, the different procurement methods or consultant selection methods, the need for&#13;
pre-qualification, estimated costs, prior review requirements, and time frame, would be&#13;
stipulated in the Procurement Plan, which would be developed by the Operator 30 days before&#13;
the end o f year. The Procurement Plan will be submitted to the C M W U Board o f Directors for&#13;
review and approval withinthe framework prescribed inthe MC. The procurement planand any&#13;
update thereof are subject to Bank's review and no objection. The Procurement Plan will be&#13;
updated at least annually or as required to reflect the actual project implementation needs and&#13;
improvements ininstitutional capacity.&#13;
&#13;
Procurement of Works and Goods: The Operator will have the overall responsibility with&#13;
respect to the procurement o f goods and works. The contracts for works and goods will be&#13;
included in the procurement plan to be developed by the Operator. Goods and works will be&#13;
procured in accordance with the Bank procedures and Guidelines, using the Bank's standard&#13;
bidding and evaluation documents. These contracts would be financed        from the Capital and&#13;
Operating Investment Fund.&#13;
&#13;
Selectionof Consultants:This would include:&#13;
&#13;
    0   Selectionandemployment o f technical and financial auditors.&#13;
&#13;
    0   Selection o f individual consultants to supportPMU, C M W U and PWA.&#13;
&#13;
The selection o f consultants will follow the Bank's Guidelines using the Bank's relevant&#13;
standarddocuments.&#13;
&#13;
Operational Costs: the operational costs under the Capital and Operating Investment Fund, to&#13;
be financed by the project, will be procuredinaccordance with the relevant Bank Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
B.      Assessment of the agency's capacityto implementprocurement&#13;
&#13;
Procurement activities will be carried out by the Operator of the MC. The Operator is staffed by&#13;
aproject director, technicalstaff and administration andfinancial staff andthe Procurement unit&#13;
is staffed by one procurement officer.&#13;
&#13;
Most o f the issues/risks concerning the procurement component for implementation of the&#13;
project have been identified and include: a) lack of standard N C B package, and b) security&#13;
conditions that may impact bid submission, contract management and completion o f projects.&#13;
The agreed corrective measures are the use o f Bank's standard bidding documents until the&#13;
national standard bidding documents are prepared as a follow up o f the Country Procurement&#13;
Assessment Review recommendations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -47-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Since the Operator has the overall responsibility with respect to procurement implementation, it&#13;
i s has been agreedthat the Central Tender Committee will limit its role to the review, through the&#13;
mechanismof the PSC, of the annual Procurement Plans on which the Operator's work will be&#13;
based.&#13;
&#13;
The overall projectrisk for procurement is Average.&#13;
&#13;
C.       ProcurementPlan&#13;
&#13;
The Operator shall develop annual Procurement Plans 30 days before the end of each year. The&#13;
Operator will submit the said plan to CMWU Board of Directors and to the PMU for approval.&#13;
The plan will be in compliance with the Bank Guidelines and will be subject to the Bank's&#13;
review and "no objection."     The Operator will update the Procurement Plan annually; the&#13;
updatedversion will be subject to Bank's approval as well.&#13;
&#13;
D.       Frequencyof ProcurementSupervision&#13;
&#13;
In addition to the prior review supervision to be carried out from Bank offices, the capacity&#13;
assessment of the Implementing Agency has recommended undertaking a post review of&#13;
procurement actions once every six month.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              -48-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 Attachment 1: Details of the Procurement Arrangement InvolvingNational Competition.\&#13;
&#13;
1.Consulting Services.\&#13;
&#13;
(a) List of Consulting Assignments with short-list o f local firms.&#13;
&#13;
 1         2               3           4                 5                   6         7&#13;
&#13;
Ref.     Descriptionof     Estimated   Selection          Review         Expected     Comments&#13;
 No.      Assignment        US$ m       Method            by Bank     -  Proposals&#13;
                             cost                       (Prior / Post)  Submission&#13;
                                                                            Date&#13;
1.      Technical and         0.7    QCBS                   Prior      August2005&#13;
        financial auditors&#13;
2.      Technical             0.4    QCBSILCS &amp;             Prior      August 2005&#13;
        Assistanceto                 Individual                        through&#13;
        PWA                          Consultants                       December2006&#13;
3.      support to PMU         1.2   Individual             Prior      May 2005     Selectionand&#13;
        and CMWU                     Consultants                                    employment of&#13;
                                                                                    individual&#13;
                                                                                    consultantsto&#13;
                                                                                    support PMU&#13;
&#13;
(b) Consultancy services estimatedto cost above US$lOO,OOO per contract by firms andabove&#13;
US$50,000 by individuals and Single Source selection of consultantswould be subject to prior&#13;
reviewbythe Bank.&#13;
&#13;
(c) Short lists composed entirely of nationalconsultants: Short lists of consultantsfor services&#13;
estimatedto cost less thanUS$150,000 equivalent per contract may be composedentirely of&#13;
national consultantsinaccordance with the provisions of paragraph2.7 of the Consultant&#13;
Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               -49-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                   Attachment2: PriorReviewThresholds&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Methodof         QCBS        QBS           LCS         CQS       Individual&#13;
Consultant                                                       Consultants&#13;
Selection                                                        and Single&#13;
                                                                  Source&#13;
3. Consultants                                                     Single&#13;
                                                                  Source&#13;
3.1 Procurement                                      &lt;$100,000&#13;
Thresholds&#13;
Prior Review      All        All         First two    First two     All&#13;
                                       contractsthen  contracts&#13;
                                        &gt;$100,000       then&#13;
                                         for firm    &gt;$100,000&#13;
                                       &gt;$50,000 for   for firm&#13;
                                        individuals &gt;$50,000 for&#13;
                                                     individuals&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   -50-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                     ANNEX 6: ENVIRONMENTAL SOCIAL ASSESSMENTS&#13;
                                                    AND&#13;
&#13;
EnvironmentalAssessment&#13;
&#13;
The proposed project would contribute to improving the environment through better&#13;
management of existing water and sanitation facilities, through increased expenditure on&#13;
essential operations and maintenance, and through a capital investment program to expand and&#13;
improve water and sanitation infrastructure. Currently there are no known project proposals&#13;
whose implementation would require land acquisition or result in involuntary resettlement. No&#13;
known archaeological or historical sites would be affected by rehabilitation sub-projects, nor&#13;
does the operating investment component of the project raise any international water issues. The&#13;
capital investment activities to be supported comprise rehabilitation, upgrading and extension of&#13;
pipedwater supply and sewerageservices inurbanareas andwater supply improvements inrural,&#13;
areas. The project does not include new wastewater treatment facilities. The project does not&#13;
include any component with major environmental impact and will result in significant&#13;
improvement inenvironmental quality through improvedwater and sanitation services.&#13;
&#13;
Environmental impact will be mitigated by improved operations and maintenance o f water and&#13;
sewerage services, which will improve the efficiency o f water use and reduce the need for&#13;
tapping new resources. Substantial past and future investments by other donors have provided&#13;
adequate collection systemsto accommodate increasedwastewater discharges resultingfrom this&#13;
project.   Management will be improved by the Operator but treatment capacity, which is&#13;
inadequate, will not be directly increasedas a result of this project. However there are plans to&#13;
build several wastewater treatment plants (funded by donors) to treat the collected sewage and&#13;
reuse the treated effluent.&#13;
&#13;
The proposed project has been classified under the environmental category "B" in accordance&#13;
withthe World Bank's Operational Policy 4.01 on Environmental Assessments. Accordingly, an&#13;
Environmental Impact Assessment and Environmental Mitigation and Management Plan has&#13;
beenpreparedas part of Project preparation.&#13;
&#13;
Keyfindings on EnvironmentalIssues&#13;
&#13;
An Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) and Environmental Management Plan (EMP) were&#13;
completed in March 2001 and remain germane to the planned project. They were assessed&#13;
during appraisal and are determinedto remain fully relevant. The complete text of the EIA and&#13;
EMP is on file with the World Bank Infoshop and available to the public via internet, and Bank&#13;
Staff via intranet (through the "Project Portal") and from the Task Team.&#13;
&#13;
Under the EIA, the environmental resourcesthat are of particular interest to the implementation&#13;
of the EMP were surveyed. Additionally, sample site-specific projects from five municipalities&#13;
were selected to assist in describing and assessing existing conditions, as well as summarizing&#13;
potential impacts.&#13;
&#13;
Multiple issues were studied to assess the environmental impacts, including: drilling and/or&#13;
rehabilitating wells, disinfecting potable water, operating desalination plants, establishing new&#13;
water and wastewater networks, rehabilitating existing water and wastewater networks,&#13;
constructing cesspits for wastewater disposal, improving wastewater treatment plants,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -51-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rehabilitating wastewater pumping stations, and reusing treated wastewater for agriculture and&#13;
infiltration. The EIA/EMP also addresses the effects of general construction activities and new&#13;
tariffstructures.&#13;
&#13;
The EMP details potential impacts and proposes mitigation measures.                Responsibility for&#13;
execution, mitigation monitoring measures and methods, and monitoring and enforcement i s&#13;
clearly spelled out betweenthe PMU and operating consultant.&#13;
&#13;
In order to monitor the project's compliance with the EMP and coordinate the environmental&#13;
training program, the Project Management Unit (PMU) will include environmental specialists.&#13;
The PMU's environment staff will be augmented, as necessary, by part time environmental&#13;
advisors and consultants, bothlocaland international.&#13;
&#13;
The environmental capacity building and training program will focuses on the preparation and&#13;
use of the appraisal/mitigation form, use o f environmental guidelines, and implementation o f the&#13;
EMP. Safety measures, proper waste disposal, and cleaning measures during construction are&#13;
also addressed.&#13;
&#13;
It is estimated that the implementation of the EMP will cost US$326,000, includingthe cost of&#13;
employing the environmental expert, capacity building and training programs, periodic&#13;
environmental assessment for water and wastewater projects, and a contingency budget for any&#13;
archaeological survey necessitatedby an unexpected chance find.&#13;
&#13;
Social Development Issues and Implementation Strategy&#13;
&#13;
Keyfindings on SocialIssues&#13;
&#13;
The social assessment findings showed that most consumers were deeply concerned about&#13;
inadequatewater quality and poor regularity/predictability of supply, and improvements in both&#13;
would bring major public benefits. There is strong support for individual metering and the&#13;
eliminationof free riders. Institutionally there is support for the setting up o f a CWU to improve&#13;
management, but also concern to ensure institutionalaccountability, particularly inthe context of&#13;
deep mistrust inthe overall regional political economy o f water resource allocation and limited&#13;
public information. There is support for the involvement of other institutions (Environment,&#13;
Health) on quality control, and for consumer representation on the governing board.&#13;
&#13;
On tariffs, consumers would be willing to pay additional amounts for improved quality, but the&#13;
actual ability to do so i s rather limited (especially with the changes in the last 12 months). It&#13;
would also have to take into account the poverty situation. Gaza's historic poverty rates have&#13;
been higher than inthe West Bank and over 2/3 o f new poverty (since October 2000) is located&#13;
there, with the likelihood that recovery will be slow and difficult. A major coping strategy o f the&#13;
poor has been to defer payment of utility bills (water, electricity, telephone) although only the&#13;
poorest of families get into serious arrears. Social safety nets to protect the most vulnerable are&#13;
porous and have limited coverage. The implication o f all this i s that tariff increases should be&#13;
accompanied by effective dissemination o f information, cultivation of customer relations,&#13;
monitoring of impacts on the poor and very poor and special provisions (universally supported)&#13;
for the very poor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -52-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Social Development Outcome&#13;
&#13;
Given the high risk context o f the project, and the need to raise water revenues to viable levels,&#13;
the main social development outcome should be to enhance confidence andtrust (or least to take&#13;
measures to prevent deterioration o f trust which would otherwise risk project outcomes). This&#13;
should be done at two levels: to enhance trust between the individual consumer and the service&#13;
provider, and to ensure public trust in the institutional arrangements for the (sub) sector.&#13;
Subsidiary social development outcomes would be adequate safety nets for the very poor and&#13;
improvement incustomer behavior inrelation to water.&#13;
&#13;
Implementation Strategyfor SocialDevelopment Outcomes&#13;
&#13;
Trust is a deeper andmore durable concept than customer satisfaction, and requires attention not&#13;
only to enhance and improve customer satisfaction, but to measure it objectively, communicate&#13;
progress regularly, as well as establish mechanisms o f consultation, handlingo f complaints, and&#13;
a transparent and accountable regulatory environment. The lead agencies for the various sub-&#13;
components remain to be determined among the CMWU, PWA, the Operator and the social&#13;
services administration.&#13;
&#13;
Regular ConsumerSurveys&#13;
&#13;
Consumer surveys are a useful tool to assess the extent o f consumer satisfaction and o f trust&#13;
between consumers and service providers. Some o f the issues that could be covered by such&#13;
surveys are consumer confidence in metering and billing; service time response to complaints&#13;
andqueries including billing; and the reliability o f supply. However, inorder to provide reliable&#13;
and incontestable results, such surveys need to be accurate and have to be conducted by highly&#13;
qualified, professional firms using a representative sample o f sufficient size and a transparent&#13;
methodology. Even in developed countries, the reliability o f the results o f such surveys i s&#13;
sometimes challenged. In WBG, where capacity in conducting such surveys in an accurate and&#13;
reliable manner is apparently limited, these concerns are more serious. Therefore, it is&#13;
inappropriate to use beneficiary-derived indicators as part o f the performance indicators that&#13;
determine the bonus payment to the private Operator; however, consumer surveys should be&#13;
conducted in order to provide information to help ensure project outcomes. Recent experience&#13;
concerning Bank work on citizen participatory monitoring o f public services as well as technical&#13;
assistancecould be made available to CMWU, which would contract out such surveys.&#13;
&#13;
Recommendation: CMWU should contract services of local consultants to conduct a pilot&#13;
consumer surveys, to be followed by regular such surveys.&#13;
&#13;
Public I nformation Campaign&#13;
&#13;
It is important to increase the public confidence inthe institutional structure. Transparency is an&#13;
essential prerequisite for such confidence.&#13;
&#13;
Recommendation:A broad-based public information campaign should be conducted, including&#13;
the media. The campaign should go well beyond explaining the need to save water, which has&#13;
been the main or even unique activity in some awareness campaigns in other countries. The&#13;
campaign should explain the role o f the private sector Operator; the role given to consumers in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               -53-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
monitoring the Operator through regular surveys, consumer committees and their board&#13;
representative; special measures to be introduced to protect the needy; the functioning o f the&#13;
complaints process; the need to increase tariffs in order to provide improved services, in&#13;
particular improved water quality through desalination and piped sewerage; indicating what the&#13;
project can and cannot do, at least in the short term, pending major capital investments. The&#13;
campaign would place particular emphasis on the need to identify illegal connections to prevent&#13;
free rider behavior. Most illegal connections have been identified and many have been&#13;
regularized, but some illegal connections remain, including a large share o f connections used by&#13;
industries. CMWU could implement the public information campaign, with a significant input&#13;
from local consultants. Parts o fthe campaign could be undertaken by the Operator.&#13;
&#13;
TargetedSupport Payments to the Poor&#13;
&#13;
Currently, municipalities exempt some consumers from paying their water bills or forgive the&#13;
accumulated arrears on water bills, presumably on the basis of social need. However, the current&#13;
practice may not be adequately targeting the poor, since these exemptions are apparently often&#13;
granted as favors to relatives and friends. The present system should be discontinued once the&#13;
C M W U is functionally established under the new project and replaced with a more targeted&#13;
system.&#13;
&#13;
However, it is not yet clear what form o f targeted support payments should and could be&#13;
introduced under the project. There is a need to identify poor water users who would find it&#13;
difficult to pay their water bills, to monitor the impacts o f tariff reforms on very poor households&#13;
and on poor users o f singly-metered sources, and to monitor the implementation o f targeted&#13;
financial support. The utility may not be best placed to perform these functions. The existing&#13;
social services system, including the Ministry o f Social Affairs, UNRWA and the NGO network&#13;
which plays an important part in social services delivery and community representatives, are&#13;
better placed to identify such households, deliver and monitor targeted support payments. One&#13;
option i s to levy a small surcharge on water bills to fund targeted financial support for poor&#13;
households. The eligibility criteria should be defined by the social services. The revenues could&#13;
be channeled into a special fund that would be controlled by both the C M W U and the social&#13;
services administration, and which would be subject to transparent rules to be communicated to&#13;
all water users through the media and other channels. Another option would be to identify grant&#13;
fundingfrom a donor, possibly underan on-going project. The funding requirements would be in&#13;
the order o f US$ 0.3 million per year, if the poorest 10 % o f users were targeted and half their&#13;
water billwould be paid from the fund.&#13;
&#13;
Recommendation: Identify an appropriate entity to implement targeted support payments as&#13;
well as the necessary funding.&#13;
&#13;
Consumer Committeesand ConsumerRepresentative on the CMWU&#13;
&#13;
The current membership o f the C M W U board includes mayors as well as a university professor&#13;
and a representative o fthe business community. This arrangement does not provide for sufficient&#13;
representation o fwater users.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -54-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Recommendation:It is suggestedthat consumer committees are formed ineach municipality or&#13;
group o f municipalities. These committees could serve as an interfacebetween the utility and the&#13;
consumers, holding public meetings, providing feedback to the Operator and C M W U on&#13;
consumer priorities and concerns, and having the right to accede to information from the&#13;
Operator, thus increasing transparency. Members o f the consumer committees could be&#13;
nominated by the municipalities and NGOs. Members would receive a small compensation&#13;
closely related to their efforts, i.e. linked to the number o f community meeting organized.&#13;
Membership would however be a part-time and volunteer function. It would be appropriate to&#13;
phase the formation o fthese consumer committees with the implementationo f works.&#13;
&#13;
Consumer committees could help in setting up rules for eligibility o f targeted support payments&#13;
to the poor, in public awareness campaigns, in drafting the Terms of Reference, supervising or&#13;
perhaps carrying out consumer surveys as well as assisting vulnerable groups, such as poor&#13;
living on illegal land who are not entitled to individual water connections. Concerning the latter&#13;
group, the existing procedures allow them to receive individual water connections, if the&#13;
Ministryo fHousingconfirms that the owners o fthe landwould not claim user rights onthe land.&#13;
Consumer committees could help insettling such issues.&#13;
&#13;
Furthermore, a consumer representative could be included on the board o f the CMWU. Given&#13;
that there apparently are no established consumer groups inthe Gaza Strip, it may be difficult to&#13;
identify a suitable candidate. One possibility would be to include a representative from an NGO&#13;
that works with refugees (who are among the poorest and least well served) and/or inthe area o f&#13;
health (because o f the impact o f intermittent supply and low water quality on health). The&#13;
representative could be a woman, since all other board members are likely to be men and&#13;
because women are more aware o f the consequences o f intermittent supply and low water&#13;
quality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -55-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                ANNEX 7: FINANCIALANALYSIS&#13;
&#13;
In the absence of fully consolidated set of audited financial statements for the municipalities&#13;
making up the CMWU, the financial analysis was carried out based solely on pro-forma&#13;
consolidated limited purpose income statements prepared by PWA with data collected from all&#13;
municipalities. Giventhe limitedavailability of financial information, this analysis is simple and&#13;
limitedto demonstrating the projected impact of the management contract on the service area.&#13;
During project implementation, as CMWU is strengthened and is capable of producing&#13;
appropriate financial statements including a consolidated balance sheet, a more elaborate&#13;
analysis should be carried out to modelits future financial performance.&#13;
&#13;
Based on the pro-forma consolidated limitedpurpose income statements prepared by PWA, the&#13;
municipalities are incurring net losses mainly due to their inability to collect the revenue for&#13;
billed water sales and sewage fees. At present, maintenance expenditures have been kept to a&#13;
minimum, given the inability of the municipalities to financially cope with the costs of&#13;
appropriately maintainingtheir water andwastewater systems.&#13;
&#13;
The analysis uses a cost-benefit structure, estimating the future financial performance o f the&#13;
municipalities with or without the project, as well as the net present value in financial terms for&#13;
the duration of the management contract. As shown in Table 1, the net present value (NPV) of&#13;
the operating surplus with the management contract at N I S 4.4 million (US$ 1million), while the&#13;
NPV of the operating surplus without the management contract i s negative at NIS 40 million&#13;
(US$9.1 million).&#13;
&#13;
Given the unpredictable political and security environment in West Bank and Gaza, as well as&#13;
the lack of available financial data, it is very difficult to meaningfully predict the long-term&#13;
future performance of CMWU. A longer-term forecast of the management contract's impact is&#13;
shown in Table 3, followed by key assumptions inTable 4. This base scenario forecast has been&#13;
prepared mainly to foresee the possible financial benefits if the level of service is maintained at&#13;
the same levels as the ones targeted at the end of the management contract for an additional 4&#13;
years, in case the option to extend the management contract is undertaken. As it i s shown, the&#13;
NPV ofthe operating cashflow for this period is positive at NIS 16.3 million (US$3.7 million).&#13;
&#13;
The management contract financed by the project will generate financial benefits to the water&#13;
andwastewater sector inGazamainlythrough an increaseinthe revenue collectionratio, as well&#13;
as through a decrease inunaccounted-for water, while increasing the maintenance expenses so as&#13;
to ensure an appropriate level o fmaintenanceto the network.&#13;
&#13;
Other benefits range from the provision of additional water supply capacity to better satisfy the&#13;
targeted population, to securing water supply and protecting water quality at a lower cost. The&#13;
project will allow households to consume a larger volume o f water than any other alternative,&#13;
which will increase their welfare (the consumer surplus) and the revenues for the utility. The&#13;
institutional component o fthe project will provide differentbenefits; among them it will improve&#13;
the finances of the water utility, its management, and will result in reduced operating costs.&#13;
Besides, the personnel will benefit from capacity buildingand training inthe different operation&#13;
andmanagementfunctions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               -56-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Assumptions&#13;
&#13;
The base scenario analysis i s based on pro-forma income statements produced by PWA for the&#13;
years 1999 - 2003 and estimates for 2004. The project implementation period is from 2005 to&#13;
2008. All o f the assumptions usedinthe analysis are presented inTable 2 below.&#13;
&#13;
KeyAssumptions&#13;
&#13;
    0   A real tariff increase o f 15% in 2006 followed by 10% increase in the two subsequent&#13;
        years. (Note:   if appropriate maintenance requirements are verified to be of a larger&#13;
        amount than what has been estimated, higher tariff increases may be required to cover&#13;
        these maintenance costs).&#13;
&#13;
    WithManagement Contract&#13;
&#13;
    0   Collection efficiency standing at 55% during the first year o f the contract and then&#13;
        increasing to 75% by the third year as outlined inthe MC.&#13;
&#13;
    0   Non-revenue water reducedto 25% by the third year o fthe management contract.&#13;
&#13;
    0   An increase inmaintenance spendingof 50% in 2005 and 2006 to bringmaintenance to&#13;
       'appropriate levels. This will be followed by increases o f 25%, and another 50% for 2007&#13;
        and 2008, mainly to account for the increased costs of operating and maintainingthe 2&#13;
        wastewater treatment plants that are expected to become operational by then.&#13;
&#13;
    Without Management Contract&#13;
&#13;
    0   Collection efficiency i s stagnant at 55%.&#13;
&#13;
    0   Non-revenue water i s also maintained at its current level of 39%.&#13;
&#13;
    0   Maintenance spending increases at the constant level o f 5%.&#13;
&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis&#13;
&#13;
A sensitivity analysis was performed on the assumptions underpinning the 7-year forecast, to&#13;
demonstrate the impact of alternative scenarios involving items critical to the project's&#13;
sustainability, such as collection rates, levels o f non-revenue water, and tariffs. The results are&#13;
as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -57-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                              Parameter                                     NPV&#13;
                                                                        (NIS million)&#13;
   1. Base Scenario (as described inassumptions above and on                 13.0&#13;
       Tables 3 and 4 below)&#13;
&#13;
   2. Increase o f 5% in collection efficiency from 2008                      7.1&#13;
       onwards &amp; 3% lower tariff increasesbetween 2006 and&#13;
       2008 (Le., tariff increasesof 12%, 7% and 7%&#13;
       respectively, for 2006,2007 &amp; 2008)&#13;
&#13;
   3. Reduction of 5% in non-revenue water from 2008                          3.7&#13;
       onwards &amp; 3% lower tariff increases between 2006 and&#13;
       2008 (i.e., tariff increasesof 12%, 7% and 7%&#13;
       respectively for 2006,2007 &amp; 2008)&#13;
   4. 5% lower tariff increasesbetween 2006 and 2008 @e.,                   -29.6&#13;
       tariff increasesof lo%, 5% and 5% respectively for 2006,&#13;
       2007 and 2008)&#13;
&#13;
   5. Reduction of 5% in non-revenue water from 2008                         33.1&#13;
       onwards&#13;
&#13;
   6. Increase o f 5% incollection efficiency from 2008                      36.7&#13;
       onwards&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
As indicated inthe table above, lower tariff increases tllan what has been forecastec betweenthe&#13;
2006 and 2008 will have to be accompanied by an increase in the expected efficiency gains&#13;
either during these periods or from 2008 onwards, as the improvements in operations and the&#13;
investments aimed at enhancing the water and wastewater networks are implemented and start&#13;
yielding results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  -58-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
iI::s&#13;
I&#13;
!h&#13;
if 8&#13;
   N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
j&#13;
12&#13;
. No&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   0&#13;
   N&#13;
   0&#13;
   N&#13;
&#13;
,!!&#13;
i::6&#13;
&#13;
I&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                     K&#13;
                     s&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      r              x&#13;
      r              P&#13;
      N&#13;
      0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      z&#13;
      0              a&#13;
                     m&#13;
      N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     r:&#13;
      m              s&#13;
      0&#13;
      N&#13;
      0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      OD             2m&#13;
      0&#13;
      N&#13;
      0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           00cq&#13;
      h    V)Nh      2m&#13;
      0     m - m&#13;
      0&#13;
      N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      W              E&#13;
                     N&#13;
      N&#13;
      0&#13;
      0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     2&#13;
      W&#13;
      0&#13;
      0&#13;
      N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
c,&#13;
u&#13;
z&#13;
Q)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
p1&#13;
&#13;
;&#13;
6                        !&#13;
c,                   m     S&#13;
&#13;
                     C     a&#13;
&#13;
u&#13;
h                    2&gt;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
wI&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
U&#13;
c(&#13;
d&#13;
d&#13;
N&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                       ANNEX 8: PROJECTPREPARATIONANDSUPERVISION&#13;
&#13;
                  ProjectSchedule                         Planned                     Actual&#13;
Time takento preparethe project (months)                   See note                  See note&#13;
First Bank mission (identification)                      March2000                 March2000&#13;
Appraisal mission departure                                                       April 4,2005&#13;
Negotiations                                                                       May 3,2005&#13;
Planneddate of effectiveness                             July 31,2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Bankstaffwho workedontheprojectincluded:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Peer Reviewersand Quality Control:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Names (in alphabetical order)                       Title&#13;
Alfred H.Nickesen                                  Manager, OPCIL&#13;
Aloysius Ordu                                      Operations Quality Adviser&#13;
Frederick P. Kranz                                 ProcurementAdvisor&#13;
Hadi Abushakra                                     ChiefCounsel&#13;
Jonathan Walters                                   Sector Manager&#13;
MarkusKostner                                      Country ProgramCoordinator&#13;
Nigel Roberts                                      Country Director&#13;
Suhail Jme'an                                      TeamLeader, Senior FinancialAnalyst&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 -63-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                        ANNEX 9: DOCUMENTSPROJECT ON           FILES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.  Approved by-laws for the CMWU (inArabic)&#13;
&#13;
2.  Terms o freference for the PMU staff approved by CMWU Board&#13;
&#13;
3.  Draft Organizational Structure ofthe CMWU approvedby the Board&amp; the minutes of&#13;
    meeting No. 7 o fthe CMWU Board&#13;
&#13;
4.  List o f all water and wastewater staff and skills inall municipalities o f Gaza&#13;
&#13;
5.  Draft Consumer Charters (inArabic)&#13;
&#13;
6.  Draft proposal for the location of CMWU branches&#13;
&#13;
7.  Terms of referencefor technical andfinancial auditors for the M C&#13;
&#13;
8.  Draft capital andoperational investmentfund&#13;
&#13;
9.  Draft technical assistancecomponent&#13;
&#13;
10. Request for Proposal for a Management Contract for the provision of water and&#13;
    wastewater services inGaza, August 16,2004.&#13;
&#13;
11. Institutional Capacity Building Programme, Package F-Legal Framework; 2004, PWA&#13;
    andthe governmentsofthe Netherlands andNorway.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             -64-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   ANNEX 10: STATEMENT OFLOANS CREDITS               AND&#13;
&#13;
                                                    WEST BANKAND GAZA&#13;
                                                                                                                         Differencebetween&#13;
                                                                                                                         expectedandactual&#13;
                                                               Original Amount inUS$Millions                               disbursements&#13;
&#13;
ProiectID   N Puroose                                       IBRD        IDA      SF       GEF      Cancel.   Undisb.    Orig.     Frm.Rev'd&#13;
&#13;
PO74595    2005   GZ-NORTHGAZA EMERGENCY                       0.00      0.00     7.80     0.00      0.00      6.30       0.90        0.00&#13;
                  SEWAGETREATMENT&#13;
PO81477    2004   GZ-SocialSafetyNet ReformProject             0.00      0.00    10.00     0.00      0.00      9.20       1.20        0.00&#13;
PO65921    2004   GZ-EMERGENCY WATER                           0.00      0.00    12.50     0.00      0.00      9.86       7.03        2.39&#13;
PO78212    2003   GZ-EMERGENCY MUNICIPAL                       0.00      0.00    20.00     0.00      0.00      6.29      19.67       12.62&#13;
                  SERVICES REHAB1&#13;
PO69986     2002  IntegratedCommunityDevelopmentProj           0.00      0.00    10.00     0.00      0.00      3.87       5.63        0.00&#13;
PO54051     2001  GZ-SOLID WASTE &amp;                             0.00      0.00     9.50     0.00      0.00       5.60      9.50        0.00&#13;
                  ENVIRONMENTAL MNGMNT.&#13;
PO71040     2001  GZ-PalestinianNGOProjectI1                   0.00      0.00     8.00     0.00      0.00      0.43       7.67        0.00&#13;
PO65593     2001  EDUCATIONACTION PROJECT                      0.00      0.00     7.00     0.00      0.00       0.64      7.00        6.13&#13;
PO58683     2000  GZ-MIDPII                                    0.00      0.00     7.50     0.00      0.00       0.58      7.50        7.38&#13;
PO40506     2000  GZ-ELEC.SEC.MV.&amp; MGMT                        0.00      0.00    15.00     0.00      0.00       1.85      15.00       13.57&#13;
PO53892     2000  GZ-HEALTH SYSTEMDEVELOPMENT                  0.00      0.00     7.90     0.00      0.00       0.08      7.90        7.81&#13;
                  I&#13;
PO51564     1999  GZ-SOUTHERNAREA WATER                        0.00      0.00    21.00     0.00      0.00       0.80     21.00       20.25&#13;
PO40503     1998  GAZA INDUSTRIAL EST.                         0.00      0.00    10.00      0.00     0.00       3.12      10.70       6.76&#13;
PO43338     1997  GZ-HOUSING FINANCE                           0.00      0.00    25.00      0.00     7.60       3.00     25.00        16.48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Total:    0.00      0.00    171.20     0.00     7.60      51.62     145.70       93.39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  STATEMENT OF IFC's Held and Disbursed Portfolio&#13;
                                                       InMillions ofUSDollars&#13;
                                                                Committed                                  Disbursed&#13;
&#13;
                                                               IFC                                        IFC&#13;
       FY Approval    Company                      Loan      Equity      Quasi     Partic.  Loan        Equity       Quasi     Partic.&#13;
&#13;
        1994          APIB                         0.00         3.73       0.00      0.00       0.00       3.73       0.00       0.00&#13;
        1997          Arab Bank                    0.00         0.00       0.03      0.00       0.00       0.00       0.03       0.00&#13;
        1997          ComBankPalestin              0.00         0.00       0.08      0.00       0.00       0.00       0.08       0.00&#13;
        1997          JordanNational               0.00         0.00       0.30      0.00       0.00       0.00       0.30       0.00&#13;
        1997          PIEDCO                       1.00         1.00       0.00      0.00       1.00       1.oo       0.00       0.00&#13;
        1999          PMHC        ,                0.00         3.00       0.00      0.00       0.00       2.23       0.00       0.00&#13;
        1998          PTF                          0.00        12.48       0.00      0.00       0.00       4.43       0.00       0.00&#13;
        1998          PTF-Mgt CO.                  0.00         0.20       0.00      0.00       0.00       0.04       0.00       0.00&#13;
        1999          PTIC                         0.00         0.49       0.00      0.00       0.00       0.49       0.00       0.00&#13;
        1997          SEF Arab Concret             0.80         0.00       0.00      0.00       0.80       0.00       0.00       0.00&#13;
        1999          SEFJerichoMotel              1.10         0.00       0.00      0.00       1.10       0.00       0.00       0.00&#13;
&#13;
                                 Total portfolio:    2.90      20.90       0.41      0.00       2.90      11.92       0.41       0.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Approvals PendingCommitment&#13;
                      FY Aooroval     Comoanv                            Loan        Eauitv      Quasi        Partic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            Total pendingcommitment:      0.00        0.00        0.00         0.00&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                          A"EX 11:COUNTRYAT A GLANCE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      West   M. East   Lower-&#13;
POVERTY and SOCIAL                                    Bank   &amp; North  middle-&#13;
                                                     8 Gaza   Africa  income         Development diamond'&#13;
                                                                                    ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2003&#13;
Population,mid-year(millions)                             3.4     3 0    2,655                 Lifeexpectancy&#13;
GNIper capita (Atlas method, US$)                        I10    2,2D     1,480&#13;
GNI(Atlas method, US$ billions)                           3.7     669    3,934                        T&#13;
&#13;
Average annual growth, 1997.03&#13;
Population (!Ad                                           4.1      19      0.9&#13;
Laborforce (%)                                                    2.9       t2                                         Gross&#13;
                                                                                                                       primary&#13;
M o s t recent estimate (latest year available, 1997-03)&#13;
Poverty(%ofpopulation belownationalpovertyline)&#13;
Urbanpopuiation(%0ftotalpopulafion)                                5a       50&#13;
Lifeexpectancyat birth (years)                            73       69       69&#13;
Infant mortality(per 1OOOlivebirths)                               44       32&#13;
Childmalnutrition (%of childrenunder5)                                        11          Access to improved water source&#13;
Access to an improvedwater source (%ofpopulation)                  aa        61&#13;
Illiteracy(%ofpopulationage b+)                                    31        1)&#13;
Gross primaryenrollment (%ofschool-age populafion)                 96       1P         -West      Bank andGaza&#13;
   Male                                                           DO        18         -Loner-middle-incomegroup&#13;
   Female                                                          92        111&#13;
&#13;
KEY ECONOMIC RATIOS and LONG-TERM TRENDS&#13;
                                              1983     1993     2002    2003         Economic ratios'&#13;
GDP (US$ billions)                                                3.4       3.5&#13;
Gross domestic investment/GDP                                     3.5       2.5&#13;
Exports of goods and serviceslGDP                                 0.3      D.O                       Trade&#13;
&#13;
Gross domestic savingslGDP                                      -30.7    -36.5&#13;
Gross national savings/GDP                                        -6.7    -0.5                          T&#13;
Current account balance/GDP                                      -10.3    -13.0&#13;
Interestpayments/GDP&#13;
Total debt/GDP&#13;
Total debt servicelexports&#13;
Present value of debt/GDP&#13;
Present valueof debt/exports                                                                      indebtedness&#13;
                                    1983-93 1993-03    2002     2003 2003-07&#13;
(average annualgrowth)&#13;
GDP                                       ..                                             -West     Bank andGaza&#13;
                                                -2.0     -B.l     -17&#13;
GDP percapita                             ..    -6.0    -22.5     -5.6                   -Loner-middle-incomegroup&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
STRUCTURE O f the ECONOMY&#13;
                                               1983    1993     2002     2003        Growth o f Investment and GDP (%)&#13;
(%of GDP)&#13;
Agriculture                                                        6.3      6.2       50 T&#13;
Industry                                                          13.3     P.O&#13;
  Manufacturing                                                   D.7       9.6&#13;
Services                                                          60.4     81.6&#13;
                                                                                                                          -&#13;
Private consumption                                               79.0    83.8&#13;
Generalgovernment consumption                                     517      52.7&#13;
Imports of goods and services                                     46.6    49.0                -GDI           -GDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            1983-93 1993-03     2002     2003&#13;
(averageannualgrowth)&#13;
Agriculture                                        ..    -4.7    -8.8&#13;
Industry                                           ..    -6.3    -24.8&#13;
  Manufacturing                                    ..    -2.3    -24.2&#13;
Services                                                  12     -8.7&#13;
&#13;
Private consumption                                .,    -3.0    -213&#13;
Generalgovernmentconsumption                       ..     119     -0.6&#13;
Gross domestic investment                          ..   -26.7    -44.0&#13;
Imports of goods and services                      ..    -5.0    -P.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                -66-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                       West Bank and Gaza&#13;
PRICES and GOVERNMENT FINANCE&#13;
                                         1983 1993     2002   2003        Inflation (%)&#13;
Domestic prices                                                                                                I&#13;
(%change)&#13;
Consumer prices                                          5.7&#13;
implicit GDP deflator                                    n.2     7.0&#13;
&#13;
Government finance&#13;
(%of GDP,includes currentgrants)&#13;
Currentrevenue                                          23.8            1        98    99   00    01    02&#13;
Currentbudget balance                                    -5.0                                                 031&#13;
&#13;
Overallsurplusldeficit                                   -5.1                     -WPQfdlator      -Cp1&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
TRADE&#13;
                                         1983 1993     2002   2003&#13;
(US$ miilions)                                                            Export and Import levels (US$ mill.)&#13;
&#13;
Total exports (fob)                       382   238      41)    339&#13;
 n.a.&#13;
 n.a.                                                                    3.000&#13;
 Manufactures&#13;
Total imports (cif)                       785   If38    1406   1506      2,000&#13;
&#13;
 Food&#13;
 Fueland energy                                                          1,000&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        I                                       I&#13;
 Capitalgoods                                                                0&#13;
&#13;
Exportpriceindex(s95=?JO)                                 6 2    no             97   98  99  00    01   02   03&#13;
&#13;
import priceindex(6'95=7JO)                               n7     8 7              aExports       Inports&#13;
Terms of trade(19951WO)                                   92      91&#13;
&#13;
BALANCE o f PAYMENTS&#13;
                                         1983 1993     2002   2003&#13;
(US$ millions)                                                            Current account balance to GDP (%)&#13;
&#13;
Exportsof goods and services                             4 8    345        0&#13;
Imports of goods and services                           1581    1693&#13;
Resource balance                                        -1.64  -138      -x)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Net income                                               372     385     -20&#13;
Net currenttransfers                                     443    443      -30&#13;
Current account balance                                 -348    -520&#13;
&#13;
Financingitems (net)                                                     -40&#13;
&#13;
Changes in net reserves&#13;
Memo:&#13;
Reserves includinggold (US$ millions)&#13;
Conversion rate(DEC,local/US$)                            4.7    4.9&#13;
&#13;
EXTERNAL DEBT and RESOURCE FLOWS&#13;
                                         1983  1993    2002    2003&#13;
(US$ millions)&#13;
Total debt outstanding anddisbursed&#13;
  iBRD&#13;
  IDA&#13;
Total debtservice&#13;
  IBRD&#13;
 IDA&#13;
Compositionof net resource flows&#13;
 Official grants&#13;
 Officialcreditors&#13;
 Privatecreditors&#13;
 Foreigndirect investment&#13;
 Portfolio equity&#13;
&#13;
World Bank program&#13;
 Commitments&#13;
 Disbursements&#13;
 Principalrepayments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    -67-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                     IBRD 33512&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            3500'E                               To&#13;
                                                                                                                                                Nazareth              3530'E&#13;
          WEST BANK                                                                                                                To Haifa&#13;
&#13;
            AND GAZA&#13;
&#13;
                SELECTED CITIES AND TOWNS&#13;
                                                                            3230'N                                                                                                     3230'N&#13;
                                                                                                                                  Yamoun&#13;
                RIVERS&#13;
                                                                                                        To Haifa                   Ya'bad    Jenin&#13;
                MAIN ROADS                                                                                               Kaffeen&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  Qabatia&#13;
                RAILROADS&#13;
&#13;
                ARMISTICE DEMARCATION LINES, 1949                                                                                         J E N I N&#13;
&#13;
                NO-MAN'S LAND AREAS,                                                                                                                            T U B A S&#13;
                                                                                                    To Netanya      TULKARM&#13;
                ARMISTICE DEMARCATION LINE, 1949                                                                            Anapta                            Tubas&#13;
                                                                                                                    Tulkarm&#13;
                JERUSALEM CITY LIMIT, UNILATERALLY                                                                                                             Tammun                            JORDAN&#13;
                EXPANDED BY ISRAEL JUNE 1967;                                                                                               Mt. 'Eval&#13;
                THEN ANNEXED JULY 30, 1980                                                                                                  (940 m)&#13;
                                                                                                                                             N A B L U S&#13;
                GOVERNORATE BOUNDARIES                                                             Qalqilyah     QALQILYAH    AH                    Nablus&#13;
&#13;
                INTERNATIONAL BOUNDARIES                                                                                                                                                        To&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                          Bet Shean&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        S A L F I T&#13;
                                              3430'E                                                                                 W e s t&#13;
  This map was produced by the Map Design Unit of The World Bank.                                                              Salfit&#13;
  The boundaries, colors, denominations and any other information                                     To&#13;
                                                                                                     Ramla                                                                     River&#13;
  shown on this map do not imply, on the part of The World Bank&#13;
  Group, any judgment on the legal status of any territory, or any                                                                    B a n k&#13;
  endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.                                                 To                                                                         nadroJ&#13;
                                                                                              Tel Aviv&#13;
3200'N                                                                                 To                                                                                              3200'N&#13;
                                                                                     Tel Aviv                                                      Tall Asur&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   (1,022 m)&#13;
                                                                                                                           R A M A L L A H                         JERICHO&#13;
&#13;
        M e d i t e r r a n e a n                                                                                             Ramallah&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                          To&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                        Amman&#13;
                           S e a                                                                                                                              Jericho&#13;
                                                                                                                                           JERUSALEM&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                          To&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                        Amman&#13;
                                                                                                                                            JERUSALEM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            I S R A E L                                                 Bethlehem&#13;
                                                                                                                                      B E T H L E H E M&#13;
                                                                  To&#13;
                                                                Tel Aviv&#13;
&#13;
                   JABALYA                                                                        To                                                                Dead&#13;
                                                                                              Ashqelon&#13;
&#13;
                                    Beit Lahia                                                                                (1,020 m)                              Sea&#13;
                                               Jabalya                                                             Hebron&#13;
                           Gaza City                                                                                             Qir Arba&#13;
&#13;
        GAZA CITY                                                                                                       H E B R O N                                                     3130'N&#13;
&#13;
 Gaza                Nusejrat&#13;
                                                                To&#13;
                                    El Bureij               Beersheba&#13;
        Deir el Balah                                                                                   Zohar              Yattah&#13;
&#13;
KHAN&#13;
YUNIS                                DEIR EL BALAH&#13;
&#13;
                     Khan                                                                                                                                 To&#13;
                     Yunis                                                                                                                               Zofar&#13;
                                                                                        To&#13;
                                                                                     Beersheba&#13;
&#13;
            Rafah&#13;
                           RAFAH&#13;
               Abu 'Awdah&#13;
  To           (105 m)&#13;
El Arish&#13;
                  To                          WEST BANK&#13;
                  Elat                          AND GAZA&#13;
&#13;
 ARAB                                                                                                     0     5    10    15 Kilometers                                                  JORDAN&#13;
REP. OF&#13;
EGYPT                                                                                                     0        5         10        15 Miles&#13;
&#13;
3100'N                                                                                                                                                                                 3100'N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               3430'E                                                       3500'E                                                  3530'E&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                        APRIL 2005&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5813484">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/05/5813484/west-bank-gaza-emergency-water-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/05/5813484/west-bank-gaza-emergency-water-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/05/5813484/west-bank-gaza-emergency-water-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2005-06-21T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/05/20/000090341_20050520083824/Rendered/INDEX/t7657.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/05/20/000090341_20050520083824/Rendered/PDF/t7657.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-05-20T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2005-05-16T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            West Bank and Gaza - Emergency Water Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Gaza Emergency Water Project aims to
            improve the provision of adequate water and wastewater
            services in Gaza, and functionally establish the Coastal
            Municipalities Water Utility (CMWU) as an autonomous
            well-run modem utility. In addition, the project has a
            secondary objective to strengthen the Palestinian Water
            Authority's (PWA) capacity to assume sector regulatory
            functions. The proposed project will achieve the outlined
            objectives through: a) funding a 3-year performance-based
            management contract to functionally establish the CMWU, as
            well as to improve the operation and quality of water and
            wastewater services in Gaza. b) providing funds to purchase
            materials, supplies and equipment that are required to
            rehabilitate water and wastewater infrastructure and enhance
            the efficient operation, maintenance and administration of
            water and wastewater systems in the service area. c)
            providing technical assistance and capacity building support
            to the PWA and the CMWU, as well as the employment of an
            independent auditor to audit the management contract outputs.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            West Bank and Gaza - Emergency Water Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>West Bank and Gaza - Emergency
            Water Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2005/05/5813484/west-bank-gaza-emergency-water-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>GZ-Gaza II Emergency Water Project -- P065920</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Conservation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>West Bank and Gaza</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Middle East!$!80463</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20050520083824</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Sanitation,Water supply,Sub-national government administration</subsc>
        <admreg>Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <prdln>Special Financing</prdln>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection,Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            adequate water, audits, Bidding, bulk water,
            capacity building, collection systems, construction,
            councils, decentralization, demand for water, desalination,
            discharge, drinking water, drinking water supply, effluent,
            employment, Environmental Assessments, Environmental Impact,
            Environmental Impact Assessment, environmental issues,
            Environmental Management, environmental quality,
            Expenditures, fertilizers, groundwater, groundwater
            abstraction, groundwater quality, health status, imports,
            income, institutional capacity, local authorities,
            managerial capacity, Middle East, Municipal Infrastructure,
            municipal services, municipal water, North Africa, permits,
            piped water, Private Sector, Procurement, programs, Project
            Management, public health, public trust, pumps, regulatory
            capacity, regulatory environment, regulatory framework, safe
            yield, safety nets, salinity, Sanitation, sanitation
            facilities, sanitation infrastructure, sanitation service,
            sanitation service delivery, Sanitation Services, sanitation
            systems, scarce water, scarce water resources, seawater,
            service connections, service delivery, service providers,
            Sewage Treatment, sewerage services, social development,
            solid waste, urban areas, WASTEWATER, wastewater reuse,
            wastewater systems, wastewater treatment, wastewater
            treatment facilities, water consumption, water law, water
            pumps, water quality, water quantity, water resources, water
            sector, water shortage, water supply, water use, Water
            Utility, wells, West Bank and Gaza
        </keywd>
        <owner>FFPSI Group (MNSIF)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Emergency Recovery Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Middle East</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF026133-PHRD-GAZA WATER AND SANITATION
            II PROJECT</trustfund>
        <repnb>T7657</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>WS/WW</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Wastewater</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Research and Surveys for Public Contracts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Appraisal</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Appraisal System</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Bonuses</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Incentives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Pay</ml:concept><ml:concept>EIA</ml:concept><ml:concept>EMMP</ml:concept><ml:concept>EMP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Wastewater</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Treatment and Disposal</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Individual Performance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Impact Assessement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Management and Mitigation Plans</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>