<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP335&#13;
Balancing Trickle Down and Basic Needs Strategies&#13;
Income Distribution Issues in Large Middle-Income Countries&#13;
with Special Reference to Latin America&#13;
Marcelo Selowsky&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 335&#13;
FILE COPYt &#13;
y.: &#13;
HG&#13;
3881.5&#13;
.W57&#13;
W67&#13;
no.335&#13;
c.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 335&#13;
Balancing Trickle Down and Basic Needs Strategies&#13;
Income Distribution Issues in Large Middle-Income Countries&#13;
with Special Reference to Latin America&#13;
Marcelo Selowsky&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (¢ 1979&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing June 1979&#13;
Second printing March 1985&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in the&#13;
Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each is&#13;
available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The World&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W, Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the European&#13;
Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'lena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
When this paper was first published Marcelo Selowsky was a member of the&#13;
Development Economics Department of the World Bank.&#13;
ISBN: 0-8213-0524-7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iii -&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This paper addresses income distribution issues and explores&#13;
various policy options to eliminate extreme poverty in a particular&#13;
typology of middle income developing countries. The countries included&#13;
in the typology are characterized by a relatively high per capita income&#13;
(above US$600 per year in 1976), a relatively high degree of industriali-&#13;
zation (industry representing over 30 percent of GNiP), a rather large&#13;
size both in population and area, and relatively well endowed resources&#13;
in agriculture. A distinctive feature is a strong inequality in the&#13;
distribution of income and wealth relative to other countries of similar&#13;
levels of per capita income.&#13;
The typical countries characterizing the typology are Brazil,&#13;
Colombia, Ecuador, Mexico, Peru, and Turkey.   iecause the Latin American&#13;
countries included represent two-thirds of the population of the region,&#13;
this report is basically addressed to that region.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iv -&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
Several people provided valuable comments during the&#13;
preparation of this report. Sebastian Pinera commented on an&#13;
earlier draft and provided important suggestions. Conversations&#13;
with P. Isenman, B.B. King, P. Knight, C. Lluch, T.N. Srinivasan,&#13;
L. Squire, M. Urrutia, J. Villarzu, R. Webb, and other colleagues&#13;
in the Bank are gratefully acknowledged. Of course, none of&#13;
them is responsible for remaining deficiencies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
v&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
SUMMARY  .  .   .   .  .  .  .  .   .  .   .  .  .   .  .  .  .   .   .  .   .   .  .  .   .  .i-i&#13;
I. POVERTY AND INEQUALITY: MAGNITUDES . . . . . . . . . . . . .1&#13;
A. The Number of People in Poverty  . . . . . . . . . . . .   2&#13;
B. The Incidence of Poverty is Higher Among Children  . . .   9&#13;
C.  The Distribution of Other Welfare Indicators . . . . . .  11&#13;
D.  Economic Characteristics of the Poor . . . . . . . . . .  13&#13;
E.  Trends and Perspectives  ... .    .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  16&#13;
II.  SOME HISTORICAL AND INSTITUTIONAL BACKGROUND . . . . . . . .  18&#13;
III.  AREAS OF INTERVENTION  ... .    .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  27&#13;
A.  Policies Without Trade-Offs: Increasing the&#13;
Employment Content of Growth . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  27&#13;
1.  Restrictions on Trade&#13;
2.  Subsidies to the Use of Capital&#13;
3. The Cost of Labor and Labor Incomes&#13;
4.  Labor Market Segmentation&#13;
5. The Wages and Employment Trade-Off&#13;
B. Increasing the Endowment of Capital in the Poor:&#13;
Identifying the Good Investments . . . . . . . . . . . .  40&#13;
1. Investment in Human Capital&#13;
- Preschool children&#13;
- Formal education&#13;
- Education and migration&#13;
2. Investment in Physical Assets: Small Farmers&#13;
- Without redistribution of land&#13;
- With redistribution of land&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- vi -&#13;
C.  The Basic Needs Approach .. . . . . . . . ,                 61&#13;
1. Toward a Children-Oriented Approach&#13;
2. The Calorie Deficit&#13;
- The aggregate magnitude: Its cost&#13;
- Deficits in young children&#13;
- Delivery systems&#13;
3. Options in the Hlealth Sector&#13;
- Present "urban-curative" bias&#13;
- Cost of expanding a preventive care system&#13;
4. Issues in Delivering Educational Services&#13;
- Enrollment and quality in rural areas&#13;
- Self-financing of higher education&#13;
IV.  BALANCING TIIE OPTIONS:  TRADE-OFFS BETWEEN BASIC&#13;
NEEDS AND GROWMTII  .... .     .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  84&#13;
A. Financing the Basic Needs Package   . . . . . . . . . . . .  84&#13;
B. Trade-Offs with Growth: Keeping Uncertainty Down . . . . .   88&#13;
APPENDIX I     - Additional Tables&#13;
APPENDIX II    - Tlle Self-Financing of Iligher Education:&#13;
A Model of Full Tuition and Loans&#13;
APPENDIX III   - Estimates of Declines in Investment due to&#13;
an Income Tax on the Richest 10 Percent of&#13;
Hlouseholds&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- vii -&#13;
SUMMARY&#13;
1.        These countries are experiencing an impressive GNP growth--from&#13;
6 to 7 percent--and have achieved high mean per capita incomes--from 600&#13;
to 1,200 US dollars. Ilean life expectancy has reached 60 years, and mean&#13;
caloric consumption equals caloric requirement. The distribution of these&#13;
high means is particularly striking. Income distribution is so unequal&#13;
that 25 percent of the population lives in absolute poverty, at least that&#13;
percentage suffers from calorie deficit, and variations of up to 20 years&#13;
are observed in life expectancies. Inequality dominates the levels of&#13;
these means.&#13;
Because relative income inequality seems, at best, neutral to&#13;
growth, improvements over time depend on the relative force of GNP and&#13;
population growth. The end result is that the absolute number of poor&#13;
(100 rillion people for all of Latin America) will remain constant over&#13;
time.&#13;
2.        The very fact that per capita income is high means that the&#13;
income and consumption deficits of the poor are only a small fraction of&#13;
GNP. Therefore, if well implemented, these countries can afford, today,&#13;
a substantial attack on poverty without hampering present growthl rates.&#13;
Today's growth redistribution trade-off differs from that of 25 years ago&#13;
when the per capita income of the countries in question was half the&#13;
present figure. Further, such a trade-off is more the result of inappro-&#13;
priate policy instruments, often applied in the name of improving income&#13;
distribution, than of an inherent incompatibility between growth and&#13;
redistribution.&#13;
3.        The policy package suggested here strives for an optimal mix of&#13;
a trickle-down and a basic-needs strategy.    It consists of:&#13;
(a)  Policies to increase the employment effect of present GNP&#13;
growth and to spread wage and employment gains to wider&#13;
and poorer segments of the labor force. Additional efforts&#13;
for factor costs to reflect relative scarcities must be&#13;
made. This is well known; however, this problem is dis-&#13;
tinctively serious in these countries and does not seem to&#13;
correct over time. A special effort is made to assess the&#13;
payoff of improving labor market functioning so that&#13;
increases in labor demand can be translated into stronger&#13;
increases in employment.&#13;
(-)  Policies to increase investment in the assets of the poor,&#13;
human and non-human, when these investments also have a&#13;
high return to the economy. Nlew evidence still shows that&#13;
basic education is effective and highly productive in&#13;
raising incomes. The payoff to physical investment, i.e,&#13;
a small-farmers strategy, is found to be highly country-&#13;
specific. First, landless labor represents the core of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- viii -&#13;
poverty in these countries; second, under the present&#13;
distribution and location of poor farmers, "good invest-&#13;
ments" will be exhausted rather quickly. Unless "good"&#13;
land can be redistributed, new farmers can be created&#13;
only if substantial additional investments are made.&#13;
How quickly these investments hit low rates of return&#13;
must be further studied.&#13;
(c) A strong reorientation toward basic needs, especially&#13;
toward children. Policy measures are suggested,&#13;
first, to reorient public expenditures in health,&#13;
education, nutrition, and shelter toward the poor;&#13;
and second, to increase these expenditures from 5 to 10&#13;
percent of GNP. This additional 5 percent must have&#13;
a strong basic needs content. Its features are:&#13;
- 1 percent of GNP to be spent in improving the quality&#13;
of primary rural education. A fraction of the present&#13;
public expenditure on higher education--l/2 of 1 per-&#13;
cent--must be diverted to school meals in rural areas.&#13;
This requires some self-financing of higher education&#13;
for which a proposal is outlined here.&#13;
1.5 percent to be devoted entirely to improving and&#13;
expanding primary-preventive-rural health care.&#13;
- 1 percent to be spent on preschool age nutrition&#13;
programs. In a country of US$800 per capita income,&#13;
this makes available US$160 per year for each pre-&#13;
school age child in the poorest quartile of the&#13;
population.&#13;
- 1.5 percent to be spent on shelter. Given present&#13;
households' expenditures in housing, this allows the&#13;
financing of shelter--of a unit value equal to 5 times&#13;
GNP per capita--for the poorest 30 percent of urban&#13;
households.&#13;
(d)  Policies (a) and (b) do not induce a trade-off with growth.&#13;
Policy (c) can. We estimate that if this additional 5 percent&#13;
of GNP is financed with a 12.5 percent additional income tax&#13;
on the richest 10 percent, losses in their investment could,&#13;
at maximum , lower GINP growth by 0.5 percent, i.e., from 6.5&#13;
to 6.0 percent. This is derived assuming the basic needs&#13;
package represents only consumption. The maximum trade-off&#13;
ratio between growth and distribution is estimated here to&#13;
be 1:10.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-  ix-&#13;
(e) Crucial in implementing the above policy is to keep&#13;
uncertainty down and "rules of the game" clear. This&#13;
is particularly important in mixed economies. Other-&#13;
wise, uncertainty will induce expected capital losses&#13;
all out of proportion to the transfer aimed at, and&#13;
the trade-off will be much larger. Private investment&#13;
is much more sensitive to uncertainty than to income&#13;
taxation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
r&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. POVERTY AND INEQUALITY: TUIE PRESENT&#13;
MAGNITUDE OF TU.E PROBLEM&#13;
During the last two decades, the growth performance of these&#13;
countries has been impressive. As shown in Table 1, the (unweighted) annual&#13;
growth rate of GNP has been 6.5 percent in the 1960-76 period. Despite the&#13;
extremely high rate of population growth (3.1 percent per annum), per capita&#13;
income growth is still almost twice that of developed nations during their&#13;
long run period of growth; that is, 3.4 percent for the countries in Table 1&#13;
against the figure of 2 percent reported for developed countries by Kuznets.&#13;
In 1976, per capita income ranged from $630 for Colombia to $'1,140 for Brazil,&#13;
a weighted average equal to $1,026; excluding countries with per capita&#13;
incomes above $2,000, they rank between the 68th and 90th percentiles of the&#13;
.Table 1: PER CAPITA INCOME AND GROWITH RATES&#13;
Growth Rates (1960-76)&#13;
Country          Population,    Per capita                          GNP per&#13;
1976       income, 1976    GNP    Population    capita&#13;
(millions)     (dollars)      M%        M%          M%&#13;
Brazil             110.0           1,140        7.7       2.9         4.8&#13;
Colombia            24.2             630        5.7       2.9         2.8&#13;
Ecuador              7.3             640        7.0       3.4         3.6&#13;
Mexico              62.0           1,090        6.4       3.4         3.0&#13;
Peru                15.8             800        5.5       2.9         2.6&#13;
Average: unweighted                  860        6.5       3.1         3.4&#13;
(weighted)              (1,026)&#13;
Turkey                               990        6.7       2.5         4.2&#13;
All Middle Income Countries          750        5.5       2.7         2.8&#13;
Source: World Development Report I, IBRD, 1978&#13;
1/ Simnon Kuznets, Modern Economic Growth, NIew Haven, Yale University Press.&#13;
1967.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
developing countries ordered according to ascending per capita income.&#13;
Vhat is striking is that these high country means, either per capita income,&#13;
per capita calorie consumption, or life expectancy, coexist with extremely&#13;
low values 'or these same variables for particular subgroups of the&#13;
population.&#13;
-T w many people live below a predetermined level of income defined&#13;
by its welfare consequences?  Pow sensitive are these numbers to different&#13;
atid debnt_hje estimates of the relative income distribution obtained for&#13;
these countries? Are these numbers dominated by the mean level of per capita&#13;
income? Pcw do they compare with numbers derived by examining welfare indi-&#13;
cators other than income? How sensitive is our final diagnosis to the use&#13;
of other indicators? This section addresses some of these questions by&#13;
putting together the fragmentary information available.&#13;
A. THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE BELOW; NUTRITION-RELATED LEVELS OF PER CAPITA INCOME&#13;
Incone levels associated with an ideal nutritional status of&#13;
households is an appealing criterion in defining an income poverty line.&#13;
Income is a proxy for the purchasing power of families and nutrition is&#13;
highly associated with purchasing power. This association with income is&#13;
less clear for other services such as primary education or basic health,&#13;
particularly when it is freely provided by governments; that is, consumption&#13;
1/&#13;
is then less dependent on the purchasing power of the family.&#13;
Before defining a nutrition-related-critical-income-line, the&#13;
acceptable degree of the voluntary lea'aape to "nonnutrition" expenditures&#13;
1/ N;utritional status can also be affected by governTment interventions&#13;
in water supplies and sanitation systems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
must he deterrined.   Two suchl leakages occur:  nonfood expenditures and&#13;
the 'inefficiency" of the present diet. In other words, existing food&#13;
expenditures would often yield a higher nutritional content if properly&#13;
1/&#13;
allocated among foods.    Two extreme definitions of a poverty line thus&#13;
arise: first, the least-cost diet wherein neither leakage has a wyelfare&#13;
value; second, the level of income at which nutrition requirements are&#13;
achieved while maintaining households' intra-food and food/nonfood&#13;
preferences.&#13;
Ongoing research at ECLA has developed a combination of these&#13;
two criteria in defining poverty lines for urban and rural Latin America.&#13;
Intra-food adjustments were made compatible with obseived patterns of food&#13;
preferences so as to increase the efficiency of diets. The optimal diet&#13;
in terms of calorie and protein requirements was priced in urban and rural&#13;
areas, and the propensity to spend on non-food items was considered in&#13;
2/&#13;
arriving at the poverty line.    These critical per capita income figures,&#13;
in 1976 dollars, appear in Table 2. They range between $200 and $250, as&#13;
compared with a mean figure of $300 derived in earlier experiments where&#13;
3/&#13;
calorie income preferences were fully maintained.&#13;
1/ There is ample evidence showing that, even at low levels of income,&#13;
calorie-income elasticities are low. Increases in incore result in a&#13;
sharp tendency to turn to more expensive sources of calories.&#13;
2/ For details on the precise methodology, see S. Piniera and S. Molina,&#13;
"Extreme Poverty in Latin Arerica Project," ECLA (preliminary).&#13;
Pedro Tejo, "Un 'Metodo para Estimar Consunos M4inimos de Alimentos para&#13;
los Paises de America Latina," November 1976 (ECLA-IBRD) Research Project).&#13;
3/ See Reutlinger and Selowsky, Malnutrition and Poverty,   World Bank Staff&#13;
Occasional Papers, Number 23, Johns lpopkins Universitv Press, 1976.&#13;
This estimate is based on cross section Latin Arerican data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2: TOTAL PER CAPITA INCOME REQUIRED TO VOLUNTARILY ALLOCATE TO FOOD AN&#13;
EXPENDITURE EQUAL TO THE COST OF AN "EFFICIENT" FOOD BASKET&#13;
(1976 dollars)&#13;
Urban Areas                         Rural Areas                         National&#13;
Cost of    Non-     Implicit       Cost of     Non-     Implicit       Cost of     Non-     Implicit&#13;
Country       food      food     required         food      food     required         food      food     required&#13;
basket    expense    income         basket    expense    income        basket     expense    income&#13;
Brazil         150       139       289             108       83        191             124       113       237&#13;
Colombia       129       120       249              97       73        170             113       102       215&#13;
Ecuador        162       150       312             121       92        213             135       118       230&#13;
Mexico         136       126        262            102       77        179             120       110       230&#13;
Peru           134       124       258              99       75        174             114       102       216&#13;
Sources:  S. Piniera and S. 2lolina: Extreme Poverty in Latin America Project, ECLA (preliminary).&#13;
Pedro Tejo, "Un metodo para estimar consumos minimos de alimentos para los paises de America Latina,"&#13;
November 1976 (ECLA-IBRD Research Project).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
W,hat is the number of people living below these poverty lines?&#13;
HIow sensitive are these numbers to the use of the several, and sometimes&#13;
quite different and debaLaable estimates of the distribution of income?&#13;
Given the wide range of estimates reported, it is helpful to explore how&#13;
the number of poor people change under extreme ranges of values. (And&#13;
this will also be true in the future for countries wlhere at present only&#13;
one estimate is available.)&#13;
Table 3 presents selected estimates of the income distribution&#13;
for these countries. Other estimates have not been reported because their&#13;
reliability is even more questionable.&#13;
Table 4 presents three hypothetical distributions covering most&#13;
of the range observed in Table 3. The first is the most unequal, a share&#13;
of 2 percent and 7 percent for the poorest 20 and 40 percent of the popu-&#13;
lation, respectively. In the second estimate, these shares become 3.5 and&#13;
10.5 percent. These ranges cover most of the estimates for Latin America.&#13;
In the third distribution, the share of all four deciles are 25 percent&#13;
higher, reflecting the "better" estimate in Colombia and the present situa-&#13;
tion in Turkey. Using these distributions and the country per capita income&#13;
figure of Table 1, Table 5 derives the fraction of the population with&#13;
incomes below the poverty lines.&#13;
Because Mlexico and Brazil have almost the same country per capita&#13;
income and very similar poverty lines, they have the same fraction of&#13;
individuals in poverty for a given hypothetical income distribution,ranging&#13;
from 13 percent for distribution II to 24 percent for distribution I. The&#13;
latter figure becomes more plausible if the recent income distribution&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3: THE DISTRIBUTION Of INCOME&#13;
Colombia       Peru           Mexico                 Brazil           Ecuador    Turkey&#13;
TM-              rr =1964        1968   1975    1960    1970   1973      1970      1973&#13;
a/&#13;
(1) Poorest 20%            4.0-/  5.2       2.4      3.5    3.4    1.9     3.5     3.1    1.8       1.8       3.4&#13;
(2) Poorest 40%            9.6   14.3       7.4     10.3   10.5    8.1    11.5   10.0     7.0       5.2      11.3&#13;
(3) Richest  5%           33.7   22.2      43.0     28.7   27.9   30.3    27.7   34.9    38.2      43.0&#13;
(4) Richest 10           49.4   39.3      52.8     41.9   42.1   43.5    39.7   47.8    51.9      56.6      39.1&#13;
Ratio of shares&#13;
(3)/(1)                8.4    4.2     17.9       8.0    8.2   15.9     7.9   11.2    21.2      23.8&#13;
(4)/(1)               12.3    7.5      22.0     12.0   12.4   22.9    11.3   15.4    28.8      31.4      11.5&#13;
(4)/(2)                5.1    2.7      7.1       4.1    4.0    5.4     3.4    4.8     7.4      10.9       3.5&#13;
Gini coefficient            .57    .50      .61      .51    .52     .56     .50    .56    .61       .68        .50&#13;
Composition of poorest&#13;
202:   rural                     .65      .80                    .75?                   .67p'                .72&#13;
urban                     .35      .20                    .25                    .33                 .28&#13;
a/ Refers to bottom quartile.&#13;
b/ Composition of the poorest 45 percent of total households.&#13;
c/ Composition of the poorest 32 percent of the population.&#13;
Sources:  Colombia - 1964 - Economically Accive Population:   Miguel Urrutia, "Income Distribution in Colombia"&#13;
International Labor Review, March-April 1976.&#13;
1974 - Households: Marcelo Selowsky, Who Benefits from Governmeat Expenditure, A Case&#13;
Study of Colombia, Oxford University Press (forthcoming).&#13;
Peru:      Labor Force:  Richard Webb, Government Policy and the Distribution of Income in Peru,&#13;
1963-1973, Harvard University Press, 1977.&#13;
Mexico:    Households: World Bank Mission Estimates from Household Survey Data.&#13;
Brazil  -  1960)- Economically Active Population:   C. Langoni,  Distribucao do   Renta  e Desenvolvi-&#13;
1970) mento Economico do Brasil.&#13;
1973 - Economically Active Population: Pesquisa National por Amostre de Domicilios, IBGE.&#13;
Turkey  - Households:   K. Dervis and S. Robinson, "The Sources and Structure of Inequality in Turkey&#13;
(1950-73),mimeo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
Table 4: SHARES OF POOREST DECILES ACCORDING TO&#13;
HYPOTHETICAL DISTRIBUTIONS OF INCOME&#13;
(percentages)&#13;
Very                 Typical              Moderate&#13;
Decile                Unequal               Inequality          Inequality&#13;
I                     II                  III&#13;
1                    0.67                    1.50                1.87&#13;
2                    1.33                    2.00                2.50&#13;
3                    2.00                    3.00                3.75&#13;
4                    3.00                    4.00                5.0&#13;
Poorest 40%            7.00                   10.50               13.12&#13;
Table 5: PERCENTAGE OF "POOR" UNDER HYPOTHETICAL&#13;
INCOME DISTRIBUTIONS&#13;
(Percent)&#13;
Country                I            II           III         Midpoint&#13;
Brazil                    24            13                         18.5&#13;
I (.62)±'       (.61)&#13;
Mexico                 I   24           13                         18.5&#13;
(.62)        (.61)&#13;
Ecuador                1  40            35                         37.5&#13;
(.65)        (.60)&#13;
Peru                      35     1      24                         29.5&#13;
(0.6)   1    (.62)&#13;
Colombia                                26.5 t       22            24.2&#13;
(.57)        (.68)&#13;
I                  ~~~~~~20.3&#13;
Weighted mean                          25.4&#13;
Note: Values in parentheses show the share of rural families among the poor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
figures reported for these countries are accepted. The fraction of poor&#13;
is higher in Colombia, and the results do not seem sensitive to the use&#13;
of distributions II or III. Ecuador and Peru have reported distributions&#13;
closer to I, which implies that 40 and 35 percent of the people live in&#13;
poverty.&#13;
Adjustments for the higher cost of living in urban areas reduces&#13;
the rural share in the poverty group: while 75 percent of the population&#13;
in the bottom quintile is rural, only 60 percent of the population below&#13;
the poverty line is rural.&#13;
By using the most plausible hypothetical distributions, the weighted&#13;
(by the population of each country) mean figure of Table 5 yields a value of&#13;
25.4 percent of families in poverty, namely, those families who arp unable&#13;
to finance, given their food-nonfood preferences, their calorie require-&#13;
ments through an "efficient diet." This figure should be (and is) lower&#13;
than an estimate of the observed fraction of people experiencing calorie&#13;
1/&#13;
deficits, 36 percent for 1975.&#13;
Finally, it is interesting to observe the sensitivity of the&#13;
aggregate income gap--the fraction of GNP that, if transferred, would lift&#13;
poor families to the poverty line--to the alternative income distributions&#13;
I and II. Even under I, one cannot escape the conclusion that these&#13;
countries do have the resource capability of solving the problem of extreme&#13;
poverty.&#13;
1/ Reutlinger and Selowsky, Malnutrition and Poverty, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Aggregate Income Gaps (Z), 1976&#13;
I               II&#13;
Brazil                  2.2             0.7&#13;
Colombia                6.5             3.6&#13;
Ecuador                 8.9             5.4&#13;
Mexico                  2.3             0.3&#13;
Peru                    4.1             1.9&#13;
B. THIE ICIDEMICE OF POVERTY IS 1HIGHER AMONiG YOUWiG CHILDREN&#13;
The fact that poor families have larger family sizes gives origin&#13;
to a larger incidence of poverty among children: the fraction of children&#13;
that are poor is larger than the fraction of adults.   What is the precise&#13;
magnitude of this differential incidence of poverty and what are its&#13;
implications for analyzing the consequences of poverty?&#13;
Table 6 shows that wlhereas 16.5 percent of all adults suffer the&#13;
welfare consequences of being in the poorest quintile, the figure for young&#13;
children is 27 percent. If poverty is defined by the welfare consequences&#13;
of living in households accounting for the bottom 40 percent of the popu-&#13;
lation, the conclusion is that 50 percent of young children are poor, while&#13;
only 35 percent of adults are poor. Poverty, then, is more a "children's&#13;
problem."&#13;
This way of presenting the poverty problem becomes more relevant:&#13;
(a) if the welfare consequences of living in tne bottom deciles are measured&#13;
in terms of different indicators for children than for adults; that is,&#13;
anthropometric deficit, life expectancy at birth, etc.; and (b) if the&#13;
propensity to spend in children--where expenditure is broadly defined,&#13;
encompassing physical and psychological elements--from increases in house-&#13;
hold per capita income is "low." Policy instruments to increase the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
Table 6: URBAN LATIN AMERICA: CHILDREN (BELOW AGE 10) AND ADULTS&#13;
BELONGING TO EACH INCOME DECILE&#13;
Percentage of total        Percentage of total&#13;
Fraction of               number of children in       number of adults in&#13;
population          /a    the country belonging       the country belonging&#13;
(deciles)        f           to each decile /b           to each decile&#13;
.10        .46                 14%                        8.0%&#13;
.10        .43                 13%                        8.5%&#13;
Poorest 20%     .445               27%                       16.5%&#13;
.10        .40                 12%                        9.0%&#13;
.10        .36                 11%                        9.5%&#13;
Poorest 40%     .41                50%                       35.0&#13;
Country         .33               .33                          .67&#13;
/a  From Table A-1.&#13;
/b Denoting N as children and T as population. The fraction of the&#13;
total number of children in the country that belong to a decile i&#13;
can be written:&#13;
=  g (i )\t1)                  s((0.1)  O (0.1) (f&#13;
N.                 ~~~~~(NJTj)            / &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
earnings capacity of the family will have a slow effect on the extent of&#13;
children's poverty.  This issue will be addressed below.&#13;
C. T7E DISTRIBUTION CF OT]iER WELFARE I)NDICATOPS&#13;
During the last two decades, the countries in question experienced&#13;
substantial gains in the mean level of selected welfare indicators. 'lean&#13;
life expectancy at birth in 1975 ranged from 56 to 63 years, with gains&#13;
between 5 to 10 years since 1960.   Infant mortality, between 50 and 70 per&#13;
thousand in 1975, declined by 30 to 40 deaths after 1960. In the 1974-75&#13;
period, the mean calorie consumption of these countries reached levels&#13;
between .95 and 1.1 times the mean calorie requirement.&#13;
Fow unequal is the distribution of these indicators across the&#13;
population? Can one observe the same pattern here as that seen for per&#13;
capita income. that is, "good" means coexisting with a large fraction of&#13;
the population showing low levels of these welfare indicators? Because,&#13;
unlike income data, country wide information on these distributions is not&#13;
yet available, many must be inferred from case studies and submeans for&#13;
regions.&#13;
In Brazil, differences in 'ife expectancy of 21 years are found&#13;
between the poorest groups in Rural Nlortheast and the richest group in&#13;
urban areas. Factors other than incone are associated with these differences,&#13;
since even within the poorest income group differences of up to 20 years&#13;
1/&#13;
can be found across regions.   Sharp differences in child mortality across&#13;
regions are found in Mexico and Ecuador. In Mexico, percentages range&#13;
1/ See Table A-2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
from 39.2 to 105.9 deaths per 1,000 live births in different states, and&#13;
1/&#13;
in Ecuador from 45.4 to 122.1.&#13;
Perhaps malnutrition best reflects the distributive problems in&#13;
these countties. A large number of undernourished individuals--in terms&#13;
of caloric .ntal:e or anthropometric deficit--coexist with a mean per capita&#13;
2/&#13;
calorie cor ,umption equal to or above requirements.&#13;
The distribution of calorie intake at the country level was&#13;
estimate' * food consumption surveys in Brazil in the early 1960s and in&#13;
Turkey in 1974.   (The 1974 Brazil ENDEF survey will provide a more recent&#13;
3/&#13;
and reliable source.) The results are reported below.&#13;
Calorie consumption as a          Percentage of the population&#13;
fraction of requirements            Turkey            Brazil&#13;
below.75                      17.4%             11.9%&#13;
below.90                      41.0%             29.1%&#13;
Mean per capita consumption          1.04              1.07&#13;
as a raction of requirements&#13;
Although they report a country mean consumption above requirements&#13;
(consistent with FAO Food Balances) these surveys show 41 and 29 percent of&#13;
the population with at least a 10 percent calorie deficit in Turkey and&#13;
Brazil, respectively.&#13;
1/ See Table A-3.&#13;
2/ See Table A-4.&#13;
3/ The requirements take into account the demographic composition of the&#13;
population. Brazil: Fundacio Getulio Vargas, "Food Consumption in&#13;
Brazil, Family Budget Studies in the early 60s." Reported in Malnutri-&#13;
tion and Poverty; Turkey: Nutrition in Turkey, National Nutrition,&#13;
Health and Food Consumption Survey, Ankara, 1974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
A review of different studies where undernutrition in young&#13;
children is measured in terms of weight deficits shows, as expected, a&#13;
higher incidence of undernutrition than in the total population. In Turkey,&#13;
20 percent of preschool children are underweight, according to Turkish&#13;
1/                                                                   2/&#13;
standards; in rural Colombia the figure is 65 percent for preschool children.&#13;
A breakdown of these figures for different degrees of undernutrition shows&#13;
that, even by choosing a less strict standard (degrees II and III, i.e., a&#13;
deficit larger than 25 percent of the Gomez standard), between 20 and 40&#13;
3/&#13;
percent of preschool children in rural Mlexico are malnourished.&#13;
D. THE ECONOMIC CHARACTERISTICS OF THE FAMILIES IN THE POVERTY GROUP&#13;
Most surveys indicate that when households are classified by per&#13;
capita household income, most of the poorest 20 to 40 percent of families&#13;
live in rural areas. This is shown in Tables A-6 to A-9, for example,&#13;
where the share of rural households in the poverty group ranges from 58&#13;
percent for Colombia (where rural households are those in towns with fewer&#13;
than 1,500 inhabitants) to 82.7 percent for Peru. Brazil's figure falls&#13;
between 64.3 and 72.9 percent, whereas Mexico and Turkey's figure is&#13;
approximately 75 percent. In several countries, rural poverty is associated&#13;
with particular regions; in the case of Brazil half the families in the&#13;
poverty group are located in the Rural Northeast, and in the case of Peru,&#13;
in the Mancha India.&#13;
1i Nutrition in Turkey, op. cit.&#13;
2/ La Politica de Salud, Departamento Nacional de Planeacion, Republica&#13;
de Colombia, Color Osprey Impresores Ltda., Bogota, D.E., Colombia.&#13;
3/ See Table A-5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Clearly, the above figures exaggerate the participation of rural&#13;
households in poverty since the purchasing power of the reported income&#13;
figures must be corrected by different price levels, particularly those of&#13;
food. In the case of Peru, for example, such adjustments lowered the&#13;
1/&#13;
percentage of rural households in the poverty group to 59 percent7- The use&#13;
of differential poverty lines provided by ECLA for urbnn and rural areas&#13;
show that approximately 60 percent of households in the poverty group are&#13;
rural.&#13;
How are these households linked to the urban and rural economies?&#13;
W4hat are their sources of income? These are important questions for identi-&#13;
fying points of "olicy intervention. Ideally, one would like to classify&#13;
rural louseholds according to the relative importance of their share of&#13;
income from ownership of land, sharecropping, and the provision of wage&#13;
labor to other farmers.   Because the typical population census or household&#13;
survey from which these poverty groups are constructed usually does not provide&#13;
this data, sectorial (i.e., agricultural census or urban employment) surveys&#13;
must be used to derive this information.&#13;
Scattered evidence tends to show that the mixture of sources of&#13;
earnings for the rural poor varies considerably in the countries explored.&#13;
In Peru, 80 percent of the rural poor are subsistence farmers of distinct&#13;
ethnic background. "Subsistence farmers are mostly Indian, Quechua or&#13;
Aymara speaking, and in 1961 about 70% were illiterate. Their principal&#13;
source of livelihood was on the average about 0.9 hectares of Sierra crop-&#13;
land, three heads of cattle, and some other livestock. Most earned some&#13;
1/ Vinod Thomas, "Tae ,leasurement of Spatial Differences in Poverty: the&#13;
Case of Peru,"World Bank Staff lorking Paper No. 273, January 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
cash income by seasonal labor on larger farms or occasional sales of&#13;
1/&#13;
livestock products."    In Colombia, approximately half the rural households&#13;
in poverty are small producers, the rest landless labor. Nevertheless, even&#13;
small producers perceived at least two-thirds of their earnings as wage&#13;
2/&#13;
labor in larger farms.&#13;
In contrast to Peru, where most rural poor are subsistence farmers,&#13;
the evidence for Brazil shows that most of the poor are landless labor.&#13;
According to the SUDENE-IBRD survey in Northeast Brazil, only 1.7 million&#13;
of the 6 million rural labor force (heads of households plus working family&#13;
members of landowners) own land. Of this 6 million, "about three million&#13;
have no access to land, and subsist on temporary employment or scrounge out&#13;
a living on lands so poor or remote that they were not captured by any of&#13;
the censuses, cadastral survey or the SUDENE/IBRD survey. These three million&#13;
and their families constitute the hard core of poverty in the Northeast.&#13;
Most landowners (even if they own only two or three hectares of poor land),&#13;
sharecroppers, renters and permanent workers, realize real incomes at or&#13;
above the absolute poverty line, but the remaining persons presumably do not,&#13;
3/&#13;
and this situation is easily traceable to their lack of access to land."&#13;
The above evidence shows that rural poverty cannot be characterized&#13;
by a single, simple occupational classification. Small farmers do not seem&#13;
1/ Richard C. Webb, Government Policy and the Distribution of Income in&#13;
Peru, 1963-1973, Harvard University Press, 1977, p. 13.&#13;
2/ Urrutia and Berry, Income Distribution in Colombia, Yale University Press,&#13;
1967.&#13;
3/ -. Iutcher and P. Scandizzo, The Agricultural Economy of ITortheast&#13;
Brazil, forthcoming.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
to represent the core of rural poverty, as is usually believed. For most&#13;
countries, lan4less labor is at least equally represented in the poverty&#13;
group, and wage earnings represent an important component of income, even in&#13;
the case of subsistence farmers. This has important policy implications,&#13;
as will be seen below.&#13;
Who are the urban poor and what are their occupational charac-&#13;
teristics? Two patterns seem to emerge from the data: 15ost of the urban&#13;
poor are located in nonmetropolitan areas (as shown in Tables A-7 and&#13;
A-10), particularly concentrated in small towns; and about half of them&#13;
are associated with commerce and thle service sector. Depending on the&#13;
country, between half and two-thirds of heads of households in the poor&#13;
families are salaried employees, the rest self-employed.&#13;
There is no single relationship between unemployment status and&#13;
households in poverty.  Open unemployment does not seem to characterize&#13;
the households in the poverty group. A recent study at ECLA shows that&#13;
most heads of households in the poverty group are employed, although a&#13;
large percentage of them are underemployed, working fewer than 39 hours&#13;
a week, and willing to work additional hours. This information is consistent&#13;
with the estimates of the ILO, which show that open unemployment in Latin&#13;
America is approximately 5 percent, while underemployment characterized&#13;
around 30 percent of the labor force.&#13;
E.  TRENDS ANID PERSPECTIVES&#13;
Evidence indicates that relative income inequality has, at best,&#13;
remained constant over these long periods of sustained economic growth.&#13;
1/ S. Pinera, "Cuantificaciln, analisis y descripcion de la pobreza en&#13;
algunos paises Latinoamericanos," Provecto Interinstitucional de&#13;
pobreza critica, ECLA, 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
Although the fraction of people in poverty lhas declined, the force of&#13;
population growth has resulted in a constant absolute number of people in&#13;
poverty. In Latin America, 100 million people live and will remain in&#13;
absolute poverty during the next two decades.&#13;
Despite a constant number of poor, the economic capability of&#13;
solving the problem of poverty has increased substantially. The aggregate&#13;
income gap defined earlier declined from 8 percent in 1960 to 4.5 percent&#13;
1/&#13;
in 1970, and today does not exceed 3 percent.&#13;
These figures clearly show that in this typology of countries&#13;
poverty is, and will increasingly be, a purely distributive problem rather&#13;
than the result of a lack of aggregate resources. Eliminating extreme&#13;
poverty while maintaining a high growth rate should be feasible. It is&#13;
the option explored in this report.&#13;
1/ S. Piniera, "lSe benefician los pobres del crecimiento economico?",&#13;
ECLA, mimeo, 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
II. HISTORICAL ANJD INSTITUTIONAL BACKGROUND&#13;
The present distribution of income and consumption is the result&#13;
of three factors: (a) the distribution of human and nonhuman assets in the&#13;
population; (b) the demand for the services of these assets derived from&#13;
the structure and functioning of the economic system; and (c) net transfers&#13;
induced by the public sector (taxes and expenditures).&#13;
Ideally we would like to know how much of the past evolution and&#13;
present levels of inequality and poverty can be explained by these different&#13;
factors; to what extent was the trend in these factors the result of forces&#13;
exogenous to public policy on the one hand, and attributable to government&#13;
intervention on the other; and most important, what might have resulted if&#13;
alternative government policies had been followed, particularly if those&#13;
policy alternatives involved a trade off between redistribution and growth.&#13;
We have neither the data nor the theory to fully explore these&#13;
questions, and it is conceivable we never will. This section simply&#13;
speculates about the probable effect that various initial conditions, trends&#13;
exogenous to public policy and government interventions had, through the&#13;
mechanisms described above in (a) to (c), on poverty and inequality. We&#13;
think this framework can be useful in identifying future points of government&#13;
intervention.&#13;
A. INITIAL CONDITIONS&#13;
Initial conditions must be discussed in relative terms, i.e.,&#13;
relatively to other typologies of countries. One comparison to be made is&#13;
with other middle income countries such as Costa Rica, Taiwan, and Korea&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
which, at similar levels of per capita income, have achieved a much more&#13;
equal distribution of income.&#13;
The countries discussed in this report are characterized by a&#13;
strong historical inequality in the distribution of wealth, particularly&#13;
land. Except in Mexico, land reform programs never took place. The dis-&#13;
tribution of nonphysical assets, especially education, followed the&#13;
distribution of family wealth given the small role of public education in&#13;
the prewar periods. In many countries, these inequalities have been&#13;
associated with the ethnic composition of the population, creating strong&#13;
cultural segmentations.&#13;
The sheer size of these countries, their geographical complexity,&#13;
and their strong differences in resource endowments across regions, compounds&#13;
the problem of ethnic segmentation. In several countries, the ethnic sub-&#13;
populations are located in the poorest regions, resulting in cultural and&#13;
geographical segmentation that diminishes the mobility of capital and labor&#13;
and dampens the potential of such mobility for improving regional equality.&#13;
These conditions are quite different from those of countries like Costa Rica,&#13;
Taiwan, and Korea.&#13;
B. TRENDS EXOGENOUS TO PUBLIC POLICY&#13;
TwIo basic trends have prevented improvements in the distribution of&#13;
income over time. One is demographic growth, unparalleled in most develop-&#13;
ment experiences; the second has been the emergence of strong tendencies in&#13;
the economy toward dualism and segmentation in most factor markets, creating&#13;
large economic rents and preventing the transmission of the gains of growth&#13;
to wider segments of the population.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
In most Latin American countries, population and labor growth&#13;
have fluctuated around 3 percent per annum over the last couple of decades,&#13;
a substantially higher rate than that experienced by most other developing&#13;
countries. (See Table 7.) At these rates, one might expect unskilled&#13;
labor to be absorbed by the economy only at declining wages. That this&#13;
does not seem to be the case is partly explained by the high growth rate&#13;
at which the urban economy has absorbed rural migration.&#13;
A second feature of demographic growth is the different rate of&#13;
population growth for different income groups. There is evidence that the&#13;
population of lower income families is increasing at a faster rate than&#13;
total population. Despite lack of direct data on demographic growth for&#13;
Table 7 : POPULATION AND LABOR FORCE GROWTH RATES&#13;
Average Annual Growth Rates&#13;
(percentages)&#13;
Total Population                 Labor Force&#13;
1960-70      1970-75           1960-70      1970-75&#13;
Brazil                   2.9          2.9              2.8          2.9&#13;
Colombia                2.8           2.8              3.0          3.2&#13;
Ecuador                 3.3           3.5              3.1          3.2&#13;
Mexico                   3.4          3.5              2.8          3.3&#13;
Peru                     2.9          2.9              2.1          3.0&#13;
All middle income        2.7          2.7              2.3          2.7&#13;
All low income           2.4          2.4              1.9          2.0&#13;
Source:  World Development Report I. The World Bank, 19Q78.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
families with different per capita incomes, regional data provides some&#13;
evidence. Using state data on mean per capita income, fertility, and&#13;
mortality rates, preliminary estimates for Brazil showed substantial differ-&#13;
ences in demographic growth at different per capita income levels. In the&#13;
poorest states of Northeast Brazil, natural population growth (3.5% a year)&#13;
1/&#13;
was almost double that of the richest states in the country (1.95% a year).&#13;
What are the implications of these differential rates of population&#13;
growth? First, unskilled labor supply tends to grow at a higher rate than&#13;
the total labor force; if, in addition (and we do have some evidence on this),&#13;
the demand for unskilled labor grows less than for skilled for a given GNP&#13;
growth, the effect on the unskilled wage becomes even worse.&#13;
The second implication of a higher population growth in lower&#13;
income groups is its effect on their per capita capital formation, human&#13;
and nonhuman. Unless strong public interventions complement the low savings&#13;
rate in the poorer groups, such as the provision of education and comple-&#13;
mentary physical assets when they already own some capital, the historical&#13;
trends will be characterized by a widening gap in the rates of capital&#13;
accumulation per capita across income groups.&#13;
The past tendency of all socioeconomic groups to create barriers&#13;
and pressures to market entry, what might be called "rent seeking behavior,"&#13;
is unique to several of these countries, and quite different from the&#13;
experiences of other countries like Taiwan and Korea. Part of this behavior&#13;
has been induced by government policies such as quantitative restrictions&#13;
1/ Constantino Lluch "Brazil: World Bank Human Resources Special Report,"&#13;
Annex II, draft, August 4, 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
and licensing in trade, credit rationing, and wage legislation increasing&#13;
the labor cost to the urban modern sector far above the opportunity cost&#13;
of labor. As a result, any sustained increase in the demand for labor has&#13;
been mostly translated into increases in wages for a relatively small&#13;
fraction of labor already employed in those sectors: lack of competition&#13;
within labor has led to higher wages for the few already employed rather&#13;
than in spreading that additional income to other workers through increased&#13;
employment. rhis explains part of the different employment performance&#13;
when we compare these Latin American countries on the one hand, and Korea&#13;
and Taiwan on the other.&#13;
As shown in several studies, labor market segmentation, defined&#13;
as wage differences (for labor of equal skill or education) associated to&#13;
particular occupation or sector of employment, explains a larger part of income&#13;
differentials of workers. Earnings surveys in urban Peru indicate that,&#13;
controlling for all personal attributes of workers (such as education, age,&#13;
and experience), size of firm, which probably is the best proxy for&#13;
unionization or restrictions to entry, had the same contribution in explain-&#13;
1/&#13;
ing wage differences as workers' education.&#13;
C. GOVEPNMENT POLICIES&#13;
i.        Rather than reviewing all past government policies that might have&#13;
had a redistributive effect, we examine those (a) undertaken with a distrib-&#13;
utive objective in mind but which, because of their implementation, were&#13;
1/ 0. Altimir and S. Piniera, "Decomposition Analysis of the Inequality of&#13;
Earnings in Latin American Countries": ECLA-World Bank Project,&#13;
August 1977, mimeo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
less successful than predicted; (b) which were under consideration but&#13;
judged incompatible with other objectives, particularly growth; (c)&#13;
abandoned because they meant a degree of redistribution unacceptable under&#13;
past political scenarios.&#13;
Two major features characterized the implementation of policies&#13;
that in spirit had a distributive objective. First, the implementation&#13;
was to be fiscally cheap: that is, the instruments selected were not to over-&#13;
burden the fiscal budget. Second, many were accompanied with an atmosphere&#13;
of political rhetoric that induced a degree of uncertainty and expected&#13;
capital losses completely out of proportion (and unnecessary) to the real&#13;
transfer among income groups being sought.&#13;
Policy instruments that were fiscally cheap and geared to a&#13;
distributive objective usually had two consequences.   If they did show a&#13;
positive distributive effect, it was only short term; in the long run, it&#13;
backfired. Second, they induced a trade off with economic efficiency and&#13;
growth that alternative implementations would have avoided. Trade inter-&#13;
ventions are good examples. Several of the forced industrial import&#13;
substitutions policies by means of tariff protection were undertaken to&#13;
increase industrial output and employment in the short run. In most&#13;
countries the long-term effect was a disincentive to the growth of the export&#13;
sector and of the most efficient import competing activities, particularly&#13;
agriculture.     Several studies show that the long-term employment effect&#13;
was completely opposite to the short term objectives originally intended by&#13;
these policies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Policies to reduce the price of foodstuffs at minimum fiscal cost,&#13;
sometimes even increasing government revenues, were also classical examples.&#13;
Fiscal expediency always meant that lower prices to consumers could only be&#13;
achieved by reducing incentives to domestic producers. Price controls on&#13;
food prices have zero fiscal cost but create black markets that, in the long&#13;
run, never benefit poor consumers. When foodstuffs were imported, subsidies on&#13;
imports only (not on total consumption) meant lower prices to consumers at&#13;
the expense of disincentives to domestic producers in the agricultural sector;&#13;
the larger the share of domestic production in total consumption, the cheaper&#13;
becomes the instrument (the price to consui.emrs can be reduced at a minimal&#13;
fiscal cost) but the higher the real resource or efficiency loss.   When&#13;
foodstuffs were initially exported, export taxes or export    prohibitions&#13;
became cheaper instruments to reduce domestic prices than general consumption&#13;
subsidies. In short, lower internal prices were reached only by discouraging&#13;
domestic production and exports, fiscal expediency always induced a trade off&#13;
between distributive oblectives and economic efficiency objectives.&#13;
Government interventions raising the cost of labor above its&#13;
opportunity cost, either by minimum wage legislation, tenure legislation,&#13;
or social security contributions, were conceived with the objective of&#13;
guaranteeing the real income and employment of urban workers. In several&#13;
countries, such legislation has become substantially more important than&#13;
that observed today in Western Europe.&#13;
These policies--quite different from those undertaken by countries&#13;
like Taiwan and Korea, where employment growth was a key feature of devel-&#13;
opment--created strong rents among labor and prevented the increase in labor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
demand to absorb the already high growth of the labor force. Again, these&#13;
employment objectives could have been better served by more(fiscally)&#13;
expensive instruments; increases in Social Security benefits could have&#13;
been financed by the general budget instead of through a tax on the employ-&#13;
ment of labor. Further, employment of unskilled labor could have been&#13;
subsidized by tax exemptions proportional to the additional labor employed&#13;
relative to a moving base year.&#13;
ii.       Economic policies in general, and redistributive policies in&#13;
particular, have fluctuated widely over time in most of these countries,&#13;
imparting a high degree of uncertainty and unpredictability to the decision&#13;
making process of most economic units. This has been a distinctive feature&#13;
of the history of these countries relatively to other country experiences.&#13;
The economic costs of uncertainty have been particularly high and&#13;
unnecessary during periods when more radical redistributive policies were under&#13;
consideration. For example, tax and land reforms occurred during political&#13;
regimes when the very concept of private property was being reevaluated--at&#13;
least in the arena of political rhetoric. The resulting uncertainty about future&#13;
capital losses was usually all out of proportion to the rea'L trar.sfer carried&#13;
out by these reforms%. The resulting capital flightse and reductions of private&#13;
investment could have been avoided if clearer rules of the game concerning&#13;
'"not expropriatable sectors" had been established. These lessons are crucial&#13;
for any redistributive policies to be undertaken in the future.&#13;
iii.      Much of the present inequality can undoubtedly be explained by a&#13;
low level of public investment in the assets of the poor.  What explains&#13;
this behavior of public policy? To what extent was this policy defended on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
the grounds it represented a trade off with growth, namely, those investments&#13;
having a lower return than alternative investments? To what extent did it&#13;
represent   a real underinvestment (their return being higher than those of&#13;
alternative investments) only explainable by past political scenarios under&#13;
which transfers of investment across income groups were unfeasible?&#13;
It is impossible to identify the extent to which this behavior of&#13;
public policy can be attributed to either of these two factors. The implicit&#13;
importance of each factor can be evaluated only if the rate of return to&#13;
invest in the poor is measured: if most of that underinvestment yielded high&#13;
returns, the trade off issue cannot be used as an argument.&#13;
What is certain is that the trade off issue was unduly exaggerated&#13;
in the past. The growth-distribution trade off resulted from extremely&#13;
mechanistic views on the factors determining GNP growth, implicit in most&#13;
postwar growth models. In these models (the best example being the labor&#13;
surplus model), asset formation in the poor did not have a driving force on&#13;
growth. Investment meant physical capital accumulation in the industrial&#13;
sector, the poor benefftting only through an increased demand for labor.&#13;
Any transfer to the poor, through taxing capital incomes in the industrial&#13;
sector, meant a consumption transfer lowering aggregate investment. No such&#13;
transfer was considered to have an asset creation effect on the poor, i.e.,&#13;
to have had an investment component in itself. A more modern and flexible&#13;
interpretation of this view is that no asset formation in the poor, in small&#13;
farmers or investing in human capital of the poor,could have a rate of&#13;
return larger than investment in physical capital with which the poor are&#13;
associated as hired labor. This remains a hypothesis to be tested&#13;
empirically.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
III. AREAS OF INTERVENTION&#13;
Areas of intervention for poverty alleviation can be classified&#13;
according to multiple criteria. They are grouped here into three major&#13;
categories. The first includes the elimination of distortions that are&#13;
adverse to a stronger trickle down effect of growth. Its objective is to&#13;
increase the employment content of growth. The second area refers to&#13;
investment policies to increase the endowment of human and physical capital&#13;
of the poor. Here we are only interested in high yielding investments,&#13;
namely, those that are good for the poor but also for the growth rate. Both&#13;
sets of policies have two features. First, they increase the welfare of the&#13;
poor by increasing their earnings capacity. Second, they do not impose a&#13;
trade-off between distribution and growth or efficiency. On the contrary,&#13;
they can benefit both, equity and growth.&#13;
The third area is "basic needs," the provision of goods and services&#13;
required to achieve a minimum level of "quality of life." In some circum-&#13;
stances, these policies can also increase the long-term productive capacity of&#13;
the poor. Sections A, B, and C address these three areas of intervention.&#13;
A. POLICIES WITHIOUT TRADE-OFFS: ELIMINATING DISTORTIONS THAT ARE ADVERSE&#13;
TO BOTH EMPLOYMENT AND GROWTH 1/&#13;
This section reviews policies to eliminate those distortions that&#13;
not only have,by definition,a negative effect on output, but also adversely&#13;
affect employment. Of special concern is the employment generation effect of&#13;
1/ This section identifies distortions to be removed and past policies to&#13;
be replaced. It does not attempt to spell out the specific way and&#13;
timing of the suggested changes. This should be addressed by specific&#13;
studies in the fields of trade, agriculture, capital, and labor markets.&#13;
- I.'~~~~~~~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
GNP growth, because it is the basic mechanism by which economic growth&#13;
trickles down to the poverty grou8s.&#13;
Although some distortions are the result of historical forces&#13;
unrelated to public policy, most have been policy-induced and, ironically,&#13;
were initially conceived to improve income distribution and employment&#13;
1/&#13;
growth.   The central point here is that the distortions   introduced were&#13;
not the result of the objective per se, but of the specific policy instruments&#13;
selected to achieve it. Thus, the trade-off between these objectives and&#13;
economic efficiency is more the outcome of choosing the wrong instruments&#13;
than of an inherent incompatibility between them.&#13;
Why were these instruments chosen in the first place? Why were&#13;
they not replaced by instruments capable of achieving the desired redistribu-&#13;
tive effects without efficiency losses? The answer is fiscal expediency.&#13;
The trade-off between employment and distributive objectives, on the one hand,&#13;
and economic efficiency on the other is the result of using fiscally cheap&#13;
instruments. The cheaper the instrument, the higher the inefficiency&#13;
generated in the process of achieving a redistributive goal. The main thrust&#13;
of this chapter is to show that, today, these countries can afford "expensive'-&#13;
policy instruments, and therefore, avoid such trade-offs.&#13;
Two sets of distortions that have adversely affected the employment&#13;
generation effect of growth are explored.   First, those that&#13;
have distorted the composition of output either by trade policies or by&#13;
internal price policies; and second, those that have increased the relative&#13;
1/ For a general taxonomy of policy and not policy-induced distortions,&#13;
see J. N. Bhagwati, "The Generalized Theory of Distortions and lWelfare"&#13;
in J.N. Bhagwati, et al., Trade, Balance of Payments and Growth (North&#13;
Holland, 1971).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
cost of labor over and above the one corresponding to the relative abundance&#13;
of labor in the economy.&#13;
1. Changes in the output mix from reducing trade restrictions&#13;
Trade restrictions provide a different premium to the export sector&#13;
6ihen they generate one dollar's worth of exporta) than to the import competing&#13;
sector(when they substitute one dollar's worth of imports). The distortion&#13;
is defined by the end result of the policy: the import substituting sector&#13;
expands relative to the export sector and ends up by using more resources per&#13;
dollar substituted than those used by the export sector per dollar generated&#13;
through exports. If import restrictions are concentrated in particular&#13;
import-competing industries (those requiring higher protection) the import-&#13;
competing sectors without (or with small) protection also tend to be&#13;
discriminated against.&#13;
Agriculture, either through its exports or its import competing&#13;
activities without protection, received most of the negative effects of such&#13;
policies. To the extent that its labor intensity is greater than that of&#13;
the highly protected industrial activities, the net effect on global employ-&#13;
ment becomes negative.&#13;
On several occasions employment creation was the objective of&#13;
tariff protection policies to the industrial sector. The question arises&#13;
why government chose such policies. One explanation is that the positive&#13;
and negative effects on employment resulting from industrial protection are&#13;
not symmetric in terms of timing or visibility. New industrial activities&#13;
emerge quickly when they are the result of tariff barriers;      the barrier&#13;
is simply the result of negotiations with domestic investors or multinational&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
enterprises, i.e., the new investment has been 'latent." The positive&#13;
effects; on employment are immediate, highly visible, and concentrated in&#13;
urban areas. Urban labor usually has a stronger political militancy than&#13;
rural labor. The negative effects of such policies usually occur over the&#13;
long run and are less visible: the mechanism is the exchange rate, which&#13;
tends to increase less than it would otherwise have, and the effect is&#13;
spread across a large number of productive units and regions (it is less&#13;
visible from a political point of view).&#13;
Trade restrictions adversely affecting the agricultural sector&#13;
have also been undertaken to keep consumer food prices below world prices.&#13;
11hen this is achieved by food import subsidies or prohibitions on food&#13;
exports, prices to domestic producers go down below t'orld prices. A policy&#13;
that lowers consumer prices without discriminating against domestic producers&#13;
involves a subsidy on total consumption, independent of the source of supply.&#13;
Obviously, this entails a larger fiscal burden than that of alternative&#13;
instruments.&#13;
Unless consumption subsidies are used, policies to keep the price&#13;
of food down will discriminate against agriculture. The cheaper (fiscally)&#13;
the instrument used, the less successful it is in reaching the objective&#13;
without adversely affecting agricultural output and employment.&#13;
2. Subsidies to the use of capital. Interest rate policies&#13;
tMost countries place ceilings on nominal interest rates that, under&#13;
inflation, yield low or negative real rates ard strong excess demands for&#13;
credit. Thus, credit becomes allocated to pressure groups and to large&#13;
enterprises where risk is minimal (interest rate differentials are not allowed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
legally so as to compensate for differential risks). Large enterprises&#13;
in the industrial sector receiving that credit are perhaps the less labor&#13;
intensive activities in the economy.&#13;
Undervalued exchange rates and imports of capital goods without&#13;
import duties are further sources of a cheap use of capital, as are tax&#13;
credits and tax exemptions for investing in "backward regions."&#13;
3. Policies to reduce the discrepancy between the cost of labor and&#13;
labor incomes&#13;
'Iinimum wage laws, social security legislation, and laws governing&#13;
the stability of employment have been typical interventions to increase the&#13;
1/&#13;
real income of labor.    Such policies have been enforced in particular&#13;
sectors of the economy, in registered enterprises and particularly in the&#13;
urban economy. For some labor skills, especially the lower ones, this&#13;
legislation has become binding and thereby increased their real wages.&#13;
To the extent the demand for labor has some price elasticity, this increase&#13;
has been achieved at the expense of a lower employment in these sectors.&#13;
From a political point of view, the room for maneuver in this field&#13;
is limited. Of importance is to avoid adverse employment effects as&#13;
governments extend wage legislation in the future to larger sectors of the&#13;
economy, such as agriculture and the informal urban sector, particularly&#13;
services. The issue is how to increase the coverage of these benefits&#13;
without substantially increasing the cost of labor to these other sectors.&#13;
1/ This is less true for SQcial Security contributions; to the extent&#13;
woikers perceive as benefits only a fraction of these contributions,&#13;
this legislation becomes partly a tax on the use of labor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Present minimum wage legislation and social security contributions&#13;
cover only a small fraction of the labor force, that in the modern urban&#13;
sector. Because this sector uses more skilled labor and is subject to more&#13;
labor union pressures, only a fraction of their employment is bound by the&#13;
minimum wage law (most workers earn a higher wage); the basic effect of&#13;
such legislation is to increase the cost of labor through social security&#13;
legislation, which sets a percentage contribution as a fraction of the wage.&#13;
Extending legislation to more traditional sectors, such as agriculture and&#13;
the informal urban sector, implies reaching activities of higher labor&#13;
intensity, higher factor substitution, and employing labor of lower skills.&#13;
Labor not covered by legislation has the lowest wages and incomes, as shown&#13;
in Table 8 for Colombia; only 8.5 percent of workers covered by the social&#13;
security system belong to the poorest quintile of households.&#13;
The employment effects of extending labor legislation, minimum wages.&#13;
coupled with legal social security contributions by employers, can be signi-&#13;
ficantly more important than the effects of that legislation in the present.&#13;
Minimum wages will increasingly become binding and therefore cover a much&#13;
larger fraction of the labor force;   the joint effect of both minimum wiage&#13;
plus social security will involve a more important increase in the cost of&#13;
labor than presently exists. If demand elasticities are higher in these&#13;
new sectors, because of higher labor intensity and higher factor substitution,&#13;
the potential negative employment effects are reinforced.&#13;
Table 9 shows some orders of magnitude by which social security&#13;
legislation increases the cost of labor. In some countries it reaches&#13;
20 percent of the wage. If the price elasticity of demand for the output&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Table 8:   COLOMBIA 1974:  DISTRIBUTION OF HOUSEHOLDS&#13;
COVERED BY THE SOCIAL SECURITY SYSTEK&#13;
Quintile                      Z of Household&#13;
1                               8.5&#13;
3                              17.1&#13;
3                              20.7&#13;
4                              24.3&#13;
5                              29.4&#13;
Total                            100.0&#13;
Source:  Marcelo Selowsky, "Who Benefits from Government Expenditures: A&#13;
Case of Colombia." (forthcoming), Oxford University Press. 1979.&#13;
Table 9: SOCIAL SECURITY CONTRIBUTIONS AS A PERCENT&#13;
OF THE WAGE, 1970&#13;
Country                         Range&#13;
Brazil                       20.7 - 21.1&#13;
Colombia                     10.8 - 18.3&#13;
Ecuador                      13.5 - 14.5&#13;
Mexico                        15.2 - 20.8&#13;
Peru                           9.5 - 13.0&#13;
Source:  OAS:   Guidelines for Achieving Maximum Employment and Growth&#13;
in Latin America, 1973.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
as well as the elasticity of factor substitution is one and the share of&#13;
labor is 0.5, an increase of 20 percent in the cost of labor will diminish&#13;
employment in those activities also by 20 percent.&#13;
To avoid such increases in the cost of labor, minimum wage laws&#13;
should be complemented by subsidies (or tax exemptions) on the use of labor,&#13;
and social security financed by the central budget instead of by the employer.&#13;
This is well known; the issue is selectivity so as to make this policy&#13;
fiscally feasible.&#13;
One solution is to use these instruments at the margin and in sectors&#13;
where labor demands are price-elastic. Subsidies could be given on the basis&#13;
of additional employment, relative to a base year or relative to a&#13;
fraction (i.e., 0.90) of the employment over, say, the last two years. The&#13;
same would apply to social security contributions; employers would be exempt&#13;
only for additional employment, the contribution to be financed by the central&#13;
budget. Sectors with higlh labor-intensity and high capital-labor substitution&#13;
such as certain activities in agriculture, construction, and commerce are&#13;
likely candidates for these policies.&#13;
The notion of policies at the -margin can also be applied to other&#13;
types of legislation. Laws imposing high penalties on the dismissal of&#13;
workers, for example, have become a typical feature of wage legislation, even&#13;
more so than in developed cotntries. The result is that the hiring of labor&#13;
has become a capital investment whose cost is governed by law. These laws&#13;
could be replaced by unemployment insurance schemes financed by the public&#13;
budget, providing unemployment payments that gradually decline over time and&#13;
only last for a limited period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
4. Labor market segmentation and the mobility of labor&#13;
In most of these countries, wage levels are strongly associated&#13;
with the degree of "modernity" of the sector of employment and with the size&#13;
of enterprises. Labor market segmentation, the extent to which labor of&#13;
equal skills receive very different salaries, is also associated with these&#13;
characteristics. The empirical evidence shows that such segmentation not&#13;
only has not diminished, but has perhaps increased over time. These wage&#13;
differentials are partly explained by the differential enforcement of labor&#13;
legislation described earlier and partly the result of labor contracts in&#13;
enterprises with strong labor unions or multinational firms paying higher&#13;
wages than domestic firms.&#13;
The end result is that "protected" or formal labor markets face an&#13;
excess supply of applicants, those failing to obtain employment ending up&#13;
in the "informal" or free entry sectors where the wage tends to clear the&#13;
market, reflecting supply-demand conditions.&#13;
IWhat are the implications of this segmentation in labor markets&#13;
for income distribution and the returns to unskilled labor? Two studies&#13;
undertaken for Colombia shed some light on this question. Table 10 shows&#13;
the strong redistribution occurring when labor segmentation disappears.&#13;
By eliminating wage differentials for laborers of equal education in urban&#13;
Colombia, the real wage of the most unskilled category of labor rises by&#13;
8 percent.   This is a lower bound as only factor substitution takes place&#13;
in this exercise. As a result, a high degree of income inequality within&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
this category of labor is eliminated. At the same time, workers in the&#13;
utilities sector, basically government, experience a decline in income of&#13;
20 percent, whereas workers in the commerce sector experience a gain of&#13;
35 percent.&#13;
Table 10: COLOMBIA 1965: WAGES OF UNSKILLED LABOR&#13;
(pesos per hour)&#13;
Present                       Wage&#13;
segmentation                equalization&#13;
Manufacturing                   1.95                        1.81&#13;
Construction                    1.66                        1.81&#13;
Utilities                       2.31                        1.81&#13;
Commerce                        1.34                        1.81&#13;
Transport                       1.47                        1.81&#13;
AVERAGE                         1.68                        -1.81&#13;
Source: C. Dougherty and M. Selowsky, "Measuring the Effects of Misallocation&#13;
of Labor," Review of Economics and Statistics, August 1973.&#13;
When additional substitution and rural-urban migration is&#13;
introduced (that is, long run adjustments are allowed), the results can be&#13;
substantially stronger. By introducing substitution in the final goods&#13;
market,.as well as the possibility of international trade, and by assuming&#13;
that urban-rural wage differentials are maintained (which limits the degree&#13;
of migration), the elimination of urban wage differential increases the&#13;
real wage of unskilled labor, urban and rural, by 35 percent. The results&#13;
of such an exercise are shown in Table 11. Segmentation is defined by a&#13;
"modern" sector employing one-third of the unskilled urban labor force at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
37 -&#13;
Table ll:EFFECT ON WAGES AND E21PLOYMENT OF UNSKILLED LABOR OF&#13;
ELIMINATING. LABOR. MARKET SEGMENTATION IN URBAN AREAS&#13;
Wage Levels for Unskilled Labor&#13;
Sector               (Pesos per man year)         Percentage Change&#13;
Segmeintation  No Segmentation    Wages   Employment&#13;
Coffee                370   (.09)          498          34.5       6.2&#13;
Agriculture           410   (.38)          552         34.6      -10.6&#13;
Services and&#13;
artisans            570   (.36)         1145         132.5    -11.7&#13;
Food industry        1850                 1145         -38.1     115.2&#13;
Textiles             1660                 1145         -31.0     121.5&#13;
Paper, Wood          1850                 1145         -38.1     153.0&#13;
Rubber, chemicals    2660                 1145         -56.9     263.0&#13;
Metals               1820                 1145         -37.0     143.4&#13;
Non-metallic         1660                 1145         -31.0     125.8&#13;
(.17)&#13;
Mining                800                 1145          43.1     -14.5&#13;
Machinery            2560                 1145         -55.2     359.2&#13;
Diverse industries   1980                 1145         -42.1     183.7&#13;
Light domestic       3920                 1145         -70.8     129.7&#13;
Construction         1470                 1145         -22.1      30.2&#13;
Transportation,&#13;
communication      1320                 1145         -13.2       7.1&#13;
Total           640                  861          34.5&#13;
1/ J. de Melo, "Distortions in the Factor Market: Some General Equilibrium&#13;
Estimates," Review of Economics and Statistics, November 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
wages substantially higher than the informal sector--services and artisans.&#13;
By eliminating the urban wage differential and allowing for migration,&#13;
employment in most manufacturing activities increases at the expense of the&#13;
urban informal sector and agriculture. Manufacturing wages fall while they&#13;
rise in the other sectors. The net effect is a substantial increase in&#13;
real wages. These extreme but illustrative examples show the importance&#13;
of preventing conditions that would generate an increase in wage differentials&#13;
over time.&#13;
5.  Trade-offs between increases in employment and increases in wates&#13;
The literature shows a growing pessimism about the possibility of&#13;
the manufacturing sector absorbing the high growth rate of labor supply&#13;
in these countries. It is argued that manufacturing employment is still a&#13;
small share of total employment (15-20 percent), and that its growth,&#13;
therefore, cannot absorb important fractions of the total labor force. It&#13;
is also argued that the rate of job creation in these sectors is low for a&#13;
given output growth, that is, employment-output elasticities are lower than&#13;
one--in other words, employment grows more slowly than output.&#13;
The second argument, however, overlooks the fact that job creation&#13;
has taken place with quite substantial increases in real wages. Clearly, one&#13;
cannot have both! Given the high growth rates in real wages, the employment&#13;
growth has been substantial, particularly relative to other historical&#13;
experiences.&#13;
Table 12 shows that,on the average, employment and real wages have&#13;
been growing at 3.6 and 3.7 percent, respectively. The question is what&#13;
the increase in employment would be if additional effort were made to translate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
~3 9&#13;
Table 12:  ANNUAL GROvtH RATES IN EMPLOYMENT AND WAGES IN&#13;
THE INDUSTFIA, SECTOR, 1963-72 (Percentages)&#13;
Country                        Emrployment                    Real Wages&#13;
Brazil                            4.7                            2.8&#13;
Colombia                          4.2                            2.7&#13;
Ecuador                           5.8                            2.5&#13;
Mexico                            1.9                            6.9&#13;
Peru                              1.3                            3.7&#13;
Unweighted Average                3.6                            3.7&#13;
Source:  UN Growth of World Industry, reported in P. Meller, "Enfoques&#13;
Sobre la Demanda de Trabajo: Relevancia para America Latina,"&#13;
CIEPLAN, June 1978.&#13;
these increases in labor demand into additional employment rather than into&#13;
additional wage increases, and what policy instruments should be employed&#13;
in such effort. The answers to these questions are relevant to the issue of&#13;
increasing the trickle down effect of an increase in labor demand.&#13;
If the increases in labor demand that led to the combination&#13;
of increases in wages and employment observed in Table 12 are maintained in&#13;
the future, the following trade-off between wage increases and employment&#13;
1/&#13;
increases will occur.&#13;
1/ Assume a Cobb Douglas function   X = L eAt  where   A  is the growth rate of&#13;
all other complementary factors of production, capital and technical progress&#13;
Differentiating logarithmically the first order conditions yields.&#13;
d2ogw = (a-l) d&amp;og L + X where    w  is the wage rate.&#13;
Assuming a=0.5, the value of X consistent with Table 12 is 0.055.&#13;
Given A, we can derive the trade off between d2ogw and dRog L.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Growth in Wiaes         Growth in Emploliment&#13;
2%                         7%&#13;
3%                          5%&#13;
4%                         3%&#13;
If wages were kept at a 2-3 percent growth rate, the employment growth rate&#13;
in these sectors could reach 5-7 percent.&#13;
The figures in Table 12 are averages for workers of all skills. As&#13;
mentioned above, evidence indicates that real wages for educated workers have&#13;
grown faster because of the short-run inelasticity of the supply of educated&#13;
manpower. Expansions of the educational sector (discussed in the next&#13;
section) will increase this elasticity and assure that additional labor demand&#13;
results in a wider employment effect rather than higher rents of already&#13;
employed workers. For lower skills, wage increases coexist with elastic labor&#13;
supplies stemming from the rest of the economy. The issue of labor market&#13;
segmentation discussed above is central to the explanation of this phenomenon.&#13;
B. INCREASING THE EARNINGS CAPACITY OF THE POOR BY AUGMENTING THEIR&#13;
ENDOWMENT OF ASSETS: IDENTIFYING THE GOOD INVESTMENTS&#13;
1. Introduction&#13;
i.      One way of increasing the earning capacity of poor households&#13;
is increasing their ownership of productive (human and physical) assets.&#13;
This policy alternative has been advanced several times by the Bank, the&#13;
small farmers' strategy being perhaps the best example. This option is&#13;
appealing because it automatically takes care of the long run, by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
increasing present ownership it increases the future flow of productive&#13;
capacity, and second, it is perceived as less paternalistic than policies&#13;
that directly subsidize the consumption of the poor.&#13;
A more explicit statement of the limitations and trade-offs of&#13;
such an option is needed. For example, what are the limits of using this&#13;
instrument for distributive purposes without a substantial trade-off with&#13;
growth objectives? What are the criteria by which this trade-off can be&#13;
judged? Can an optimal level of intervention in this area be identified,&#13;
that is, a level of additional asset-creation in the poor that does not&#13;
adversely affect growth?&#13;
ii.     Investments in the poor that do not adversely affect growth are, by&#13;
definition, those whose rate of return (valued at shadow prices, without any&#13;
distributive weights element) is higher than the opportunity cost of capital&#13;
to the economy. Therefore, the magnitude of the underinvestment in the poor&#13;
can be defined as that amount of high yielding asset formation which does not&#13;
materialize oecause of the market imperfections facing the poor, particularly&#13;
in capital markets. Correcting such underinvestment does not introduce a&#13;
trade-off between distribution and growth; on the contrary it has positive&#13;
effects on both equity and growth.&#13;
Why have not governments taken care of this underinvestment if&#13;
they indeed were interested in growth? Two reasons are possible: either&#13;
few of these good investments remain, or the market imperfections facing&#13;
the poor were a way of chanelling credit and investment toward higher income.&#13;
groups. In other words, credit rationings allowed income groups with access&#13;
to credit to undertake investments with returns below the opportunity cost&#13;
of capital to the economy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
iii.      The first task, therefore, is to exhaust the search for good&#13;
investments in the poor. Only by first identifying and evaluating the&#13;
contribution of these investments to their incomes can we then proceed&#13;
to other interventions involving a higher degree of trade-off.&#13;
The availability of "good investments" depends on the particular&#13;
characteristics of the poor; the existence of such investments is highly&#13;
country specific, highly interdependent and highly dynamic; it depends on&#13;
the age characteristics of the poor (there are fewer good investments to&#13;
be made in the very old), their human capital potential (for example, the&#13;
fraction of physically and mentally handicapped in the poverty group), and&#13;
their initial ownership of physical capital (for example, the fraction of&#13;
artisans and small farmers or sharecroppers among the poor). Some empirical&#13;
evidence helpful in identifying these investments is discussed below.&#13;
2. Investments in human capital&#13;
These investments include all interventions that, by influencing&#13;
the characteristics of individuals, affect their productivity as labor inputs.&#13;
Investment in education and on-the-job training are interventions whose&#13;
productivity effects have been well studied. Interventions at preschool age&#13;
among poor children, infant nutrition, and other environmental variables such&#13;
as health and psychological stimulation, have been analyzed but not yet&#13;
quantified for their economic impact.&#13;
These investments are particularly important because half of the&#13;
poor individuals are children below age 15, w~hose future productive potential&#13;
is influenced by early interventions: raising the income of households in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
the present does not guarantee a sufficient investment in children on the&#13;
part of their parents; in most societies the impossibility of borrowing&#13;
against human-capital formation (there is no collateral) increases the&#13;
possibility of underinvestment in education by poor families.&#13;
2a.  InteAvention   at ptuchoot agu in chid&amp;en&#13;
o6 poot 6amZiUu&#13;
Growing empirical evidence shows that preschool children of poor&#13;
families have a lower performance in most ability tests than matching&#13;
controls from higher income groups. Much of this difference can be attributed&#13;
to the nutritional-health-psychological environment of preschool age children.&#13;
If environmental deficits affect the future productivity of the individual&#13;
as well as his future capability of benefitting from schooling, the question&#13;
arises whether countries are not indeed underinvesting in preschool age&#13;
interventions for poor children.&#13;
Table 13 presents a survey of studies whose specific aim was to&#13;
evaluate the effect of infant malnutrition on specific types of abilities&#13;
in young children that are crucial to basic learning. They show the mechanism&#13;
by which early malnutrition can affect the effectiveness of later schooling.&#13;
Other causal mechanisms by which early malnutrition affects learning&#13;
have been suggested in the literature. Evidence shows, for example, that&#13;
infectious diseases are likely to be less severe and less frequent in well-&#13;
1/&#13;
nourished children; to the extent that infectious diseases affect the child's&#13;
responsiveness to his environment, they also affect his cognitive development.&#13;
1/ N. Scrimshaw, "Nutrition and Infection," in Recent Advances in lhuman&#13;
Nutrition, ed. J. Brock (London: J. Churchill, 1961).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
Table 13: STUDIES ON THE EFFECT OF MALNUTRITION&#13;
ON LEARNING&#13;
Probable Effect&#13;
Authors                  Deficit in              on Consequent&#13;
Performance               Learning&#13;
Cravioto and De Licardie       Auditory-visual inte-     Reading ability&#13;
(Mexico)                       gration&#13;
Cravioto et al. (Mexico)        Visual-kinesthetic       Writing and draw-&#13;
integration              ing abilities&#13;
Champakam et al (India         Visual identification     Reading abilities&#13;
Cravioto et al. (Mexico,        Kinesthetic-visual,      General learning&#13;
Guatemala); Guthrie,            kinesthetic-haptic,      abilities&#13;
et al. (Philippines)           haptic-visual, and&#13;
auditory-visual&#13;
integration&#13;
Source: J. Cravioto and E. de Licardie, "The Effect of Malnutrition on the&#13;
Individual," Nutrition, National Development, and Planning, ed.&#13;
A. Berg et al. (Cambridge, Mass.: M.I.T. Press, 1973).&#13;
In almost all studies apathetic behavior is identified as one of&#13;
the clearest effects of malnutrition. Cravioto and De Licardie hypothesize&#13;
about the further effects of apathy: "It should be recognized that the&#13;
mother's response to the infant is to a considerable degree a function of&#13;
the child's own characteristic of reactivity....   Apathetic behavior in its&#13;
turn can reduce the value of the child as a stimulus and diminish the adult's&#13;
responsiveness to him. Thus, apathy can provoke apathy and so contribute to&#13;
1/&#13;
a cumulative pattern of reduced adult-child interaction."&#13;
Direct nutritional interventions to reach young children in poor&#13;
families will be discussed at length in the next section. IHere we address&#13;
other preschool age interventions.&#13;
1/ Cravioto and De Licardie, op.cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
.. 45 -&#13;
Policies to change the out-of-lhome environment through widescale&#13;
preschool compensatory programs are difficult to undertake in the short run,&#13;
unless such programs are simply extensions of existing elementary schooling&#13;
that can draw children into kindergarten programs one or twqo years earlier.&#13;
Experience in the United States shows that because extensions of the&#13;
"kindergarten type" are either insufficient in themselves or improperly&#13;
designed, they cannot compensate for the environmental deprivation suffered&#13;
by low income children. A more complex program is required.&#13;
A partial solution, at least in the short run, might be a corrective&#13;
policy geared to lower income children who enter primary school at a later age&#13;
(1-3 years later) than higher income students. Educational programs for&#13;
young women concerning childrearing practices would provide another type of&#13;
solution.&#13;
Two kinds of educational programs are important. First, nutrition&#13;
education, particularly that relevant to infant-feeding and breastfeeding&#13;
practices. Growing evidence indicates that the decline in breastfeeding&#13;
practices in low-income families of urban areas is a main determinant of&#13;
infant malnutrition. The resource cost of substituting breast milk appears&#13;
quite large; preliminary estimates suggest that if 20 percent of the mothers&#13;
in the urban areas of developing countries do not breastfeed, the loss in&#13;
breast milk is around $365 million per year; if half of the other 80 percent&#13;
discoutinue breastfeeding after the sixth month, the total loss reaches&#13;
$780 million.&#13;
1/ A. Berg, The Ilutrition Factor: Its Role in National Development,&#13;
(The Brookings Institution, Washington, D. C., 1973).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
Second, education on childrearing practices with particular&#13;
emphasis on early stimulation is another course of action. Implementing&#13;
educational proerams of this type requires some preliminary research, which&#13;
has not taken place on a wide scale in developing countries. Questions&#13;
that arise are: flow different are childrearing practices across families&#13;
in developing countries? What are the factors determining these differences?&#13;
Are they related to income or to particular ethnic groups of the&#13;
population?&#13;
2b.  Invetme,ent in 6oxmat education&#13;
In spite of spectacular expansions in enrollments and in the&#13;
supply of educated labor, the evidence suggests that basic education is&#13;
still an effective and productive way of increasing the earnings of poor&#13;
households. Arguments against, based on presumably high levels of unemploy-&#13;
ment among educated labor and on the notion that education is simply a&#13;
screening device (to allocate "scarce" jobs in the modern sector), cannot&#13;
be confirmed by existing evidence.&#13;
What is the evidence? First, still today, poor households are&#13;
characterized by extremely low levels of schooling among their working&#13;
members, as well as low levels of school enrollment among their children;&#13;
second, basic education has an important net impact on the earnings of&#13;
labor, even if unemployment is taken into account and only possibilities&#13;
of work in the informal sector are considered; third, education not only&#13;
has an important potential impact on the incomes of the poor, but it also&#13;
represents a high yielding investment from an efficiency point of view.&#13;
In other words, it is good for equity and for growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
Data by income groups show that 30 percent of heads of household&#13;
in the poorest quintiles of families in Colombia have zero years of school-&#13;
ing. Almost 60 percent have only two years or less. In the same income&#13;
1/&#13;
group, only 54 percent of children age 6-11 attend school.     Cross-section&#13;
regional data for the other countries show that an important number of pro-&#13;
vinces still have enrollment rates under 60 percent for children below age&#13;
10.&#13;
Controlling for other factors positively associated with schooling&#13;
and having an independent effect on labor earnings, the effect of schooling&#13;
is still important. Table 14 presents a summary of results for nine Latin&#13;
American countries; even controlling for occupation and type of activity&#13;
(employment variables), years of schooling explains between 7 and 25 percent&#13;
of earnings inequality. This is a strong test for education: education&#13;
also changes productivity by inducing cross occupational and cross sectorial&#13;
mobility, an effect that is not captured by these estimates. These percentages&#13;
are, therefore, a lower bound for thie capacity of education in explaining&#13;
2/&#13;
productivity differentials-!&#13;
Similar results are reported for several cities of Colombia.&#13;
Controlling for occupation, economic sector, and social stratum, primary&#13;
1/ Itarcelo Selowsky, V.Who Benefits from Government Expenditures:  A Case&#13;
Study in Colombia (Oxford University Press, 1979), forthcoming.&#13;
2/ If any change in a worker's occupation (associated with additional&#13;
schooling) is the result of education acting as a rationing device&#13;
in highly paid sectors or occupations, the above results would be&#13;
the relevant ones. In.this case the change in worl:ers' wage does&#13;
not reflect a productivity gain.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Table 14: LATIN AMERICA--Contribution of Different Characteristics&#13;
to the Explanation of Earning Inequality..&#13;
Ranges Encompassing all Country Results&#13;
Personal Variables          Employment Variables&#13;
Education&#13;
Areas              (years of&#13;
schooling)      Age         Occupation     Activity&#13;
Urban&#13;
Employees            7 - 17       10 - 21         6 - 12       5 -  9&#13;
Self-employed       8 - 22        15 - 26         3 -  9       3 - 10&#13;
Rural&#13;
Employees           9 - 13        10 - 18         3 -  6       3 -  7&#13;
Self-employed      13 - 25        12 - 20         0 -  8       1 - 4&#13;
1/ Countries included are: Argentina, Brazil, Colombia, Costa Rica, Chile,&#13;
Mexico, Panama, Peru, and Venezuela.&#13;
Source:  Oscar Altimir and Sebastian Piiiera, "Decomposition Analysis of&#13;
the Inequality of Earnings in Latin America," ECLA-Wlorld Bank,&#13;
August 1977.&#13;
education increases earnings by 40, 16.4, and 38.3 percent in the cities&#13;
1/&#13;
of Bogota, Barranquilla, and Cali.&#13;
Basic education is undoubtedly an important way of increasing&#13;
the incomes of poor households. Whether it is also a good investment from&#13;
the point of view of resource allocation depends on the economic costs of&#13;
1/ Phillip Musgrove, Consumer Behavior in Latin America: An Eciel Study&#13;
(Brookings Institution, 1978).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
49 -&#13;
achieving increases in earnings capacities. The question is: What is the&#13;
rate of return on investing in primary education?&#13;
Table 15 shows rates of returns for different levels of schooling.&#13;
Not only is the return on primary education higher than any conceivable&#13;
opportunity cost of capital (the mean rate of return is 28.7 percent), but&#13;
1/&#13;
it is substantially higher than the return on other levels of schooling.&#13;
Clearly, countries are underinvesting in basic education relative to higher&#13;
levels of schoolingl&#13;
Why do not poor households increase their enrollment in basic educa-&#13;
tion as a reaction to its high rate of return? Why do rich households still&#13;
invest in higher education in spite of its low rate of return? Although&#13;
public primary education is free, other costs of schooling, basically forgone&#13;
earnings, are important costs for poor families. Their implicit discount&#13;
rate is also high, even in comparison with the high rates of return to primary&#13;
education. Higher education is highly subsidized in most countries, conse-&#13;
quently the private rate of return faced by rich households is substantially&#13;
1/ How does unemployment affect these rates of return? Ilow do these estimates&#13;
capture the popular notion that unemployment makes education a less appeal-&#13;
ing policy instrument? Unemployment affects both the costs (foregone&#13;
earnings) and benefits (additional earnings) of additional schooling, and&#13;
it is not obvious that the rate of return may fall after this adjustment.&#13;
Second, even if it falls it may still be quite large. Some of the&#13;
estimates in Table 15 automatically take unemployment into account. Most&#13;
of them are based on yearly or monthly incomes of the total population:&#13;
the earnings reflect unemployment periods in shorter units of time.&#13;
The most important downward adjustment is unemployment that results&#13;
from search activities when school graduates enter the labor force. (The&#13;
first flows of earnings, to which rates of return are highly sensitive.)&#13;
In Colombia, this adjustment broughtdown rates of return to basic education&#13;
from 40 to 28 percent, still a respectable rate of return.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
Table I5: SOCIAL RATES OF RETURN TO EDUCATION, BY&#13;
EDUCATIONAL LEVEL&#13;
Country             Year         Primary       Secondary       Higher&#13;
Mexico                    1963         25.0           17.0            23.0&#13;
Venezuela                 1957         82.0           17.0            23.0&#13;
Colombia                 1966          40.0           24.0            8.0&#13;
Chile                     1959         24.0           16.9            12.2&#13;
1/&#13;
Brazil                    1962         23.5           13.1            14.5&#13;
Turkey                    1968          -              -               8.5&#13;
India                    1960          20.2           16.8           12.7&#13;
Malaysia                  1967          9.3           12.3            10.7&#13;
Philippines               1966          7.0           21.0            11.0&#13;
South Korea              1967          12.0            9.0            5.0&#13;
Thailand                  1970         30.5           13.0            11.0&#13;
Nigeria                   1966         23.0           12.8            17.0&#13;
Ghana                    1967          18.0           13.0           16.5&#13;
Kenya                     1968         21.7           19.2             8.8&#13;
Uganda                    1965         66.0           28.6            12.0&#13;
Average                1965         28.7           16.7           12.9&#13;
1/ For primary and secondary, Jallade.&#13;
Source:   C. Psacharopoulos, Returns to Education: An International&#13;
Comparison, 1973.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
51 -&#13;
larger than the one shown in Table 15. This becomes clear in Table 16:&#13;
not only rich households are being subsidized but this subsidy encourages&#13;
investment in a sector with an economic return barely matching the oppor-&#13;
tunity cost of capital relevant to most countries!&#13;
The policy implications of the above are that the incentives for&#13;
poor families to increase their enrollment rates must be increased.    The&#13;
constraint is not the capacity of schools but the demand for schooling by&#13;
poor households. Additional incentives to compensate for foregone earnings&#13;
(particularly in rural areas where employment opportunities for children&#13;
are higher) and transportation costs are easy to implement; school breakfast&#13;
and lunches, free transportation by schLool buses are some examples. Such&#13;
measures can be easily financed by a redistribution of subsidies within the&#13;
educational sector, specifically by eliminating subsidies to higher education.&#13;
These measures will be analyzed in detail in Section C.&#13;
Table 16: TOTAL (INCLUDING ALL ECONOMIC COSTS) AND&#13;
PRIVATE CINCLUDING ONLY PRIVATE COSTS)&#13;
RATES OF RETURN TO hiIGHER EDUCATION&#13;
Country                         Total             Private&#13;
Brazil                                8.0                15.5&#13;
Turkey                               14.5                38.1&#13;
Colombia                              8.5               26.0&#13;
Philippines                          11.0                12.5&#13;
Thailand                             11.0                14.0&#13;
Source:  G. Psacharopoulos, Rates of Return to Education, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
Z . TLtvc ;l- &lt;nt in education. RWat-uWL5bn   sgAtion&#13;
r rollment  n primary education is especially low in rural areas.&#13;
Bec- tte education inc:-eases the probability of migration toward urban areas&#13;
(specially .mong young school graduates), expansions of enrollment in rural&#13;
areas will increase, or at least maintain, the present high migration rates.&#13;
How apprehensive should we feel about schooling inducing further migration&#13;
flows?&#13;
The estimated rates of return reported above are based on samples&#13;
that do include migrants presently working i4a urban areas. However, these arc&#13;
average rates (for migrants and nonmigrants), and do not provide independent&#13;
evidence on the rate of return specific to rural students who eventually&#13;
will migrate to urban areas. The reason for a possible lower rate of return&#13;
for migrants is the notion that migrants experience high rates of unemploy-&#13;
ment upon arrival and that only informal, low paying jobs are available to&#13;
1/&#13;
them.  This notion is not supported by the facts.    Indeed, most migrants&#13;
find jobs in a reasonably short period of time (see Table 17) and those&#13;
beginning in low paying jobs move up the occupational ladder rather quickly.&#13;
In sum, there seem to be few occupational differences over time between&#13;
migrants and nonmigrants of the same sex, age, and level of schooling.&#13;
3. TncreasinR the physical assets of the poor in the rural areas.&#13;
Identifying the good investments. Complementarities between&#13;
investments and the transfer of land&#13;
Policies to increase the ownership of physical assets by poor&#13;
households are particularly relevant in rural areas. As illustrated in&#13;
Table 18, the possibilities of such policies depend heavily on the initial&#13;
1/ The best survey of the e"'pitical evidence is by L. Yap, "Internal Migration&#13;
in Less Developed Countries," Wporld Bank Staff Working Paper #215,&#13;
September 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
Table 17: TIME REQUIRED FOR MIGRANTS TO FIND FIRST JOB&#13;
IN CITIES&#13;
Cumulative Percentage&#13;
City               Sample Description          Finding W4ork Within a&#13;
'.eriod of Time&#13;
City-wide Samples&#13;
Santiago, Chile          Economically-active         43%   Immediately (2 days)&#13;
migrants who arrived        66%   1 month&#13;
in Santiago within         85%    6 months&#13;
previous decade&#13;
Male Female&#13;
Brazil: 6 cities         Adult migrants              85%    74%    1 month&#13;
including Rio                                        95%    90%    Less than&#13;
and Sao Paulo                                                      6 months&#13;
Seoul, Korea             Household heads, of         26%   Immediately&#13;
whom 80% are migrants             (pre-arranged)&#13;
64%   "Soon"&#13;
76%   6 months&#13;
Lima, Peru               1967 survey of migrants     Over 75%      3 months&#13;
Poor Sections of City&#13;
Santiago, Chile          Family heads or their       47%   "Immediately"&#13;
wives in a callampa         91%   3 months&#13;
settlement. 85% manual&#13;
laborers or self-&#13;
employed artisans.&#13;
Buenos Aires,            Residents of a villa        75%   2 weeks&#13;
Argentina                miseria, mostly recent      85%   1 month&#13;
migrants, 61% day&#13;
laborers or unskilled&#13;
workers&#13;
Rio de Janeiro,          Residents of 3 favelas&#13;
Brazil                   (a) those with experience   85%   1 month&#13;
in unskilled urban or&#13;
rural work&#13;
(b? those with previous    65%   1 month&#13;
skilled jobs&#13;
Source: From L. Yap, op cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 18: POSSIBILITIES OF FINDING GOOD INVESTMENTS THAT INCREASE&#13;
AGRICULTURAL ASSETS OF THE RURAL POOR&#13;
(SF/LL = ratio of subsistence farmers to landless labor&#13;
in the poverty group)&#13;
Without Redistributing Ownership of Land                   With Land Reform&#13;
Proportional         Investment in         Possibilities of       Proportional to the&#13;
Country     to the ratio        intensive margin         investing in         ratio of "good land"&#13;
(SF/LL)         of SF (constraints)     extensive margin        per landless labor&#13;
Peru         High(SF/LL)               Low                  Low                     Moderate&#13;
(location, quality&#13;
3/1           of land, water)&#13;
Mexico      Medium(SF/LL)           Meditm                Medium              Moderate - High&#13;
Colombia         1/2          (water, leakages)&#13;
Brazil      Low(SF/LL)               Medium               Medium                       High&#13;
Turkey           1/3          (water, leakages)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
occupational distribution of rural households. Without considering transfers&#13;
of existing land, this option depends on: the fraction of existing land-&#13;
owners in the poverty group, such as the ratio of subsistence farmers to&#13;
landless laborers among the poor, SF/LL; the possibility of finding high&#13;
yielding investments among subsistence farmers;    and the yield on the&#13;
investment in extending cultivable land eventually to be transferred to poor&#13;
households. When a redistribution of existing land is feasible, such invest-&#13;
ments can then be calibrated to take into account the complementarity between&#13;
investment and transfers.&#13;
3a.  Inve4lOnt6 -in the ab6ence o6 tedLbution, of Zand&#13;
The effectiveness of this option depends on how important is the&#13;
fraction of landowners or small farms in the poverty group. Unlike in Asia,&#13;
most rural poor in Latin America are landless; a possible exception is Peru.&#13;
In most Latin American countries landless families account for two-thirds of the&#13;
rural poor. The question arises, therefore, whether the present enthusiasm&#13;
for a "small farms strategy" to poverty alleviation can be justified in the&#13;
context of Latin America. Without redistributions of land, that strategy&#13;
reaches only a small fraction and the better off of the rural poor.&#13;
Credit, extension services, and investment in roads and irrigation&#13;
schemes are typical interventions that could increase the productive capacity&#13;
of small farmers. The question is how many of these investments have a high&#13;
rate of return and could easily be targeted to the poor. Two features of these&#13;
countries limit the effectiveness of such policies: location and country size,&#13;
and the problem of targeting without substantial leakages to high income groups.&#13;
Subsistence farmers are rarely concentrated so that regional policy&#13;
packages could be designed. In Peru's Sierra, farmers are still dispersed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
Tab.i.e 19: INDICATOR OF DISPERSION OF RURAL POOR IN PERU&#13;
Percentage of poor in                    Number of Sierra&#13;
Rural Labor Force                           Provinces&#13;
0 -  20                                    9&#13;
21 - 40                                    20&#13;
41 -  60                                   32&#13;
61 - 80                                    30&#13;
81 - 100                                    2&#13;
Total                                     93&#13;
Source: R. Webb , Government Policy and the Distribution of Income in Peru,&#13;
op. cit.&#13;
(see Table 19), and with physical barriers making some of these policies&#13;
extremely costly. Because in most countries subsistence farmers coexist&#13;
with large farms, only specific programs can be targeted (credit, technical&#13;
assistance); other programs such as roads or irrigation would subsidize&#13;
other farmers as well. Unless "nontarget farmers" are charged for the&#13;
programs, the financial cost per "subsistence farmer reached" becomes&#13;
prohibitive.&#13;
Because of their crop pattern, irrigation is perhaps the main&#13;
constraint to increase the productivity of the small farmers. Their location,&#13;
however, (basically the high plateaus) makes investment in irrigation a costly&#13;
undertaking and economies of scale resulting from cooperative arrangements&#13;
are prevented by distance and geographical dispersion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
The conclusion is that with present patterns of ownership and&#13;
spatial distribution of land, possibilities of increasing farmers' income&#13;
by means of high yielding investments are limited.&#13;
1/&#13;
3b.  lnvetnent46 with change6 in the owbnehip o4 tanr&#13;
Countries that have undertaken land reform include Mexico (1940)&#13;
and Bolivia (1955), where large "haciendas" farmed with traditional&#13;
technology were subdivided into small farms. Peru is still implementing&#13;
the land reform begun in 1973. The general evidence as to long-term&#13;
effects of such reforms indicate that small farmers have increased their&#13;
previously low income, and farm output has increased overall.&#13;
Several specific lessons seem to emerge from those experiences:&#13;
the minimum farm size required to sustain farmers' incomes and to take&#13;
advantage of minimum economies of scale is still high, consistently ranging&#13;
between 30 and 40 hectares, of which at least two-thirds is cropland and&#13;
pasture; given this required farm size, only 30 to 50 percent of the rural&#13;
population benefits. Over time, high population growth erodes the relative&#13;
initial effect of the reform by increasing the relative number of landless&#13;
families; maintenance of productivity gains not only requires high initial&#13;
levels of investment, but also high levels of technical assistance and credit&#13;
over time; the positive effects are less clear when large commercial&#13;
estates or modern livestock operations were subject to land reform. There&#13;
is a difference between redistributing land from "haciendas" with traditional&#13;
crops and redistributing land from high technology,highly mechanized estates.&#13;
What can we learn from these experiences so as to evaluate&#13;
options available today? In countries where some reforms have taken place&#13;
1/ Parts of this section draw heavily on Shlomo Eckstein, et al.,"Land Reform&#13;
in Latin America: Bolivia, Chile, Mexico, Peru and Venezuela," World Bank&#13;
Staff Working Paper #275, April 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
and where u.vrefo'red Land consists basically of large, commercial estates,&#13;
for which eco:.omies of scale and technology are important (livestock, sugar,&#13;
cotton) , or of large traditional haciendas with small cropland potential&#13;
(large estates in Mexico and Peru have only 10 percent of the cropland but&#13;
35 pe-cent of posture land) agrarian reform options are less clear.   Redis-&#13;
tribution of highly commercialized estates can entail a high efficiency&#13;
cost unless cooperatives are implemented to maintain the gains of economies&#13;
of scale; but the latter involve    changing difficult social and&#13;
institutional constraints. Redistributing traditional haciendas of lower&#13;
quality land, basically suited for pasture, requires high additional invest-&#13;
ments to support smaller family units.&#13;
The agrarian reform option becomes more important for countries&#13;
that have not experienced redistributions of land and where the increase&#13;
in output from reformed land could be achieved at good rates of return on&#13;
the additional investment required. Brazil, Colombia, and to a lesser&#13;
degree, Turkey, are countries where this is more probable.&#13;
What is the possibility, in some of these countries, of&#13;
redistrlbutions of land,that either maintain their production level without&#13;
additional investment resources or, if additional investment resources are&#13;
required to raise the incomes of the beneficiaries, they do it with a high&#13;
rate of return.&#13;
Several simulation exercises have been made assuming that the&#13;
high productivity per hectare, usually observed in smaller farms, will be&#13;
replicated when land is redistributed. Obviously, this always yields an&#13;
increase in output. The problem is that the associated investment cost&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
to maintain this replication--i.e., roads, irrigation, water, extension--&#13;
is not brought explicitly into the picture so as to allow the computation&#13;
of the net return to the reform.&#13;
The IBRD-SUDENE study on Northeast Brazil provides such an&#13;
information. This study develops a model simulating the effects of land&#13;
redistribution where 790,000 new farm modules of 34.8 hectares each are&#13;
1/&#13;
created.   The initial conditions and the results of the land reform are&#13;
summarized in Table 20. Workers without access to land currently represent&#13;
two-thirds of the rural labor force and the main core of Brazilian poverty.&#13;
The establishment of such "module farms" gives land access to 20 percent of&#13;
the landless labor in the poverty group (temporary and permanent workers&#13;
and sharecroppers), increasing their per capita family income from 50 to&#13;
130 dollars per year. The net increase in value added of the region, net&#13;
of accruals to all factors other than land and over and above the opportunity&#13;
cost of labor, is 219 million dollars. The required additional investment&#13;
per module is $3,500, a total of $2.7 billion. The implied rate of return&#13;
to this redistribution cum investment is 8 percent.&#13;
The effects of this rather radical agrarian reform on the regional&#13;
distribution of income are shown in Table 21. The percentage of households&#13;
below a poverty line of $78 per capita decline from 86.6 to 77.8 percent, a&#13;
substantial change in absolute numbers, but clearly not the solution for the&#13;
problem of poverty in the rural Northeast. Although the absolute number of&#13;
beneficiaries is high, around three-quarters of a million households, the&#13;
absolute base of people in poverty is equally large; four million members of&#13;
the rural labor force still remain in absolute poverty.&#13;
1/ G. Kutcher and P. Scandizzo, The Agricultural Economy of Northeast Brazil,&#13;
(forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
1/&#13;
Table 20: RURAL NORTHEAST BRAZIL&#13;
I.    The Rural Poor in the Present:   A Functional Breakdown&#13;
Dependent&#13;
Number of    Population&#13;
Poverty Level                 Classification          Agents        (million)&#13;
Less than US$50              Temporary workers      2.7 million       3.5&#13;
per capita                                          or less&#13;
Not substantially            Sharecroppers            240,000         1.2&#13;
above US$50               Permanent workers         895,000        4.5&#13;
per capita                 Smallest farmers          67,000          .335&#13;
Above US$50 per capita       Medium farmers           384,000         1.92&#13;
but less than $130&#13;
10-12&#13;
Totals                                            4.3 million    million&#13;
II.   Potential for Land Redistribution&#13;
Number of existing large farms                37,038&#13;
Average size, ha.                                742&#13;
Module size                                     34.8&#13;
Potential number of modules                  790,000&#13;
III. Effects of the Land Redistribution&#13;
Net money income per module                  US$781 ($130 per capita)&#13;
Net increase in value added 1/               US$219.2 millions&#13;
Required additional investment&#13;
per module (US$3500 per module)            US$2,765 millions&#13;
Rate of return of the investment&#13;
cum redistribution                         8%&#13;
1/ Net of accruals to all factors other than land and over and above the&#13;
opportunity of labor.&#13;
Source: Kutcher and Scandizzo, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6A v&#13;
Table 21: NORTHEAST BRAZIL: EFFECTS OF THE REFORM&#13;
ON THE DISTRIBUTION OF RURAL INCOMES&#13;
Family Income                    % of Households&#13;
US$                    Base Case         Land Reform&#13;
(1)                (2)             (2) - (1)&#13;
Below 469                   88.6               77.8              - 10.8&#13;
469 - 938                    1.3               14.0             + 12.7&#13;
938 -1875                    4.9                8.1             +   3.2&#13;
+1875                    5.2                0.1              -  5.1&#13;
100.0               100.0                0&#13;
Source:  Kutcher and Scandizzo, op. cit.&#13;
C. THE DIRECT PROVISION OF SERVICES: THE "BASIC NEEDS APPROACH"&#13;
1. Introduction: Toward a children-oriented basic needs approach&#13;
i.        Measuring poverty alleviation in terms of welfare indicators other&#13;
than income opens a new set of policy considerations. Not only per capita&#13;
income is unequally distributed, but calorie consumption, life expectancy&#13;
and infant mortality. They reflect inequality in the consumption&#13;
of particular services,such as housing, sewerage, water, education, and&#13;
health. Policies to increase their consumption above levels resulting from&#13;
private demand and supply of these services define what by now has become&#13;
known as a "basic needs" strategy.    It  implies interfering with resource&#13;
allocation to reach these critical consumption levels at early stages of&#13;
development, despite strategies to accelerate the growth in income of the&#13;
poor. This strategy becomes more important the smaller the trickle down&#13;
effect of high growth rate policies on the income of the poor, the fewer&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
th." posF-ibIlities of increasing the earning capacity of the poor by high&#13;
vyelenpg investments in their assets, the smaller the marginal propensity&#13;
bv the poor to spend on basic needs, and the lesser the possibility of&#13;
the private sector supplying them, particularly when the suDDly of these&#13;
services is characterized by strong complementarities and economies of&#13;
scale.&#13;
Two sets of issues are central in evaluating these policies.&#13;
First, at the macro-level, they involve some trade-off with growth to the&#13;
extent these services may have a more limited effect on the productivity&#13;
of the poor. What becomes important is to calibrate this trade-off at the&#13;
present (high) level of per capita income in these countries; this trade-off&#13;
appears different today at per capita incomes of $1,000 than it did 25 years&#13;
ago when these countries had only half this income level. The second set&#13;
of issues is microeconomic: (a) how can these services be delivered without&#13;
major leakages to other income groups, (b) without inducing an effect simply&#13;
equivalent to an income transfer, and (c) how can children be reached when&#13;
intrafamily leakages also occur?&#13;
ii.       Nutrition and child care, consumption of health services, shelter&#13;
with water and sewerage, and basic education are typical services that&#13;
determine "quality of life." The specific policy choice and mix are clearly&#13;
countrv and regional specific, and involve a high degree of value judgment.&#13;
Even objective judgments from the medical field, such as "optimal calorie&#13;
reauirement," are still highly controversial.&#13;
The choice of a specific basic needs strategy depends on the&#13;
initial deficit, the age composition of the poor, the effect of rural-urban&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
migration in redefining basic needs over time, and the income elasticity&#13;
of the poor for different basic needs, namely, the rate at which the&#13;
deficit will be closed by income growth in the poverty group.&#13;
iii.      Several factors point toward a children-oriented approach to&#13;
basic needs. First, basic needs deficits are associated with the distri-&#13;
bution of income, and poor families have more children; the incidence of&#13;
children with basic needs deficits is larger than adults. Second, life&#13;
expectancy at birth--basically determined by infant mortality--is perhaps&#13;
the prime basic need. Infant nutrition, lowering of infectious diseases&#13;
due to better shelter, and childcare are crucial inputs in this process.&#13;
Third, evidence shows that the marginal propensity to spend on children&#13;
(by defining a broad concept of such spending such as mothers' time, quality&#13;
of parents-children interaction) is low. Additional rural-urban migration,&#13;
a distinctive feature of the future, will compound the problem. All these&#13;
propensities are lower in urban areas. In sum, normal income growth will&#13;
not solve the basic needs deficits of children.&#13;
2. The calorie deficit&#13;
2a.  Agg)egate magnitude: i" coo6t&#13;
Countrywide survey data on the present distribution of calories&#13;
in the population is extremely scanty. An alternative is to allocate known&#13;
aggregate (or country mean) consumption across income groups by using&#13;
available income distribution data and assumptions about the relationship&#13;
1/&#13;
between consumption and income.&#13;
1/ This follows the technique used in M4alnutrition and Poverty , cit&#13;
A semi-log calorie income relationship is specified with an elasticity&#13;
equal to 0.15 at a level of consumption equal to requirements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
Consumption by income groups was derived for the two alternative&#13;
income distributions discussed above (distributions I and II) and for&#13;
several ranges of country-mean consumption, 0.9, 1.0, and 1.1 times the&#13;
mean calorie requirement. These values encompass most of the range of the&#13;
Latin American countries in question and, for a given country, allow a&#13;
2/&#13;
sensitivity analysis.   The resulting calorie deficit was priced using the&#13;
"cost per calorie" implicit in the cost of the food basket used by ECLA in&#13;
defining poverty lines. As mentioned above, this basket includes an&#13;
"efficiency correction" but also maintains consumer preferences.&#13;
Table 22 shows the cost of the calorie deficit as a percentage&#13;
of &amp;NP under the worst distribution of income (Distribution I). The results&#13;
are shown for countries of different GNP per capita and different mean&#13;
calorie availability over mean requirement. Under the worst of circumstances,&#13;
this cost is between 1.5 and 2 percent of GNP for countries of US$600-800&#13;
per capita income and about 1 percent for the countries above US$1,000.&#13;
2b.  Cat.otie deic46 in young chWid'Len: inte)ventionz&#13;
The nature of the calorie deficit in Latin America illustrates&#13;
children's dimensions of basic needs: 111 million individuals, belonging&#13;
to the poorest income groups, experience calorie deficits; of them, 51.6&#13;
million are young children, 55.4 percent of all young children in the&#13;
regiot. The mean incidence of malnutrition in the population, 35.8 percent,&#13;
results from the fact that 27.4 percent of adults are malnourished and&#13;
1/ For the fifth quintile a share of income of 4 and 5 percent is used for&#13;
distributions I and II, respectively.&#13;
2/ See Table A-4 in the Appendix.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
65 -&#13;
Table 22:   COST OF THE CALORIE DEFICIT AS A FRACTION OF GNP&#13;
(%)&#13;
M~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
GNP per capita,               Mean Calorie Availability Over&#13;
dollars                       Mean Calorie Requirement&#13;
0.9          1.0        1.1&#13;
600                         1.95         0.70       0.0034&#13;
800                         1.46         0.52       0.0025&#13;
1000                         1.17         0.42       0.0020&#13;
1100                         1.06         0.38       0.0018&#13;
Source: Table A-ll.&#13;
55.4 percent of children. The distributive dimension of malnutrition--the&#13;
strong association between malnutrition and poverty--gives origin to a&#13;
larger incidence of malnutrition among children.&#13;
Table 23: LATIN AMERICA: THE DIFFERENTIAL INCIDENCE&#13;
OF CALORIE MALNUTRITION AMONG YOUNG&#13;
CHILDREN, 1975&#13;
Number of people     Percentage that&#13;
(millions)         are malnourished&#13;
Young children (below age 10)         51.6                 55.4&#13;
Rest of the population                60.4                 27.4&#13;
Total                          111.0                 35.8&#13;
Source: Marcelo Selowsky,"The Economic Dimensions of Malnutrition in&#13;
Young Childrent"World Bank Working Paper #294, October 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
Projections for the representative child in the poorest income groups&#13;
are more disturbing than for the representative adult. First, the scattered&#13;
empirical evidence does not show significantly higher calorie-income elasti-&#13;
cities for children than for adults. Second, to the extent that development&#13;
in general (and urbanization in particular) increases women's participation&#13;
in the labor force, infant nutrition could deteriorate because of further&#13;
declines in breastfeeding. If additional purchased food for the infant&#13;
(from additional earnings of women now participating in the labor force) does&#13;
not compensate for losses in breast-milk consumption, the net effect may be&#13;
a deterioration in the infant's nutritional status. Thus, higher household&#13;
incomes due to women's participation in the labor force could be consistent&#13;
with a deterioration in the level of nutrition of children.&#13;
Other factors associated with urbanization--and urbanization will&#13;
be a distinctive feature of the future--will also tend to adversely affect&#13;
young children. Competing expenditures such as transportation, clothing,&#13;
and housing are more important in urban than rural areas, and affect the&#13;
share of income spent on food. Relative prices of food also tend to be&#13;
higher in cities. In addition, new commodities become available to be&#13;
consumed basically by adults, such as entertainment and fashion. As a result,&#13;
the share of income spent on children's food may decline because expendi-&#13;
tures other than food become necessary and new commodities for adults become&#13;
available. These considerations suggest that the future will not solve the&#13;
problem with the desired speed. Therefore, the need for specific nutrition&#13;
interventions becomes imperative.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
2c. The e64etivenies c' taAget ouLented 6ood p,'Lo2town&#13;
sIm c     QUten  1/&#13;
i.        Interventions to increase calorie consumption in malnourished&#13;
children range from general food subsidies (for example, subsidies on the&#13;
import of cereals) to specific programs for poor children, such as school&#13;
breakfasts. To reach children in the poorest group, the first kind of&#13;
program subsidizes all consumers, rich and poor, adults and children. The&#13;
program has what might be called a large "leakage." The second has less&#13;
leakage, only to the extent that some food is diverted to the adults in the&#13;
family. These considerations do not always make target programs more cost&#13;
effective. Target oriented programs can be very expensive administratively;&#13;
on the other hand, the leakage of general food subsidies can become smaller&#13;
if the subsidy is concentrated on a single food consumed basically by poor&#13;
households or poor children.&#13;
The above becomes clearer if the cost of a program whose objective&#13;
is to increase children's food consumtption by one dollar is divided into:&#13;
(a) the cost of the intrafamily leakage, equivalent to the subsidy on adults'&#13;
consumption in poor families that is necessary to achieve the objective,&#13;
(b) the income-group leakage, or the subsidy received by nontarget families,&#13;
and (c) the administrative costs of the program.&#13;
General programs are those where (b) becomes an inportant part of&#13;
the fiscal cost of the program; nontarget groups must then be subsidized to&#13;
reach target families. Examples are general food production subsidies or&#13;
subsidies on food imports, and ration shop schemes for the entire population.&#13;
Target-oriented programs are those wlhere this component of the cost is rela-&#13;
tively smaller:   food stamips or ration-shop programs for specified families,&#13;
1/ For a more thorough discussion of this issue, see Marcelo Selowsky, "The&#13;
Economic Dimensions of Mallnutrition in Young Children," World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper #294, Ocober 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
+-r1--hore and on-site feeding programs in specific schools and health&#13;
centers.&#13;
ii.       Target-oriented food programs are presently being implemented in&#13;
several developing countries. Ration-shops with free or subsidized rations&#13;
for pres-1ected families, take-home and on-site feeding programs for children&#13;
1/&#13;
in specifi- schools, and health centers are some examples.    Other countries&#13;
are considering and experimenting with interventions such as food stamps for&#13;
specified populations.&#13;
What is the effectiveness of these programs in increasing children's&#13;
food consumption? Ilow much of a program's food simply replaces old consumptioni?&#13;
How much of the food intended for children is diverted to adults? What are&#13;
the magnitudes of these replacements and diversions that make these programs&#13;
more or less effective than income transfers equivalent to the subsidy&#13;
embodied in the program?&#13;
Any transfer of a food commodity in excess of wihat the household&#13;
is voluntarily willing to consume will be sold to households with different&#13;
food preferences or to households not reached by the program. The program will&#13;
be equivalent to an income transfer, and its effectiveness will be proportional&#13;
to the marginal propensity to spend on children's food. The effect on calories&#13;
will depend on the calorie content of that additional food. A parameter captur-&#13;
ing both elements is the calorie-income elasticity of children's consumption;&#13;
if that elasticity is 0.5, any food program embodying a subsidy equivalent&#13;
to a per capita income transfer of 10 percent will increase the calorie intake&#13;
of children by 5 percent.&#13;
1/ For an excellent survey on present experieaces in supplementary feeding in&#13;
different countries, see Simon Maxwell, "Food Aid and Supplementary Feeding:&#13;
Impact and Policy Implications," Institute of Development Studies, University&#13;
of Sussex, November 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
Several food programs operate like an income transfer without house-&#13;
holds reselling the concessionary food: (a) Programs that transfer free or&#13;
subsidized food in magnitudes smaller (or in infra-marginal amounts) than&#13;
the amount previously consumed by the family, will replace initial levels of&#13;
consumption and release purchasing power of a value equal to the subsidy&#13;
(this characteristic holds for most of the ration-shops and take-home programs&#13;
presently implemented in most countries) L/; (b) A site feeding program for&#13;
children (breakfast and lunch in school) when the food consumed on site is&#13;
smaller than the amount of that food previously consumed at home (here the&#13;
site-food will, in part,replace the food eaten at home); (c) A Food-stamp&#13;
program providing stamps of a smaller value than the initial (preprogram)&#13;
food consumption level of the family. The income transfer is equal to the&#13;
concessionary component of the stamps--the difference between the value of&#13;
the stamps and the price charged for them. Programs more effective than&#13;
equivalent income transfers are food stamp programs for which a sufficiently&#13;
high price is charged and "full feeding" programs for children,distributing&#13;
sufficient food to potentially replace all food previously eaten at home.&#13;
The programs described above do not induce substitutions between&#13;
foods. But what happens if programs do change the composition of food&#13;
consumption? How, then, can the change in calorie consumption be predicted?&#13;
When substitution occurs, the increment in the consumption of a particular&#13;
food (subsidized or provided by the program) can induce a decline in the&#13;
consumption of other foods, that is, foods that are substitutes. If the&#13;
1/ This is the experience of the ration-shop schemes in India and Sri Lanka.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70o -&#13;
depree ef svbstituticn is strong and the foods being substituted account&#13;
for an importpnt share of the initial calorie consumption, the net effect&#13;
1/&#13;
.r 'a lorie Intake could be negative.   Information on such substitution is&#13;
-v'-trevmely rcanty, even at the level of aggregate household consumption,&#13;
and for children it is nonexistent. Thus, one can speculate only about the&#13;
effectiveness of programs that induce these substitutions. It will become&#13;
clear that znny of the current nutrition interventions fall into this&#13;
category.&#13;
Milk price subsidies or free distribution of milk (as in take home&#13;
programs) in amounts substantially above previous household consumption are&#13;
typical cases. If resale is not possible, these policies will induce a&#13;
substitution among food commodities. If children consume two basic foods,&#13;
cereals and milk, these programs will increase children's consumption of&#13;
milk and decrease children's consumption of cereals, if both foods are&#13;
substitutes. (The decline in milk's implicit price decreases children's&#13;
cereal consumption.) Moreover, total calorie consumption could decline&#13;
if, as is usually the case, most of the calories are derived from cereals.&#13;
It can be shown that, in this case, even a small degree of substitution&#13;
between the two foods could induce a negative effect on calorie intake.&#13;
Milk subsidies and free distribution of milk are currently popular programs,&#13;
perhaps conceived to increase the consumption of high quality proteins.&#13;
If calories are the major nutritional problem, however, a re-evaluation of&#13;
milk programs along the lines described above becomes imperative.&#13;
1/ For a formal presentation of the relation between cross elasticities and&#13;
calorie consumption, see Reutlinger and Selowsky, op. cit., pp. 44-45.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
3.  Options in the health sector:   the change of present biases&#13;
3a.  The "utban-cumative" biao o0 pte6ent syztem.&#13;
The .;mpoAtance o d demand&#13;
i.        Present public health systems are characterized by an expensive&#13;
urban-curative orientation. Social security systems have become increasingly&#13;
important in providing health services, but because their beneficiaries are&#13;
mainly middle-income urban employees, belonging either to the public sector&#13;
or to the modern private sector, they fail to reach nonaffiliated urban&#13;
workers and individuals in rural areas.&#13;
Table 24 shows that in Colombia households in the poorest&#13;
quintile living in large cities receive a subsidy from the public health&#13;
sector 5 times larger than those in rural areas. Table 25 shows that in&#13;
Brazil the percentage of public health expenditures devoted to preventive&#13;
medicine declined from 87.1 to 29.7 from 1949 to 1975. The effect is that,&#13;
in spite of an increase in total public expenditures in health as a percentage&#13;
of GUIP from 1.0 to 2.5, the amount spent on preventive medicine as a percentage&#13;
of GNP has remained constant.&#13;
ii.   The expansion in the supply of rural, preventive-oriented health care&#13;
will not, per se, guarantee increases in the consumption of these services.&#13;
Interventions increasing the utilization of health institutions and in those&#13;
factors affecting the demand for health services must also be identified.&#13;
It was found in urban Colombia that, controlling for the income of the house-&#13;
hold, the level of family education had an important impact on the number&#13;
of visits to doctors. In fact, doubling the level of schooling of the&#13;
household head increased per capita visits by 18 percent. Thus, any deter-&#13;
minant of"health conscientiousness," schooling probably being one of them,&#13;
becomes a point of intervention.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
Table 24: SUBSIDIES PER HOUSEHOLD FROM THE PUBLIC HEALTH SYSTEM, 1974&#13;
(dollars per year)&#13;
Income                 Large     Intermediate   Small       Rural        Total&#13;
Quintile               Cities 1/    Cities 2/   Towns 3/    Areas 4/     Country&#13;
1 (Poorest)             60           32           19         12            22&#13;
2                       41           28          20          15            23&#13;
3                       55           26          21         15             28&#13;
4                       28           35          14          13            23&#13;
5 (Richest)             21           18          19           8            18&#13;
Total Country           35           27          19          14            23&#13;
1/ More ½ million.&#13;
2/ 30-50 thousand..&#13;
3/ 1.5-30 thousand.&#13;
Source: M. Selowsky: WhoNBenefits from Government Expenditure. op. cit.&#13;
Table 25   BRAZIL: COMPOSITION OF PUBLIC HEALTH EXPENDITURES&#13;
(Percentages)&#13;
1949        1965        1969        1975&#13;
INDIVIDUtJ,-CURATIVE&#13;
(Basically Social Security System)    12.9        35.8        59.2         70.2&#13;
COLLECTIVE-PREVENTIVE                87.1         64.1        40.8        29.7&#13;
Ministry of Health                   (35.3)      (25.9)      (13.0)       (5.4)&#13;
States                               (51.8)      (38.2)      (27.8)      (24.3)&#13;
Total                               100.0       100.0        100.0       100.0&#13;
Source: P. Knight and D. Mahar: World Bank,"Brazil Human Resources Special&#13;
Report: Annex III,"October 25, 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73-&#13;
3b.  The Co4t 4a a    P          enie cdtxe woEted'&#13;
hLRa   AY6tefIem6. SmuZation6&#13;
How expensive is a preventive care oriented health system aimed&#13;
at a full coverage of the population? Preliminary estimates for Brazil&#13;
show that such a system could be financed by maintaining the present 2.5&#13;
1/&#13;
percent share of health expenditures in GNP.&#13;
These estimates are based on a strategy that would change the&#13;
present "urban-based-individual-curative system" trend. The alternative&#13;
is a stronger emphasis on primary and collective health care in rural&#13;
areas and poor regions based on the PIASS plan (Program for Grass&#13;
Roots   Health and Sanitation Actions in the Northeast).    The principle&#13;
behind PIASS is that "a large variety of health problems may be success-&#13;
fully prevented and/or treated at the community level, without recourse&#13;
to expensive hospitalization in urban areas, and that preventive and&#13;
simple curative services should be integrated with more complex curative&#13;
services through well-defined institutional channels." 2/&#13;
This system is based on three levels of medical facilities of&#13;
increasing complexity: first, rural health posts in communities of 500-&#13;
2,000 inhabitants staffed by local auxiliaries, whose function is to prevent&#13;
infectious diseases and detect more complex diseases. Second, health centers&#13;
servicing three health posts and staffed by a nurse, a sanitation auxiliary,&#13;
and a day-per-week visit by a doctor based in a larger health center. This&#13;
larger health center is attached to a regional hospital, which represents the&#13;
third level of health facilities and also serves the urban population.&#13;
1/ Peter Knight and Dennis Mahar, "Brazil Iluman Resources Special Report,&#13;
Annex III: Health and Nutrition," World Bank, mimeo, October 25, 1978.&#13;
2/ Knight and Mahar, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
By costing out the expansion of such institutions (operating and&#13;
capital costs) and by projecting population growth, two alternative pro-&#13;
jections are made and shown in Table 26. The first aims at full coverage&#13;
by the year 2000 and assumes a 7 percent GDP growth rate in the period&#13;
1980-2000. The second involves a more moderate increase in coverage and&#13;
assumes a GDP growth of 4 percent. In both cases the total health expendi-&#13;
ture as a fraction of GDP remains in the 2-2.5 percent range.&#13;
Table 26: BRAZIL: COVERAGE AND COSTS OF EXPANDING A&#13;
RESTRUCTURED HEALTH SYSTEM&#13;
Percentage Coverage&#13;
Urban             Rural Northeast a/      Cost Percent of GDP&#13;
Projec-     Projec-     Projec-      Projec-     Projec-      Projec-&#13;
tion I      tion II      tion I      tion II     tion I       tion II&#13;
1975        79.0         79.0       0(50)        0(50)         -&#13;
1980       100.0        92.8       30(60)       15(60)        2.3           2.2&#13;
1985       100.0        96.4       65(80)       30(65)        2.4           2.4&#13;
1990       100.0       IOO.O       85(100)      45(70)        2.3           2.5&#13;
2000       100.0       100.0      100(100)      70(80)        2.0           2.5&#13;
a/  This coverage reflects the expansion of the first level    of health posts.&#13;
Values in parentheses refer to the capacity of the second and third levels,&#13;
which are highly influenced by the presernt structure of the system.&#13;
This exercise shows that 2.5 percent of GDP can finance a proper&#13;
health system in a $1,000 per capita income country with reasonably good&#13;
growth. if the system is restructured to a less expensive primary care-&#13;
oriented system. Most of the other countries discussed here spend between&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
1 and 1.5 percent of GNP on health; therefore, it is likely that an additional&#13;
percentage point of spending, plus a restructuring of their systems along the&#13;
lines described above,could have considerable impact on the health coverage&#13;
1/&#13;
of the population.&#13;
4. Issues in delivering educational services&#13;
4a. The ithJL pxLO4ity: incvtea,-Lng enottment and&#13;
the quag-ity o6 educaEton in   ant axtea&#13;
The first priorities in expanding educational services are to&#13;
expand rural enrollment rates by increasing incentives to attend school, and&#13;
to increase the quality of teachers and teaching materials in rural areas.&#13;
Neither goal can automatically be attained by simply expanding the physical&#13;
supply of schools or school places.&#13;
Expansion of rural enrollment implies drawing an increasing number&#13;
of children from families of lower socioeconomic status and less densely&#13;
populated areas. Their low enrollment is the result of factors affecting the&#13;
demand for schooling as well as of the availability of school places. Low&#13;
educational levels of parents and the cost of schooling--foregone earnings&#13;
and transportation costs--are crucial factors in influencing the demand for&#13;
additional schooling.&#13;
An illustrative case is Brazil. In 1974, enrollment rates of&#13;
children ages 7-14 were 72.5, 55.3, and 44.4 percent for the total country,&#13;
2/&#13;
total rural areas, and rural Northeast, respectively.    Table 27 shows the&#13;
pyramid ratio (the percentage of children in each grade as a fraction of the&#13;
enrollment in the first grade) for the first 6 years of primary schooling.&#13;
1/ Based on a Bank study mission visit to Cuba, I estimate that Cuba spends&#13;
roughly 4 percent of the GNP on health. Its health system is highly&#13;
rural and primary-care-oriented.&#13;
2/ Yves Tencalla, W4orld Bank, Brazil Education Sector Memorandum, mimeo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
Table 27: BRAZIL: PYRAMID RATIO&#13;
(Percentages)&#13;
Grade                  Country                 Rural Areas&#13;
1                      100.0                     100.0&#13;
2                       55.2                      38.3&#13;
3                       44.4                      24.8&#13;
4                       36.9                      15.7&#13;
5                       32.1                       2.6&#13;
6                       25.2                       1.0&#13;
Source:  Tencalla, op. cit.&#13;
The constraint here is due,not to a lack of school places,but to&#13;
insufficient incentives to remain in school. Subsidies to school attendance,&#13;
such as school breakfasts and lunches, free provision of textbooks and&#13;
clothing, and transportation, are relevant policy options. In the state of&#13;
Goias, for example, experiments with school meal programs increased effective&#13;
1/&#13;
school attendance from 67-80 percent to 84-95 percent.&#13;
Another constraint is that teachers in rural primary schools,&#13;
particularly in the more backward regions, have extremely low levels of&#13;
pedagogical training. Ninety percent of the teachers in Northeast Brazil&#13;
lack pedagogical training altogether and most have little primary schooling.&#13;
In 1972, 31 percent of the Northeast teaching force had not completed&#13;
primary education, and in 1974, 77 percent of these teachers were reported&#13;
to have had only primary schooling.&#13;
1/ Federal University of Goias-INIEP-SEC-CNAE Project, 1976.&#13;
2/ Tencalla, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 7&#13;
The inability to attract better teachers results fron t'le low&#13;
salaries paid by the rural municipalities in Northeast Brazil.    Teachers&#13;
with complete primary education receiLve between CZ$10-51 a month, compared&#13;
with the legal minimum salary of US$57. They usually work without contracts,&#13;
1/&#13;
and their salaries fluctuate according to the budget of the rural municipio.&#13;
From the above data it is clear that a larger fraction of a&#13;
country's primary education budget must be used, first, to increase incentives&#13;
to attend rural schools, basically school meals (this is quite related to the&#13;
nutrition objectives discussed earlier), and second, to improve the working&#13;
conditions and increase the salaries of teachers in rural areas.&#13;
4b.  FinancLn  pJtokitiez:   ttan    e4tkng AicaL 4ub6i4diQe&#13;
Aum   AgheA educat on: towaoJd the  eti-Jinancig o6&#13;
hfgfgheA educa.on&#13;
Preliminary estimates show that, for Latin America, providing six&#13;
years of schooling to the overall population would increase the educational&#13;
2/&#13;
budget by 6 to 17 percent.    Because the share of expenditures in education&#13;
in GNP is approximately 3-4 percent, this increase amounts to 1/5 - 2/3 of&#13;
one percent of GNP. This is the cost of expanding the supply of primary&#13;
school places; an additional fiscal effort is required if better teacher&#13;
salaries and school meals in rural areas becomes also part of this package.&#13;
W.hat additional sources of finance can be conceived within the educational&#13;
sector?&#13;
1/ Tencalla, op. cit.&#13;
2/ Sebastian Piniera, Preliminary Estimates from the Critical Povertv in&#13;
Latin America Project, ECLA.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
The most obvious way to finance these measures is to gradually&#13;
eliminate ehe subsidy to higher education and transfer these funds to&#13;
primary rural education. In most countries, public expenditure for higher&#13;
education represents half the expenditure for primary education. A substan-&#13;
tial amount of public funds could be released, therefore, if higher education&#13;
became self-financed.&#13;
Subsidies to higher education are perhaps one of the most regressive&#13;
transfers in the economy, clearly more unequally distributed than personal&#13;
income, as shown in Figure 1 for Colombia. Equity and efficiency point to a&#13;
clear solution: the replacement of free higher education with a system where&#13;
tuition covering the cost of education is charged and students are given&#13;
loans to be repaid after graduation.&#13;
1/&#13;
In Appendix II, a model exploring this option is presented.    In&#13;
the model, a fraction of students (the poorer ones) are entitled to a yearly&#13;
loan equal to their tuition plus their foregone earnings while in school.&#13;
The loan must be repaid in 10 yearly installments after graduation, at an&#13;
interest rate of 10 percent. Assuming that 50 to 70 percent of enrolled&#13;
students receive loans, the system would become self-financed within 12 to&#13;
15 years.&#13;
5. Housing and associated services in urban areas: a cost simulation&#13;
exercise&#13;
Location and typical dwelling standards limit the access of the&#13;
poor to new housing and a lack of capital markets compounds the problem.&#13;
Table 28 shows that, in Bogota and Mexico City, the cheapest housing unit&#13;
1/ See Appendix II.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
%       100                               _                   7&#13;
Income                                                          /&#13;
Subsidy     8&#13;
80&#13;
s°0tt~~~~ I&#13;
Primary       /&#13;
60&#13;
40__                        _  _ _/&#13;
/     ~Income &#13;
20       00X0&#13;
/               -     H~~~~~~~~Iligher&#13;
20        40        60         80        100  % Households&#13;
FIGURE 1&#13;
DISTRIBUTION OF THE SUBSIDY TO EDUCATION AID OF PERSOUIAL IC1CO!.E&#13;
currently available cannot be afforded by 47 and 55 percent of the inhabitants&#13;
of these cities, respectively. Alternative housing standards and locations&#13;
are identified to analyze the sensitivity of costs and the subsidy required&#13;
to finance the difference between mortgage payments and household expenditures&#13;
for rents. Practically all households in Mexico City could afford multi-&#13;
family dwellings with basic services located on the periphery of the city.&#13;
In Bogota, only 15 percent of households would be unable to finance these&#13;
types of housing; to afford these dwellings, a subsidy of only 12.9 percent&#13;
on the required mortage would be required. The issue is how to implement&#13;
these new standards of housing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 28: COST OF HOUSING UNITS OF VARIOUS STANDARD AND LOCATION, PERCENTAGE OF&#13;
HOUSEHOLDS UNABLE TO AFFORD THEM AND REQUIRED SUBSIDY ON THEIR RENTS /a&#13;
(in 1976 US$)&#13;
Bogota                      Mexico City&#13;
Location                          Cost   Households   Subsidy     Cost   Households   Subsidy&#13;
(%)         (%)                 (x)         (X)&#13;
Periphery&#13;
Single family, individual services       1256       17         21.7      2063       14          9.2&#13;
Multi-family,       "        "           1809       36         21.9      1960       12          3.4&#13;
it    of     basic services            1134       15         12.9      1274        4           -&#13;
Intermediate zones&#13;
Single family, individual services       4787       73         71.1     31184       95+        92.6&#13;
Multi-family,      "         "           2509       50         44.1      7777       72         70.1&#13;
"1   "1      basic services            1837       36         23.5      7096       69         67.1&#13;
Present cheapest housing unit               2477       47          -        4988       55           -&#13;
Per capita income country:                      US$635                          US$1090&#13;
/a  Subsidy is defined as the percentage by which monthly income available for housing falls short of&#13;
required monthly payment. Based on repayment period of 25 years, 10% interest rate and a sbare of&#13;
income devoted to income equal to 15 percent.&#13;
Source: Orville Grimes, Housing for Low-Income Urban Families, Johns Hopkins University Press, 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
Because these examples are quite specific to a particular&#13;
metropolis (for example, the results are very sensitive to location in the&#13;
case of Mexico City), a sensitivity analysis is presented for a typical&#13;
country of US$800 dollars per capita income under the two alternative&#13;
income distributions discussed above, I and II. The objective is to compute&#13;
the subsidy that would allow urban households in the poorest 40 percent (of&#13;
total households) to afford (a) a dwelling equal to twice the per capita&#13;
GNP, $1,600, (b) a dwelling five times the per capita GNP, $4,000.&#13;
Table 29 shows the required yearly subsidy assuming households in&#13;
the bottom 40 percent devote 15 percent of their incomes to housing. It&#13;
is assumed that 45 percent of the total households in the bottom 40 percent&#13;
are urban. Table 30 shows that under the worst circumstances, with the more&#13;
unequal distribution of income (I) and the dwelling to be financed amounting&#13;
to five times per capita GNP, the cost of the subsidy is 1.28 percent of&#13;
GNP per year. The subsidy will benefit urban households in the bottom&#13;
40 percent of the income distribution, accounting for 30 percent of all&#13;
urban households.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 29: REQUIRED SUBSIDY TO FINANCE A HOUSING MORTGAGE UNDER DIFFERENT DISTRIBUTION&#13;
OF INCOME (I, II) AND VALUES OF DWELLING. TYPICAL COUNTRY OF US$800 PER&#13;
CAPITA INCOME (VALUES IN DOLLARS)&#13;
V           /a&#13;
Annual household    Yearly rent     Yearly mortgage payment       Required yearly subsidy&#13;
income          expenditure     for a dwelling equal in            per household&#13;
(family size      (15% income)        value, to:                                                Assumed&#13;
Deciles     equal to 6)                        Twice GNP    Five times         1600          4000          fraction&#13;
per capita   GNP p.c.                                       in urban&#13;
I        II        I      II          1600        4000            I    II     I     II          areas&#13;
1        324       720       49     108          176         440           127   68     391   332           0.3&#13;
2        636       960       95     144          176         440            81   32     345   296           0.4&#13;
3        960      1440      144     216          176         440            32   -      296   224           0.5&#13;
4       1440      1920      216     288          176         440            -    -      224   152           0.6&#13;
/a   At 25 years and at 10% interest.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83&#13;
Table 30: FISCAL COST OF THE SUBSIDY TO URBAN HOUSEHOLDS&#13;
Income Distribution I    Income distribution II&#13;
V=1600     V=4000       V=1600       V-4000&#13;
Mean yearly subsidy per&#13;
household (dollars):          80        314           50         251&#13;
Urban households with&#13;
subsidies as a fraction&#13;
of:&#13;
- all households           0.12        0.18         0.07        0.18&#13;
/a&#13;
-  all urban households    0.20        0.30         0.12        0.30&#13;
Cost as a fraction of&#13;
GNP (%) /b                  0.21       1.28         0.13        1.02&#13;
/a  It is assumed 60 percent of households are urban.&#13;
/b  A country average family size of 5.5 is assumed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 84 -&#13;
IV, BALANCING THE OPTIONS: TRADE-OFFS&#13;
BETWEEN BASIC NEEDS AND GROITR&#13;
A. FINANCING THE BASIC NEEDS PACKAGE&#13;
Based on the above considerations, our recommendation is to&#13;
increase public subsidies to basic needs oriented sectors, from their&#13;
present levels of 5-7 percent of GNP to a new level of 10 percent of GNP&#13;
(Table 31). This must be accompanied by changing the nature of delivery&#13;
systems in each sector and transferring regressive segments of subsidies&#13;
within each sector. Without this qualitative change, those additional&#13;
resources will lose a large part of their poverty oriented objective.&#13;
The share of GNP spent on higher education must be kept constant or decline&#13;
as a consequence of a policy of self financing. In health, the share of&#13;
urban based curative medicine must be kept constant, and all increments&#13;
devoted to primary-preventive rural health care.&#13;
Table 31: RESOURCE REQUIREMENTS&#13;
Resources per sector&#13;
Nj                     (as % of GNP)&#13;
Sectors         Actual        TarRet        Reallocations within Sectors&#13;
Education        3-4           5       Toward self financing of higher&#13;
education: food programs and&#13;
teacher's quality in rural areas&#13;
Health          1-2.5          2.5     Pro collective-preventive rural&#13;
health care systems&#13;
Nutrition       &lt; 1            1.0     Target oriented instead of general&#13;
food subsidies&#13;
Housing         &lt; 1            1.5     Eliminating subsidies to middle&#13;
class housing. New standards for&#13;
lower income groups&#13;
Total            5-7          10.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
For countries like Brazil, which have already reached 2.5 percent&#13;
public spending in health, additional funds amount to only 3 percent of GNP.&#13;
For other countries the increment reaches 5 percent, a doubling of public&#13;
spending in these sectors.&#13;
Table 32 presents some options for financing such a program. In&#13;
the oil producing countries--Colombia, Mexico, and Ecuador--domestic oil&#13;
prices are kept substantially below world prices. It is estimated that&#13;
lifting them to world price levels would increase government revenues by&#13;
3, 2.5, and 4 percent of GNP in these countries, respectively. Half of&#13;
this increase could be devoted to finance the basic needs package, the&#13;
other half to finance investment in the oil sector. In the case of Mexico,&#13;
additional oil production will increase government saving, even by&#13;
maintaining low domestic prices, by an additional 4.3 percent of GNP (from&#13;
1/&#13;
2.2 to 6.5) by the year 1982.   Half of this increase, 2.15 percent of GNP,&#13;
is another source of finance.&#13;
If lifting the price of oil (row 1 in Table 32) is considered&#13;
politically unfeasible or having a regressive impact (which we doubt, an&#13;
important issue to be researched), additional taxation would be the alter-&#13;
native option.&#13;
Not a single report fails to emphasize that there is still room&#13;
for additional fiscal revenues by increasing (effective) direct taxation&#13;
at the top of the income distribution and also by increasing the tax base.&#13;
In several oil producing countries, additional oil revenues have been&#13;
accompanied by declines in the tax ratio (taxes over GNIP) in the rest of the&#13;
1/ World Bank economic mission estimate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
Table 32: SOURCES OF FINANCE&#13;
(Percentages of GNP)&#13;
Brazil    Peru     Colombia   Mexico   Ecuador&#13;
Half the increase in net                          1.5       1.25      2&#13;
revenues out of increasing&#13;
the price of domestically&#13;
sold (and produced) oil&#13;
to world prices./a&#13;
Half the additional                                         2.15&#13;
savings out of increased&#13;
oil production (at present&#13;
domestic prices)&#13;
Additional taxation (in        3         4        1.2       2         4.8&#13;
parenthesis,taxation from    (1.2)      (1.2)    (1.2)     (1.2)      (1.2)&#13;
eliminating exemption on&#13;
imputed rent on owner&#13;
occupied dwelling)&#13;
Eliminating the subsidy                           1&#13;
to the electricity&#13;
sector&#13;
Additional government                             1&#13;
royalties from coal and&#13;
uranium exploitation&#13;
TOTAL                      3         4       4.7        5.4       6.8&#13;
/a  The additional oil revenues obtained by charging domestic consumers the&#13;
world price is, as a fraction of GNP, 3%, 2.5% and 4% for Colombia,&#13;
Mexicoaand Ecuador.   If only 0.5% of GNP can be raised by manipulating&#13;
this option, the difference will have to be obtained by additional&#13;
taxation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
economy. In the case of Ecuador, this ratio declined from .186 to .138&#13;
between 1972 and 1977. Maintaining the 1972 figure yields the additional&#13;
share of .048 used in Table 32.&#13;
It is estimated that eliminating tax exemptions on imputed rent&#13;
on owner-occupied dwellings--one of the most regressive subsidies--could&#13;
yield a tax equal to 1.2 percent of GINP. If the upper 10 percent of the popu-&#13;
lation receives a share of GNP equal to 0.4 and their imputed rent is 0.2&#13;
of their income, their tax base will increase in 0.08 of GNP. If their&#13;
income tax is 15 percent it yields an additional 1.2 percent of GNP. In&#13;
several countries, particularly Mexico and Brazil, either inflation or&#13;
high levels of deductions erode the tax base. In Brazil tax deductions&#13;
exempt families with gross incomes up to four or five times the per capita&#13;
GNP.   In Colombia, adjusting property prices at commercial values could&#13;
yield an additional 1 percent of GNP, and tax reforms now being contemplated&#13;
in Peru could yield additional taxation equal to 4 percent of GNP.&#13;
Sources of finance from reallocating subsidies presently given&#13;
to other sectors have not been contemplated here, except for Colombia, where&#13;
1 percent of GNP could be made available by eliminating the subsidy to the&#13;
electricity sector. Defense represents at least one-fourth of the fiscal&#13;
budget in several countries. In Peru, several of the present subsidies to&#13;
electricity and consumer goods--benefitting consumers of all income groups--&#13;
are not considered here a source of finance because their elimination is&#13;
part of their present anti-inflationary program. In the case of Brazil,&#13;
the investment budget of the government is held constant in this exercise.&#13;
1/ lWorld Bank economic mission estimates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
B.  TRADE-OFFS WITH GROWTH: KEEPING UNCERTAINTY DOWN&#13;
What is the maximum loss to the long term growth rate induced by&#13;
this additional 5 percent of GNP devoted to basic needs? Let us assume the&#13;
worse scenario: (a) This additional basic needs package has zero productive&#13;
or asset creation effect on the poor. We conceive of it as a pure consumption&#13;
transfer (though this would not be the case, particularly in the case of&#13;
education). (b) Oil revenues are not feasible sources of financing;&#13;
therefore, the 5 percent is financed entirely by an additional 12.5 percent&#13;
income tax, levied on the income of the richest 10 of the population account-&#13;
ing for 0.4 percent of GNP. In terms of investment incentives, this tax,&#13;
which affects the income of new investment, is clearly worse than the tax&#13;
options discussed above, such as the elimination of deductions and exemptions&#13;
on imputed rent and increases in property taxes (which tend to tax a larger&#13;
share of inframarginal income).&#13;
What is the maximum effect of this tax on the investment behavior&#13;
of the richest 10 percent and its impact on the overall country investment&#13;
1/&#13;
rate? Two capital market scenarios are presented to estimate this effect.&#13;
Within each, extreme parameter values and assumptions are used to derive an&#13;
upper bound for the decline in investment.&#13;
One scenario is a closed economy capital market, that is, no&#13;
capital flight takes place. The decline in investment results from both a&#13;
smaller supply of savings (a function of the marginal propensity to save&#13;
by this income group) and a decline in the net yield of new investment&#13;
1/ See Appendix III for calculations under different scenarios.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
opportunities. The decline is largest by assuming a perfectly elastic&#13;
demand for investment, that is, the new equilibrium net yield goes down by&#13;
the amount of the additional tax.&#13;
In the open economy case we assume that domestic investors can&#13;
invest abroad and that the return abroad is not affected by the new tax.&#13;
This assumes that either the proceeds of this investment can only be consumed&#13;
abroad or the proceeds can be brought back into the country in a way such&#13;
that the new tax can be evaded.&#13;
To derive maximum values we assume that initially (a) this income&#13;
group investment accounts for 10 percent of GNP, a rather high figure;&#13;
(b) this group pays a 20 percent (tl) income tax; the additional 12.5 percent&#13;
tax (t2) is equivalent, therefore, to a decline of 15.6 percent in the yield of&#13;
new investment (t2/1-tl). In the closed economy case, the results are a&#13;
function of the marginal propensity to save and the interest elasticity of&#13;
the supply of savings, e. We assume a rather high figure of 0.25 for the&#13;
propensity and 0.5 and 1.0 for the elasticity. In the open economy case only&#13;
the interest elasticity of the demand for investment, n , is relevant; a&#13;
range between 0.5 and 1.5 is used in the analysis.&#13;
Table 33 shows the results. In the worst of circumstances, the&#13;
decline in the country's investment rate is 2.5 percentage points; that is,&#13;
if the rate was initially 20 percent, the new rate will be 17.5 percent. If&#13;
the social return to capital in the economy is 0.2 (gross of taxes, depre-&#13;
ciation, and excess market wage over the opportunity cost of labor), the&#13;
decline in the growth rate will be at most one half of 1 percent (0.2 x 0.025).&#13;
If a country's historical growth rate was 6 percent per year, the maximum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
effect will be to reduce that rate to 5.5 percent: At the most "the trade-&#13;
off ratio" between redistribution and growth is 10:1; in other words, a&#13;
5 percent transfer of GNP toward "consumption" results in a half a percent&#13;
lower GI? growth.&#13;
1/&#13;
Table 33: DECLINES IN THE COUNTRY'S INVESTMIENT RATE&#13;
Closed Economy Case                     Open Economy Case&#13;
Interest     Marginal   Interest                Interest elas-&#13;
elasticity  propensity     rate     Total       ticity of demand   Total&#13;
of savings    effect      effect    effect      for investment     effect&#13;
£ = 0.5        0.01      0.007      0.017         n = 0.5          0.0078&#13;
e = 1.0        0.01      0.014      0.024         n = 1.0          0.0156&#13;
nl = 1.5         0.0234&#13;
1t Appendix III.&#13;
Crucial in the implementation of such a policy is to keep&#13;
uncertainty down. Investment behavior is much more sensitive to uncertainty&#13;
than to net yields; if the tax reform takes place in a milieu where other&#13;
"rules of the game"--concerning other property incomes or property rights--&#13;
are being questioned, the negative effects on investment could be&#13;
substantially larger.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -I&#13;
APPENDIX I&#13;
ADDITIONAL TABLES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A-1:  FRACTION (f) OF CIILDREN (BELOW AGE 10) IN DIFFERENT GROUPS OF&#13;
THE POPULATION ORDERED ACCORDING TO HOUSEHOLD PER CAPITA INCOME&#13;
Colombia                  Bogota                  Quito                   Lima&#13;
Population  Children    Population   Children    Population  Children    Population   Children&#13;
(%)        (f)          (M)          (f)         (%)        (f)          (2)         (f)&#13;
Poorest      20.0       0.43          14.8       0.43         17.8       0.48          9.2        0.43&#13;
Next         20.0       0.37           8.3       0.43         14.9       0.43         12.4        0.34&#13;
Next         20.0       0.31           7.1       0.39         13.5       0.37          9.4        0.32&#13;
Total       100.0       0.32         100.0       0.33        100.0       0.35        100          0.29&#13;
Population&#13;
Sources: Colombia--M. Selowsky: Who Benefits from Government ExPenditure: A Case Study in Colombia&#13;
Cities----Special Tabulation from ECIEL Study: P. Musgrove, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
Table A-2: ESTIMATES OF LIFE EXPECTANCY BY HOUSEHOLD INCOME LEVEL,&#13;
BY STATE GROUPS, 1970&#13;
Average Monthly Income in Cruzeiros&#13;
Sub-region                   1-150     151-300     301-500      501+&#13;
(1)        (2)         (3)        (4)&#13;
1. Amazonia a/                      53.4      53.9         54.8       58.2&#13;
2. Maranhao-Piaui                   50.0      50.8        52.7        55.7&#13;
3. Central Northeasth/              42.8      46.1        50.3        54.4&#13;
4. Bahia-Sergipe                    48.9      50.3         51.9       54.9&#13;
5. Minas Gerais-Espirito Santo      53.8      55.4         55.6       62.3&#13;
6. Rio de J. Guanaba                54.1      54.8         57.6       62.1&#13;
7. Sao Paulo                        54.7      56.1         58.7       63.9&#13;
8. Parana                           54.8      56.5         59.3       63.7&#13;
9. S. Catarina-R.G. Sul             60.5      61.2        63.4        66.9&#13;
10. Central-Westi/                   56.5      57.1         58.2       63.3&#13;
Brazil                           49.9      54.5        57.6        62.0&#13;
Source: Carvalho and Wood (1977:11). Reported in Merrick T. and Moran, R.,&#13;
"World Bank Brazil Human Resources Report."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 94 -&#13;
Table A-3: INFANT MORTALITY RATES BY PROVINCES&#13;
(per thousand live births)&#13;
Mexico, Central Region, 1971            Ecuador, Sierra Region, 1974&#13;
Guanajuato               83.8           Azuay                   84.6&#13;
Queretaro                64.1           Bolivar                  71.7&#13;
Hidalgo                  60.6           Canar                    64.5&#13;
Mexico                  105.0           Carchi                   98.8&#13;
Distrito Federal         73.2           Chimborazo             105.7&#13;
Morelos                  39.2           Cotopaxi               122.1&#13;
Puebla                   79.7           Imbabura               100.4&#13;
Tlaxcala                105.9           Loja                    45.4&#13;
Pichincha                75.0&#13;
Tungurahua               98.4&#13;
National Total           63.3                                    70.2&#13;
Source:   Mexico -- Anuario Stadistico, 1971.&#13;
Ecuador - Country Economic Report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A-4: MEAN PER CAPITA DAILY CALORIE CONSUMPTION&#13;
(1974-76 PERIOD) AND REQUIREMENTS&#13;
Mean per capita          Per capita          /&#13;
Country           calorie consumption,      requirements&#13;
(Per day)           CR   (per day)&#13;
(1)                   (2)&#13;
Mexico                      2721                 2330             1.17&#13;
Colombia                    2181                 2320               94&#13;
Brazil                     2513                  2390            1.05&#13;
Ecuador                    2120                  2290              .92&#13;
Peru                       2352                  2350            1.00&#13;
Turke /                    2836                  2520             1.12&#13;
/a 1974 data.&#13;
Source: Provisional FAO Food Balance Sheets.&#13;
Table A-5: MEXICO:    FREQUENCY OF PROTEIN/CALORIE MALNUTRITION&#13;
IN PRESCHOOL-AGED CHILDREN IN RURAL ZONES&#13;
Percent of Cases Based on Degree of Malnutrition /a&#13;
Zone  Norma1~~~~~~  I~~        II~~~           /e&#13;
Zone            Normall)    Grade       Grade I A    Grade IILL-    Total&#13;
North             30.4       50.4        18.8          0.4          100.0&#13;
Center-West      25.1        42.7        28.0          4.2          100.0&#13;
Gulf of Mexico   27.5        44.1        25.5          2.9          100.0&#13;
South            19.6        44.2        30.8          5.4          100.0&#13;
Southeast        10.8        50.5        34.5          4.2          100.0&#13;
/a  Based on Gomez classification: % theoretical weight for age.&#13;
lb  90% - 1007' of average weight; /c  75% - 90%; /d  60% - 75%; /e   Less&#13;
than 6nl,.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
Table A-6:   DISTRIBUTION OF HEADS OF HOUSEHOLD IN THE&#13;
POOREST INCOME QUINTILE ACCORDING TO La&#13;
LOCATION, SECTOR, AND OCCUPATION, 1974&#13;
(percent)&#13;
URBAN AREAS:&#13;
Self-employed&#13;
a.  Manufacturing                   5.2             16.0&#13;
b.  Services                       10.8|&#13;
Wage Labor                                                    34.6&#13;
a.  Manufacturing                   4.9&#13;
b.  Construction                     5.5    0       18.6&#13;
c.  Services                        8.2&#13;
RURAL AREAS&#13;
a.  Landowners                                      25.6&#13;
b.  Sharecroppers                   6.6&#13;
c.  Tenants and colonos             3.9             18.6&#13;
58.2&#13;
d. Agricultural labor living&#13;
on farms                        8.1&#13;
e. Households not living&#13;
on farms                                        14.0&#13;
Ill-defined occupations                              7.2&#13;
TOTAL                                 100.0&#13;
/a Quintiles according to household per capita income.&#13;
Source: M. Selowsky, Who Benefits from Government: A Case Study in&#13;
Colombia (forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
Table A-7: DISTRIBUTION OF FAMILIES IN THE POVERTY GROUPS&#13;
(Families below two minimum wages or 1/3 of the&#13;
families), 1974-75      CPercentages)&#13;
Regions                     Metropolitan    Other Urban     Rural    Total&#13;
Sao Paulo &amp; Rio                  4               4            4       12&#13;
South                            2               2            8       11&#13;
Minas Gerais &amp; E.S.              1               3            8       12&#13;
Northeast                        3              12           37       52&#13;
North &amp; D.F.                                     4            9       13&#13;
TOTAL                       9              25           66      100&#13;
Source: World Bank Document on Income Distribution in Brazil.&#13;
Table A-8: COMPOSITION OF HOUSEHOLDS IN THE POVERTY GROUP,&#13;
ACCORDING TO OCCUPATION OF HEAD (Percentages)&#13;
Peru                                         Turkey&#13;
(poorest 25%)                                  (poorest 20%)&#13;
Sierra Rural                82.7            Farmers                 67.4&#13;
Coast &amp; jungle farmers       1.1            Rural labor              4.8&#13;
Wage earners                 7.1            Artisans                 9.7&#13;
Urban self-employed          9.1            Unskilled labor         13.6&#13;
Other                    4.5&#13;
100.0                                   100.0&#13;
Sources: Peru: R. Webb&#13;
Turkey: K. Dervis and S. Robinson.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 98 -&#13;
Tabhi A-9:  DISTRIBUTION OF TIHE POOREST 45 PERCENT OF&#13;
FAMILIES, 1975 /a&#13;
(According to lhousehold income)&#13;
Sector. ;in'    of worker                 Percentage of total families&#13;
Total        Urban          Rural&#13;
No ')ccupation                           11.9         4.1             7.8&#13;
Agriculture                              52.4          1.7           50.7&#13;
Owner                                  0.6         0.1             0.5&#13;
Self-employed                         33.0         0.6            32.4&#13;
Non-salaried in family business        0.3           -             0.3&#13;
Salaried employee                     18.5         1.0            17.5&#13;
Mining                                    0.5          0.3            0.2&#13;
Owner                                   _           _&#13;
Self-employed                           -           -               -&#13;
Salaried employee                      0.5         0.3             0.2&#13;
Petroleum and Electricity                 0.2         0.2              -&#13;
Owner&#13;
Self-employed                           -           -&#13;
Salaried Employee                      0.2         0.2              -&#13;
Manufacturing                            10.7          4.5            6.2&#13;
Owner                                  0.3          0.1            0.2&#13;
Self-empioyed                          4.6         1.0             3.6&#13;
Salaried employee                      5.8         3.4             2.4&#13;
Construction                              3.0         1.9             1.1&#13;
Owner &#13;
Self-employed                          0.9         0.5             0.4&#13;
Salaried employee                      2.1         1.4             0.7&#13;
Commerce, Services, Transport            20.0        10.6             9.4&#13;
Owner       .                          0.3         0.1             0.2&#13;
Self-employed                          8.1         3.9             4.2&#13;
Salaried employee                     11.6         6.6             5.0&#13;
Government                                1.1         0.9             0.2&#13;
Owner                                   -           -               -&#13;
Self-employed                           -           -               _&#13;
Salaried employee                      1.1         0.9             0.2&#13;
Insufficient Information                  0.2         0.2              -&#13;
Total                                   100.0        24.4            75.6&#13;
Unemployed                            11.9         4.1             7.8&#13;
Owner                                  1.2          0.4            0.8&#13;
Self-employed                         46.8         6.2            40.6&#13;
Non-salaried in family business        0.3           -             0.3&#13;
Salaried employee                     39.8        13.7            26.1&#13;
la Defined as families whtose monthly income was less thian 1,621 pesos.&#13;
Source: World Blank Mission estimates from CENIET survey data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
Table A-10: LOCATION OF THE URBAN POOR IN THE POOREST&#13;
30 PERCENT OF THE POPULATION&#13;
City Size                 Peru                  Colombia&#13;
(thousands)&#13;
+ 500                     25.9                   30.5&#13;
/1&#13;
100 - 500                     18.5                   23.4&#13;
/2&#13;
2,000 - 10,000                  55.5                   45.9&#13;
Sources: Peru: Richard Webb, On the Statistical Mapping of Urban&#13;
Poverty and Employment, World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
No. 227.&#13;
Colombia: Marcelo Selowsky, Who Benefits from Government&#13;
Expenditures, Oxford University Press,(forthcoming).&#13;
/1 Refers to city size between 30 and 500 thousand.&#13;
/b Towns with less than 1,500 inhabitants.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-100-&#13;
T. '.e A-1l1 1STIMAIFP DAILY PER CA'ITA CALORIE CONSUMPTION BY DECILES:&#13;
SENSITIVITY TO AGGREGATE CALORIE CONSUMPTION ( /C    ) 1/&#13;
AND THE DISTRIBUTION OF INCOME        /CR&#13;
iDstsri bvton of Income I       Distribution of Inco*e II&#13;
Decile                     /CR &#13;
0.9       1.0        1.1        0.9       1.0       1.1&#13;
1             1356       1597      1834       1587      1826      2065&#13;
2             1604      1843       2082       1691      1930      2169&#13;
3             1752      1991       2230       1837      2076      2315&#13;
4             1898       2137      2376       1939      2178      2417&#13;
5             2000      2239       2428       2019      2258      2496&#13;
Daily Per Capita Calorie Deficit in Each Decile&#13;
1              794.       553      307         563       324        85&#13;
2              546       307        68         459       220        -&#13;
3              398       159        -          313        74        -&#13;
4              252        13        -          211        -         -&#13;
5              150        -         -          131        -         -&#13;
Mean             428        258      187         335       206         85&#13;
Yearly cost of&#13;
the deficit per&#13;
person (dollar.)&#13;
2/      23.4      14.1      10.2        18.3      11.3       4.6&#13;
Fraction of Mal-&#13;
nourished Indi-&#13;
viduals           0.5        0.3      0.2         0.5       0.3        0.2&#13;
1/ C/CR - Mean calorie availability over mean calorie requirement.&#13;
2/ A cost of 1.5 cents per 100 calories is used; corresponds to the value&#13;
of a food basket equals to $125 dollars per year yielding 2300 calories&#13;
per day. (See Table 2.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 101 -&#13;
AMPENDIX 11&#13;
THE SELF-FINANCING OF HIGHER EDUCATION:&#13;
A MODEL OF FULL TUITION AND LOANS&#13;
How many years would it take the higher education system to become&#13;
self supporting under this scheme of full tuition plus loans. We have&#13;
constructed   a hypothetical example to illustrate some orders of magnitude.&#13;
For expository purposes we will distinguish between the institutions&#13;
providing higher education (universities) from the government (or the Ministry&#13;
of Education). We define the present system as one that does not charge any&#13;
tuition and where universities are completely financed by the government.&#13;
Suppose the cost to the budget per student year is equal to a.    The&#13;
public cost of higher education under the existing scheme will be, for any&#13;
future year t, equal to   Ct  -  aSt  where  St  is the stock of students in&#13;
the system in that year. Next figure shows the future path of Ct for Latin&#13;
America (and where year   0  is the base year)    assuming   S  grows at 11%&#13;
per year and equal to the (compounded) rate of the period 1960-71. Given that&#13;
we are interested in trends and not in the scale of the variables we simply&#13;
assume a-l.&#13;
In year 0 the new scheme starts: a yearly tuition equal to a&#13;
is being charged for each of the 5 years of higher education. At the same&#13;
time loans to finance that tuition a plus the yearly foregone b (where&#13;
b-Ba) are offered to "low income" students being accepted. These loans have&#13;
to be repaid (after graduation) in 10 equal yearly installments at an interest&#13;
rate of 10% per year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 102 -&#13;
The effect of the program is that now a fraction y of the&#13;
enter)ne students will be "poor" students. After the 5th year the fraction&#13;
of "p.:or" students in the stock will be equal to the fraction of "poor"&#13;
students ertering the system (in the flow of admittance) under the new&#13;
program. (1-y) becomes the fraction of rich students in the stock.&#13;
U:'der this scheme the cost to the government in any year t&#13;
(after t'he 5th year) will be equal to the yearly loan program:&#13;
(23)      Ct  =     (a+b)YS&#13;
if    b  =   a&#13;
(24)      C' =   aSt (1+S)&#13;
(25)      C'  =  y(l+a)Ct&#13;
t &#13;
The new cost to the government,   Ct   will be higher or lower than the earlier&#13;
one, Ct, depending on the values of 6 and y .&#13;
We will use S = 0.6, a figure based on Psacharopoulos' data, and&#13;
two alternative values of   y;  y = .5 and  y = .7.  With those figures we get&#13;
two alternative values for C':&#13;
y  =  .5           C'      .80Ct&#13;
Y  =  .7           C'     1.12C&#13;
For  r  =   .7  the new cost is higher.  The reason is that a "high"   Y  means&#13;
more "poor" students--to which loans have to be given--in relation to "rich"&#13;
st-,dent from whom tuition is now being collected.&#13;
After five years the government begins receiving a repayment flow&#13;
1/&#13;
(Rr) out of the graduating students to whom loans were granted.     The larger&#13;
the value of y the larger tliis repaymcnt flow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 103 -&#13;
Footnote 1 of previous page&#13;
1/ A student that receives for 5 years a yearly loan of (a+b) will have at&#13;
graduation, a debt equal to:&#13;
(1)   D = (a+b)   E  (i+r)Y  = (a+b)-(l+r)[(l+r) -1]&#13;
i-i                r&#13;
where r is the opportunity cost of capital. He is allowed to repay&#13;
that debt in 10 equal yearly installments at an interest rate r. Define&#13;
as 6(a+b) that (constant) yearly repayment; the present value of that&#13;
flow is therefore:&#13;
10    1             1      1&#13;
(2)   'S(a+b)  I   ~     - 6(a+b)j[1- (l+r&#13;
i=l (l+r)i          (:i )o&#13;
Equalizing (1) and (2) we solve for&#13;
(l+r)[(l+r)5 - 1]&#13;
(3)   6 '           1&#13;
[ 1 -     10]&#13;
for r - 0.10, 6 becomes equal to 1.093.&#13;
Of the At newly admitted students in any year t, a fraction y&#13;
will be entitled to receive loans. If the loan program begins in year&#13;
0 the repayment flow will begin in year 5. The expression for that&#13;
flow for any year T (where T &gt; 5) is:&#13;
T-5&#13;
(4)   RF      Y(a+b)8A [ E   (l+x)t]        where t - 0, if T &lt; 14&#13;
t-0                      t - T-14, if T &gt; 14&#13;
t-T-14&#13;
where  A   is the annual growth rate of new admittance and    A   are new&#13;
admissions when the program begins.&#13;
Recalling that b = 3a we can express (4) as a fraction of&#13;
tor C  by just knowing   X  and the fraction    O  the ratio of new&#13;
admittance to the stock of students in the base year. For Latin America&#13;
the value of   X  is 17% for the period 1960-71; for        the value for&#13;
1971 was used.                                           0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 104 -&#13;
From the attached figure we can see that the system becomes self&#13;
supported between the 12th and 13th year after the program begins. This&#13;
result seems to be relatively insensitive to the value of               .&#13;
$&#13;
Ct-1 .12Cr&#13;
r - .10&#13;
0 -..6&#13;
W-.5     C".80OC                                                       C&#13;
t     t                                RF(J-.7)              C'-.80Ct&#13;
X-.7   c'  1. 12Ct &#13;
tX&#13;
0 1 2 35 6 7 8    9   1    11    2   1   14    5    1     7   8Ya&#13;
0    1    2    3    4    5    6    7    8    9  10   111213 14          1516        1718 Years&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 105 -&#13;
APPENDIX III&#13;
ESTIMATES OF DECLINES IN INVESTMENT AS A RESULT&#13;
OF AN INCOME TAX ON THE RICHEST 10 PERCENT OF HOUSEHOLDS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 106 -&#13;
CLOSED ECONOMY CASE: MAXIMUM EFFECT&#13;
(Perfectly elastic investment function)&#13;
j s ~~~~~~~t2Y.4Y s                        S(YO 04)&#13;
r                                                            MEI&#13;
r (1-t1)&#13;
r(l-t1-t2)&#13;
A        IO.4&#13;
A     ^1 + ^2&#13;
t2&#13;
A   -   (t2) (0.4) (GNP) (m8+) + (I        C(1-ti)&#13;
GNP        (0.4)t MS) +   GNP    (0.4)t m }&#13;
tl - 0.2; t2 - 0.125; mx  = 0.2;  =F a 0.1&#13;
CHANGE INVESTMENT RATIO&#13;
Propensity to save effect     Lower interest rate effect       Total Effect&#13;
0.01                    (E   0.5)  0.007               0.017&#13;
0.01                    (e = 1.0   0.014               0.024&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 107 -&#13;
OPEN ECONOMY CAPITAL MARKET: MAXIMUM EFFECT&#13;
(return abroad not affected by taxation) 1&#13;
r abroad&#13;
I I&#13;
I  I D(l-1-t2)&#13;
t2    I&#13;
GNP      n  1-tl  GNP&#13;
.  (0.1) (0.156). n&#13;
-  (0.0156)  n&#13;
CHANGE INVESTMENT RATIO&#13;
A  5  0.0078               if   n    =   0.5&#13;
GNP&#13;
=     0.0156               if   n    =   1.0&#13;
=     0.0234               if   r    =   1.5&#13;
1/ Returns on capital invested abroad can only be consumed abroad. Otherwise&#13;
investment alternatives abroad must also be taxed, the negative effect&#13;
on domestic investment becoming smaller.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
i&#13;
i&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   orld    Bank                          French: Croissance et emploi en Chine.    Oxford University Press, 1980. 444 pages&#13;
Economica, 1980. ISBN 2-7178-0282-7,      (including index).&#13;
Publications                              Stock No. IB 0548, S7.95.                 LC 79-23354. ISBN 0-19-520115-9, hard-&#13;
Spanish: Crecimiento economico y empleo   cover; ISBN 0-19-520116-7, paperback.&#13;
of Related                                en China. Editorial Tecnos, 1980. ISBN    Stock Nos. OX 520115, $27.50 hardcover;&#13;
Interest                                  84-309-0871-4, Stock No. IB 0530, 57.95.  OX 520116, S12.95 paperback.&#13;
Household Income or&#13;
Employment Patterns and                   Household Income per Capita&#13;
Income Growth                            in Welfare Comparisons&#13;
Joseph J. Stern and Jeffrey D.            Gautam Datta and Jacob Meerman&#13;
Lewis                                     Staff Working Paper No. 378. 1980. 32&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 419. 1980. 70     pages (including 3 appendixes, references).&#13;
pages (including bibliography, 2 appen-   Stock No. WP 0378. S3.&#13;
dixes).                                   SokN.W         38  3&#13;
Stock No. WP 0419, S3.                    How Segmented is the Bogota&#13;
The Determinants of Labor&#13;
Earnings in Developing                     Employment Policy in                     Labor Market?&#13;
Metropolises: Estimates from               Developing Countries: A                  Gary S. Fields&#13;
Bogota and Cali, Colombia                  Survey of Issues and Evidence            Staff Working Paper NO. 434. 1980. 9&#13;
Rakesh Mohan                               Lyn Squire                               pages (tncluding bibliography).&#13;
Rakesh Mohan          Lyn Squire                              ~~~~~~~~~~~Stock No. WP 0434. 53.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 498. 1981. 135     Low rates of growth in industrial em-&#13;
pages (including 2 appendixes, bibliog-    ployment, high rates of unemploy-        Incidence of Poverty and the&#13;
raphy).                                    ment among new entrants to the ur-       Characteristics of the Poor in&#13;
Stock No. WP' 0498. S55                    ban labor market, and low levels ofPeislrM                 aya,17&#13;
labor productivity and remuneration       Peninsular Malaysia, 1973&#13;
Differences in Income,                     are the three issues addressed in this   Pravin Visaria&#13;
Nutrition, and Poverty within              study. The author identifies the impor-  Staff Working Paper No. 460. 1981. 221&#13;
tant determinants of labor demand         pages (including statistical appendix).&#13;
Brazil                                     and supply and the extent to which       Stock No. WP 0460. S10.&#13;
Vinod Thomas                               the growth of labor demand has been&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 505. 1982. 91      constrained-and labor supply ad-         Income Distribution and&#13;
pages (including references, map).         vanced-by inappropriate policies. On     Poverty in Mexico&#13;
Stock No. WP 0505. S3.                    the demand side, industrial trade pol-    Joel Bergsman&#13;
icy, agricultural growth, and the oper-&#13;
The Distribution of Income in              ation of capital markets are discussed;  Staff Working Paper No. 395. 1980. 46&#13;
Brazil                                    on the supply side, attention is fo-      pages (including references).&#13;
Guv P. Pfeffermann and Richard            cused on population and education         Stock No. WP 0395. 53.&#13;
C. Webb                                    policy.                                  Income Distribution Policy in&#13;
Staff Working Paper NO. 356. 1979. 126     Oxford University Press, 1981. 242 pages  the Developing Countries: A&#13;
pages (incuding 2 apendixes).(including bibliography, index).th               De    loigCu         resA&#13;
pages (including 2 appendixes).            LC 81-2844. ISBN 0-19-520266-X, hard-    Case Study of Korea&#13;
Stock No. WP 0356. S5.                    cover: ISBN 0-19-520267-8, paperback.     Irma Adelman and Shernan&#13;
Economic Growth and                        Stock Nos. OX 520266, 516.95 hardcover;  Robinson&#13;
Employment in China                        OX 520267, $7.95 paperback.              Seeks to answer the question of how&#13;
Thomas G. Rawski                           Growth and Equity in Semi-               much can actually be done to improve&#13;
income distribution by means of a dy-&#13;
Examines how China's agricultural         Industrialized Countries                  namic general equilibrium model for&#13;
sector has made significant strides to-   Joel Bergsman                             investigating the potential impact of&#13;
ward full employment for a labor force    Staff Working Paper No. 351. 1979. 115    standard policy instruments and pro-&#13;
of nearly half a billion persons.         pages (including references).             grams intended to improve the relative&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1979. 208 pages  Stock No. WP 0351. $5.                    and absolute incomes of the poor.&#13;
(including maps, bibliography, index).                                              Oxford University Press, 1978. 364 pages&#13;
LC 79-19550. ISBN 0-19-520151-5, hard-    Growth with Equity: The                   (including 6 appendixes, index).&#13;
cover. ISBN 0-19-520152-3, paperback.     Taiwan Case                               LC 76-14269. ISBN 0-19-920084-X, hard-&#13;
Stock Nos. OX 520151, S18.95 hardcover;   John C. H. Fei, Gustav Ranis, and         cover. Stock No. OX 920084, $12.50.&#13;
OX 520152, S7.95 paperback.               Shirley W.Y. Kuo                          Income Inequality and Poverty:&#13;
Introduces a method for tracing the in-   Methods of Estimation and&#13;
equality of family income to the ine-&#13;
qualitv of various kinds of factor in-    Policy Applications&#13;
Prices subject to change without notice   come and the shares of factor income      Nanak C. Kakwani&#13;
and may vary by country.                  in family income.                         Deals with income distribution meth-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ods and their economic applications.      Labor Productivity: Un Tour              A Model for Income&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1980. 432 pages  d'Horizon                               Distribution, Employment, and&#13;
(including bibliography, indexes).        Susan Horton and Timothy King           Growth: A Case Study of&#13;
LC 80-14229. ISBN 0-19-520227-9. Stock    Staff Working Paper No. 497. 1981. 72   Indonesia&#13;
No. OX 520227, $12.95 paperback.          pages (including bibliography).          Syamaprasad Gupta&#13;
Inequality and Poverty in                 Stock No. WP 0497. S3.                  Presents a quantitative framework to&#13;
explore the implications of alternative&#13;
Malaysia: Measurement and                                                         policies for investment, emplovment,&#13;
Decomposition                                NEW                                  income distribution, and fiscal activity&#13;
Sudhir Anand                                                                      for medium-term and long-term&#13;
An account of income inequalities and     Labor and Poverty                        growth.&#13;
povertv in Malavsia. The research is      Michael Lipton                           The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1977.&#13;
policv oriented and the findings, to      Explores factors that enable poor       138 pages (including S appendixes, bibliog-&#13;
which the author's statistical technique  households to transform their capacity  raphy).&#13;
is applied, are thoroughly discussed.     to produce income in the labor market.   LC 76-53909. ISBN 0-8018-1950-4, Stock&#13;
A range of issues is covered, from data   Discusses effect of dependency on       No. JH 1950, $5.50 paperback.&#13;
problems to conceptual questions aris-   wage rates and labor duration on un-&#13;
ing with respect to measurement.         emplovment rates. Also looks at disad-    Patterns in Household Demand&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1982. 384 pages  vantage factors such as age, sex, caste,  and Saving&#13;
(including bibliography, index).          and health. Suggests that access to      Constantin Lluch, Alan A. Powell,&#13;
LC 81-14178. ISBN 0-19-520153-1, hard-    physical and human assets may need       and Ross A. Williams&#13;
cover. Stock No. OX 520153, S27.50.      mto be redstributed to Improve labor      Studies the evolution of the structure&#13;
of consumer preferences as a function&#13;
International Migrant Workers'           Staff Working Paper No. 616. 1983. 160   of economic development.&#13;
Remittances: Issues and                  pages                                    Oxford University Press, 1977. 312 pages&#13;
Prospects                                ISBN 0-8213-0266-3.Stock No. WP 0616.    (including bibliography, indexes).&#13;
Gurushri Swamv                                                                    LC 77-3442. ISBN 0-19-920097-1, hard-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 481. 1981. 64                                             cover; ISBN 0-19-920100-5, paperback.&#13;
pages (including 2 appendixes. bibliog-                                            Stock Nos. OX 920097, S22.50 hardcover;&#13;
raphy).                                                                           OX 920100, $12.95 paperback.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0481. S3.&#13;
Stock No. WP048Poverty and Growth in Kenya&#13;
__________  nn t     Paul Collier and Deepak Lal&#13;
NEW                             ~L ~.. Sm                         %M           Staff Working Paper No. 389. 1980. 76&#13;
pages (including 2 appendixes, bibliog-&#13;
Labor-Based Construction                                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~raphy).&#13;
Labor-Based Construction                                        ^     .            Stock No. WP 0389. $3.&#13;
Programs: A Practical Guide&#13;
for Planning and Management                                                       Poverty and Unemployment in&#13;
Basil Coukis and others                                                           India: An Analysis of Recent&#13;
Summarizes the basic technical and or-                                     _      Evidence&#13;
ganizational know-how needed to de-                                               Pravin Visaria&#13;
sign and implement labor-based civil&#13;
works projects. In this practical, heav-  Manpower and International              Staff Working Paper No. 417. 1980. 42&#13;
ilv illustrated manual, decisionmakers    Labor Migration in the Middle           pages (including statistical annex).&#13;
and project managers can examine          East and North Africa                   Stock No. WP 0417. $3.&#13;
some new ways of thinking about con-     Ismail Serageldin, James A.&#13;
struction and the complexity of these     Socknat, Stace Birks, Bob Li, and       Public Expenditure in&#13;
projects. Ten years of research and       Clive A. Sinclair                       Malaysia: Who Benefits and&#13;
field work in nine countries provide an   Thrh&#13;
authoritative base for this guidebook.    This study of labor market trends in     Why&#13;
the region from 1975 to 1985 analvzes   Jacob Meerman&#13;
the demand for and supply of man-        A methodologically novel study of the&#13;
94. 392 pages.                            power bv country, sector, occupation,   household distribution of public serv-&#13;
ISBN 19-561511-5, hardcover; ISBN         sex, educational level, and ethnic com-  ices in relation to incomes. The studv&#13;
19-561512-3, paperback. Stock Nos. OX     position. It indicates the sources and  examines public spending for educa-&#13;
561511, $24.95 hardcover; OX 561512,      destinations of workers and examines    tion, medical care, agriculture, public&#13;
512.95 paperback.                         the social and economic effects of mi-  utilities, and welfare transfers and the&#13;
gration for both importers and export-   use of these services bv households.&#13;
Labor Migration from                      ers, particularly the implications for  Oxford University Press, 12979. 404 pages&#13;
Bangladesh to the Middle East             government policy and planning.         (including map, bibliography, index).&#13;
Syed Ashraf Ali and others                Oxford University Press. 1983. 152 pages  LC 79-1122. ISBN 0-19-520096-9, hard-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 454. 1981. 396   (including appendixes, index).           cover; ISBN 0-19-520097-7, paperback.&#13;
pages (including appendix).              ISBN 0-19-520406-9, hardcover. Stock No.  Stock Nos. OX 520096, $27.50 hardcover;&#13;
Stock No. WP 0454. S15.                   OX 520406, $27.50.                      OX 520097, $12.50 paperback.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Rural Enterprise and Nonfarm              skilled labor by examining market con-  Who Benefits from&#13;
Employment                                ditions that cause a significant spread  Government Expenditure? A&#13;
Dennis Anderson and Mark                  between economic and market wages.       Case Study of Colombia&#13;
Leiserson                                 The Johns Hopkins University press, 1977.  Marcelo Selowskv&#13;
218 pages (including 5 appendixes, bzbiiog- &#13;
Examines the importance of rural non-    2                                         Clearlv identifies which income groups&#13;
farm activities as a source of emplov-    raphy).                                  benefit from public expenditures and&#13;
ment and income for the poorest           LC 76-47398. ISBN 0-8018-1938-5, hard-  attempts to separate the factors behind&#13;
groups of the world's rural population.   cover; ISBN 0-8018-1949-0, paperback.   the supplv of and demand for a public&#13;
A World Bank Paper. 1978. 87 pages (in-   Stock Nos. TH 1938, $14 hardcover; fH    service as a means of understanding&#13;
cluding 25 annexes).                      1949, $5.50 paperback.                   the present pattern of consumption.&#13;
Stock Nos. BK 9087 (English), BK 9057    The Urban Labor Market and               Oxford University Press, 1979. 202 pages&#13;
(French), BK 9059 (Spanish). $5.          Income Distribution: A Study            (including statistical appendix. bibliog-&#13;
of Malaysia                              raphy, index).&#13;
NEW                                  Dipak Mazumdar                           LC 79-16384. ISBN 0-19-520098-5, hard-&#13;
cover; ISBN 0-19-520099-3, paperback.&#13;
An integrated analysis of differences in  Stock Nos. OX 520098, 520; OX 520099.&#13;
Saudis in Transition: The                income among urban households, the       $9.95&#13;
Challenges of a Changing                 determinants of employment rates of&#13;
Labor Market                             household members, and the major         Women in the Urban Labor&#13;
Naiem A. Sherbinv, Ismail A.             factors affecting personal earnngs.      Markets of Africa: The Case of&#13;
Sirageldin, and M. Ismail                Oxford University Press, 1981. 392 pages  Tanzania&#13;
Serageldin                               (including index).                       Nwanganga Shields&#13;
Presents the first svstematic and com-   LC 80-24413. ISBN 0-19-520213-9, hard-    Staff Working Paper No. 380. 1980. 136&#13;
prehensive examination of a rapidly      cover: ISBN 0-19-520214-7, paperback.    pages (including 5 appendixes).&#13;
changing labor market in a developing     Stock Nos. OX 520213, S26; OX 520214,   Stock No. WP 0380. 55.&#13;
countrv that does not face the tvpical   $9.95.&#13;
capital constraints. Using hitherto un-&#13;
available data on many labor activities&#13;
and processes in Saudi Arabia, the au-&#13;
thors examine the push of modernity          Staff     W   orking        Papers&#13;
and the pull of tradition and measure&#13;
their effects on skill formation, wage       Staff Working Papers are documents  Some 200 Staff Working Papers not&#13;
levels, and geographic and occupa-           based on research conducted within  available from the Bank are available&#13;
tional mobilitv. Thev review the basic      the World Bank or by its consultants  through the National Technical Infor-&#13;
conceptual and methodological issues         on issues affecting the economic and  mation Service (NTIS).&#13;
involved in the analvsis of the Saudi        social development of developing&#13;
labor market and present a detailed ac-      countries. The texts are released in an&#13;
count of the dynamics of labor supply       inforrnal manner to make the results of&#13;
and demand and the characteristics of        this research available quickly. On av-&#13;
both the workers and their employers.        erage, sixty such working papers are&#13;
Oxford Unzversity Press. 1984. About 256     issued annually. The pnce&#13;
Oxford University                ~~~~~of a year's outpuit of    V&#13;
pages .                                      Staff`Working Papers o&#13;
ISBN 0-19-520457-3. July 1984. $22.50        is $180.                      ___&#13;
hardcover.                                                                                     -&#13;
Size of Land Holding, Living&#13;
Standards and Employment in&#13;
Rural Western India, 1972-73                                                  --&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 459. 1981. 117                           *' .&#13;
pages (including statistical appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP 0459. $5.                                  , ,&#13;
Some Aspects of Relative                                             .&#13;
Poverty in Sri Lanka, 1969-70                         ///&#13;
Pravin Visana                                                                           -       .&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 461. 1981. 254&#13;
pages (including 5 annexes).                                 ;   M e&#13;
Stock No. WP 0461. $10.                           s           i4;' /&#13;
Unskilled Labor for                                      ;,                                                        -'&#13;
Development: Its Economic                      x&#13;
Cost                                                  4&#13;
Orville John McDiarmid                                                                              -&#13;
Estimates the economic cost of un-                            ;-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of this form.)         P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                                Name&#13;
Firm                                                 Title&#13;
Address                                              Firm&#13;
City               State   _ Postal Code             Address&#13;
Country             Telephone (     )                City             State_      Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                              Country            'Telephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my D Check D International Money Order D Unesco Coupons D International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my D VISA O MasterCard O American Express 0 Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number            Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
O Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Intemnal&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                      Routing Code  Quantity  U nit Price  Total Amount s&#13;
All prices subject to change.  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  S&#13;
Total copies       Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $__&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Total   $&#13;
IBRD-0053                                                         Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World                     Attn: Mr. Giancarlo Bigazzi              Attn: Mr. J.M. Hernandez&#13;
Distrib   utors  of  W orld               Via  Lam arm ora  45                     Castello  37&#13;
Bank Publications                         50121                                    Madrid&#13;
ARGENTINA                                 Florence                                 SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL,                       JAPAN                             ,      Lake liouse Bookshop&#13;
Attn: Ms. Monica Bustos                   Eastern Book Service                     Attn: Mr. Victor Walatara&#13;
Florida 165 40 piso                       Attn: Mr. Terumasa Hirano                41 Wad Ramanavake Mawatha&#13;
Galeria Guemes                            37-3, Hongo 3-Chome, Bunkvo-ku 113       Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                        Tokyo                                     SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW GUINEA,             KENYA                                     ABCE Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel&#13;
FIJI, SOLOMON ISLANDS,                    Africa Book Services (E.A.) Ltd.         Attn: Mr. Eide Segerback&#13;
WESTERN SAMOA, AND                       Attn: Mr. M.B. Dar                        Regerinsgatan 12, Box 16356&#13;
VANUATU                                   P.O. Box 45245                           S-T13 2/ Stockholm&#13;
The Australian Financial Review          Nairobi                                   SWITZERLAND&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)              KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                        Librairie Pavot&#13;
Attn: Mr. David Jamieson                 Pan Korea Book Corporation                Attn: Mr. Henri de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                     Attn: Mr. Yoon-Sun kim                    6, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadwav                                 P.O. Box 101, Kwanghwamun                 1211 Geneva&#13;
Sydney, NSW 20001                        Seoul                                     TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                  MALAYSIA                                  Oxford University Press&#13;
Publications des Nations Unies           University of Malaya Cooperative          Attn: Mr Anthony Theobold&#13;
Attn: Mr. Jean de Lannov                 Bookshop Ltd.                             Maktaba Road, P.O. Box 5299&#13;
av. du Roi 202                           Attn: Mr. Mohammed Fahim Htj              Dar es Salaam&#13;
1060 Brussels                            Yacob                                     THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                                   P.O. Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru          Central Department Store, Head Office&#13;
Le Diffuseur                             Kuala Lumpur                              Attn: Mrs. Ratana&#13;
Attn: Mrs. Suzanne Vermette              MEXICO                                    306 Silom Road&#13;
C.P. 85, Boucherville J4B 5E6            INFOTEC                                   Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                   Attn: Mr. Jorge Cepeda                    Thailand Management Association&#13;
COSTA RICA                               San Lorenzo 53- 1, Col. del Valle,        Attn: Mrs. Sunan&#13;
LibreriaSTre RIA                     ,   Deleg. Benito Juarez                      308 Silom Road&#13;
Libreria TrejOs                          010lxc,DF                                  ago&#13;
Attn: Mr. Hugo Chamberlain               0310 Mexico, D.F.                         Bangkok&#13;
Calle 11-13, Av. Fernandez Guell         MIDDLE EAST                               TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                 Middle East Marketing Research            Societe Tunisienne de Diffusion&#13;
DENMARK                                  Bureau                                    Attn: Mr. Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur                       Attn: Mr. George Vassilou                 5 Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Attn: Mr. Wilfried Roloff                Nlakaios Bld  A                           Tunis&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 11                       Nicosia                                   TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V.                    Cyprus                                    Haset Kitapevi A.S.&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                  (Branch offices in Bahrain, Greece,       Attn: Mr. Izzet Izerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                 Morocco, Kuwait, United Arab              469, Istiklal Caddesi&#13;
Al Galaa Street                          Emirates, Jordan)                         Bevoglu-Istanbul&#13;
Cairo                                    NETHERLANDS                               UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
MBE BV                                   NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                  Attn: Mr. Gerhard van Bussell             Microinto Ltd.&#13;
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa                  Noorderwal 38,                            Attn: Mr. Roy Selwyn&#13;
Attn: Mr. Kari Litmanen                  7241 BL Lochem                            Newman Lane, P.O. Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100                   NORWAY                                    Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                              Johan Grundt Tanum A.S.                   England&#13;
FRANCE                                   Attn: Ms. Randi Mikkelborg                UNITED STATES&#13;
World Bank Publications                  P.O. Box 1177 Sentrum                    The World Bank Book Store&#13;
66, avenue dc'lna                        Oslo 1                                    600 19th Street, NW.&#13;
75116 Paris                              PANAMA                                    Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of             Ediciones Libreria Cultural Ilanamena     (Postal address: P.O. Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                               Attn: Mr. Luis Fernandez Fraguela R.      Washington, D.C. 20013, U.S A&#13;
Attn: Mr. Joachim Krause                 Av. 7, Espana 16                          Baker and Tavlor Company&#13;
Simrockstrasse 23                        Panama   one 1                            501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn I                            PHILIPPINES                               Niomence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                         National Book Store                       380 Edison Wav&#13;
Asia 2000 Ltd.                           Attn Mrs. Socorro C. Ramos                Reno, Nevada, 89564&#13;
Attn: Ms. Gretchen Wearing Smith         70l oizaN Avenue                          5w KJ-hv Avenue&#13;
6 Fl., 146 Prince Edward Road            . anda                                    Somerville, New Jersey, 08876&#13;
Kowloon                                  PORTUGAL                                  Commerce, Georgia 30599&#13;
INDIA                                    I.i% rarli Portugal&#13;
\ttn Mr. Antonio Alves Martins           Bernan Associates&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd.        R~LIa Do) Carmo 70-74                    9730-E George Palmer Hif hwav&#13;
Attn: Mr. D.P. Veer                         LDnham9                                         Maryland, 21)76&#13;
5 Ansari Road, Post Box 7015               -Lackam                                          North A   ,   Inc.&#13;
New Delhi 110002                         1 i,bn                                    Blackwell North America, Inc.&#13;
(Branch offices in Bombav, Bangalore.    SAUDI ARABIA                              1001 Fries Mill Road&#13;
Kanpur, Calcutta, and vfadras)           larir Book Store                          Blackwood, New Jersey 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                                Attn Mr Akram Al-Agil                    Sidnev Kramer Books&#13;
Pt Indira Limited                        P o Box 3196                              1722 H Street, N.W&#13;
Attn: Mr. Bambang Wahvudi                Rivadh                                    Washington, D.C. 20006&#13;
JI, Dr. Sam Ratulangi No. 37             SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                  Lnited Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                            Information Publications Private, Ltd.    United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                  Attn Ms. Janet David                     New York, N Y 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                           02-06 1st Floor, Pei-Fu Industrial&#13;
Attn: Mr. James Booth                      Building                                VENEZUELA&#13;
12 North Frederick Street                24 New Industrial Road                   LAbreria del Este&#13;
Dublin I                                 Singapore                                 Attn Mr. Juan Pericas&#13;
Dublin-1 Singapore                    Avda Francisco de Miranda, no. 52&#13;
ITALY                                    SPAIN                                     Edificio Galipan, Aptdo. 60 337&#13;
Licosa Commissionaria Sansoni SPA        Mundl-Prensa Libros, S A                  Caracas 1060-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                          European Office               Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                   66, avenue d'1ena             Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.        75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234             Telephone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK            Telex: 842-620628             Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                            Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
-                0, .1       S     0.j21...524.7&#13;
1                                      .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ k&#13;
.,&#13;
!SS      02321      SN     -2302-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="5839250">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/03/5839250/balancing-trickle-down-basic-needs-strategies-income-distribution-issues-large-middle-income-countries-special-reference-latin-america
        </url>
        <availablein>Spanish,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="Spanish" entityid="000231615_20121015121139" node_id="5839250"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/03/5839250/balancing-trickle-down-basic-needs-strategies-income-distribution-issues-large-middle-income-countries-special-reference-latin-america</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/03/5839250/balancing-trickle-down-basic-needs-strategies-income-distribution-issues-large-middle-income-countries-special-reference-latin-america</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/06/02/000011823_20050602155048/Rendered/INDEX/SWP335.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/06/02/000011823_20050602155048/Rendered/PDF/SWP335.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1985-03-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2005-06-02T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Revised</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309936</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Balancing trickle down and basic needs
            strategies : income distribution issues in large
            middle-income countries with special reference to Latin America
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper addresses income distribution
            issues and explores various policy options to eliminate
            extreme poverty in a particular typology of middle income
            developing countries. The countries included in the typology
            are characterized by a relatively high per capita income
            (above US$600 per year in 1976), a relatively high degree of
            industrialization (industry representing over 30 percent of
            GNP), a rather large size both in population and area, and
            relatively well endowed resources in agriculture. A
            distinctive feature is a strong inequality in the
            distribution of income and wealth relative to other
            countries of similar levels of per capita income. The
            typical countries characterizing the typology are Brazil,
            Colombia, Ecuador, Mexico, Peru, and Turkey. Because the
            Latin American countries included represent two-thirds of
            the population of the region, this report is basically
            addressed to that region.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Balancing trickle down and basic needs
            strategies : income distribution issues in large
            middle-income countries with special reference to Latin America
        </docna>
        <display_title>Balancing trickle down and basic
            needs strategies : income distribution issues in large
            middle-income countries with special reference to Latin America</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1985/03/5839250/balancing-trickle-down-basic-needs-strategies-income-distribution-issues-large-middle-income-countries-special-reference-latin-america</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Governance Indicators,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Achieving Shared Growth</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>Latin America,Caribbean</count>
        <authors>
            <author>SELOWSKY, M.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000011823_20050602155048</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 335</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Basic education; Calorie deficiency; Capital
            investments; Children; Employment creation; Foods; Health
            care delivery; Housing; Human capital; Land tenure;
            Nutrition education; Per capita income; Preschool education;
            Small scale farming; Trade barriers; Labor costs; Labor
            mobility; Labor markets
            Basic education; Calorie deficiency; Capital
            investments; Children; Employment creation; Foods; Health
            care delivery; Housing; Human capital; Land tenure;
            Nutrition education; Per capita income; Preschool education;
            Small scale farming; Trade barriers; Labor costs; Labor
            mobility; Labor markets
        </keywd>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0524-7</isbn>
        <owner>LCS</owner>
        <repnb>SWP335</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Higher Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education – Enhancing Access, Equity and Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Minimum Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Land Reform</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>