<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>294                                                                                                                                                                                       32843&#13;
                                                                                                          privatesector        P U B L I C       P O L I C Y     F O R       T H E&#13;
&#13;
   NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         NOTE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             2005&#13;
                                                                                                             Controlling Market Power&#13;
                 JUNE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Michel Kerf, Isabel Neto,    Balancing Antitrust and Sector Regulation in Telecoms&#13;
                                                                                and Damien Géradin&#13;
                                                                                                             Among the countries fully liberalizing their telecommunications&#13;
                                                                                Michel Kerf&#13;
                                                                                                             sector, some have chosen to rely mainly on sector-specific rules,&#13;
                                                                                (mkerf@worldbank.org) is&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                an infrastructure policy     often applied by sector-specific institutions, while others have&#13;
                                                                                adviser in the World         depended on economywide antitrust rules and institutions to control&#13;
                                                                                Bank's East Asia and&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Pacific Region and a         market power. This Note describes the choices made by five notable&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                visiting professor at the&#13;
                     PRESIDENCY                                                                              reformers: Australia, Chile, New Zealand, the United Kingdom, and the&#13;
                                                                                University of Liège.&#13;
                                                                                                             United States. Drawing on their experiences, it then assesses whether&#13;
                               VICE                                             Isabel Neto is a&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                telecommunications           antitrust or sector-specific processes have dealt more quickly and&#13;
                                                                                specialist. Damien Géradin&#13;
                                                                                                             effectively with key regulatory issues.&#13;
                                                                                is a professor at the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                University of Liège and at&#13;
                                                                                                             The regulatory frameworks for telecommunica-        largely on general antitrust rules and institu-&#13;
                                   DEVELOPMENT                                  the College of Europe,&#13;
                                                                                                             tions adopted at different times by the five coun-  tions. This framework was modified in 2001 to&#13;
                                                                                Bruges.&#13;
                                                                                                             tries reflect different balances between antitrust  introduce sector-specific rules, such as those on&#13;
                                              SECTOR                                                         and sector-specific approaches (table 1).           interconnection, number portability, carrier&#13;
                                                                                This is the first of three&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Notes evaluating how best       The United States has emphasized a sector-       preselection, and roaming. In addition, a&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                to balance antitrust and     specific approach. It adopted the Telecommu-        telecommunications commissioner with spe-&#13;
                                                    PRIVATE                     sector-specific approaches   nications Act of 1996 to bring down all barriers    cialized staff was appointed to the antitrust&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                in regulating                to competition in the telecommunications mar-       authority.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                telecommunications.          ket and, especially, to enable long-distance oper-     Chile, the United Kingdom, and Australia&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                The second focuses on        ators to enter the local markets previously         adopted what were in effect compromises&#13;
                                                           GROUP&#13;
                                                                                the regulation of            monopolized by the regional local operators.        between the more radical U.S. and (pre-2001)&#13;
                                                                                interconnection. The third   The Telecommunications Act contains no less         New Zealand approaches.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                BANK            discusses how the balance    than 335 pages of sector-specific regulations,         A pioneer in liberalizing telecommunications,&#13;
                                                                                between antitrust and        and the Federal Communications Commission           Chile had to learn largely by trial and error. The&#13;
                                                                                sector-specific regulation   (FCC), the sector-specific agency in charge of      rules adopted in the early 1980s to allow multi-&#13;
                                                                                affects competition.         applying these rules, employs more than 2,100       ple entry into each market segment contained&#13;
                                                                    WORLD                                    staff.                                              few sector-specific provisions (and few licenses&#13;
                                                                                                                In New Zealand, by contrast, the regulatory      were awarded early on to new entrants). Addi-&#13;
                                                                         THE                                 model adopted at the end of the 1980s relied        tional sector-specific provisions were adopted in&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C O N T R O L L I N G M A R K E T P O W E R B A L A N C I N G A N T I T R U S T A N D  S E C T O R R E G U L A T I O N I N T E L E C O M S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Table Balance between antitrust and sector-specific regulation of telecommunications&#13;
&#13;
                                     1      Country                          Rules                                                         Institutions&#13;
                                            Australia                        Mix of sector-specific and antitrust rules,                   Antitrust authorities with telecommunications&#13;
                                                                             with most sector-specific rules integrated into               group&#13;
                                                                             general antitrust legislation&#13;
                                            Chile                            Mix of sector-specific and antitrust rules                    Sector-specific regulator&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Distinct antitrust authorities&#13;
                                            New Zealand                      Before 2001, predominantly antitrust                          Before 2001, antitrust authorities&#13;
2                                                                            Since 2001, a mix of sector-specific and                      Since 2001, antitrust authorities with&#13;
                                                                             antitrust rules                                               telecommunications commissioner&#13;
                                            United Kingdom                   Before 2003, predominantly sector-specific                    Sector-specific regulator with antitrust powers&#13;
                                                                             (included in licenses)&#13;
                                                                             Since 2003, general authorization regime with&#13;
                                                                             increasing reliance on competition law&#13;
                                            United States                    Predominantly sector-specific                                 Sector-specific regulator&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Distinct antitrust authorities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     1987 (on tariff setting) and in 1994 (on inter-                                      Successes of antitrust&#13;
                                     connection, vertical separation between the local                                    Reliance on antitrust yielded some good results&#13;
                                     and long distance markets, and choice of long                                        when the courts intervened to stop clear abuses&#13;
                                     distance carriers on a call-by-call basis). While a                                  of dominant positions. In a dispute over local&#13;
                                     sector-specific regulator was established as early                                   loop interconnection in New Zealand, for exam-&#13;
                                     as 1977, antitrust authorities remain important,                                     ple, judges agreed that the incumbent, Telecom,&#13;
                                     since they determine, for example, whether the                                       was abusing its dominant position relative to its&#13;
                                     prices of particular telecommunications services                                     competitor Clear when it forced Clear's cus-&#13;
                                     need to be regulated.                                                                tomers to dial an access code and imposed on&#13;
                                        In the United Kingdom until very recently,                                        Clear the same interconnection price paid by&#13;
                                     sector-specific rules were mostly included in                                        any of Telecom's large end users with their own&#13;
                                     operators' licenses and implemented by Oftel,                                        switches. In Chile antitrust authorities took&#13;
                                     the telecommunications regulator. But the                                            action to prevent the incumbent provider of&#13;
                                     sector regulator could also enforce economy-                                         local services (CTC) from offering discounts to&#13;
                                     wide antitrust rules contained in the Compe-                                         its own subscribers, but not to others, on certain&#13;
                                     tition Act of 1998. Since 2003 individual                                            fixed-to-mobile services.1&#13;
                                     licenses have been replaced by a general                                                 Antitrust provisions have also been successfully&#13;
                                     authorization regime, and sector-specific reg-                                       applied in merger controls. In Australia operators&#13;
                                     ulation is being curtailed in favor of general                                       chose to cancel merger plans when antitrust&#13;
                                     competition law. In addition, Oftel has been                                         authorities announced that the proposed merg-&#13;
                                     replaced by Ofcom, a somewhat broader com-                                           ers would probably violate the antitrust law. Sim-&#13;
                                     munications regulator also responsible for                                           ilarly, in the United States MCI WorldCom and&#13;
                                     broadcasting and cable.                                                              Sprint decided to call off their planned merger&#13;
                                        In Australia the Telecommunications Act of                                        after antitrust authorities declared that the trans-&#13;
                                     1997 removed all restrictions on entry into the                                      action would reduce competition. And in Chile a&#13;
                                     telecommunications market and introduced a                                           statement by antitrust authorities that a merger&#13;
                                     sophisticated set of access rules as well as other                                   between the local operations of the incumbent&#13;
                                     specific rules relating to, for example, number                                      and those of a cable operator would eliminate a&#13;
                                     portability, operator preselection, and override                                     promising source of local competition persuaded&#13;
                                     dial codes. These sector-specific rules are                                          the two operators to substantially revise their&#13;
                                     applied by antitrust authorities.                                                    merger plans.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Shortcomings of antitrust                            ter competition in sectors where no competition&#13;
Antitrust-based regulation appears to have some      existed before. In the United States, for exam-&#13;
drawbacks, however. Interconnection issues, for      ple, where the local market was divided into&#13;
example, have often been difficult to resolve        regional monopolies before adoption of the&#13;
through antitrust. In New Zealand the Clear-         Telecommunications Act of 1996, antitrust pro-&#13;
Telecom case posed a big challenge to the regu-      visions cannot prevent a merger between two&#13;
latory model before the 2001 reforms: judicial       incumbent local operators.&#13;
processes aimed at determining a fair intercon-         Antitrust provisions are also ill suited to&#13;
nection price lasted several years, different courts imposing general structural remedies such as&#13;
                                                                                                             3&#13;
took different positions on the same issues, and     vertical separation between different segments&#13;
in the end judges refused to set a price, leaving    of the telecommunications market. In Chile,&#13;
the parties to reach a specific agreement con-       after long antitrust proceedings in the courts to&#13;
forming to broadly defined principles.               determine whether the incumbent provider of&#13;
   Unbundled access to the local loop and            local services and the incumbent provider of&#13;
resale of local services have generally not taken    long distance services could compete in each&#13;
place under an antitrust-based regime such as        other's market, it was the legislature that clari-&#13;
that adopted in New Zealand. For unbundling,         fied the situation by imposing some vertical sep-&#13;
however, specific regulation has not necessarily     aration between the two market segments.&#13;
yielded better results. One main reason is that         All five countries have relied on sector-&#13;
determining adequate pricing and other condi-        specific rules to ensure that universal service&#13;
tions of access to distinct unbundled elements       objectives are met and to regulate the allocation&#13;
of a given network is far from straightforward.      and use of the radioelectric spectrum. In both&#13;
   Agreement on number portability, carrier          cases such rules are needed to optimize the allo-&#13;
preselection, and roaming also proved difficult      cation of scarce public resources: public subsi-&#13;
to reach in New Zealand without sector-specific      dies funding universal service schemes in the&#13;
rules. Some operators reached an agreement on        first case, and the spectrum in the second.&#13;
number portability in 1999, but the government&#13;
had to threaten to intervene at several stages       Striking the right balance&#13;
and the process took a long time. Preselection       The experiences of the five countries suggest&#13;
agreements for long distance fixed-to-fixed calls    that sector-specific rules are needed to:&#13;
were also negotiated commercially before the          Specifyinterconnectionpricesandconditions.&#13;
&#13;
2001 reforms. But preselection for fixed-to-          Set the prices of resale services and perhaps&#13;
&#13;
mobile calls did not exist, nor did roaming.            the conditions under which the incumbent&#13;
   Control of retail prices also proved problem-        should provide unbundled access to the local&#13;
atic under antitrust. In Chile, for example, the        loop (though experience suggests that design-&#13;
pricing provisions of the 1982 General Law of           ing and implementing adequate unbundling&#13;
Telecommunications were vague, and prices               rules is extremely difficult).&#13;
were set through informal negotiations between        Allow number portability, carrier preselec-&#13;
&#13;
incumbent companies and the Ministry of Econ-           tion, and roaming.&#13;
omy. Prices were set at inefficient levels, cross-    Control end-user prices in market segments&#13;
&#13;
subsidization between services was maintained,          where competitive pressures remain weak,&#13;
and antitrust authorities did not intervene to          such as that for fixed local calls.&#13;
correct the situation. Only after the adoption of     Impose certain types of structural remedies,&#13;
&#13;
more specific provisions were these problems            such as vertical separation between different&#13;
corrected.                                              market segments.&#13;
   Even in merger controls, applying antitrust        Define and fund universal service objectives&#13;
&#13;
provisions may not always promote competition.          and allocate rights to use the radioelectric&#13;
In many countries antitrust merger provisions           spectrum.&#13;
are designed to prevent behaviors that would            Antitrust rules also remain essential in all five&#13;
lessen competition and so are inadequate to fos-     countries, to:&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C O N T R O L L I N G M A R K E T P O W E R B A L A N C I N G A N T I T R U S T A N D S E C T O R R E G U L A T I O N I N T E L E C O M S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Deal with a range of issues of economic reg-                            Greater competition in the local loop may&#13;
   ulation not addressed by the sector-specific                    also eliminate the need to regulate end-user&#13;
   rules above (for example, to ensure merger                      prices. Indeed, as competition has taken hold,&#13;
   reviews and prohibit anticompetitive prac-                      the Australian, Chilean, and U.S. regulators have&#13;
   tices).                                                         progressively reduced the number of telecom-                              viewpoint&#13;
 Fill any gaps in sector-specific regulatory                       munications services subject to price regulation.&#13;
   regimes.                                                              More intense competition in the local loop&#13;
   The experiences of the five countries also sug-                 would thus shift the appropriate balance&#13;
                                                                                                                                             is an open forum to&#13;
gest that specialized entities are needed to deal                  between the two regulatory approaches toward&#13;
                                                                                                                                             encourage dissemination of&#13;
with some of the most complex issues requiring                     economywide rules. And a move toward greater&#13;
                                                                                                                                             public policy innovations for&#13;
regulatory intervention in telecommunications.                     reliance on economywide rules would bolster&#13;
                                                                                                                                             private sector­led and&#13;
Both a sector-specific agency (with or without                     the case for entrusting an economywide rather&#13;
                                                                                                                                             market-based solutions for&#13;
antitrust powers) and an economywide antitrust                     than a sector-specific regulator with controlling&#13;
                                                                                                                                             development. The views&#13;
entity with sufficient expertise in telecommuni-                   market power in telecommunications. Some&#13;
                                                                                                                                             published are those of the&#13;
cations may be well suited to the job.2                            steps in that direction have already been taken.                          authors and should not be&#13;
   There appears to be growing convergence                         Australia opted to entrust its competition                                attributed to the World&#13;
among the five countries toward the balance                        authority with responsibility for regulating                              Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
suggested here between sector-specific and                         telecommunications. New Zealand has now fol-                              organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
&#13;
antitrust regulation. For example, Chile and                       lowed suit. And the United Kingdom recently                               the conclusions represent&#13;
&#13;
New Zealand, which had few sector-specific rules                   replaced its telecommunications-specific regu-                            official policy of the World&#13;
&#13;
when they liberalized their telecommunications                     lator with a broader communications regulator,                            Bank or of its Executive&#13;
&#13;
markets, have subsequently adopted such rules.                     emulating the United States, where the FCC's                              Directors or the countries&#13;
&#13;
Conversely, the United Kingdom, whose frame-                       competence extends to both telecommunica-                                 they represent.&#13;
&#13;
work initially relied heavily on sector-specific                   tions and broadcasting.&#13;
provisions, has shifted toward more emphasis on                                                                                              To order additional copies&#13;
&#13;
antitrust.                                                                                                                                   contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
&#13;
   Convergence can also be observed on insti-                                                                                                managing editor,&#13;
&#13;
tutional issues. Indeed, since the 2001 reforms                    Notes                                                                     Room F 4K-206,&#13;
&#13;
in New Zealand, all five countries have estab-                                                                                               The World Bank,&#13;
                                                                         1. What constitutes an abuse of dominant position&#13;
                                                                                                                                             1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
lished either a sector-specific regulatory agency                  varies with market conditions and with the intensity of&#13;
                                                                                                                                             Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
or a specialized department within an econo-                       competitive pressures. Free or discounted on-net calling&#13;
&#13;
mywide antitrust authority.                                        between fixed and mobile phones is now allowed in some&#13;
                                                                                                                                             Telephone:&#13;
                                                                   countries where there is enough competition.&#13;
                                                                                                                                             001 202 458 7281&#13;
The way forward                                                          2. This does not mean, however, that the authority of&#13;
                                                                                                                                             Fax:&#13;
The spread of new technologies is likely to facil-                 a specialized regulator should necessarily extend to every&#13;
                                                                                                                                             001 202 522 3480&#13;
itate competition in the local segment of the                      sector-specific rule listed. For example, given the broad&#13;
                                                                                                                                             Email:&#13;
telecommunications market in the five coun-                        socioeconomic implications of universal service regimes,&#13;
                                                                                                                                             ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
tries. This, in turn, is likely to allow progressive               specialized regulators--especially if they focus on one sec-&#13;
&#13;
relaxation of some sector-specific regulation. For                 tor only--may not be best placed to administer such&#13;
                                                                                                                                             Produced by Grammarians,&#13;
example, as new local service providers become                     regimes.                                                                  Inc.&#13;
more numerous and more competitive, the&#13;
incumbent will face greater incentives to offer                    Reference                                                                 Printed on recycled paper&#13;
them equitable interconnection conditions.                               Géradin, Damien, and Michel Kerf. 2003. Controlling&#13;
&#13;
Long distance and mobile operators will also                       Market Power in Telecommunications: Antitrust vs. Sector-&#13;
&#13;
find it easier to conclude favorable intercon-                     Specific Regulation. New York: Oxford University Press.&#13;
&#13;
nection agreements when they can negotiate&#13;
with any one of a number of local service&#13;
providers. As a result, a sector-specific intercon-&#13;
nection price regime may some day become&#13;
unnecessary.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        T h i s N o t e i s a v a i l a b l e o n l i n e :&#13;
                                                                                   h t t p : / / r r u . w o r l d b a n k . o r g / P u b l i c P o l i c y J o u r n a l&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6040141">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/06/6040141/controlling-market-power-balancing-antitrust-sector-regulation-telecoms
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/06/6040141/controlling-market-power-balancing-antitrust-sector-regulation-telecoms</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/06/6040141/controlling-market-power-balancing-antitrust-sector-regulation-telecoms</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/07/01/000011823_20050701131908/Rendered/INDEX/329430PAPER0VP294kerf.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/07/01/000011823_20050701131908/Rendered/PDF/329430PAPER0VP294kerf.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-07-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2005-06-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Controlling market power : balancing
            antitrust and sector regulation in telecoms
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Among the countries fully liberalizing
            their telecommunicationssector, some have chosen to rely
            mainly on sector-specific rules,often applied by
            sector-specific institutions, while others havedepended on
            economywide antitrust rules and institutions to
            controlmarket power. This Note describes the choices made by
            five notablereformers: Australia, Chile, New Zealand, the
            United Kingdom, and theUnited States. Drawing on their
            experiences, it then assesses whetherantitrust or
            sector-specific processes have dealt more quickly
            andeffectively with key regulatory issues.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Controlling market power : balancing
            antitrust and sector regulation in telecoms
        </docna>
        <display_title>Controlling market power :
            balancing antitrust and sector regulation in telecoms</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2005/06/6040141/controlling-market-power-balancing-antitrust-sector-regulation-telecoms</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <count>Chile,United States,Australia,New Zealand,United Kingdom</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Kerf, Michel</author>
            <author>Neto, Isabel</author>
            <author>Geradim, Damien</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000011823_20050701131908</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>North America!$!80465</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Oceania!$!80466</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Rest Of The World,Rest Of The World,East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific,Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 294</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Antitrust, Antitrust authorities, antitrust
            authority, antitrust law, antitrust legislation, antitrust
            regulation, authorization, competition law, economic
            regulation, innovations, judges, legislature, licenses,
            market conditions, Market Power, market segments,
            monopolies, phones, PRESIDENCY, price regulation, PRIVATE
            SECTOR, provisions, PUBLIC POLICY, public resources, public
            subsidies, regulator, regulators, regulatory agency,
            regulatory frameworks, regulatory intervention, regulatory
            regimes, retail, retail prices, spread, telecommunications,
            telecommunications regulator, telecommunications services,
            Telecoms, unbundling, universal service, universal service objectives
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge Management - WB (FPDKM)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>North America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Oceania</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>32843</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Antitrust Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mergers Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Abuse of Dominant Position</ml:concept><ml:concept>Abusive Market Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Exclusionary Practices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Dominance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Unfair Business Practices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Unilateral Conduct</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anti-Competitive Conduct</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anti-Monopoly</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competition Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competition Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restrictive Practices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Servers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Switches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monopolization and Abuse of Dominance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Antitrust</ml:concept><ml:concept>Antitrust </ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Network Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>