<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                    33043&#13;
          Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances&#13;
&#13;
                                     Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Abstract&#13;
&#13;
A strong inter-regional equity bias has been a distinctive feature of the Japanese local public&#13;
finance system. This paper shows that substantial equalization of revenues per capita is&#13;
achieved via transfers from the central government and that, over time, this appears to have&#13;
substantially improved the regional distribution of income: the Gini coefficient of per capita&#13;
regional income declined from around 0.17 in 1950 to 0.10 in 1990. Now that considerable&#13;
regional equality has been achieved, a greater concern for the exercise of local preferences is&#13;
being voiced.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     World Bank Institute&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 2001&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
May 2001&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank enjoys copyright under protocol 2 of the Universal Copyright Convention.&#13;
This material may nonetheless be copied for research, educational, or scholarly purposes only in&#13;
the member countries of The World Bank. Material in this series is subject to revision. The&#13;
findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed in this document are entirely those of the&#13;
author(s) and should not be attributed in any manner to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or the members of its Board of Executive Directors or the countries they&#13;
represent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances&#13;
Nobuki Mochida&#13;
2001. 33 pages. Stock No. 37171&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                        Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Foreword v&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Basic Framework of the Current System 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Characteristics of Local Tax System in Japan 8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Intergovernmental Fiscal Transfer and Regional Disparity 13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Implications of the Japanese Experience 17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Endnotes 20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Bibliography 22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appendix 25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            iii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Foreword&#13;
&#13;
This paper was prepared for a project on Local Government Development in Japan. The&#13;
project was organized by the World Bank Institute under the auspices of the Program for the&#13;
Study of Japanese Development Management Experience financed by the Policy and Human&#13;
Resources Development Trust Fund of the Government of Japan.&#13;
&#13;
The principal objectives of this Program are to conduct studies on Japanese and East Asian&#13;
development management experience and to disseminate the lessons of this experience to&#13;
developing and transition economies. Typically, the experiences of other countries are also&#13;
covered in order to ensure that these lessons are placed in the proper context.               This&#13;
comparative method helps identify factors that influence the effectiveness of specific&#13;
institutional mechanisms, governance structures, and policy reforms in different contexts. A&#13;
related and equally important objective of the Program is to promote the exchange of ideas&#13;
among Japanese and non-Japanese scholars, technical experts and policy makers.&#13;
&#13;
The papers commissioned for this project cover a number of important issues related to local&#13;
government development in Japan. These issues include: the process of controlled&#13;
decentralization; increasing political inclusiveness; redistributive impact of local taxes and&#13;
transfers; allocation of grants; municipal amalgamation; personnel exchanges; personnel&#13;
policies; agency-delegated functions; and local policy initiatives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Farrukh Iqbal, Program Manager&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                v&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances&#13;
&#13;
Nobuki Mochida1&#13;
University of Tokyo, Japan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Japanese local public finances account for roughly 70 percent of general public&#13;
expenditure and 80 percent of public capital formation. This suggests that, in implementation&#13;
terms at least, local governments play an important role in the provision of public services.&#13;
The efficiency and equity characteristics of the Japanese local government system are,&#13;
therefore, likely to have an important effect on regional and national development. The&#13;
purpose of this paper is to examine Japan's intergovernmental relations from a fiscal&#13;
viewpoint. It is divided into four sections. The first section provides an outline of the basic&#13;
framework of the system. The second provides an analysis of the local tax system. The&#13;
third provides data on the regional equalization effect of intergovernmental transfers. The&#13;
fourth and concluding section discusses some lessons of experience to date for other countries&#13;
as well as for Japan.&#13;
&#13;
Basic Framework of the Current System&#13;
&#13;
Centralized and Decentralized Aspects&#13;
&#13;
       The main features of the Japanese system are centralized tax administration,&#13;
decentralized provision of public services, and dependence of local government on&#13;
intergovernmental transfers. In other words, intergovernmental fiscal relations are marked by&#13;
a vertical fiscal imbalance in Japan.1 Table 1 provides comparative data on vertical fiscal&#13;
imbalance in 10 major countries based on national accounts. It can be seen that the average&#13;
amount of imbalance is quite large although the degree does vary from country to country. In&#13;
particular, three countries, Japan, England, and Australia, exhibit the highest levels of&#13;
imbalance between expenditure responsibilities of local governments and their tax resources.&#13;
In Sweden and France the imbalance is more moderate, while in federal states, except&#13;
Australia, the level of imbalance is relatively low.&#13;
Vertical fiscal imbalance can be high if tax shares of local governments are very low and/or if&#13;
their expenditure responsibilities are very high. In the case of Japan, the latter is more likely&#13;
to be the reason. The local tax share of total tax revenues in Japan is 36.5 percent, which is&#13;
on the high side for OECD countries. On the other hand, as already noted, expenditures&#13;
channeled through local governments are very high, at 70% of the total. Indeed, this share is&#13;
the highest among OECD countries, higher even than the 50-60 percent observed in the&#13;
Scandinavian countries. Despite this high rate of spending through local governments, it&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1The author wishes to thank Jun Ma, Jisoon Lee, Farrukh Iqbal, Jørgen Lotz, Dubravko Mihaljek, James Mak,&#13;
Jhungsoo Park, Michio Muramastu, Steven R. Reed, and Shun'ichi Furukawa for helpful comments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
would be inaccurate to characterize Japan as a decentralized system because a considerable&#13;
amount of decision-making authority has tended to rest with central units. In Japan, the&#13;
central government exercises its discretionary powers on local expenditure through delegation&#13;
of program implementation responsibilities to local chief executives financed, at least in part,&#13;
by specific-purpose grants.&#13;
&#13;
Table 1: Vertical Fiscal Imbalance in Selected OECD Countries (FY 1992) (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Vertical fiscal imbalance&#13;
                             (a)                (b)&#13;
                        Expenditure          Revenue                            Dependence on&#13;
                          share of           Share of       Surplus/Deficit     Central transfer&#13;
                        subnational         Subnational                          Grants as % of&#13;
 Country                government          government          (b) ­ (a)       current receipts&#13;
 United States        51.4               45.9              - 5.5                20.9&#13;
&#13;
 Canada               65.3               53.2              - 12.1               35.4&#13;
&#13;
 Australia            48.6               23.0              - 25.6               40.3&#13;
&#13;
 Germany              58.6               47.2              - 11.4               18.5&#13;
&#13;
 Denmark              57.3               32.3              - 25.0               45.5&#13;
&#13;
 Sweden               47.6               38.7              - 8.9                22.2&#13;
&#13;
 United               31.9               0.07              - 31.2               79.8&#13;
 Kingdom&#13;
 France               31.1               18.0              - 13.1               38.6&#13;
&#13;
 Spain                43.6               19.7              - 23.9               46.6&#13;
&#13;
 Japan                69.2               36.5              - 32.7               39.6&#13;
&#13;
 Average              47.3               27.0              - 20.3               36.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: OECD, National Accounts, 1996; IMF, Government Finance Statistics, 1996.&#13;
&#13;
Large Scale Redistribution of Sources of Revenue2&#13;
&#13;
        The above-noted imbalance is addressed by intergovernmental transfers. There is large-&#13;
scale reallocation of revenue through earmarked and general subsidies in Japan. Table 2 shows&#13;
the distribution of tax share and fiscal transfer between central and local government. In 1993,&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
total tax revenues were ¥90,705 billion, which is divided into national and local taxes. Before&#13;
fiscal transfers, local taxes account for only 37.0 percent of total revenue. However, a&#13;
substantial portion of national taxes is transferred to the local governments. Major fiscal&#13;
transfers are of two broad types. Unconditional transfers are tax-sharing grants on a lump-sum&#13;
basis financed by the local allocation tax. Conditional grants are matching categorical grants that&#13;
are known as specific-purpose grant. After reallocating the tax sources among levels of&#13;
government, the final share of total tax revenue accruing to local governments increases to 52.5&#13;
percent. This means that one-fourth of central tax revenue is used at the local level.&#13;
&#13;
Table 2: Redistribution of Tax Revenue between National and Local Government (%)&#13;
&#13;
                                     1950     1960     1970       1980         1985        1993&#13;
&#13;
(1) Government Expenditure&#13;
    Net Total/GNP                    23.6     18.8     20.3       29.4         27.6        30.0&#13;
    Net National/GNP                 10.4      5.9       5.9        9.9        10.2        10.3&#13;
    Net Local/GNP                    13.2     12.8     14.4       19.5         17.4        19.6&#13;
(2) Tax Allocation before&#13;
         Fiscal Transfer&#13;
    National Tax/Total Tax           75.2     70.8     67.5       64.1         62.6        63.0&#13;
    Local Tax/Total Tax              24.8     29.2     32.5       35.9         37.4        37.0&#13;
    Income Tax/Total Tax             38.6     21.7     31.2       38.1         39.4        36.9&#13;
(3) Fiscal Transfers&#13;
    Transfer as % of general         35.1     47.2     48.7       44.0         38.5        36.0&#13;
         account&#13;
    Local allocation tax as          17.1     17.8     22.0       18.7         17.8        20.4&#13;
         % of general account&#13;
    Transfer as % of local           40.8     39.3     37.7       40.8         34.7        31.8&#13;
         revenues&#13;
    Local allocation tax as          19.9     14.8     17.0       17.3         15.5        18.0&#13;
         % of local revenues&#13;
(4) Final Share of tax after&#13;
    Fiscal Transfer&#13;
     of National government          65.2     57.0     51.1       46.0         45.3        47.5&#13;
    of Local government              34.8     43.0     48.9       54.0         54.7        52.5&#13;
&#13;
Source: Mochida, N. (1993), p. 57.&#13;
Note: Transfer includes both local allocation tax and specific-purpose grant.&#13;
&#13;
        Intergovernmental transfers are needed not only to balance the budget at the sub-&#13;
national level, but also to offset regional inequalities arising from differences in physical and&#13;
demographic endowments. Given regional gaps in tax revenues and financial needs, some&#13;
means of fiscal equalization is necessary to provide local public services in poor areas. The&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
most important means devised to handle this problem is the unconditional tax-sharing grant.&#13;
In Japan, the local allocation tax system plays a key role through the equalization transfer&#13;
scheme. Although specific-purpose grants, local transfer taxes, and even some local taxes also&#13;
have the effect of equalization, to some extent the discussion in Japan concerns the local&#13;
allocation tax because of its key role in the equalization transfer system.&#13;
        A comparison of per capita local tax revenue and per capita revenue from general&#13;
fiscal sources (that is, local taxes and local allocation tax) of prefectures shows a substantial&#13;
reduction of disparities. This can be seen in Table 3 which groups prefectures into five&#13;
categories according to the index of fiscal capacity, which is defined as the basic fiscal&#13;
capacity divided by basic fiscal need of each local government. A marked difference is&#13;
observed in per capita prefectural tax revenues among localities in fiscal year 1993, the largest&#13;
in Tokyo, ¥196,000, the smallest in Okinawa, ¥60,000, corresponding closely to the&#13;
difference in their economic resources and the per capita income of their inhabitants.&#13;
Disproportionate local allocation tax is provided to areas with lower resource bases to achieve&#13;
some degree of equalization. The correlation between per capita prefectural tax revenue and&#13;
per capita local allocation tax is ­0.71.&#13;
        As a result, per capita revenues from general sources in the area with low tax bases&#13;
increases considerably. A surprise is that the coefficient of variation in prefectural tax&#13;
revenue, accounting for 0.2408, differs little with that in general revenue, which accounts for&#13;
0.2293. This phenomenon resulted in a reversal of the rank-ordering of disparities among&#13;
prefectures rather than a deterioration of the equalization effect. The degree of reversal in the&#13;
relative wealth of prefectures can be measured by the rank-ordering correlation. The rank&#13;
order correlation between per capita prefectural tax and per capita general revenue is ­0.5195.&#13;
After fiscal transfer, the prefectures with lower tax capacity, as measured by prefectural tax&#13;
revenue, had the higher total resources, as measured by general revenue. General resources of&#13;
Aichi, Osaka, and Kanagawa are only a half those of Tottori, Shimane, and Kochi. It may be&#13;
assumed that the Japanese equalization system reduces geographical fiscal inequalities quite&#13;
extensively, although many questions about the mechanism remain unsettled.3&#13;
&#13;
MoHA's Role&#13;
&#13;
        Two ministries dominate when it comes to local fiscal matters in Japan. One is the&#13;
Ministry of Finance (MoF) and the other is the Ministry of Home Affairs (MoHA). There&#13;
is often conflict between the two as the latter plays the role of a counterpower in the central&#13;
bureaucracy against MoF incursions into local matters. Therefore, MoHA is often to said to&#13;
be "an opposition party within the national government." Today, MoHA has a secretariat,&#13;
three bureaus, two departments, and a college. Two of these bureaus, the Local Finance&#13;
Bureau and the Local Tax Bureau, are intimately connected with local fiscal matters. The&#13;
former deals with planning and implementation of the local finance system.            The local&#13;
allocation tax is the most important fiscal transfer the bureau has devised. The latter is&#13;
charged with planning and implementation of the local tax system. Since the taxpayer and tax&#13;
base are the same for national and local taxes, this bureau establishes the organization for&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
national, prefectural, and municipal levels. Based on the framework provided by the Local&#13;
Tax Law, each local government prepares its own tax bylaws for its tax administration.&#13;
Table 3: Fiscal Equalization by Local Allocation Tax (47 Prefectures, FY 1993)&#13;
&#13;
                      Prefectural     Local      General      Per capita (thousand of Yen)&#13;
                      tax revenue allocation tax revenue                     Local&#13;
                       (hundred     (hundred    (hundred Prefectural allocation           General&#13;
Classification          million)     million)    million)      tax            tax         revenue&#13;
A     Aichi             9,552            69     10,017         143              1            150&#13;
      Osaka            11,369           272     12,232         130              3            140&#13;
      Kanagawa          9,210           124      9,765         115              2            122&#13;
B     Shizuoka          4,495           927      5,853         122            25             159&#13;
      Saitama           6,286         1,563      8,145          98            24             127&#13;
      Chiba             5,652         1,448      7,408         102            26             133&#13;
      Hyogo             5,738         2,286      8,400         106            42             155&#13;
      Kyoto             2,800         1,213      4,221         108            47             162&#13;
      Tochigi           2,188         1,240      3,621         113            64             187&#13;
      Ibaragi           3,122         1,742      5,049         110            61             177&#13;
      Fukuoka           4,363         2,394      7,039          91            50             146&#13;
      Gunma             2,121         1,203      3,513         108            61             179&#13;
      Hiroshima         2,930         1,837      4,971         103            64             174&#13;
      Gifu              2,201         1,546      3,927         107            75             190&#13;
      Shiga             1,398         1,079      2,574         114            88             211&#13;
      Mie               1,949         1,469      3,586         109            82             200&#13;
      Miyagi            2,342         1,661      4,183         104            74             186&#13;
C     Okayama           1,925         1,752      3,830         100            91             199&#13;
      Ishikawa          1,290         1,217      2,688         111           105             231&#13;
      Nagano            2,266         2,116      4,606         105            98             214&#13;
      Kagawa            1,064         1,072      2,220         104           105             217&#13;
      Toyama            1,261         1,388      2,750         113           124             246&#13;
      Fukushima         2,120         2,222      4,549         101           106             216&#13;
      Nara              1,150         1,348      2,580          84            98             288&#13;
      Fukui             1,082         1,152      2,317         131           140             281&#13;
      Yamaguchi         1,505         1,757      3,394          96           112             216&#13;
      Niigata           2,539         2,828      5,607         103           114             227&#13;
      Yamanashi            879        1,228      2,202         103           144             258&#13;
D     Hokkaido          5,205         7,114     12,837          92           126             227&#13;
      Ehime             1,253         1,854      3,224          83           122             213&#13;
      Wakayama             941        1,560      2,600          88           145             242&#13;
      Kumamoto          1,364         2,306      3,816          74           125             207&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Prefectural     Local     General     Per capita (thousand of Yen)&#13;
                     tax revenue allocation tax revenue                 Local&#13;
                       (hundred     (hundred   (hundred Prefectural allocation      General&#13;
Classification         million)      million)   million)      tax        tax        revenue&#13;
      Oita              1,003         1,865      2,984        81        151           241&#13;
E     Yamagata          1,007         1,938      3,068        80        154           244&#13;
      Saga                 740        1,476      2,288        84        168           261&#13;
      Nagasaki          1,095         2,320      3,528        70        148           226&#13;
      Iwate             1,093         2,489      2,714        77        176           262&#13;
      Kagoshima         1,200         2,743      4,085        67        153           227&#13;
      Tokushima            688        1,565      2,319        83        188           279&#13;
      Miyazaki             815        1,958      2,862        70        167           245&#13;
      Okinawa              735        1,800      2,605        60        147           213&#13;
      Akita                919        2,198      3,218        75        179           262&#13;
      Aomori            1,041         2,471      2,626        70        167           245&#13;
      Tottori              486        1,356      1,914        79        220           311&#13;
      Shimane              615        1,848      2,546        79        237           326&#13;
      Kochi                590        1,863      2,531        71        226           307&#13;
F     Tokyo            23,191              -   24,447       196            -          206&#13;
      Average         138,779        80,878    229,456      112          65           186&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Ministry of Home Affairs&#13;
Note 1: general revenue means the sum of prefectural tax, local allocation tax, and local&#13;
transfer tax.&#13;
Note 2: 47 prefectures are grouped into 5 categories based on the index of fiscal capacity.&#13;
A 1.0~, B 0.5~1.0, C 0.4~0.5, D 0.3~0.4, E~0.3&#13;
&#13;
Division of Expenditure Responsibility&#13;
&#13;
       It is local government that shoulders the responsibility of Japan's domestic&#13;
administration. Almost all administrative functions closely connected with the daily life of&#13;
the nation are carried out by local government. As a result, local public finance accounts for&#13;
approximately two-thirds of the public expenditure burden, on the basis of final&#13;
disbursement. Table 4 shows how expenditure responsibilities are shared between national&#13;
and local governments across a range of public services.        As can be seen, the central&#13;
government directly performs relatively few public functions such as national defense,&#13;
pension-related public welfare expenditure, and expenditure to repay a debt. About 80&#13;
percent of the disbursements of the national government's general account are simply&#13;
transferred to other accounts, with local government gaining the largest share. In contrast,&#13;
local governments are responsible for a major share of public spending, including that for&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
national land conservation and development, school education, social education, police and&#13;
fire-defense, social welfare, sanitation, and general administration.&#13;
The strength of Japan's system is that considerably more public spending takes place at the&#13;
local level than at the national level. The assignment of expenditure responsibilities is&#13;
determined by national legislation (such as the Local Finance Law and the Local Autonomy&#13;
Law) and cannot be altered at the discretion of the           central government. The central&#13;
government has no legal right to issue unfunded mandates to local government. Nevertheless,&#13;
the national government remains heavily involved in almost every aspect of local public&#13;
spending. Unlike the American and Canadian systems, there is no clear separation of central&#13;
and local function. As a result, major programs (education, health, public works) are&#13;
formulated by national ministries and financed by many specific grants. Therefore, the issue&#13;
for Japan is not so much to change/enlarge the expenditure assignments themselves, but to&#13;
redefine responsibilities for designing, implementing, and financing these assignments.&#13;
&#13;
Table 4: Expenditure Shares between National and Local Governments (FY1994)&#13;
&#13;
Expenditure Category                                    Percent Spent Through&#13;
(Percent share of total in parenthesis)     National Government           Local Government&#13;
General government (13.2)                              19                             81&#13;
&#13;
National defense (3.3)                                 19                             81&#13;
&#13;
National land conservation (21.2)                      21                             79&#13;
&#13;
Industry and economy (7.1)                             21                             79&#13;
&#13;
Education (14.8)                                       13                             87&#13;
&#13;
Social welfare (22.5)                                  33                             67&#13;
&#13;
Pension (1.3)                                          92                               8&#13;
&#13;
Debt service (15.2)                                    62                             38&#13;
&#13;
Other (1.4)                                           100                               0&#13;
&#13;
Average                                                34.5                           65.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Ministry of Home Affairs, Local Public Finance System, 1996.&#13;
&#13;
        In this respect, both the reform of agency delegated functions and reduction of the&#13;
national government disbursement for specific purposes are of great importance. In addition&#13;
to ADF, specific-purpose grants are distributed on the condition that the recipient follow the&#13;
directives issued by the national government. If a local government fails to observe national&#13;
directives, it is asked to refund the disbursement in whole or in part. A basic principle that&#13;
underlies national government control seems to be uniformity throughout the country.&#13;
However, detailed conditions attached to grants lead to waste and administrative inefficiency,&#13;
and they do not sufficiently take local preferences into account.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Characteristics of Local Tax System in Japan&#13;
&#13;
Tax Assignment4&#13;
&#13;
        In Japan, the ratio of total tax burden to GDP of 27­28 percent does not seem as high&#13;
as those of other major OECD countries. Total tax revenue in fiscal year 1994 amounted to&#13;
¥86.5 trillion, 62.4 percent is national taxes and 37.6 percent is local taxes.5 The ratio of local&#13;
tax of local governments total revenue is 35.2 percent, which is not always low from the&#13;
viewpoint of international comparison.6 Every local government is authorized by the Local&#13;
Tax Law to levy and collect several kind of local taxes. Final authority to levy local tax,&#13;
however, is guaranteed by local ordinances and bylaws enacted by each local assembly. If a&#13;
local assembly does not establish local ordinances and bylaws, the taxpayer has no obligation&#13;
to pay taxes to the local government.&#13;
        A good local tax system should satisfy several criteria. The first is revenue response&#13;
to economic growth. In the long run, it is desirable that local revenue increase and decrease in&#13;
line with local expenditure needs. Although a buoyant tax base allows windfall revenue gains&#13;
to local government, this problem can be overcome provided that the long-run local elasticity&#13;
of the tax base to economic growth is equal to one (Bennett and Krebs 1987, p. 251). It&#13;
should be noted that unlike United States and the United Kingdom, where local governments&#13;
rely predominantly on property tax, Japan's local tax system does well in revenue response&#13;
to economic growth. This is mainly because the major source of local own-revenue is a kind&#13;
of tax-base sharing that is similar to a surtax on the national income tax base. Approximately&#13;
60 percent of prefectural taxes revenue and 40 percent of municipal tax revenues are imposed&#13;
on the income of individuals and corporations.&#13;
        There is good evidence to show that elasticities of local taxes are higher than unity.&#13;
Table 5 indicates that elasticity of tax revenue to economic growth is 1.26 and 1.35,&#13;
respectively, for prefectures and municipalities during 1971­90. Among local taxes, municipal&#13;
individual inhabitants tax is highest, at 1.74, prefectural individual inhabitants tax accounts for&#13;
1.43, and municipal corporation inhabitants tax accounts for 1.42. Contrary to general belief,&#13;
the responsiveness of property tax, which is called the fixed-assets tax by MoHA, is not less&#13;
than unity, primarily because of the sharp rise in market value of land in the late 1980s and the&#13;
assessments made at regular intervals. According to these elasticities, the share of local tax in&#13;
total tax revenue is relatively high in comparison with other unitary states.&#13;
        The individual inhabitant tax is a burden-sharing tax--all residents are required to&#13;
share the cost of maintaining local community functions according to their ability to pay. It&#13;
can be likened to a membership fee for being a part of the local community.7 The inhabitants&#13;
tax has two forms, each based on a different tax source: per capita and income. The former is&#13;
a lump-sum component, while the latter is levied on income in a manner similar to the&#13;
collection of the national individual income tax. The inhabitants' income tax, however, is&#13;
assessed on the income of a year previous to the income assessed in the national income tax.&#13;
Generally speaking, the inhabitants' tax is the best choice for raising a large amount of local&#13;
tax revenue, because it places the responsibility on as many inhabitants as possible to finance&#13;
local public services.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        The second criteria is small revenue fluctuations over time. Strong fluctuations in&#13;
revenue during the business cycle can be regarded positively for a national tax, but is not for&#13;
local taxes. First, local expenditures are fairly continuous and revenue fluctuation makes&#13;
planning difficult. Second, local expenditures should not run contrary to national economic&#13;
policy, although the scope for local authority to pursue a countercyclical budget policy is&#13;
rather limited. As Table 5 indicates, the fixed-assets tax produces fairly stable revenue. In&#13;
contrast, corporation inhabitants tax and enterprise tax fluctuate strongly during business&#13;
cycle, since these taxes are generally imposed on net income, not on sales or turnover.&#13;
Individual inhabitants tax fluctuates less than corporation inhabitants' tax and enterprise tax.&#13;
Apparently the instability of enterprise tax revenue is its most serious problem, because of&#13;
its large share in prefectural tax revenue.8 Introduction of a new tax base such as sales,&#13;
capital, or value added taxes has been suggested in order to make tax revenue less sensitive to&#13;
business conditions. The introduction of a local consumption tax in fiscal year 1997 may also&#13;
be a first step toward revenue stability.9&#13;
        The third criteria is distribution among local authorities. A local tax system should&#13;
produce a relatively balanced distribution of revenue among local government in relation to&#13;
their expenditure needs. Large differences in the tax base between localities may cause many&#13;
undesirable effects that require intergovernmental fiscal equalization. Tobacco tax levied on&#13;
the number of cigarettes score highly in balanced distribution of tax revenue among localities.&#13;
The base of the fixed-assets tax is also evenly distributed throughout the country. It should&#13;
be stressed that regional disparity in financial capacity has been gradually reduced during&#13;
postwar, high economic growth era. Table 5 indicates that the Gini coefficient of per capita&#13;
prefectural tax revenue decreased from 0.2297 in fiscal year 1965 to 0.1113 in fiscal year&#13;
1994. However, a marked difference is still observed in per capita prefectural tax revenues&#13;
among localities in fiscal year 1994, the largest in Tokyo, ¥183,000, the smallest in Okinawa,&#13;
¥56,000, corresponding closely to the difference in their economic resources and the per&#13;
capita income of the inhabitants.&#13;
        The fourth criteria is local fiscal autonomy and fiscal equivalence. The power to&#13;
determine the tax rate and base allows local variations in fiscal burdens to be sensitive to local&#13;
preferences, which should encourage fiscal accountability. Despite strict uniformity,10 there&#13;
are two options available to local government for setting the tax rate and base in Japan. One&#13;
is that the central government sets fixed tax rate for a number of local taxes, but provides&#13;
ranges for some others. Each local authority can use the standard tax rate with an upper-limit&#13;
set by MoHA and MoF.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 5: Evaluation of Local Tax System&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       Criteria for local tax system&#13;
                                    Tax revenue&#13;
                                    in FY 1995       Distribution among&#13;
                                                                                Fiscal equivalence&#13;
                                                          localities                                      Revenue Elasticity1 Fluctuation2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              Actual range of tax rate&#13;
                                                    FY1965       FY 1994&#13;
                                                                               (number of localities)&#13;
                                  million     %&#13;
                                    Yen&#13;
                                                      (Gini        (Gini     below      at        over&#13;
                                                  coefficient) coefficient) standard standard standard&#13;
                                                                            tax rate  tax rate  tax rate&#13;
&#13;
  Prefectural tax&#13;
  Inhabitants tax&#13;
     individual                     2,662     19.1   0.261        0.1504       0        47          0             1.43           0.88&#13;
      interest rate                   991      7.1      -         0.1760       0        47          0              -               -&#13;
     corporation rate                 805      5.7  0.3192        0.1374       0         1         46             1.13           1.49&#13;
  Enterprise tax                    4,235     30.4  0.3225        0.1708       0        40          7             1.26           1.28&#13;
  Prefectural tobacco tax             378      2.7  0.0823        0.0583       0        47          0             0.90           1.52&#13;
  Light oil delivery tax            1,332      9.5  0.1446        0.1403       0        47          0             1.15           0.99&#13;
  Automobile tax                    1,587     11.4  0.1924        0.0829       0        40          0             1.08           0.86&#13;
  Real property acquisition tax       787      5.6  0.2540        0.1557       0        47          0             1.27           1.05&#13;
  Automobile acquisition tax          611      4.3      -         0.1132       0        47          0             1.21           0.77&#13;
  Others                              520      3.7      -           -          -          -          -             -               -&#13;
  Sub-total (A)                    13,908 100.0     0.2297        0.1113       -          -          -            1.26           0.74&#13;
&#13;
  Municipal tax&#13;
  Inhabitants tax&#13;
      individual                    6,532     33.0  0.2184        0.1661       0         3237       0             1.74           0.75&#13;
       corporation rate             2,273     11.4  0.3017        0.1611       0         1785     1237            1.42           1.04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Municipal tobacco tax               669      3.3  0.0827        0.0583       0         3237       0             0.90           1.50&#13;
  Fixed assets tax                  8,429     42.6  0.1552        0.1268       0         2944     289             1.40           0.52&#13;
  City planning tax                 1,304      6.5      -         0.4031       -          -          -            1.49           1.05&#13;
  Others                              559      2.8      -           -          -          -          -             -               -&#13;
  Sub-total (B)                    19,766 100.0     0.1694        0.1441       -          -          -            1.35           0.61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Source: MOHA, Statistical yearbook for local tax (Chihozei ni kansuru sankokeisusiryou), for each year.&#13;
  Notes:    1) Measured as elasticity of tax revenue to growth during 1971-90.&#13;
           2) Measured as the coefficient of variation during 1971-90.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         But principle and practice differ. Good evidence for this is presented in Table 5.&#13;
There are no localities with a tax rate below the standard tax rate, because these localities&#13;
are prohibited from issuing local bonds by the Local Public Finance Law.11 It is difficult&#13;
to find any tax competition among local governments in Japan. At the same time, all but&#13;
one prefecture raised corporate tax over the standard tax rate, but they did not increase&#13;
personal tax for fear of the electoral consequences. Excess tax revenues levied by local&#13;
governments over the standard tax rate represent only ¥1,878 hundred-million at the&#13;
prefectural level and ¥4,751 hundred-million at the municipal level. The former accounts&#13;
for only 1.3 percent of total prefectural tax revenue, and latter for 2.3 percent of total&#13;
municipal tax revenue. As a result, almost all localities use a uniform rate for the same tax&#13;
base. For example, in fiscal year 1996, 2,944 out of 3,233 municipalities applied the same&#13;
standard tax rate to the property tax base. This suggests that there is strong preference&#13;
for equal access to public services and equitable sharing of the burden in Japan.&#13;
         The other option is concerned with the imposition of new taxes not listed in the&#13;
law. Local government is given the authority to propose new taxes, but must seek the&#13;
approval of the MoHA and MoF. In fiscal year 1996, only 14 prefectures and 21&#13;
municipalities were given permission to use nonlisted taxes such as a nuclear fuel tax on&#13;
nuclear power plants. Local governments in Japan have relatively large receipts from&#13;
local taxes, but since the flexibility in determining the tax base and rate is strictly limited,&#13;
it is difficult to see how they can be accountable to their constituents at the margin, as&#13;
both efficiency and local autonomy require.12&#13;
&#13;
Local Public Finance Program&#13;
&#13;
         Japan's intergovernmental system is well-designed to enforce fiscal responsibility.&#13;
The probability of a local government going bankrupt or getting itself into severe financial&#13;
difficulties is less than in North America or Western Europe. As Reed (1986) points out&#13;
very clearly, Japan is like France in the sense that the central government takes&#13;
responsibility for enforcing proper financial practices on local government, while in other&#13;
countries this responsibility lies more with the local electorate and the banking system.&#13;
         In this regard, attention should be paid to the role of the Local Public Finance&#13;
Program. The Local Public Finance Program serves as a tool to estimate annual aggregate&#13;
local revenue sources to cover standardized local spending. MoHA assumes the role of&#13;
formulating the Local Public Finance Program every year, and it has primary&#13;
responsibility for ensuring that local governments have enough revenue to balance the&#13;
program. On the expenditure side, the Local Public Finance Program covers the whole of&#13;
local governments` standard activities except for special local public enterprise accounts,&#13;
which are run on an independent profit system, and a few other special accounts. On the&#13;
revenue side of the program, it covers all the standard local revenue sources such as local&#13;
taxes, local allocation tax, national disbursement, local loans, fees, and tuition. The most&#13;
important function of the Local Public Finance Program is to ensure fiscal responsibility,&#13;
because if the estimated program does not balance in the year, MoHA must propose&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
some measure such as local tax amendments, increases in the Local Allocation Tax, or an&#13;
increase in local loans.&#13;
        As the following episode indicates, a kind of special measure, such as borrowing&#13;
from the Fund Management Board of the MoF and a deficit-covering bond issue, is not&#13;
determined automatically, but is based on arbitrary political negotiation between MoHA&#13;
and MoF. MoHA is responsible for the Local Public Finance Program, and it negotiates&#13;
very hard with the MoF in order to secure sources of revenue for local governments. In&#13;
principle, the tax-sharing ratio of Local Allocation Tax must remain unchanged, even if the&#13;
total amount of the financial shortage exceeds the legal amount of local allocation tax. The&#13;
national government is required to raise the tax-sharing ratio if the legal amount of local&#13;
allocation tax differs "continuously" and "remarkably" from the financial shortage. But&#13;
this fundamental principle could not be applied strictly in the post-rapid-growth era. In&#13;
practice, the short-term borrowing from the Fund Management Board of the MoF and&#13;
issue of deficit-covering local bonds played a key role in local public finance in addition to&#13;
raising the tax-sharing ratio.&#13;
        This can be found in table 6 which summarizes the "Special Measure concerning&#13;
Local Public Finance" after the oil crises. The discussion was focused on whether the tax-&#13;
sharing ratio would be altered based on the provision of local allocation tax law (clause 2,&#13;
article 6-3). By fiscal year 1984, both short-term borrowing from the Fund Management&#13;
Board of the MoF and the issue of deficit-covering local bonds played a key role in the&#13;
local public finance. In fiscal year 1977, while MoHA and the representatives of local&#13;
authorities claimed a rise in the tax-sharing ratio of 5 percent, MoF has rejected this&#13;
request because of the huge financial deficit in the national budget. As a result, the&#13;
following memorandum was confirmed between the minister of finance and the minister&#13;
of home affairs in 1977: (a) to make up for the amount of financial shortage by increases&#13;
in both the local allocation tax and deficit-covering local bonds; and (b) to increase the&#13;
amount of local allocation tax by transferring provisional local grants from the general&#13;
account and by borrowing from the Fund Management Board of the MoF. In the latter&#13;
case, it was agreed to redeem a half amount of the principal and the total amount of&#13;
interest by the burden of the general account of national budget.13&#13;
        However, revenue of the three national taxes increased steadily in the "bubble&#13;
economy" of the late 1980s. The amount of financial shortage, therefore, has been&#13;
reduced quite extensively. In fiscal year 1984, the following new memorandum was&#13;
confirmed between the two ministers:          (a) to suspend borrowing from the Fund&#13;
Management Board of the MoF as a rule after fiscal year 1984; (b) to redeem half the&#13;
amount of both principal and interest by the burden of each national and local&#13;
government; and (c) to transfer a special addition of local allocation tax from the general&#13;
account of national budget , in place of borrowing from the Fund Management Board of&#13;
the MoF.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 6: Special Measure Concerning Local Public Finance (hundred million&#13;
yen)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Fiscal Year             1975-79         1980-84            1985-89             1990-97&#13;
&#13;
1.    Amount of financial 28,046              20,593 (100)      16,514 (100)         46,213 (100)&#13;
shortage                      (100)&#13;
2.    Increase     in   local 15,413          9,757 (47.4)      2,709 (16.4)         24,783&#13;
allocation tax                (54.9)                                                 (53.4)&#13;
-borrowing      from    Trust                 8,932 (43.3)      900 (5.4)&#13;
Fund Bureau                   14,408          825 (4.0)         1,809 (10.9)         20,812&#13;
-other                        (51.3)                                                 (45.6)&#13;
                              1,005 (3.5)                                            3,971 (8.6)&#13;
3. Increase in local bond     12,676          10,836 (52.6) 11,872 (71.9) 21,430&#13;
                              (100)                                                  (46.4)&#13;
4. Increase in local tax      0 (0)           0 (0)             1,933 (11.7)         0 (0)&#13;
&#13;
Note: Figures in parentheses are percentage of the amount of financial shortage. All&#13;
figures are average per year.&#13;
Source: Ministry of Home Affairs, 1989..&#13;
&#13;
Intergovernmental Fiscal Transfer and Regional Disparity14&#13;
&#13;
Evolution of Fiscal Equalization&#13;
&#13;
        The first regular scheme for equalizing local finance was the local distribution tax&#13;
in 1940, which was carried out in connection with tax reform of central and local&#13;
governments corresponding to the quasi-war situation.15 The local distribution tax was a&#13;
kind of national tax, and the proceeds were shared with local units. The funds were&#13;
distributed among localities without restriction, not by the tax source principle, but by a&#13;
formula designed to provide equalization. However, the local distribution tax had some&#13;
defects from the viewpoint of local autonomy. First, the tax-sharing ratio varied in&#13;
practice from year to year, partially in accordance with the fluctuation in receipts caused&#13;
by the sensitivity of income taxation, and partially in keeping with the fiscal deficit in&#13;
national finance. Second, in the distribution tax, the total amount to be given to individual&#13;
local units was divided into two parts, which were apportioned separately: one according&#13;
to the need for services, the other according to fiscal capacity, and these parts had no&#13;
relationship with each other.&#13;
        A big change in the basic structure of the fiscal equalization system was brought&#13;
about by the U.S. Occupation after World War II. Great stress was placed on the&#13;
importance of local autonomy in a democratic nation, and the prewar system was&#13;
completely restructured in order to encourage decentralization. In accordance with the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Shoup Recommendation, the distribution tax was converted to the local finance&#13;
equalization grant in 1950 (chihozaisei heiko-kofukin).16&#13;
         It is true that the equalization grant was more reasonable than the distribution tax.&#13;
The equalization grant was computed by means of a formula that contained two parts, the&#13;
first relating to the measure of the local need for basic services, and second relating to the&#13;
measure of local financial ability.17 The total financial capacity was then subtracted from&#13;
total financial need, and the difference served as the basis for computing the grant for each&#13;
locality. In the case of the equalization grant, the total amount was determined more&#13;
closely in accordance with the difference between fiscal needs and resources of localities,&#13;
irrespective of national tax revenue.&#13;
         Four years of experience revealed that it had not worked as well as had been&#13;
hoped. The aggregate sum of the grant was not paid out of the general funds of national&#13;
government as computed by the formula, but was determined every year, taking into&#13;
consideration, among other things, the degree of stringency in national finance. So, every&#13;
year it gave rise to friction between local and national officials in the determination of the&#13;
total amount. In view of these considerations, the equalization grant was abolished in&#13;
1953, and in its place the local allocation tax (LAT) was introduced in 1954.&#13;
&#13;
Legal Framework and Operation18&#13;
&#13;
         LAT is governed by the local allocation tax law. This law stipulates that LAT&#13;
should be based on a uniform formula; the final authority to approve the distribution lies&#13;
with the National Assembly. According to the law, the MoHA is responsible for the&#13;
operation (calculating the amount of LAT) of the transfer and for determining&#13;
modification coefficients.19 Not granting MoHA the final authority to approve the&#13;
formula and unit costs is an important mechanism to deter any attempt to manipulate&#13;
distribution. A certain degree of flexibility is also given to MoHA, because it has the&#13;
authority of determine modification coefficients, which marginally affect the distribution&#13;
of LAT.&#13;
         In addition, MoHA has the responsibility to collect data, which are used for the&#13;
calculation of LAT and to put them in order. And each governor is duty-bound to&#13;
present these data to MoHA, and each mayor is obligated to present these data to the&#13;
governor. What kind of role do local governments have on operating LAT? In the LAT&#13;
for prefectural government, all staff are bound only to collect data and present them to&#13;
MoHA and the Local Autonomy Information Center. Paradoxically, only MoHA is&#13;
calculating LAT.20&#13;
         This legal framework ensures that no single locality or senior official effectively&#13;
influences the distribution of LAT in favor of a particular region without affecting many&#13;
other regions.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                       Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Practical Effects of Fiscal Equalization21&#13;
&#13;
                              Now we proceed to analyze the practical effects of the Japanese system on the&#13;
general revenue of local bodies. To determine the actual degree of equalization achieved,&#13;
per capita local allocation tax is added to the per capita local tax in order to obtain a&#13;
notional total reflecting the area's resources after the addition of the local allocation&#13;
tax--this is termed general financial resources (GFR). The disparity is then determined, as&#13;
measured by the Gini coefficient, in the GFR, and it is compared with the initial disparity&#13;
in local tax per capita. The extent of the improvement (or deterioration) can then be&#13;
measured as the difference between the Gini coefficient of local tax and that of GFR,&#13;
divided by the former. This measure can be expressed by the following equation:&#13;
&#13;
                                    ø = ( G2 ­ G1 ) / G2&#13;
&#13;
                              Where G1 stands for the Gini coefficient of GFR, G2 for the Gini coefficient in&#13;
local tax, and ø denotes the extent of the improvement (I have termed this the equalization&#13;
coefficient in this chapter). Figure 1 indicates the change in the extent of improvement&#13;
measured by the Equalization Coefficient. As Figure 1 demonstrates, the extent of&#13;
improvement has changed drastically every ten years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                Figure 1. Extent of Equalization by LAT&#13;
&#13;
                              0.20                                                                               0.8&#13;
&#13;
                              0.18                                        GINI coefficient of per capita&#13;
                                                                          regional income                        0.7&#13;
                              0.16                                        coefficient of equalization&#13;
     income                                                                                                      0.6&#13;
                              0.14&#13;
&#13;
                              0.12                                                                               0.5            equalization&#13;
           regional                                                                                                                         of&#13;
                   in         0.10                                                                               0.4&#13;
&#13;
                              0.08                                                                               0.3&#13;
                              0.06&#13;
                     disparity                                                                                   0.2 coefficient&#13;
                              0.04&#13;
&#13;
                              0.02                                                                               0.1&#13;
&#13;
                              0.00                                                                               0&#13;
                                 1950                   65                          80&#13;
                                                                fiscal year&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Figure 2: Regional distribution of fiscal resources&#13;
&#13;
                            0.35&#13;
                                                                               per capita local tax&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            0.30                                               per capita general revenue&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            0.25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            0.20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            coefficient&#13;
                            0.15&#13;
                       GINI&#13;
&#13;
                            0.10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            0.05&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            0.00&#13;
                               1950              65                        80&#13;
&#13;
                                                        fiscal year&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         THE FIRST HALF OF THE RAPID-GROWTH ERA (1954 TO 1964). Increase in pre-&#13;
grant disparity is a feature of this period. The disparity in financial resources among rich&#13;
and poor local authorities became larger and was maintained at a high level. A large&#13;
number of young people moved from rural areas to the metropolitan areas such as Tokyo,&#13;
Osaka, and Nagoya. To deal with this social problem, the political slogan of&#13;
"Improvement of Regional Disparity" became one of the main national policy goals and&#13;
was embodied in the National Comprehensive Development Plan, established in October&#13;
1962. In line with this national policy guideline, local allocation tax was distributed&#13;
mainly to the backward districts in inverse proportion to their financial capacities. As a&#13;
result, local allocation tax served to reduce resource disparities by 70 percent each year.&#13;
&#13;
         THE SECOND HALF OF THE RAPID GROWTH ERA (1965­74). The reduction of&#13;
pregnant disparities and the reversal of the rank-ordering is a distinctive characteristic of&#13;
this period. There was a sharp decrease in the disparities among rich and poor districts.&#13;
The Gini coefficient of per capita regional income decreased from 0.1248 in fiscal year&#13;
1965 to 0.0753 in fiscal year 1975. This improvement in regional disparities was not&#13;
caused by the success of the National Comprehensive Development Plan, but by the&#13;
dispersion of factories around the country and the increase in the number of people&#13;
employed in the local public works. Nevertheless, the distribution of the local allocation&#13;
tax followed the principle of equalization all the more. As a result, resources disparities&#13;
actually increased after the equalizing effect of the local allocation tax is taken into&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
account (see figure 2). However, this increase actually resulted in a reversal of the rank-&#13;
ordering of disparities among prefectures. We should notice that the sharp decline in the&#13;
equalization coefficients means enforcement of improvement rather than the deterioration&#13;
of the equalizing effect.&#13;
&#13;
        THE OIL CRISES AND AFTERWARDS (THE MID-1970S TO THE MID-1980S). Gradual&#13;
increase in pregnant disparity is a characteristic of this period. During this time, the&#13;
disparities in the per capita local tax began to increase again as a result of population&#13;
concentration in the Tokyo metropolitan area caused by the internationalization of&#13;
financial market. As figure 2 demonstrates, the Gini coefficient of the per capita local tax&#13;
increased gradually after the oil crises. At the same time, the negative correlation between&#13;
per capita tax revenue and the per capita local allocation tax became weaker, because of a&#13;
shortage in the total amount of local allocation tax. As a result of these trends, reversal of&#13;
the rank-ordering of disparities among prefectures was corrected somewhat.&#13;
&#13;
        THE BUBBLE ECONOMY AND THEREAFTER (1985 TO THE PRESENT). A sharp&#13;
reduction of pre-grant disparities and a reversal of rank-ordering is a characteristic of this&#13;
period. There was a marked decrease in the regional disparities, as figure 2 indicates. The&#13;
Gini coefficient of local tax declined from 0.19 in fiscal year 1988 to 0.15 in fiscal 1993.&#13;
As a result, the equalization coefficient has dropped drastically, from 0.4120 in fiscal year&#13;
1988 to 0.085 in fiscal 1993. It is noteworthy that there is little difference between pre-&#13;
grant disparities and the area's resource disparities after the addition of local allocation tax.&#13;
However, these trends do not mean there was a deterioration of the equalization effect, as&#13;
mentioned above, but instead a reversal of the rank-ordering of disparities among&#13;
prefectures. These trends can be explained by both fundamental tax reform and the&#13;
collapse of the bubble economy.&#13;
&#13;
Implications of the Japanese Experience&#13;
&#13;
Relevance to Developing and Transitional Economies&#13;
&#13;
        The defining characteristic of Japan's system of intergovernmental fiscal relation&#13;
has been the strong collective preference for equal access to public goods. While local&#13;
autonomy was also a popular objective, especially among progressive or left-wing&#13;
politicians, equal access to public goods and fair sharing of the burden of financing these&#13;
goods were viewed as essential for economic and social development.                    Interregional&#13;
redistribution was, therefore, the central issue for Japan's system of intergovernmental&#13;
fiscal relations.   A Japanese-style approach, with the assignment of expenditure&#13;
responsibilities determined by national legislation (such as the local finance law and the&#13;
local autonomy law), and not alterable at the discretion of the central government, may be&#13;
a good solution for societies that have substantial regional tensions.                 The central&#13;
government must have no legal right to place unfunded mandates on local government, but&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the central government does exercise its discretionary powers on local expenditure&#13;
through the delegated function, financed by specific-purpose grants.&#13;
        In developing and transitional economies, income disparity across regions tends to&#13;
worsen after the initial decentralization efforts.          Japan experienced large regional&#13;
disparities in the early stage of postwar economic development. The Japanese&#13;
government responded, and attention should be paid to the significant role played by the&#13;
local allocation tax.22 LAT is distributed according to a uniform formula based on basic&#13;
financial need and basic financial capacity. The application of the formula contributed to&#13;
the removal of intense negotiation and lobbying during postwar development. LAT is&#13;
also paid annually to local governments with basic financial needs that exceed their&#13;
financial capacity, and it varies directly with local fiscal needs and inversely with local&#13;
fiscal capacity. Such an approach corrected horizontal fiscal imbalance in Japan. Finally,&#13;
LAT is not a kind of general grant, but a shared-tax system. An automatic increase in&#13;
major national taxes was the cause of a continuous increase in the financial pool of the&#13;
local allocation tax during the rapid growth era.&#13;
&#13;
Current Issues in Japanese Local Finance&#13;
&#13;
        The current system faces considerable challenges in the medium term, given the&#13;
changing preference of the public with respect to local autonomy. In the 1990s, Japan&#13;
has faced the second transitional phase since World War II. This means a shift away from&#13;
a society that emphasizes equal access to public services and equitable sharing of the&#13;
burden of paying for them, toward a society that gives priority to the individual citizen's&#13;
expressed preference. Where local governments are unable to set their own tax rates, the&#13;
concept of local accountability does not function effectively. The current system needs&#13;
to evolve during the process of fiscal decentralization in order to redefine expenditure&#13;
responsibilities, gain more flexibility in tax rate setting, and to enhance transparency in the&#13;
equalization transfer scheme.&#13;
        In Japan, the national government remains heavily involved in almost every aspect&#13;
of local public spending. Unlike the American and Canadian systems, there is no clear&#13;
separation of central and local function. As a result, major programs (education, health,&#13;
public works) are formulated by national ministries and financed by many specific grants.&#13;
Therefore, the issue for Japan is not so much to change and enlarge the expenditure&#13;
assignments themselves, but to redefine responsibilities for designing, implementing, and&#13;
financing these assignments. In this respect, both reexamination of agency-delegated&#13;
functions and reduction of the national government disbursement for specific purposes&#13;
are important. Detailed conditions attached to grants lead to waste and administrative&#13;
inefficiency, and they do not sufficiently take into account local preferences.&#13;
        Japan's local tax system scores highly in revenue response to economic growth.&#13;
However, the corporation inhabitants tax and the enterprise tax fluctuate greatly during&#13;
the business cycle, since these taxes are generally imposed on net income, not on sales or&#13;
turnover. A marked difference is still observed in per capita prefectural tax revenues&#13;
among localities. Local governments in Japan have relatively large receipts from local&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
taxes, but since the flexibility in determining the tax base and rate is strictly limited, it is&#13;
difficult to see how they can be accountable to their constituents at the margin, as both&#13;
efficiency and local autonomy require. Therefore, the issue for Japan is how to make the&#13;
local tax system more accountable and ensure stability of tax revenue.&#13;
        Local accountability is indispensable not only for taking into account local&#13;
preference but also for macroeconomic control. We can draw some relevant points from&#13;
European experience for Japan facing with heavy fiscal deficit. As measured by the real&#13;
rate of growth in local government spending, both England and Norway are countries&#13;
where control appear to be easy to apply because their local governments do not have&#13;
their own taxation of much importance. On the other hand, Denmark and Sweden, who&#13;
rely on their own taxation and local accountability, did better. This seems to confirm that&#13;
even when local authorities are free to decide on their own income tax rate, it is through&#13;
negotiations would it be possible to have the necessary macroeconomic control.&#13;
        After the burst of so called bubble economy at the beginning of 1990, financial&#13;
shortage of Japan's local finance has been increasing drastically as indicated by Table 6.&#13;
On this background local governments as a whole had to borrow huge amounts of short-&#13;
term money from Fiscal Investment and Loan Program of MoF and had to issue deficit-&#13;
covering local bonds almost every year. The weight of local bond revenue to total local&#13;
revenues has reached 15.2 percentage which is the worst since the World Was II. In 1998,&#13;
fiscal deficit of Japan's general government accounted for 4.7 percentage of GDP, of&#13;
which 1.9 percentage was the share of local government. Of course there are many policy&#13;
options to reduce fiscal deficit, but it should be stressed that own taxation results in local&#13;
accountability and that negotiation system is better than formal control through grants&#13;
and tax ceiling (on this point, see Mochida and Lotz 1999).&#13;
        Given Japan's history of strong collective preference for equal access to public&#13;
goods, it is unrealistic to imagine that local autonomy will evolve toward a system that&#13;
will allow substantial regional differences to reemerge. Therefore, a role for LAT will&#13;
remain. However, the present LAT system is not a complete one, but is still evolving.&#13;
        An effective intergovernmental transfer system, in general, should satisfy several&#13;
criteria. The first criteria is revenue adequacy. The local allocation tax is not a kind of&#13;
general grant, but a shared-tax system. An automatic increase in major national taxes was&#13;
the cause of a continuous increase in the financial pool of the local allocation tax during&#13;
the rapid growth era. At the same time, total fund of transfer is sensitive to business&#13;
conditions because a major component of the fund is income-elastic national taxes.&#13;
During the period of 1970­95, the rate of increase in the financial pool for transfer has&#13;
changed between ­14.1 percent and 43.5 percent every year. Indeed, both short-term&#13;
borrowing from the Fund Management Board of the MoF and deficit-covering local bond&#13;
issues play a key role in filling the gap between total entitlement of local allocation tax&#13;
and the financial pool of the transfer in the post-rapid-growth era. A future reform&#13;
necessary for revenue adequacy is to make the financial pool less sensitive to business&#13;
conditions and more stable.23&#13;
        The second criteria is local tax effort. Basic financial revenue is measured by using&#13;
figures of the major tax base and the standard tax rate. To retain incentives for local&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
government to collect their own tax, basic financial revenue is calculated based on the&#13;
prescribed percentage of the sum of local tax revenues. Regions with high tax effort are&#13;
not penalized, and regions with low tax effort are not encouraged. As for tax effort,&#13;
however, the local tax system is a question. Concerning local taxes, the base and rates of&#13;
general taxes cannot be determined by the independent initiatives of local government&#13;
under the local tax law. The tax base and the tax rates can be altered by the proposal of&#13;
both the MoHA and the MoF. This implies that a uniform rate is levied on the same tax&#13;
base in all prefecture and municipalities. Present local tax systems should be changed into&#13;
more flexible systems, in which the tax rate is determined at the discretion of local&#13;
governments. In order to win national taxpayer's confidence, on the other hand, recipient&#13;
local governments should express their efforts to reduce LAT by enlarging the relevant tax&#13;
bases or using a non-listed local tax.&#13;
        The third criteria is equity. Because local allocation tax is paid annually to local&#13;
governments with basic financial needs that exceed their basic financial capacity, it varies&#13;
directly with local fiscal needs and inversely with local fiscal capacity. Such an approach&#13;
actually corrected horizontal fiscal imbalance in Japan. Before the 1970s, the transfer&#13;
system contributed significantly to equality. But after that, as regional fiscal disparities&#13;
have fallen over time, there has been less inequality to fix through local allocation tax and&#13;
the intensity of the equalization effect has fallen. Future reform, therefore, should be&#13;
carried out based not only on equity criteria, but also on efficiency grounds in order to&#13;
eliminate or reduce "differential net fiscal benefits" which encourage fiscally induced&#13;
migration..&#13;
        The fourth criteria is transparency and stability. Local allocation tax is distributed&#13;
according to a uniform formula based on basic financial need and basic financial capacity.&#13;
The application of the formula contributed to removing intense negotiation and lobbying&#13;
during postwar development.          However, calculation of the transfer became too&#13;
complicated for local governments to forecast their own revenue(including the transfer) in&#13;
order to prepare their budgets. A kind of special measure, such as borrowing from the&#13;
Fund Management Board of the MoF and deficit-covering bond issues, is not determined&#13;
automatically, but based on arbitrary political negotiation between MoHA and MoF.&#13;
Future reform is necessary to strengthen the transparency of the present system.&#13;
&#13;
Endnotes&#13;
&#13;
1. Vertical fiscal imbalance is the disparity between revenue means and expenditure needs&#13;
at various levels of government.        This results from the division of expenditure&#13;
responsibilities and revenue-raising powers between the central and local governments.&#13;
2. For the historical development of the equalization scheme in Japan, see Mochida 1993&#13;
chapters 4 and 5.&#13;
3. It is to be noted that these figures refer merely to the per capita amount of the&#13;
prefecture. Financial needs for local function are not necessarily proportional to the&#13;
number of inhabitants. In a sparsely populated district, for example, per capita revenue&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
produces a large figure, in spite of the low level of accomplishment of services. A densely&#13;
settled district, however, requires fiscal means beyond the average.&#13;
4. This section is based on Ishi (1993) and MoHA (1996a, b, c).&#13;
5. The major components of total tax revenue are income tax, consumption tax, and&#13;
property tax. The amount of income tax was ¥50.2 trillion in fiscal 1994, of which 65.3&#13;
percent is national tax, 18.7 percent is prefectural tax, and 16.0 percent is municipal tax.&#13;
The amount of consumption tax is ¥20.7 trillion, of which 76.8 percent is national tax,&#13;
19.3 percent is prefectural tax, and 3.9 percent is municipal tax. The amount of property&#13;
tax is ¥15.6 trillion, of which 34.0 percent is national tax, 4.5 percent is prefectural tax,&#13;
and 61.5 percent is municipal tax. See MoHA (1996b).&#13;
6. Major sources of total annual local government revenues in fiscal year 1993 are local&#13;
taxes (35.2 percent), local allocation tax (16.2 percent), central government disbursements&#13;
(14.3 percent), loans (14.0 percent), charges and fees (2.3 percent), and local transfer tax&#13;
(2.1 percent).&#13;
7. The inhabitants' tax is collected by both prefectures and municipalities. In levying&#13;
this tax, mutual cooperation is established among the municipal, prefectural, and national&#13;
governments. When the municipal governments levy their inhabitants' tax on individuals,&#13;
they collect the prefectural inhabitants' tax as well, using the same tax base. Information&#13;
on taxable income necessary for computing the local inhabitants' tax is given by the&#13;
national government.&#13;
8. In calculating the tax base of the corporate tax at the national level, the prefectural&#13;
enterprise tax is allowed as a deduction. If a taxpayer has an office within the jurisdiction&#13;
of two or more prefectures, the tax base is allocated to all prefectures concerned. The&#13;
allocation is made on the bases of number of employees.&#13;
9. For local consumption tax, see MoHA (1996a).&#13;
10. All revenue sources are subject to control by the national government under the local&#13;
tax law. The tax base and rates of major items are legislated by the Diet and can be altered&#13;
by the proposal of both the MoHA and MoF.&#13;
11. Local governments that collect local tax below the standard tax rate cannot apply for&#13;
permission for debt financing. (See local public finance law, article 5.1.)&#13;
12. It should be noted that in the prewar period, the local surtax method, in which a&#13;
piggyback surtax was applied to the national tax, played a key role, but it was abolished&#13;
in the postwar era to support local autonomy. Today, each level of local government&#13;
levies its own taxes, including local income tax, separate from the collection of national&#13;
taxes.&#13;
13. The third point is to carry over special addition of local allocation tax in order to&#13;
make up for the difference in interest between local bonds placed on the market and those&#13;
absorbed by the Fund Management Board of the MoF.&#13;
14. This section is based on mainly Mochida (1996). There is valuable literature,&#13;
written in English, concerning the local allocation tax. See, for example, Ito (1967),&#13;
Yonehara (1987), and Ishi (1993).&#13;
15. But we had already had grants as forerunners in the 1930s. Marked territorial&#13;
inequalities in per capita prefectural tax revenue were seen during the Great Depression.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
As device to counter depression, the provisional grant (rinji-chihozaisei hokyukin) was&#13;
introduced. These grants were used for the salaries of primary school teachers and natural&#13;
disaster rehabilitation, and they were apportioned among rural districts.&#13;
16. The 1949 Shoup Mission played a significant role in shaping the style of the tax&#13;
system in postwar Japan. On this subject, see Ishi (1993, chapter 2).&#13;
17. The local need for each item was computed as the number of units of the service,&#13;
multiplied by the standard cost per unit of the service at an acceptable, but minimal,&#13;
quantity and quality. The total need for each locality was the sum of the amounts needed&#13;
for all basic services combined. The financial capacity of each locality was computed as&#13;
70 percent of revenues that all regular local taxes would yield, assuming that they were&#13;
levied at a standard rate with standard levels of assessment and collection.&#13;
18. This section is based on mainly Yamauchi (1996).&#13;
19. MoHA has four bureaus; one is the Local Finance Bureau. Within the bureau, there&#13;
are eight divisions. The Local Finance Division and the Local Allocation Tax Division,&#13;
which belong to the Local Finance Bureau, are in charge of LAT. The former manages the&#13;
affairs of the special local allocation tax; the latter, the ordinary allocation tax. The Local&#13;
Allocation Tax Division employs 18 persons, including a director, 2 assistant directors,&#13;
and 15 staff members.&#13;
20. But the MoHA makes its own opportunity to hear wishes of local governments. It&#13;
holds a conference at least four times a year to make information available to them&#13;
formally and informally, and the parties sometimes discuss the matter together during the&#13;
process of calculation.&#13;
21. For detailed arguments for this section, see Mochida. (1996, 1993, 1990), Kaizuka&#13;
and others (1987), and Ishikawa (1995).&#13;
22. For the role of LAT in the Welfare State, see Hayashi (1992).&#13;
23. To stabilize the financial pool for LAT, Fujita examined a number of methods,&#13;
including creating a new special account, calculating the tax base with a 5-year moving&#13;
average, and returning to the equalization grant introduced by the Shoup recommendation.&#13;
See Fujita (1972, pp. 143­47).&#13;
&#13;
Bibliography&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Benett, R. J., and G. Krebs. 1987. Local Business Taxes in Britain and Germany. Baden-&#13;
        Baden: Nomos Verlagsgessellschaft.&#13;
&#13;
Dubravko, M. 1996. "Intergovernmental Relations and Local Public Finance in Japan."&#13;
        IMF Discussion Paper. Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
Fujiwara, T. 1996. "The Role of the Ministry of Autonomy in Intergovernmental Fiscal&#13;
        Relations in Japan." Paper presented at the workshop on International Experience&#13;
        in Intergovernmental Fiscal Transfer: the Experience from Japan and Other&#13;
        Countries. March, 1996 Hanoi.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Hayashi, T. 1992. Fukushi Kokka no Zaiseigaku (Public Finance of Japanese Welfare&#13;
        States). Tokyo: Yûhikaku.&#13;
&#13;
Ishi, H. 1993. "Local Taxation and Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations." In The Japanese&#13;
        Tax System, 2d ed. Oxford, U.K.: Oxford University Press.&#13;
&#13;
Ishikawa, T. 1995. "Growth, Human Development, and Economic Policies in Japan:&#13;
        1955­1993." University of Tokyo, Faculty of Economics, discussion paper&#13;
        series, 95-F-32.&#13;
&#13;
Ito, H. 1967. "Equalization of Local Finance in Japan." Finanzarchiv N. F. 26, Heftl.&#13;
        Boston: Little Brown.&#13;
&#13;
Kaizuka, K., and others. 1987. Chihôkôfu-zei no Kinô to Hyôka (Local Allocation&#13;
        Tax--Function and its Evaluation). Ministry of Finance, Financial Review, 4.&#13;
        Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
Ma, J. 1996a. "Intergovernmental Fiscal Transfer: A Comparison of Nine Countries."&#13;
        Paper presented to the Workshop on Intergovernmental Fiscal Transfer: The&#13;
        experiences from Japan and other Countries. Hanoi, March 1996.&#13;
&#13;
------. 1996b. "Reforming Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations in China: The Relevance&#13;
        of Japanese Experience." Discussion paper, World Bank Workshop on Local&#13;
        Government and Economic Development in Japan:                    Lessons for Economies&#13;
        Undergoing Decentralization." August 3-5,1996 Honolulu.&#13;
&#13;
MoHA. 1989. Chihokoufuzeiseido Enkakusi (The History of Local Allocation Tax).&#13;
        Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
______. 1996a. Local Tax Administration in Japan. Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
------. 1996b. Local Public Finance System. Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
------. 1996c. Local Public Finance in Japan. Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
Mochida, N. 1990. "Chihôkôfu-zei Seido no Kôzo to Kinô (The Structure and the Function&#13;
of the Local Allocation Tax Grants)." Keizai to Keizaigaku (Economy and Economics) No.&#13;
65: 61-89.&#13;
&#13;
------. 1993. Toshi Zaisei no Kenkyu (Public Finance of Japanese Cities). University of&#13;
        Tokyo Press.&#13;
&#13;
------. 1995. "Balancing Equity and Decentralization." Social Science Japan 5,&#13;
        Newsletter of the Institute of Social Science, University of Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
------. 1996. "Japan's Local Allocation Tax--An Equalization Transfer Scheme."&#13;
        University of Tokyo, Faculty of Economics, discussion paper 95-F-32.&#13;
&#13;
Mochida, N. and J. Lotz. 1999. "Fiscal Federalism in Practice, the Nordic Countries and&#13;
        Japan." The Journal of Economics, Faculty of Economics, University of Tokyo.&#13;
        64 (4).&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Reed, S. 1986. Japanese Prefecture and Policymaking. Pittsburgh, PA: University of&#13;
       Pittsburgh Press.&#13;
Shibata,T ed., 1993. Japan's public sector : how the government is financed , University&#13;
   of Tokyo Press. Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
Shoup Mission.1949. Reports on the Japanese Tax System, The Shoup Mission, Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
Wolman, H., and Page E. 1987. "The Impact of Intergovernmental Grants on Subnational&#13;
       Resources Disparities:     A Cross-National Comparison." Public Budgeting &amp;&#13;
       Finance, autumn. 17(3).&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 1995. "A Proposal for the EDI Research Project on Local Government and&#13;
       Economic Development in Japan: Lessons for Economies Undergoing&#13;
       Decentralization." World Bank Economic Development Institute, Washington,&#13;
       DC.&#13;
&#13;
Yamauchi, K. 1996. "By Whom, When and How is the Japanese Local Allocation Tax&#13;
       Calculated?" Paper presented the Workshop on Intergovernmental Fiscal&#13;
       Transfers. July 8-10, 1996 Vienna.&#13;
Yonehara, J. 1987. "Financial Relations Between National and Local Governments." In&#13;
Shibata T. ed., Public Finance in Japan, University of Tokyo Press.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appendix&#13;
&#13;
Computation Formula of Local Allocation Tax&#13;
&#13;
        LAT has continued to the present with some minor alterations. The framework of&#13;
the local allocation tax is founded on the former distribution tax, enforced between 1940&#13;
and 1949, while retaining the formula used in the equalization grant for the distribution of&#13;
funds to localities. In the LAT system, the total amount to be distributed to local&#13;
authorities is a fraction of yields from major national taxes. The present system is a&#13;
shared tax, in which a share in the proceeds of national taxes is granted to poor localities,&#13;
without limitation on use. The calculation proceeds as follows. First, the total amount of&#13;
the local allocation tax is calculated according to the formula below:&#13;
&#13;
(1)     TT = 0.32* ( NTy + NTc + NTa ) + 0.29* NTv + 0.25* NTt&#13;
&#13;
        Where TT denotes total financial pool of transfer, NTy is the total yield of&#13;
personal income tax, NTc is that of corporate income tax, NTa is that of alcohol tax, NTv is&#13;
80 percent of consumption tax revenue, NTt is total yield of the tobacco tax. These&#13;
prescribed percentages of five major national taxes are apportioned among local bodies in&#13;
proportion to the amount of the difference between need and revenue. This is expressed&#13;
by following equation.&#13;
&#13;
(2)                     LATi = Ni ­ Ci&#13;
&#13;
        Where LATi denotes local allocation tax to ith region, Ni is basic financial need of&#13;
ith region, and Ci is the basic financial capacity of ith region. It is annually paid to local&#13;
governments whose basic financial needs exceed their basic financial revenues. Rich&#13;
localities with revenue that exceeds need are neither eligible for the grants nor liable to&#13;
contribute money for fiscal adjustment, as is the case in some countries.&#13;
        Before calculating basic financial needs, public services for each prefecture and&#13;
municipality are divided into some service items (gyôsei-kômoku). In the prefectures,&#13;
there are 24 service items such as police, roads and bridges, and primary school; for each&#13;
municipality there are 24 service items such as city planning, parks, garbage collection,&#13;
and so on. Basic financial needs of ith local authority are calculated according to following&#13;
formula:&#13;
&#13;
(3)             Ni =?k ( Iik * Uik * Mik )&#13;
&#13;
        Where Iik is a measurement unit for service K of ith region, Uik is unit cost for&#13;
service K of ith region, and Mik is a modification coefficient for service K of ith region. For&#13;
each local body, according to the formula mentioned above, basic financial needs for each&#13;
service item are calculated as the number of measurement units by multiplying the unit&#13;
cost, adjusted by modification coefficients. The total basic need in each locality is the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26 Nobuki Mochida&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
sum of the amounts needed for all service items combined. The first step is to select&#13;
measurement units. A measurement unit reflects the number or size of the beneficiaries of&#13;
a particular expenditure. For example, a measurement unit for education is number of&#13;
teachers, that of police is number of policemen, and that of roads is length of roads.&#13;
        The second step is to determine a unit cost. Unit cost is a kind of net standard&#13;
cost per measurement unit for each service item. Assuming a certain local body with&#13;
standard conditions and scale, the unit cost for each service item is calculated based on&#13;
following formula. In a prefecture, only one fictitious local body with a population of 1.7&#13;
million and a land area of 6,500 square kilometers is assumed as a "standard local body";&#13;
in a municipality, population is 0.1 million and land area 160 square kilometers.&#13;
&#13;
(4)              U = (Cg ­ Rs) / S&#13;
&#13;
        Where U is unit cost, Cg is gross standard cost, Rs is special revenue, and S is a&#13;
figure of measurement unit. The third step is to determine modification coefficients. The&#13;
unit cost, however, is uniform throughout the country, and no regard is given to either the&#13;
unique services nor to the special circumstances of localities. So an exceedingly complex&#13;
adjustment is made of the unit cost applicable to such services and localities by means of&#13;
detailed modifiers determined in accordance with their differences. Modification&#13;
coefficients are currently classified according to eight categories.&#13;
        On the other side, the basic financial revenue of each locality is expressed as a&#13;
combined total of two types of revenue: (1) 80 percent in the case of prefectures, and 75&#13;
percent in municipalities of the sum of the yields of all regular local taxes, assuming that&#13;
each is levied at the uniform rate or standard rate prescribed in the local tax law, and (2)&#13;
the sum of revenues from local transfer taxes. This is expressed in the following equation:&#13;
&#13;
(5)              Ci = G (Bij* tj + LTTi&#13;
                                )&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Where G is 0.75 (for a municipality) and 0.80 (for a prefecture), Bij is ith region's&#13;
jth tax base, tj is the standard tax rate on the jth tax base, and LTTi is revenue from the&#13;
local transfer tax. There are two reason for adopting such prescribed percentages. First,&#13;
it is impossible to measure completely the basic financial needs of all local governments&#13;
with a uniform formula. Second, it is necessary to retain incentives for local governments&#13;
to collect their own taxes. At the same time, all revenues allotted from the local transfer&#13;
tax are included, mainly because it is collected by the national government and has no&#13;
relation to the tax collection effort at the local level.&#13;
        The funds available for transfer calculated in advance, however, do not necessarily&#13;
cover the sum of the entitlement--that is, the aggregate amount of the deficiencies of local&#13;
governments with basic financial needs that exceed their basic revenues. The method&#13;
currently used is either to increase the size of the fund or to adjust the size of the&#13;
entitlement proportionally, according to the size of the fund. First, some special measure&#13;
has been taken every year without changing the tax-sharing ratio to increase the size of the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   Taxes and Transfers in Japan's Local Public Finances 27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
pool.    These special measures, which will be explained later from an historical&#13;
perspective, can be divided into following five types:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Borrowing from a special account of the Fund Management Board of the MoF&#13;
Carrying forward local allocation tax&#13;
Cancellation of a local allocation tax cut&#13;
Transfer of a provisional local grant&#13;
Special addition/reduction of the local allocation tax.&#13;
&#13;
        In addition to the above-mentioned special measure, final adjustment is necessary&#13;
to adjust the size of the entitlement proportionally, according to the size of the fund, by&#13;
using an adjustment coefficient. The actual amount of ordinary allocation tax granted to a&#13;
local government is calculated according to following formula:&#13;
&#13;
(6)            LATi= (Ni­ Ci) ­ _Ni&#13;
&#13;
        Where LATidenotes local allocation tax to ith region, Ni is the basic financial needs&#13;
of ith region, Ci is the basic financial capacity of ith region, and _ is the adjustment&#13;
coefficient.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6090939">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/05/6090939/taxes-transfers-japan&#146;s-local-public-finances
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/05/6090939/taxes-transfers-japan&#146;s-local-public-finances</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/05/6090939/taxes-transfers-japan&#146;s-local-public-finances</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/07/25/000011823_20050725151631/Rendered/INDEX/330430JP0wbi37171.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/07/25/000011823_20050725151631/Rendered/PDF/330430JP0wbi37171.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2001-05-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2005-07-25T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Taxes and transfers in Japan&#146;s local public finances
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            A strong inter-regional equity bias has
            been a distinctive feature of the Japanese local public
            finance system. This paper shows that substantial
            equalization of revenues per capita is achieved via
            transfers from the central government and that, over time,
            this appears to have substantially improved the regional
            distribution of income : the Gini coefficient of per capita
            regional income declined from around 0.17 in 1950 to 0.10 in
            1990. Now that considerable regional equality has been
            achieved, a greater concern for the exercise of local
            preferences is being voices. This paper was prepared for a
            project on Local Government Development in Japan. The
            project was organized by the World Bank Institute (WBI)
            under the auspices of the Program for the Study of Japanese
            Development Management Experience financed by the Policy and
            Human Resources Development Trust Fund of the Government of
            Japan. The principal objectives of this Program are to
            conduct studies on Japanese and East Asian development
            management experience and to disseminate the lessons of this
            experience to developing and transition economies.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Taxes and transfers in Japan&#146;s local public finances
        </docna>
        <display_title>Taxes and transfers in Japan&#146;s
            local public finances</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2001/05/6090939/taxes-transfers-japan&#146;s-local-public-finances</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <count>Japan</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Mochida, Nobuki</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000011823_20050725151631</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Asia!$!80460</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>WBI Working paper series</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accountability, accounting, administrative
            functions, assets, banking system, bond issues, bonds,
            bureaucracy, central government, debt, Debt service,
            decision-making authority, discretionary powers,
            distribution of income, districts, economic growth,
            equalization, expenditure assignments, expenditure
            responsibilities, federal states, financial capacities,
            financial capacity, financial difficulties, financial
            resources, Fiscal, fiscal capacity, fiscal decentralization,
            fiscal deficit, fiscal equalization, fiscal resources,
            fiscal responsibility, fiscal year, Government Finance,
            Human Resources, Human Resources Development, institutional
            mechanisms, intergovernmental fiscal relations,
            intergovernmental relations, intergovernmental system,
            intergovernmental transfer, intergovernmental transfers,
            Legal Framework, legislation, levels of government,
            lobbying, local accountability, local authorities, local
            authority, Local Autonomy, Local Finance, Local Government,
            local government spending, local governments, local public
            finance, local revenue, local revenue sources, local
            spending, Local Tax, local taxes, market value, metropolitan
            areas, ministers, Ministry of Finance, municipalities,
            national accounts, national budget, national level, national
            policy, national taxes, politicians, prefectures, property
            tax base, public expenditure, public finance, Public Finance
            Law, public finance system, Public Finances, public goods,
            public services, public spending, public welfare, revenue
            adequacy, revenue sources, social education, social welfare,
            subnational government, Tax, tax administration, tax burden,
            tax capacity, Tax Law, tax rate, tax rates, tax reform, tax
            revenue, tax revenues, Tax System, taxation, transition
            economies, transparency, value added taxes
        </keywd>
        <owner>Office of the Vice President (WBIVP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>33043</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Compliance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Self Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxpayer Registry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxpayer Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization and Subnational Regional Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Equalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Federalism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inter-Governmental Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking and Finance Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipal Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax and Revenue Policy and Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Laws and Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inter-governmental Fiscal Relations</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Japan</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>