<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                           33025&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Post-Conflliict Recovery&#13;
iin Uganda&#13;
&#13;
Frank Warnock and Patrick Conway&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1999&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank enjoys copyright under protocol 2 of the Universal Copyright Convention. This material&#13;
may nonetheless be copied for research, educational, or scholarly purposes only in the member&#13;
countries of The World Bank. Material in this series is subject to revision. The findings, interpretations,&#13;
and conclusions expressed in this document are entirely those of the author(s) and should not be&#13;
attributed in any manner to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or the members of its Board&#13;
of Executive Directors or the countries they represent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Posttt-Conffflliicttt Recoverrry iin Uganda&#13;
Frank Warnock and Patrick Conway&#13;
&#13;
1999. 34 pages. Stock No. 37152&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                         Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Parrrttt A::: Posttt-Conffflliicttt Recoverrry iin Uganda,,, 1987 .......................................................................................................................................................................................................................................1&#13;
&#13;
  Background..................................................................................................................................................................1&#13;
&#13;
  Pre-Independence Economy ..................................................................................................................................2&#13;
&#13;
  Political and Economic History: Independence Through 1985........................................................................3&#13;
&#13;
  The First Year of Museveni's Regime: 1986............................................................................................................4&#13;
&#13;
  The Current Political and Economic Situation: January 1987.............................................................................6&#13;
&#13;
  Policy Decision............................................................................................................................................................8&#13;
&#13;
  Bibliography.................................................................................................................................................................8&#13;
&#13;
  Sources.........................................................................................................................................................................8&#13;
&#13;
  Appendix...................................................................................................................................................................10&#13;
&#13;
Parrrttt B::: Posttt-Conffflliicttt Recoverrry iin Uganda,,, 1992 ....................................................................................................................................................................................................................................15&#13;
&#13;
  Overview of Policies and Aggregate Performance: Fiscal 1987­88 to 1990­91.......................................15&#13;
&#13;
  International Support for the Reform Program....................................................................................................17&#13;
&#13;
  Government Budgetary Policy................................................................................................................................17&#13;
&#13;
  Financial Sector Development ...............................................................................................................................18&#13;
&#13;
  Foreign Exchange Availability .................................................................................................................................18&#13;
&#13;
  Agricultural Sector Performance............................................................................................................................19&#13;
&#13;
  Manufacturing and Service Sector Performance................................................................................................20&#13;
&#13;
  The Current Situation: June 1992..........................................................................................................................20&#13;
&#13;
  Policy Dilemma ..........................................................................................................................................................21&#13;
&#13;
  Bibliography...............................................................................................................................................................21&#13;
&#13;
  Sources.......................................................................................................................................................................21&#13;
&#13;
  Appendix B................................................................................................................................................................22&#13;
&#13;
Postttscrrriipttt::: Posttt-Conffflliicttt Recoverrry iin Uganda,,, 1995 ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................29&#13;
&#13;
Tablles and Charrrttts&#13;
&#13;
Table A1. Selected Economic Indicators, 1965­86.............................................................................................10&#13;
&#13;
Table A2. Selected Social Indicators, 1960­85.....................................................................................................10&#13;
&#13;
Table A3. Central Government Operations, Selected Years................................................................................11&#13;
&#13;
Table A4. Industrial Origin of Gross Domestic Product at Factor Cost, 1960­86. ..........................................11&#13;
&#13;
Table A5. Industrial Origin of Gross Domestic Product at Factor Cost, 1965 and 1986. ..............................12&#13;
&#13;
Table A6. Production and Trade, 1960­86. ...........................................................................................................12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Tablles and Charrrttts (contttiinued)&#13;
&#13;
Table A7. Major Trading Partners, 1960­86. ...........................................................................................................13&#13;
&#13;
Table A8. Exchange Rates, 1960­86. .......................................................................................................................13&#13;
&#13;
Chart A1. Ugandan Coffee, 1965­86.......................................................................................................................14&#13;
&#13;
Table B1. GDP by Sector at Constant 1991 Prices, Fiscal 1985­91. ..................................................................22&#13;
&#13;
Table B2. GDP by Sector at Constant 1991 Prices, FY 1985­91.........................................................................22&#13;
&#13;
Table B3: Contributions to Real GDP Growth by Expenditure, Fiscal 1985­91 ...............................................23&#13;
&#13;
Table B4. GDP by Expenditure at Constant 1991 Prices.......................................................................................23&#13;
&#13;
Table B5. GDP by Expenditure at Constant 1991 Prices.......................................................................................24&#13;
&#13;
Table B6. Production of Principal Commodities, 1986­92 ..................................................................................24&#13;
&#13;
Table B7. Exports of Cash Crops, 1986­92 ............................................................................................................25&#13;
&#13;
Table B8. Balance of Payments, FY 1985­91...........................................................................................................25&#13;
&#13;
Table B9. Exchange Rates, FY 1985­91....................................................................................................................26&#13;
&#13;
Table B10. Financial Indicators, FY 1986­91............................................................................................................26&#13;
&#13;
Table B11. Central Government Operations, FY 1985­91. ..................................................................................27&#13;
&#13;
Table B12. Destination of Central Government Expenditure................................................................................27&#13;
&#13;
Chart B1. Price of Ugandan coffee, 1965­92. ........................................................................................................28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                        Part A:::&#13;
                               Post-Conflliict Recovery iin Uganda,,, 1987&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Francis Unyofu sat back in his office chair and stared at the dilapidated ceiling. He had&#13;
 not thought life in the government would be quite like this. But fifteen years of political and&#13;
 economic chaos could not be erased in just one year. And there were certainly higher pri-&#13;
 orities than renovating this government office. At least, there was peace now--well, in most&#13;
 parts of the country--so Uganda could try to return to some form of normalcy.&#13;
&#13;
       At independence in October 1962, there was little indication that Uganda was headed&#13;
 for such privations. Independence came without a struggle: the British set a timetable for their&#13;
 withdrawal and stuck to it. It was Ugandans, not Europeans, who now grew the cotton and&#13;
 coffee, bringing a relatively high living standard, financing the education of their children, and&#13;
 raising expectations for the future. There was an impressive number of educated and pros-&#13;
 perous middle-class professionals, the prestigious national Makere University, and a gleaming&#13;
 new teaching hospital at Mulago. At independence, Uganda looked optimistically to the fu-&#13;
 ture. Now, twenty-five years later, it is just looking to rebuild.&#13;
&#13;
       It is January 1987, one year after Yoweri Museveni led the National Resistance Army (NRA)&#13;
 to power. The past year was spent bringing an inclusive coalition together and debating the&#13;
 country's economic and political future. These have been exciting times in the capital, Kam-&#13;
 pala. But the time for debate is past. The people are getting edgy: long queues exist for con-&#13;
 sumer goods, unemployment is so high that it is not even counted, and many factories are&#13;
 not operating. Yes, the time for debate is past. It is now time for a concrete economic pro-&#13;
 posal, and it is up to Francis Unyofu as advisor to the new finance minister, Dr. Crispus Ki-&#13;
 yonga, to draw it up. Dr. Kiyonga was quite clear in his orders to Francis: devise a strategy to&#13;
 increase economic activity while maintaining macroeconomic stability.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Backgrrround&#13;
&#13;
       Uganda is blessed with a pleasant climate and excellent growing conditions. Situated at&#13;
 the equator, rain is much more regular than in other African countries; only in the northern&#13;
 lowlands is the climate hot, dry, and less suitable for cultivation. About the size of Ghana&#13;
 (197,000 square kilometers), Uganda is surrounded by Kenya, Sudan, the former Zaire, Tan-&#13;
 zania, and Rwanda and, therefore, landlocked. The nearest seaport is in Mombasa, Kenya,&#13;
 1,300 kilometers by rail from Kampala. Uganda is also overwhelmingly rural: government esti-&#13;
 mates from 1986 show that, of its 15.1 million inhabitants, only 458,000 live in Kampala. Jinja,&#13;
 the next largest city, has only 45,000 inhabitants.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Although Uganda has twenty-eight tribal groups, the major ethnic division occurs be-&#13;
 tween the mainly pastoral Nilotic tribes of the north, such as the Acholi and the Lango, and&#13;
 the mainly agricultural Bantu tribes of the south, the largest being the Baganda. Historically, the&#13;
 southern Bantu tribes have been less warlike and aggressive than the northern Nilotes. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This is the first part of a three-part case created by Frank Warnock and Patrick Conway of the Univer-&#13;
sity of North Carolina at Chapel Hill on the subject of Ugandan economic growth. Thanks to Philip&#13;
English and Jorge Araujo for useful comments on its content.&#13;
&#13;
                                                             1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                        Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
British capitalized on this distinction by recruiting its security forces from the northern tribes.&#13;
This initiated a military domination of the south by the north, which lasted from before inde-&#13;
pendence until 1986, when the predominately Bantu-based NRA seized power.&#13;
&#13;
     In addition to the traditional tribal divisions, powerful religious divisions exist. Two-thirds&#13;
of the population is Christian, evenly split between Roman Catholics and Protestants, whereas&#13;
15 percent is Muslim. Membership of the religious communities often cuts across tribal divi-&#13;
sions. For example, at independence the main political parties included the Kabaka Yekka&#13;
(KY), which was mainly Protestant and Bagandan; the United People's Congress (UPC), which&#13;
was Protestant but non-Bagandan; and the Democratic (DP), which was Bagandan and mainly&#13;
Roman Catholic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Prrre-IIndependence Economy&#13;
&#13;
     At independence and throughout the 1960s, Uganda had one of the most vigorous and&#13;
promising economies in Sub-Saharan Africa.1 It relied overwhelmingly on agriculture, which&#13;
accounted for almost two-thirds of gross domestic product (GDP) and 90 percent of ex-&#13;
ports in 1960. The manufacturing sector, although small, was growing and supplied the&#13;
economy with basic inputs and consumer goods. The transportation system, which included&#13;
an effective network of roads, railways, and port and air transport, was widely regarded as&#13;
one of the best in Sub-Saharan Africa. Railroads and paved roads connected Uganda with&#13;
the seaport of Mombasa. Airports linked the more important Ugandan towns with other East&#13;
African territories (Kenya and Tanganyika). Entebbe boasted a modern international airport,&#13;
and steamer services ran on the lakes and the River Nile. In addition, Uganda had a large sub-&#13;
sistence sector. This nonmonetized sector comprised almost one-third of the country's eco-&#13;
nomic activity, and much of the population remained outside the formal economy.&#13;
&#13;
     Uganda's two biggest cash crops, cotton and coffee, made up 76 percent of its ex-&#13;
ports. Some of the world's best quality tea was grown on a few large Asian-owned estates.&#13;
Valuable minerals, notably copper, had been discovered, and water power resources were&#13;
substantial. Export earnings not only financed the country's import requirements but also re-&#13;
sulted in a current account surplus.&#13;
&#13;
     Prior to independence, the major destinations of Ugandan exports included India (20&#13;
percent of total exports, mostly cotton), Britain (16 percent, mainly cotton and coffee), the&#13;
United States (15 percent, all coffee), and Kenya (12 percent, sugar and a variety of prod-&#13;
ucts). Ugandan imports were primarily manufactures from the United Kingdom (19 percent of&#13;
total imports) and Japan (9 percent). Imports from Kenya were also significant, representing&#13;
24 percent of total imports.&#13;
&#13;
     At independence, Uganda was a member of the East African Currency Board along with&#13;
Kenya and Tanganyika. The currency board was the sole issuer of notes and coins, and the&#13;
East African shilling was at par with the United Kingdom shilling. Inflationary financing of fiscal&#13;
deficits was not an option and pre-independence fiscal deficits were correspondingly small,&#13;
amounting to 0.1 percent of GDP in 1960.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1All tables supporting the data discussed in this text are in the appendix of part A. Much of the data is presented&#13;
for years representing the various regimes since 1960: pre-independence (1960), Obote I (1965), Amin (1971&#13;
and 1977), Obote II (1981), and Museveni (1986).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                      Part A: 1987&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Uganda's relative affluence had been translated into strong governmental social welfare&#13;
services. The country's health sector had developed into one of Africa's most extensive and&#13;
had pioneered health and nutrition programs for low-income citizens. Primary and secondary&#13;
education was characterized by a pupil-teacher ratio that was 25 percent below the African&#13;
average in 1960.&#13;
&#13;
      Although prospects were bright at independence, some seeds of economic misman-&#13;
agement had already been planted. The colonial government strictly regulated the buying&#13;
and selling of major cash crops through marketing boards. At first, the marketing boards were&#13;
set up as a way to unify sales to Allied wartime supply agencies and provide some insurance&#13;
to growers against fluctuating prices. Later, however, as coffee and cotton prices rose on the&#13;
world markets, the marketing boards did not raise the prices they paid to the farmers. As&#13;
substantial surplus funds accumulated, considerable transfers were made to the central gov-&#13;
ernment for direct budget support. Steep export taxes were also imposed, particularly on&#13;
cotton. The producers of cash crops, thus, began to finance government expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Polliitttiicall and Economiic Hiistttorrry::: IIndependence Thrrrough 1985&#13;
&#13;
      When Uganda became independent on October 9, 1962, Dr. Milton Obote, a Protestant&#13;
northerner of the Lango tribe, was the first prime minister. Obote packed his government and&#13;
army with ethnic and religious compatriots. Dissent from the southern Bantu tribes was bru-&#13;
tally repressed, and, in March 1968, Obote suspended the constitution and assumed all&#13;
powers of government.&#13;
&#13;
      The economy did relatively well in the 1960s, as real GDP growth averaged 4.8 percent&#13;
per year from 1965 to 1970. Cash crop production was quite strong, with 1965 coffee and&#13;
cotton production at 218,000 tons and 243,000 tons, respectively. Copper production was&#13;
at a historical high in the late 1960s at more than 16,000 tons per year. The manufacturing&#13;
sector was small but growing, reaching 6 percent of GDP by 1965 and 7.3 percent by 1971.&#13;
&#13;
      In 1966 the Bank of Uganda became the Central Bank. It promptly withdrew from the East&#13;
African Currency Board and issued a new currency, the Ugandan shilling, which remained at&#13;
par with the UK shilling until 1973.2 The bank also took over exchange control and the func-&#13;
tion of controlling commercial banks through credit control. In this way, the government&#13;
could decide who would get foreign exchange and who had access to bank credit. Central&#13;
government borrowing to finance fiscal deficits began increasingly to crowd out private&#13;
borrowing, and the annual rate of growth of domestic credit quickly increased from nearly&#13;
zero in the early 1960s to more than 20 percent by 1967.&#13;
&#13;
      In 1971 General Idi Amin, a member of a northern Nilotic tribe called the Kakwa, staged a&#13;
successful coup and went on to brutalize the country with a surge of tribal massacres and&#13;
political killings. Amin carried out murderous acts in particular on Obote's Lango tribe and&#13;
their neighbors the Acholi and maintained a constant persecution of Christians. After redis-&#13;
covering his Islamic heritage in an effort to secure aid from Libya and Saudi Arabia, Amin&#13;
promptly reduced Uganda's Muslim population by expelling almost all of Uganda's 70,000&#13;
Asians of Indian and Pakistani decent. The Asians, who had been active in agribusiness,&#13;
manufacturing, and commerce, were forced to leave behind their businesses and belong-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2 In following references to currency, "shilling" and "USh" refer to the Ugandan shilling, unless otherwise specified.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                          Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ings. But they could have faced a worse fate: in the eight years under Amin's rule, an esti-&#13;
mated 300,000 people were killed.&#13;
&#13;
     Uganda's once vibrant economy collapsed during Amin's reign. Real GDP growth aver-&#13;
aged 0.2 percent per year in the first half of the 1970s. The second half was worse as real&#13;
GDP fell an average of 3.5 percent per year from 1976 to 1980, while per capita incomes fell&#13;
to among the lowest levels in the world.&#13;
&#13;
     Cash crop production suffered during the Amin regime. By 1977 cotton production had&#13;
fallen to 14,000 tons, just 6 percent of the 1965 level. Although India was once the single&#13;
largest destination for Ugandan products, the expulsion of Asians and reduction of cotton&#13;
production effectively reduced exports to India to nil. Asians managed many of the tea es-&#13;
tates, so tea production all but ceased as well. Coffee production also fell, but not nearly as&#13;
much, as Ugandan smallholders were still able to produce even with political unrest. Copper&#13;
production in 1977 was just 15 percent of its 1971 level, and by 1979 copper production&#13;
ceased. The manufacturing sector began to contract.&#13;
&#13;
     Uganda registered a substantial budget deficit for nearly every year in the 1970s as mili-&#13;
tary expenditures grew substantially. Deficits equivalent to more than 50 percent of current&#13;
revenues were not unusual: in 1974 the deficit reached 134 percent. Only in the mid-1970s,&#13;
when the price of coffee skyrocketed, were the deficits relatively small. Even then, the gov-&#13;
ernment was crowding out private investment: by the mid-1970s, claims on the central gov-&#13;
ernment (government borrowing) were consistently near 70 percent of domestic credit. Pri-&#13;
vate savings and investment were reduced to about 6 percent of GDP, well below the&#13;
1960s ratio of 15 percent.&#13;
&#13;
     Amin was forced to flee the country in 1979, and Milton Obote returned to power in&#13;
1980 in an election that was widely regarded as rigged. Obote's new army conducted sav-&#13;
age acts of reprisal against tribes that had been loyal to Amin. For the Baganda, persecuted in&#13;
Obote's first reign, it was more of the same. By 1981 guerrilla groups were forming in the&#13;
bush. The largest was Yoweri Museveni's National Resistance Movement, which drew its sup-&#13;
port from the southern Bantu tribes. After five years of civil war, Obote was overthrown for a&#13;
second time in July of 1985 by a group led by General Tito Okello (an Acholi). In January&#13;
1986, Museveni seized power. Okello's army retreated to the north, looting along the way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Fiirrrsttt Yearrr offf Musevenii'''s Regiime::: 1986&#13;
&#13;
     Yoweri Museveni came to power in January 1986 in a devastated Uganda. The country&#13;
had suffered dictatorship, tribal and regionally based violence, army lawlessness, and brutal&#13;
human rights abuses for most of its twenty-three years as an independent nation. Life expec-&#13;
tancy, measured as less than fifty years, was one of the worst in the world. Real government&#13;
spending on health programs and education fell to 27 percent and 9 percent, respectively,&#13;
compared with their average levels in the 1970s.&#13;
&#13;
     Uganda was in economic shambles. Its roads, railways, hospitals, and schools were de-&#13;
stroyed. Real per capita GDP, at $230, was 60 percent of its level in 1971.3 Its average annual&#13;
rate of growth from 1965 to 1985 was -2.6 percent, the lowest in the world for that period.&#13;
The only sector that grew substantially in this period was the government. The nonmonetary&#13;
sector (primarily agriculture) remained resilient throughout the turmoil and, in 1986, made up&#13;
&#13;
3 In the following references to currency, the word "dollar" and the symbol "$" refer to U.S. dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            Part A: 1987&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
40 percent of overall production. Indeed, most Ugandans relied on this subsistence sector&#13;
for the basic means of their survival.&#13;
&#13;
     Coffee, which is grown mainly by smallholders in Uganda, had fared much better as a&#13;
sector during the fifteen years of unrest than had the largely estate-grown cotton and tea&#13;
sectors. In 1986 coffee production was at 160,000 tons or 73 percent of its 1965 level,&#13;
while cotton production plummeted to only 7 percent of its 1965 level. The sugar industry,&#13;
which had once produced enough to satisfy domestic demand and export to nearby coun-&#13;
tries, collapsed in the early 1980s. With the closing of the Kilembe copper mine in 1977,&#13;
copper production virtually ceased.&#13;
&#13;
     The industrial sector had suffered greatly from the country's unrest and economic prob-&#13;
lems. After years of neglect and destruction, Uganda's factories were operating far below&#13;
capacity: only ten of eighty-three establishments surveyed by the Ministry of Planning and&#13;
Economic Development in 1985 were operating at more than 30 percent of capacity,&#13;
whereas twenty-nine recorded no output at all. Estimates of capital-labor ratios in the mid-&#13;
1980s indicate that Uganda's average capital-labor ratio was only 10 percent that of Tanzania&#13;
and 7 percent that of Kenya.&#13;
&#13;
     The lack of foreign exchange to buy spare parts and lack of functioning infrastructure pre-&#13;
sented serious obstacles to industrial growth. One need only look at the dilapidated road&#13;
system in and around Jinja, the nation's former industrial hub to understand the formidable&#13;
task facing manufacturers: even if they secured the foreign exchange needed to buy im-&#13;
ported inputs, transporting their goods was nearly impossible.&#13;
&#13;
     The banking sector had contracted during fifteen years of negative economic growth. In&#13;
1970 Uganda had 290 commercial bank branches. By 1987 only eighty-four remained, of&#13;
which fifty-four were branches operated by government-owned banks. And why would a&#13;
Ugandan want to deposit money at a bank? With inflation at more than 200 percent and Cen-&#13;
tral Bank­controlled interest rates around 20 percent, it was a losing proposition. Not surpris-&#13;
ingly, Uganda's gross domestic saving and investment each represented less than 10 percent of&#13;
GDP, and domestic consumption was consistently more than 100 percent of GDP.&#13;
&#13;
     The Ugandan shilling had not fared well. Fixed at 7 shillings to the dollar for most of its&#13;
existence, it was repeatedly devalued during Obote's second regime. At first, in mid-1981,&#13;
Obote let the shilling float: it immediately fell to 4 percent of its previous value before settling&#13;
at a rate of 78 per dollar. A shortage of foreign exchange gave rise to the kibanda (informal&#13;
and illegal) market. By the end of 1985, the official rate was 1,400 shillings to the dollar,&#13;
whereas the kibanda rate was almost three times higher at 4,000, indicating that even at&#13;
1,400 the official rate was vastly overvalued. Once at par with the Kenyan shilling, the Ugan-&#13;
dan shilling had become virtually worthless: on the streets of Kampala, one Kenyan shilling&#13;
could fetch 500 Ugandan shillings.&#13;
&#13;
     Museveni faced a difficult transformation from guerrilla leader to the leader of a nation. He&#13;
could have pursued the route of previous Ugandan coups and massacred his defeated oppo-&#13;
nents, looting along the way, but instead moved to discipline his forces. Drake Ssekeba, the&#13;
editor of The Star, an independent Ugandan newspaper, noted this: "Every time there is a coup&#13;
in Uganda there is looting. When Museveni and his men came, there was no looting. That was&#13;
one of the earliest signs that Museveni was different from those who came before him."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                         Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     At his installation Museveni voiced his concern for human rights: "The people of Uganda&#13;
should only die from natural causes, which are not under our control." To be sure, he contin-&#13;
ued to fight insurgent groups, mostly in the north, but offered total amnesty to those who&#13;
surrendered their weapons.&#13;
&#13;
     In forming a government, Museveni chose a broad, national front regime: anyone who&#13;
wanted to join his party was to be accepted, even if they were enemies the day before. The&#13;
coalition government was inclusive and comprised leaders from many of the movements that&#13;
formed in opposition to Milton Obote.&#13;
&#13;
     Peace finally came to most of Uganda. The slaughter of political dissidents and of families&#13;
and children stopped after his National Resistance Army took power. Yet, by late 1986 con-&#13;
cern grew that the Museveni government was failing to provide the direction or policies&#13;
needed to rebuild the country's devastated economy and improve the plight of the average&#13;
Ugandan. The skills needed to conduct a successful guerrilla war were not necessarily the&#13;
same as those needed to steer the country toward recovery.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Currrrrrenttt Polliitttiicall and Economiic Siitttuatttiion::: Januarrry 1987&#13;
&#13;
     The first year of the Museveni regime was marked by a tentativeness in governance that&#13;
led, according to some, to serious misjudgments in economic policy. A senior Western fi-&#13;
nancial expert noted that "agriculture is heavily, heavily discriminated against in favor of the&#13;
urban consumers, traders, and importers." Several economic decisions have benefited urban&#13;
consumers with a calamitous effect on Uganda's fiscal condition.&#13;
&#13;
     The new economic strategy announced in August 1986 by the finance minister, Mr. Pon-&#13;
siano Mulema, a professor of economics, was a disaster. Its centerpiece was a huge revalua-&#13;
tion of the Ugandan shilling. Since May 1986, two legal exchange rates had existed: official&#13;
transactions were carried out at a rate of 1,400 shillings to the dollar and all other transactions&#13;
at a legal market rate of about 5,000 shillings to the dollar. Transactions also occurred in the&#13;
informal kibanda market. Mr. Mulema abolished the legal market rate, so all legal transactions&#13;
would be at the 1,400 shilling rate. Every exporter has since vowed to keep his money&#13;
abroad; every would-be importer rushed to get licenses to import at the new, artificially fa-&#13;
vorable rate. The kibanda rate immediately shot up to 8,000 shillings per dollar. In October&#13;
1986, Mulema was replaced by Dr. Crispus Kiyonga, who has a medical background&#13;
&#13;
     Kiyonga has a difficult task. The government's finances are shaky at best. In an attempt to&#13;
enable Ugandan citizens to purchase imported consumer goods, the government fixes their&#13;
prices below world prices. This, of course, puts considerable pressure on the government's&#13;
finances: for example, in July 1986 the government imported $4.8 million worth of sugar to&#13;
sell at subsidized prices. Similarly, government subsidies enable Ugandans to buy petrol for&#13;
about 10 US cents per liter, the lowest price in any country that does not produce oil.&#13;
&#13;
     The subsidies of imported consumer goods put pressure on the government in another&#13;
way: it requires foreign exchange. At independence, exports of cotton, coffee, tea, grain,&#13;
copper, and a few manufactures earned a substantial amount of foreign exchange. Uganda&#13;
now exports only coffee. Export earnings of $400 million per year barely covers the $200&#13;
million debt service payments and imports of oil, sugar, and spare parts for the army.&#13;
&#13;
     With the nonmonetary sector representing almost 40 percent of economic activity, col-&#13;
lection of income taxes has become a formidable problem, forcing the government to turn&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                           Part A: 1987&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
again to the coffee producers. Export taxes on coffee provide more than 50 percent of the&#13;
government's revenue. Moreover, the government controls the marketing of coffee through&#13;
the Uganda Coffee Marketing Board (CMB). The international price of Ugandan coffee has in-&#13;
creased almost 50 percent since its 1980 lows, but it has been the government, not coffee&#13;
growers, that has benefited. CMB periodically increases the prices it pays growers, but in&#13;
practice the currency depreciation wipes out any increased purchasing power: increases in&#13;
official CMB prices consistently bring the price paid to producers back up to 10 percent of&#13;
the world price (computed at the kibanda exchange rate).&#13;
&#13;
    Coffee grows in Uganda, even if it is neglected, but farmers pick the beans only if they&#13;
are paid to do so. Some farmers sidestep CMB by smuggling their coffee into Kenya or&#13;
Rwanda for sale at the average world price of about $1.80 a pound. Bananas, which grow&#13;
with little maintenance on the smallholder coffee estates, give coffee growers another&#13;
choice: they can pick bananas, a stalk of which fetches, in Ugandan shillings, at least seven&#13;
times as much as a pound of coffee.&#13;
&#13;
    Smuggling has become a way of life in Uganda and not only for coffee farmers. Price&#13;
controls on consumer goods, along with the controlled official exchange rate, offer smug-&#13;
glers profitable opportunities. A small-time Ugandan smuggler can buy 20 liters of petrol for&#13;
$2, strap it to his bicycle and cross the border to Kenya or Rwanda and sell it for $20. Back in&#13;
Uganda, he can sell the foreign exchange at the kibanda rate of 16,000 shillings to the dollar,&#13;
reaping a net one-day profit of 288,000 shillings. By comparison, a government minister's&#13;
monthly salary is about 90,000 shillings. The minimum monthly wage is 10,000 shillings, not&#13;
enough to buy a stem of bananas or two pounds of sugar.&#13;
&#13;
    The manufacturing sector is hampered by its own foreign exchange problem: imported&#13;
parts and machinery are required to rehabilitate existing factories, but the foreign exchange to&#13;
purchase them is unavailable. Skilled workers--specifically, engineers and repair peo-&#13;
ple--and people with management experience are greatly needed. Moreover, a substantial&#13;
portion of the manufacturing sector is based on processing agricultural products. The prob-&#13;
lems plaguing the agriculture sector also hamper industrial production.&#13;
&#13;
    Overseas companies seem interested in investing in Uganda but are still quite cautious.&#13;
The memories of the expulsion of the Asian business community hold some companies back.&#13;
The government is trying to attract foreign investment by publicly welcoming it, but in prac-&#13;
tice overseas companies are finding ambivalent attitudes among individual government offi-&#13;
cials, who give different impressions based on their own viewpoints.&#13;
&#13;
    Uganda's relationships with its neighbors are not as smooth as in the past. Political and&#13;
economic strains caused the demise of the East African Community in 1977. Uganda's rela-&#13;
tionship with Kenya deteriorated further in 1986, as each country alleged the other had been&#13;
providing support for opposition groups. In the west and north, the movement of ethnic&#13;
groups across the boundaries with Rwanda, Zaire, and Sudan has been a source of friction.&#13;
Relations with Tanzania have remained good, although its economy is in poor shape as well.&#13;
&#13;
    Ugandans believe in Museveni, but their patience is wearing thin. "Rehabilitation by the&#13;
government is very slow," says the Reverend Wilson Sentongo, waiting for rations of food&#13;
and other supplies. "We do not know what their plan is. They are telling us to tolerate things.&#13;
Museveni has sympathy for us, we know, but the problem is supplies are not here and we&#13;
need help."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                     Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Members of the government and many other Ugandans are deeply divided on which&#13;
course the economy should take. Exchange rate policy and government price controls are&#13;
the two main issues; the August 1986 budget already cut back fiscal spending. The World&#13;
Bank and other donors are pushing strenuously for exchange market reform, but Museveni is&#13;
determined not to let them dictate Ugandan policy. At the same time, Museveni is a pragma-&#13;
tist who wants to do what is best for Uganda.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Polliicy Deciisiion&#13;
&#13;
      A presidential economic council has been set up to coordinate all aspects of national&#13;
economic planning and investment. The council is advisory to the president and includes Dr.&#13;
Kiyonga, the ministers of marketing and commerce, and the governor of the Bank of Uganda.&#13;
Museveni has stressed that he wants economic activity to reattain pre-independence levels.&#13;
As an economic advisor to Dr. Kiyonga, Francis Unyofu must draw up a strategy to increase&#13;
economic activity without compromising macroeconomic stability.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Biiblliiogrrraphy&#13;
&#13;
Barro, Robert and J. W. Lee. "International Measures of Schooling Years and Schooling Quality." Ameri-&#13;
      can Economics Review 86(2): 218­33, 1993.&#13;
&#13;
Economist Intelligence Unit (EIU). Country Profile: Uganda. London, 1988.&#13;
&#13;
------. Country Report: Uganda. London, 1987.&#13;
&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD). The Economic Development of Uganda.&#13;
      Baltimore, Md.: Johns Hopkins Press, 1962.&#13;
&#13;
International Monetary Fund (IMF). International Financial Statistics. Washington, D.C., 1985 and 1995.&#13;
&#13;
------. Direction of Trade Statistics Yearbook. Washington, D.C., various years.&#13;
&#13;
King, Robert G. and Ross Levine. "Capital Fundamentalism, Economic Development, and Economic&#13;
      Growth," Carnegie-Rochester Conference Series on Public Policy, Amsterdam: North-Holland,&#13;
      1994.&#13;
&#13;
Library of Congress, Federal Research Division. Uganda: A Country Study. Washington, D.C., 1992.&#13;
&#13;
Sharer, Robert and Calvin McDonald. "Uganda, 1987­94," in Michael T. Hadjimichael and others, Ad-&#13;
      justment for Growth: The African Experience. Washington, D.C.: International Monetary Fund, 1996.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. World Development Report. Washington, D.C., various years.&#13;
&#13;
------. Uganda: The Challenge of Growth and Poverty Reduction. Washington, D.C., 1996.&#13;
&#13;
------. Uganda: Growing Out of Poverty. Washington, D.C., 1993.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sourrrces&#13;
&#13;
      Francis Unyofu is a creation of the authors, but the other details of Ugandan history are factual.&#13;
Rather than interrupt the narrative, we credit here those sources from which substantial information has&#13;
been drawn. More detailed citations are available, when needed, from the authors.&#13;
&#13;
      "Background" was drawn from Library of Congress (1992).&#13;
&#13;
      "Pre-Independence Economy" was drawn from IBRD (1962).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               Part A: 1987&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     "Political and Economic History: Independence Through 1985" was drawn mainly from EIU quar-&#13;
terly Country Reports and annual Country Profiles.&#13;
&#13;
     "The First Year of Museveni's Regime: 1986" was drawn from EIU (1988), Library of Congress&#13;
(1992) and various articles that appeared in The New York Times, The Economist, and The Financial&#13;
Times, with precise citations available from the authors.&#13;
&#13;
     "The Current Political and Economic Situation: January 1987" was drawn from EIU (1988) and vari-&#13;
ous articles that appeared in The New York Times, The Economist, and The Financial Times.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                         Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Appendiix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table A1. Selected Economic Indicators, 1965­86.&#13;
(percent)&#13;
&#13;
Indicator                                  1965­70           1971­75            1976­80        1981­86&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Real GDP growth                                4.8               0.2               ­3.5           3.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Real per capita GDP growth                     2.5              ­2.5               ­6.0           1.6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Gross domestic investment                     14.4              10.9                6.0           7.2&#13;
   (percent of GDP)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Gross domestic savings                        16.0              11.1                6.0           4.6&#13;
   (percent of GDP)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Inflation                                      4                17                 59a           78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
a. Average annual inflation rate for 1976 to 1978.&#13;
Sources: Sharer and others (1996); IMF (1985 and 1995).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table A2. Selected Social Indicators, 1960­85.&#13;
&#13;
Indicator                                 1960            1970               1980               1985&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Pupil teacher ratio                    30.7               33.5                33.6              34.5&#13;
(primary)&#13;
                                       (42.6)             (43.1)             (41.2)             (39.2)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Drop-out rate                                             22.4                24.3              24.3&#13;
                                                          (43.4)             (36.6)             (37.5)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Adult illiteracy                       65                 60                  52                57&#13;
                                       (85)               (70)               (63)               (48)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Population per physician               15.0                 9.2               26.8              21.9&#13;
(thousands)&#13;
                                       (39.4)             (31.8)             (22.9)             (23.8)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Life expectancy                        44                 50                  54                48&#13;
                                       (38)               (45)               (47)               (51)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sources: Barro and Lee (1993) data set; World Bank, World Development Report (various years).&#13;
Note: Averages for Africa in parentheses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 Part A: Appendix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table A3. Central Government Operations, Selected Years.&#13;
&#13;
                                              1960            1971­75     1976­80      1981­86&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Central government&#13;
(percent of GDP)&#13;
  Revenue                                     12.9             10.0          8.3         5.3&#13;
  Grants                                        1.1             0.1          0.1         0.4&#13;
  Expenditure                                 13.9             17.2         10.4         8.2&#13;
  Deficit (-)                                 -0.1             -7.2         -2.0        -2.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Claims on central government                  n/a              63.9         69.2        53.7&#13;
(percent of domestic credit)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Domestic credit                               n/a              29.3         32.9        65.3&#13;
(annual growth rate)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sources: IMF (1995); IBRD (1962).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table A4. Industrial Origin of Gross Domestic Product at Factor Cost, 1960­86.&#13;
(percent of real GDP)&#13;
&#13;
                                          1960          1965     1971    1977     1981    1986&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture                               63.8          53.2     51.1    54.4     55.1    63&#13;
Manufacturing                               4             6       7.3     6.4      3.9     3.3&#13;
Construction                                2.6           1.9     1.7     1.1      0.6     2.9&#13;
Transport, communications,&#13;
  and commerce                            12.1          17       16.8    12.3     10.6    17.1&#13;
Government                                  4.3           6       6.9    10       14       6.5&#13;
Other monetary                            13.2          15.9     16.2    15.8     15.8     7.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Nonmonetary                               27.2          32.9     30.0    30       39.8    39.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sources: IBRD (1962), EIU Country Profiles (various issues).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                     Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table A5. Industrial Origin of Gross Domestic Product at Factor Cost, 1965 and 1986.&#13;
(at 1966 prices)&#13;
&#13;
                                                   1965                              1986&#13;
&#13;
                                      millions of USh                   millions of USh&#13;
                                                           percent                         percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture                          3,077                   53.2           3,968           55.1&#13;
Mining and quarrying                         111              1.9                7            0.1&#13;
Manufacturing                                373              6.4             314             4.4&#13;
Electricity, gas, and water                   60              1.0              95             1.3&#13;
Construction                                 107              1.8              54             0.8&#13;
Transport, communications,&#13;
  and commerce                               982             17.0             702             9.8&#13;
Government                                   345              6.0             932           13.0&#13;
Other services                               732             12.6           1,126           15.6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDP                                        5,787            100.0           7,196           100.0&#13;
 (o/w nonmonetary)                         1,904             32.9           2,867           39.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Average annual growth rate of         1.0%&#13;
real GDP, 1965­86:&#13;
&#13;
Sources: Quarterly Economic Report and Country Profile (EIU).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table A6. Production and Trade, 1960­86.&#13;
&#13;
                                        1960         1965        1971    1977         1981       1986&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Coffee&#13;
  Production (thousands of tons)         113         218          191     156          128       160&#13;
  Percent of total exports                40.8         42.0       50.7     92.9        98.0       96.6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Cotton&#13;
 Production (thousands of tons)          210         243          75       14           4         18&#13;
 Percent of total exports                 35.9         23.1       17.6       2.6        0.9        1.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Copper&#13;
 Production (tons)                   14,515       16,870       16,900   2,500           nil       nil&#13;
 Percent of total exports                  8.9         11.0        8.3       0.0        0.0        0.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sugar (percent of exports)                 3.6          1.2        1.0       0.0        0.0        0.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tea (percent of exports)                   3.5          3.3        4.7       2.1        0.1        0.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total Exports (percent of GDP)            27.4          3.3        1.8       1.0        4.6       10.3&#13;
Total Imports (percent of GDP)            17.1         25.7       17.2       4.1        nil       16.7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sources: IBRD (1962); World Bank (1993); IMF (1995).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  Part A: Appendix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table A7. Major Trading Partners, 1960­86.&#13;
&#13;
                                             1960            1971          1977     1981     1986&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Exports (percent of total)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          United Kingdom                      16.2            21.8         17.5     13.7     15.6&#13;
          United States                       15.3            20.1         37.8     40.2     29.1&#13;
          Japan                                2.7             9.8          3.2      5.6      3.8&#13;
          India                               20.1             7.4         nil       0.0      0.0&#13;
          Kenya                               12.3             8.7          0.4      0.7      0.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Imports (percent of total)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          United Kingdom                       18.7            24.6          9.1     14.3     13.5&#13;
          United States                        n/a              5.4          0.7      1.9      1.5&#13;
          Japan                                 8.7            10.3          3.2      1.5      5.7&#13;
          India                                 2.2             3.6          2.6      5.3      7.6&#13;
          Kenya                                23.7            21.5         56.6     33.0     37.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: IMF, Direction of Trade Statistics Yearbook, (various years).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table A8. Exchange Rates, 1960­86.&#13;
&#13;
                       Official           Kibanda         Real Effective&#13;
                     (USh/US$)             (USh/US$)      (1987=100)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1960­74                      7&#13;
1977                         8&#13;
1980                         8                                 435&#13;
1981                       85                                  308&#13;
1982                     106                                   107&#13;
1983                     240                                     83&#13;
1984                     520                                     57&#13;
1985                   1,400                4,000                74&#13;
1986                   1,400               12,000                78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sources: Bank of Uganda and International Monetary Fund.&#13;
Note: Official and kibanda rates are end of year. The real effective rate&#13;
is annual average.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                      Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Chart A1. Ugandan Coffee, 1965­86.&#13;
(US dollars/pound)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
$2.50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
$2.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
$1.50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
$1.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
$0.50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
$0.00&#13;
    1965 1966 1967 1968 1969 1970 1971 1972 1973 1974 1975 1976 1977 1978 1979 1980 1981 1982 1983 1984 1985 1986&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                      Part B:::&#13;
                            Post-Conflliict Recovery iin Uganda 1992&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Progress has been made, thought Francis Unyofu. Six years after Yoweri Museveni and his&#13;
National Resistance Movement took power, Uganda has made remarkable strides in over-&#13;
coming as grim a legacy as any African government has known. Improved security has been&#13;
an important factor in allowing the country to rebuild. Economic policy has helped, too. The&#13;
past six years has seen economic growth averaging more than 5 percent per year, as idled&#13;
land and vacant factories were brought back into use. The economy has also achieved lower&#13;
price inflation.&#13;
&#13;
       Now, in 1992, Uganda is at a crossroads. Economic growth is slowing, and inflation is&#13;
beginning to rise. Uganda is highly indebted to foreign lenders. Further increases in capacity&#13;
utilization will be a costly means to grow and cannot represent a strategy for sustained eco-&#13;
nomic growth. Infrastructure remains inadequate in transport and communications. The pre-&#13;
ferred road is clear: public and private investments are needed to continue the reconstruc-&#13;
tion. Some of this can come from abroad, if Uganda's economic prospects appeal to inter-&#13;
national investors, although Uganda is currently seen as a high-risk country. But what about&#13;
Ugandans, Francis thought?&#13;
&#13;
       It is June 1992, and Francis is a department head in the Finance Ministry--now called the&#13;
Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning. The minister, his boss, is recently appointed--Mr.&#13;
Joshua Mayanga-Nkangi, the former minister of planning and economic development, re-&#13;
placed Dr. Kiyonga. His department has been tasked to devise a strategy to increase produc-&#13;
tive investment for the next five years while maintaining fiscal and monetary discipline. The&#13;
minister has asked Francis to direct this effort.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overrrviiew offf Polliiciies and Aggrrregattte Perrrffforrrmance::: Fiiscall 1987­88 ttto 1990­91&#13;
&#13;
       In May 1987 the Museveni government announced its first economic program.4 It had six&#13;
basic components:&#13;
&#13;
       ·     A new Ugandan shilling (USh) went into circulation at a rate of 60 to the dollar.5 This&#13;
             represented a 77 percent reduction in value of the shilling. Old shillings could be&#13;
             converted to new shillings at the rate of 100 to 1, but such conversions were subject&#13;
             to a 30 percent tax.&#13;
&#13;
       ·    The Rehabilitation and Development Plan was inaugurated. This plan was a timetable&#13;
            for government expenditures designed to restore production capacity and rehabili-&#13;
            tate economic and social infrastructure. The plan called for funding of $1.3 billion for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This is the second part of a three-part case created by Frank Warnock and Patrick Conway of the&#13;
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill on the subject of Ugandan economic growth. Thanks to&#13;
Philip English and Jorge Araujo for useful comments on its content.&#13;
4 The Ugandan fiscal year runs from July 1 to June 30.&#13;
5  In the following references, the word "dollar" and the symbol "$" refer to U.S. dollars. The word "shilling" and&#13;
acronym "Ush" refer to the Ugandan shilling, unless otherwise noted.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                     Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           four years, with transport to receive the major share (29 percent), followed by agri-&#13;
           culture (24 percent), industry and tourism (21 percent), social infrastructure (17 per-&#13;
           cent), and mining and energy (7 percent).&#13;
&#13;
     ·     Prices paid to farmers were increased by up to 500 percent as an incentive to revive&#13;
           agricultural production.&#13;
&#13;
     ·     The price of petrol was increased by 50 percent, somewhat closer to its real market&#13;
           value, in an attempt to reduce smuggling and government outlays.&#13;
&#13;
     ·     The salaries of civil servants were doubled in an effort to restore some of their lost&#13;
           purchasing power.&#13;
&#13;
     ·     Under an International Monetary Fund program, the government promised to tighten&#13;
           its budget and reduce inflation by restricting monetary expansion.&#13;
&#13;
     In the first year, insufficient tax revenues along with a falling international price for coffee&#13;
led to a large budget deficit. The government turned to the Bank of Uganda to finance its&#13;
deficit, thus, continuing its inflationary policy of previous years. In July 1988, however, the&#13;
government redoubled its efforts at macroeconomic stabilization. In his fiscal 1988­89&#13;
budget presentation, Finance Minister Crispus Kiyonga announced additional economic re-&#13;
forms:&#13;
&#13;
     ·     The shilling would be devalued by a further 60 percent to USh150 to the dollar.&#13;
&#13;
     ·     Further efforts would be made to reduce the budget deficit.&#13;
&#13;
     ·     Producer prices and public sector wages would be increased.&#13;
&#13;
     Still later, a policy of regular adjustments of the exchange rate to maintain a real effective&#13;
depreciation was introduced.&#13;
&#13;
     In the period under consideration, growth in real GDP exceeded 5 percent on average.&#13;
In the prior fiscal year (fiscal 1986­87), real growth was 3.7 percent a year. In the subse-&#13;
quent four fiscal years the annual growth rate averaged 6.2 percent. In fiscal 1991­92, the&#13;
economic growth rate once again fell to under 4 percent a year.6 Both public and private&#13;
investment increased during the period represented by fiscal 1986­87 to fiscal 1991­92.&#13;
Private investment rose from 8 percent of GDP in fiscal 1985­86 to 10.6 percent on average&#13;
for the period fiscal 1987­88 to 1990­91, but settled back to 9 percent of GDP in fiscal&#13;
1991­92. Public investment, in contrast, rose throughout the period from 3.5 percent of GDP&#13;
in the prior fiscal year to 6.8 percent of GDP in the final year. The period 1980­93 was char-&#13;
acterized by a strong push in primary education and tremendous increases in enrollment in&#13;
that age cohort. Secondary education, however, remained below average for low-income&#13;
countries.&#13;
&#13;
     This investment was for the most part financed through foreign borrowing, because do-&#13;
mestic saving (public and private) was negative on average for each period. The public fiscal&#13;
deficit played a large part in this negative saving; fiscal deficits rose from 4.2 percent of GDP&#13;
in 1985­86 to 14.1 percent of GDP in 1991­92. In fiscal 1990­91 the annual inflation rate&#13;
was down to 25 percent, representing a drastic improvement from more than 200 percent&#13;
inflation in 1986­87. As noted above, however, the inflation rate rose in fiscal 1991­92 to&#13;
above 40 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6Tables providing evidence corroborating the discussion in the text can be found in the appendix to part B.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                Part B: 1992&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IInttterrrnatttiionall Supporrrttt ffforrr ttthe Reffforrrm Prrrogrrram&#13;
&#13;
       The World Bank, International Monetary Fund, and other donors responded vigorously to&#13;
Museveni's reform policies by pledging $310 million in aid in fiscal 1987­88. This was $50&#13;
million more than the government had sought and was earmarked for purchasing essen-&#13;
tials--imports of raw materials, spare parts, and capital goods needed to get production&#13;
rolling again. All debt repayments that Uganda was to make in fiscal 1987­88 were also re-&#13;
scheduled; this released the country from $66 million in international payments that year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Goverrrnmenttt Budgetttarrry Polliicy&#13;
&#13;
       The desired fiscal deficit reduction did not materialize during fiscal 1986­87 to 1990­91.&#13;
Government revenue remained quite low as international coffee prices plummeted, tax col-&#13;
lection remained inadequate, and the proposed sale of twenty-two parastatal enterprises&#13;
did not develop as quickly as planned. With the government's commitment to public invest-&#13;
ment and the continuing petrol subsidy, reduction of the budget deficit became an impossi-&#13;
ble task. Fiscal deficits averaged nearly 7 percent of GDP in the late 1980s. Grants and foreign&#13;
aid financed a portion of the deficits, but Uganda accumulated a substantial foreign debt as&#13;
well. Uganda's debt service ratio (as a percent of exports) rose above 70 percent by 1991.&#13;
&#13;
       A number of government policies were intended to reduce the adverse effects of these&#13;
deficits:&#13;
&#13;
       ·       First, the government for the most part avoided borrowing from the Bank of Uganda&#13;
               in financing its fiscal deficits. The government was increasingly able to turn to external&#13;
               funding, both loans and grants, with the result that domestic borrowing averaged&#13;
               only 0.2 percent of GDP during these years.&#13;
&#13;
       ·       Second, the government lessened its reliance on revenues from coffee taxes and the&#13;
               Coffee Marketing Board. By fiscal 1990­91, coffee taxes and budgetary contributions&#13;
               of the board represented only 10 percent of government revenue, down from 35&#13;
               percent in fiscal 1986­87. This was accomplished by reducing the coffee export tax&#13;
               rate and increasing collection of customs duties and sales taxes, which became the&#13;
               principal sources of recurrent revenue by fiscal 1990­91.&#13;
&#13;
       The Museveni government also became more successful in income tax collection by in-&#13;
creasing delegation of responsibility for collection by local governments. Nevertheless, the&#13;
restructuring of revenue collection was hampered by the sheer size of the nonmonetary&#13;
sector. Although its importance declined during this period, at the end of the period, it re-&#13;
portedly still represented 32 percent of total economic activity.&#13;
&#13;
       The government realizes that social and infrastructural spending has been inadequate be-&#13;
cause central government spending has, in the past, been dominated by defense. Official&#13;
numbers indicate that defense swallowed 22 percent of government spending in fiscal&#13;
1990­91, although unofficial estimates are closer to 50 percent. At the same time, education&#13;
received only 14 percent of recurrent spending, and health received a meager 5 percent.&#13;
&#13;
       To be sure, the government has tightened its belt in some areas. For example, the civil&#13;
service has undergone a restructuring; almost one-half of the 225,000 civil service positions&#13;
were eliminated in 1990­91. Unfortunately, this has done little for the image of the govern-&#13;
ment, because many low-level workers were released, whereas the extravagance of high-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                       Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
level officials is chronicled daily in the press. Moreover, those still at work earn a less-than-&#13;
subsistence salary. At the bottom end of the ladder, civil servants earn only 1,000 shillings&#13;
per month--the price of a bunch of bananas. Permanent secretaries heading government&#13;
agencies earn only 6,000 shillings monthly. Most bureaucrats spend much of their time work-&#13;
ing on outside income-earning activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Fiinanciiall Sectttorrr Devellopmenttt&#13;
&#13;
     Most private citizens have had access to commercial banks or other saving institutions&#13;
but have remained uninterested in depositing their earnings with those institutions. In 1970&#13;
banks held time deposits valued at 5.9 percent of GDP, but by 1989 the same ratio had&#13;
fallen to 0.7 percent. (In contrast, in 1991, in neighboring Kenya, time deposits represented&#13;
17 percent of GDP.)&#13;
&#13;
     Two reasons appeared paramount in the private choice not to save through the banking&#13;
system:&#13;
&#13;
     ·    The Bank of Uganda set nominal interest rates, but these rates were lower in annual&#13;
          terms than the inflation rate. Putting money in the bank, thus, was a losing proposition&#13;
          for Ugandans, because the purchasing power of the funds withdrawn from the bank,&#13;
          even after interest was earned, was less than its original value.&#13;
&#13;
     ·    Corruption scandals have lowered confidence in banking institutions. In 1989 the&#13;
          state-owned Uganda Commercial Bank was charged with defrauding depositors. In&#13;
          1991 the bank was again linked to a conspiracy to defraud the government. (A Dan-&#13;
          ish aid worker discovered the conspiracy and was subsequently shot in broad day-&#13;
          light in Kampala.) These frauds were associated with documented mismanagement at&#13;
          the bank and were made worse in the public eye by the extravagant lifestyle of the&#13;
          bank's managing director. High-ranking officials in other banks were also charged with&#13;
          fraud. Also in 1991, the manager of the Orient Forex Bureau was arrested at Entebbe&#13;
          airport while smuggling out $1 million in cash, traveler's cheques, and bank drafts.&#13;
&#13;
     The Bank of Uganda was accused of inadequately supervising the banking system; in-&#13;
deed, in the banks investigated, reserves against deposits were discovered to be woefully&#13;
below the required 10 percent. Evidence also exists of insolvency on the part of the larger&#13;
commercial banks, including the state-owned Uganda Commercial Bank. These banks have&#13;
substantial accumulated losses, a high proportion of nonrecoverable loans, and a weak cash&#13;
flow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Forrreiign Exchange Avaiillabiilliittty&#13;
&#13;
     Foreign exchange remained the single biggest constraint for businesses. Hard currency&#13;
continued to be available only erratically and without advanced notice, making planning im-&#13;
possible. According to one report, even some parastatals (government-controlled enter-&#13;
prises, many of which were confiscated or taken over when abandoned by Asians expelled&#13;
in 1971) were driven to buy dollars on the kibanda (informal and illegal) market to pay for&#13;
essential imports. Moreover, the Bank of Uganda was under attack for widespread misman-&#13;
agement and corruption in the area of foreign exchange and import licenses. In an attempt to&#13;
gain some control of the illegal market in hard currencies, in 1990 the government legalized&#13;
the kibanda by introducing a system of authorized foreign exchange (forex) bureaus.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     Part B: 1992&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     The continued overvaluation of the shilling on the official foreign exchange market made&#13;
life difficult for Ugandan exporters. Even with periodic devaluations, the shilling was vastly&#13;
overvalued: the kibanda rate was typically two or three times higher than the official rate.&#13;
Even the later policy of real effective depreciation was only partially successful. This helped&#13;
to close the gap between the official and kibanda rates, but by 1991 the official rate was up&#13;
to 558, compared to 780 in the forex bureaus, for a remaining premium at 40 percent. Not&#13;
surprisingly, Uganda's annual trade deficit averaged more than $400 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agrrriicullttturrrall Sectttorrr Perrrffforrrmance&#13;
&#13;
     Much of Uganda's economic growth during this period is attributable to the agricultural&#13;
sector. Funding of $400 million from the Rehabilitation and Development Plan helped, as did&#13;
improvements in infrastructure. Efforts were made to both increase production of traditional&#13;
cash crops (coffee, cotton, tea, and tobacco) and promote cultivation of nontraditional agri-&#13;
cultural crops (NTA) such as maize, beans, peanuts, soybeans, sesame seeds, and a variety&#13;
of fruits. Traditional cash crops on average contributed little during this period to real GDP&#13;
growth, but NTA crops contributed almost 30 percent of observed real growth.&#13;
&#13;
     Some of the traditional cash crops made a comeback. Recognizing the linkages cotton&#13;
has with other industries such as local textile mills, soap factories, and animal feed, the gov-&#13;
ernment initiated an emergency cotton production program in 1989 that provided extension&#13;
services, tractors, and other inputs for cotton farmers. Although cotton suffered from rural&#13;
insecurity and labor shortages in the central and southeastern regions of the country, exports&#13;
increased from about 3,000 tons per year in the late 1980s to nearly 8,000 tons in 1991.&#13;
&#13;
     The return of Asians expelled in the early 1970s revitalized the tea and sugar sectors. Tea&#13;
exports rebounded dramatically, rising from 2,000 to 3,000 tons in the late 1980s to 7,000&#13;
tons in 1991. Sugar production also increased substantially--from nil in 1987 to more than&#13;
40,000 tons in 1991--as old estates were rehabilitated in joint government ventures with the&#13;
original owners.&#13;
&#13;
     This period was unfortunately a difficult time for Ugandan coffee growers, pulling down&#13;
the average contribution of cash crops to GDP growth. Even in good times the price that&#13;
CMB paid to growers never amounted to much more than one-tenth of the world price. In&#13;
December 1988, the situation worsened: due to its own budgetary shortfalls CMB was un-&#13;
able to pay farmers for new deliveries. Although the government agreed to provide funds for&#13;
these obligations, some farmers were unpaid for another year. The situation deteriorated fur-&#13;
ther in July 1989 when the International Coffee Organization--a consortium of coffee-&#13;
producing nations that set international production quotas and prices--collapsed and coffee&#13;
prices plummeted. Furthermore, the government continued to apply the official exchange&#13;
rate to coffee exports (but not to other exports), denying the industry the benefits of the&#13;
more advantageous rates of the new forex bureaus.&#13;
&#13;
     Coinciding with the collapse of world coffee prices, the government took the first step in&#13;
liberalizing the Ugandan coffee market. In 1990 CMB's monopoly in the export of coffee was&#13;
broken as four private cooperatives were licensed to export directly; however, low produc-&#13;
tion and farm level productivity--many of the coffee trees were more than 40­50 years old&#13;
and had reached the end of their economic life--continued to plague the coffee sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                           Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Because the domestic market is small, agricultural exports are the key to growth. Several&#13;
government programs were intended to expand NTA exports. In late 1988 the government&#13;
made it easier for private companies to retain foreign exchange earned for NTA exports and&#13;
to use it to purchase imports. The general patterns of NTA exports have been quite erratic,&#13;
however, and have been significantly influenced by exogenous factors, such as the 1990­91&#13;
drought in Sudan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Manufffacttturrriing and Serrrviice Sectttorrr Perrrffforrrmance&#13;
&#13;
     The industrial sector grew strongly in the late 1980s. It began (and remained) a small per-&#13;
centage of total GDP, but represented between 20 and 40 percent of the annual contribu-&#13;
tions to aggregate growth observed in the period 1986­92. Construction was the most&#13;
buoyant part of the industrial sector, but manufacturing grew strongly during this period as&#13;
well. The services sector represented about one-third of GDP throughout this period and&#13;
grew at roughly the growth rate of GDP.&#13;
&#13;
     A main goal of the government in the late 1980s was to decrease Uganda's dependence&#13;
on imported manufactured goods by rehabilitating existing enterprises. Run-down plant and&#13;
equipment and shortages of spares and foreign exchange, however, continued to hamper&#13;
the manufacturing sector's recovery. Growth in construction was strong but held back by a&#13;
shortage of inputs such as cement, even though the requirements for basic construction are&#13;
all produced locally.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Currrrrrenttt Siitttuatttiion::: June 1992&#13;
&#13;
     Fiscal 1991­92 has been a difficult one in Uganda. Real GDP growth, which averaged&#13;
more than 5 percent per year in the first five years of Museveni's regime, slowed to 3.6 per-&#13;
cent as a drought reduced crop production. Coffee prices did not recover, and coffee ex-&#13;
port receipts fell to $117 million, one-third of the fiscal 1986­87 level. Imports fell to levels&#13;
not seen since 1986. Donor countries slowed aid disbursements, necessitating government&#13;
borrowing from the Bank of Uganda to finance a large fiscal deficit. The drought put upward&#13;
pressure on food prices, and this, coupled with increased government borrowing, resulted&#13;
in a setback on the inflation front as inflation increased to 42 percent. The shilling continued&#13;
its depreciation on the kibanda market to 1,000 per dollar, a 76 percent fall in value from the&#13;
previous year.&#13;
&#13;
     The new four-year Rehabilitation and Development Plan continues the government's ag-&#13;
gressive public expenditure policy but emphasizes changes in the government's spending&#13;
priorities. Resources are being switched out of the productive sectors into social infrastruc-&#13;
ture, primarily as a result of the government's determination to fight the HIV/AIDS epidemic.&#13;
Water projects are also receiving a greater share compared to the previous Rehabilitation and&#13;
Development Plan; fewer funds are available for manufacturing and agriculture.&#13;
&#13;
     The public is growing increasingly disillusioned with high-level corruption. The ministries&#13;
of agriculture, commerce, and energy have figured prominently in continuing revelations of&#13;
corruption and malpractice. Corruption is also reportedly hampering the sales of parastatals,&#13;
because there is talk of delays designed to favor candidates with government links. Problems&#13;
with corruption persist throughout the civil service, in which salaries are still too low.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  Part B: 1992&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      On March 28, 1992, Dr. Crispus Kiyonga, the finance minister since November 1986, was&#13;
sacked. A new joint ministry of finance and economic planning was formed. Kiyonga's re-&#13;
placement was Joshua Mayanga-Nkangi, formerly minister of planning and economic devel-&#13;
opment. Nkangi pledged to get back on the path of fiscal and monetary discipline that Ki-&#13;
yonga had initially chosen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Polliicy Diillemma&#13;
&#13;
      Economic growth during the first six years of the Museveni government was strong, es-&#13;
pecially when compared with Uganda's previous economic results. Now, in mid-1992, there&#13;
is evidence that the engine of growth for that period has run out of steam. Foreign investment&#13;
has trickled into Uganda, especially as expropriated properties are returned to their owners,&#13;
but investor confidence remains low. Finance Minister Nkangi is committed to maintaining&#13;
tight fiscal control in a period of lagging fiscal revenues. The scope for expansion without&#13;
active private participation in productive investment, thus, is likely to be limited.&#13;
&#13;
      Francis Unyofu's department must devise an economic strategy to increase productive&#13;
investment while maintaining fiscal and monetary discipline. The minister recognizes that this&#13;
might require a reallocation of existing public investment funds and seeks recommendations&#13;
for such reallocations if necessary.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Biiblliiogrrraphy&#13;
&#13;
Economist Intelligence Unit. Country Profile: Uganda. London, 1988 and 1991.&#13;
&#13;
------. Country Report: Uganda. London, 1992.&#13;
&#13;
International Monetary Fund. International Financial Statistics. Washington, D.C., 1995.&#13;
&#13;
Library of Congress, Federal Research Division. Uganda: A Country Study. Washington, D.C., 1992.&#13;
&#13;
Sharer, Robert and Calvin McDonald: "Uganda, 1987­94" in Michael T. Hadjimichael and others, Ad-&#13;
      justment for Growth: The African Experience. Washington, D.C.: International Monetary Fund, 1996.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank: Uganda: Growing Out of Poverty. Washington, D.C., 1993.&#13;
&#13;
------. Uganda: The Challenge of Growth and Poverty Reduction. Washington, D.C., 1996.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sourrrces&#13;
&#13;
      Francis Unyofu is a creation of the authors, but other details of Ugandan history are factual. Rather&#13;
than interrupt the narrative, we credit here those sources from whom substantial information has been&#13;
drawn. More detailed citations are available, when needed, from the authors.&#13;
&#13;
      All data in Appendix B are as presented in World Bank (1993 and 1996).&#13;
&#13;
      "Overview of Policies and Aggregate Performance: Fiscal 1987­88 to 1990­91" is drawn from Li-&#13;
brary of Congress (1992), EIU Country Profile (1988 and 1991), and various articles that appeared in&#13;
The New York Times, The Economist, and The Financial Times, with precise citations available from the&#13;
authors.&#13;
&#13;
      "The Current Political Situation: June 1992" is drawn mainly from EIU (1992).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                        Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appendiix B&#13;
&#13;
Table B1. GDP by Sector at Constant 1991 Prices, Fiscal 1985­91.&#13;
(percent of GDP)&#13;
                                                                            1987­88 to&#13;
Sector                                        1985­86         1986­87        1990­91     1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture                                     56.2             55.2         53.7        50.2&#13;
  Cash crops                                     3.8              3.5          3.3         3.4&#13;
  Food crops                                    38.0             37.6         36.8        33.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Industry                                        10.3             11.3         12.5        13.8&#13;
  Mining and quarrying                           0.1              0.1          0.2         0.3&#13;
  Manufacturing                                  5.0              4.9          5.5         6.6&#13;
   Coffee, cotton, sugar                         0.5              0.5          0.6         0.9&#13;
    Food products                                0.6              0.6          0.8         0.8&#13;
  Construction                                   4.3              5.4          5.9         5.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Services                                        33.5             33.5         33.9        36.0&#13;
 Trade                                          10.4             10.3         10.9        11.8&#13;
 Transport and communication                     3.9              4.0          4.1         4.2&#13;
 General government                              3.8              3.7          3.5         3.7&#13;
 Education                                       4.0              3.8          3.6         3.6&#13;
 Health                                          1.6              1.6          1.5         1.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDP at factor cost                             100.0           100.0         100.0        100.0&#13;
  o/w nonmonetary                               35.8             35.3         33.6        30.1&#13;
&#13;
Source: Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B2. GDP by Sector at Constant 1991 Prices, FY 1985­91&#13;
(average annual growth rates)&#13;
                                                                            1987­88 to&#13;
Sector                                        1985­86         1986­87        1990­91     1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture                                     1.3              1.8          5.0         ­1.1&#13;
  Cash crops                                  ­16.4             ­3.8          5.2          5.2&#13;
  Food crops                                    5.3              2.6          5.0         ­3.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Industry                                       ­4.6            13.3           9.8         11.2&#13;
  Mining and quarrying                        ­12.2             ­9.7         33.8         12.4&#13;
  Manufacturing                                ­4.8              2.4         10.7         18.9&#13;
   Coffee, cotton, sugar                       ­0.6              4.3         10.1         54.5&#13;
   Food products                               ­5.6            12.3          12.2          9.0&#13;
  Construction                                 ­5.9            28.4           9.0          3.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Services                                        0.5              3.8          7.1          7.9&#13;
 Trade                                         ­2.6              2.6          8.4          9.0&#13;
 Transport and communication                    5.1              7.0          6.9          4.5&#13;
 General government                             1.6              2.8          4.3         11.8&#13;
 Education                                      0.6              0.2          5.1          1.5&#13;
 Health                                         2.3              3.6          3.5          6.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDP at factor cost                              0.4              3.7          6.2          3.6&#13;
  o/w nonmonetary                               4.5              2.3          3.8         ­3.1&#13;
&#13;
Source: Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  Part B: Appendix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B3: Contributions to Real GDP Growth by Expenditure, Fiscal 1985­91&#13;
                                                                                1986­87 to&#13;
Expenditure                                  1985­86          1986­87            1990­91             1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumption                                    128.3           ­609.4              81.6                90.5&#13;
 Private                                       125.1           ­528.1              75.9                43.1&#13;
 Public                                          3.4            ­81.5               5.7                55.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Gross domestic investment                       13.1           ­649.2              22.3               ­19.7&#13;
&#13;
 Fixed capital formation                        18.6         ­1,232.5              12.8               ­10.7&#13;
  Private                                      247.9           ­529.3               5.1               ­22.0&#13;
  Public                                       ­87.8           ­804.8               7.7                16.4&#13;
 Net change in stocks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Resource balance                               ­41.4          1,358.6              ­3.9                29.2&#13;
 Exports GNFS                                    4.6              54.8              1.7                24.1&#13;
 Imports GNFS                                   45.6         ­1,160.5               5.6               ­11.6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDP at market prices                           100.0            100.0             100.0               100.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Addendum:                                       ­0.3                3.8             5.9                 3.2&#13;
 Growth rate in GDP at factor cost&#13;
&#13;
Source: Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning, and authors' calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B4. GDP by Expenditure at Constant 1991 Prices&#13;
(percent of GDP)&#13;
                                                                                1987­88 to&#13;
Expenditure                                  1985­86         1986­87             1990­91             1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumption                                   104.9           104.0               101.4              101.6&#13;
 Private                                       94.0             93.1               91.2               89.8&#13;
 Public                                        10.9             10.9               10.2               11.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Gross domestic investment                      12.5             14.7               16.6               14.6&#13;
 Fixed capital formation                       12.5             16.5               16.7               14.7&#13;
  Private                                       9.0             10.8               10.6                8.0&#13;
  Public                                        3.5               5.7                6.0               6.8&#13;
 Net change in stocks                           0.0               0.3              ­0.0               ­0.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Resource balance                              ­15.7           ­20.2               ­18.2              ­14.5&#13;
 Exports GNFS   a                               8.3               7.7                7.0               7.2&#13;
 Imports GNFS                                  24.0             27.9               25.2               21.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDP at market prices                          100.0           100.0               100.0              100.0&#13;
Source: Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning.&#13;
aGoods and nonfactor services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                        Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B5. GDP by Expenditure at Constant 1991 Prices.&#13;
(average annual growth rates)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            1987­88 to&#13;
Expenditure                                   1985­86         1986­87        1990­91       1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumption                                     2.0              2.9           5.4           4.6&#13;
 Private                                        2.2              2.8           5.6           2.5&#13;
 Public                                         0.5              3.7           3.8          24.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Gross domestic investment                       1.8             22.0           9.1          ­6.9&#13;
 Fixed capital formation                        2.5             37.1           5.2          ­3.7&#13;
  Private                                      46.0             24.3           3.3         ­14.2&#13;
  Public                                      ­42.1             70.0           8.6          12.5&#13;
 Net change in stocks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Resource balance                                4.4             33.4           1.4         ­10.3&#13;
 Exports GNFS   a                               0.9             ­3.5           1.6          17.1&#13;
 Imports GNFS                                   3.2             20.7           1.5          ­2.7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDP at market prices                           ­0.3              3.8           6.4           3.2&#13;
Source: Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning.&#13;
aGoods and nonfactor services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B6. Production of Principal Commodities, 1986­92&#13;
&#13;
Commodity                         1986          1987      1988        1989   1990     1991     1992&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sugar (tons)                           0           0      7,535     15,859  28,915   42,456  53,539&#13;
&#13;
Beer (thousands of liters)       6,603        16,484     21,139     19,516  19,420   19,529  18,718&#13;
&#13;
Textiles (thousands of           9,733        10,465     11,067     11,589  8,172     8,901    9,650&#13;
  square meters)&#13;
&#13;
Cement (tons)                   16,376        15,904     14,960     17,378  26,920   27,138  37,881&#13;
&#13;
Source: Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 Part B: Appendix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B7. Exports of Cash Crops, 1986­92&#13;
&#13;
                                  1986          1987      1988        1989    1990     1991     1992&#13;
&#13;
Coffee&#13;
   Tons                        140,800       148,153     144,254   176,453   141,489  124,819 119,006&#13;
   Value                       394,200       307,535     265,279   262,811   140,384  117,641  95,372&#13;
     (thousands of US$)&#13;
   Percent of total                   96.9        92.2       99.6        94.6    79.0     67.9     63.1&#13;
     exports&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tea&#13;
   Tons                          2,800         2,100      3,079      3,195    4,760    7,018    7,816&#13;
   Value                         3,100         1,900      3,079      3,195    3,566    6,780    7,721&#13;
     (thousands of US$)&#13;
   Percent of total                    0.8         0.6        1.2         1.2     2.0      3.9      5.1&#13;
     exports&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Cotton&#13;
   Tons                          4,875         3,443      2,088      2,321    3,808    7,819    7,535&#13;
   Value                         5,086         4,097      2,968      4,020    5,795   11,731    8,218&#13;
     (thousands of US$)&#13;
   Percent of total                    1.3         1.2        1.1         1.4     3.3      6.8      5.4&#13;
     exports&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tobacco&#13;
   Tons                                0           0         39        490    2,269    2,467    2,322&#13;
   Value                               0           0         58        569    2,821    4,540    4,333&#13;
     (thousands of US$)&#13;
   Percent of total                    0.0         0.0        0.0         0.2     1.6      2.6      2.9&#13;
     exports&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B8. Balance of Payments, FY 1985­91&#13;
(in $US millions)&#13;
&#13;
                                   1985­86      1986­87   1987­88    1988­89  1989­90 1990­91  1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Exports GNFS                          389.0      406.0       323.9     304.0   245.7    198.9   195.1&#13;
 o/w coffee                           360.0      365.0       285.9     276.0   159.0    127.0   116.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Imports GNFS                          446.0      600.0       682.0     712.0   675.8    670.5   581.5&#13;
 o/w petrol                            61.0        63.0       69.0       76.0    78.0    87.0    57.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Trade balance                         ­57.0     ­194.0     ­358.1     ­408.0  ­430.1   ­471.6  ­386.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Net factor income                     ­44.0       ­47.0      ­57.0     ­66.0   ­77.0    ­58.2   ­87.0&#13;
Current private transfers             101.0      100.2       120.0     114.0     78.0    80.5   135.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C/A balance (excl. grants)              0.0     ­140.8     ­295.1     ­360.0  ­429.1   ­449.3  ­337.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Official transfers                     31.0        40.1       92.4     131.0   152.7    261.9   206.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C/A balance (incl. grants)             31.0     ­100.7     ­202.7     ­229.0  ­276.4   ­187.4  ­131.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall balance                        24.0       ­78.7      ­64.7    ­101.9   ­44.1   ­101.3  ­121.1&#13;
Sources: Bank of Uganda and International Monetary Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                       Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B9. Exchange Rates, FY 1985­91.&#13;
&#13;
                                   1985­86     1986­87    1987­88     1988­89  1989­90 1990­91    1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Official rate (USh/$)                 11         22            60       170       320      558      983&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Average bureau rate (USh/$)           30        110           285       474       662      780    1,130&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Premium bureau/official              166        407           376       178       107       40       15&#13;
(percent)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sources: Bank of Uganda; Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning&#13;
Note: Forex bureaus were legalized in July 1990.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B10. Financial Indicators, FY 1986­91.&#13;
&#13;
                                   1985­86 1986­87        1987­88     1988­89  1989­90    1990­91 1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(annual growth rates)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Domestic credit                     70        141          195        183        16       51      58&#13;
  Broad money (M2)                   150         91          212        125        57       47     ­84&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(percent)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  M2/GDP                              10.2        6.8           6.8       6.7       6.8      7.5     7.6&#13;
  Claims on private sectora           44         50           56         50        51       61      88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Inflation                          148        217          168        131        45       25      42&#13;
  Nominal interest rateb                                      38         43        39       37      32&#13;
  Real interest rate                                       ­130         ­88        ­6       12     ­10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
a. Percent of total domestic credit.&#13;
b. Ninety-one-day treasury bill, end-year basis.&#13;
Sources: Bank of Uganda; Statistics Department, Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        26&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             Part B: Appendix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B11. Central Government Operations, FY 1985­91.&#13;
(percent of GDP at market prices)&#13;
                                                                             1987­88 to&#13;
                                      1985­86               1986­87             1990­91             1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total revenue                            6.4                   4.6                6.7                  6.7&#13;
 Tax revenue                             6.3                   3.8                6.1                  6.2&#13;
   o/w coffee                            4.3                   1.6                0.9                  0.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total expenditure                       10.7                   8.8               12.8                 20.9&#13;
 Current expenditure                     7.9                   5.5                6.9                 11.6&#13;
   o/w wages and salaries                1.2                   1.0                1.1                  1.7&#13;
 Capital expenditure                     2.7                   3.3                5.7                  9.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall deficit (cash)                  ­4.2                  ­4.2               ­6.7               ­14.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Financing&#13;
 Budgetary grants                        1.1                   0.4                2.5                  7.0&#13;
 External                                1.0                   0.3                4.1                  5.1&#13;
 Domestic                                2.1                   3.4                0.2                  2.0&#13;
&#13;
Sources: Ministry of Finance and Economic Planning, Statistics Department, and the International Monetary Fund&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table B12. Destination of Central Government Expenditure&#13;
(percent of total expenditures)&#13;
&#13;
                                         1986­87                1987­88 to 1990­91               1991­92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total current expenditure                   62.5                       54.8                        56.4&#13;
  General public services                   11.5                         9.4&#13;
  Defense and security                      26.4                       23.7&#13;
  Education                                  7.6                         8.1&#13;
  Health                                     1.9                         2.4&#13;
  Other social services                      3.6                         1.3&#13;
  Economic services                          6.9                         3.8&#13;
  Interest payments                          4.5                         6.2                       15.7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total capital expenditure                   37.5                       45.2                        43.6&#13;
  General public services                    6.6                       18.9&#13;
  Defense and security                       1.4                         2.2&#13;
  Education                                  4.0                         2.1&#13;
  Health                                     0.7                         1.5&#13;
  Other social services                      2.1                         1.5&#13;
  Economic services                         22.8                       19.1&#13;
&#13;
Source: International Monetary Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                       Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Chart B1. Price of Ugandan coffee, 1965­92.&#13;
(US$/pound)&#13;
&#13;
 $2.50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 $2.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 $1.50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 $1.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 $0.50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 $0.00&#13;
     1965    1967   1969    1971     1973    1975    1977     1979   1981    1983     1985     1987  1989  1991&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Note: The dotted portion of the line indicates the period of time addressed in part B of this case.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                  Postscriipt::: Post-Conflliict Recovery iin Uganda,,, 1995&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Since launching the first Reconstruction and Development Plan in 1987, Uganda has made&#13;
steady progress in macroeconomic stabilization. After a brief setback in fiscal 1991­92, the&#13;
government introduced a policy shift to encourage private saving and investment. The com-&#13;
ponents of this policy were:&#13;
&#13;
      ·    Foreign exchange controls have been eliminated, and the shilling is determined on&#13;
           the market.&#13;
&#13;
      ·    Marketing of cash crops has been opened to competition, although in practice the&#13;
           old marketing boards still market a large share of the crops.&#13;
&#13;
      ·    Price controls have been eliminated. The role of the government in cash crops has&#13;
           subsequently shifted toward supervision and quality control.&#13;
&#13;
      ·    The Ugandan Revenue Authority was established in an attempt to broaden the gov-&#13;
           ernment's revenue base.&#13;
&#13;
      ·    The size of the civil service and army were cut in half.&#13;
&#13;
      ·    The Ugandan Investment Authority was established to provide information and li-&#13;
           censes, greatly simplifying the old system.&#13;
&#13;
      ·    The Bank of Uganda stopped controlling the level of interest rates.&#13;
&#13;
      Uganda has achieved a degree of macroeconomic stability. Vast improvements have&#13;
been made on the inflation front as reduced fiscal deficits and restrictions on government&#13;
borrowing from the Bank of Uganda brought inflation to below 10 percent by 1993, a far cry&#13;
from the 200 percent rate observed in the mid-1980s. Exporters are actually having to deal&#13;
with an appreciating Ugandan shilling, something unheard of for a generation.&#13;
&#13;
      Production has responded to the economic and political stability of the Museveni regime.&#13;
Growth in real GDP picked up again after a disappointing fiscal 1991­92, averaging between 5&#13;
and 10 percent per year, as all formal sectors--agriculture, industry, and services--expanded.&#13;
In particular, the food crop sector, recently freed from a myriad of government regulations and&#13;
in position to export to drought-stricken areas of Africa, posted strong gains (12.3 percent in-&#13;
crease) in fiscal 1992­93. The manufacturing sector grew almost 15 percent in fiscal 1993­94,&#13;
although crumbling infrastructure continues to be a problem. To be sure, some infrastructure&#13;
has been renovated; many roads, in particular, have been completely resurfaced.&#13;
&#13;
      The value of exports continued to fall until the world price of coffee recovered in fiscal&#13;
1994­95. Export diversification, however, has been quite successful: nontraditional exports&#13;
doubled in 1993 and are currently about 30 percent of total exports. A large gap, however,&#13;
still exists between exports and imports.&#13;
&#13;
      Although macroeconomic stability and the removal of various disincentives have helped&#13;
Uganda recover from its crisis, the country still faces a number of economic problems. Fore-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 This is the third part of a three-part case created by Frank Warnock and Patrick Conway of the Uni-&#13;
 versity of North Carolina at Chapel Hill on the subject of Ugandan economic growth. Thanks to Philip&#13;
 English and Jorge Araujo for useful comments on its content.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                  Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
most are the low levels of investment and savings, which by 1995 increased to 18 and 5 per-&#13;
cent of GDP, respectively. At the heart of the problem is the weak performance of the financial&#13;
sector, which is still far too narrow, consisting only of the seriously undercapitalized Bank of&#13;
Uganda, ten commercial banks--still dominated by the now privatized Uganda Commercial&#13;
Bank--and two development banks. Bad loans are taking their toll on the banking system, as the&#13;
widening spreads between deposit and lending rates point to profitability problems. Moreo-&#13;
ver, the public is still somewhat wary of the financial sector, although the ratio of time deposits&#13;
to GDP has risen by 1993 to 2.3 percent of GDP. A financial reform program has been de-&#13;
signed with the World Bank. Among the recommendations of that program is a recapitalization&#13;
of the Bank of Uganda to enable a strengthening of regulatory powers.&#13;
&#13;
    The government, even with the establishment of the Revenue Authority, still suffers from&#13;
low revenue collection. Foreign aid finances 60 percent of government spending. As&#13;
HIV/AIDS continues to sap the resources of the nation, there is a great need for human capital&#13;
investment, particularly in the areas of health and education. Government spending for health&#13;
and education has increased steadily in real terms in the 1990s, mostly to increase salaries.&#13;
Spending in these areas as a share of GDP still falls short of averages for Sub-Saharan Africa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Post-Conflliict Recovery&#13;
iin Uganda&#13;
&#13;
Teaching Notes&#13;
&#13;
Frank Warnock and Patrick Conway&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1999&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank enjoys copyright under protocol 2 of the Universal Copyright Convention. This material&#13;
may nonetheless be copied for research, educational, or scholarly purposes only in the member&#13;
countries of The World Bank. Material in this series is subject to revision. The findings, interpretations,&#13;
and conclusions expressed in this document are entirely those of the author(s) and should not be&#13;
attributed in any manner to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or the members of its Board&#13;
of Executive Directors or the countries they represent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Posttt-Conffflliicttt Recoverrry iin Uganda&#13;
Teaching Notes&#13;
Frank Warnock and Patrick Conway&#13;
1999. 8 pages. Stock No. 37153&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                             Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Posttt-Conffflliicttt Recoverrry and Uganda Teachiing Notttes .....................................................................................................................................................................................................................1&#13;
&#13;
  The Big Picture.............................................................................................................................................................1&#13;
&#13;
  Part A.............................................................................................................................................................................1&#13;
&#13;
  Part B..............................................................................................................................................................................3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                Post-Conflliict Recovery iin Uganda&#13;
                                              Teachiing Notes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         This case has been written to facilitate analysis of economic growth prospects in devel-&#13;
 oping economies, with special emphasis on those emerging from military or political conflict.&#13;
 We have used this case in both classroom and workshop settings and in these notes provide&#13;
 suggestions for its effective use.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 The Biig Piicttturrre&#13;
&#13;
         We have written the case in three parts. Part A discusses the evolution of the Ugandan&#13;
 economy from independence to 1987. Part B examines the period 1987­92. The last part is&#13;
 a postscript, providing details of more recent policy choices as well as continuing problems&#13;
 for the future. The case has two "decision points" in 1987 and 1992, corresponding to the&#13;
 end of parts A and B, respectively. At these points, the workshop participants are asked to&#13;
 analyze the situation and provide recommendations. Parts A and B should be distributed and&#13;
 read in advance of the session at which they will be discussed, although part B should not&#13;
 be handed out until the discussion of part A is complete.&#13;
&#13;
         This case will work best as a teaching medium if undertaken in parts. We recommend that&#13;
 part A be examined in a 1.5-hour session. The product of that session should be a list of rec-&#13;
 ommendations for the Ugandan government to implement in order to achieve its goal as stated&#13;
 in the case. In a subsequent 1.5-hour session, although not necessarily immediately following,&#13;
 the group can examine part B. Once again, the product of the session should be enumeration&#13;
 of policies to attain the government's goals. The last part, the postscript, can be handed out at&#13;
 the end of the second session for the participants' edification and comment, if time permits.&#13;
&#13;
         We have chosen this structure because we believe that the issues of economic growth in&#13;
 Uganda can be separated into two stages. The first, bringing productive resources idled by&#13;
 conflict back into operation, dominates part A. The second, the need for investment in social&#13;
 capital, infrastructure, and productive capacity to sustain economic growth, is more evident&#13;
 in part B. You may not view this distinction as important in your own use of the case, but you&#13;
 will find that the following notes are keyed to that distinction.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Parrrttt A&#13;
&#13;
         Uganda's history (with the possible exception of Idi Amin) is not common knowledge,&#13;
 so we would advise beginning the case discussion with an introductory period focusing on&#13;
 the political and economic situation in Uganda from 1962 to 1987. Useful initial questions to&#13;
 ignite comment might include:&#13;
&#13;
         ·   Where would you rather live: Uganda in 1962 or Uganda in 1987?&#13;
&#13;
         ·   What is the quality of life in Kampala in 1987?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This instructor's note has been prepared to accompany a case in three parts created by Frank War-&#13;
nock and Patrick Conway of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill on the subject of Ugan-&#13;
dan economic growth. Thanks to Philip English and Jorge Araujo for useful comments on its con-&#13;
tent.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     ·   Has Uganda provided a successful example of economic growth since independence?&#13;
&#13;
     These questions will lead to an enumeration of the political and military crises of the inter-&#13;
vening period. The most important points for the group to take away from this discussion is&#13;
the strong potential of the economy in 1962, especially in agricultural crops for the world&#13;
market, and the effect of the crisis in destroying productive capacity (physical and social&#13;
capital) and idling economic resources. Most participants will recognize the direct effect of&#13;
war and destruction in idling resources but may not recognize the indirect effects through&#13;
the manipulation of relative prices of export crops and foreign exchange to meet budgetary&#13;
needs. You could introduce this concept through a question such as:&#13;
&#13;
     ·   The fields of coffee growers were for the most part unscathed by the crisis, but the pro-&#13;
         duction and export of coffee nevertheless fell steadily after 1965. Why?&#13;
&#13;
     Once a common base of understanding is established among workshop participants,&#13;
you can turn to the task at hand. Have the group identify the actor (Francis Unyofu) and the&#13;
task (strategy to increase economic activity while maintaining macroeconomic stability). De-&#13;
fining terms and agreeing on ways to measure the goal are usefully done at this early stage.&#13;
&#13;
     If you as instructor have set the goal of economic growth, it will be helpful to define pos-&#13;
sible sources of growth and possible markets for increased production. For example, this&#13;
discussion could lead to the following matrix:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Sourrrces:::           Agriculture          Manufacturing         Services&#13;
  Ugandan&#13;
  East African&#13;
  World&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Each entry in the matrix is a possibility, although some are more likely. For example, agri-&#13;
culture in Uganda implies coffee and tea, but those only find sufficient buyers on a world&#13;
market. Conversely, manufacturing can probably not compete on the world market initially&#13;
and will have to focus on the local (Ugandan or perhaps East African) market.&#13;
&#13;
     For a change of pace, at this point we recommend a bit of role playing. Once the potential&#13;
sources of growth are identified, designate individuals within the workshop to play the parts of&#13;
producers in those areas, for example, a smallholder in coffee production, textile mill operator,&#13;
or hotel manager. Have each of them describe what incentives are necessary for them to ex-&#13;
pand their operations. Do not limit them to economic incentives, because political security&#13;
should be quite important. You can list the economic incentives by sector for use in the poli-&#13;
cymaking phase of the workshop. Encourage questioning of the role players by those not tak-&#13;
ing a role. Perhaps, designate the others as members of a presidential fact-finding commission.&#13;
&#13;
     The goal of the session is to come up with a strategy for encouraging economic growth.&#13;
Build on the results of the role playing to define candidate strategies. (These will almost cer-&#13;
tainly include export-oriented and import-substituting strategies but may also include gov-&#13;
ernment stimulus.) Ask for the pros and cons of each, listing them and eliciting comments as&#13;
you go. These comments should include discussion of the implications of each pro and con&#13;
for macroeconomic stability. In the end, ask for a vote. If time permits, look for ways to build&#13;
a consensus strategy (i.e., try to address the objections of the minority).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                Teaching Notes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        To wrap up, ask whether the choice of strategy was driven in the minds of participants&#13;
by the specific situation in Uganda. Did the existence of unused resources (excess capacity)&#13;
make one strategy or another more attractive? If so, why? Is this a strategy that Uganda should&#13;
maintain for decades or only for the near future?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Parrrttt B&#13;
&#13;
        We presume that workshop participants will already have worked on part A and no&#13;
need exists for further review of Uganda's economic history. Some review of the analysis&#13;
conducted in the first session will, however, be helpful.&#13;
&#13;
        The initial question for this session could mirror that of the first session, for example:&#13;
&#13;
        ·    Where would you rather live: Uganda in 1986 or Uganda in 1992?&#13;
&#13;
        ·    What is the quality of life in Kampala in 1992?&#13;
&#13;
        ·    Has Uganda been a successful example of economic growth since 1987?&#13;
&#13;
        The goal of this opening question is to (a) put the participants "in character," that is,&#13;
thinking as Ugandans, and (b) focus on the economic growth and quality-of-life aspects of&#13;
the economy. After responding, the participants can answer "why." These answers will fill out&#13;
the group's shared knowledge of economic performance since 1986.&#13;
&#13;
        You will note that we have divided the economic performance tables in the appendix of this&#13;
section into four periods. The first (fiscal 1985­86) represents the situation at the end of part A.&#13;
The second (fiscal 1986­87) represents the impact of the policies chosen. The third period (fis-&#13;
cal 1987­88 to fiscal 1990­91) was one of relatively stable performance, which is indicated by&#13;
the annual average of those years. The fourth period (fiscal 1991­92) may be considered the&#13;
present for purposes of decisionmaking in the case. A written summary for this final period is pre-&#13;
sented in the section entitled "The Current Situation: June 1992" near the end of part B.&#13;
&#13;
        Next, we recommend reviewing the policy decisions of the first session and comparing&#13;
those with the policies undertaken by the Ugandan government. Did the Ugandans follow&#13;
your advice? It is important to note both similarities and differences. You may ask the partici-&#13;
pants to speculate on why the differences occurred.&#13;
&#13;
        It is important to highlight early on the apparent inconsistency in the sets of reforms put&#13;
forward in this part. Promises of fiscal balance occur side by side with increased public in-&#13;
vestment and increased wages for public sector workers. Whatever the merits of the latter&#13;
policies, participants in the workshop should recognize the evident tension. As you pro-&#13;
ceed, you can then ask what impact these tensions had on the economy (i.e., inflationary&#13;
pressure, real exchange rate appreciation, and increased foreign indebtedness).&#13;
&#13;
        Be sure to define the task for this session early on. Focus on both parts of the task. "In-&#13;
crease productive investment" need not be capital stock but could also be human capital.&#13;
For what reason must "fiscal and monetary discipline" be maintained? Are fiscal and monetary&#13;
discipline independent constraints, or are they related? If so, how?&#13;
&#13;
        You could mirror the structure of the first session by playing the roles of various potential&#13;
investors (agricultural, manufacturing, and service as well as private domestic, government&#13;
domestic, and foreign). What will be necessary to encourage such investment? Alternatively,&#13;
for a change of pace, designate small groups to devise a strategy for encouraging investment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                       Post-Conflict Recovery in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
by sector (agricultural, manufacturing, and service). In this case, task the groups to identify a&#13;
strategy targeted to that sector. They should identify present constraints on investment, in-&#13;
centives they would offer to investors, and the identity of the investor they are targeting&#13;
(government, private domestic, or foreign).&#13;
&#13;
    Participants may find themselves returning to the prescriptions offered in part A as rec-&#13;
ommendations for this part as well. This is useful and important to understanding the Ugandan&#13;
experience. You can pursue this line with such questions as:&#13;
&#13;
    ·    From your perspective (manufacturers), has foreign exchange reform improved your ac-&#13;
         cess to currency to purchase essential inputs? Why or why not?&#13;
&#13;
    ·    From your perspective (agricultural), has reform of the Uganda Coffee Marketing Board&#13;
         improved incentives to coffee growers?&#13;
&#13;
    After these activities, return to a plenary session. Pull together a list of constraints to in-&#13;
vestment. These should fall broadly into the following categories:&#13;
&#13;
    ·    Unprofitable to invest&#13;
&#13;
    ·    Foreign exchange costs&#13;
&#13;
    ·    Insufficient infrastructure&#13;
&#13;
    ·    Insufficient labor skills for wage paid&#13;
&#13;
    ·    Foreign competition at lower prices&#13;
&#13;
    ·    Government competition at lower prices&#13;
&#13;
    ·    Lack of access to economic financing.&#13;
&#13;
    This list can be linked directly to a list of incentives to productive investment. Collect a list&#13;
of such incentives, and evaluate each for its effect on fiscal and monetary discipline.&#13;
&#13;
    A similar role play will be useful in examining the incentives to domestic saving. You could&#13;
begin with a question such as:&#13;
&#13;
    ·    This investment must be financed. To whom should we turn for financing?&#13;
&#13;
    Then ask for the identities of potential financing sources. Designate an individual to repre-&#13;
sent each source, and explore the potential for increased financing from each. Do not allow&#13;
the stock answer "let the government finance it." Given that the government is already in fiscal&#13;
deficit, explore where the government will in turn obtain financing.&#13;
&#13;
    Call for proposed strategies, look for common ground among them, and encourage par-&#13;
ticipants to forge a consensus strategy. If a number of strategies remain, conduct a vote for&#13;
the preferred strategy. If time permits, designate one (or more) participants as the president&#13;
and his advisors. Have the others present the strategy to him, and ask for his critique of it.&#13;
&#13;
    Wrap up this session with a review of the beginning and ending points of discussion.&#13;
Highlight the differences in strategies derived in parts A and B, as well as any similarities.&#13;
&#13;
    Distribute the postscript so the participants may see what the Ugandans actually did in&#13;
1992.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6093475">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/01/6093475/post-conflict-recovery-uganda
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/01/6093475/post-conflict-recovery-uganda</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/01/6093475/post-conflict-recovery-uganda</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2005-07-25T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/07/26/000012009_20050726101940/Rendered/INDEX/330250rev0WBCS0wbi37152and37153.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/07/26/000012009_20050726101940/Rendered/PDF/330250rev0WBCS0wbi37152and37153.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-07-26T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Post-conflict recovery in Uganda
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In attempting to present the
            post-conflict recovery picture in Uganda, this paper first
            outlines the 1987 background in the country, through its
            political and economic situation at the time, supported by
            tables on economic, and social indicators, on the Central
            government operations, the industrial origin of gross
            domestic product (GDP) at factor cost (1960-86), and further
            tables on production and trade, and exchange rates. Then an
            overview of policies and aggregate performance on fiscal
            1987-88 to 1990-91 leads to the international support
            response to the reform program, when a number of government
            policies were intended to reduce the adverse effects of the
            deficit. The paper examines the financial sector and the
            foreign exchange availability, and, the agricultural sector
            performance. Much of Uganda's economic growth at the
            beginning of 1990 is attributable to the agricultural
            sector: traditional cash crops - coffee, cotton tea, and
            tobacco - including non-traditional crops, i.e., maize,
            beans, soybeans, etc. However, the period was a difficult
            one for Ugandan coffee growers, pulling down the average
            contribution of cash crops to GDP growth. The situation in
            1992, in particular Fiscal 1991-92 was a difficult one,
            conducive the policy dilemma, to devise an economic strategy
            to increase productive investment, while maintaining fiscal
            and monetary discipline. Teaching Notes accompanies this
            paper to facilitate analyses of economic growth prospects,
            with special emphasis on emerging from military or political conflict.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Post-conflict recovery in Uganda
        </docna>
        <display_title>Post-conflict recovery in Uganda</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1999/01/6093475/post-conflict-recovery-uganda</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <count>Uganda</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Warnock, Frank</author>
            <author>Conway, Patrick</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000012009_20050726101940</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            adverse effects, agribusiness, agricultural
            production, agricultural products, agriculture, Airports,
            Balance of Payments, Bananas, beans, budget deficit, capital
            goods, Cash Crops, Central Bank, Central Government, central
            government spending, citizens, Coffee, coffee farmers,
            coffee growers, coffee prices, coffee producers, Coffee
            production, commercial bank, commercial banks, constitution,
            consumers, cotton, cotton prices, cotton production, crop,
            crop production, crowding out, cultivation, debt, debt
            service, dictatorship, domestic borrowing, economic
            activity, Economic Development, economic growth, Economic
            History, economic problems, Economic Situation, Electricity,
            exchange rate, Exchange Rates, Expenditure, Exports,
            farmers, Financial Sector, Fiscal, fiscal deficit, fiscal
            deficits, foreign borrowing, foreign debt, Foreign Exchange,
            foreign investment, formal economy, GDP, government
            borrowing, government controls, government expenditures,
            government officials, government policies, Government
            revenue, government spending, government subsidies, grain,
            Gross Domestic Product, growth rate, imports, income, income
            taxes, inflation, inflation rate, insurance, interest rates,
            legal exchange rates, licenses, local governments,
            macroeconomic stability, macroeconomic stabilization,
            ministers, Ministry of Finance, oil, per capita incomes,
            Price controls, produce, Public investment, Public Policy,
            public sector, public sector wages, purchasing power, Real
            GDP, Rehabilitation, revenue collection, Revenue Grants,
            roads, sales taxes, savings, seeds, social infrastructure,
            social welfare, streets, sugar, tax, tax collection, tax
            rate, tax revenues, tea, unemployment, wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>Poverty Reduction &amp; Econ Mng Div (WBIPR)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>33025</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>