<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>  DominicanRepublic-SocialCrisisResponseAdjustment Loan(SCRAL)&#13;
                                (Loan 7215-DO)&#13;
&#13;
                   Releaseof TrancheA -FullCompliance&#13;
&#13;
                I.PROGRAMPERFORMANCEOVERALL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1. The Dominican Republic Social Crisis Response Adjustment Loan (SCRAL) in&#13;
   the amount of US$lOO million was approved by the Board of Directors on&#13;
   February 12, 2004, andbecame effective on March 4, 2004. The loan comprises&#13;
   three single currency tranches: a first tranche, and two floating tranches&#13;
   henceforthidentified as Tranche A andTranche B.&#13;
&#13;
2. As per loan agreement nr. 72150 DO signed by the Borrower on February 13,&#13;
   2004, the disbursement o f Tranche A i s triggered by a series o f actions in the&#13;
   social sector, while Tranche B by a different set o f action inthe electricity sector.&#13;
   The release o f hnds for each ofthe floating tranches occurs as soon as the sector-&#13;
   specific conditions materialize andnot necessarily ina sequential order.&#13;
&#13;
3. The first tranche inthe amount o f US$49 million was released on March 8, 2004&#13;
   upon meeting a set of actions before Board presentation. Tranche B inthe amount&#13;
   o f US$25 million was released on April 13, 2005.            This Tranche Release&#13;
   Document (TRD) sets forth a description o f the tranche conditions and&#13;
   compliance status o fthe borrower for Tranche A o fUS$25 million.&#13;
&#13;
4. Macroeconomic Framework. In the aftermath o f the May 2004 elections,&#13;
   market confidence returned as a result o f the perceived strong commitment of&#13;
   President Femandez' administration to stabilize the economy and restore growth.&#13;
   The new administration immediatelyinitiatednegotiations withthe IMFfor a new&#13;
   Stand-By Agreement (SBA), including a macro stabilization program with&#13;
   revenue and expenditure measures to reduce the fiscal gap, commitments on&#13;
   improved debt management process, a range o f banking measures to retum the&#13;
   sector to sound footing, and reform o f public sector financial institutions to&#13;
   improve the design and execution o f fiscal policies. As a first step, a tax reform&#13;
   package was prepared in consultation with the IMF and passed by Congress in&#13;
   October 2004. Since July 2004, the peso has appreciated from RD$45/US$ to&#13;
   less than RD$30/US$ in November 2004 and has remained stable since then.&#13;
   Inflation has come down significantly and spreads on external bonds have also&#13;
   fallen inrecent months.&#13;
&#13;
5. InApril 2004 the Paris Club agreed to reschedule debt obligations, pending an&#13;
   agreement o f comparable treatment byprivate creditors.     A market-friendlybond&#13;
  restructuring with private creditors was recently completed, with higher-than-&#13;
   anticipated investor participation. The result was a restructuring o f over 93&#13;
  percent o f outstanding bonds, whose maturities were pushed from 2006 and 2013,&#13;
  to 2011 and 2018, respectively, providing the Government with liquidity relief&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                DR SCRALSocial Sector TrancheReleaseMemorandum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   andpavingthe way for the completiono fParis Clubnegotiations. Inaddition, the&#13;
   Central Bank has managed to stabilize base money and interest rates have&#13;
   declined.&#13;
&#13;
6. The Board o f the IMF approved the SBA on January 31, 2005. Developments&#13;
   under the program remainpositive and preliminary information indicates that the&#13;
   end-June 2005 fiscal and monetary targets have been met with comfortable&#13;
   margins(see IMF assessmentletter inattachment). The continued implementation&#13;
   o f cautious fiscal and monetary policies has contributed to strengthening market&#13;
   confidence, reducing inflation, and lowering interest rates. Preliminary data&#13;
   indicate that real GDP grew by 4.3 percent inthe first quarter o f 2005 suggesting&#13;
   that GDP growth for 2005 could reach 3.5 percent. Meanwhile, the 12-month&#13;
   inflation rate fell to -1.0 percent inJune from 28.7 percent inDecember 2004, and&#13;
   the average interest rate on Central Bank certificates has fallen to close 10&#13;
   percent. Inthis regard, and despite the rapid growth in Central Bank certificates in&#13;
   early 2005 - reflecting the larger-than-anticipated accumulation o f international&#13;
   reserves - the Central Bank's quasi-fiscal losses remain within the program's&#13;
   estimates.&#13;
&#13;
7. In the financial sector the Government has moved to improve prudential&#13;
   regulations, in accordance with the IMF SBA, in particular by strengthening&#13;
   supervision and gradually raising commercial banks' capitalization to&#13;
   international standards.       In addition, Congress recently approved the World&#13;
   Bank's Technical Assistance Loan for the Financial Sector, which should further&#13;
   help strengthen bankingsupervision andconsolidation.&#13;
&#13;
8. The electricity sector has shown some positive signs o f improvement, with&#13;
   decreased distribution losses and increased collections, although it i s still not&#13;
   financially solvent.      Congress recently approved the World Bank's Technical&#13;
   Assistance Loan for the Energy Sector which should improve sector perfonnance&#13;
   in preparation for the recently approved World Bank US$l50 million Power&#13;
   Sector Adjustment Loan which supports a program to improve the sector's&#13;
   financial and technical viability, particularly in the improvement o f collection&#13;
   rates, revision o f tariffs, reduction o f transmission losses and in stolen electricity,&#13;
   andoverallimprovements inthe stability and supply of electricitynationwide.&#13;
&#13;
Poverty Trends and Social Issues&#13;
&#13;
9. The country's impressive economic growth duringthe 1990s (5.9 percent per year&#13;
   on average) lifted about 5 percent o f Dominicans out o f poverty (2 percent out o f&#13;
  extreme poverty). Butpersistent disparities inthe distributiono fhuman, physical&#13;
   and financial assets and inefficiency and inequity inpublic spendingprevented a&#13;
  faster decline in poverty.       Inparticular, large segments of the rural population&#13;
  have not participated inthe benefits o f growth, and income and inequality remain&#13;
  at the average level o f the LAC region, already the highest in the world.&#13;
  Preliminary results from a recent living conditions survey indicate that about 36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                        DR SCRALSocial Sector Tranche Release Memorandum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         percent of the population had incomes insufficient to cover their basic needs in&#13;
         2004, andover 13 percent couldnot even affordminimumfood requirements.&#13;
&#13;
    10. Social indicators in the Dominican Republic remain below the L A C region's&#13;
         average and that o f countries with similar income per capita. According to the&#13;
         2004 UNDP Human Development Index the country ranks 98 among 177&#13;
         countries.    At current rates and trends, the Dominican Republic is not well&#13;
         positionedto achieve some MillenniumDevelopment Goals (MDGs), particularly&#13;
         those related to the eradication o f hunger, improvement o f child and maternal&#13;
         health, and environmental sustainability.&#13;
&#13;
    11.Preliminary assessments of the impact of the recent crisis on the poor indicate a&#13;
         dramatic increase in the percentage o f people living in poverty and a general&#13;
         worsening o f living conditions across income groups. About 15 percent o f&#13;
         Dominicans (about 1.3 million) fell in poverty during 2000-2004 and close to 7&#13;
         percent (over half a million) became unable to afford even the basic food needs.'&#13;
         The bulk o f the increase in poverty occurred during 2002-04 since poverty&#13;
         remained stagnant during 2000-02. The increase in poverty is similar to that&#13;
         observed inArgentina duringthe severe crisis o f 2000-2002.&#13;
&#13;
    12. These figures reflect the toll o f rampant inflation on living conditions. Average&#13;
        real labor earnings fell by almost one third and open unemployment worsened by&#13;
         one percentage point from early 2002 to early 2004.                      A qualitative study&#13;
         completed in December 2004 on the social dimensions o f the economic crisis&#13;
        under the SCRALrevealed that somepoor households responded to the decline in&#13;
        real incomes by removing their children from school, reducing food consumption,&#13;
        and eliminating services (phone, gas and electricity).                Years o f slow, albeit&#13;
        important, reduction o f poverty rates and improved living standards were&#13;
        reversed, all of which weaken the country's capacity to meet the MDGs by 2015.&#13;
&#13;
    13. Poverty rates stand at 31 percent in urban areas and 45 percent in rural zones.&#13;
        Povertyrates are higher among households headed by females and elderly people,&#13;
        and take their heaviest toll on children and youth through increased rates of&#13;
        malnutrition, school dropouts, youth unemployment and risky behavior. This&#13;
        indicates that while economic growth is critical to reduce poverty in the&#13;
        Dominican Republic, it has to be complemented by a range o f public actions to&#13;
        ensure that poorpeoplebenefit including the most vulnerable amongthe poor.&#13;
&#13;
   Social Sector Reforms&#13;
&#13;
   14. InJanuary 2004 the Government began an ambitious set o f social sector reforms,&#13;
        described in the Policy Reform Matrix detailed in the Staff Appraisal Report,&#13;
        which constitute the overall program supported by this loan.                      The reforms&#13;
        included both crisis response actions and medium term reforms, addressing&#13;
&#13;
'Resultsarefrom an on-goinganalysisof the Labor ForceSurveys 1998-2004and a2004 living conditions survey&#13;
(ENCOVI), whichwill befinalizedinan ongoingpovertyassessment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             DR SCRAL Social Sector Tranche Release Memorandum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    education, health, nutrition, poverty, and social sector expenditures. Fifteen o f&#13;
   these measures were undertaken before presentation o f the SCRAL to the Board.&#13;
   Nineteen additional measures have been implemented since February 2004,&#13;
   including eight major reforms which are included in Schedule 3 o f the SCRAL&#13;
   Loan Agreement for Floating Tranche "A", all o f which have been fully complied&#13;
   with (described fkther inSection 11).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
15. Overall program actions implemented since February2004 include inter alia:&#13;
&#13;
    0  Satisfactory protection o f priority social program expenditures inthe 2004 and&#13;
       2005 National Budgets (equivalent to US$130 million, each year);&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   0  Full financing o f a universal school feeding program reaching 1.6 million&#13;
       children in grades 1-8 each day, incorporation o f students previously served&#13;
      by the World Food Program, and the launching of a comprehensive extemal&#13;
       impact evaluation o f this program;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   0  Implementation o f a conditional cash transfer (CCT) program for 100,000&#13;
      poor mothers who send their children to primary school, including the&#13;
      establishment o f an operational unit for program administration, development&#13;
      o f a comprehensive operational manual satisfactory to the Bank which uses a&#13;
      proxy-means test for beneficiary selection, and the launching o f a baseline&#13;
      impact evaluation for this program;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   0  Enrollment o f over 74,000 poor individuals in the subsidized component o f&#13;
      the nationalhealthinsurance system;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   0  Continuation o f a policy allowing undocumented children to enroll inprimary&#13;
      school, benefiting at least 20,000 youth in school year 2004-2005, and&#13;
      provision o f over 11,000 birth certificates to previously undocumented&#13;
      children;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   0  Support from the National Council o f Social Security to                         12,000&#13;
      undocumented families, identified as otherwise available to participate innon-&#13;
      contributory health insurance system, to obtain their identitycards;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   0  Development o f an Operational Manual satisfactory to the Bank by the food&#13;
      subsidy program, "Comer es Primero", and implementation o f this program&#13;
      inaccordancewiththe Operational Manual;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   0  Continued legal reform o f the health sector, including (i)         promulgation by&#13;
      presidential decree o f the "Regulation o f Human Resources in the National&#13;
      Health System", (ii)    approval by the Secretary o f Public Health and Social&#13;
      Assistance (SESPAS) o f the Resolution which initiates the separation o f&#13;
      functions inthe health sector, by which i s authorized the creation o f Regional&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            DR SCRAL Social Sector Tranche ReleaseMemorandum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Public Health Service Providers, and (iv) revision o f the process for&#13;
        categorizing beneficiaries for the non-contributory health insurance system&#13;
        acceptable to the Bank;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    0   Promulgation o f a presidential decree ordering the elimination o f eight&#13;
        ineffective social programs, and the consolidation o f many other programs&#13;
        resultinginincreased rationalizationo fthe social protection sector ingeneral;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    0   Updating o f the Operational Manual and econometric formula used to select&#13;
        beneficiaries according to levels o f poverty, approved by the Social Cabinet,&#13;
        andupdatingo fthe nationalpovertymap using2002 Census data; and&#13;
&#13;
        Contracting o f five civil society organizations to monitor government&#13;
        implementation o f key social programs supported by the SCRAL (school&#13;
        feeding, the CCT program, support to undocumented families, the targeted&#13;
        food subsidyprogram, etc.), and submission o ftheir reports to Government.&#13;
&#13;
16. Inaddition, the Government has moved forward with overall reform o f the health&#13;
    sector supported by the recent launched World Bank financed Health Sector&#13;
    Reform Adaptable Programmatic Loan, and it has substantially improved the&#13;
    implementation o f its national HIV/AIDS prevention and control programs. In&#13;
    the education sector, the Government announced in early February 2005 its&#13;
    intention to work with all major donors on the preparation and implementation o f&#13;
    a Sector Wide Approach (SWAP), which should significantly improve access and&#13;
    quality o f education over the next few years.&#13;
&#13;
17. Finally, the Femandez Government launched inAugust 2004 the Unified System&#13;
    for Beneficiary Selection (Sistema Unico de Beneficiarios, STCTBEN), a&#13;
    sophisticated systemwhich uses the updatedNational PovertyMap andhousehold&#13;
    surveys in areas o f extreme poverty to identify those households most inneed o f&#13;
   public social programs. SIUBEN will be used for targeting o f almost all public&#13;
    social programs, which should greatly improve efficiency, transparency and&#13;
    effectiveness o f these programs, while reducing indiscriminate use o f social&#13;
   programs for politicalpurposes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            DR SCRALSocial Sector TrancheReleaseMemorandum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11. PROGRESS IN MEETING FLOATING TRANCHE RELEASE "A"&#13;
CONDITIONSRELATEDTO THE SOCIAL SECTOR&#13;
&#13;
18. General Conditions: The status o f the two general conditions associated with the&#13;
    Loani s as follows:&#13;
&#13;
    - the macroeconomic policy fiamework o f the Borrower i s satisfactory. This&#13;
    conditionis met, on the basis of the assessmento fthe country's macroeconomic&#13;
    performance inSection Iabove.&#13;
    - The progress achieved by the Borrower in carrying out the Program is&#13;
    satisfactory. This conditionis met, demonstrated inparagraphs 12-15 above and&#13;
    intherecent disbursement ofthe electricity sector tranche.&#13;
&#13;
19. The actions described in Schedule 3 o f the Loan Agreement have been taken in&#13;
    form and substance satisfactory to the Bank. This condition is met. Government&#13;
    Performance inmeeting each ofthe specific conditions for floating tranche release&#13;
    "A" is describedbelow inParagraphs 18-25.&#13;
&#13;
20. Condition 1. (a) The Secretary o f Education (SEE) has approved an operational&#13;
    manual for the Cash Transfer Program; and (b) The beneficiaries o f the Cash&#13;
    Transfer Program have been selected, as o f January 1, 2004, in accordance with&#13;
    the proxy-means test developed bythe Borrower's NationalPlanningOffice.&#13;
&#13;
    The Secretary o f Education signed a resolution dated May 11, 2005, approving&#13;
    this operational manual, satisfactory to the Bank, a copy o f which has been&#13;
    submitted to the Bank. The Director o f the National PlanningOffice submitted a&#13;
    letter to the Bank on April 22, 2005 indicating that between January and August&#13;
    2004 (under the previous Government) a total o f 254 mothers were added to this&#13;
    program using a different, geographic poverty targeting criteria to replace 254&#13;
    mothers whose children were no longer in primary school.              However, this&#13;
    represents less than 0.25 percent o f the total number o f program beneficiaries&#13;
    (100,000). Thus, overall performance is considered acceptable. Since September&#13;
    2004 no mothers have been added to the program. For the upcoming school year&#13;
    (2005/2006) mothers will be selected using the newly approved Operational&#13;
   Manualwhich includes use o fthe proxy meanstest.&#13;
&#13;
21. Condition 2. Birthcertificates have been issued to at least 11,000 undocumented&#13;
   children enrolled in the Borrower's school system pursuant to an agreement&#13;
   between the Secretary o fEducation andthe Borrower's central election council.&#13;
&#13;
   The Borrower submitted evidence demonstrating that 11,09 1 undocumented&#13;
   children received their birth certificates. This evidence has been certified by the&#13;
   Resident Representative o f the UNDP in the Dominican Republic (UNDP was&#13;
   hiredby the Government to supervise fulfillment o f SCRAL conditionalities) ina&#13;
   letter dated May 11,2005.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             DR SCRALSocial Sector TrancheRelease Memorandum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22. Condition 3. The Social Cabinet has approved an operational manual, prepared&#13;
    by the Borrower's "Comer es Primero" program, for a targeted food subsidy&#13;
    program, and implementationo fthis programhas been initiated.&#13;
&#13;
    The head o f the Social Cabinet (Vice President of the Country) has signed a&#13;
    resolution dated May 20, 2005, approving this operational manual, a copy o f&#13;
    which has been submitted to the Bank. This program has been initiated among&#13;
     16,000 households (reaching 80,000 beneficiaries) on a pilot basis and i s due to&#13;
     scale up to 150,000 households by the endo f 2005. It has also been supervised by&#13;
    civil society (see Condition 8 below).&#13;
&#13;
23. Condition 4. The Borrower's non-contributory health insurance program has&#13;
    enrolled and affiliated at least 70,000 poor individuals in the Borrower's health&#13;
    regions IV and V defined in the Borrower's General Health Law, dated March&#13;
    2001.&#13;
&#13;
    The National Social Security Council (CNSS) and National Health Insurance&#13;
    Agency (SENASA) have submittedsatisfactory evidence to the Bank that 74,548&#13;
    poor individuals in these regions have been affiliated in the non-contributory&#13;
    healthinsurance program.&#13;
&#13;
24. Condition 5. A Presidential Decree has been issued declaring the effectiveness o f&#13;
    a regulation for the improvement of human resources management in the public&#13;
    health sector.&#13;
&#13;
    This decreewas signed andpublishedinthe Gaceta Oficial on October 28,2004.&#13;
&#13;
25. Condition 6. The following actions to revise the process o f categorizing the&#13;
    beneficiaries o f the Borrower's non-contributory health insurance program have&#13;
    been taken:    (a) a Presidential Decree has been issued for the declaration of&#13;
    effectiveness o f an amendment, approved by the Borrower's National Social&#13;
    Security Council, to the regulations governing such non-contributory health&#13;
    insurance program; and (b) an operational manual for community committees has&#13;
    been approved by the Borrower's Consejo Nacional de Seguridad Social for&#13;
    purposes o f selecting the beneficiaries o fthe above reference program.&#13;
&#13;
    (a) The Presidential Decree was signed on March 21, 2005 and subsequently&#13;
    published inthe Gaceta Oficial. (b) On May 18, 2005 the Consejo Nacional de&#13;
    la Seguridad Social, Act # 130, approved the modifications to the operational&#13;
    manual for community committees to conform to the Presidential Decree o f&#13;
   March 21, 2005 regarding the selection o f beneficiaries for the non-contributory&#13;
    healthinsurance program.&#13;
&#13;
26. Condition 7. A Presidential Decree has beenissued to eliminate at least 5 social&#13;
   programs considered to be ineffective pursuant to the matrix submitted by the&#13;
   Social Cabinet to the Bank on December 23,2003.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            DR SCRAL Social Sector TrancheReleaseMemorandum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   The Presidential Decree was signed on December 13, 2004 and published in&#13;
   national newspapers. The decree eliminates 8 social programs in the areas o f&#13;
   housing, health, training, employment and agriculture, which has reduced&#13;
   duplication and helpedconsolidate the sector.&#13;
&#13;
27. Condition 8. The Borrower has submitted to the Bank: (a) an independent&#13;
   monitoring report, prepared by one or more civil society organizations, on the&#13;
   progress achieved in the carrying out o f the Program, including the actions&#13;
   detailed inthis Schedule; and (b) the Borrower's comments on such report.&#13;
&#13;
   OnMay 24,2005 the Bank receivedthis independent monitoringreport, prepared&#13;
   by the Consultative Council of Civil Society, and the Borrower's comments on&#13;
   this report prepared by the Technical Secretariat of the Presidency. The report&#13;
   assesses government implementation o f five critical social sector reforms related&#13;
   to: (i) enrollment o f undocumented children in school; (ii)       performance o f the&#13;
   school feeding program; (iii)  support to undocumented families otherwise eligible&#13;
   for subsidized health insurance; (iv) implementation o f the subsidized nutrition&#13;
   program, "Comer es Primero"; and (v) implementation o f the conditional cash&#13;
   transfer program for poor mothers to in exchange for school attendance by their&#13;
   children.&#13;
&#13;
   Relative to the Government's SCRAL-supported policy to permit the enrollment&#13;
   o f undocumented children inschool, the civil society monitoring revealed uneven&#13;
   application o f this policy.   Approximately 75 percent o f 380 families with&#13;
   undocumented children surveyed indicated they had been able to enroll their&#13;
   children, but 25 percent o f these families stated their children had been denied&#13;
   access. The Bank raised this issue with the Minister o f Education, who re-&#13;
   clarified the Government's policy on May 18 at a major conference regarding&#13;
   undocumented Dominicans. Undocumented Dominican children will be allowed&#13;
   to enroll up to 8th grade, and will be given school identitycards untilsuch time as&#13;
   they obtain their late birth certificates.   This is a good case o f civil society&#13;
   monitoring resultinginefforts by Government to take corrective action.&#13;
&#13;
   Concerning the school feeding program, civil society concluded that inmore than&#13;
   90 percent o f the schools surveyed the meals arrived inthe quantity, quality and&#13;
   timing required. In a few cases, the number and size of the food rations were&#13;
   below requirements, because o f delays in Government payments to private sector&#13;
   suppliers.&#13;
&#13;
   With regards to support to undocumented families, civil society concluded the&#13;
   government's efforts were poorly organized, poorly targeted, one-off events&#13;
   which created publicity but little substantive change in the status o f&#13;
   undocumented families, such that the vast majority o f undocumented families&#13;
   remain excluded from nationalhealth insurance. The government agency charged&#13;
   with this action, the ConsejoNacional de Seguridad Social, acknowledged this in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             DR SCRAL Social Sector TrancheReleaseMemorandum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    their own report, concluding that targeted, household-specific actions are&#13;
    required.   Subsequent to the completion o f this report by civil society, the&#13;
    National Health Insurance Agency (SENASA) embarked on its own campaign to&#13;
    assist undocumented families, applying lessons leamed, and successfully&#13;
    documented and enrolled 36,000 newbeneficiaries.&#13;
&#13;
    Regardingthe nutrition subsidy program, civil society concluded the programwas&#13;
    indeed reaching extremely poor households and that the participating grocery&#13;
    stores were appropriately selected and were respecting the program's criteria, but&#13;
    that supervision o f fulfillment o fresponsibilities (such as child vaccination) which&#13;
    are a condition for receiving the subsidy had not begun. This i s not to be&#13;
    unexpected for a program which is just beginning, and this issue i s now being&#13;
    addressedas part o fpreparation o fthe Social ProtectionInvestment Loan.&#13;
&#13;
    Finally, concerning the conditional cash transfer program to poor mothers for&#13;
    their children's school attendance, civil society concluded the program was,&#13;
    overall, functioning with acceptable targeting mechanisms (that is, the vast&#13;
    majority o f beneficiaries were very poor mothers with children in school), but&#13;
    with uneven payment systems and no effective supervision o f children's&#13;
    attendance. This programhas since received extensive technical assistance as part&#13;
    o f the SCRAL, and has developed new systems and procedures for both payment&#13;
    and school attendance verification.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CONCLUSION&#13;
&#13;
28. In view o f the overall satisfactory performance and progress with the&#13;
   implementation o f the program supported by the Loan, including the&#13;
   macroeconomic framework and the specific conditions o f release referred to in&#13;
    Schedule 3 o f the Loan Agreement, the Bank has informed the Borrower o f the&#13;
    availability for disbursement o f the floating Tranche "A" o f the Loan in the&#13;
   equivalent o fUS$25 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6217431">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/08/6217431/dominican-republic-social-crisis-response-adjustment-loan-scral-project-release-floating-tranche-based-full-compliance
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/08/6217431/dominican-republic-social-crisis-response-adjustment-loan-scral-project-release-floating-tranche-based-full-compliance</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/08/6217431/dominican-republic-social-crisis-response-adjustment-loan-scral-project-release-floating-tranche-based-full-compliance</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2005-08-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/08/11/000160016_20050811154922/Rendered/INDEX/33304a.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/08/11/000160016_20050811154922/Rendered/PDF/33304a.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>7215</loan_no>
        <docdt>2005-08-10T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2005-08-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Dominican Republic - Social Crisis Response
            Adjustment Loan  (SCRAL) Project : release of floating
            tranche "A" based on full compliance
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Dominican Republic Social Crisis
            Response Adjustment Loan (SCRAL) was approved by the Board
            of Directors on February 12, 2004, and became effective on
            March 4, 2004. The loan comprises three single currency
            tranches: a first tranche, and two floating tranches
            henceforth identified as Tranche A and Tranche B. This
            Tranche Release Document (TRD) sets forth a description o f
            the tranche conditions and compliance status of the borrower
            for Tranche A of US$25 million, and concludes that that the
            macroeconomic framework and specific conditions of release
            referred to in Schedule 3 of the Loan Agreement have been satisfied.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Dominican Republic - Social Crisis Response
            Adjustment Loan  (SCRAL) Project : release of floating
            tranche "A" based on full compliance
        </docna>
        <display_title>Dominican Republic - Social
            Crisis Response Adjustment Loan  (SCRAL) Project : release
            of floating tranche "A" based on full compliance</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2005/08/6217431/dominican-republic-social-crisis-response-adjustment-loan-scral-project-release-floating-tranche-based-full-compliance</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>DO-Dominican Republic Social Crisis Response
            Adjustment Loan -- P085433</projn>
        <docty>Tranche Release Document</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Rural Poverty Reduction,Poverty Assessment,Safety Nets and Transfers,National Governance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Rural Development,Social Protections and Labor,Poverty Reduction,Governance,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Dominican Republic</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Caribbean!$!80452</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20050811154922</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <subsc>Central government administration,Other social services,Health,General education sector</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Rural Development,Social Protections and Labor,Poverty Reduction,Governance,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice,Health and other social services,Education</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            average level, Census data, civil society,
            decree, Development Goals, economic growth, elderly people,
            execution, expenditure, extreme poverty, families, financial
            institutions, financial sector, fiscal, fiscal gap, food
            consumption, food needs, government agency, Government
            Performance, Government's policy, health insurance,
            health insurance program, Health Service, household surveys,
            housing, Human Resources, income, inequality, Labor Force,
            legal reform, living conditions, living standards, macro
            stabilization, Macroeconomic Framework, malnutrition,
            mothers, National Planning, national poverty, poor, poor
            households, poor individuals, poor people, poverty
            assessment, poverty map, poverty targeting, Poverty Trends,
            Presidency, primary school, private sector, public actions,
            Public Health, public sector, public spending,
            rationalization, rural population, school dropouts, school
            feeding, school system, schools, Service Providers, social
            dimensions, Social indicators, Social Issues, social
            program, social programs, social protection, social sector,
            social sector expenditures, Social Security, targeting
            mechanisms, tax reform, Technical Assistance, transparency,
            unemployment, urban areas, vaccination, youth unemployment
        </keywd>
        <owner>Social Protection Sector (LCSHS)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Structural Adjustment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Caribbean</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>33304</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>CCT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Conditional Cash Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Dominican Republic</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>