<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                        Slovak Republic&#13;
     Health Sector ModernizationSupport Sectoral Adjustment Loan (Loan 7195- SK)&#13;
                         Second Tranche Release- FullComeliance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     I. BACKGROUND&#13;
&#13;
 1.     The HealthSector Modemization Support SectoralAdjustment Loan (HSMS SECAL)&#13;
 i s supportinghealth sector reforms inthe Slovak Republic (the Borrower) aimed at improving&#13;
the efficiency and effectiveness of public expenditures on health care, enhancing the quality&#13;
of services, and increasing the regulatory and planning and policy-making capacity of the&#13;
Ministry of Health. The reforms supported through the HSMS SECAL are part of the&#13;
Govemment's Manifesto for health sector reform, which was approvedinNovember 2002.&#13;
&#13;
                        11.     RECENTECONOMIC PERFORMANCE&#13;
&#13;
2.      The economy has been gathering strength over recent years. Real GDP has risen&#13;
steadily from 2.0 percent in 2000 to 5.5 percent in2004, and growth has remained robust at&#13;
5.1 percent in the first quarter of 2005. Meanwhile, inflation i s abating: average consumer&#13;
price inflation declined from 7.5 percent in 2004 to 2.7 percent in January-June 2005. High&#13;
inflation in2004 was causedby the last major round of de-regulation of administratedprices.&#13;
Core inflation remained low at 2.6 percent in 2004 and 1.1 percent in January-June 2005.&#13;
Despite large cuts in interest rates and several rounds of market interventions, the koruna i s&#13;
appreciating(5.7 percent year-on-year at end-December 2004 and 3.9 percent year-on-year at&#13;
end-June2005).&#13;
&#13;
3.      Although the current account deficit increased to 3.5 percent of GDP in 2004, it&#13;
remains within comfortable margins. Foreign direct investments have regained their&#13;
movement upwards, with manynew contracts inthe automotive, electronics and engineering&#13;
sectors, although the levels are still lower than in 2002. The expansion in exports halved,&#13;
from 22.5 percent in 2003 to 11.4 percent in 2004, below the 12.7 percent growth rate of&#13;
imports. The negative contribution of net exports to overall economic growth, caused&#13;
primarilyby the retooling of the German-ownedVolkswagen Slovakia car assembly plant,&#13;
Slovakia's major exporter, is expected to be a temporary occurrence. Rising technology&#13;
imports and recovering domestic demand are expected to fbrther fuel the rapid increase in&#13;
imports.&#13;
&#13;
4.      Supportedby strong revenueperformance, the fiscal outcome for 2004 was better than&#13;
expected. The 2004 consolidatedbudget deficit (including local budgetsand off-budget costs)&#13;
was 3.3 percent of GDP. The 2005 deficit i s targeted at 3.4 percent of GDP, excluding the&#13;
costs of pension reform, which will divert a portion o f payroll taxes from the state-run pay-&#13;
as-you-go scheme to private accounts (adjusted for pension reform, however, the projected&#13;
deficit would be 4.2 percent of GDP). The 2006-08 budget framework envisages a further&#13;
decline in the deficit (excluding the cost of pension reform) to 2.9 percent of GDP in 2006&#13;
and 1.6percent of GDP in2007, consistentwith Euro adoption in2009.&#13;
&#13;
5.      As a result of rapid GDP growth, the first quarter of 2005 reported 7.2 percent real&#13;
wage growth, after 2.5 percent growth in 2004 and 2.0 percent decline in 2003 (year-on-&#13;
year). However, wages still remain much lower than inother Visegrad countries:hourly labor&#13;
costs in2003 expressed as percentageof the EuropeanUnionaverage (EU15=100) were 25.6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 in Hungary, 26.7 in Poland, 27.3 in the Czech Republic, and only 20.2 in Slovakia. The&#13;
 increase was highest in agriculture (10.1 percent) which benefited the most from EU&#13;
 membership, in manufacturing (9.9 percent) reflecting increased demand o f foreign&#13;
 companies for domestic skilled labor, andpublic administration (7.5 percent).&#13;
&#13;
 6.     High unemployment remains a concem however, particularly among low-skilled&#13;
 labor. The registered unemployment rate declined to 13.1 percent in December 2004 and to&#13;
 11.1 percent in June 2005, down from the reported 15.6 percent in December 2003. Recent&#13;
 reforms, which resulted in a major improvement o f the business environment and increased&#13;
 labor market flexibility, attracted foreign investments, which - as seasonally adjusted figures&#13;
 seem to indicate - have started generating employment since the third quarter o f 2004. New&#13;
jobs have been generated especially in the westem part o f the country. Regional disparities&#13;
 remain deep, mainly because o f poor transport infrastructure, with the registered&#13;
 unemployment rate atjust 2.3 percent inthe capital, Bratislava, but approaching 28 percent in&#13;
 the two poorest districts located in central-south Slovakia. Meanwhile, the duration o f&#13;
 unemployment continues to rise.&#13;
&#13;
      111.   PROGRESSINIMPLEMENTING THE HEALTHREFORMPROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
 7.     The first two years o f the health reform program have focused on controlling the&#13;
growing indebtedness o f the health system and ensuring fiscal sustainability, and a series o f&#13;
measures have been adopted to keep health expenditures within the bounds set by revenue&#13;
collections. Collectively known as "Stabilization Measures", these efforts consisted&#13;
essentially of: (i)&#13;
                  introduction o fnominal copayments for patients; (ii) changes inthe process&#13;
and procedures related to procurement and reimbursemento f pharmaceuticals; and (iii)      pilot&#13;
projects for hospital restructuring in the three large districts o f Bratislava, Kosice and&#13;
Banska-Bystrica.&#13;
&#13;
8.      Patient copayments have been introduced at all levels and types o f care (except for&#13;
emergency care, preventive care and health services for children under the age of 6 years),&#13;
andpatients are now requiredto pay SKK20 peroutpatient visit andSKK5O per day for every&#13;
inpatient day for a maximum o f 10 days (the last day i s free). People identified as poor and&#13;
vulnerable receive a monthly subsidy o f SKK50 per person to defray additional expenses on&#13;
account o f copayment for health services. In the two years since the introduction o f fees in&#13;
the health care system, Slovaks have paid a total o f SKK2.7 billion to doctors, pharmacies,&#13;
andhospitals, andthe number ofvisit to physicians has decreasedby 8 percent. This hasbeen&#13;
accompanied by a reduction inthe number o f pharmaceutical prescriptions, resultinginhuge&#13;
savings for the healthcare system as a whole.&#13;
&#13;
9.      The impact o f copayments on access and utilization o f health services i s regularly&#13;
monitored, and initial survey reports and public opinion polls do not provide any evidence o f&#13;
access and utilization o f health care being adversely affected by the introduction o f&#13;
copayments. Early results indicate that only 2 percent o f those surveyed stated that they did&#13;
not seek care becauseo fthe copayments.&#13;
&#13;
10.     The most significant and far-reaching measure to control pharmaceutical expenditures&#13;
that has been adopted i s that of open competition among pharmaceutical providers, which i s&#13;
conducted on-line so that all bidders have complete information about the bids of their&#13;
competitors as well. This simple measure has led to a significant reduction in the prices o f&#13;
many drugs.At the same time, the insurance companies reimbursethe patients on the basis o f&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 the lowest price in every therapeutic category, which i s determinedon the basis o f daily dose&#13;
 requirementsand publishedin a handbook that is widely circulated among pharmacies. The&#13;
 pharmacies are required under the law to explain to the patient the substitutability and&#13;
 availability o f drugs and the different copayments associatedwith them. Patients choosing the&#13;
 higher-priced drugs make the higher copayment as determined and laid down in the&#13;
 handbook. As a result of these measures, the rate o f growth o f expenditures on drugs during&#13;
 2003-04 dropped to low single digits (adjusted for increase in V A T taxes), lower that the&#13;
 annual double-digit inflation inthe vicinity o f 12to 15 percent inprevious years.&#13;
&#13;
 11.     Rationalizingthe numbero fhospitals andhospital bedsby consolidating hospitals and&#13;
reconfiguring the mix o f hospital beds i s a priority in the ongoing reform program of the&#13;
Ministryof Health. A detailedassessment of all hospitals has been carried out and a master&#13;
plan for hospitals i s close to finalization. A network o f essential hospitals i s being drawn up&#13;
 and will be strengthened during the rationalization process. Hospitals and hospital beds&#13;
 identifiedas excess capacity inthe three big cities of Bratislava, Banska-Bystrica and Kosice&#13;
are included in the first round o f the consolidation process. The Ministry o f Health has also&#13;
established a Hospital Restructuring Fund to support specific capital investments in the&#13;
hospital sector inthe near future.&#13;
&#13;
 12.     Inaddition, steps are beingtakento corporatizepublic hospitals andmakethemfully&#13;
autonomous in their functions. Corporate hospitals will not have an implicit govemment&#13;
guarantee, which will send an important signal to suppliersthat they cannot simply continue&#13;
to lend to hospitals. This is expected to create hard budget constraints for hospitals and&#13;
compel them to attach high priority to efficiency. Corporate hospitals will be allowed to&#13;
retain savings and keep revenues, which they may re-invest in the hospital operation, thus&#13;
generating additional incentives for hospitals to change their input mix and align inputs more&#13;
closely with outputs. For hospitals that continue to build arrears, there will be the prospect o f&#13;
bankruptcy or the possibility o f selected bailouts by the Government or commercial buy-&#13;
backs inexchange for a rationalizationplan.&#13;
&#13;
 13.     Since the hospital restructuring program i s focusing on the three big cities o f&#13;
Bratislava, Banska-Bystrica and Kosice where overcapacity i s most severe, the rationalization&#13;
process o f hospital facilities i s not likely to have a negative impact on access to health care&#13;
services. The Ministry o f Health recognizes that the rationalization o f hospital services in&#13;
rural areas will need to be conducted with caution. This i s particularly true for mountainous&#13;
areas, where travel time to the nearest facility might be severely extended in case o f a&#13;
hospital closure. These facilities are proposed to be included in the network o f essential&#13;
hospitals andprotected from closure.&#13;
&#13;
14.     The net result o f the stabilization measures was that annual systemic debt fell fkom&#13;
SKK9 billion in 2002 to SKK4.8 billion in 2003 to SKK2.4 billion in 2004, which i s under&#13;
0.3 percent o fGDP.&#13;
&#13;
15.     System measures - the second o f the three steps in the reform program - aim to&#13;
increase the efficiency o f the system and mobilize resources. Supporting legislation for this&#13;
step o f the reform program has already been passed in the Parliament. The system measures&#13;
place emphasis on reforming the health insurance system and reducing the benefit package&#13;
covered by mandatory social health insurance. Legislation with respect to these measures has&#13;
taken the form o f the following six Acts: (ijAct on Health Insurance, which regulates social&#13;
and private health insurance; (iij Act on Health Insurance Companies and the Health Care&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 Surveillance Authority, which introduces budget constraints, transparent financial&#13;
 relationships, accounting and auditing; (iii)Act on Providers, which introduces increased&#13;
 independence in decision-making and autonomy o f individual healthcare providers and their&#13;
 responsibility for consequences of their decisions; (iv) Act on the Ambulance Service, which&#13;
 organizes and integrates emergency service; (v) Act on Healthcare, which defines healthcare&#13;
 and forms of its provision, rights and duties, handling of health documentation, and&#13;
 regulation o f provision o f health-related services; and (vi) Treatment Act, which defines and&#13;
 develops the scope o f services covered under social health insurance. Network measures- the&#13;
 thirdofthe three steps inthereformprogram-aimat improving the quality andefficiency o f&#13;
 health care providers. A Health Care Surveillance Authority has recently been set up for this&#13;
 purpose, and has become operational. A Hospital Restructuring Fundhas recently been set up&#13;
 andi s expected to become hllyoperational soon.&#13;
&#13;
              IV.     PROGRESSAGAINST TRANCHE RELEASECRITERIA&#13;
&#13;
 16.     The Borrower has maintained a satisfactory macroeconomic policy framework, as&#13;
judged on the basis o f the macroeconomic scenario defined in the 2004 Country Partnership&#13;
 Strategy with the Borrower. According to this macroeconomic scenario, economic growth in&#13;
the Slovak Republic would exceed the average for EU countries, inflation would be&#13;
maintained at low levels, substantial FDI flows would continue, the current account deficit&#13;
would average about 3 percent of GDP through 2007, and the Govemment's fiscal deficit&#13;
would decline to 3 percent o f GDP in that year. These criteria would also be considered to&#13;
constitute satisfactory progress towards meeting the Maastricht criteria and subsequently&#13;
joining the European Monetary Union. All o f these criteria have been met, as described in&#13;
Section I1above, confirming that the Borrower has maintained a satisfactory macroeconomic&#13;
policy framework.&#13;
&#13;
 17.    Progress against specific tranche release criteria as set out in Section Io f Schedule 2&#13;
o fthe LoanAgreement i s described below.&#13;
&#13;
18.     Condition 1: The contribution of the health system to the general budget deficit has&#13;
been reduced to one percent (1 percent) o f GDP.&#13;
&#13;
19.     This condition has been met. The stock of debt attributable to accumulated health&#13;
system deficits has continued to grow but at a declining pace, which i s the goal o f this&#13;
condition. In2003 the health system deficit fell to less than 0.4 percent o f GDP and to less&#13;
than 0.3 percent in2004. The gap is projected to be closed in2005. Stabilization measures&#13;
introduced during the first two years o f the reform program contributed significantly to this&#13;
narrowing o f the gap between health system revenues and expenditures. These measures&#13;
included the introduction o fnominal copayments for patients, simple but effective changes in&#13;
pharmaceutical policies, and hospital restructurings. As a result, the annual deficit in the&#13;
health sector fell from SKK9 billion in2002 to SKK4.8 billion in2003 and to SKK2.4 billion&#13;
in2004, corresponding to thedecliningpercentagesof GDP shown above.&#13;
&#13;
20.     Condition 2: The Borrower has developed mechanisms and institutional&#13;
arrangements acceptable to the Bank for the inclusion of new treatment procedures and&#13;
pharmaceuticals into the essentialpackage o fhealth services.&#13;
&#13;
21.     This conditionhas been met. In September 2004, the Borrower's National Council&#13;
passed Act No. 577/2004 on the scope o f healthcare covered by public health insurance and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 on settlements for healthcare-relatedservices, which regulates, inter alia, the inclusion ofnew&#13;
 treatment procedures and pharmaceuticals into the essential package of health services. The&#13;
 Act became effective on January 1, 2005. Article 3 of this Act establishes the Catalogue of&#13;
 Health Procedures in relation to Diagnosis, and lays down the criteria for inclusion of health&#13;
 procedures into this Catalogue. Article 12 of the Act lays down the criteria for inclusion of&#13;
 new pharmaceuticals, and establishes that new drugs can be introduced in the List of Drugs&#13;
 only ifit is demonstratedthat the drug's benefitsare superior to those of similar drugs already&#13;
 in the List of Drugs. The Statute of the Catalogue Commission was approved by the&#13;
 Ministerial Board inMarch2005 and the Chairmanand 11members ofthe Commissionhave&#13;
 been appointed already. The Catalogue Commission is functioning as an advisory board to&#13;
 the Ministerof Health andhas its principal offices inthe Ministry of Health.&#13;
&#13;
 22.      Condition3: Selective purchasing and contract monitoring capacity satisfactory to&#13;
 theBankhasbeendevelopedinthe Health InsuranceCompanies.&#13;
&#13;
 23.      This condition has been met. Selective purchasing and contracting capacity has&#13;
 been developed in the Health Insurance Companies. Two companies - VSZP and Sideria -&#13;
 started to implement selective purchasing in 2004 while others have started this year. The&#13;
process of collection and analysis of relevant data for criteria selection has started and the&#13;
 first set ofresultsare expectedby the end ofthe year.&#13;
&#13;
24.      Condition4: The Borrower has reduced the number of hospitals incurring debt by&#13;
twenty-five percent (25 percent) comparedto 2002.&#13;
&#13;
25.      This condition has been met. Of the 46 health care facilities under review, eight&#13;
facilities had no new debts by 2004 (defined as outstanding arrears above S K K 1 million at&#13;
the endofthe year) and five facilities haddebts smaller than2002 levels.&#13;
&#13;
26.      Condition5: The Health Care SurveillanceAuthority has become operational and i s&#13;
implementingits businessplan.&#13;
&#13;
27.      This conditionhas been met. In September 2004, the Borrower's National Council&#13;
passed Act No. 578/2004 on healthcare providers, medical workers, professional&#13;
organizationsinthe health services and on the amendment and supplementingo fcertain laws,&#13;
which constitutes the legal framework for the Health Care Surveillance Authority (HCSA).&#13;
The Act became effective on January 1, 2005. HCSA became fully operational and&#13;
functioning in November 2004, and has begun to perform its regulatory functions. HCSA&#13;
also controls and supervises the legal and financial matters of the public health insurance&#13;
companies for the fulfillment of obligations established in the law and those that emanate&#13;
from the healthcontractswith beneficiaries.&#13;
&#13;
28.      Condition6: The Borrower has developed, on the basis of a mapping exercise, an&#13;
implementation plan satisfactory to the Bank for rationalization of hospital capacity in the&#13;
districts of Bratislava, Kosice and BanskaBystrica.&#13;
&#13;
29.      This condition has beenmet. The plansfor rationalization ofthe hospital capacity in&#13;
the districts ofBratislava, Kogice and BanskaBystrica, also called Restructuring Plans for the&#13;
respective districts, have been developedbasedon the results of the nation-wide assessment&#13;
of hospitals carried out by experts between October 2004 and February 2005. The mapping&#13;
and evaluation exercise covered all 44 state owned hospitals; 19 non-state hospitals also&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 participated in the exercise. The preparation o f the Restructuring Plans i s part o f a complex&#13;
 process o f rationalizing hospital capacity in Slovakia interlinkedwith the updated definition&#13;
 o f the MinimumPublic Network o fproviders andthe preparation o f the HealthRestructuring&#13;
 Fund (the financial tool for the realization of the rationalization and development plans&#13;
 prepared within the framework o fthe Hospital Master Plan - MinimumPublic Network). The&#13;
 Ministry o fHealth issued a Regulation on the MinimumNetwork ofHealthCare Providers in&#13;
 November 2004, which also has an impact on the Restructuring Plans in the three selected&#13;
 districts.&#13;
&#13;
 30.     Condition 7: Seventy-five percent (75 percent) of hospitals in the districts of&#13;
 Bratislava, Kosice and Banska Bystrica have commenced operating as autonomous entities&#13;
 with self-governingboards.&#13;
&#13;
 3 1.     This conditionhas been met. In September 2004, the Borrower's National Council&#13;
passed the six health Acts that formed the legislative basis o f the health care reforms in the&#13;
 country. This legislation, which became effective on January 1, 2005, envisages the&#13;
 transformation o f health insurance companies into joint-stock companies and health care&#13;
 facilities into either joint-stock companies or not-for-profit organizations. The process o f&#13;
 transformation o f health care providers under the governance o f the Ministry o f Health i s&#13;
covered by Articles 84 and 91 o f Act No. 578/2004 (on Health Care Providers, etc.). The&#13;
previous legislative status allowed for full autonomy o f the hospital directors, but was based&#13;
on the Law on Public Service. Under the new legislation, the autonomy i s based on the&#13;
Commercial Code while undergoing transformation from state-owned entities intojoint-stock&#13;
companies.&#13;
&#13;
32.      Six hospitals in Bratislava have been combined into one faculty hospital, which has&#13;
become autonomous. Likewise, the specialized cardiology and oncology hospitals in&#13;
Bratislava, two general hospitals and one carlology hospital in Banska-Bystrica and two&#13;
general hospitals, one cardiology hospital and one oncology hospital in Kosice have also&#13;
become autonomous. With this, all hospitals (i.e., 100 percent) in the districts o f Bratislava,&#13;
Banska Bystrica and Kosice have become autonomous. The nature and extent o f hospital&#13;
autonomy as it stands today empowers the hospital directors to hire and fire their staff freely&#13;
(withinthe bounds laid down by the MinimumPersonnel Requirements)and to remunerate&#13;
them based on performance. Health facilities also have autonomy in procurement and can&#13;
choose what, how much and when they will procure as long as it i s within the fkamework o f&#13;
the Public Procurement Act. Health facilities enter into direct contracts with the health&#13;
insurance companies, and are authorized to retain their earnings from all business activities,&#13;
including from patient copayments.&#13;
&#13;
33.      Condition 8: The Borrower has developed a concept and implementation plan for&#13;
social care and long term care, acceptable to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
34.      This condition has been met. A detailed and comprehensive concept,&#13;
implementation planand comparative study for social and long-term care has beendeveloped&#13;
andpublished. A draft law basedonthe above mentioned documents has also beenprepared.&#13;
&#13;
35.      Condition 9: The Borrower is implementing a public information campaign in&#13;
support o fthe healthreform.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
36.     This conditionhas been met. The public information campaign beinginiplemented&#13;
by the Borrower includes conferences, workshops, prints, monitoring o f media, etc. in&#13;
support o f the health reform. Duringthe first year, the public information campaign produced&#13;
a large volume o f printed information materials (brochures, leaflets, posters) targeted to the&#13;
general public. These covered issues such as "Information for the Patients on Health Care&#13;
Fees," "The Rights of the Patients within the Reform Laws," "Get Informed on your&#13;
Pharmaceutical," and "Payments within the Health Care System." Materials targeted to&#13;
specialists and health care staff included "Health Care in the Slovak Republic Concept,"&#13;
"New Healthcare: News and Information," "New Healthcare: How It Will Be?," "Reform&#13;
Agenda: Health Reform in Slovakia," "The Analysis o f the Development until the Approval&#13;
o f Six Refomi Laws," "Slovak Reform o f Health Care: From Fees to Systemic Changes,"&#13;
"The State of Social and Long-term Care in Slovakia," a comparative study "Long-term Care&#13;
inOECD Countries and the System of Social Services in Slovakia," "Model for Long-term&#13;
Care for the Slovak Republic Based on the Integration o f Health Care and Social Care."&#13;
Selected materials were published inall importantnation-wide dailies and weeklies.&#13;
&#13;
37.     Several conferences have also been organized as part of the public information&#13;
campaign, including an intemational conference on "New Healthcare as a Challenge and&#13;
Opportunity" and two conferences in cooperation with WHO on "Health Care Reform:&#13;
Strategic Purchase o f Health Care" and "National Medicine Policy: Pharmaco-economics as&#13;
Effective Tool for Practice." Several seminars and workshops for specialists have been&#13;
organized in cooperation with the Association o f Private Doctors and the Slovak Medical&#13;
Society. Inorder to establish a virtual information center, the Ministry o f Healthhas launched&#13;
aninternetportal www.novezdravotnictvo.sk and its English version www.newhealthcare.sk.&#13;
&#13;
                                     V.      CONCLUSION&#13;
&#13;
38.       In view o f the overall performance and progress with the implementation of the&#13;
program supported by the loan, the maintenance o f a satisfactory macroeconomic policy&#13;
framework, and the compliance with the specific conditions o f release referred to Section&#13;
2.02 (d) (11) o f the Loan Agreement, the Bank has informed the Borrower o f the availability&#13;
of the second tranche inthe amount of Euro 15 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6227473">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/08/6227473/slovak-republic-health-sector-modernization-support-sectoral-adjustment-loan-project-release-second-tranche-full-compliance
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/08/6227473/slovak-republic-health-sector-modernization-support-sectoral-adjustment-loan-project-release-second-tranche-full-compliance</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/08/6227473/slovak-republic-health-sector-modernization-support-sectoral-adjustment-loan-project-release-second-tranche-full-compliance</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2005-08-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/08/16/000160016_20050816114736/Rendered/INDEX/33333b.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/08/16/000160016_20050816114736/Rendered/PDF/33333b.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>7195</loan_no>
        <datestored>2005-08-16T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2005-08-11T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Slovak Republic - Health Sector
            Modernization Support Sectoral Adjustment Loan Project :
            release of the second tranche - full compliance
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Health Sector Modemization Support
            Sectoral Adjustment Loan is supporting health sector reforms
            in the Slovak Republic (the Borrower) aimed at improving the
            efficiency and effectiveness of public expenditures on
            health care, enhancing the quality of services, and
            increasing the regulatory and planning and policy-making
            capacity of the Ministry of Health. This memorandum
            summarizes progress in the implementation of the sectoral
            reform program and actions taken by the Government to meet
            the specific conditions of the second tranche. The
            memorandum concludes that the conditions for the release of
            the second tranche have been met, that substantial progress
            has been made in implementing the overall sectoral reform
            program, and that the Borrower has maintained a satisfactory
            macroeconomic policy framework. In view of the overall
            progress in implementing the program supported by the loan,
            and the full compliance with the specific conditions of
            release referred to in Section 2.02 (d) (11) of the Loan
            Agreement and described in this Tranche Release Document,
            the Government is being informed that the second tranche
            (Euro 15 million) of the Loan is being released for disbursement.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Slovak Republic - Health Sector
            Modernization Support Sectoral Adjustment Loan Project :
            release of the second tranche - full compliance
        </docna>
        <display_title>Slovak Republic - Health Sector
            Modernization Support Sectoral Adjustment Loan Project :
            release of the second tranche - full compliance</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2005/08/6227473/slovak-republic-health-sector-modernization-support-sectoral-adjustment-loan-project-release-second-tranche-full-compliance</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>SK-Health Reform Project -- P065954</projn>
        <docty>Tranche Release Document</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Regional Rural Development,Gender and Health,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Health Systems Development &amp; Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Gender,Health, Nutrition and Population,Rural Development,Communities and Human Settlements</teratopic>
        <count>Slovak Republic</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20050816114736</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Central government administration,Health,Compulsory health finance</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Gender,Health, Nutrition and Population,Rural Development,Communities and Human Settlements</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice,Health and other social services</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            agriculture, allocative efficiency,
            Ambulance Service, cities, districts, doctors, economic
            growth, expenditures, health care, health expenditures,
            Health facilities, HEALTH REFORM, Health Sector, health
            services, health system, hospital autonomy, hospital beds,
            hospital services, hospitals, laws, media, Medicine,
            Partnership, patients, pharmacies, physicians, posters,
            professional organizations, public health, public hospitals,
            rural areas, settlements, Social Services, specialists,
            sustainability, transport, unemployment, workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Human Development Sector Unit (ECSHD)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Sector Adjustment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF026121-PHRD-HEALTH SECTOR
            MODERNIZATION PROJECT,TF039771-SLOVAKIA - HEALTH PROJECT</trustfund>
        <repnb>33333</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability and Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Health Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery of Health Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Care Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Service Management and Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Medical Supplies, Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceutical Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Services Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceuticals</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Slovakia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>