<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                          Highlights of IFC's 2005 Annual Report&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Investing in Progress&#13;
with Experience, Innovation, and Partnership&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The International Finance Corporation invests in private sector enterprises and provides               Strategic Objectives&#13;
technical assistance and advisory services, helping to reduce poverty and improve people's              · Expanding access to finance. IFC works&#13;
lives. In fiscal 2005, IFC played a key role in promoting a sustainable private sector in                 with financial institutions to broaden access&#13;
developing and transition countries. The Corporation set a record in its profitability and                to finance, with emphasis on smaller&#13;
achieved measurable development impact.                                                                   enterprises, housing finance, and leasing.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          IFC's advice and innovative products also&#13;
This fiscal year...&#13;
                                                                                                          strengthen financial markets.&#13;
 · To support tsunami relief, IFC set up a matching grant program for partner companies                 · Increasing private participation in key&#13;
   in East and South Asia. IFC also established a tourism loan facility to support the recovery.          sectors. In infrastructure and social&#13;
 · IFC established the Global Trade Finance Program, which helps banks deliver trade                      sectors, IFC promotes new approaches&#13;
   financing by providing risk coverage in difficult markets.                                             that increase private participation in&#13;
 · With the World Bank, IFC continued to assess the investment climate of developing                      delivering crucial services.&#13;
   countries, including through the annual Doing Business report.&#13;
                                                                                                        · Helping successful enterprises grow.&#13;
 · Through structured finance and local currency financing, IFC arranged an increasing&#13;
                                                                                                          With many client companies poised to&#13;
   number of innovative transactions that build domestic financial markets.&#13;
                                                                                                          become competitive global players, IFC&#13;
 · IFC increased investments in renewable energies and helped develop the market&#13;
                                                                                                          provides long-term financing and global&#13;
   for carbon finance.&#13;
                                                                                                          experience to raise standards and&#13;
 · The Corporation advised governments on bringing private participation into&#13;
                                                                                                          improve performance.&#13;
   infrastructure, health care, and other public services, with 25 such transactions&#13;
   underway in FY05.                                                                                    · Focusing where needs are greatest. In&#13;
&#13;
 · With donors, IFC sponsored financial markets technical assistance in more than                         high-risk and low-income countries, IFC&#13;
&#13;
   60 countries, with emphasis on access to finance for small businesses and on high-risk                 uses its capital and advice to demonstrate&#13;
&#13;
   or low-income economies, particularly in Africa and the Middle East.                                   the viability of private enterprises and to&#13;
&#13;
 · IFC launched key initiatives to support women entrepreneurs and grassroots businesses;                 help governments improve the&#13;
&#13;
   the Corporation also helped set up a regional association of African business schools and              investment climate.&#13;
&#13;
   assisted private companies in addressing HIV/AIDS.                                                   · Ensuring sustainability. IFC applies its&#13;
 · IFC reviewed its Safeguard Policies, Policy on Disclosure of Information, and                          expertise in corporate governance and&#13;
   Environmental, Health, and Safety Guidelines through broad consultation with                           environmental and social development to&#13;
   stakeholders, including governments, IFC clients and partners, and representatives                     strengthen clients' operations and to&#13;
   of civil society.                                                                                      improve practices throughout the project&#13;
 · Malta and Timor-Leste joined IFC, bringing membership to 178 countries.                                finance community.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                OPERATIONAL RESULTS SUMMARY, FY05                                       RESOURCES AND INCOME, FY05&#13;
&#13;
   New projects committed:                                               236, in 67 countries         Operating income                     $1.95 billion&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      Net income                           $2.02 billion&#13;
   Total financing committed:                                                   $6.45 billion&#13;
&#13;
      Financing committed for IFC's own account:                                $5.37 billion&#13;
                                                                                                      Paid-in capital                      $2.4 billion&#13;
      Syndications mobilized from other financial institutions:                 $1.08 billion&#13;
                                                                                                      Retained earnings                    $7.4 billion&#13;
&#13;
   Total committed portfolio:                                                   $19.3 billion*        Borrowings for the fiscal year       $2.0 billion&#13;
&#13;
      Loans as a % of committed portfolio:                                             77%            Net worth                            $9.8 billion&#13;
&#13;
      Equity as a % of committed portfolio:                                            17%&#13;
&#13;
      Guarantees as a % of committed portfolio:                                          5%&#13;
&#13;
      Risk management products as a % of committed portfolio:                            1%&#13;
&#13;
   *For IFC's own account as of June 30, 2005.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Highlights of FY05 Operations&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                            COURTESY OF NEWMONT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IFC's operating income rose to a record $1.95 billion in FY05,                                                                At June 30, 2005, IFC's committed portfolio was $19.3 billion,&#13;
from $982 million in FY04. The strong growth reflected                                                                  an increase of 7.6 percent over the previous fiscal year. IFC also&#13;
significant realized gains on sales of investments, robust dividend                                                     held and managed for participants $5.3 billion in syndicated&#13;
income from the equity portfolio, greater loan portfolio income,                                                        loans. The committed portfolio included 1,314 companies in&#13;
and the positive impact of a release of loss reserves.                                                                  119 countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
How                                                                                                                                What&#13;
IFC offers a full range of investment products; the Corporation also                                                               IFC is active in all commercial sectors in its developing member countries.&#13;
&#13;
increasingly provides technical assistance and advisory services to                                                                Funding is often accompanied by assistance on industry best practice,&#13;
&#13;
private sector enterprises and related government agencies.                                                                        corporate governance, environmental and social issues, and links with&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                   local small businesses.&#13;
&#13;
                    COMMITMENTS BY PRODUCT, FY05                                                                                                         COMMITMENTS BY SECTOR, FY05&#13;
                    Includes IFC's account and syndications (millions of U.S. dollars)                                                               Includes IFC's account and syndications (millions of U.S. dollars)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Finance and insurance                                               $2,227            34.5%&#13;
                                                 TOTAL $6,449&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Transportation and warehousing                                         561             8.7&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Industrial and consumer products                                       552             8.6&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Loan syndications 1,076                                                    Primary metals                                                         330            5.1&#13;
       Risk management                                                                                                             Pulp and paper                                                         327            5.1&#13;
                   products 4&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Utilities                                                              322             5.0&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Oil, gas, and mining                                                   314             4.9&#13;
           Guarantees 216                                                                                                          Agriculture and forestry                                               278             4.3&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Chemicals                                                              237             3.7&#13;
             Equity** 612                                                                                                          Nonmetallic mineral product manufacturing                              222             3.4&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Accommodation and tourism services                                     203             3.1&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Information                                                            200            3.1&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Collective investment vehicles                                         188             2.9&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              Loans* 4,541                                         Wholesale and retail trade                                             143             2.2&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Food and beverages                                                     139             2.2&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Textiles, apparel, and leather                                          84             1.3&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Plastics and rubber                                                     41             0.6&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Education services                                                      39             0.6&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Construction and real estate                                            23             0.3&#13;
&#13;
                                    * Includes loan-type quasi-equity products.                                                    Health care                                                             20             0.3&#13;
&#13;
                                  ** Includes equity-type quasi-equity products.&#13;
                                                                                                                                   TOTAL COMMITMENTS                                                  $6,449            100%&#13;
   IFC also mobilized $1.1 billion through structured finance related to guarantees, loans, and equity investments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Where&#13;
IFC invests in companies and financial institutions in all developing regions. The 2005 Annual Report provides a full list of investment commitments.&#13;
&#13;
(Projects involving more than one developing region are classified as "Global.")&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              COMMITMENTS BY REGION, FY05                                                                             INVESTMENT PORTFOLIO BY REGION, FY05&#13;
                           Includes IFC's account and syndications (millions of U.S. dollars)                                                                For IFC's account (millions of U.S. dollars)&#13;
&#13;
                                                         TOTAL $6,449                                                                                                      TOTAL $19,274&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            Global                                                                                                              Global&#13;
                                    Middle East and            95          Sub-Saharan Africa* 445                                                       Middle East and        245         Sub-Saharan Africa* 1,698&#13;
                                     North Africa*                                                                                                        North Africa*&#13;
                                           315                                                                                                                 1,210&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      East Asia and                                                                                                  East Asia and&#13;
                                                                                       the Pacific                                                                                                     the Pacific&#13;
                                                                                            811                                                                                                          2,940&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Latin America                                                       South Asia                                       Latin America&#13;
                  and the Caribbean                                                           643                                     and the Caribbean&#13;
                         1,783                                                                                                                 6,125&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                        South Asia&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                         1,634&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    Europe and                                                                                                        Europe and&#13;
                                                                   Central Asia*                                                                                                     Central Asia*&#13;
                                                                        2,357                                                                                                            5,423&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        *Some amounts include regional shares of investments that are officially classified as global projects.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Regional Overview for FY05&#13;
See IFC's Annual Report for more information on the year's regional activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sub-Saharan Africa                                                               Europe and Central Asia&#13;
Commitments: 30 projects in 14 countries                                         Commitments: 67 projects in 15 countries&#13;
&#13;
Total financing: $445 million for IFC's account                                  Total financing: $2.4 billion ($1.9 billion for IFC's account)&#13;
                                                                                                                 ($419 million in syndications)&#13;
IFC is working to address Africa's development through a combination&#13;
&#13;
of investment and technical assistance. IFC's new investments include            In the region's financial sector, IFC continues to be active in restructuring&#13;
&#13;
a microfinance institution and a cement producer in Nigeria, a black             and privatizing existing institutions and in promoting the development of&#13;
&#13;
economic empowerment transaction with a South African bank, and                  housing finance, leasing companies, and securitization. In infrastructure, the&#13;
&#13;
innovative funding for private schools in Ghana. Technical assistance            Corporation is emphasizing investments in the energy and transportation&#13;
&#13;
is being delivered through the new Private Enterprise Partnership for            sectors and helping privatize utilities in potential EU accession countries.&#13;
&#13;
Africa, a joint program with IDA at the World Bank, and other                    IFC is also expanding access to financing and business expertise for smaller&#13;
&#13;
initiatives; the focus includes leasing, export promotion, reforms of            enterprises, targeting strategic industries through building supply chains and&#13;
&#13;
business regulation, and helping companies respond to the challenges             access to markets, and working to improve the investment environment and&#13;
&#13;
of HIV/AIDS. IFC also initiated several infrastructure advisory                  strengthen corporate governance. Examples of investments in the region&#13;
&#13;
assignments this year and concluded a successful private concession              include vehicle leasing operations, a household appliance manufacturer,&#13;
&#13;
for a port in Madagascar.                                                        discount retail outlets, a gas distribution company, and hospitals.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
East Asia and the Pacific                                                       Latin America and the Caribbean&#13;
Commitments: 40 projects in 11 countries                                         Commitments: 54 projects in 17 countries&#13;
&#13;
Total financing: $811 million ($740 million for IFC's account)                   Total financing: $1.8 billion ($1.4 billion for IFC's account)&#13;
                                 ($72 million in syndications)                                                   ($385 million in syndications)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IFC's focus includes deepening and diversifying the region's financial           IFC is emphasizing long-term financing to a wide range of corporates&#13;
&#13;
systems, strengthening corporate governance and environmental                    and investments with a broad impact on social and economic inclusion.&#13;
&#13;
performance, and improving the climate for private investments in                This year IFC addressed underinvestment in infrastructure with projects&#13;
&#13;
infrastructure. The year saw financial sector investments that support           in the energy and transportation sectors and continued to introduce&#13;
&#13;
housing finance, leasing, and increased lending to smaller enterprises;          structured finance and other innovative financial products in local capital&#13;
&#13;
in Malaysia, IFC became the first supranational to undertake a bond              markets. Committed projects ranged from major manufacturers, a wind&#13;
&#13;
issue using Islamic finance. Infrastructure investments include a                power plant, and a university, to companies in the telecommunications,&#13;
&#13;
shipping firm in China and an electricity distributor in the Philippines         airline, port, and logistics sectors. Technical assistance is a rapidly&#13;
&#13;
that combines hydroelectric and photovoltaic power. The technical                growing component of IFC's work in the region, with a focus on&#13;
&#13;
assistance work of IFC's four regional facilities includes innovative            privatization, streamlined business regulations, improved access to&#13;
&#13;
partnerships to establish more sustainable supply chains for industries          markets, more socially responsible enterprises, and stronger&#13;
&#13;
in China and Indonesia.                                                          competitiveness for small businesses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
South Asia                                                                      Middle East and North Africa&#13;
Commitments: 20 projects in 2 countries                                          Commitments: 21 projects in 8 countries&#13;
&#13;
Total financing: $643 million ($443 million for IFC's account)                   Total financing: $315 million&#13;
                                 ($200 million in syndications)&#13;
                                                                                 With the launch of the Private Enterprise Partnership for the Middle East&#13;
&#13;
IFC invested in manufacturing companies to help them become                      and North Africa, IFC increased its capacity to provide technical assistance&#13;
&#13;
internationally competitive, in tourism projects to help regional                throughout the region in addition to financing. The new facility is helping&#13;
&#13;
companies recover from the tsunami, and in water, power, and                     train Iraqi bankers, surveying corporate governance at banks in Lebanon,&#13;
&#13;
telecommunications projects to help sustain economic growth and                  and promoting leasing in Afghanistan and Yemen. IFC's investment program&#13;
&#13;
improve the quality of life for communities. New investments include             this year encompassed the financial sector, manufacturing, oil and gas,&#13;
&#13;
a port management company, a merchant hydropower plant, and                      education, agribusiness, and infrastructure. IFC is also providing infrastructure&#13;
&#13;
emerging companies in pharmaceuticals, biotechnology, and IT                     advisory services for irrigation in Morocco and an airport in Saudi Arabia.&#13;
&#13;
outsourcing. IFC's SouthAsia Enterprise Development Facility                     The Corporation provided its first-ever funding for a Murabaha facility, an&#13;
&#13;
continues its work to improve the business environment, strengthen               Islamic finance product, and, as part of its own borrowings, launched a&#13;
&#13;
providers of business services, and increase access to financing for             bond issue in Moroccan dirhams.&#13;
&#13;
smaller businesses.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Development Impact&#13;
                                                                                                                                   KENJI YUHAKU&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IFC continues to show positive development impact, as              environmental, social, health, and safety performance&#13;
measured by the independent Operations Evaluation Group,           have not improved in line with other outcomes.&#13;
which evaluates mature projects in terms of project business     · IFC has invested more, and achieved better outcomes, in&#13;
performance, economic sustainability, environmental impacts,       key sectors--financial markets, infrastructure, information&#13;
and private sector development. This year's findings showed        technology, and health and education--increasing their&#13;
the following trends:                                              share of total commitments to 55 percent in FY05.&#13;
 · Based on a synthesis of performance ratings for projects      · The risk profile of recent commitments has improved.&#13;
   approved in 2001­2003, 59 percent of operations made          · IFC has successfully steered resources toward poorer&#13;
   positive contributions to development.                          countries and regions where access to finance is&#13;
 · IFC project success rates are improving generally, but          most difficult.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
How IFC Operations Help Reduce Poverty and Improve People's Lives&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      INPUTS                       OUTPUTS                               OUTCOMES                                    IMPACTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Investment                              Demonstration&#13;
   Operations                                  Effects&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     Poverty&#13;
                                                                                                                    Reduction&#13;
&#13;
                              Sustainable                  Sustainable&#13;
                                                                                       Economic&#13;
                                 Private                  Private Sector&#13;
                                                                                        Growth&#13;
                              Investment                   Development&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    Improved&#13;
                                                                                                               Living Standards&#13;
    Technical                                 Improved&#13;
    Assistance,                                Business&#13;
 Advisory Services                             Climate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
For IFC's Annual Report and information on products&#13;
and services, please contact IFC Corporate Relations.&#13;
&#13;
INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION&#13;
2121 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433 USA&#13;
Telephone 202-473-3800&#13;
Fax 202-974-4384&#13;
www.ifc.org&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6311742">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/01/6311742/investing-progress-experience-innovation-partnership-highlights-ifcs-2005-annual-report
        </url>
        <availablein>Japanese,Russian,Portuguese,French,Spanish,Chinese,Arabic,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="Japanese" entityid="000160016_20050927184521" node_id="6311742"/>
            <available_in lang="Russian" entityid="000160016_20050928094718" node_id="6311742"/>
            <available_in lang="Portuguese" entityid="000350881_20091007112812" node_id="6311742"/>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="000160016_20050927183607" node_id="6311742"/>
            <available_in lang="Spanish" entityid="000160016_20050928100856" node_id="6311742"/>
            <available_in lang="Chinese" entityid="000090341_20051205102340" node_id="6311742"/>
            <available_in lang="Arabic" entityid="000160016_20050927184147" node_id="6311742"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/01/6311742/investing-progress-experience-innovation-partnership-highlights-ifcs-2005-annual-report</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/01/6311742/investing-progress-experience-innovation-partnership-highlights-ifcs-2005-annual-report</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2005-09-27T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2005-09-27T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/09/27/000160016_20050927183155/Rendered/INDEX/336580ENGLISH0IFC1ExecSummary12005.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/09/27/000160016_20050927183155/Rendered/PDF/336580ENGLISH0IFC1ExecSummary12005.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-09-27T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2005-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            International Finance Corporation (IFC)
            annual report 2005 : Investing in progress with experience,
            innovation, and partnership
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The International Finance Corporation is
            at the forefront of private sector development: we are
            redefining how poverty can be reduced and lives improved
            through a stronger private sector in emerging markets.
            Accomplishing this goal means reaching people, regions, and
            sectors that have not yet shared in the overall growth of
            emerging markets. It means innovation-forging new
            partnerships with governments and other multilateral
            institutions, identifying new roles for the private sector,
            creating products that develop financial markets, and making
            it easier for disadvantaged people to launch a business or
            own a home. It means building on significant strengths in
            many countries and industries-helping established
            enterprises become more competitive and sustainable as they
            expand their operations or extend their reach into new
            markets. It also means bringing to developing economies
            proven products and techniques, both from industrialized
            countries and, increasingly, from other developing
            countries. Above all, it means tailoring our global
            expertise to local needs. This executive summary for the
            2005 IFC annual report highlights the strategic objectives
            of the institution in expanding access to finance,
            increasing private participation in key sectors, helping
            successful enterprises grow, focusing where needs are
            greatest, and ensuring sustainability.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Highlights from the IFC annual report 2005
        </docna>
        <display_title>International Finance Corporation
            (IFC) annual report 2005 : Investing in progress with
            experience, innovation, and partnership : Highlights from
            the IFC annual report 2005</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2005/01/6311742/international-finance-corporation-ifc-annual-report-2005-investing-progress-experience-innovation-partnership-highlights-ifc-annual-report-2005</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>World Bank Annual Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Microfinance,Private Participation in Infrastructure,Municipal Financial Management,Financial Intermediation,Non Bank Financial Institutions</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20050927183155</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            banks, business environment, capital
            markets, company, corporate governance, Corporation,
            Demonstration Effects, Disclosure, Disclosure of
            Information, economic growth, Enterprise Development,
            entrepreneurs, financial institutions, financial markets,
            health care, housing, housing finance, insurance,
            International Finance, leasing, manufacturers, microfinance,
            microfinance institution, Middle East, North Africa, private
            companies, private enterprises, Private Investment, private
            sector development, privatization, profitability, project
            finance, public services, Risk management, securitization,
            small businesses, Sub-Saharan Africa, technical assistance, Utilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off.VP, Real Sect.&amp;Europe/C.Asia (CIOVP)</owner>
        <repnb>33658</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Investir dans le progres en alliant
            experience, innovation et partenariats : les grands points
            du Rapport Annual 2005 de la SFI
            Investindo no progresso com experiencia,
            inovacao e parceria : destaques do Relatorio Anual de 2005
            da IFC
            Invertir en progreso con experiencia,
            innovacion y espiritu de colaboracion : aspectos destacados
            del Informe Anual de la CFI 2005
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Finance and Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment and Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civic Participation and Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance for Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mortgages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disclosure of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Renewable Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Corporate Law</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>