<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                               Documentof&#13;
                                             The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                ReportNo T7662-IQ&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                 FOR A PROPOSEDIDA CREDIT&#13;
&#13;
                                        OF SDR 69.1MILLION&#13;
&#13;
                                (US$lOOMILLIONEQUIVALENT)&#13;
&#13;
                                   TO THE REPUBLICOF IRAQ&#13;
&#13;
                                                   FORA&#13;
&#13;
                        THIRD EMERGENCY EDUCATIONPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             October31,2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HumanDevelopmentSector&#13;
MiddleEast and NorthAfrica Region&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricted distribution and may be used by borrowers only in the performance of their&#13;
official duties. Its contents may not otherwise be disclosed without World Bank authorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                     CURRENCY EQUIVALENT&#13;
                                (Exchange Rate Effective October 19, 2005)&#13;
                                           Currency Unit = US$&#13;
                                          US$1 = Iraqi Dinar 1476&#13;
                                          SDR 1= US$1.45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              FISCAL YEAR&#13;
                                           January to December&#13;
                               ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
CFAA       Country Financial Accountability            MOHESR     Ministry of Higher Education and&#13;
           Assessment                                             Scientific Research&#13;
CFP        Country Financing Parameters                MOF        Ministry of Finance&#13;
CPA        CoalitionProvisional Authority              MOPDC      Ministry of Planning and Development&#13;
                                                                  Cooperation&#13;
DAD        Donor Assistance Database                   NCB        National Competitive Bidding&#13;
ECOP       Environmental Code of Practice              NER        Net Enrolment Rate&#13;
E S C W    Emergency School Construction and           NGO        Non Governmental Agency&#13;
           Rehabilitation Project&#13;
ESSAF      Environmental and Social Screening and      OFFP       Oil for FoodProgram&#13;
           Assessment Framework&#13;
ESWG       Education Sector Working Group              OPR        Operational Procurement Review&#13;
ETPP       Emergency Textbook Provision Project        PFS        Project Financial Statements&#13;
FM         Financial Management                        P I M      Project ImplementationManual&#13;
FMA        Fiduciary Monitoring Agent                  PIP        Project Implementation Plan&#13;
FMR        Financial Monitoring Report                 PMT        Project Management Team&#13;
&#13;
FMS        Financial Management System                 SA         Special Account&#13;
GDP        Gross Domestic Product                      SBD        Standard Bidding Document&#13;
IBRD       International Bank for Reconstructionand    SDR        Special Drawing Rights&#13;
           Development&#13;
ICB        International Competitive Bidding           SOE        State-Owned Enterprise&#13;
ID         Iraqi Dinar                                 T A        Technical Assistance&#13;
IDA        International Development Association       TOR        Terms of Reference&#13;
IMF        International Monetary Fund                 UN         United Nations&#13;
IRFFI      International Reconstruction FundFacility   UNDB       United Nations Developmental Business&#13;
           for Iraq&#13;
ISRB       Iraqi Strategic Review Board                UNESCO     United Nations Educational, Scientific and&#13;
                                                                  Cultural Organization&#13;
ITF        Iraq Trust Fund                             UNICEF     United Nations Children's Fund&#13;
KRG        Kurdistan Regional Government               UNIDO      United Nations Industrial Development&#13;
                                                                  Organization&#13;
MIM        Master Implementation Manual                us         United States&#13;
MOE        Ministry of Education                       USAID      United States Agency for International&#13;
                                                                  Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    IVice President                                   I ChristiaanPoortman&#13;
     Country Director                                  Joseph P. Saba&#13;
     Sector Director                                   Michal Rutkowski&#13;
     Sector Manager                                    Regina Bendokat&#13;
     Task Team Leader                                  Peter Buckland&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                         FOROFFICIAL USEONLY&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 REPUBLICOF IRAQ&#13;
&#13;
                           THIRD EMERGENCY EDUCATIONPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                                              TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    CREDIT AND PROJECTSUMMARY                                ....................................................................................................................         .I&#13;
    A.  BACKGROUNDAND STRATEGY                                     ...............................................................................................................        2&#13;
    B.  BANK RESPONSEAND STRATEGY                                       ...........................................................................................................       6&#13;
    C.  DETAILEDPROJECTDESCRIPTION                                          ........................................................................................................      8&#13;
    D.  INSTITUTIONALARRANGEMENTSAND PROJECTIMPLEMENTATION                                      ...................................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    .................................... 11&#13;
    E.  FINANCIALAND ECONOMICJUSTIFICATION                                                                                                                                               17&#13;
    F.  RISKS  ...............................................................................................................................................................           20&#13;
      ANNEX 1:SUMMARY COST TABLES                      .............................................&#13;
      ANNEX 2: PROJECT MANAGEMENT                     .............................                          ...................................&#13;
      ANNEX 3 :PROCUREMENT ARRANGEMENTS AND PRO                                                                                         ...............................................  28&#13;
      ANNEX 4: FINANCIAL        MANAGEMENTDISBURSEMENT    AND&#13;
                                          SUPERVISION PLAN...................................................&#13;
                                                                                               ..........         .................................................&#13;
      ANNEX5: RESULTS-BASED&#13;
      ANNEX6:CODES OFPRACTICEFOR PREVENTIONAND MITIGATION OFENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS......&#13;
      ANNEX7: ECONOMICANALYSIS ....................................................&#13;
                                                                      SCHEDULE ........................................&#13;
                                                                                                                 ................................................&#13;
      ANNEX8: COMPONENTIIMPLEMENTATION&#13;
      ANNEX 9: GEOGRAPHICALDISTRIBUTION BY TYPEAND PHASE                                             ....................&#13;
      ANNEX10: DONOR         SUPPORTTO EDUCATION IRAQ.                   IN                                         ...................................&#13;
      ANNEX 11:TIMETABLEOF KEYPROJECTPROCESSING                                                       ..................&#13;
      ANNEX 12:NAMES STAFF/CONSULTANTSWHO WORKED ON THE PROJEC&#13;
                            OF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    TABLES&#13;
    TABLE1: CLASSROOMSAND ENROLMENT GOVERNORATE ..............................................................................&#13;
                                                             BY                                2004                                                                                       3&#13;
    TABLE2: INTERNATIONALCOMMUMENTS FOR ASSISTANCETOEDUCATION IRAQ ..................................................                                                                     6&#13;
     TABLE3: PROJECTCOSTS BY COMPONENT, INCLUDINGCONTINGENCIES (us$MILLION) ...........................................  IN&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                          15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricted distribution and may be usedby recipients only in&#13;
the performance of their official duties. Its contents may not be otherwisedisclosed&#13;
without World Bank authorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   REPUBLIC OF IRAQ&#13;
                   THIRD EMERGENCY EDUCATIONPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
CREDIT AND PROJECTSUMMARY&#13;
&#13;
 Recipient:          Republic of Iraq&#13;
&#13;
 ImplementingAgency: Ministry of Education&#13;
&#13;
 Amount &amp; Terms:     SDR 69.1 million (US$lOO million equivalent)&#13;
&#13;
                     35 years maturity with 10 years grace period&#13;
&#13;
 Objectives&amp;         The main objective of the project is to alleviate overcrowding in primary and&#13;
 Description:        secondary schools through school construction and provision of furniture and&#13;
                     equipment. The project will also lay the groundwork for broader education&#13;
                     reform and system reconstruction.&#13;
&#13;
                     Component 1: School Construction (US$97.25 million) will finance the&#13;
                     construction, equipping and furnishing of about 82 new schools (1,500&#13;
                     classrooms).&#13;
                     Component 2: Institutional Strengthening for System Development and&#13;
                     Reform (US$1.80 million) will finance a comprehensive program to support&#13;
                     education system development and the design of a national school&#13;
                     construction and maintenance program.&#13;
                     Component 3: Project Management (US$O.95 million) will finance the&#13;
                     costs of implementing the project and further build the capacity of the project&#13;
                     management team in the Ministry of Education.&#13;
&#13;
 Benefitsand Risks   Benefits:The project will directly benefit approximately 57,000 students, by&#13;
                     financing the construction, furnishing and equipping of about 82 new schools&#13;
                     (around 1,500 additional classrooms). This will help improve the learning&#13;
                     environment which currently suffers from highly congested school facilities,&#13;
                     and increase access for children currently not enrolled in school. The school&#13;
                     buildings constructed under this project will serve as a model for other&#13;
                     agencies interested in assisting in school construction. The Ministry of&#13;
                     Education's institutional capacity will be strengthened to carry out policy and&#13;
                     system development for reform. Inaddition, the project will create substantial&#13;
                     local employment: civil works for school construction will be carried out by&#13;
                     Iraqi contractors, creating an estimated 980,000 person-days of employment.&#13;
&#13;
                     Risks: The project will be implemented in a high-risk environment. The&#13;
                     major risks to the project are the unstable security and political environment&#13;
                     and the limited capacity o f the government and private sector. In previous&#13;
                     education projects in Iraq, capacity building provided by Bank staff during&#13;
                     supervision missions has helped accelerate project preparation and&#13;
                     implementation. A full presentation of risks, along with measures to mitigate&#13;
                     their impact, i s provided in Section F.&#13;
&#13;
 ProjectAppraisal    This Project has been prepared in accordance with Emergency Recovery&#13;
 Document:           Assistance procedures (Operational Policy 8.50). There i s no Project&#13;
                     Appraisal Document for this Project.&#13;
&#13;
 ClosingDate:        The Credit i s expected to be disbursed within three years. The closing date is&#13;
                     January 31,2009.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 ProjectID Number:   PO96234&#13;
&#13;
 Map No.             IBRD 32954&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     REPUBLICOF IRAQ&#13;
&#13;
                      THIRD EMERGENCY EDUCATIONPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                     TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A.       BACKGROUND AND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
Country Background&#13;
&#13;
1.       Iraq-which   enjoys both abundant natural resources and skilled human resources-attained&#13;
the status o f a middle-income country in the 1970s. B y the early 198Os, income per capita reached&#13;
over US$3,600, and the country's infrastructure and systems o f education and healthcare were&#13;
considered the best in the region. Since that time, two decades o f successive wars and a repressive&#13;
state-dominated economic system have stifled growth and crippled basic infrastructure and social&#13;
services. Internationaltrade sanctions imposed in 1991took a further toll on the economy. B y 2002,&#13;
GDP per capita had fallen to about US$SOO. The invasion by Coalition forces in March 2003&#13;
brought the economy to a near stand-still-resulting   ina further decline inthe GDPper capita to an&#13;
estimated US$518. A UN-World Bank Joint Needs Assessment prepared in mid-2003 pointed out&#13;
that Iraq's human development indicators were among the lowest in the region.&#13;
2.       Since 2003, Iraq has made some progress on both the political and economic fronts. The&#13;
country i s undergoing a complex political transition, taking steps towards a constitutionally-elected&#13;
government. Iraq's GDP, driven by a partial recovery o f the oil sector and high world oil prices,&#13;
rebounded by nearly 50 percent in 2004 to about US$942. However, GDP i s projected to increase&#13;
by only about 2.6 percent in 2005.' Continued violence and instability have slowed reconstruction&#13;
efforts, increased security costs, impeded investment, and hampered efforts to further increase oil&#13;
production. Many basic services have not yet returned to their pre-2003 level, and unemployment i s&#13;
estimated at 30 percent or more.&#13;
&#13;
3.       Ongoing insecurity has also slowed the implementation and disbursement of donor-&#13;
financed projects, despite pledges of about US$32 billion at the October 2003 Donor&#13;
Conference in Madrid. Donors have deposited about US$1 billion in the International&#13;
Reconstruction Fund Facility for Iraq (IRFFI). This includes about US$400 million in the&#13;
World Bank Iraq Trust Fund (ITF), almost all of which was committed to nine projects in&#13;
2004, including two projects inthe education sector.&#13;
&#13;
4.       One of Iraq's main challenges i s to build political legitimacy and credible and&#13;
inclusive institutions needed for stability and sustainable economic prosperity. In this&#13;
context, restoring and improving basic services are essential for improving the quality of&#13;
life, increasing government credibility, and restoring stability. International experience&#13;
with reconstruction in conflict-affected countries has shown that well-targeted government&#13;
expenditures on social services, including education, are particularly important for reducing&#13;
the risk of further conflict.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I The projected GDP growth rate for 2005 has been revised downward since the Second Interim Strategy&#13;
Note dated August 23, 2005.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Education Sector&#13;
5.        Only five months after the May 2003 invasion, Iraq's primary and secondary schools&#13;
opened for the 2003104 school year. Despite ongoing insecurity and uncertainty, the school system&#13;
continued to operate through a second academic year, and has now commenced a third. Iraq's&#13;
national budget financed the recurrent costs of sustaining the education system in the 2004/05&#13;
school year. Slower than expected economic recovery limited public resources available for capital&#13;
investment. International donors have provided supplemental support for school rehabilitation,&#13;
textbooks, basic learning materials, furniture and equipment, and teacher training.&#13;
6.        The resumption o f schooling and continuity o f learning are major achievements.&#13;
Nevertheless, the educational system continues to face major challenges in terms of access, quality,&#13;
and efficiency. Massive backlogs accumulated over the past two decades in school construction and&#13;
maintenance, human resource development, and policy and system development are the key&#13;
underlying problems. Educational strategy documents prepared over the past two years cite school&#13;
overcrowding as the single most pressing problem confronting the Iraqi educational system.&#13;
7.        School Overcrowding. Some six million children are enrolled in 19,000 primary and&#13;
secondary institutions accommodated in 14,000 physical locations. Very few schools have been&#13;
built in Iraq since the mid-1990s. As a result, more than 2,630 primary schools and 750 secondary&#13;
schools operate in double shifts using shared facilities, and 254 primary and 56 secondary schools&#13;
operate in triple shifts. Table 1, using relatively conservative pupi1:classroom ratios o f 40: 1 at the&#13;
primary level and 36:l at the secondary level, indicates that there i s a deficit o f at least 107,000&#13;
classrooms to accommodate the 2003/4 enrolment.&#13;
&#13;
                   Table I:Classrooms and Enrolment by Governorate 2004&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        TotalAdditional&#13;
                            Primary                             Secondary                 Classrooms&#13;
&#13;
  Governorate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Erbil&#13;
Sulaymaniyah&#13;
Dohuk&#13;
Thiqar&#13;
Karkh2&#13;
Basra&#13;
Babil&#13;
Risafa 2&#13;
Risafa 1&#13;
Kerbala&#13;
Ninevah&#13;
Karkh 1&#13;
Najaf&#13;
Diala&#13;
Anbar&#13;
Salaheldin&#13;
Diwaniya&#13;
Missan&#13;
Wasit&#13;
Kirkuk&#13;
Muthana&#13;
TOTAL&#13;
FromMOE2( 314 survey data.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8.       Full primary enrolment would add another 500,000 pupilsto the primary system, requiring&#13;
an additional 12,500 primary classrooms. Ministry of Education (MOE) data indicate that there are&#13;
over 1,000 "mud schools", community-built structures, many of which are unsafe and need&#13;
replacement. The shortage of classrooms i s unevenly distributed across the governorates (see Table&#13;
l), thegreatestshortagesbeinginNinevahandintheurbanareasofBasraandBaghdad&#13;
    with&#13;
(Risafa 1and 2, Karkh 1and 2). Data aggregatedat the governorate level can mask wide variations&#13;
within the governorate. For example, even governorates with average pupi1:classroom ratios of&#13;
around 30:l have congested schools in urban areas, as evidenced by the fact that multiple session&#13;
schools exist in every governorate.&#13;
&#13;
9.       Poor and overcrowded facilities are contributing to low school enrolment rates. Despite&#13;
having achieved universal primary enrolment by 1980, Iraq's primary Net Enrolment Rate (NER)&#13;
declined to 86 percent in 2003/04, implying that at least 500,000 children of primary school age-&#13;
mostly girls in rural areas and both boys and girls in the more densely populated urban areas-are&#13;
not registered in primary school. Girls' net enrolment rates in some rural areas are as low as 30-40&#13;
percent, and attendance rates are even lower. Lack of facilities and the poor and highly congested&#13;
condition of schools are among the key factors responsible for the low enrolment and attendance&#13;
rates inmany areas.&#13;
10.      Only two governorates (Basra and Najaf) have primary NER above 90 percent. The lowest&#13;
NER tend to be in the predominantly rural governorates of Muthanna, Wasit, and Missan, where&#13;
over a quarter of primary school-age children are not in school. Thus, while these governorates&#13;
have among the lowest pupi1:classroom ratios, they have a high need for additional classrooms&#13;
when taking account of childrennot enrolled in school.&#13;
11.      Fewer than three-quarters of primary students continue to secondary school, with transition&#13;
rates below 50 percent in rural areas. The NER for secondary education, at 36 percent (as low as 8&#13;
percent for girls in rural areas), i s among the lowest in the region. Just over three-quarters of those&#13;
who enroll in secondary schools complete the cycle, with a slightly higher survival rate for girls as&#13;
well as children inrural areas.&#13;
&#13;
12.      Overcrowdedfacilities are also a main cause of system inefficiency. Although pupi1:teacher&#13;
ratios for primary and secondary schools are relatively low at about 20:1, pupi1:classroom ratios are&#13;
high at 44:l. Over 270,000 teachers employed in primary and secondary schools have access to&#13;
only 134,000 classrooms, creating inefficiencies in teacher utilization, because only half the&#13;
teachers employed have access to a classroom at any given time.&#13;
13.      Education Policy and System Development. The rigidity of a highly centralized&#13;
authoritarian administration and decades of isolation from international experience in education&#13;
policy and system development have left Iraqwith an education system largely unchanged since the&#13;
1970s. Throughout Iraq, there is a strong awareness that the education system requires a major&#13;
overhaul to play a significant role in the transition to a more market-oriented and competitive&#13;
economy and a democratic and accountable political system. It i s likely to take several years to&#13;
develop the national consensus needed for fundamental education system reform. Thus, the current&#13;
transitional environment creates a window of opportunity for capacity building in policy and&#13;
system development. There is a growing recognition in the MOE of the value of developing the&#13;
human and institutional resources that will be required to conceptualize, negotiate, and implement&#13;
system reform, including eventually new legislation and procedures. The MOE i s seeking&#13;
assistanceboth to manage the interim policy and strategy adjustments that will be required to nurse&#13;
the system through the next few years, and to lay the groundwork for more substantial system&#13;
development that will promote better alignment with the national consensus on development&#13;
strategy as it emerges.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Government Strategy and Donor Involvement&#13;
14.     In 2003, under the Coalition Provisional Authority and Governing Council, the MOE was&#13;
one of the first ministries to organize a donor meeting (November 2003) and produce a sector&#13;
strategy, which identified the most urgent needs and indicated possible directions for future&#13;
reform. Under the subsequent government (Interim Iraqi Government), the MOE produced an&#13;
update of the strategy, focusing mostly on quantifying capital and human development backlogs,&#13;
especially teacher training.&#13;
15.     During 2005, under the Iraq Transitional Government, the MOE worked to strengthen its&#13;
capacity to lead the education sector and improve donor coordination. During an education sector&#13;
donor meeting in Amman in July 2005, the Minister of Education presented an overview of needs&#13;
and priorities to international partners and compiled a list of all donor activities. InAugust 2005,&#13;
the MOE launched an Education Sector Working Group (ESWG) for coordinating the planning and&#13;
implementation of educational projects supported by various agencies and non-governmental&#13;
organizations (NGO). The MOE is in the process of revising its education strategy paper, which&#13;
will provide a framework for all donor support. One of the key challenges i s to move from a needs-&#13;
based approach to a more strategic framework. Another challenge i s to build better linkages&#13;
between general and higher education.&#13;
&#13;
16.     The United States (US), United Nations (UN),and World Bank have been the main&#13;
donors supporting the education sector since April 2003 (see Table 2 and Annex         lo). The U S has&#13;
provided support mainly through the United States Agency for InternationalDevelopment (USAID)&#13;
and mainly for school rehabilitation, ranging from minor repairs to major reconstruction. The UN&#13;
has provided assistancethrough the UNITF and through direct UNcontributions, involvingmainly&#13;
UNICEF, UNESCO, and UN Habitat, and supporting a wide range of activities, including school&#13;
supplies, textbooks and learning materials, equipment, capacity building, and school rehabilitation.&#13;
The World Bank, using the World Bank ITF, has focused on emergency textbook printing for&#13;
2004/05, major school rehabilitation, school construction, and capacity building for the sector.&#13;
&#13;
17.     Since the first donor meeting in November 2003, donors have coordinated their support for&#13;
the education sector through conference calls, regular meetings, and a coordinating structure that&#13;
evolved into the ESWG. As a result, significant interventions have been complementary. For&#13;
example, the UN and the U S provided financing for textbooks for the 2003/04 school year. The&#13;
World Bank financed all textbooks for the 2004/05 school year; while the UN provided school&#13;
supplies and school kits for every student. For the school year 200906, both the UNand the World&#13;
Bank (through cost savings from the previous year) are contributing financing for textbooks. Inthe&#13;
area of school rehabilitation, the needs are so great that there is little possibility of overlap or&#13;
duplication. The MOE reports that 3,820 schools have benefited so far from various levels of repair&#13;
or rehabilitation; yet this represents less than a third of the overall backlog in school rehabilitation.&#13;
&#13;
18.     In addition to the main donors, there are a number of national and international NGOs&#13;
providing support for the education sector. The MOE i s also reaching out to other international&#13;
development partners, including the Japan Bank for International Cooperation and the Islamic&#13;
Development Bank, both of which participated in the appraisal mission for the Third Emergency&#13;
EducationProject and have expressedan interest inproviding parallel financing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Education in Iraq: Current Situation and New Perspectives, Dr.Ala'din A.S. Alwan, Minister of Education,&#13;
Ministry of Education, 2004&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Table 2: International Commitmentsfor Assistance to Education in Iraq&#13;
                                      April 2003-September2005&#13;
                                             (US$ million)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Source: MOE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B.       BANK RESPONSEAND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
19.      Under the First InterimStrategy Note for Iraq, the Bank allocated US$lOO million-about&#13;
25 percent of ITF resources-to two emergency education projects. The US$40 million Emergency&#13;
Textbook Provision Project (ETPP) financed the printing of textbooks for primary and secondary&#13;
schools in 2004/05, while the Emergency School Construction and Rehabilitation Project (ESCRP)&#13;
i s financing the rehabilitation of some 143 schools and the constructionof some 117 new schools.&#13;
&#13;
20.      In September 2005, the Bank`s Executive Directors discussed a Second InterimStrategy&#13;
Note, which builds on the experience of the First InterimStrategy Note and provides a framework&#13;
for up to US$500 million in IDA resources and additional ITF resources. The overall objective of&#13;
the Second Interim Strategy Note i s to help buildefficient, inclusive, and accountable institutions as&#13;
needed for stability, good governance, and sustainable economic prosperity. Under the umbrella of&#13;
institution building, the Bank Group's work program is organized into four pillars: (i)  restore basic&#13;
service delivery; (ii) enable private sector development; (iii) strengthen social safety nets; and (iv)&#13;
improve public sector governance. Pillar one, restoring basic services, explicitly includes a&#13;
commitment to "addressing access, equity, and quality in the education system" through&#13;
eliminating backlogs in school construction and through institutional strengthening for reform.&#13;
21.      Within this framework, the Bank's strategy for education in Iraq has three main objectives,&#13;
drawing on its world-wide experience with reconstruction inconflict-affected areas, namely:&#13;
&#13;
      0  to promote stability by addressing basic needs for continuity of learning, such as&#13;
         emergency provision of textbooks;&#13;
&#13;
      0  to address the key factors undermining equity and efficiency: rehabilitation and&#13;
         construction of schools; and&#13;
&#13;
      0  to strengthen system governance by building capacity for project implementation, for&#13;
         system development, and for longer-termreform.&#13;
22.      These three objectives are being implemented simultaneously and complement each other.&#13;
Provision of textbooks i s accompanied by support for textbook revision and capacity building for&#13;
curriculum reform. School rehabilitation and construction activities introduce international&#13;
standards for procurement and financial management, more systematic monitoring, and greater&#13;
transparency in reporting. System development activities build on the experience, competence and&#13;
systems developed through project implementation. Another project that is under consideration i s&#13;
the proposed ITF-financed Capacity Building for Education and Training Reform Project. This will&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
help lay the groundwork for substantial reform of the education and training system to promote&#13;
better alignment of education and training with the needs of a changing labor market and an&#13;
economy intransition.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Bank-FinancedEducationProjectsand Lessons Learned&#13;
23.     The ETPP, approved in May 2004, was the first ITF-financed sectoral project in Iraq,&#13;
responding to an urgent request from the MOE to finance the printing and distribution of 69 million&#13;
textbooks for all primary and secondary schools for the 2004/05 school year. The project benefited&#13;
six million primary and secondary school pupils. It was also designed to maximize local content&#13;
and employment by contracting local printers to the maximum extent possible, taking into&#13;
consideration the quantity of paper available in Iraq. Competitive bidding procedures led to cost&#13;
savings of about US$9 million, which were used to procure additional textbooks for 2005/06.&#13;
Activities are also underway to strengthen capacity for textbook development and production,&#13;
linkedto curriculumreform.&#13;
24.     The ESCRP (US$60 million), approved in October 2004, aims to alleviate school building&#13;
hazards and school overcrowding by constructing 117 new schools and by rehabilitating 143&#13;
schools needing urgent repair, covering all 18 governorates of Iraq. The project directly benefits&#13;
about 130,000 pupils (7 percent of pupils in overcrowded or damaged schools.) The use of local&#13;
firms for design and supervision and local construction companies for rehabilitation and&#13;
construction i s also creating substantial near-term employment. Project implementation is on&#13;
schedule: 135 schools have been rehabilitated, and an additional 9 schools will be rehabilitated by&#13;
the end of 2005. Local consultants are in the process of designing construction of the first 31 new&#13;
schools, for which procurement will take place before the end of 2005. The Bank i s also supporting&#13;
the MOE indeveloping a broad strategic framework for reform and a donor coordination strategy.&#13;
&#13;
25.     The ETPP and ESCRP have shown that emergency education projects with simple designs&#13;
can be implemented under the current circumstances. The MOE has demonstrated its capacity to&#13;
satisfactorily implement emergency operations. Also, the Bank i s able to carry out project&#13;
supervision, despite the current limitations on access of international staff to Iraq. The Bank has&#13;
relied heavily on a cadre of excellent local staff and consultants in Iraq for daily supervision and&#13;
monitoring, and has met project counterparts outside Iraq on a quarterly basis for intensive&#13;
supervision missions. Well-designed project launch workshops have also proven to be highly&#13;
effective in facilitating implementation.For example, the ESCRPproject launch workshop gathered&#13;
MOE focal points from 17 governorates and helped build MOE staff capacities in the areas of&#13;
procurement, financial management, disbursement, and monitoring. Workshop participants&#13;
finalized bidding documents for school rehabilitation, and contracts were advertised shortly&#13;
thereafter, allowing a prompt start of the project.&#13;
&#13;
26.     Implementing projects through Iraqi ministries has numerous benefits, including greater&#13;
ownership and sustainability and negligible security costs. Under the ESCRP, the unit costs for&#13;
school rehabilitation have been 30 to 40 percent below comparable projects implemented by donor&#13;
agencies. Most importantly, recipient-executionstrengthens overall institutional capacity. Under the&#13;
ETPP, the MOE used, for the first time, competitive bidding procedures that meet international&#13;
standards. Recognizing the cost savings achieved, the MOE is now applying these procedures to&#13;
textbooks financed from their own budget. Underthe ESCRP, the MOE i s usingIraqiprivate sector&#13;
building contractors and design and supervision services from private consultants, an innovation&#13;
that results in more efficient use of MOE technical resources, strengthens the capacity of the MOE&#13;
in every governorate, and fosters the growth of the private sector. Similarly, new procedures for&#13;
transparent financial management and reporting are setting examples for ministry practices. The&#13;
Bank's investment projects thus have a wider impact on overall policy and institutional capacity.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
27.      The ETPP and ECSRP have also shown the value of linking policy reform to practical&#13;
activities. For example, the ETPP complements provision of textbooks with a component to build&#13;
capacity for textbook development and production according to international best practice and&#13;
linked to curriculum reform.&#13;
28.      Lessons Learned from Reconstruction in Conflict-Affected Environments. The World&#13;
Bank education strategy in Iraq and the proposed project reflect lessons from World Bank&#13;
experience in conflict-affected countries, such as Afghanistan, East Timor, Bosnia-Herzergovina,&#13;
Algeria, Sierra Leone and Kosovo, as well as in West Bank and Gaza. First, experience has shown&#13;
the importance of promptly resumingnormal schooling and the value of early and visible impact. A&#13;
second lesson i s the importance of institutional development in the ministry to lay the basis for&#13;
wider system reform. A third lesson is the importance of early and effective donor coordination&#13;
under the leadership of the government.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Rationale for Bank Involvement&#13;
29.      The Bank has considerable experience insupporting large-scale school rehabilitation and/or&#13;
construction projects in conflict-affected settings. The Bank was the lead agency for education in&#13;
the UNWorld Bank Joint Needs Assessment, working closely with UNagencies and USAID. Soon&#13;
after the appointment of a Minister of Education in 2003, the Bank developed a strong working&#13;
relationship with the MOE, including weekly conference calls to provide advice on key policy and&#13;
reform issues. The strong Bank-MOE dialogue led to the financing of the ETPP, the Bank's first&#13;
ITFoperation inIraq implementedby a line ministry.&#13;
30.      Emergency education projects in conflict-affected countries usually focus on rehabilitation,&#13;
as has been the case in Iraq over the last two and a half years. However, the situation in Iraq also&#13;
warrants an early focus on new school construction, because school overcrowding i s a major&#13;
impediment to increasing access to basic education and improving the quality and efficiency of the&#13;
education system. The World Bank i s one of few donors at this time with a substantial commitment&#13;
to school construction (Table 2).&#13;
31.      The Bank is one of the few donors that finance projects implemented by Iraq's own&#13;
ministries, resulting in better policies and stronger institutional capacity at both the central and&#13;
governorate levels. The Bank's support for school construction and related policy reform will&#13;
strengthen the MOE's capacity to design and implement a large-scale national school construction&#13;
program financed in the future by other donors and Iraq's own budget. The Bank will also support&#13;
the MOE to develop a national school maintenance program. The Bank i s thus positioned to&#13;
provide support for the key policy and system development dimensions that will improve overall&#13;
governance of the education sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C.       D E T A I L E D PROJECTDESCRIPTION&#13;
&#13;
Project Objective&#13;
32.      The principal objective of the project i s to alleviate overcrowding inprimary and secondary&#13;
schools through school construction and provision of furniture and equipment. The project will also&#13;
lay the groundwork for broader school reformand systemreconstruction.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Project Components&#13;
33.      The project, which will amount to SDR 69.1 million (US$lOO million equivalent), i s a&#13;
follow up to two ITF-financed projects in Iraq and draws extensively upon their experience.&#13;
Summary and detailed cost tables are provided inAnnex 1.The project will have three components:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Component 1: School Construction (US$97.25 million, including contingencies)&#13;
34.      The component will finance the construction o f buildings and provision o f furniture and&#13;
equipment for about 82 new primary and secondary schools in 15 governorates, creating around&#13;
1,500 additional classrooms to accommodate some 57,000 students3.There are over 300 sites that&#13;
have already been designated for schools by local authorities throughout the country. Allocation of&#13;
resources across governorates was agreed at project appraisal on the basis o f (i)     wide coverage, to&#13;
address part o f the backlog in each regional directorate, including the construction o f one complete,&#13;
modem secondary school in each governorate; and (ii)       increased allocation to governorates where&#13;
data indicate greater congestion, lower net enrolment rates, or a higher proportion o f "mud&#13;
schools." Identification o f specific sites in each directorate will be finalized at the project launch&#13;
workshop usingthe following criteria: (i)    targeting sites in communities where enrolment rates are&#13;
lowest and/or pupi1:classroomratios are highest; and (ii)   preference for sites that will reduce gender&#13;
disparities. Final site selection will be limited to those that conform to basic school planning&#13;
criteria, are accessible to necessary services, and are vacant and therefore involve no population&#13;
resettlement.&#13;
Component 2: Institutional Strengthening for System Development and Reform (US$1.80&#13;
million, including contingencies)&#13;
35.      This component will finance development of a comprehensive program to support system&#13;
development and strengthen governance at the central and directorate levels of the MOE. This&#13;
component builds on the improved governance capacity established through ETPP and ESCRP&#13;
implementation, and will include the design of a school construction and maintenance program to&#13;
systematically address the school construction backlog. Other system development activities will&#13;
focus on building the human and institutional capacity to conceptualize, design, operationalize and&#13;
implement policy and system reform. Three target areas for system development have been agreed&#13;
with the MOE: (i)     strategic planning for system development; (ii) options for teacher&#13;
                                                                              policy&#13;
management (such as recruitment, training and development, deployment and utilization); and (iii)&#13;
institutional strengthening for curriculum development and reform. The project will develop and&#13;
implement a comprehensive program to support system development and strengthen governance at&#13;
central, regional, and directorate levels.&#13;
&#13;
36.      The specific system development-related activities will be defined during the project&#13;
launch workshop, and will include: (i)   technical assistance for studies and data collection conducted&#13;
in Iraq in key policy areas relating to policy and system reform, teacher policy, curriculum&#13;
development and physical infrastructure planning, construction and maintenance; (ii)          institutional&#13;
and organizational development, including information and management systems, management&#13;
development practices and policies, and policy options modeling; (iii)       learning from experience of&#13;
other countries through study tours, international seminars, and conferences; and (iv) short term&#13;
training programs in key policy areas for selected officials.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 The Kurdishgovernorates have opted for only electricity and transport projects from the present IDA&#13;
allocation.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Component 3: Project Management (US$0.95 million, includingcontingencies)&#13;
37.      Project management will be the responsibility of the MOE under the leadership of the&#13;
Project Management Team (PMT) currently supervising implementation o f the ESCRP and the&#13;
ETPP. The PMT i s an integral part of the MOE, staffed by MOE officials assigned to the project&#13;
team on a full-time basis. To accommodate the additional demands o f this project, the capacity of&#13;
the PMT will be supplemented in the areas of team leadership (appointment of a Deputy Team&#13;
Leader), progress monitoring and reporting, financial management, and procurement. Project&#13;
management costs will include the provision of furniture, equipment, technical assistance, and&#13;
training necessary for the management o f the project, as well as operating costs of the PMT.&#13;
Project DesignIssues&#13;
38.      School Design Standards. The designs used for existing schools reflect the norms and&#13;
educational approaches o f the 1970s when there was a massive expansion of physical capacity in&#13;
the system. However, they do not generally provide for media centers or computer laboratories, and&#13;
the science laboratories at the secondary schools were designed for teacher demonstration rather&#13;
than pupil participation in experiments. The present designs result in classrooms that average 43&#13;
square meters, smaller than international standards require, because the designs assume relatively&#13;
low pupi1:classroom ratios of around 30:1, while the average pupi1:classroom ratio i s presently&#13;
44:l. The MOE recognizes the need to ensure that schools built for the new Iraq reflect&#13;
international norms, the most appropriate designs, the most efficient use o f space, and, as far as&#13;
possible, accommodate the needs o f disabled students and teachers. Rather than proposing standard&#13;
designs, this project will employ new design standards for schools, furniture, and equipment that&#13;
meet the latest international norms and, in the case o f schools, provide for larger classrooms of&#13;
about 52 square meters. The switch from standard designs (a set of standard plans) to design&#13;
standards - a set of technical specifications that incorporate international norms - provides for&#13;
greater flexibility to accommodate varying local conditions while still ensuring a degree of&#13;
uniformity and institutions that meet the pedagogical requirements of 21st Century education. The&#13;
MOE will refine these design standards through the project, and apply them to all future school&#13;
construction.&#13;
39.      National School Construction and Maintenance Program. The MOE has approached&#13;
the Bank for support to strengthen its capacity to plan and implement a national school construction&#13;
and maintenance program to address the schools backlog. While the education system in the 1980s&#13;
had the capacity for planning and implementing large-scale capital works programs, this&#13;
institutional capacity has diminished over the last decade. Approaches to school construction in the&#13;
past relied heavily on the public sector and on centrally planned large-scale construction programs.&#13;
In recent years responsibility for school construction and maintenance has been devolved to the&#13;
regional directorates, and there exist in each directorate school construction and maintenance&#13;
divisions with competent staff. The Bank i s able to draw on its international experience and build&#13;
on the experience, implementation mechanisms and institutional capacity developed in the ESCRP&#13;
to support development o f a national school construction and maintenance program. Moreover, the&#13;
implementation o f the ESCRP and this project will result in every directorate having teams of&#13;
seasoned professionals with experience in overseeing school construction projects using modem&#13;
design standards and construction methods. This will position them well to contribute to the&#13;
development o f a national program to address the massive construction backlog and plan for&#13;
maintenance and expansion o f the system.&#13;
40.      School construction will include classrooms, facilities (such as laboratories, libraries, and&#13;
administration centers), and site development for basic recreation facilities and services. The MOE&#13;
has a strong preference for construction o f complete schools that provide a model for future&#13;
construction programs, rather than a modular approach that would focus initially on classrooms&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
with a future plan to add subsidiary buildings (administration centers, laboratories, libraries, and&#13;
multi-purpose halls). The MOE recognized the risk that other priorities could result in extended&#13;
postponement of completion of schools, and opted for a smaller number of complete schools. The&#13;
one concession to a modular approach was with respect to multi-purpose halls. The plan provides&#13;
for frame construction of covered spaces which would provide accommodation for assembly and&#13;
sports activities, with the understanding that subsequently communities, government, or other&#13;
donors could provide the resources to convert these structures into fully functional multi-purpose&#13;
halls.&#13;
41.      The provision of furniture and equipment will address, to the extent possible, issues of&#13;
access for disabled students and teachers. The MOE has been in discussions with UNICEF and&#13;
U N D O regarding updating the design of classroom furniture to permit greater flexibility in&#13;
classroom layout and a wider range of pedagogical approaches. Using the updated design, the MOE&#13;
will finalize the list of school furniture to be financed by the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
D.       INSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTSAND PROJECTIMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
42.      Project Scope and Geographical Area. At the request of the Iraqi authorities, the&#13;
project's school construction program will cover 15 governorates (the Kurdishgovernorates have&#13;
opted for only electricity and transport projects from the present IDA allocation). The governorates&#13;
covered are: Anbar, Babylon, Baghdad, Basrah, Diwaniyah, Diyala, Kirkuk, Karbala, Muthanna,&#13;
Missan, Najaf, Ninewa, Sala Al-Din, Thi Qar, and Wassit. Each of these governorates has one&#13;
MOE directorate, except Baghdad which has six (Karkh 1, Karkh 2, Karkh 3, Risafa 1, Risafa 2,&#13;
and Risafa 3). The distribution of schools to be constructed in each Directorate can be found in&#13;
Annex 9.&#13;
&#13;
43.      Project Duration. Although the MOE i s working on an accelerated schedule to have all&#13;
school construction completed by September 2007, the project's implementation schedule reflects a&#13;
more cautious approach to take into account the risks outlined below (Section F). The Credit's&#13;
three-year timeframe allows: (i)the completion of system development activities, which will be&#13;
carried out over at least two years; (ii)      completion of all school construction contracts with&#13;
provision for possible delays due to security or other unforeseen problems; and (iii)the payment of&#13;
retention funds on the civil works contracts, which can only be made one year after completion of&#13;
the schools.&#13;
&#13;
ProjectManagementStructure&#13;
44.      The PMT is headed by a PMT Leader who i s an assigned senior official (Director General&#13;
level) from the MOE, and supported by a Deputy (Director level). The PMT Deputy Leader will&#13;
manage day-to-day project activities under the supervision of the PMT Leader, who will be&#13;
responsible for overall direction and control and will liaise with the Minister of Education. The&#13;
PMT will manage and oversee procurement, financial management, and planning, monitoring, and&#13;
reporting. Site identification, procurement of local civil works, and project supervision will be the&#13;
responsibility of the project focal points ineach governorate, operating under the supervision of the&#13;
PMT. PMT functions will be led by assigned MOE staff or, where necessary, by Iraqi consultants&#13;
selected on a competitive basis. The PMT will serve as the main point of communication with the&#13;
Bank.&#13;
45.     The Bank reassessed the capacity of the PMT and MOE project focal points duringproject&#13;
pre-appraisal. As a result, additional staff will be assigned by the M O E to support the following&#13;
areas: progress monitoring and reporting, financial management, and procurement. Where suitable&#13;
MOE personnel are not available, consultants will be appointed until there is sufficient local&#13;
capacity for full integration of the functions into the PMT and the MOE.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
46.     Site identification, local civil works procurement, monitoring, and overall supervision of&#13;
subproject implementation will be in the hands of twenty qualified engineers (project focal points)&#13;
located in the MOE offices in each directorate under the supervision of the PMT. As inthe ESCRP,&#13;
the MOE will employ private-sector local consulting firms to provide design and supervision&#13;
services for all school construction, including assistance with preparation of bidding documents.&#13;
These designated project focal points have already been identified and are working effectively on&#13;
the ESCRP subprojects.&#13;
47.     Project implementation (including procurement, disbursement, and financial management)&#13;
will be undertaken in conformity with the Master Implementation Manual (MIM) developed in&#13;
2005 for all Bank-financed projects in Iraq. A Project Implementation Manual (PIM) relating to&#13;
issues specific to the project will be prepared prior to the start of project implementation. A project&#13;
launch workshop will provide hands-on training to all MOE Directorate focal points to finalize all&#13;
bidding documents for the first phase of school construction.&#13;
48.     The bottlenecks in contract and expenditure authorization experienced in the ETPP and&#13;
ESCRP were addressedduring pre-appraisal with the participation of senior MOE finance officials,&#13;
and representatives of the Ministry of Finance (MOF) and the Ministry of Planning and&#13;
Development Cooperation (MOPDC), and special arrangements to expedite contract and&#13;
expenditure approval have been agreed. The project accounts that facilitate small expenditures have&#13;
been reopened by permission of the Ministry of Finance, and will be used for expenditures below&#13;
an agreed threshold for this project.&#13;
&#13;
49.     Use of Consulting Firms for Design and Supervision Services. The PMT will hire&#13;
consulting firms to assist in initial site visits and surveys (if needed) and for the provision of&#13;
professional services as required for the execution of the works.&#13;
50.     Ad hoc Consultancies. The PMT will be assisted by consultants hired on an ad hoc basis&#13;
where the need arises.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Procurement&#13;
General&#13;
51.     Procurement for this project will be carried out in accordance with the World Bank's&#13;
"Guidelines: Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" dated May 2004; and "Guidelines:&#13;
Selection and Employment of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers" dated May 2004, and the&#13;
provisions stipulated in the Financing Agreement. The general description of various items under&#13;
different expenditure categories is indicated below. For each contract to be financed by the Credit,&#13;
the procurement methods or consultant selection methods, the need for prequalification, estimated&#13;
costs, prior review requirements, and time frame are agreed between the Recipient and the Bank&#13;
project team in the Procurement Plan (PP). The PP will be updated as requiredto reflect the actual&#13;
project implementation needs and improvements in institutional capacity. A General Procurement&#13;
Notice was published in the United Nations Developmental Business (UNDB) on October 20,&#13;
2005, and it will be revised after the project i s approved by the Bank's Board of Executive&#13;
Directors.&#13;
52.     Reference to the Environmental Codes of Practice for Preventing and Mitigating&#13;
Environmental Impacts (ECOP) will be made in the construction bidding documents. Safeguard&#13;
procedures will be included inthe technical specifications of contracts.&#13;
53.     Advance procurement. To speed up the construction of schools, advance procurement will&#13;
be used for the first package of school designs and preparation of bidding documents. The process&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
of selecting a consultingfirm to provide procurement management support and capacity building to&#13;
the MOE will start as soon as the Request for Proposal i s ready and project implementationbegins.&#13;
&#13;
54.      Procurement of Works. Works procured under this project will include the construction of&#13;
about 82 schools. Due to the small value of each contract, the scattering of the schools over 15&#13;
governorates, and the volatile security conditions in Iraq, internationalcontractors are not expected&#13;
to be interested in the works contracts. All procurement of works estimated at less than US$2.5&#13;
million equivalent per contract will follow National Competitive Bidding (NCB) procedures. The&#13;
NCB standard bidding documents for procurement of works which were prepared as part of the&#13;
MIMwill be used. Shopping procedures, when needed, will be used for procurement of works of&#13;
small value estimated at US$lOO,OOO or less.&#13;
&#13;
55.      Procurement of Goods. Goods procuredunder this project will include school furniture and&#13;
equipment, and office furniture, equipment and supplies needed for project implementation. The&#13;
procurement will be done using the Bank's Standard BiddingDocument (SBD) for all International&#13;
Competitive Bidding (ICB). The NCB SBD for procurement of goods which were prepared as part&#13;
of the MIM will be used for contracts estimated at less than US$200,000 per contract. Shopping&#13;
procedures will be used for procurement of goods of small value estimated at US$lOO,OOO or less.&#13;
56.       Selection of Consultants. Consultant services procured under this project will include:&#13;
selection of a consulting firm to assist the PMT in all procurement-related issues, including: setting&#13;
up, within the MOE, of a procurement monitoring and reporting system, provision of training to the&#13;
MOE procurement staff, assistance to the PMT in bidding document preparation, bid evaluation&#13;
and physical spot checks and reporting; selection of individual consultants and/or firms to provide&#13;
training; capacity building in financial management; and selection of consulting firms to provide&#13;
consultancy services in school design and construction supervision. International consulting firms&#13;
may not be interested in design and supervision of school construction while the security situation&#13;
i s volatile. Accordingly, it i s possible that shortlists for all consultants' services for design and&#13;
supervision of school construction may be composed entirely of national consultants. As the&#13;
security conditions improve and international consultants show interest, the shortlist may include&#13;
international consultants. It i s also expected that consulting offices associated with local&#13;
universities may be included in the shortlists. University-based consultants will not be given&#13;
preference over other private consultants.&#13;
&#13;
57.       Operating Costs: The Credit will finance expenditures directly related to the management&#13;
of the project, such as: (i)&#13;
                           maintenance of office equipment; (ii)    transportation and travel, including&#13;
per diem allowances for project staff intravel status; (iii) of office space; (iv) office supplies,&#13;
                                                              rental&#13;
utilities and office administration, including translation, printing and advertising; (v) fuel costs; (vi)&#13;
communication costs; (vii) costs for production of bidding documents and drawings; (viii)&#13;
commercial bank charges; and (ix) any other project management support costs as agreed by the&#13;
Recipient and IDA, but excluding salaries of the Recipient's civil servants. These items will be&#13;
financed by the project and will be procured using MOE administrative procedures for shopping,&#13;
satisfactory to IDA.&#13;
Assessment of the MOE capacity to implementprocurement&#13;
58.      An Operational Procurement Review (OPR) for Iraq was completed in June 2005 and sent&#13;
to the government for comments. The most urgent action needed from the government i s to clarify&#13;
the legal framework for public procurement and enact the needed legal and regulatory instruments&#13;
either through the existing CPA Order No. 87 or through a new law. In the meantime, it i s&#13;
necessary that World Bank-financed projects be implemented under clearly specified procurement&#13;
procedures, to be reflected in relevant provisions of the legal agreements and supported by a PIM&#13;
for eachproject, derived from the MIMprepared for Iraqin 2005.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
59.     An assessment of MOE's capacity to implement project procurement was updated in&#13;
August/September 2005 and i s included inthe project file.&#13;
&#13;
60.     Procurement activities will be carried out by the MOE. The MOE Engineering and School&#13;
Building Directorate has 45 engineers in Baghdad and at least 3 engineers in every governorate.&#13;
There are at least three engineers who are familiar with procurement who are working on the on-&#13;
going education project financed from the ITF. One of these engineers i s assigned as a procurement&#13;
consultant working on the ESCRP. The Engineering and School Building Directorate staff has&#13;
experience in school construction and rehabilitation. During 1993 and 1994, the M O E rehabilitated&#13;
more than 5,000 schools with an estimated value equivalent to US$l20million. To strengthen the&#13;
procurement capacity o f the M O E staff, another procurement officer will join the PMT. This&#13;
procurement officer was identified at negotiations.&#13;
61.     The MOE procurement and technical staff who will conduct procurement have already&#13;
gained experience in procurement in accordance with the Bank procurement guidelines through the&#13;
several training sessions attended under the Capacity Building Iand I1projects financed from the&#13;
ITF as well as through the on-the-job training provided by Bank procurement staff. Further&#13;
procurement training will continue throughout project implementation.&#13;
Procurement risk assessment&#13;
62.     The procurement risk i s rated h&amp;.     The risks associated with procurement were identified&#13;
in the assessment of MOE procurement capacity and include: (i) lack of good laws and&#13;
                                                                          the&#13;
regulations and o f modern standard documentation; (ii)    the habits acquired by procurement staff in&#13;
the previous era which will take time to change; (iii) experience o f procurement staff in use&#13;
                                                        limited&#13;
o f Bank procurement guidelines and international sound procurement practice; (iv) limited access&#13;
of international Bank procurement staff to supervise the project in the field; (v) delays in&#13;
implementing the procurement plan due to lack of experience in procurement planning and the&#13;
volatile security conditions in Iraq; (vi) increase of prices o f raw construction materials due to high&#13;
demand and unavailability o f these materials which may impact subproject completion due to&#13;
contractors' unwillingness to continue work based on old contract prices; (vii) possible looting of&#13;
construction sites; and (viii) delays in bid submission and/or implementation due to deteriorated&#13;
security conditions in some areas in Iraq.&#13;
&#13;
63.     The corrective measures which have been agreed upon are: (i)            assignment of another&#13;
procurement officer to the PMT on a full-time basis; (ii)   recruitment o f a procurement management&#13;
consulting firm to assist the PMT in procurement, train the MOE staff on procurement, establish a&#13;
procurement monitoring and reporting system, and conduct physical spot inspections; and (iii)        use&#13;
of the MIMand the NCB SBDs. See the risk table in section F for more details.&#13;
Procurement Plan&#13;
64.     The MOE, at pre-appraisal, developed a draft Procurement Plan for project implementation,&#13;
which provides information on procurement packages and methods. This plan (Annex 3) was&#13;
agreed upon between the MOE and the Bank project team at negotiations, and i s available at the&#13;
PMT in Baghdad, in the project's database, and on the Bank's external website. The Procurement&#13;
Plan will be updated in agreement with the Bank, as required to reflect the actual project&#13;
implementation needs and improvements in institutional capacity.&#13;
Frequency of Procurement Supervision&#13;
65.     In addition to the prior review of contracts, supervision will be carried out from Bank&#13;
offices, and based on the capacity assessment o f the MOE, post reviews o f procurement will be&#13;
conducted on at least 20 percent o f the contracts subject to post review. Where security conditions&#13;
make travel to Iraq impossible for international Bank staff, the Bank will employ a supervision&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
agent, an independent firm that will operate in Iraq and support the Bank in carrying out its&#13;
supervision function. In addition, the Bank will rely on the reports o f a procurement management&#13;
consulting firm, as well as on reports from a procurement consultant who works for the Bank from&#13;
within Iraq.&#13;
Project Costsand Financing&#13;
66.     The project will be implemented over a period of 36 months, with effectiveness planned for&#13;
February, 2006, and a closing date o f January 31, 2009. The estimated total cost o f the project i s&#13;
SDR 69.1 million (US$lOO million equivalent). In accordance with the Country Financing&#13;
Parameters approved for Iraq in September 2005, the Credit will finance 100 percent of project&#13;
expenditures. There i s provision for retroactive financing from the Credit for eligible expenditures&#13;
after November 1,2005. Project costs by component are presentedin Annex 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Component                                                                US$million&#13;
         ComDonent 1: SchoolConstruction                                                 97.25&#13;
         Component 2: Support to SystemDevelopment                                        1.80&#13;
         Component 3: Support to Project Management                                       0.95&#13;
         TOTAL PROJECT COSTS                                                            100.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
67.     The 2003 Board paper on IDA lending to Iraq provides that IDA assistance should be on&#13;
regular IDA "blend terms'I4. Blend terms provide 10 years' grace and 35 years' maturity and include&#13;
a standard provision that IDA can request accelerated repayment o f a credit once certain conditions&#13;
are met including that the Gross National Income o f the borrower has exceeded IDA's operational&#13;
cutoff for three consecutive years. There i s a strong likelihood that Iraq will meet the criteria for the&#13;
application o f this provision in three years, and such early application would leave Iraq with&#13;
effective terms that are worse than if it had received this credit on "hardened terms". Hardened&#13;
terms provide 10 years' grace and 20 years' maturity and apply to countries that have exceeded the&#13;
IDA cutoff for two consecutive years. IDA has therefore agreed that it will not exercise the right to&#13;
request accelerated repayments for a period of five years after the date o f approval o f the credit by&#13;
the Executive Directors, with any accelerated repayments only commencing after the grace period&#13;
ends. This ensures that Iraq would receive the benefit o f financial terms that are, at least, more&#13;
beneficial than current IDA hardened terms.&#13;
Disbursement&#13;
68.     The project will adopt the same disbursement methods that are used for the two ITF-&#13;
financed projects, ETPP and ESCRP, currently under implementation by the MOE. Disbursements&#13;
for eligible expenditures over US$lO,OOO        will be made directly by the Bank to contractors,&#13;
suppliers, and consultants. Eligible expenditures under US$lO,OOO will be paid by the MOE.from&#13;
its own resources which will then be reimbursed by the Bank. Annex 1describes the allocation of&#13;
the Credit proceeds according to each expenditure category.&#13;
FinancialManagement&#13;
69.     The project financial resources extended through an IDA Credit will be managed within the&#13;
framework o f the Iraqi government systems and allocations will be reflected in the MOE&#13;
investment budget. The MOF i s the representative of the Recipient o f the Credit. It will play a&#13;
wider role in allocating the budget and recording the Bank disbursements as expenditures against&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  See IDA'sRoleinPotentialWorld BankLendingto Iraq, IDNSecM2003-0549, October 17,2003&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the project budget. In addition, MOPDC will play a monitoring role through maintenance of the&#13;
Donor Assistance Database.&#13;
&#13;
70.     Presently, the MOE is implementing two ITF-financed projects for education. The financial&#13;
management arrangements for the proposed project will be similar to those being followed under&#13;
the ITF-financed projects, taking into consideration the experience gained and the issues faced&#13;
during their implementation. An assessment of MOE's financial management capacity has already&#13;
been conducted. This assessment has been updated through interviews in Amman with MOE staff&#13;
and the representatives of the MOPDC and MOF.&#13;
71.     The fiduciary riskthat the Credit will not usedfor the intended purposes, with due regardto&#13;
economy, efficiency, and the sustainable achievement of the project's development objective, is&#13;
considered as high. The financial management risk as an element of the fiduciary risk is also&#13;
considered as high.This rating is the result of the assessment performedby the Bank team and the&#13;
outcome of the various reports issued by independent auditors and other donors.&#13;
&#13;
72.     This financial management risk will be partly managed through the following: (i)&#13;
reinforcing the present controls as applied by the MOE; (ii)  engaging two additional accountants to&#13;
support the financial officer already following on the ongoing projects; (iii)&#13;
                                                                             making direct payments&#13;
to contractors, consultants, and vendors, while payments below the threshold of US$lO,OOO will be&#13;
reimbursed to the MOE upon presentation of supporting documentation and proof of payment; (iv)&#13;
the generation of monthly reports from the governorates advising the MOE in Baghdad about their&#13;
commitments and expected disbursements; (v)            maintaining a fixed assets spreadsheet for&#13;
purchased and delivered equipment and furniture; (vi) initially, using a spreadsheet application to&#13;
follow up on the project accounts and to generate the project reports, with the option of installing an&#13;
accounting system at the PMT, depending on the availability of vendors that are capable of&#13;
providing the needed support inside Iraq; and (vii) engaging an independent auditor with&#13;
international experience acceptable to IDA to perform the project audit and issue an independent&#13;
auditor opinion, in addition to reviewing the quarterly interim financial management reports&#13;
(FMRs). All the above activities and procedures will be documented ina chapter of the PIM.&#13;
73.     In addition, the residual risk, where possible, will be managed during project&#13;
implementation through close monitoring and supervision by the project's financial management&#13;
system (FMS), supported by financial management consultants if needed.&#13;
74.     These financial management-related risks and risk-management strategies are summarized&#13;
in tabular form in the project risk analysis (Section F). The project financial management&#13;
arrangements and identifiedrisks are detailed inAnnex 4.&#13;
Project Supervision&#13;
75.     All project activities should be completed within 36 months. Supervision will include visits&#13;
to MOE, MOF, MOPDC, and to the school sites for the purpose of reviewing implementation&#13;
progress, impact of the project activities, and related documentation. Until security conditions&#13;
permit international Bank staff to travel to Iraq, in-country supervision will continue to be&#13;
undertaken by local Bank staff with the support of a supervision agent, an independent consulting&#13;
firm to be contracted by the Bank to help carry out in-country supervision. The supervision agent&#13;
will prepare reports for discussion with the World Bank and MOE at supervision meetings, which&#13;
would take place quarterly.&#13;
Environmental and Social Safeguards&#13;
76.     Environmental Safeguards: The Project i s rated as category "B". Environmental impacts&#13;
would be those associated mainly with: (i)      construction works (e.g. safety, dust, noise, waste&#13;
material, traffic); (ii)&#13;
                       provision of sanitary services, water supply, and waste management; and (iii)&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
maintenance of facilities. Because of the emergency conditions, the requirement to carry out limited&#13;
Environmental Analysis as part of project preparation has been waived. However, for subprojects&#13;
with adverse environmental impacts, a limited environmental analysis will be done during project&#13;
implementation but before subproject approval. The Environmental and Social Screening and&#13;
Assessment Framework (ESSAF) was disclosed in the country and in the Infoshop on September&#13;
19, 2005. Based on the ESSAF, the following standards will be applied during implementation: (i)&#13;
inclusion of standard environmental codes of practice (ECOP) in the school construction bid&#13;
documents; (ii)use of Safeguard Procedures for Inclusion in the Technical Specifications of&#13;
Contracts; (iii) use of the Checklist of Likely Environmental and Social Impacts of Subproject; (iv)&#13;
review and oversight of any major construction works by specialists; (v) implementation of&#13;
environmentally and socially sound options for civil works; and (vi) provision for adequate budget&#13;
and institutional arrangements to monitor effective implementation and adequately maintain&#13;
sanitary facilities after completion (Annex 6).&#13;
77.     Pest Management. OP 4.09 has been triggered. No pesticides will be procured under the&#13;
project. However, pesticides may be used against termites (spraying of foundations with pesticide).&#13;
The use of chemicals to destroy termites would not include pesticides on the negative list, which&#13;
includes all Persistent Organic Pollutants (POPS) and Chemicals, in World Health Organization&#13;
classes Ia and Ib. A list of pesticides to be used will be sent to the Bank and guidelines for safe&#13;
handling will be developed duringproject implementation.&#13;
&#13;
78.     Resettlement and Land Acquisition: OP 4.12 should not be triggered because there will not&#13;
be any displacement of populations or new land acquisition. However, the Bank approved ESSAF,&#13;
specifically elaborated for due diligence in the case of Iraq, should be used to ensure that this is&#13;
indeed the case, and should there be any need for land acquisition, the same guidelines will be&#13;
followed.&#13;
79.      Capacity buildingon Safeguards and on the implementationof the ESSAF has already been&#13;
undertaken with the Ministry of Environment and other line ministries. During the project launch&#13;
workshop, special training on safeguards and on the ESSAFfor school construction will be carried&#13;
out by a Safeguard Specialist. Capacity building on safeguards will continue during project&#13;
implementation especially for the project focal points and designated staff, who will receive&#13;
training on safeguardrequirements.&#13;
&#13;
E.       FINANCIAL AND ECONOMICJUSTIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
80.     Macroeconomic framework: Despite the tremendous difficulties currently facing Iraq, the&#13;
medium-term economic outlook is satisfactory as long as oil production continues to expand and&#13;
world oil prices remain at favorable levels. The fiscal condition should be sustainable in the&#13;
mediumterm provided the government controls the growth of recurrent expenditures, and revenues,&#13;
which depend on oil production and price, do not fall. The recent International Monetary Fund&#13;
(IMF)report (July 2005) shows that in2004, GDP increasedby nearly 50 percent, driven mainly by&#13;
the recovery of the oil sector. After a continuous decline during the last decade, per capita income&#13;
rose to US$940, still less than a quarter of what Iraq used to have two decades ago. Overall GDP&#13;
growth is projected to reach 17 percent in 2006 and then decline gradually to 7 percent and&#13;
continue at that level up to 2010.&#13;
81.     Allocations to education: The combined budgets of MOE and Ministry of Higher&#13;
Education and Scientific Research (MHESR) have a very low share of 4.5 percent in the&#13;
government budget in 2005; it is by far the lowest when compared to other countries in the region&#13;
where the ratio i s twice or three times that in Iraq. This is mainly due to the fact that the&#13;
government budget for 2005 (ID36 trillion) reflects post-conflict conditions with public subsidy&#13;
programs (card ration), state-owned enterprise (SOE) subsidies, and war damage compensation&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
making up 60 percent o f the budget. The share of salaries, which has doubled from 2004, was only&#13;
16 percent o f the budget. Capital goods acquisition (e.g. armored vehicles) and other security&#13;
related materials take up 10 percent of the operational budget. The Iraqi Transitional Government's&#13;
National Development Strategy includes economic reform policies such as privatization,&#13;
restructuring and phasing out of SOE subsidies. If these policies are effectively implemented, more&#13;
resources will be freed up and the financial share of the line ministries, including education, can&#13;
increase.&#13;
82.      The MOE budget: The government policy in 2004 and 2005 was to keep the education&#13;
system functioning, and thus top priority was given to operational expenditure. The government&#13;
relied on international organizations, donors, and bilateral support to finance the reconstruction&#13;
efforts. The M O E budget for 2005 (ID1.3 trillion) consists almost entirely o f operational&#13;
expenditures (92 percent), and a substantial proportion o f the operational expenditure goes to&#13;
salaries (95 percent). Services and asset maintenance make up the rest of the operational budget.&#13;
Allocation for investment expenditure in the MOE budget i s a relatively small amount of ID100&#13;
million (8 percent o f MOE budget). The project will have a significant fiscal impact when&#13;
compared to the current size of the MOE investment budget.&#13;
83.      A range of donor agencies has been involved in supporting education in Iraq since May&#13;
2003, with the U S as the major bilateral partner, and the UN and the World Bank providing&#13;
assistance largely through the two trust funds. The World Bank ITF-financed projects, with a total&#13;
value o f US$lOO million, have focused on emergency textbook printing for 200415, school&#13;
rehabilitation and construction, and capacity building; and the UN financed programs o f US$80&#13;
million have targeted a       wide range o f activities, including school rehabilitation, supplies,&#13;
equipment, and capacity building.While these programs represent a good start, they are small when&#13;
compared to the sector's needs (US$4.8 billion) assessedby the UN/WB Needs Assessment Study&#13;
(October 2003).&#13;
84.      Budgetary and financial management: Iraq lacks adequate financial management&#13;
mechanisms and data reporting frameworks; it also lacks a fully functional statistical reporting&#13;
system. Education financial management has suffered from problems ranging from the poor&#13;
security environment and difficulties in communication with the education authorities in the&#13;
governorates to the non-transparent recording o f financial transactions that affected the MOE's&#13;
ability to allocate resources effectively or to track overall spending and outcomes. The project will&#13;
provide technical support to address urgent problems such as the fragmentation o f the budget,&#13;
inadequate reporting o f expenditures financed both by the government budget and donors, and&#13;
weak accountability. Some basic institutional issues will need to be resolved regarding the role o f&#13;
various actors in addressing issues of budgeting and financial management.&#13;
85.      Institutional capacity: The project will pioneer new design standards for school&#13;
construction that will be incorporated into the national school construction and maintenance&#13;
program. The modus operandi using recipient implementation with support for institutional&#13;
strengthening for better implementation, system development and reform will provide a model for&#13;
other donor financed projects.&#13;
86.      Policy reforms and system eficiency: There is a growing recognition in the MOE of the&#13;
value of developing the human and institutional resources that will be required to conceptualize,&#13;
negotiate and implement financial system reform and policy options. The project will support the&#13;
MOE to manage the interim policy and strategy adjustments that will be required to improve the&#13;
efficiency o f the system and to lay the groundwork for more substantial system development that&#13;
will promote better efficiency of expenditure and provide policy alternatives. There are substantial&#13;
savings that can be generated from improving the efficiency o f the education system and&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                      19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
streamlining the teaching force that would free up resources for part of the enormous need for&#13;
reconstruction and upgrading the education system inIraq.&#13;
&#13;
87.       Cost-effectiveness of school construction standards: The designs used for existing schools&#13;
reflect the norms and educational approaches of the 1970s when schools were designed for teacher&#13;
demonstration rather than pupil participation in experiments. Classrooms are on average smaller&#13;
(43 square meters) than international standards recommend because they were constructed on the&#13;
basis of a relatively low student:classroom ratio of around 30:1, while the current average is 44: 1.&#13;
The project will develop and refine an approach to school design with efficient utilization of space&#13;
and up-to-date design standards. For example, the project will introduce standardized materials&#13;
schedules to encourage the utilization of economically available components throughout the&#13;
country, using modular design', an economical structural span, appropriate orientation of buildings&#13;
to maximize benefits from the local environment to reduce energy costs, and appropriate local&#13;
buildingmaterials andbuildingtechnology to increasedurability andreduce maintenance costs.&#13;
88.       Project's impact on employment creation:The school construction under the project will be&#13;
implemented by local contractors in the governorates and would generate approximately 41,000&#13;
person-days inconsultant services and over 980,000 person-days of work inthe construction sector.&#13;
The conflict and the economic decline have destroyed a large number ofjobs inthe formal and non-&#13;
formal sectors and resulted in an unemployment rate of approximately 30 percent. At present, the&#13;
demand for labor is too low to absorb the continuous demographic increase and workers already&#13;
unemployed. The project will increase the demand for labor in the construction sector and, where&#13;
building materials are bought from local manufacturing firms, the increase will also extend to&#13;
workers inthese firms.&#13;
89,       Fiscal impact of the project: The project would have a significant impact on the capital&#13;
expenditure of MOE. The project would be implemented over three years (2006-2008) with an&#13;
average of ID50 billion a year. These annual allocations represent 42 percent of the annual&#13;
investment expenditure of MOE. The relatively small allocation of investment expenditure reflects&#13;
the government policy of giving top priority to operational outlays to keep the education system&#13;
functioning while depending heavily on foreign donors in the reconstruction efforts. The project&#13;
allocations represent about 3 percent of the total MOE budget and have a marginal fiscal impact on&#13;
the overall education budget.&#13;
&#13;
90.       Project sustainability: The project mainly finances building of new primary and secondary&#13;
schools. School construction is a one-time investment to address accumulated backlogs. The project&#13;
includes provision for financing equipment and furniture for all new schools. Given that the new&#13;
schools will largely accommodate staff and students reassigned from existing overcrowded schools,&#13;
the project will not significantly increase the recurrent costs in terms of teacher salaries or&#13;
management costs. Maintenance of buildings and equipment of the project schools will be covered&#13;
by the MOE recurrent budget. Future maintenance costs of the project schools will be a very small&#13;
share of the overall MOE operational budget and budget projections show that they do not&#13;
constitute a sustainability problem. However, the sustainability of maintenance costs of all schools&#13;
in Iraq (14,000 schools) could become an issue during the short to medium term, as two thirds of&#13;
the public budget goes to transfers and subsidies and the share of the line ministries is quite small&#13;
(MOE share i s 3.5 percent of the government budget in 2005). The expected increase in oil exports&#13;
and the economic reform policies that are being introduced, such as privatization, restructuring of&#13;
SOEs, and phasing out subsidy programs, are expected to stimulate sustainable growth over the&#13;
mediumterm and provide fiscal space for such types of expenditure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5Modular design here refers to a design standard that permits different school modules (classroom blocks,&#13;
laboratories, administration blocks etc.) to be configured in different ways to accommodate the requirements&#13;
of the site.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   F.       RISKS&#13;
&#13;
   91.      This project will be implemented ina high-riskenvironment. The major risks to the project&#13;
   are the unstable security and political environment and the limited capacity o f the government and&#13;
   the private sector. The distribution of the schools across 15 governorates responds to a political&#13;
   imperative for inclusion, provides greater flexibility to accommodate an unpredictable&#13;
   implementation environment, distributes the implementation load across a wider base, and builds&#13;
   the capacity of the system at the governorate level. These risks and others are addressed below:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Risk                     Rating                    MitigationMeasures&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Possibility of high prices due to high demand           Planning will include generous provision for price and&#13;
on local construction industry and local          H     other contingencies. Competitive bidding may also&#13;
inflation (including fuel costs).                       help minimize high costs.&#13;
&#13;
Difficulty inhiring expatriate Technical                Capacity building will focus on local staff. Where&#13;
Assistance (TA) consultants wherever local              possible, support from international TA will be&#13;
&#13;
expertise is lacking.                                   provided through email, phone and video conferences,&#13;
                                                        and meetings outside Iraq.&#13;
School year starting dates may not coincide             Construction activities are on new sites and will not&#13;
with construction schedule.                             disruut schoolinn.&#13;
                                                        Use will be made of local consultants contracted to&#13;
Inability of international Bank staff to carry          assist in supervision. Inaddition, special monitoring&#13;
out in-country supervision.                             instruments would be designed for the use of MOE&#13;
                                                        implementation staff and these supervision consultants.&#13;
                                               ProcurementRisks&#13;
The lack of good laws and regulations, of               A decree was issued by the previous Minister of&#13;
modern standard documentation, and the                  Education rectifying shortcomings inthe current&#13;
habits acquired by procurement staff inthe              procurement practice at the MOE. Continuous training&#13;
Drevious era. which will take time to change.           to be urovided bv a urocurement management firm.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                      21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        I A procurement   management firm will provide&#13;
                                                                                I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Weakness of procurement staff in using Bank               assistanceto the PMT inprocurement using World&#13;
&#13;
procurement guidelines and international                 Bank procurement guidelines, bidding document&#13;
&#13;
sound procurement practice.                              preparation, and bid evaluation and also will provide&#13;
                                                          training in procurement. Close supervision by Bank&#13;
                                                          staff.&#13;
                                                          Selection of a procurement management firm to&#13;
Inability of international Bank procurement               conduct spot physical inspection and assist the PMT in&#13;
staff to supervise project in the field.                  reporting. A local consultant who works with the Bank&#13;
                                                          will conduct procurement supervision from the field.&#13;
Delays in implementing the procurement plan              The procurement management firm will provide&#13;
due to lack of experience inprocurement                   assistance to the PMT in procurement related issues&#13;
planning and the volatile security conditions             and also will provide training inprocurement.&#13;
in Iraq.&#13;
OverallProcurementRisks                        I   H    I&#13;
                                           Fina :ial Man: ement Risks&#13;
Country Level&#13;
Limited direct knowledge of the Bank about          H     Use of MOE controls strengthened by PMT&#13;
the Iraqi government financial systems,                   verification, a parallel accounting system, direct&#13;
controls, and procedures.                                 payment, hiring of external auditors, and documenting&#13;
                                                          all procedures in a procedure manual will help manage&#13;
                                                          these risks.&#13;
Limited knowledge about the Bank's policies        M      Regular communication between the Bank and the&#13;
and guidelines by the Iraqi authorities leading           PMT, frequent training workshops, and quarterly&#13;
to non-compliance.                                        reviews of Financial ManagementReports by the&#13;
                                                          external auditor.&#13;
Project Level&#13;
Limited capacity to meet financial                        Supporting the current PMT with additional&#13;
management requirements of the project at                 accountants to maintain the centralized financial&#13;
MOE and governorates.                                     management function that receives informationfrom&#13;
                                                          the decentralized focal points, records commitments,&#13;
                                                          processespayments, maintains project accounts and&#13;
                                                          generates reports.&#13;
The security conditions which do not allow                Requiring the external auditor to do periodical physical&#13;
timely visits by the project team to perform              inspection for sites under construction where&#13;
physical inspections on the project sites.                necessary.&#13;
The lack of a fixed assets management               H     Having the PMT maintain a fixed assets spreadsheet&#13;
system to maintain information about                      for purchased and delivered equipment and furniture&#13;
purchased and delivered equipment and                     and requiring the auditor to give an opinion on the&#13;
furniture.                                                statement of equipment and furniture.&#13;
Delays in issuing authorizations for payments       H     Streamlined arrangements for processing of contract&#13;
leading to overdue contractors' payments and              approvals and payment authorizations have been put in&#13;
thus undermining competitiveness and                      place.&#13;
leadingto higher costs.&#13;
The banking payment system shortfalls,              M     The Bank issuing payment advices and giving PMT&#13;
where payments may be delayed or lost.                    access to ClientConnection to timely monitor the&#13;
                                                          payment date and investigate any considerable delay.&#13;
Possible low level of coordination and              M     Having all parties involved, responsible and&#13;
reporting arrangements between the PMT                    accountable for the monthly reporting system by&#13;
procurement, financial management,                        governorate and addressing any problemimmediately.&#13;
monitoring and evaluation and the focal&#13;
points at the governorates leading to different&#13;
results and discrepancies between reporting&#13;
on physical progress and related&#13;
expenditures.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Not being able to maintain a project account  H  PMT submitting formal request to MOF to ensure&#13;
for payment of small amounts (less than          access to the project account throughout the project&#13;
US$lO,OOO) throughout the life of the            life. The MOF, MOE Director General of Accounting,&#13;
project leading to delays inpayments and         and PMT will meet in Baghdad to discuss these issues,&#13;
reimbursements.                                  including the project account.&#13;
&#13;
Overall FMRisks                               H&#13;
OVERALL PROJECTRISKS                          H&#13;
&#13;
   H=HighRisk;S =Substantial Risk;M=ModestRisk;N=Low or Negligible Risk&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                          23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 ANNEX 1:SUMMARY COST TABLES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Republic of Iraq&#13;
Third Emergency Education Project&#13;
Project Components      -- Totals Including Contingencies&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
&#13;
                              COMPONENTS                                 TOTAL&#13;
&#13;
 A. COMPONENT I: SCHOOL CONSTRUCTION&#13;
    1. Anbar                                                                 3,580.90&#13;
   2. Babylon                                                                4,661.30&#13;
   3. Basrah                                                                 5,741.75&#13;
   4. Dewaniyah                                                              3,641.17&#13;
   5. Diyala                                                                 3,641.17&#13;
   6. Karbala                                                                3,580.90&#13;
   7. Karkh 1                                                                4,661.35&#13;
   8. Karkh 2                                                                4,721.60&#13;
   9. Karkh 3                                                                3,641.17&#13;
    10. Kirkuk                                                               3,580.90&#13;
   11. Missan                                                                3,641.17&#13;
   12. Muthanna                                                              3,641.17&#13;
    13. Najaf                                                                3,641.17&#13;
    14. Ninewa                                                               4,661.30&#13;
   15. Risafa 1                                                              4,721.60&#13;
    16. Risafa 2                                                             4,7216 0&#13;
   17. Risafa 3                                                              4,661.30&#13;
    18. Salah AI-Din                                                         3,641.17&#13;
   19. Thi-Qar                                                               4,7216 0&#13;
   20. Wassit                                                                3,580.90&#13;
   21. To be identified la                                                   14,164.81&#13;
 Subtotal COMPONENT I: SCHOOL CONSTRUCTION                                   97,250.00&#13;
 B. COMPONENT II: SUPPORT TO SYSTEM DEVELOPMENT                               1,795.00&#13;
 C. COMPONENT 111:      SUPPORT TO PROJECT MANAGEMENT                           955.00&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                                                       100,000.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
\a Sites to be identified during Launch Workshop, according to selection criteria&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                           24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iraq&#13;
Third Emergency Education Project&#13;
Expenditure Accounts by Components Totals IncludingContingencies&#13;
                                     -&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      COMPONENT II:      COMPONENT 111:&#13;
                                                   COMPONENT I:          SUPPORT           PROJECT&#13;
                                                      SCHOOL           TO SYSTEM         MANAGEMENT&#13;
                                                  CONSTRUCTION        DEVELOPMENT                              TOTAL&#13;
 I.Investment Costs&#13;
   A. Civil Works                                         80,978.40                                              80,978.40&#13;
   B. Goods&#13;
      Lab Equipment                                        5,897.04                                               5,897.04&#13;
     Office and other Equipment                            1,800.96                              47.55            1,848.51&#13;
      Furniture                                            1,896.01                                               1,896.01&#13;
   Subtotal Goods                                          9,594.02                              47.55            9,641.57&#13;
   C. Training                                                                   689.69         287.32              287.32&#13;
   D. Consultants' Services&#13;
     Design&amp; SupervisionConsultants                        6.677.89                                               6.677.89&#13;
     TechnicalAssistance                                                        1,10540         334.76            2,129 85&#13;
   Subtotal Consultants' Services                          6,677.89             1,10540         334.76            8,807.74&#13;
   E. OperatingCosts                                                                            284.98              284.98&#13;
Total PROJECTCOSTS                                        97,250.30             1,795.09        954.61           100,000.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iraq&#13;
Third Emergency Education Project&#13;
(US$ million)&#13;
                                                  Disbursement Forecast&#13;
                                             (World Bank Fiscal Year: Julv-June)&#13;
       F Y O 6                      t Y U 1                               t Y U M                        t Y U Y&#13;
   Q3         Q4        Q1       Q2        Q3      Q4       Q1        Q2         Q3      Q4     Q1         Q2      Q3*&#13;
    0.01       0.01      0.05    0.50      4.00     8.50    17.50     19.50      19.50   26.50   2.50       1.33     0.10&#13;
    0.01       0.02      0.07    0.57      4.57    13.07    30.57     50.07      69.57   96.07  98.57     99.90   100.00&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                        25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    ANNEX 2: PROJECTMANAGEMENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A.  Project Management Structure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Project ManagementTearnlwithin the MOE (MOE-PMT)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Directorate Level Coordination&#13;
                                Designated Coordinators at each&#13;
                                          of the 20 Directorates&#13;
                            To work closely with Directorate technical staff for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          I          School Level Coordination                  I&#13;
                    .............l...........L....           ....... ...........&#13;
                                                                       J..&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Stakeholders&#13;
                                        Teachers, Students, Parents&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B. ResponsibilityMatrix&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Key:&#13;
R=Review/Clear E=Execute&#13;
* Ifdecentralized                  S=Support       A=Approve       N=Notified&#13;
                    PMT&#13;
&#13;
Legend:&#13;
MOF:Ministry of Finance; MOPDC:Ministry of Planning and Development Cooperation; MOE:&#13;
Ministry of Education; PMT:Project Management Team (inMOE); DIR:Directorate of Education&#13;
at Governorate level; SCH: School; AUD: FinancialAuditor; PRO:Procurement Consultant (inthe&#13;
case of civil works, PRO includes the private consultants hired to prepare constructiondocuments&#13;
and provide design &amp; supervision services); WB:World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Consultants hired to (i)&#13;
                        supervise projects; (ii)&#13;
                                               prepare contract documents &amp; supervise the works; and (iii)&#13;
provide full design &amp; supervision services, inaccordance with the Procurement Plan.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      ANNEX 3: PROCUREMENTARRANGEMENTS AND PROCUREMENTPLAN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I. General&#13;
&#13;
1.       Project information:&#13;
Country:                                  Republic of Iraq&#13;
Recipient:                                Republic of Iraq&#13;
ProjectName:                              Third EmergencyEducationProject&#13;
ProjectNo.:                               PO96234&#13;
Credit Amount:                            SDR 69.1million (US$lOO million equivalent)&#13;
Project ImplementingAgency (PIA):         The Ministry of Education&#13;
&#13;
2.       Bank's approvalDate of the ProcurementPlan: October 19,2005&#13;
&#13;
3.       Date of GeneralProcurementNotice: October 20, 2005&#13;
&#13;
4.       Period coveredby this procurementplan: Three years&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11.      Goods and Works andNon-ConsultingServices&#13;
&#13;
1.       Prior Review Threshold ProcurementDecisions subject to Prior Review by the Bank as&#13;
         stated inAppendix 1to the Guidelines for Procurement:&#13;
&#13;
            ProcurementMethod               PriorReview Threshold                     Comments&#13;
  1.    Shopping(Goods andWorks)       Firstthree purchase orderdcontracts&#13;
 2.     NCB (Goods)                    &gt;=us$loo,ooo&#13;
 3.     NCB (works)                    &gt;=us$200,000                          Could be revisedduring&#13;
                                                                             project implementation&#13;
 4      Direct Contracting/Purchase    All&#13;
 5      ICB (Goods/works)              All                                   If security improvedinIraq&#13;
                                                                             ICB could be usedfor&#13;
                                                                             larger works contracts&#13;
&#13;
2.       Reference to Project ImplementationManual&#13;
&#13;
The ProjectManagementTeam (PMT) will preparea simple Project Implementation Manual (PIM)&#13;
by the start of the project in February 2006. The PIM will be based on the MIM which was&#13;
preparedby an international consulting firm financed under the Capacity Building Trust Fund for&#13;
Iraq.&#13;
&#13;
3.       Other Special Procurement Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
Due to the emergency nature of the project, advance procurementwill be used for the preparation&#13;
of the first phase design and supervision packages. About nine small contracts for the supervision&#13;
of schools construction will be signed as extension of existing contracts with nine local qualified&#13;
consulting firms. These firms are the ones who will prepare the design and bidding documents for&#13;
these nine schools. These local consulting firms were selected competitively using Consultant&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Qualification method under the ongoing ESCRP to prepare design, bidding documents and&#13;
construction supervision of similar projects. All remaining design and supervision consultancy&#13;
services contracts will be procured usingLeast Cost Based Selection method and there will be an&#13;
advertisement in the UNDB and dgMarket for expression of interest for contracts estimated at&#13;
US$200,000or more.&#13;
&#13;
4.       Procurement Packages with Methods and Time Schedule&#13;
&#13;
It is not expected at this time that international contractors would be interested in the works&#13;
contracts under this project, especially given the current security situation in Iraq and the scattered&#13;
locations o f the subprojects over 15 governorates. Therefore, no civil works contracts are expected&#13;
to be procured using ICB procedures. However, if the security conditions improve during project&#13;
implementation, the PMT would consider packaging smaller contracts into large contracts that may&#13;
attract international firms. There i s no domestic preference under the project. A detailed&#13;
procurement plan i s attached.&#13;
&#13;
111.     Selection of Consultants&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Selection Method                Prior Review Threshold               Comments&#13;
    1. Competitive Methods (Firms)          &gt;=us$100,000&#13;
    2.  Single Source (Firms)               All&#13;
    3.  Individual Consultants              &gt;=IJS$SO.OOO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.       Short list comprised entirely of national consultants&#13;
&#13;
Based on the response for expression of interest to be advertised inUNDB and dgMarket, a short list&#13;
of consultants for services may be comprised entirely of national consultants in accordance with the&#13;
provisions of paragraph 2.7 o f the Consultant Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
3.      Any Other Special Selection Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
The selection of an international procurement management consulting firm was not successful&#13;
under the previous education projects due in part to the high cost o f security measures. The PMT i s&#13;
considering other alternatives, such as selection of a local qualified consulting firm. The selection&#13;
method will be Quality and Cost Based Selection (QCBS) under advance procurement. The short&#13;
list may include less than 6 firms because o f the volatile security conditions in Iraq and the lack of&#13;
qualified local firms in procurement in Iraq. It i s also expected that international consulting firms&#13;
may not be interested in design and supervision of school construction while the security situation&#13;
i s as volatile as i s the case now in Iraq. As the security conditions improve and international&#13;
consultants show interest, the composition o f the short lists would be assessed by the PMT and the&#13;
Bank team for inclusion o f international consultants. It i s also expected that consulting offices&#13;
associated with local universities may be included in the short lists. University-based consultants&#13;
shall not have preference over private consultants.&#13;
&#13;
4.       Consultancy Assignments with Selection Methods and Time Schedule&#13;
&#13;
These are indicated in the procurement plan below.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IV.     Implementing Agency Capacity BuildingActivities with Time Schedule&#13;
&#13;
The agreed CapacityBuilding Activities are listed with time schedule&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Expectedoutcome I                   Estimated       Estimated     Start    Comments&#13;
 Activity Description                 cost (US$)     Duration      Date&#13;
&#13;
 Training on procurement, settingup      300,000     12months      February LocaUregional&#13;
 a procurementmonitoring system at                                 2006     consultingfirm&#13;
 the ministry of education, support&#13;
 the PMT inbidding document&#13;
 preparation,bids evaluation,&#13;
 reporting and spot physical                                     l         l&#13;
 inspection&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                              31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      ProcurementPlanfor GoodsandWorks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-rn&#13;
8                                                                                                                                                                                    7&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      Comple-&#13;
                 Procurement                                       Estimated&#13;
m                   System                     Descriptlon                                                                                                                             tion&#13;
c                     Ref.#                                        (USS)I C                                                                                                            Date&#13;
h&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   I&#13;
B                      C                                                                       G I H I             1   1        N      I        P            V     I         X       -&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                     -A&#13;
P I                1. WORKS              I                   I                 I          l           l      1         I               I              I             I              I          I&#13;
P       1.1 Construction of New Schools. 12 Classrooms   - Phase I             1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
P       TEEP.WN.NCB1.BAG R3.PH-I           BaghdadiR3             $    629,050       1         1         NCB     PRIOR      26-Feb-06 26-Mar-06 j     I   21-May-06     31-May-06 30-Jan-07&#13;
&#13;
P  I    TEEP WN NCBl BAG K1 PH-I         IBaghdadiKl              $    629,050  1    1         1   1     NCB 1   PRIOR  1 26-Feb-06 I 26-Mar-06 1         21-May-06 j    31-May-06 30-Jan-07&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   I            1&#13;
P    1  TEEP.WN.NCB1.ANB.PH-I            IAnbar               11                                                                                                                               1&#13;
                                                                  $    629,050  1    1    1    1    1    NCB 1   PRIOR  1   26-Feb-06 126-Mar-06      1   21-Map06 131-Mav-06I 30-Jan-07        1&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl BAB PH-I              Babyion                                                                                     1              1&#13;
                                                                  $    629,050       1         1         NCB     PRiOR      26-Feb-06 26-Mar-06           21-May-06 I31-May-O6/ 30-Jan-07&#13;
&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl MIS PH-I              Missan             11  $    629,050  11   1   1I    1   1I    NCB 1I  PRIOR  11   26-Feb-06 126-Mar-06     ~   21-May06 131-May-061 30-Jan-07 1&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                I&#13;
P  I    TEEP WN NCBl KAR PH-I            (Karbala             1   $    629,050       1     1   1    1    NCB 1   PRIOR  1    26-Feb-06 126-Mar-061 21-May-06 131-May-061 30-Jan-07              1&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl KER PH-I              Kirkuk                               1&#13;
                                                                  $    629,050       1         1         NCB     PRIOR       26-Feb-06 126-Mar-06     ~   21-May-06 131-May-06( 30-Jan-07&#13;
&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl NIN PH-I             INinawa             1I                                    I1&#13;
                                                                  $    629,050            i1                 1I         I1             I               1                                        I&#13;
                                                                                ~    1         1         NCB     PRiOR       26-Feb-06 26-Mar-06          21-May-06 131-May-061 30-Jan-07&#13;
&#13;
P    I  TEEP WN NCBl WAS PH-I             IWassil             1 $      629,050  1    1     1   1    1    NCB 1   PRiOR  1    26-Feb-06 26-Mar-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                         1             1  21-May-06 131-May-06/ 30-Jan-07       I&#13;
                            Subtotal 1.1  1                       $  5,661,450       9         9                                                                                                 1&#13;
&#13;
P       1.2 Construction of New Schools. 24Classrooms    - Phase II&#13;
P    I  TEEP WN NCBl BAG R1 PH-II         IBaghdadiRl         1   $  1,399,940  1    1     1   1     1   NCB  1  PRIOR  I    07-Jul-06 104-Aug-061 23-Sep-06 128-Sep-06/ 28-Sep-07               1&#13;
P    I  TEEP WN NCBl BAG R2 PH-II         IBaghdadiRP         1 $    1.399 940  i    1     1   1     j   NCB  1  PRIOR  I    07-Jui-06 04-Aug-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                         I                20-Sep-06  1 25-Sep-06 1 25-Sep-07&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl BAG R3 PH-Ii          BaghdadiR3             $  1,399,940       1         1         NCB     PRIOR       07-Jul-06       04-Aug-06 11 20-Sep-06       25-Sep-06 25-Sep-07&#13;
&#13;
P    1  TEEP.WN NCBl BAG K1 PH-II         IBaghdadiKl         1                                      '&#13;
                                                                  $  1,399,940   1   1      1  1     1   NCB  1  PRIOR   I   07-Jul-06   1 04-Aug-061     PO-Sep-06    1  25-Sep-06 25-Sep-07&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                    1            1&#13;
P       TEEP.WN.NCB1.BAG KZPH-iI           BaghdadiKP             $  1,399,940       1         1         NCB     PRIOR       07-Jul-06       04-Aug-06    20-Sep-06 125-Sep-06 25-Sep-07'&#13;
&#13;
P       TEEP.WN.NCBl,BAG.K3.PH-II          BaghdadiK3             S  1,399,940       1         1         NCB     PRIOR       07-Jul-06       04-Aug-06    20-Sep-06  I    25-Sep-06 25-Sep-07&#13;
&#13;
P       TEEP.WN.NCB1 .ANB.PH-iI           \Anbar                  $  1,399,940       1 I 1               NCB     PRIOR       07-Jul-06       04-Aug-06    20-Sep-06       25-Sep-06 25-Sep-07&#13;
&#13;
P    I  TEEP.WN.NCB1.BAB.PH-I1            babvlon               1 $  1,399,940   1    1     1  1     1   NCB  1  PRIOR    1  07-Jul-06 104-Aug-06       1 20-Sep-06 125-Sep-06I 25.~ep-071&#13;
&#13;
P    1  TEEP WN NcBl BAS PH-II            /Basrah               [ $  1399,940        1         1         NCB     PRiOR       07-Jul-06       04-Aug-06    20-Sep-06    ~  25-Sep-06 125-Sep-07&#13;
&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl BAS PH-II            IDewaniyah              $  1,399,940   11  i 1    11       1i  NCB  1I PRIOR    11 07-Jul-06    1I 04-Aug-06  1I20-Sep-06    I 25-Sep-06 1 25-~ep-07&#13;
P    I  TEEP.WN.NCB1.OlY.PH.II            IOiyala               I1$  1,399,940   I    1     I  1      1  NCB   I PRIOR    I  07-Jul-06 04-Aug-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                          I             1 20-Sep-06    1 25-Sep-06 I 25-Sep-07 1&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl KAR PH-II             Karbala              1 s  1,399,940   1    1     1   1     1  NCB   1 PRIOR    1  07-Jul-06 104-Aug-06       1 20-Sep-06    1  25-Sep-06/ 25-~ep-07&#13;
&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl KER PH-II             Kirkuk                 $  1,399,940        1         1        NCB     PRIOR       07-Jul-06       04-Aug-06    20-Sep-06       25-Sep-06 25-Sep-07&#13;
&#13;
P    1  TEEP.WN.NCB1.MIS.PH-I1            /Missan               1 $  1,399,940    1   1     1   1        NCB   1 PRIOR    1   07-Jul-06 104-Aug-06/ 20-Sep-06           1 25-Sep-061 25-Sep-07    1&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl MUT PH-II            IMuthanna                               1         1                  j&#13;
                                                                  $  1399.940         1         1        NCB     PRIOR       07-Jul-06 104-Aug-061 20-Sep-06              25-Sep-06 125-Sep-07&#13;
&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl NAJ PH-II            'Najaf                11                                    111                 1I&#13;
                                                                  $  1,399,940    I   1     1   1        NCB   I PRIOR        07-Jul-06   I 04-~ug-06I    20-Sep-06     1125-Sep-06 125.~ep-07&#13;
&#13;
P      1TEEPWN NcBi NIN PH-II             INinawa               1 $   1,399,940       1      1  1     1  NCB   I PRIOR        07411.06       04-Aug-06  1 20-Sep-06     1 25-Sep-06 25-Sep-07&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                    1              1&#13;
P       TEEP WN NCBl SAL PH-ii            ISalah AI Din                                               1                                                 1&#13;
                                                                  $   1,399,940       1         1        NCB     PRIOR        07-Jul-06      04-Aug-06    20-Sep-06 125-Sep-06 125-Sep-07&#13;
&#13;
P    I1 TEEP WN NCBl THI PH-II            lThi Oar              11                           11                1I         11I             I11&#13;
                                                                  $   1,399,940   I11 1         1        NCB     PRIOR        07-Jul-06      04-Aug-06   1PO-Sep-06     I 25-Sep-06  125-Sep-07&#13;
&#13;
P    1  TEEP WN NCBl WAS PH-II            IWassil               1 $   1,399,940   1   1      I  1     1  NCB PRIOR&#13;
                                                                                                               1          1   07-Jul-06 104-Aug-061 20-Sep-06 125-Sep-06 125-Sep-071&#13;
     I                      Subtotal 1.2  I                     1 $ 27,998,800    1  20      1 20     1        I          1               I              I              i            I             I&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11 731       1.3 Construction of New Schools. 18 Classrooms. Phase Ill                                                                                   I&#13;
   741 P  I1 TEEP.WN.NCB1 BAG.Rl.PH4          IBaghdad/Rl       1 $    1,876,720l1  2   1i  1   1 l NCB 1l PRIORII 15-Sep-06 I1    13-Oct-06II  29-Nov-06 106-Dec-06 06-Oct-07&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                        I1           I1&#13;
   761 P  I  TEEP WN NCBl BAG R2 PH-Ill       IBaghdadiR2      i   $   1,876,720    2 I     1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-06 04-Dec-07&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1  801 P  1  TEEP WN NCBl BAG K1 PH-Ill        lBaghdadiK1      1 $    1,876,720i   2     1 1    1  NCB 1  PRIOR 1   15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06&#13;
                                                                                                                              I             i   29-Nov-06 I04-Dec-06/ 04-Dec-071&#13;
1  821 P  I  TEEPWN.NCB1.BAG K2.PH-Ill         lBagldadiK2      1  $   1876.720   1 2     1 1    1  NCB I  PRIOR   1 15-Seo-06 13-Ocl-06&#13;
                                                                                                                              I             1   29-Nov-06 104-Oec-061 04-Dec-071&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   841 P  I  TEEP WN NCBl BAG K3 PH-Ill        lBaghdadiK3         $     938,360     1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06     04.Dec-06 04-Dec-07&#13;
&#13;
   66  P     TEEP WN NCBl ANB PH-Ill            Anbar              $    938,360      1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-06 04-Dec-07&#13;
1  681 P  1  TEEP.WN.NCB1.BAB.PH-Ill           IBabyion         1  $   1,676,720  1 2     1 1   1   NCB  1 PRIOR 1   15-Sep-06 13-Ocl-06&#13;
                                                                                                                              I               1 29-Nov-06 I04-Dec-08I 04-Dec-07/&#13;
&#13;
   90  P     TEEP WN NCBl BAS P H 4             Basral          j                         1     I        1       I              1             1            1            1&#13;
                                                                   $   1,876,720  ~ 2       1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-06 04-Dec-07&#13;
&#13;
   92  P     TEEP WN NCBP BAS PH-IiI            Basral             $    938,360      1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-08 04-Dec-07&#13;
I  941 P  1  TEEPWN NCBl BAS PH-Ill            IDewaniyaI      ! $      938,360   1  1    1 1   I NCB 1    PRIOR I   15-Sep-06 13-0ct-06&#13;
                                                                                                                              I              1  29-NOv-06 104-Dec-061 04-Dec-071&#13;
&#13;
   96  P     TEEP WN NCBl DIY PH-Ill            Diyala             $    938,360 j    1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-06' 04-Dec-07&#13;
&#13;
  102 P      TEEP WN NCBl KAR PH-Ill            Karbala            $    938360       1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-06 04-Dec-07&#13;
&#13;
  104  P     TEEP WN NCBl KER PH-Ill            Kirkuk             $    938,360      1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Ocl-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-06, 04-Dec-07&#13;
1 1061 PI    TEEPWN.NCB1 MIS.PH-Ill           IMissan           1 $     938,360           1     I       1        1             1              1                                       1&#13;
                                                                                  ~  1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Se0-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06 104-Oec-061 04-Dec-07&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  110  P     TEEP WN NCBl NAJ PH-Ill            Naja1              $     938,360  1  1  I   1    1  NCB  1 PRIOR   1 15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                1             1 29-Nov-06 104-Dec-06/ 04-Dec-07&#13;
! 1121 PI    TEEP.WN.NCB1.NIN.PH-Ill           INinawa          1I $   1,876,720  1 2   1   1    !  NCB  1 PRiOR   I 15.Sep-06  j  13-Oct-06  1 29-Nov-06  1 04-Dec-061 04-Dec-07 1&#13;
  114  P     TEEP.WN.NCB1.SAL.PH-Ill            Salal AI Din       $     938,360     1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-06 04-Dec-07&#13;
&#13;
  118  P     TEEP.WN.NCB1.THI PH-Ill            Tli Oar            $   1,876,720     2      1       NCB  ~ PRIOR     15-Sep-06 13-Ocl-06        29-Nov-06     04-Dec-06! 04-Dec-07&#13;
&#13;
  1201 P  1  TEEP WN NCBl WAS PH-Ill          IWassiI           1  $     938,360  1  1    1 1    1  NCB  1 PRIOR   1 15-Sep-06 13-Oct-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                1             1 29-Nov-06  1 04-Dec-06 1 04-Dec-07 1&#13;
  1231 P  1                      Subtotal 1.3  1                1  $  28,150,800  1 30    1 21   I       1         1            1             I            I              I            I&#13;
  1261 P    11.4 Constructionof New Schools. 12 Classrooms Phase IV               1       1        1      1        I            I             I            I              I            I&#13;
  1271 P  1  TEEP WN NCBl BAG R1 PH-IV         IBaghdadiRl      1 S      666,960  1  1    1 1    I NCB I   PRIOR   1 15-Ocl-06 12-Nov-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                1              129-Dec-06  I 03-Jan-07 1    03-Jan-08  1&#13;
  1291 P    1TEEP.WN NCB1.BAG.RZ.PH-IV         IBagIdadiRP      1  $     666,960  1  1    1 1    I NCB I   PRIOR   1 15-Oct-06 12-Nov-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                 1             129-Dec-06  I 03-Jan-07 j    03-Jan-08  1&#13;
  131  P     TEEP WN NCBl BAG K2 PH-IV          BaghdadiKP      I                  1      1      I       1          1            1                           1            1&#13;
                                                                   $     666,960     1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Oct-06 12-Nov-061 29-Dec-06           03-Jan-07 03-Jan-06&#13;
&#13;
  133  P     TEEP WN NCBl BAG K3 PH-IV          BagldadiK3         $     666,960     1      1       NCB  ~ PRIOR     15-Oct-06 12-Nov-06        29-Dec-06     03-Jan-07 03-Jan-08&#13;
&#13;
  1351 P    1TEEP WN NCB2 BAS PH-IV            /Dewaniyah       1 $      666,960  1  1    1 1     1 NCB   1PRIOR    115-Oct-06 12-Nov-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                 I             129-Dec-06  1 03-Jan-07 1    03-Jan-08  I&#13;
  1371 P    1TEEP WN NCBl DIY PH-IV            IDiyala          1  $     666,960     1    1 1     1 NCB   1PRIOR    I15-Oct-06 12-Nov-06       129-Dec-06  I 03-Jan-07 1    03-Jan-08  1&#13;
  143  P     TEEP WN NCBl MIS PH-IV             Missan          j                 11      1       1       1         I            11            1           1              1&#13;
                                                                   $     666,960     1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Oct-06 12-Nov-06        29-Dec-06      03-Jan-07 03-Jan-08&#13;
&#13;
  145  P     TEEP WN NCBl MUT PH-IV             Mulhanna           $     666,960     1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Oct-06 12-Nov-06        29-Dec-06      03-Jan-07 03-Jan-08&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                          1&#13;
  1471 P    1TEEPWN.NCB1.NAJ.PH-IV             INaIaf           1  $     666,960   1 1     11     1 NCB   1PRIOR    115-Ocl-06 12-Nov-06&#13;
                                                                                                                                 I             129-Dec-06    1 03-Jan-07 1  03-Jan-08   1&#13;
  149  P     TEEP WN NCBl SAL PH-IV             Salah AI Din       $     666,960     1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Oct-06 12-Nov-06        29-Dec-06     03-Jan-07 03-Jan-08&#13;
&#13;
  153  P     TEEP WN NCBl THI PH-IV             Thi Qar            $     666,960     1      1       NCB    PRIOR     15-Oc1-06 12-Nov-06        29-Dec-06      03-Jan-07 03-Jan-08&#13;
&#13;
                                 Subtotal 1.4  1                1  S   7,336,560   111     111    I       1         1            I             I             I             I            I&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                 33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1 1581      1            2. GOODS       I                  I                  I      l         l     1      I             I         I           I            I          i&#13;
I11591        2.1 Furniture             I                                                                                 I         I                                   i&#13;
  1601 P    11TEEPG.FNCB1.PH.i          /BGovernorate      II $      142,000  I1  9  l1 1    1 l NCB I1PRIORI1  30.Apr-05 128-May061 14-Jul-06  II  19.Jul-06 16-DBC-061&#13;
                                                                                                                                                             I1&#13;
1 1621 P    1 TEEP.G.F.NCB1.PH.II       )l5Governorates     1 $      655,000    123    1I icB1       I PRIOR 1  30.Jan.07 127-Feb-071 15.Aqr-07    ~18-Apr.071 15-Sep-071&#13;
1 1641 P    1 TEEPG.F.ICB1 PH.4         115 Governorates   I $       878,000    136    11   j    ICE I PRIOR   130-Jan-07 27.Feb-07 1          I             I&#13;
                                                                                                                          ~           15-Apr-07     18-Apr-07 15-Sep07/&#13;
1 1661 P    1 TEEP.G.F.ICB1 PH-IV       18Govetnorates     I $       Z~I,OOO    114  I  1  I     ICB  1PRIOR   130-Jan-07 l27-Feb.07/ 15-Aqr.07    116-Apr-07 15.~ep.071&#13;
                                                                                                                                                             1&#13;
&#13;
r 1701      1 2.2Eauiornent             I                  I                  I      l        l     1        I            I         I              I         I          1&#13;
1 1711 P    1 TEEP.G.E.ICB1.PH-I        18 Governorate     15       346.000     19   1  1  I     ICB  1PRIOR I  30-Aor.06 128-Ma"-051 14-Jul-06    119-Jul-06 15-Dee-051&#13;
                                                                                                                                                             1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   SH I IShopping (inaccordance with section 3 5 01 the Guidelines)          I            I                        I         I&#13;
                                   NA = lNot aoolicable    1                         I       I       I                              I&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                 34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               Procurement Planfor Consultants' Services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  2       3.1 Sewlces for Deslgn 6 Superdslon of New Sohoolr&#13;
&#13;
  3       3.1.1 Phase I (for 8 Governorates). 12 CIassroomr~Supewlsion Sewlces&#13;
&#13;
  4  P      TEEP DC DLS-BAG W-PH-I           IBaQhdadlR3                  S        33,580   DCI'      PRIOR                                1   8-May06        15-May06        28.Feb-07   1&#13;
  8  P      TEEP DC DLS-BAG K1-PH-I          IBaghdadIKl                  S        33,580   DCI'      PRIOR                                    8.May-06       15.May.06       28-Feb-07&#13;
&#13;
  8  P      TEEP DC DLS-ANB-PH.1              Anbar                       S        33.560   DCI'      PRiOR                                    8-May-06       15.Ma.y-06      28-Feb-07&#13;
&#13;
 10 P       TEEP DC DLS-BABPH-I              1Babylon                     S        33,560   DCI.      PRIOR                                    8-May06        15-May06        28-Feb-07&#13;
&#13;
 12 P       TEEP DC DLS-BAS-PH.1             /Missan                      S        33,560   DCI'      PRIOR i                                  8-May-06       15-May46        28.Feb07    j&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        I S        33.560  1DCI'    1 PRIOR    1            I              1   B-MayOB     1  15-May-06 I     28.Feb-07    1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 29  P      TEEP LCS-DES-8, M,T.PH-il         0asrah. Missan,Thiqar       S     357,300    1LCS       PRIOR      16-Demo5      13-Jam06        19-Mar06    1  22-Mar-06       23-a1.07&#13;
&#13;
 31  P      TEEP LCS-DLS-0, M, W-PH-I1        Dewaniyah. Muthana. W a s S       357,300     LCS       PRIOR      16.Dec05      13-Jan46    ,   19-Mar05       22-Mar06        23-Ocl07     ,&#13;
&#13;
 33  P      TEEP LCS-DLS-K, B, N-PH-Ii        Ksrbala, Babel, Nqal        $     357,300     LCS       PRIOR      16-Dec05      13-Jan06        19.Mar46       22.Mar46        23-Oct-07&#13;
&#13;
 35  P      TEEP LCS-DLS-A. S-PH.4            Anbar. Salah Aidin          $     238,200  I  LCS       PRIOR      16-Dm45       13.Jan-06       19-Ma(-06      22-Mar08        23-at-07&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I51 1P   1  TEEP LCS-D&amp;SK2. K3 PH-Ill        IBaahdad W.K3              I $     237,780    ILCS     I PRIOR    I 14.~eb-06   I  14.~ar.06   I  IB.MW.OB     i 21.~ay-06   1    6 . ~ ~ 0 7  I&#13;
3    P      TEEP LCS-DLS Bas P H 4           IBasrah                       $    237,780     LCS       PRIOR      14.Feb.05      14-Mar06       18-May06       21-May46         5-NOV-07&#13;
&#13;
 55  P      TEEP LCS-D&amp;ST,M PH-Ill           iThiqar, Missan               $    237,780     LCS       PRIOR      14-Feb-06      14.Mar46    ' 18-May06 21-May-06               6-Now07&#13;
&#13;
 57  P      TEEP LCS-DLSD, M, W PH-Ill       /DeWmlyah, Muthsna. Wass S         237.780     LCS       PRIOR      14-Feb-06      14-Mar06       18-May06       21-May-06        6-Nov07&#13;
&#13;
 59  P      TEEP LCS-D&amp;SK B PH.111           IKarbala Naiaf                S    158.520     I C s     PRIOR      14-Feb-06      14-Mar-06      18-May-06      21.Mav-OB        6-Now07      I&#13;
&#13;
 61  P      TEEP LCS-DE B P H 4               0abyIon                      S    158,520     LCS       PRIOR      14-Feb-06      14-Mar-06      18-May06       21-May06         6-Nov07&#13;
&#13;
 631 P   1  TEEP LCS-DLSA, S. D PH.iI1       IAnbar, Saiah Aldln, D~yala S      237,780     LCS       PRiOR      14.Feb.06      14-Mar-06   1  18-May-OB 21-May06              6-No"-07&#13;
1651 PI     TEEP LCS-D&amp;SK1 PH-4              INInawa. Klrkuk             I S    237.780    1LCS      1PRIOR     i14.Feb.06    1 14-Mar06      118-May-06    1 21-May05      1  B-Nov07      1&#13;
 73                                               Sub101d for 3.1.3        I 2,377,800                                                                      1                               i&#13;
&#13;
 75       3.1.4 Phase iV (for 15 Governorales)~12 CIassrooms                                                                                                I&#13;
 76  P      TEEP LCS-DLS R1.2 PH.IV           hghdad R1. RZ                8    111.880     LCS       PRIOR      26.~ar.06      23-Apr-05      27-Jun-06      30-Jun-06       31-Jaw08&#13;
1781 P   1  TEEPLCS-D&amp;SK2.3PH-lV             10aahdad. W K3              I $    111,880    1LCS      1PRIOR     126-Mar06    I  23.Aor.06   1  27.Jun-06     130-Jun-06   1   31-Jan08       1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 93  P      TEEPQCBS-PRO                     I                             S    300000     1QCBS     1PRIOR     12-Jan-06     1 30-Jan-05     1 5-Aor06 1      8-A~r06      1  8-A~r.07      1&#13;
&#13;
                                    QCBS = Quality and Cosbbased Selection (in accordance with s e ~ l i o n2 ~1 - 2 28 of the Guidelines)&#13;
                                      LCS = Least-Cost Sel~~tion(in accordance With section 3 6 of the Guidelmes)&#13;
                                     CQS = Selection Based on consultanls' Qualifications (in accordance with section 3 7 of the Guidelines)&#13;
                                        IC = Selection 01 Individual Consultants (8" accordance with Sections 5 1 - 5 4 01 the Guidelines1&#13;
                                        DC= Direscl Canlract~ng&#13;
                                      SSS = Sinple Source Selection in accordance With sections3 09. 3 13 of the Guidelines&#13;
                                       NA = Not Applicable&#13;
                                           *IIExtend#nuexistinu contract^ financed under ESCRP for supervision based of the SatisfaCIoIypeltormance&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               ANNEX 4: FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT AND DISBURSEMENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
FinancialManagement&#13;
I. ExecutiveSummaryandConclusion&#13;
1.       The project financial resources extended through an IDA Credit will be managed within the&#13;
framework of the Iraqi government systems and allocated by the MOF within the MOE budget. The&#13;
MOF is the representative of the Recipient of the Credit. It will play a wider role in allocating the&#13;
budget and recording the Bank disbursements as expenditures against the project budget. In&#13;
addition, a monitoring role is expected to be played by the MOPDC, through the Donor Assistance&#13;
Database (DAD).&#13;
2.      Presently, the MOE is implementing two projects financed through the ITF. One of these&#13;
two projects has a similar design, objective and implementation mechanism. The financial&#13;
management arrangements will be similar to those being followed under the ITF projects taking&#13;
into consideration the experience gained and the issues faced during the implementation of the&#13;
ongoing projects. A full financial management assessment had previously been conducted on MOE&#13;
capacity. This assessment has been updated through interviews, in Amman, with the ministry staff&#13;
and the representatives of the MOPDC and MOF.&#13;
3.       The fiduciary risk that the Credit would not be used for the intended purposes, with due&#13;
regard to economy, efficiency, and the sustainable achievement of the project's development i s&#13;
considered as high. The financial management risk, an element of the fiduciary risk, i s also&#13;
considered as high. This rating is the result of the assessment performed by the Bank team and the&#13;
outcome of the various reports issuedby independent auditors and other donors.&#13;
4.       This financial management risk will be partly managed through: (i)  reinforcing the present&#13;
controls as applied by the MOE; (ii)    the engagement of two additional accountants to work and&#13;
support the financial officer already following on the ongoing projects; (iii)    payments to most&#13;
contractors, consultants and vendors will be made through direct payment method, while payments&#13;
below the threshold of US$lO,OOO        will be reimbursed to the ministry upon presentation of&#13;
supporting documentation and proof of payment; (iv) the generation of monthly reports by the&#13;
governorates advising the MOE in Baghdad about their commitments and expected disbursements;&#13;
(v) maintaining a fixed assets spreadsheet for purchased and delivered equipment and furniture;&#13;
(vi) initially, a spreadsheet application will be used to follow on the project accounts and to&#13;
generatethe project reports. However; the option to install an accounting system at the PMT will be&#13;
considered, depending on the availability of vendors that are ready to provide the needed support&#13;
inside Iraq; and (vii) the engagement of an independent auditor, with international experience&#13;
acceptable to the Bank, to perform the project audit and issue an independent auditor opinion, in&#13;
additionto reviewing the quarterly interimfinancial reports (FMRs).&#13;
5.       All the above activities andprocedures will be documented ina chapter of the PIM.&#13;
6.       The residual risk will be managed during project implementation through close monitoring&#13;
and supervision by the project FMS.&#13;
&#13;
11.      Managing Financial Management Risk&#13;
Country Financial Management Risk&#13;
7.       A Country Financial Accountability Assessment (CFAA) was not undertaken for Iraq.&#13;
However, many reports, including the IMF-World Bank Report of April 2005 on Iraq Public&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Financial Management' show a high inherent risk in almost all the main functions o f a financial&#13;
management system (budgeting, internal controls, accounting, reporting). The security situation, the&#13;
significant weakness o f budget reporting and of the banking system, which hampers domestic&#13;
payments, and many years of isolation add to that risk.&#13;
8.       Inadditiontotheroleofthe PMT,the MOFhasawider monitoringrolethroughitscontrol&#13;
o f allocation o f the project funds to the M O E budget and its recording of the Bank disbursements as&#13;
expenditures against this budget'. In addition, the MOPDC will monitor all international donor-&#13;
financed projects through the Development Assistance Database.&#13;
Project Financial Management Risk.&#13;
9.       The MOE PMT has demonstrated its commitment to applying the Bank guidelines&#13;
throughout the currently implemented projects. Nevertheless, the project FM risk remains high. A&#13;
detailed assessment i s included in the overall project risk (Section F). It can be summarized as&#13;
follows:&#13;
&#13;
     0   Limited capacity to meet FMrequirements of the project at M O E and governorates;&#13;
&#13;
     0   The limited ability to carry out on-site supervision missions and physical inspections;&#13;
&#13;
         The lack o f a fixed assets management system to keep track o f purchased and delivered&#13;
         equipment and furniture;&#13;
&#13;
     0   Delays in issuing authorizations for payments leading to overdue contractors' payments&#13;
         and thus undermining competitiveness and leading to higher costs;&#13;
&#13;
     0   The banking payment system shortfalls, where payments may be delayed or lost;&#13;
&#13;
     0   Possible coordination and reporting difficulties between the PMT procurement, financial&#13;
         management, monitoring and evaluation officials and the focal points at the directorates&#13;
         leading to discrepancies between reports on physical progress and related expenditures;&#13;
&#13;
     0   Problems in the maintenance of the project account for payment o f small amounts (less&#13;
         than US$lO,OOO)       throughout the life of the project leading to shortages and payment&#13;
         delays.&#13;
111.      MOEProjectArrangements&#13;
The FMrisk i s partly managed through a set of procedures classified as follows:&#13;
10.       Payment Authorization and Flow of Information, The project activities, including&#13;
invoices for advance payments or for actual incurred expenditures, are subject to MOE applicable&#13;
controls and procedures in addition to the PMT verification and approval. Streamlined&#13;
arrangements for processing of contract approvals and payment authorizations have been put in&#13;
place to overcome delays experienced in the current projects. Having small contracting packages&#13;
and monthly monitoring reports, sent by the focal points to the PMT, will help inmanaging the risk&#13;
of the wide coverage of the project. Inthe absence o f a fixed assets management system, records of&#13;
the equipment and furniture purchased and delivered to schools will be maintained in a spreadsheet&#13;
as part of the FMRs and will be periodically subject to review by the external auditor.&#13;
11.      Accounting System. The PMT has a financial team composed o f a financial officer and&#13;
two accountants. This team will undertake the project request for payments, accounting and&#13;
reporting activities. It will coordinate closely with the MOE financial department and the focal&#13;
points at the governorates. An accounting system will be a highpriority to be installed at the PMT&#13;
&#13;
'*EnhancingSoundPFM-Short-to       Medium-TermsReforms&#13;
  Moreinformationabout the GovernmentBudget, includingMOEbudgeti s disclosedunder Annex 7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
to reduce book keeping risks since the project will generate about 1,loo9financial transactions.&#13;
This system should be able to follow on the project accounts and generate the financial reports&#13;
neededfor monitoring and decision making. Untilsoftware developers who can provide continuous&#13;
support inside Iraq are identified and accounting software is installed at the PMT, spreadsheet&#13;
applications will be used to record the project transactions. There is an on-going project to install a&#13;
Financial Management Information System (FMIS) to support the operations of a fully functional&#13;
Treasury Department in the Ministry of Finance and a nationwide network of 60 remote data entry&#13;
points at line ministries and governorates. The extent of implementation expected during the life of&#13;
this project cannot be determined at this stage.&#13;
&#13;
12.        Flow of Fundsand Controls&#13;
&#13;
                             E-mail Notification of Disbursement&#13;
                                              +&#13;
               I&#13;
               I                          1&#13;
               I&#13;
               I&#13;
               I&#13;
&#13;
                         RequestPayment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Account&#13;
                                                                  MOEPMT&#13;
&#13;
                          Reimbursements&#13;
&#13;
               I                          I                  1&#13;
                                               Contractors,&#13;
                           DirectPayment       Supplier and&#13;
                                               Consultants&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
13.      Reporting&#13;
Quarterly: The MOE will generate interim quarterly Financial Monitoring Reports (FMRs), which&#13;
may be reviewed by the external auditor who will give an explicit professional opinion (negative&#13;
assurance) whether the project FMRs give a true and fair view of the status of the project. The&#13;
reviewed FMRs will be submitted by the MOE to the Bank within 45 days from the end of the&#13;
period. These reports consist o f&#13;
&#13;
     0   FinancialReports:to include a statement of sources and uses of funds by category, and a&#13;
         uses of funddexpenditure report by directorate and category comparing actual and planned&#13;
         expenditures. Also, a narrative report explaining all variances that exceed 15 percent when&#13;
         compared to plan and the proposed corrective actions should be included as an annex to the&#13;
         financial reports.&#13;
&#13;
    0    Contracts Reports: to provide information on contracts, including information on all&#13;
         authorized contract variations, showing contracts' financial status against plan, and&#13;
         percentageof works completed against payments.&#13;
&#13;
     0   EquipmentandFurnitureReports:to provide information on goods purchased and&#13;
         delivered under the project per directorate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 As per the procurement plan 182civil works and goods contracts are expected to be signed under the project&#13;
with average of about 3.5 payments per contract, in addition to an estimate of 540 transactions related to&#13;
consultants and other PMT payments.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14.     The proposed format of the reports i s in the project files and will be finalized with the&#13;
MOErepresentatives duringthe project launchworkshop.&#13;
&#13;
15.     Annually: Audited Project Financial Statements (PFS), showing yearly and cumulative&#13;
balances, will be submitted to the Bank. PFS will include:&#13;
&#13;
    (i)      Statement o f sources and uses of funds by category.&#13;
&#13;
    (ii)    Appropriate schedules classifying project expenditures by directorate and category.&#13;
&#13;
    (iii)    L i s t of commitments or signed contracts&#13;
&#13;
    (iv)     Statement o f equipment and furniture purchasedby directorate.&#13;
16.     Audit Arrangements. An external independent auditor with international experience will&#13;
be engaged to perform the project audit and issue an independent opinion on the PFS and&#13;
compliance with World Bank Procurement Guidelines and terms o f the Financing Agreement&#13;
signed with IDA. The external audit report will encompass all o f the Project's activities and will be&#13;
in accordance with internationally accepted auditing standards. MOE will remit a project audit&#13;
report to the Bank not later than six months after the end of each fiscal year. The auditor selection&#13;
process will be launched directly after the Financing Agreement i s signed. An Escrow account will&#13;
be used to pay the auditor after the project closing date. In addition to the audit reports, the auditor&#13;
will prepare a "management letter" identifying any observations, comments, and deficiencies in the&#13;
system and controls that the auditor considers pertinent, and will provide recommendations for their&#13;
improvements.&#13;
17.     Moreover, and as mentioned in the quarterly reporting section, the auditor will review the&#13;
quarterly interim financial reports (FMRs) and express an explicit professional opinion (negative&#13;
assurance) whether the project FMRs give a true and fair view of the state o f the project's affairs.&#13;
18.     Project Implementation Manual. All the above activities and procedures will be&#13;
documented within a financial management chapter o f the project implementation manual. This&#13;
manual will be based on the recently finalized and adopted MIM that discloses procurement and&#13;
financial management guidelines, rules, and documents to be used for both ITF and IDA projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Action                                                 DueDate&#13;
&#13;
  Designate two additional accountants to project        Directly after Agreement Signature&#13;
&#13;
  Appoint external auditor                               Directly after Agreement Signature&#13;
&#13;
  Finalize FMChapter in PIM                              December 31,2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IV.     Bank Financial Management Supervision&#13;
19.     Where security conditions make travel to Iraq impossible for international Bank staff,&#13;
supervision missions will be undertaken in Amman. The project will require intensive supervision&#13;
duringthe start up phase to ensure timely implementation of the agreed upon action plan including&#13;
hiringthe two additional accountants, appointment of the auditor and finalizing the FMchapter in&#13;
the PIM. Financial supervision of the project will be carried out initially every three months to&#13;
ensure compliance with Bank requirements and to develop financial management ratings.&#13;
V.      DisbursementArrangements&#13;
20.     The Banks strategy in Iraq i s to implement projects though the Iraqi Ministries (rather than&#13;
Project Implementing Units outside government structures), ensuring that appropriate and effective&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
financial controls are in place over the use o f funds provided by the Bank, while at the same time&#13;
working together to strengthen the Ministries' own financial control processes and procedures.&#13;
Taking into consideration the highrisk environment assessedfor the project, including the assessed&#13;
high financial management risk, the disbursement arrangements will compensate by continuing to&#13;
use conservative disbursement methods. The disbursement methods used will be:&#13;
&#13;
(i)     Direct Payments to contractors, suppliers and consultants for eligible expenditures, for&#13;
disbursements over US$lO,OOO.&#13;
&#13;
(ii)    Reimbursement to the MOE for eligible expenditures under US$lO,OOO paid from the&#13;
M O E resources.&#13;
&#13;
(iii)   Special Commitments to a commercial bank to reimburse the commercial bank for&#13;
payments made to a supplier against Letters of Credit issued at the request of the MOE for eligible&#13;
expenditures.&#13;
21.     These are the disbursement methods that have been used for the two existing WB ITF&#13;
education projects currently under implementation by the M O E and which have proven to be&#13;
effective. Extensive training has been provided to the PMT on the Bank's disbursement processes.&#13;
Supporting documentation, e.g., copies of invoices and receipts, i s required to be provided with all&#13;
requests to disburse funds. The original copies o f the supporting documentation will be maintained&#13;
by the MOE and made available for review by Bankrepresentativesupon request.&#13;
22.     Country Financing Parameters (CFP) have been approved for Iraq in September 2005. The&#13;
CFP allow for the financing of 100 percent of project expenditures. The MOE contributes&#13;
implementation support, including the assignment o f MOE staff to the PMT, MOE staff support in&#13;
the M O E Directorates, and some related operating expenses.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                   40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         ANNEX 5: RESULTS-BASEDSUPERVISIONPLAN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Expected Project Outputs&#13;
&#13;
             Summary for all Directorates (see PIMfor Breakdownby Directorate)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               ITY DESCRIPTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   Construction of 82 New Schools in 15 Governorates (20 Directorates1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Phase 1: 9,12-Classroom Primary Schools at 8 Governorates (9 Directorates)&#13;
&#13;
 A   Bidding DocumentsCompleted/a           February7,2006          9&#13;
&#13;
 B   ConstructionContracts Awarded            May 25,2006           9                 5.66&#13;
&#13;
 C   Schools Completed                      October 30,2007         9                 5.66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 A   Bidding DocumentsCompleted               May 21,2006          23&#13;
&#13;
 B   ConstructionContracts Awarded         September 10,2006       23                 32.20&#13;
&#13;
 C   Schools Completed                        June 30,2008         23                 32.20&#13;
1Phase 3: 36,lS-Classroom Primary Schools at 15 Governorates (20 Directorates)                 I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  ntracts Awarded&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Notes:&#13;
   a/ Designand bidding documents are beingpreparedand fundedunder ESCRP&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   ANNEX 6: CODES OF PRACTICEFORPREVENTIONAND MITIGATION OF&#13;
                                 ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        PotentialImpacts                             PreventionandMitigationMeasures&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Water Supply&#13;
8       Installation or rehabilitationI tubewells or dug wells.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Disease caused by poor water&#13;
quality:&#13;
                                       D   Redesign to prevent contaminationif adjacent comparable&#13;
8 contamination by seepage from&#13;
  latrines.                               sources are found to be contaminated.&#13;
&#13;
                                           Subsequent monitoring o f installed or rehabilitated sources.&#13;
D creation of stagnant pools of&#13;
  water.                                   Appropriate location, apron and drainage around tubewells and&#13;
                                          dug wells to prevent formation of stagnant pools.&#13;
&#13;
                                       0   Provision of cover and hand-pump to prevent contamination of&#13;
                                          dug wells.&#13;
&#13;
                                       0  Where pit latrines are used they should be located more than&#13;
                                          10mfromany water source. The base should be sealed and&#13;
                                          separated by at least 2m o f sand or loamy soil from the&#13;
                                          groundwater table.&#13;
                                          Where nightsoil latrines or septic tanks are built they should be&#13;
                                          sealed. Outflows should drain either to a soak away located at&#13;
                                          least 10mfrom any water source or be connected to a working&#13;
                                          drain.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Social Risks:&#13;
&#13;
0 Lack o f clear division o f rights/  0  Ensure sufficient community participation and organization for&#13;
  responsibilities may result in          effective planning and management o f infrastructure.&#13;
  maintenance problems o f&#13;
  wells/pumps.                         0  Identify proper mechanism of rights and responsibilities over&#13;
                                          well/pump/reservoir usage through participatory village focus&#13;
0 Access to water may be captured         groups.&#13;
  by interest groups.&#13;
                                       0  Ensure that local accessible materials are used when&#13;
0 Use o f foreign equipment/              developing/rehabilitating wells in order to provide&#13;
  materials may hinder                    maintenance.&#13;
  maintenance of pumps/wells.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                            42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Potential Impacts                        Preventionand MitigationMeasures&#13;
&#13;
                                   ianitation and Wastewater&#13;
        Latrines, cesspits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Contamination of water supplies:&#13;
&#13;
    contaminationof groundwater      DWhere pit latrines are usedthey should be located more than&#13;
   because of seepage.                10mfrom any water source. The base should be sealed and&#13;
&#13;
   contaminationof surface waters     separatedvertically by not less than 2m of sand or loamy soil&#13;
&#13;
   due to flooding or over-flowing.   from the groundwater table.&#13;
&#13;
                                      Where nightsoil latrines or septic tanks are built they should be&#13;
                                      sealed. Outflows should drain either to a soak away located at&#13;
                                      least 10mfrom any water source or be connected to a working&#13;
                                      drain.&#13;
                                      Maintenance training to be delivered along with new latrines.&#13;
&#13;
Diseasecaused by poor handling      0 Training and healtheducation to be provided to nightsoil&#13;
practices of nightsoil.               handlers where affected by interventions.&#13;
&#13;
                                    0 Protective clothing and appropriate containers for nightsoil&#13;
                                      transportation to be provided.&#13;
&#13;
Diseasecausedby inadequate          0 Nightsoil should be handled using protective clothing to&#13;
excreta disposal or inappropriate     prevent any contaminationof workers skinor clothes.&#13;
use of latrines.                      Where nightsoil is collected for agricultural use it should be&#13;
                                      stored for a sufficient period to destroy pathogens through&#13;
                                      composting. At the minimumit shouldbe stored in direct&#13;
                                      sunlight and turned regularly for a period of at least 6 weeks.&#13;
&#13;
                                    0 Septic tanks shouldnot be constructed nor septic waste&#13;
                                      collectedunless primary and secondary treatment and safe&#13;
                                      disposal i s available.&#13;
&#13;
                                     0Health and hygiene education to be provided for all users of&#13;
                                      latrines.&#13;
&#13;
                                     0Awareness campaign to maintain sanitary conditions.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                             43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Potential Impacts                        Preventionand Mitigation Measures&#13;
&#13;
Disease caused by inadequate&#13;
collection and disposal, including&#13;
health risks from:&#13;
&#13;
  insects, rats.                       B Sufficient frequency of collection from transfer stations.&#13;
  burningof waste.&#13;
                                       B Containment o f waste during collection and transfer.&#13;
&#13;
                                       B Promote separation at source to reduce spreading by rag-&#13;
                                         pickers during recycling.&#13;
                                         Minimize burning.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Provide dailv soil covering.&#13;
                                                                    "&#13;
&#13;
                                Cons uction of Schools and Classrooms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Environmental Impacts:&#13;
&#13;
Disease caused by inadequate             Ensure designs include adequate sanitary latrines and access to&#13;
provision o f water and sanitation.      safe water.&#13;
&#13;
    Improper disposal o f wastes.        Ensure inclusion o f adequate sanitation facilities and&#13;
&#13;
    Sanitation problems.                 maintenance.&#13;
&#13;
    Some construction related            Ensure planning, design and maintenance of infrastructure i s&#13;
&#13;
    problems but usually minor in        appropriate to local needs, traditions, culture and desires.&#13;
&#13;
    nature.                              Proper disposal o f all solid wastes, containers, infectious&#13;
&#13;
    Spread o f disease from              wastes.&#13;
&#13;
    incoming laborers.                   Public health awareness.&#13;
&#13;
    Damage to historical buildings.      Priority given to rehabilitation o f toilets in rehabilitation o f&#13;
&#13;
    Injury and death from                schools.&#13;
&#13;
    earthquakes                          Ensure actions involving historicalbuildings are&#13;
                                         revieweddesignedby qualified specialists.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Apply low cost seismic structural design&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                         44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Potential Impacts                      Preventionand Mitigation Measures&#13;
&#13;
Social Impacts:&#13;
&#13;
   The vulnerable groups (women,&#13;
   poor children, migrants,           Before the start of each infrastructure project, develop&#13;
&#13;
   pastoralists and the poor) may     comprehensive organizational and maintenance plan,&#13;
&#13;
   not benefit from infrastructure    commitment from local government and public to maintain&#13;
&#13;
   construction and rehabilitation.   school supplies, medical supplies, etc.&#13;
&#13;
   Schools/health posts may&#13;
   become abandoned due to the&#13;
   lack o f commitment.&#13;
&#13;
   Buildinginfrastructure system&#13;
   alone without needs assessment&#13;
   may not benefit the community.&#13;
&#13;
   Infrastructure investments may&#13;
   be misappropriated by&#13;
   governments.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               ANNEX 7: ECONOMICANALYSIS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Introductionand Background&#13;
The education system in Iraq that flourished in the 1980s went through a major financial crisis in&#13;
the 1990s as a result o f three major wars and over a decade of sanctions. This led to massive&#13;
degradation and deterioration of the education system and an accumulated backlog in capital&#13;
development and maintenance. This has resulted in:&#13;
         A sharp decline in education expenditure: Education expenditure declined dramatically&#13;
         during the 1990s as a result of the war and the economic embargo. In 1988/89, the&#13;
         education sector budget was US$2.5 billion (about 6 percent o f GDP) and expenditure per&#13;
         student was US$623. Over the 1993-2002 period, the Oil for Food Program (OFFP)&#13;
         provided US$1.744 billion for the education sector, mainly for supplies and equipment and&#13;
         salaries, while other recurrent expenditures were covered by the very limited government&#13;
         resources. As a result, expenditure per student declined to an extremely low level, reaching&#13;
         US$35 by 2003. Duringthe last two years, more resources were allocated to education and&#13;
         in2005, expenditure per student increasedto US$170.&#13;
         A substantial decline in teacher salaries: The OFFP did not include cash payments and, as&#13;
         a result, the funds were not used for meeting recurring expenditure o f any kind. This inturn&#13;
         added to the financial crisis o f the sector and led to a substantial decline in teaching staff&#13;
         salaries. The average teacher salary fell over the decade o f the nineties from US$500 per&#13;
         month to US$5-30 per month and this led to a massive exodus o f trained teachers and other&#13;
         qualified academic and non-teaching staff. However, a new salary structure that was&#13;
         established in 2004 increased the monthly average salary o f teachers to US$120 and it was&#13;
         raised again to US$200 in 2005.&#13;
&#13;
     0   A signifcant deterioration in system eficiency: The extremely low allocations to the sector&#13;
         led to rapid deterioration in all aspects o f the education system. New students were&#13;
         admitted to existing schools because there were no funds to build new schools. One-third o f&#13;
         the schools are operating in double and triple shifts to accommodate additional students.&#13;
         This has also contributed to an increase in dropouts and repetition. The crowded&#13;
         classrooms, shortage of teaching and learning materials, and the loss o f qualified teachers&#13;
         got much worse after the last war due to the damage to the education institutions and&#13;
         looting of its equipment and physical infrastructure.&#13;
Rationalefor InvestinginEducation&#13;
Investment in restoring the education system is crucial to Iraq. There are substantial benefits from&#13;
investment in education, especially in conflict-affected societies. Investment in education has an&#13;
immediate positive effect on society in conflict, because a well-functioning school system provides&#13;
a sense o f normalcy and encourages the population to invest in the future. Iraq has strong human&#13;
capital base that will be key to the task o f restoring the education sector.&#13;
Education increasesproductivity, raises income, and reduces poverty: The Household Survey (HS)&#13;
in Iraq conducted in 2004 showed a strong correlation between income level and education&#13;
attainment. People with higher education in Iraq enjoy better economic conditions than people with&#13;
little or no education. The majority (78 percent) o f the households in the lowest income quintile&#13;
have no education or completed only primary school, whereas more than one-third (36 percent) o f&#13;
those who fall in the highest income category have secondary and higher education (Table la).&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Table la: Completed education of population (15 years+) by income in 2004&#13;
                             per capita household income quintiles, (%)&#13;
&#13;
              Education       Lowest       Low      Medium      High        Highest   Total&#13;
                Level         Income     Income      Income    Income       Income&#13;
&#13;
                    Higher           5         5           9          13         22       11&#13;
                 Secondary           6         7           9          11         14         9&#13;
              Intermediate          11        13           15         16         14        14&#13;
                  Primary           30        32           32         28         23       29&#13;
              No education          48        43           35         32         27       37&#13;
                     Total         100        100         100       100          100      100&#13;
&#13;
             Table lb: Per capita household income by education of household head in&#13;
                                              2004, (9%)&#13;
&#13;
              Education       Lowest       Low      Medium       High       Highest   Total&#13;
                Level         Income     Income      Income    Income       Income&#13;
                    Higher          13         14          19         25         29       100&#13;
                 Secondary          18         19          22         21         20       100&#13;
              Intermediate          21        22           22         17          18      100&#13;
                  Primary           26        25           20          17         12      100&#13;
              No education          27        24           20          17         13      100&#13;
                     Total  I       23        22           20          18         17      100 I&#13;
&#13;
The relationship between education and income i s illustrated clearly in Table lb. Among families&#13;
where the household head has completed higher education, 29 percent belong to the highest income&#13;
quintile with an additional 25 percent among the second highest income quintile. On the other hand,&#13;
in families where the household head never attended school, 13 percent belong to the highest&#13;
income quintile and 17 percent to the second highest quintile. This shows that, although entrance to&#13;
the labor market i s currently difficult in Iraq for the educated young people, economic return on&#13;
education i s highin the long run.&#13;
Investment in education has externalities and social bene$ts. Internationalresearch has consistently&#13;
shown that investment in primary and secondary education generates a wide range o f externality&#13;
benefits. It increases female labor force participation, reduces fertility, and improves the welfare o f&#13;
women. In addition, maternal and child health and nutrition outcomes and child, infant and&#13;
maternal mortality outcomes are strongly associated with female education attainment. An example&#13;
from the recent household survey in Iraq shows that child nutrition levels rise, in a statistically&#13;
significant way, as the education level o f the mother increases. Public investment in education,&#13;
especially basic and secondary education, has the potential to generate strong social benefits.&#13;
Education Sector Expenditure and Financing&#13;
Macro-economic framework and medium-term prospects: Despite the tremendous difficulties&#13;
currently facing Iraq, the medium-term economic outlook i s satisfactory as long as the expansion in&#13;
oil production continues and world oil prices remain at favorable levels. The fiscal condition should&#13;
be sustainable in the medium-term provided the government controls the growth o f recurrent&#13;
expenditures, and revenues, which depend on oil production and price, do not fall. The recent IMF&#13;
report (July 2005) shows that in 2004, GDP increased by nearly 50 percent, driven mainly by the&#13;
recovery o f the oil sector. After a continuous decline during the last decade, per capita income rose&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                        47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
in 2004 to US$940, still less than a quarter of what it had been two decades ago. Overall GDP&#13;
growth is expected to reach 17 percent in2006 and then decline gradually to 7 percent and continue&#13;
at that level up to 2010 according to the IMFprojections.&#13;
The post-conflict government budget: The public budget for 2005 released by the MOF is ID 36&#13;
trillion (US$24 billion). One fifth of the budget is investment expenditure and the rest is operational&#13;
expenditure. Total revenue i s about ID 29 trillion (US$19 billion) and 96 percent of the revenue&#13;
comes from oil exports. The deficit of ID 7 trillion (US$5 billion), i s expected to be financed from&#13;
carry-overs and assets abroad. The government budgetary process in the past two years has been to&#13;
give the three governorates inthe northern Kurdistan region a block grant according to the share of&#13;
the population in that region. The two governments in that region in turn allocate these funds to the&#13;
line ministries to cover their recurrent and investment expenditure.&#13;
The government budget (includingKurdistanregion) reflects post-conflict conditions where public&#13;
subsidies programs (card ration), SOE subsidies, and war damage compensation to Kuwait make up&#13;
60 percent of the total expenditure and 70 percent of the operational outlays. The share of salaries&#13;
(payroll, pension, and employee expenditure) that has doubled from 2004 was only 16 percent of&#13;
the total operational budget (without the subsidies programs, the share is 50 percent). Capital goods&#13;
acquisition (e.g., armored vehicles) and other security materials account for 10 percent of the&#13;
operational budget (figure 1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Figure 1: GovernmentBudget by Major Items of Expenditure&#13;
                                                 (ID36tr)&#13;
                                         Interlor  other&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Education share of the national budget: The substantial amount earmarked to subsidies and transfer&#13;
programs left small amounts for the line ministries. The shares of the Ministries of Oil and Defense&#13;
in the total government budget are 10 percent and 6 percent respectively. As for education, the&#13;
combined share of MOE and MHESR budgets i s 4.5 percent of the total budget. There is no&#13;
information on the expenditure of the two Ministries of Education in the Kurdistan region.&#13;
However, the Kurdistan region expenditure on education has a marginal impact on the share of the&#13;
education sector inthe total government budget. The proportion allocated to the education sector in&#13;
the public budget is by far the lowest when compared to other countries in the region where the&#13;
ratio is twice or three times the ratio in Iraq (figure 2). The recent government National&#13;
Development Strategy included economic reform policies such as privatization, restructuring SOEs,&#13;
and phasing out the subsidies program. If these policies were effectively implemented, more&#13;
resources would be freed up and the financial share of the line ministries, including education,&#13;
could be increased.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Figure 2: Percentage of Public Education Expenditure to Government Budget&#13;
                                                 (Most recent years)&#13;
&#13;
      30 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      25 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      20 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      15 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      10 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       5 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       0 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The post-conflict MOE budget: The government policy in the last two years was to keep the&#13;
education system functioning, and thus top priority was given to operational expenditure. The&#13;
government relied on international organizations, donors, and bilateral support to finance the&#13;
reconstruction efforts. The M O E budget for 2005 (ID1.3 trillion) consists almost entirely o f&#13;
operational expenditure (92 percent), and a substantial proportion o f the operational expenditure&#13;
goes to salaries (95 percent). Services (mostly related to security) and materials and fuels make up&#13;
the rest of the operational budget (table 2).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Table2: MOE budgetfor 2005&#13;
                                                         IDmil          %&#13;
                        Salaries                        1,103,048        94.45&#13;
                        Services                          28,553          2.44&#13;
                        Raw materials, fuel,              26,310          2.25&#13;
                        Assets maintenance                 3,109          0.27&#13;
                        Capital goods acquisition          6,560          0.56&#13;
                        Other                                250          0.02&#13;
                        Total operational               1,167,830         100&#13;
                        Investment                        100,000         7.89&#13;
                        Total Oper &amp; Invest             1,267,830&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Allocation for investment expenditure in the M O E budget i s a relatively small amount o f ID100&#13;
million (8 percent o f MOE budget). The project will have a significant fiscal impact when&#13;
compared to the current level of the MOE investment budget. A number of international agencies&#13;
have been involved in supporting education in Iraq since M a y 2003. Because o f the lack o f&#13;
coordination and speed o f implementation, the data on donor support to education i s fragmented&#13;
and scattered and not reflected in the government budget. The Ministry of Planning i s responsible&#13;
for coordinating these activities and there are plans to assess these programs and incorporate them&#13;
in the investment budget in the coming years. The UN and the World Bank have been providing&#13;
assistance largely through the two IRFFI trust funds. The U S i s a major bilateral donor and its&#13;
support has been provided through contracts granted to USAID financed from U S Supplemental&#13;
Budget for Iraq. The World Bank ITF-financed projects, with a value o f US$lOO million, have&#13;
focused on emergency textbook printing for 2004/5, school rehabilitation and construction, and&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                      49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
capacity buildingin the sector. The United Nations Development Group ITF-financed programs of&#13;
US$SO million include a wide range o f activities, such as school rehabilitation, supplies, equipment,&#13;
and capacity building. The UN also implements other programs financed by USAID and other&#13;
donors (Annex     lo). All   these programs represent a good start but are still very small when&#13;
compared to the sector needs (over US$4.8 billion) assessed by the UNWB Needs Assessment&#13;
Study (October 2003).&#13;
Projectimpactand support&#13;
Project support to budgetary and financial management: Iraq lacks proper financial management&#13;
mechanisms and adequate data reporting frameworks; it also lacks a fully functional statistical&#13;
framework. Education financial management has suffered from a wide range o f problems including&#13;
the poor security environment and difficulties in communication with the education authorities in&#13;
the governorates, as well as the non-transparent recording o f financial transactions that affected the&#13;
MOE's ability to allocate resources effectively or to track overall spending and outcomes. The&#13;
project will provide technical support to address urgent problems such as the fragmentation o f the&#13;
budget, inadequate reporting of expenditures financed both by the government budget and donors,&#13;
and weak accountability. Some basic institutional issues will need to be resolved regarding the role&#13;
o f various actors in addressing issues of budgeting and financial management.&#13;
Project support to policy reforms and system efficiency: There i s a growing recognitioninthe MOE&#13;
of the value of developing the human and institutional resources that will be required to&#13;
conceptualize, negotiate and implement financial system reform and policy options. The project&#13;
will support the ministry to manage the interim policy and strategy adjustments that will be&#13;
required to improve the efficiency o f the system and to lay the groundwork for more substantial&#13;
system development that will promote greater efficiency o f expenditure and provide policy&#13;
alternatives. Substantial savings that can be generated from improving the efficiency o f the&#13;
education system and streamlining the teaching force would free up resources for reconstruction&#13;
and upgrading o f the education system inIraq.&#13;
Cost-effectiveness of project's schools construction standards: The designs used for existing&#13;
schools reflect the norms and educational approaches o f the 1970s, at a time when school&#13;
laboratories were designed for teacher demonstration rather than pupil participation in experiments.&#13;
Classrooms are on average smaller (43 square meters) than international standards require because&#13;
they were constructed on the basis o f a relatively low student:classroom ratio o f 30:1, while the&#13;
current average i s 44: 1. The project will use cost-effective school designs with efficient utilization&#13;
o f space and the latest design standards. Schools to be supported by the project are designed with&#13;
sufficient administration space and efficient use o f circulation and wall space. In addition, the&#13;
project will introduce standardized materials schedules to encourage the use o f economically&#13;
available components throughout the country, use o f modular" design and an economical structural&#13;
span, provide appropriate orientation o f buildings to maximize benefits from the local environment&#13;
to reduce energy costs, and use appropriate local building materials and building technology to&#13;
increase durability and reduce maintenance costs.&#13;
&#13;
Project's impact on employment creation: The school construction under the project would be&#13;
implemented by local contractors in the governorates and would generate approximately 4 1,000&#13;
maddays inconsultant services and over 948,000 maddays of work inthe construction sector. The&#13;
conflict and the economic decline have destroyed a large number o f jobs in the formal and non-&#13;
formal sectors and resulted in an unemployment rate o f approximately 30 percent. At present the&#13;
demand for labor i s too low to absorb the continuous demographic increase and workers already&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
loModular design here refers to a design standard that permits different school modules (classroom blocks,&#13;
laboratories, administration blocks etc.) to be configured in different ways to accommodate the requirements&#13;
of the site.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                        50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     unemployed. The project will increase the demand for labor in the construction sector and, if the&#13;
     building materials are bought from local manufacturing firms, the increase will also extend to&#13;
     workers in these firms.&#13;
     Fiscal impact ofthe project: The project would have a significant impact on the capital expenditure&#13;
     o f MOE. The project could be implemented over three years (2006-2008) with an average o f ID 50&#13;
     billion a year. These allocations represent 42 percent of the annual investment expenditure of MOE.&#13;
     The relatively small allocation o f investment expenditure reflects the government policy of giving&#13;
     top priority to operational outlays to keep the education system functioning while depending&#13;
                                                              1                     1          1&#13;
     heavily on foreign donors in the reconstruction efforts. The project allocations represent about 3&#13;
     percent o f the total budget and have a marginal fiscal impact on the overall education budget (Table&#13;
     3).&#13;
&#13;
                              Table3: Fiscal Impact and Sustainability of the Project&#13;
                              I  2005      2006      200750      200820     2009      2010        2011      2012&#13;
Project investment (US$ mil)                     30&#13;
Project investment (ID mil)                 45,000    75,000      30,000&#13;
Schools O&amp;MMOEbudget         I&#13;
(IDmil) (4%)                                  1,800    4,800       6,000      6,000     6,000       6,000     6,000&#13;
&#13;
Operational                     1,167,830 1,338,963 1,414,784   1,486,533  1,555,454 1,621,752   1,688,679 1,757,848&#13;
&#13;
(of which non-salary exp)         58,392    66,184    69,932      13,479     76,886    80,163      83,471    86,890&#13;
&#13;
Investment                        100,000   113,812   120,257     126,355    132,214   137,849     143,538   149,417&#13;
&#13;
Total                          1,267,830  1,452,775 1,535,040  1,612,889  1,687,668  1,759,601  1,832,216  1,907,266&#13;
% of proj inv/ MOE budget                       3 1       4 9         1 9&#13;
% O&amp;M Exp/ MOE non-salar&#13;
exp                                             2 7       6 9         8 2        7 8       7 5         1 2       6 9&#13;
% of proj inv / MOE invest&#13;
budget                                         39 5     62 4         23 7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Sustainability of the project: The project covers primarily building o f new primary and secondary&#13;
     schools. School construction i s a one-time investment to address accumulated backlogs. The plan&#13;
     includes provision for financing equipment and furniture for all new schools. Given that the new&#13;
     schools will largely accommodate staff and students reassignedfrom existing overcrowded schools,&#13;
     the project will not significantly increase the recurrent costs in terms o f teacher salaries or&#13;
     management costs. School maintenance i s currently the responsibility o f the MOE, for which&#13;
     provision i s made in the annual budget. The capacity building component will include technical&#13;
     assistance for the development o f a national education school construction and maintenance&#13;
     program, to support the establishment o f a more effective and affordable approach to school&#13;
     maintenance.&#13;
     Maintenance o f buildings and equipment o f the project schools will be covered by the MOE&#13;
     recurrent budget. Future maintenance costs o f the project schools will be a very small share of the&#13;
     overall M O E operational budget and budget projections show that they do not constitute a&#13;
     sustainability problem. However, the sustainability o f maintenance costs of the total schools&#13;
     (14,000 schools) could become an issue during the short to medium term, as two-thirds of the&#13;
     public budget goes to transfers and subsidies and the share o f the line ministries i s quite small&#13;
     (MOE budget i s 3.5 percent in 2005). However, the expected increase in oil exports that make up&#13;
     two thirds of GDP, and the economic reform policies that are being introduced, such as&#13;
     privatization, restructuring SOEs, and phasing out subsidies program, are expected to stimulate&#13;
     sustainable growth over the mediumterm and provide resources for such types o f expenditure.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
..&#13;
U&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
dd&#13;
Bzz&#13;
c&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                          a&#13;
                          0&#13;
                           W&#13;
                           G&#13;
&amp; 9 &amp; 9 &amp; 9 6 9 b 9 b 3&#13;
-                          C&#13;
&#13;
                           v)&#13;
                           c&#13;
&#13;
                           d&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                           53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   ANNEX 10: DONORSUPPORTTOEDUCATIONINIRAQ&#13;
                                          (US$ThousandEquivalent)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Category                                USAID                UN          WorldBank&#13;
                                                                                                  (ITF&amp;IDA)&#13;
&#13;
Constructionof new schoolbuildings                         I          5,000  I                I          138,200&#13;
Rehabilitationof schoolsandtechnicalinstitutes&#13;
- including rehabilitation of water and sanitation                  113,600            49,575             10,000&#13;
facilities.&#13;
Textbooks - textbook editing, printing, distribution,&#13;
and procurement.                                                                       17,800             40,000&#13;
&#13;
Teachingand learningmaterials - education kits&#13;
and school bags for students, recreation kits, guides&#13;
for non-formal education instructors, reference&#13;
books to university libraries, handbooks for non-                    13,200            47,283&#13;
formal education learners, printed materials and&#13;
audio-visual materials for in-service teacher&#13;
training.&#13;
Furnitureandequipment- desks and chairs,&#13;
computers, equipment for computer labs and                           24,800            12,217              10,000&#13;
science labs.&#13;
Improvingeducationquality - teacher training,&#13;
study visit of non-formal education staff, literacy&#13;
campaigns, workshop on curriculum, visual aides                      11,300             6,976&#13;
for literacy classes, activities for early childhood,&#13;
support for examinations.&#13;
EducationGovernance and Finance- EMIS&#13;
(training, software development, computer&#13;
provision, school survey), training infinance,                        2,900             1,853               1,800&#13;
&#13;
budget and accounting.&#13;
TOTAL                                                      I        170,800  I        135,704 I          200,000&#13;
&#13;
NOTE:&#13;
These data were derived from the documents presentedby the MOE to the Education Sector Working Group&#13;
inSeptember 2005. They include the US$lOO million for this project (TEEP).The MOE acknowledges that&#13;
this list i s not complete, but it reflects the main inputs over the past two years. Funding sources for the UN&#13;
activities include USAID, Japanese Government, Korean Government and Qatar Fund.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                  54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ANNEX 11:TIMETABLE OF KEY PROJECTPROCESSINGEVENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sequence                                     Timing&#13;
Time taken to prepare andprocessthe project  4 months&#13;
Identificationandpreparation mission         July 2005&#13;
Appraisal                                    August 2005&#13;
Negotiations                                 October 2005&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                        55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  ANNEX 12: NAMESOF STAFF/CONSULTANTSWHO WORKED ON THE PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Name                     Function&#13;
Peter Buckland           Task Team Leader, Sr. Education Specialist, MNSHD&#13;
Mohamed Allak            Consultant Senior Economist, MNSHD&#13;
CCline Gavach            Operations Analyst, MNSHD&#13;
Vasilios Demetriou       Consultant Sr. Implementation Specialist, MNSHD&#13;
Majed El-Bayya           Sr. Procurement Specialist, MNAPR&#13;
Mona El-Chami            Financial Management Specialist, MNAFM&#13;
David Webber             Lead Finance Officer, L O A G l&#13;
Mitsue Uemura            Consultant Education Specialist, MNSHD&#13;
Vikram Raghavan          Counsel, LEGMS&#13;
Layla Qaissy             Project Assistant, MNSHD&#13;
Nazaneen Ali             Procurement Specialist, MNAPR&#13;
Stefanie Brackmann       Environmental Safeguards Specialist, MNSRE&#13;
Colin S Scott            Lead Social Safeguards Specialist, MNSRE&#13;
Emma Etori               Language ProgramAssistant, MNSHD&#13;
&#13;
Ad Hoc Advisory Committee:&#13;
&#13;
Name                     Function&#13;
Joseph Saba              Country Director, MNC02&#13;
Regina Bendokat          Sector Manager, MNSHD&#13;
Alfred Nickesen          Manager, OPCS Representative&#13;
Faris Hadad-Zervos       Sr. Operations Officer, MNCIQ&#13;
Kathryn Funk             Sr. Country Officer, MNC02&#13;
Jane Sansbury            Administrator, World Bank IraqTrust Fund, MNC02&#13;
Hiroko Imamura           Senior Counsel, LEGMS&#13;
David Webber             Lead Finance Officer, L O A G l&#13;
Sherif Arif              Regional Environmental and Safeguards Advisor, MNSRE&#13;
Aloysius Ordu            Regional Quality Advisor, MNAOS&#13;
Samia Msadek             Regional Financial Manager, MNAFM&#13;
Nadjib Sefta             Regional Procurement Manager, MNAPR&#13;
Keiko M i w a            Education Specialist, Peer Reviewer, ECSHD&#13;
RobinHorn                Lead Education Specialist, Peer Reviewer, ECSHD&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6401259">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/10/6401259/iraq-third-emergency-education-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/10/6401259/iraq-third-emergency-education-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/10/6401259/iraq-third-emergency-education-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2005-11-29T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/11/09/000012009_20051109094008/Rendered/INDEX/T76620rev.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/11/09/000012009_20051109094008/Rendered/PDF/T76620rev.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2005-11-09T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2005-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Gray cover</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309938</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Iraq - Third Emergency Education Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The main objective of the Third
            Emergency Education Project is to alleviate overcrowding in
            primary, and secondary schools through school construction,
            and provision of furniture and equipment. The project will
            also lay the groundwork for broader education reform, and
            system reconstruction. The project components are as
            follows: 1) School Construction - will finance the
            construction, and equipment and furniture provision in new
            schools; 2) Institutional Strengthening for System
            Development and Reform - will finance a comprehensive
            program to support education system development, and the
            design of a national school construction and maintenance
            program; and, 3) Project Management - will finance project
            implementation costs, including capacity building of the
            project management team in the Ministry of Education. In
            spite of the many project benefits, particularly that it
            will help improve the learning environment, major risks to
            the project are the unstable security and political
            environment, as well as the limited capacity of the
            government, and private sector. In the previous education
            projects in Iraq, capacity building provided by Bank staff
            during supervision missions, helped accelerate project
            preparation and implementation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Iraq - Third Emergency Education Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Iraq - Third Emergency Education Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2005/10/6401259/iraq-third-emergency-education-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>IQ-Iraq Third Emergency Education Project -- P096234</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Secondary Education,Teaching and Learning,Gender and Education,Primary Education,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Education,Gender</teratopic>
        <count>Iraq</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe, Middle East and North Africa!$!107234</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Middle East!$!80463</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000012009_20051109094008</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa</admreg>
        <subsc>Primary education,Secondary education</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Education,Gender</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Education</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            academic year, Accountability, achievements,
            basic education, basic learning, basic needs, basic
            services, capacity building, classroom, classroom ratio,
            CLASSROOMS, comprehensive program, computer laboratories,
            curriculum, curriculum development, curriculum reform,
            demonstration, disabled students, donor agencies, DONOR
            SUPPORT, Education Policy, education projects, education
            reform, Education Sector, education system, educational
            approaches, educational projects, employment, Enrolment
            Rate, enrolment rates, Financial Management, fundamental
            education, gender disparities, girls, Higher Education,
            Human Development, human resource development, institutional
            development, International Commitments, international
            standards, interventions, Islamic Development Bank, labor
            market, leadership, learning, learning materials,
            legislation, libraries, local authorities, natural
            resources, Needs Assessment, NER, operating costs,
            pedagogical approaches, policy reform, political
            environment, practical activities, primary classrooms,
            primary school, primary school-age children, primary
            schools, primary students, primary system, printing, pupils,
            rural areas, savings, school buildings, School Construction,
            school facilities, school furniture, school reform, school
            rehabilitation, school supplies, school system, schooling,
            schools, science laboratories, Scientific Research,
            secondary education, secondary level, secondary school,
            secondary schools, social safety nets, social services,
            sports, strategic planning, study tours, subsidiary,
            teacher, teacher management, teacher training, teachers,
            Technical Assistance, Textbook Provision, textbooks,
            training programs, transport, universal primary enrolment,
            universities, urban areas,
        </keywd>
        <owner>Human Development Group (MNSHD)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Emergency Recovery Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe, Middle East and North Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Middle East</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T7662</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Curriculum Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textbooks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Integrated Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pesticides</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Procurement Implementing Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Standard Bidding Documents</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Research and Surveys for Public Contracts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Higher Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education  Enhancing Access, Equity and Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Curriculum Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning Materials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Procurement Laws</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Iraq</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>