<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                 Document of&#13;
                                              The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
                                        FOROFFICIAL USEONLY&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   ReportNo: T7673    - AF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                      FORA PROPOSED GRANT OF&#13;
&#13;
                                             SDR 20.6 MILLION&#13;
&#13;
                                     (US$30 MILLIONEQUIVALENT)&#13;
&#13;
                                                      TO&#13;
&#13;
                             THE ISLAMIC REPUBLICOFAFGHANISTAN&#13;
&#13;
                                                    FORA&#13;
&#13;
         SUSTAINABLEDEVELOPMENTOF NATURAL RESOURCESPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 May 16,2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Oil, Gas and Mining PolicyDivision&#13;
Oil, Gas, Mining &amp; ChemicalsDepartment&#13;
Afghanistan, Bhutanand MaldivesCountry Unit&#13;
South Asia RegionalOffice&#13;
&#13;
   This document has a restricted distribution and may be used by recipients only inthe performance of&#13;
  their official duties. I t s contents may not otherwise be disclosed without the World Bank authorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                             CURRENCY EQUIVALENT&#13;
                                   (as o f April 2006)&#13;
                                 Currency Unit:Afghani&#13;
                                   US$l.OO =49.89&#13;
                           GOVERNMENT FISCAL YEAR&#13;
                                  March 21 - March 20&#13;
                        ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
ADB    AsianDevelopment Bank                M o F      Ministryo fFinance&#13;
AGS     Afghanistan Geological Survey       NEPA       National Environment Protection Agency&#13;
ANDS   AfghanistanNational                  PACB       Public Administration Capacity Building&#13;
        Development Strategy&#13;
ARDS   AfghanistanReconstruction and        PFEM       Public Finance and Expenditure&#13;
        Development Services                           Management&#13;
BGS     British Geological Survey           P F M      Public Financial Management&#13;
DA      Designated Account                  P M U      Program Management Unit&#13;
EITI    Extractive Industries               PRR        Priority Restructuring and Reform&#13;
        Transparency Initiative&#13;
FM      Financial management                PRSP       Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper&#13;
FMS     Financial management system         SDU        Special Disbursement Unit&#13;
IDA     International Development           SOEs       State-owned enterprises&#13;
        Association&#13;
I-ANDs  InterimAfghanistan National         TSS        Transition Support Strategy&#13;
        Development Strategy&#13;
I S N   Interim Strategy Note               USAID      US Agency for International Development&#13;
MDGs    MillenniumDevelopmentGoals          USGS       US Geological Survey&#13;
MEW     Ministryo fEnergyandWater           USTDA      U S Trade and Development Agency&#13;
MOM     Ministryo fMines&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Country Director:  Alastair McKechnie&#13;
                   Sector Director: Rashad Kaldany&#13;
                  Sector Manager:   Peter A. Van der Veen&#13;
                Country Manager:    Jean Mazurelle&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               AFGHANISTAN&#13;
              SUSTAINABLEDEVELOPMENT OF NATURAL RESOURCESPROJECT&#13;
                                            TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                           TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
SECTIONA-BACKGROUND AND STRATEG&#13;
SECTIONB-BANK RESPONSEAND STRAT                                                                                    ....................................... 6&#13;
SECTIONC-DETAILED PROJECTDESCRIPTION............................................&#13;
SECTIOND-STUDIES AND TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE................................................................&#13;
SECTIONE-INSTITUTIONAL          ARRANGEMENTSAND PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION.................................                                                    19&#13;
SECTIONF-FINANCIAL AND ECONOM                                                                                                                ..............22&#13;
SECTIONG-ACTION PLAN......................                                                 ........................................................... 25&#13;
APPENDIX 1: EXTRACTIVE INDUSTRY STATE-OWNEDENTERPRISES INTHE MINISTRY OF MINES.....28&#13;
APPENDIX 2: LETTER OF SECTOR DEVELOPMENT POLICY .......................................................&#13;
APPENDIX 3: MOM OVERALL DONOR ASSISTANCETO THE MINERAL SECTORINAFGH&#13;
APPENDIX 4: GOVERNANCE AND TRANSPARENCYINTHE NATURAL RESOURCESSECTOR.................39&#13;
APPENDIX 5: PROCUREMENTARRANGEMENTS.....................................                                                                    ...............41&#13;
APPENDIX 6: FINANCIAL MANAGEMENTANNEX OF SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT OF NATURAL&#13;
RESOURCESPROJECT                                           ..........................................................................................      41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                LIST OF TABLES&#13;
&#13;
Table C-1 Project ComponentCost (in US$million)..............................................................................&#13;
Table C-2: DetailedDescriptionof Project Components .........................................................................&#13;
Table F-1 MiningReform"Before" and "After": Resultsin SelectedCountries............................................&#13;
Table G-1 Afghanistan:SustainableDevelopment of NaturalResourcesProject Results Framework...........&#13;
Table G-2 Project Implementationand PerformanceIndicators.............................................................&#13;
Table A6-1 Allocation of Grant Proceeds.            ..........................................................................&#13;
&#13;
                                                LIST OF FIGURES&#13;
&#13;
Figure E-1 Conceptual Frameworkfor PersonnelandUnits underthe Project.............................................................. 20&#13;
Figure F-1 Surface Rents and Tax Receipts, Santa Cruz Province, Argentina, 1992-2000 ...........................................                           23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                     SECTION A-BACKGROUND AND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
Background: The MineralsSector&#13;
&#13;
1.        Mining and hydrocarbons development in Afghanistan is an engine o f economic&#13;
growth; and essential to reconstruction and development. Despite having abundant natural&#13;
resources, a vibrant minerals sector has eluded Afghanistan. Years o f neglect have stripped&#13;
the Ministry o f Mines (MOM)its institutional capacity to manage and the ministry is&#13;
struggling to meet new challenges. The barriers facing MOMhave been summarized in the&#13;
International Development Association (IDA) document Mining as a Source of Growth&#13;
(2004).' This study concludes that institutions responsible for mineral resources are not&#13;
appropriately organized, staffed and equipped to grow the sector. The ministry has several&#13;
state-owned enterprises, and this organizational structure does not reflect MOM'S    new role as&#13;
mineral sector regulator rather than owner and operator o f mining enterprises. Stimulating&#13;
new investment into the mining sector will, therefore, require a concerted effort towards&#13;
institutional strengthening and capacity building.&#13;
&#13;
2.        The study, Mining as a Source of Growth, estimated that the gross annual market&#13;
value o f solid minerals produced could increase from the estimated US$60 million currently&#13;
to US$253 million per annum by 2008 (four-five year time horizon). A longer term growth&#13;
scenario-ten to twelve years into future-could see the development o f very large iron ore&#13;
deposits, industrial scale coal mines for power generation, gas-to-power development, and&#13;
one or two gold mines and other industrial minerals production facilities. More recent&#13;
projections, based on the significantly higher commodity prices o f recent years, estimate that&#13;
total minerals production could reach US$ 600-800 million by 2015. Such growth scenarios&#13;
would imply significant economic benefits in terms o f value added, royalties and taxes to the&#13;
government, export earnings, new jobs, and substantial community development spin-offs.&#13;
Government revenues by 2015 could reach US$ 100-150 million. The Government&#13;
acknowledges that mining sector development cannot be spearheaded by public sector&#13;
investments but rather will require substantial new private sector investment. This, in turn,&#13;
requires that the Government establish conditions and an enabling environment to attract and&#13;
retain investment by private local and international companies. Also, the government must&#13;
ensure that public institutions are strengthened and that sufficient capacity within them exists&#13;
to administer the laws andregulations ina transparent manner.&#13;
&#13;
3.        The Afghanistan mineral sector is described according to five major commodity&#13;
groups (i)  hydrocarbons, (ii) fossil fuels (principally coal), (iii) and ferrous metals,&#13;
                               solid                                    base&#13;
(iv) construction materials (principally crushed stone and cement), and (v) dimensional stone&#13;
and gemstones. These industries were much more productive in the 1970s and 1980s than&#13;
they are today. Existing mineralproduction is now limited to small coal operations inBaghlan&#13;
and Bamyan provinces, limestone for two operating cement plants, construction materials&#13;
(sand, gravel, crushed rock) nationwide, and gemstones and dimensional stone from artisanal&#13;
operations. There has beenlimited production o f oil inSar-i-Pol but this has been shut in.&#13;
&#13;
4.        Today, all hydrocarbon activities and large-scale mining are controlled by the&#13;
 government, whereas smaller-scale mining o f construction is unregulated and occurs within&#13;
the informal sector. Overall, the conditions o f hydrocarbon and large-scale coal mining&#13;
 activities are not conducive to private sector participation, although, as essential materials,&#13;
their production must be sustained. Current production falls far short o f the sector's potential,&#13;
 and although still operating, all existing operations suffer from chronic neglect, damage from&#13;
war, and severe under-funding. The resource base could support substantially larger&#13;
 operations and there are identified deposits that have not been exploited; most notably Aynak&#13;
 copper and Hajigak iron ore deposits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 'TransitionalIslamicState of Afghanistan: Miningas a Source of Growth, ReportNo. 28231-AF,&#13;
 March2004, The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
                                                 1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Background:The Ministryof Mines&#13;
&#13;
5.      Historically, the Ministry o f Mines and Industries2 , now renamed the Ministry o f&#13;
Mines, has operated as a vertically integrated extractive industry conglomerate with&#13;
enterprises reporting to the center, but operating autonomously in terms o f budget planning&#13;
and revenues management. In January 2005, the Government was reorganized, and MoM's&#13;
portfolio was expanded to include light industry.For the past several decades MOMhas been&#13;
centered on extractive industries and associated heavy industries: (a) mining o f minerals and&#13;
construction materials, (b) petroleum exploration and production, and (c) the operation o f&#13;
downstream industries that utilize extractive industry outputs. With the addition o f the light&#13;
industries wing in early 2005, MOMadded a cluster o f 10 textile-based enterprises. The&#13;
ministry was restructured in March 2006, and light industries were transferred out o f what&#13;
was at the time Ministry o f Mines and Industries.After the last restructuring, approximately&#13;
4,000 employees work for MOMand its various state-owned enterprises.&#13;
&#13;
6.      As a regulatory agency, MOMwill need to provide a transparent and efficient&#13;
regulatory environment that enables private-sector led investment and facilitates sustained&#13;
economic growth and revenues to the government. Key actions required o f MOMin achieving&#13;
this objective will target:&#13;
&#13;
             improved fiscal and regulatory regimes through new policies, laws and tax&#13;
             provisions based on international best practices;&#13;
             building new institutions of government to effectively regulate and enforce the&#13;
             hydrocarbon and mininglaws&#13;
         0   building technical capacity in the administration and regulation o f hydrocarbon&#13;
             andmininglaws and ensure institutional efficiencies;&#13;
             assisting other ministries in infrastructure and land-use decision making by&#13;
             providingmore complete assessments o f mineral resource potential;&#13;
             undertaking sector promotion for sustained long-term growth based on private&#13;
             sector investment&#13;
             moving existing enterprises to market- and private-finance based principles-&#13;
             MOMwill leadthis transition from government-owned and controlled to private-&#13;
             sector run inmining, hydrocarbons, and associated industry.&#13;
&#13;
7.       During project preparation, a preliminary evaluation o f MoM's functions and&#13;
structure was conducted. This evaluation identified major structural issues that were not being&#13;
resolved by other government reform initiatives, such as the Priority Restructuring and&#13;
Reform (PRR) process, on which MOMmade very little headway. The evaluation concluded&#13;
that MOMis currently structured as a Soviet-styled production ministry-a             mass o f semi-&#13;
commercial activities and mixed semi-regulatory activities. There is no clear distinction&#13;
between the role o f regulator and business operator with the inevitable result that the MOM&#13;
has conflicting objectives and compromised outcomes, particularly in terms o f the trade-offs&#13;
between social and environmental sustainability and commercial objectives.&#13;
&#13;
8.       Makingthe transition o f MOMfrom owedoperator o f enterprises into the regulatory&#13;
role will require several key actions, some o f which have already been taken or are underway.&#13;
Other actions will be supported by the proposedproject.&#13;
&#13;
             Creating a Modern Legal and Regulatory Framework. The MOMhas worked&#13;
             with other key ministries to draft andpass Minerals (July 2005) and Hydrocarbon&#13;
             (December 2005) Laws. Both laws reflect international standards o f quality,&#13;
             apply to all investors local and foreign, and provide the basis for transparent&#13;
             allocation o f mineral and hydrocarbon rights to private entities. The project will&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  The Ministryof Mines and Industrieswas renamedinApril 2006 the Ministry o f Mines. This name&#13;
maybe subjectto further change as some heavy mineral-related industries (i.e. cement) may remain&#13;
within MOM.&#13;
&#13;
                                                2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
           support engaging legal experts to help the government draft mining regulations&#13;
           and a model investment contract. A model contract for exploration and&#13;
           production sharinghas been drafted, which could form a basis for negotiation of&#13;
           new production.&#13;
           Improving sector governance and transparency. The government is adopting a&#13;
           number o f initiatives to enhance governance and transparency in the mining&#13;
           sector. These initiatives, supported by the project, are aimed at ensuring that the&#13;
           miningtitles andcontracts are issuedina competitive and transparent mannerand&#13;
           that the fundamental terms and conditions o f the deal is "fair" by comparison to&#13;
           international best practices.&#13;
           Adopting an Internationally Competitive Fiscal and Mining Taxation Package.&#13;
           The 2005 Amendment to the Income Tax has specific provisions for extractive&#13;
           industry investors. It also authorizes the Minister o f Finance to income tax&#13;
           stability subject to certain conditions.&#13;
           Building Capacity and Strengthening Supervisory Institutions. A key issue, given&#13;
           the existing staff profiles and functional responsibilities in MOM,is to build&#13;
           capacity and competencies required for the new role o f regulator and&#13;
           administrator o f the sector. This involves not only the creation o f new units and&#13;
           departments within MOMsuch as a cadastre office and a unit for mines&#13;
           inspection, among others, but also augmenting the technical capacities o f MOM&#13;
           staff. Because o f the political turbulence o f the past years little training has taken&#13;
           place for MOMstaff and exposure to international best practices is extremely&#13;
           limited. As well, the ministryhas not attracted new staff so the staff age profile is&#13;
           advanced. Finally, staff are used to the owner/operator role and have little&#13;
           understanding o f regulatory functions. Thus, a major effort is required to build&#13;
           capacity in all key functions within MOM.&#13;
           Enhancing the Capacity of            Government Institutions        to Attract Sector&#13;
           Participation in the Development ThereoJ The government needs a program o f&#13;
           investment promotion which involves,             amongst others, public outreach,&#13;
           establishing an investor-friendly climate, and negotiating contracts quickly and&#13;
           expeditiously ina transparent manner.&#13;
           Improving Knowledge of          Afghan    Geoscience.      Increasing geo-scientific&#13;
           knowledge in key areas through systematic data collection, compilation, and&#13;
           maintenance o f a well-organized data base can help attract new investment and&#13;
           help develop the sector.&#13;
&#13;
        0  Inventoly and Strategic Planfor Minerals-Based State-Owned Enterprises. The&#13;
           principal state-owned enterprises        (SOEs)     and departments        carrying out&#13;
           commercial activities have been identified and described as part o f ongoing work&#13;
           in the SOE Department o f the Ministry o f Finance (MoF). The enterprises and&#13;
           departments include the Mines Extraction Company, North Coal Enterprise, State&#13;
           Gas Enterprise, Jabal Seraj and Ghori Cement Enterprises, Kud Bergh Fertilizer&#13;
           and Power Enterprise, Hydrology Engineering Research Service Enterprise,&#13;
           Afghan Geological Survey, Department o f Oil and Gas, and the Oil and Gas&#13;
           Exploration Department. There are also two non-operating enterprises: Technical&#13;
           Services Enterprise and Rukhaman Marble Enterprise. Important or large&#13;
           enterprises and departments within MOMare described inAppendix 1&#13;
&#13;
Sector Strategy&#13;
&#13;
9.      Previously, the former Ministry o f Mines and Industries produced two key&#13;
documents, (1) "The Strategy for the Mineral Resources Sector, Afghanistan," (April 2005)&#13;
and (2) a Letter o f Sector Development Policy (February 2006). This letter o f sector&#13;
development policy is appended to this technical annex. Both documents define the guiding&#13;
principles and commitments o f the ministry to good sector governance. MOMis fhrther&#13;
&#13;
                                                3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
guided by the "Afghanistan Investment Climate Assessment Rep~rt"~-in that good&#13;
governance via a sound legal framework, judicial and regulatory enforcement, and&#13;
hnctioning government has been cited as essential to attract private investment into&#13;
Afghanistan. Overall, MOMstates the current state o f the industry is not indicative o f the&#13;
underlying mineral wealth, and properly governed, the minerals sector should be a source o f&#13;
economic growth and a key instrument in fighting poverty. Thus, MOMis challenged to&#13;
facilitate positive economic impacts by creating good governance through institutional&#13;
strengthening and capacity building, and establishing conditions and an enabling environment&#13;
to attract and retain private investments.&#13;
&#13;
10.      Mineral sector strategy has been developed inresponse to higher-level considerations&#13;
relating to long term growth. On January 22,2006, the cabinet formally approved the Interim&#13;
Afghanistan National Development Strategy (I-ANDs).This five-year strategy follows the&#13;
National Development Framework prepared in 2002 and the Securing Afghanistan Future&#13;
(SAF) exercise prepared in 2004, and aims to transform the economy to enable the private&#13;
sector to be the engine o f growth and empower the poor to participate hlly in that growth. I-&#13;
ANDs is a five-year strategic plan consisting o f three pillars+l)  security, (2) governance,&#13;
rule o f law, and human rights, and (3) economic and social development. These pillars are&#13;
indispensable to realizing the Government's vision o f consolidating peace and stability&#13;
through just, democratic processes and institutions, reducing poverty, and achieving&#13;
prosperity through broad-based and equitable economic growth. The three pillars are built&#13;
into sectoral programs, and an appropriate emphasis is placed on enhancing infrastructure and&#13;
development o f natural resources. I-ANDs sets high-level goals and underpins the basis for&#13;
the Afghanistan Compact, a commitment made by the Government o f Afghanistan and the&#13;
international community during a conference in London on January 31, 2006. The&#13;
Afghanistan Compact is a five-year blueprint for reconstruction based upon detailed&#13;
outcomes, benchmarks, and timelines for delivery in security, governance and human rights,&#13;
and social and economic development. For mining and natural resources, the Compact's&#13;
benchmarks are (1) creation o f an enabling regulatory environment for profitable extraction o f&#13;
mineral and natural resources by end-2006, and (2) improved investment environment and&#13;
infrastructure to attract domestic and foreign direct investment to mining and natural&#13;
resources by end-2010.&#13;
&#13;
11.       The goal o f the Natural Resources and Mining component within I-ANDs i s to ". ..&#13;
establish Afghanistan as a globally competitive and attractive destination for investment in&#13;
industries, mineral and hydrocarbon exploration, development and mining in a manner that&#13;
protects these resources and their benefits for hture Afghan generations."4        Measurable&#13;
Benchmarks include (a) creating an enabling regulatory environment by end-2006, (b)&#13;
enhancing the investment and infrastructural environment in order to attract domestic and&#13;
foreign direct investment in mining and natural resources, and (c) increasing government&#13;
revenue through minerals production. The I-ANDs further states that MOMwill lead on the&#13;
development and protection o f Afghanistan's mineral, oil and gas reserves, and will establish&#13;
the necessary regulatory environment for attracting private investment, negotiation o f&#13;
contracts, and ensuring that resources are extracted in a sustainable way that maximizes&#13;
revenues and protects the environment.           MOM will coordinate with the National&#13;
Environmental Protection Agency (NEPA) to ensure that development o f mineral resources is&#13;
conducted in accordance with sound environmental practices.&#13;
&#13;
 12.      To date, donor coordinationhas been ad hoc inthat the former Ministry o f Mines and&#13;
Industries lacked the capacity in the earliest years (2002-2004) to defme long-term sector&#13;
strategies and guiding policies. Without a minister for much o f this period, management o f&#13;
the day-to-day operations o f MOMbecame fragmented. Furthermore, without a Program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 The InvestmentClimatein Afghanistan:Exploiting Opportunitiesin an UncertainEnvironment,The&#13;
World Bank, December 2005.&#13;
  Interim AfghanNational Development Strategy (I-ANDs), VolumeI1- ConsolidatedProgram&#13;
Summaries, 2.1.5 NaturalResourcesAnd MiningProgram, PolicyOverview.&#13;
&#13;
                                               4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Management Unit (PMU) or other central coordinating unit, donors were without a common&#13;
framework in which they could respond to the many needs o f the sector (see Section E:&#13;
Institutional Arrangements). Despite these handicaps, senior managers at MOMmanaged to&#13;
attract and support an overall suite of interventions that addressed many key issues. Donors&#13;
active in the sector include the Department for International Development (DfID)-British&#13;
Geological Survey (BGS), Asian Development Bank (ADB),U S Geological Survey (USGS),&#13;
and U S Trade and Development Agency (TDA). An accounting o f donor activities within the&#13;
sector are presented inAppendix 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                     SECTION B-IDA RESPONSEAND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
1.       The World Bank's Board o f Executive Directors approved a Transitional Strategy&#13;
Support (TSS) for Afghanistan inMarch 2003 and an Interim Strategy Note (ISN) on May 25,&#13;
2006. The ISN is anticipated to guide IDA'Sengagement over a two-year period. By 2008, the&#13;
government plans to have developed its full Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper (PRSP),&#13;
paving the way for preparation o f a Country Assistance Strategy. The pillars o f the I S N are:&#13;
         0    Building the capacity o f the state and its accountability to its citizens to ensure&#13;
              the provision o f services that are affordable, accessible and o f adequate quality&#13;
         0    Promoting growth of the rural economy and improvingrural livelihoods&#13;
         0     Supporting growth o f a formal, modem, and competitive private sector.&#13;
&#13;
2.       The ISN identifies public administration and corruption as two key areas emerging as&#13;
challenges. It specifically mentions that good governance is essential to avoid the&#13;
misallocation o f national resources that could lead to increased poverty, corruption, and&#13;
renewed conflict, the so-called paradox o f plenty. Afghanistan has an opportunity to put in&#13;
place systems to reap the benefits o f its natural resources for the nation as a whole. However,&#13;
the I S N points to the need for a concerted approach to prevent corruption by strengthening&#13;
institutions and implementing competitive, transparent processes that encourage quality&#13;
investors who can sustain sector growth before the country can reap the benefits o f its mineral&#13;
resources. The proposed Sustainable Development o f Natural Resources Project will support&#13;
activities that are designed to improve the governance o f the minerals sector, enable sector&#13;
growth through private sector participation, and help the Ministry o f Mines (MOM)separate&#13;
the policy and regulatory roles from operational and commercial functions.&#13;
&#13;
InternationalDevelopmentAssociation(IDA) Activities&#13;
&#13;
3.       The IDA has been working with MOMsince 2002. The activities undertaken with&#13;
participation o f the IDA include:&#13;
&#13;
          0    Technical assistance inthe minerals sector for policy development and reforms&#13;
          0    Assistance for preparing sector legislation, sector-specific tax amendments, and&#13;
               a model contract for hydrocarbons&#13;
          0    Compilation and analysis o f existing geoscience data&#13;
          0    Assessment o f the sector potential and institutional shortcomings with a view to&#13;
               making recommendations for hture actions for sector growth&#13;
          0    Assistance for developing an integrated energy strategy.&#13;
&#13;
4.        A large volume o f data on hydrocarbons has been compiled and analyzed by&#13;
Gustavson Associates under the IDA'SEmergency Infrastructure Reconstruction Project. The&#13;
data were used to produce a high-confidence, short-term gas production forecast as well as&#13;
assess long-term hydrocarbon development andproduction potential. For solid minerals, IDA&#13;
gathered and analyzed available data, and the findings are summarized in"Mining as a Source&#13;
o f Growth" (2004).&#13;
&#13;
 5.       IDA conducted two large studies to assess the sector potential and institutional&#13;
 shortcomings to achieve the potential, one inminingand the other inhydrocarbons. Mining as&#13;
a Source of Growth estimated the current and future production o f different minerals, their&#13;
values, and their potential contribution to economic development; identified obstacles to&#13;
 sector growth and attracting private capital; suggested a strategic path for sector growth;&#13;
 described the needed reforms to the legal, fiscal, and institutional regimes; andrecommended&#13;
 specific action steps for the next two years. "Evaluation o f Investment Options for the&#13;
 Development o f Oil and Gas Infrastructure in Afghanistan" (2005)-funded         by the US Trade&#13;
 and Development Agency (USTDA) and managed by IDA -examined immediate, medium-&#13;
 term, and long-term oil and gas potential; conducted a study on demand for natural gas in&#13;
 Kabul; evaluated alternative strategies for the (existing) fertilizer plant, (existing) gas&#13;
 processing plants, a small refinery, and a pipeline from Sherbergan to Kabul; conducted an&#13;
&#13;
                                                  6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
institutional review o f MOMcoupled with some training activities, and recommended an&#13;
investment program. For natural gas, low prices and a lack o f history o f prompt payment by&#13;
consumers were identified as serious obstacles to gas market development. The IDA held a&#13;
workshop on gas pricing principles with MOMand other interested ministries inJuly 2005.&#13;
&#13;
6.       Recognizing that appropriate sector and tax laws need to be in place before any&#13;
investment can be contemplated, the IDA assisted MOMin drafting mining and upstream&#13;
hydrocarbons laws, and worked closely with M o F and MOMindrafting special tax provisions&#13;
for extractive industries. The Cabinet approved the Minerals Law o f Afghanistan in July&#13;
2005, and the Hydrocarbons Law in December 2005. The Income Tax Law o f 2005 has a&#13;
chapter spelling out taxation rules for qualifying extractive industrytaxpayers. The provisions&#13;
include ring-fencing rules, accelerated depreciation, treatment o f pre-production expenses and&#13;
the business receipt tax, recognition o f deduction for contributions to a fund for&#13;
environmental and social obligations, and loss carry-forward and tax stability agreements.&#13;
IDA also helped examine different fiscal options for hydrocarbons and helped draft a model&#13;
production sharingagreement. Workshops were held to explain to MOMstaff key elements o f&#13;
internationally acceptable laws, regulations, contracts, and tax regimes.&#13;
&#13;
 7.       The sub-sector studies and assessments are useful and necessary, but they do not&#13;
 capture the inter-related nature o f energy sector developmental issues and, consequently, the&#13;
 trade-offs that may be entailed in the strategic decision-making process. In response to the&#13;
 government's request to assist inelaborating a strategy for the development o f the country's&#13;
 energy sector with particular reference to priority policy reforms and associated investments&#13;
 over the short to medium term, IDA also prepared and presented an energy strategy note in&#13;
 February 2005, pullingtogether policy issues for electricity, hydrocarbons, and coal.&#13;
&#13;
 Coordinationwith Other Donor Activities&#13;
&#13;
 13.      The Asian Development Bank (ADB), the British Geological Survey (BGS), and&#13;
 various agencies within the U.S. government-USTDA,               US Agency for International&#13;
 Development (USAID), and U S Geological Survey (USGS)-are              playing a major role in&#13;
 assisting MOMin the minerals sector. IDA has worked closely with BGS which has carried&#13;
 out mineral data compilation, assessments, and digitization; institutional strengthening o f the&#13;
 Afghanistan Geological Survey (AGS); and investment promotion. BGS activities are funded&#13;
 until 2007. The components of this proposed project were discussed in detail with BGS to&#13;
 ensure that the activities o f the two institutions complement one another and ensure long-term&#13;
 sustainability.&#13;
&#13;
  14.      ADB is focused primarilyon natural gas. It has several technical assistance programs&#13;
  for capacity building and regulatory reform in the gas sector. Under its Emergency&#13;
 Infrastructure Rehabilitation and Reconstruction Project, it will be rehabilitating a natural gas&#13;
 pipeline and several producing wells. ADB is preparing a stand-alone natural gas project in&#13;
  the amount of about US$50millionto go to its Board in2007, with a planned US$100 million&#13;
 private sector guarantee to further support rehabilitation o f gas-producing wells and pipelines.&#13;
  To complement the activities o f ADB, the proposed project will focus primarily on solid&#13;
  minerals, with support for policy issues in the oil sector. The P M U under this project is&#13;
  envisaged to be for the entire ministry.&#13;
&#13;
  15.      Inaddition to funding"Evaluation of InvestmentOptions for the Development o f Oil&#13;
  and Gas Infrastructure inAfghanistan," USTDA i s currently assisting MOMin conducting a&#13;
  cement industry study. It has recently completed analysis o f existing data for oil and gas&#13;
  prospects in the north. In the south, USGS is carrying out an airborne geophysical survey&#13;
  using funds provided by the Government o f Afghanistan. USAID recently completed a&#13;
  feasibility study for a power plant usingnatural gas, and is working with ADB and MOMto&#13;
  clarify the logistics and fundingsources for producing gas for the power plant.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16.      This proposed project complements other donors' activities by focusing on overall&#13;
regulatory and policy-making functions o f MOM,helping MOMto separate its commercial&#13;
activities from its regulatory and policy role, and strengthening the institutional framework&#13;
for mineral sector development through establishing and putting into operation a number o f&#13;
units needed to regulate mineral production.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                  SECTION C-DETAILED PROJECTDESCRIPTION&#13;
&#13;
1.      The objective o f this project i s to assist the MOMin improving its capacity to&#13;
effectively regulate Afghanistan's mineral and hydrocarbon resources sector in a transparent&#13;
manner and foster private sector development. It is designed to support MOMin developing&#13;
and implementing a plan for MOM'S      transition from being a producer o f minerals and other&#13;
commodities to a policy-maker and regulator. Among the benefits to Afghanistan o f&#13;
development o f its mineral resources will be tax revenues, employment, rural development,&#13;
and economic spin-offs. The project will help&#13;
&#13;
      (1)   Improve internal efficiencies o f ministry departments by strengthening capacity&#13;
            and streamlining processes within the Administration Department&#13;
      (2)   Develop regulatory capacity by establishing and putting into operation three new&#13;
            departments-Inspectorate,    Cadastre, and Environmental and Social Protection&#13;
      (3)   Develop mineral resources by supporting the activities o f the Sector Policy Unit&#13;
            and the following three departments-Afghanistan         Geological Survey, Mines and&#13;
            Hydrocarbons, and Industrial Enterprises.&#13;
      (4)   Enhancing sector governance through upfront technical assistance: establishment&#13;
            o f an International Advisory Council and the endorsement and implementation o f&#13;
            the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative (EITI)&#13;
&#13;
2.       According to OP8.50 (Emergency Recovery Assistance) under which this grant falls,&#13;
emergency recovery projects are normally fully implemented intwo to three years. Given the&#13;
extremely thin institutional capacity at MOM,however, it is proposed that this project be&#13;
implemented over five years.&#13;
&#13;
3.       The project will establish a Program Management Unit (PMU) to supervise day-to-&#13;
day implementation o f the project and coordinate with other donor projects. The P M U will&#13;
also have procurement and financial management specialists and an advisor for EITI and the&#13;
International Advisory Council. The project components and their corresponding costs are&#13;
summarized in Table C-1    .&#13;
&#13;
I------&#13;
Table C-I Project Component Cost (in US$ million)&#13;
&#13;
i     Component                                          Activities                                   US$&#13;
&#13;
  Program                Coordination of the externalbudget, assist coordinationofthe internalbudget&#13;
  Management Unit        project procurement, and accounting                                         3,400,000&#13;
&#13;
Component 1:&#13;
  ImprovingInternal      Strengthen the AdministrationDepartment                                     1,300,000&#13;
  Efficiencies&#13;
Component 2:             Render operational a Miningand HydrocarbonsTitle Registry and Cadastre&#13;
  Developing             Department&#13;
  Regulatorycapacity     Render operational a Miningand HydrocarbonsInspectorateDepartment           9,000,000&#13;
&#13;
                         Render operational a Social and EnvironmentalProtectionDepartment&#13;
&#13;
Component3:              Formulatesector policy andprepare andpromulgate legislation,guidelines,&#13;
  DevelopingMineral      and standards specific to mining andhydrocarbons&#13;
  Resources              Strengthen geologicalknowledgethroughdata collection,geologic mapping,&#13;
                         andmineraldistrict studies                                                  10,000,000&#13;
&#13;
                         Raise investmentawareness and promotethe sector&#13;
                         Conduct assessment of SOEs and design sub-sectorstrategies&#13;
&#13;
Component 4:             Improvetransparency, competition,and fairnessthroughthird-partyopinions&#13;
  EnhancingSector        on transactionsprovidedby an InternationalAdvisory Council                   1,350,000&#13;
  Governance             Full publicationand verification of companypaymentsandgovernment&#13;
&#13;
                                                  9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       Component                                          Activities                                   US$&#13;
                           revenuesin extractiveindustriesby implementingthe EITI&#13;
&#13;
Other                      Workshops, training, vehicles, works, equipment, furniture                 4,500,000&#13;
&#13;
                           Incrementaloperatingcosts-vehiclesand equipment                              450,000&#13;
&#13;
Total                                                                                                 30,000,000&#13;
&#13;
Component 1:ImprovingInternalEfficiencies&#13;
&#13;
4.        Activities inthis component will strengthen capacity and streamline processes within&#13;
the Administration Department o f MOM covering: budget and planning, financial&#13;
management, human resources, information technology, and asset management. The project&#13;
will assist MOMin having an operating information technology and financial management&#13;
system.&#13;
&#13;
5.        Financial management, including budgeting, is a weakness o f MOMat present, which&#13;
i s true for most o f the other ministries. This project will define a strategy for development o f a&#13;
Finance and Accounts Unitincluding staffing, budget, and skills requirements; define systems&#13;
for performing accounting, financial management and internal audit functions; and provide&#13;
technical support to the budgetary process.&#13;
&#13;
Component 2: DevelopingRegulatory Capacity&#13;
&#13;
6.        This component will develop MOM'S        regulatory capacity and put into operation three&#13;
new essential departments: (1) Mining and Hydrocarbons Inspectorate, which will house a&#13;
Small-scale Mining and Extension Services Unit, (2) Mining and Hydrocarbons Title&#13;
Registry and Cadastre, and (3) Environmental and Social Protection Department, under which&#13;
falls a Liaison Unit,linking MOMto the National Environmental ProtectionAgency (NEPA).&#13;
&#13;
7.        A Mining Licensing Board will review the activities of the three departments with&#13;
respect to the rights o f investors to operate inthe sector. The Board will consist o f three MOM&#13;
department heads and two external advisors. It will check conformity o f award, renewal,&#13;
cancellation or termination, and surrender o f licenses, titles, and contracts with applicable&#13;
procedures and make recommendations to the Minister accordingly. For all applications for&#13;
mining titles and hydrocarbon contracts, the Board will check the financial and technical&#13;
competencies o f the applicant and the compliance o f the proposed work program to&#13;
established guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
8.        The project will prepare operational guidelines and operationalize a Mining and&#13;
Hydrocarbons Inspectorate. The Mining and Hydrocarbons Inspectorate will begin the&#13;
process o f formalizing the many operating mines currently not licensed and not paying&#13;
royalties; inspect extractive industry operations to monitor compliance with occupational&#13;
health, safety, and work-procedural regulations as well as terms o f contracts where applicable;&#13;
and enforce other sector-specific laws and regulations. The Inspectorate will also supervise&#13;
compilation and publication o f statistics and information about the production and sale o f&#13;
minerals and hydrocarbons. The Small-scale Mining and Extension Services Unit under the&#13;
Inspectorate will provide technical support and guidance to small-scale miners and assist in&#13;
the formalization o f the many operations currently not paying royalties.&#13;
&#13;
9.        Mining and Hydrocarbons Title Registry and Cadastre will house a Licensing Unit&#13;
and a Production and Royalty Audit Unit. The Licensing Unit will process and register&#13;
various applications from investors and license holders; issue mineral rights in the form o f&#13;
licenses, authorizations, and contracts; ensure compliance therewith; and maintain a register&#13;
o f industry activity. The Production and Royalty Audit Unit will verify annual mineral and&#13;
hydrocarbonproduction; assess royalties based on the quantities and qualities o f the minerals&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
and hydrocarbons produced in accordance with the minerals and hydrocarbons legislation;&#13;
and ensure payment thereof to the central Treasury. Given the lack o f capacity and experience&#13;
with these modem cadastre and inspection functions, the project will deploy significant&#13;
technical assistance to these units throughout the duration o f the project.&#13;
&#13;
10.      One o f the principal aims o f the project is to create appropriate environmental and&#13;
social management units within MOM,as required by the Minerals and Hydrocarbons Laws,&#13;
and to train ministry staff to monitor and supervise the environmental performance o f the&#13;
sector.   The    Environmental    and Social     Protection    Department    will develop   an&#13;
environmental/social policy framework for future sector development; establish and assist&#13;
NEPA in enforcing sector-specific environmental guidelines and procedures; monitor&#13;
compliance therewith by private companies; and evaluate, jointly with NEPA, environmental&#13;
impact assessments, environmental management plans, and abandonment plans as may be&#13;
required under the legislation. A key function o f this department is liaison with NEPA on&#13;
broader oversight o f environmental issues across sectors. Throughout the technical assistance&#13;
process particular emphasis will be given to training and the development o f internal capacity&#13;
within MOMto carry out these tasks independently.&#13;
&#13;
Component3: DevelopingMineral Resources&#13;
&#13;
 11.      Promoting the development o f mineral resources is the largest component in the&#13;
project. This component will support activities in the Sector Policy Unit and in the&#13;
Afghanistan Geological Survey, Mines and Hydrocarbons Department, and Industrial&#13;
Enterprises Department.&#13;
&#13;
 12.      The Sector Policy Unit will formulate extractive industries policy and undertake&#13;
market analysis by way o f analyzing supply and demand. It will also prepare sector laws,&#13;
regulations, and guidelines with input from other departments andunits.&#13;
&#13;
 13.      The Afghan Geological Survey will receive technical support for mapping o f&#13;
 prospective mineral regions and mineral resource assessments to encourage new private&#13;
 sector exploration investment. The project will also support the development o f a geographic&#13;
 information system for internet-based distribution o f information and a public information&#13;
 center. This builds upon the work carried out by the British Geological Survey (BGS) and&#13;
 U.S. Geological Survey in building capacity within the department. AFG will house a&#13;
 Business Development Unit to design short-term resource development strategies and serve as&#13;
 the interface to the private sector on basic information, MOMactivities as defined by sector&#13;
 laws and regulations, and tender o f resource properties. The Business Development Unitwill&#13;
 promote investment by participating in industry trade shows and conferences and preparing&#13;
 promotional materials.&#13;
&#13;
 14.      The Department o f Mines and Hydrocarbons Development and the Department o f&#13;
 Industrial Enterprises will be assessed in terms o f assets, operations, financial positions,&#13;
 future business prospects, and human resources. Based on the initial assessment, sub-sector&#13;
 strategies for the state-owned enterprises (SOEs) operating under these departments will be&#13;
 developed.&#13;
&#13;
 Component4: EnhancingSector Governance&#13;
&#13;
  15.     The government, through the project, will devise and implement a number o f&#13;
 measures to ensure competition, transparency, and adherence to international best practices in&#13;
 respect o f authorizing new investments in the sector. The approach to governance in this&#13;
 project is described in greater detail in Appendix 4. Within MOM,the project will provide&#13;
  significant advisory technical assistance, create the Mining Licensing Board, and confer&#13;
  operations o f the mining cadastre to a qualified private firm. Associated policy work will&#13;
  focus on management o f revenues and sharing o f benefits. In addition, the project will help&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
establish and support an International Advisory Council and promote the implementation o f&#13;
the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative (EITI).&#13;
&#13;
16.      The International Advisory Council will consist o f a number o f experts widely&#13;
recognized in their respective fields for their knowledge o f the sector and emerging trends in&#13;
governance and transparency in the mining and hydrocarbons sectors. The Council will&#13;
review procedures for awarding licenses and contracts for all major transactions as well as the&#13;
negotiated licenses and contracts themselves, andprovide a second opinion on the conformity&#13;
o f each transaction with international best practice and the "fairness" o f the deal. The Council&#13;
will also conduct an annual audit o f cadastre functions. The Council will report to the&#13;
Minister o f Mines who will present the Council's findings to the Inter-Ministerial Committee&#13;
established by the Mining and Hydrocarbons Laws and the management committee o f the&#13;
Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
17.      The EITI supports improved governance in extractive industries through the full&#13;
publication and verification o f company payments and government revenues from oil, gas,&#13;
and mining. The government, as part o f negotiations for the project, has indicated its&#13;
intentions to endorse the principles o f the EITI. The project will help establish a multi-&#13;
stakeholder EITI committee, which will agree upon basic EITI procedures and develop a&#13;
work plan. The committee will draw members from the government, extractive industries, and&#13;
civil society. The committee will design a reporting template and engage the public in&#13;
dissemination and discussion o f the audit findings.&#13;
&#13;
18.      All components are described more specifically inTable C-2&#13;
&#13;
Likely Risksand Mitigation Measures&#13;
&#13;
19.      T h e risks to achieving the sector goals are highand can be split into those that cannot&#13;
be mitigated (political, security) and those that can. A deterioration o f the security situation or&#13;
a reversal in the political process will limit the ability o f the Government to implement the&#13;
reformprogram. Project risks include the following:&#13;
&#13;
8.       Deteriorating security in the country is a major risk factor that may discourage&#13;
foreign consultants to participate in the project and make it difficult to carry out activities&#13;
outside o f Kabul. Despite efforts to improve security by both the Government and the&#13;
international community, the IDA Interim Strategy Note reports a deteriorating security&#13;
situation in which insurgents represent a greater threat to the expansion o f government&#13;
authority than in any point in time since late 20015. The project cannot mitigate this risk. To&#13;
this end, most o f the technical assistance will take place inKabul and extensive travel around&#13;
the country is not required to implement the project. Furthermore, it will be the responsibility&#13;
o f MOMto exert hegemony over mineral resources.&#13;
&#13;
9.       Reversal of the vision and policy framework outlined in I-ANDsmay affect MoM's&#13;
restructuring plans and formulation and implementation o f a long-term strategy for its SOEs.&#13;
This risk, which is outside MoM's control, does not appear to be significant at the moment,&#13;
given the consultations that took place during the preparation o f I-ANDS, but the level o f&#13;
involvement by the new Parliament is yet to be tested.&#13;
&#13;
 10.     Possibilityfor political interference ("rent seeking") and corruption, given the large&#13;
revenue potential from Afghanistan's mineral resources, is also a risk. Afghanistan has&#13;
adopted good governance practices in its recently approved legislation, but the ability o f the&#13;
government to strictly adhere to and monitor compliance will be a challenge, especially given&#13;
the very weak judicial system. Transparency clauses are found in the Mining and&#13;
Hydrocarbons Laws, and compliance with these provisions will be monitored in the&#13;
monitoringframework.&#13;
&#13;
  InterimStrategyNote for Islamic Republic of Afghanistanfor the period FY07-08, World Bank&#13;
AfghanistanCountryUnit, March21, 2006.&#13;
&#13;
                                                 12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
11.     Weak implementation capacity o f the executing agency to implement the project is a&#13;
major risk. The Program Management Unit, which will be established under this project with&#13;
support from other donors, is designed to mitigate this risk by hiring international and local&#13;
consultants with requisite expertise who will train and work closely with MOMcounterparts.&#13;
These will include those responsible for procurement and financial management. The core&#13;
consultants for this purpose came on stream inApril 2006 andwould help mitigate this risk.It&#13;
might be difficult to find an adequate number o f suitable local counterparts, especially for&#13;
newly created units. Outsourcing o f some o f the activities inthe early years o f the project may&#13;
need to be considered.&#13;
&#13;
12.     Non-Transparent transactions are a key investor risk. The private sector may be&#13;
unwilling to invest in the minerals sector owing to a general risk aversion to conducting&#13;
business in a post-conflict setting, concern about the readiness o f regulatory institutions, or&#13;
concern about discretionary actions by the ministry in a non-transparent fashion. To bolster&#13;
investor interest and confidence, the government will want to foster stability and security&#13;
through implementation o f transparent, non-discriminatoryhon-discretionaryactions based on&#13;
competitive business processes. The risk o f non-transparent processes within the sector will&#13;
be partially addressed through capacity building within the project, but remains a&#13;
responsibility o f the MOM.&#13;
&#13;
13.     Lack of established mechanisms for inter-ministerial coordination needs to be&#13;
addressed, as a number o f measures contemplated inthe project rely critically on coordination&#13;
with other ministries, particularly the Ministry o f Finance, Ministry o f Justice, and the&#13;
Ministry of Energy and Water. Strengthening inter-ministerial coordination is an important&#13;
focus o f this project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
c&#13;
L&#13;
m&#13;
n&#13;
8&#13;
.-cE&#13;
0&#13;
Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Y&#13;
v1&#13;
.I&#13;
3C&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     .Y&#13;
      B&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      B&#13;
      c)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
em&#13;
2     n&#13;
      734&#13;
.e    c,&#13;
      Q)&#13;
$&#13;
0     E0&#13;
.I    c,&#13;
cl    u&#13;
M&#13;
C     i&#13;
      Q)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
z&#13;
.I    L&#13;
E     M&#13;
      s&#13;
      E&#13;
      .I&#13;
      E&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5t?&#13;
.I&#13;
Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
.I&#13;
E&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
L&#13;
0&#13;
Y&#13;
d&#13;
0&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       .1,&#13;
       a,&#13;
&#13;
       I&#13;
       m&#13;
       .I&#13;
       .I&#13;
       Y&#13;
&#13;
I&#13;
.I     Y&#13;
2I      c&#13;
&#13;
6k4     e5&#13;
        L&#13;
        m&#13;
._&#13;
3*     BE&#13;
        m&#13;
I&#13;
m       a,&#13;
E      .I&#13;
        L&#13;
0      Y&#13;
.I&#13;
Y&#13;
m&#13;
z       s&#13;
       U&#13;
       YE&#13;
&#13;
I&#13;
a,&#13;
&#13;
3&#13;
E       $&#13;
       .I&#13;
        Y&#13;
       3E&#13;
        u&#13;
&#13;
        Y&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
               SECTION D-STUDIES AND TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE&#13;
&#13;
Studies and technical assistance (TA) required for short-term recovery, reduction of loss in&#13;
case of a future disaster, or development o f a disaster mitigation strategy.&#13;
&#13;
Not applicable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
            SECTION E-INSTITUTIONAL             ARRANGEMENTS AND PROJECT&#13;
                                      IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
InstitutionalArrangements&#13;
&#13;
1.         The Ministry o f Mines (MOM) will have overall responsibility for project&#13;
implementation. It is recognized that MOMhas a weak implementation capacity and lacks&#13;
qualified personnel as a result o f the twenty-five years o f conflict when a number o f trained&#13;
people left the country and the majority did not have access to higher education. Many o f the&#13;
staff are close to retirement, and have had virtually no exposure to policy formulation, sector&#13;
regulation, recent developments in international industry practice (technological advances;&#13;
health, safety, and environmental standards; regulatory, fiscal, and contractual regimes),&#13;
modem methods o f management, contract negotiation, and supervision o fprivate investors.&#13;
&#13;
2.         As a result o f these constraints, MOMwill retain the services of several consultant&#13;
f i r m s as well as individual local and international consultants to provide teams o f technical&#13;
staff. The project will be implementedover a five-year period from July 2006 to July 2011. In&#13;
order to build capacity, a "train the trainer approach" will be employed, with initial&#13;
international     staff undertaking     much o f the      initial capacity   buildingiinstitutional&#13;
strengthening, but progressively transferring to national staff who, once trained, will lead in&#13;
later years. The ability o f MOMline staff to be trained and to progressively take over project&#13;
implementation is critical to the sustainability o f the project. A broad sketch o f the&#13;
organizational structure under the project is given in&#13;
&#13;
 3 ,        Figure E-1.&#13;
&#13;
 4.         Under this project, a Program Management Unit (PMU) will be created to oversee the&#13;
 day-to-day implementationo f the project and ensure compliance with provisions inthe Grant&#13;
 Agreement which govern procurement, financial andproject management. Other donor-&#13;
 funded programs within the Ministry would also come under the general umbrella o f the&#13;
 P M U intime.&#13;
&#13;
 5.         The ministryhas an immediate need for a functioning inspectorate and cadastre. For&#13;
 this reason, it was agreed during the negotiation that two departments would be staffed with&#13;
 international inspection and cadastre specialists and that these hnctions would commence&#13;
 immediately, initially undertaken entirely by the international specialists. Training will be&#13;
 provided to the ministrystaff inparallel to ensure that, by the end o f the project, ministry staff&#13;
 will be able to perform the inspection andcadastre functions entirely on their own.&#13;
&#13;
 6.         Two project elements will interact closely with entities outside o f MOM.The&#13;
 International Advisory Council provides its findings and reports via the Minister o f Mines to&#13;
 the Inter-Ministerial Committee established by the Miningand Hydrocarbons Laws and to the&#13;
 donor community through the management committee o f the Afghanistan Reconstruction&#13;
 Trust Fund. The principal counterpart for the EITI multi-stakeholder committee i s the&#13;
 MinistryofFinance.&#13;
&#13;
 ProcurementArrangements&#13;
&#13;
 7.         Procurement arrangements are described in Appendix 5. The procurement o f goods&#13;
 and services financed by IDA will be carried out in accordance with the appropriate World&#13;
 Bank guidelines. A procurementlfinancial management specialist has been hired by MOM&#13;
 under the Project Preparation Facility (PPF) to assist the ministry in preparing procurement&#13;
 packages. A procurement team will be established for the project, led by an international&#13;
 procurement specialist initially. Prior review threshold and methods o f procurement are&#13;
  summarized inAppendix 5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure E-I Conceptual Framework for Personnel and Units under the Project&#13;
                                                                                                    Ministry of Mines&#13;
                t&#13;
                I    S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         DBpuly Minister               Mininga Hydrocarbons&#13;
                                                                                                          Deputy Minister&#13;
                                                                          Geoscience&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          of Afghanistan            and Hydmcartons&#13;
                                                                         GeOkgIcal survey                                  Enterpnse~&#13;
 Technical&#13;
                  Limnsing                                                                              Procunmenl&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 RoyaltyAudit                                                    Hydrocarban                                  Feflilizer&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        Mines Affairs&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  Geoscience&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Pnvate-Senor&#13;
                                                                              Promtiona&#13;
                                                                              DeveloDmenl&#13;
&#13;
%-&#13;
      Developing Regulatory Capacity    ImprovingInternal Efpciencies                       Developing Mineral Resources&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
FinancialManagement,Disbursement,and Audit&#13;
&#13;
8.         Financial management (FM) arrangements are described in Appendix 6. The&#13;
procurement/ financial management specialist hired under the PPF will assist MOMin&#13;
confirming interim unaudited financial reports formats and developing a financial&#13;
management manual and a project implementationmanual.&#13;
&#13;
9.         Quarterly unaudited interim financial statements will be used for project monitoring&#13;
and supervision. The financial statements will be produced based on records kept on Excel&#13;
spreadsheets or some other simple database. For disbursement, a single designated account&#13;
will be opened at D aAfghanistan Bankor ina local commercialbank.&#13;
&#13;
10.        MoF-Special Disbursement Unit (SDU) will verify that the project FM system at&#13;
MOMcorrectly handles preparation of payment applications, expenditure reconciliation,&#13;
recording o f expenditures, and obtaining and processing cash advances from SDU.&#13;
&#13;
Environmentaland Social Safeguards&#13;
&#13;
11.        This project focuses on the provision o f technical assistance and capacity building to&#13;
MOM.The project will implement the tasks related to environmental and social safeguards&#13;
with reference to the National Environmental Action Plan in cooperation with the National&#13;
Environmental Protection Agency (NEPA).&#13;
&#13;
12.        The project will not involve direct IDA investments in specific mineral assets or the&#13;
preparation of pre-feasibility, feasibility, or engineering studies. The nature o f advisory&#13;
services to be provided to MOMis to enhance the capacity o f MOMto evaluate and facilitate&#13;
mineral and hydrocarbon investment in a manner that is consistent with international best&#13;
practice in terms o f technical, environmental and social standards.&#13;
&#13;
                                                               20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13.      It is recognized that there are currently a number of potential investors covering a&#13;
range o f mineral and hydrocarbon commodities that are waiting for the formalization o f the&#13;
regulatory framework in order to take advantage o f opportunities to invest inthe sector. This&#13;
could result, during the implementation o f the project, in the need for advice on specific&#13;
mineral-based transactions to be provided to MOM.These transactions will be used by the&#13;
technical assistance project as case studies to develop the required internal capacity to&#13;
facilitate mineral investment. In such cases the project will ensure that full environmental&#13;
impact assessments be prepared by the investor consistent with the requirements o f MOMand&#13;
NEPA.The transaction case studies will thus provide opportunities to train MOMstaff inthe&#13;
application o f the relevant safeguard policies and environmental and social assessment&#13;
procedures.&#13;
&#13;
14.      Work is also required to prepare strategic assessments and evaluations o f existing&#13;
SOEs. This work will be in the nature o f strategic technical andpolicy assessments as well as&#13;
training o f MOMstaff intechnical, environmental and social assessment evaluations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
             SECTION F-FINANCIAL AND ECONOMICJUSTIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
1.        The World Bank Group's work over the past 20 years with many countries on mining&#13;
sector      reform     agendas      helps      to      address    two    common         questions:&#13;
(1) I s there a good economic justification for using public funds to pay for expensive&#13;
technical assistance to improve the enabling environment and thereby to help attract new&#13;
investment?&#13;
(2) How much could the government benefit from extractive industries in the medium and&#13;
longer        terms      if     new        investment        were      to     be       generated?&#13;
These questions relate to the direct consequences that use o f public funds may have to&#13;
generate income and other benefits streams for the country. Equally important are the results&#13;
which may be achieved in terms o f preventing fraud and other negative impacts o f the sector&#13;
if public funds are not used for the purposes o f strengthening government oversight of the&#13;
sector.&#13;
&#13;
2.        The World Bank Group's programs in developing countries that aim to improve the&#13;
ability o f the government to attract private sector investment and to monitor and regulate it in&#13;
an effective manner provide strong evidence that funding technical assistance is beneficial to&#13;
directly stimulate revenues for the government as well as to prevent abuse and fraud. Table F-&#13;
1 shows the "before" and "after" results o f the reform programs in terms o f increased&#13;
exploration investment, production, and exports.&#13;
&#13;
Table F-1 MiningReform"Before" and "After": Resultsin SelectedCountries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 3,       Specifically, the mining sector reform programs provide extensive technical&#13;
 assistance to re-write the basic sector legislation and regulations; liberalize the fiscal regime&#13;
 while, at the same time, tighten up on tax compliance; strengthen public sector oversight&#13;
 institutions including cadastre management and mines inspectorate; improve environmental&#13;
 review and controls on projects; improve and enhance the geo-science database; and provide&#13;
 extensive training and capacity building in key functions. The results o f these programs has&#13;
 been demonstrably positive: in almost every instance key indicators such as exploration&#13;
 expenditure, production value, export earnings, tax receipts, and value added from the sector&#13;
 have increased substantial from the levels before the reforms.&#13;
&#13;
 4.       The case o f Argentina is indicative of the results that can be achieved. In 1991, the&#13;
 new government announced an ambitious program o f macro economic and sector reforms to&#13;
 reduce the presence o f the state in all sectors o f the economy. The government, with technical&#13;
 assistance provided by two successive Bank projects in the total amount o f US$70 million,&#13;
 initiated work to reform the mining legislation, improve the tax regime, strengthen&#13;
 government oversight institutions at the federal and provincial levels, put into place a modem&#13;
 computerized mine title and registry system, up-grade the geological information systems to&#13;
 international standards, and undertake other reforms. Argentina mineral production has&#13;
 increased from US$341 million to US$1,3 10 million; annual expenditures in exploration are&#13;
 over US$150 million and incapital expenditures US$350 million. Finally, exports o f minerals&#13;
 have increased ten-fold from US$78 million to US$700 million. In 2001, by value, minerals&#13;
 exports earnings surpassed those o f beef. The exploration and production booms have&#13;
&#13;
                                                  22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
logistics, analytical laboratories, and payments of wages and taxes which will contribute&#13;
directly to regional economies in mineral rich provinces. It is anticipated that exploration&#13;
expenditures by miningcompanies could reach US$10-20 million per year within five years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                 SECTION G-ACTION PLAN&#13;
&#13;
1.      T h i s section tabulates and summarizes the principal agreements reached during&#13;
negotiations, and the key implementation activities and indicators that are to serve as&#13;
monitoring devices for the borrower and IDA.&#13;
&#13;
Table G-1 Afghanistan: Sustainable DevelopmentofNaturalResources Project&#13;
ResultsFramework&#13;
&#13;
ProjectDevelopment         Definition                     Outcome Indicators&#13;
Objective&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Enhancethe governance      Transparency,competition,      Effectivereviewby the Ministry with advice&#13;
of the mineraland          and fairness of mineraland     from the InternationalAdvisory Council&#13;
hydrocarbonresources       hydrocarbon development&#13;
sector                     agreements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Effectivelyregulatethe     Strict adherence to the         Issuanceof miningtitles within the timeframe&#13;
sector in a transparent    dispositions ofthe Minerals     defined inthe Minerals Law&#13;
manner                     Law and HydrocarbonsLaws&#13;
                           and associatedregulationsin&#13;
                           the issuance of miningtitles,&#13;
                           licenses, and contracts, and    All new hydrocarbon exploration,development,&#13;
                           compliance ofthe contractors    and productionresultingfrom competitive&#13;
                           with their contractual          tender&#13;
                           obligations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Foster private sector      Ability to attract new          Two new medium-size mines under&#13;
development                investments                     developmentby 2010&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           Two hydrocarbonlicensingrounds by 2011&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.        Table G-2 lists, against each identified activity, which entity (government, consultant,&#13;
donor, other) is responsible for the task, and the expected benchmark outputs according to the&#13;
implementation dates specified.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
x&#13;
41ci&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       g s&#13;
&#13;
x             m z m -&#13;
-&#13;
4 -&#13;
&#13;
x             0 0 0 0&#13;
4 -&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
m&#13;
Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 d&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  m    d&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 N     m&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       CI&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             .-M&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX 1:EXTRACTIVE INDUSTRYSTATE-OWNEDENTERPRISES&#13;
INTHE MINISTRY OF MINES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Important state-owned enterprises and departments inextractive industries under the Ministry&#13;
o f Mines are described belowS6&#13;
&#13;
        Mines Extraction Company              The Law of Mines gives this company exclusive&#13;
        rights to all mineral and metal deposits other than coal and hydrocarbons. It enters&#13;
        into contracts with private firms for extraction o f minerals and metals. Revenues and&#13;
        expenditures appear to be neither recorded nor reported.&#13;
&#13;
        North Coal Enterprise        T h i s enterprise suffers from long-standing neglect o f the&#13;
        mines, lack o f development capital and maintenance budget, and effects o f poor past&#13;
        mining practices. From an annual production o f 250,000 tonnes as recently as 15&#13;
        years ago, annual production is now down to 30,000 tonnes. The enterprise also&#13;
        purchases for distribution an additional 60,000 tonnes o f coal per year from artisanal&#13;
        production. Capital investment o f US$5 million is needed immediately (and being&#13;
        provided as emergency assistance by MoF) with an additional US$4 million over the&#13;
        next three years to return production to 190,000 tonnes per year (tpy). Annual coal&#13;
        demand for cement alone could easily reach 200,000 tonnes in the not too distant&#13;
        future.&#13;
&#13;
        State Gas Enterprise       From the daily peak production o f 11 million cubic meters&#13;
        (m') in 1978-79, the State Gas Enterprise is currently producing 0.5 million m3per&#13;
        day. Infrastructure for localproduction o f gas, treatment, and transport is non-existent&#13;
        or functioning inefficiently.&#13;
&#13;
        Cement Enterprises         Ghori (1&amp;2), Herat, and Jabal Seraj are the four operating&#13;
        cement enterprises. Among them, only Ghori 1 is producing at a reasonable level (50&#13;
        percent o f capacity). Coal and electricity shortages are the main constraints on&#13;
        production. All four enterprises use technology that is obsolete and much less&#13;
        efficient than modern processes.&#13;
&#13;
        Kud Bergh Fertilizer and Power Plant             This plant uses inefficient and obsolete&#13;
        technology and suffers from high operating cost, extensive cannibalization o f&#13;
        equipment and machinery, and a lack o f ready available spare parts. It is not a viable&#13;
        entity and even full rehabilitation is not expected to make this plant economic. This&#13;
        plant has not been paying regularly for gas, the primary feedstock.&#13;
&#13;
        Afghan Geological Survey (AFG)              AFG has been receiving assistance from the&#13;
        BritishGeological Survey (BGS) andthe US.Geological Survey (USGS). There was&#13;
        significant geological mapping o f the country between 1967 and 1971 by Italian,&#13;
        German, Soviet, and Afghan geologists. Soviet and Afghan geologists have also in&#13;
        the past completed mineral evaluation studies on 110 deposits.&#13;
&#13;
        Department of Oil and Gas            Created in 2003, this department is responsible for&#13;
        the State Gas Enterprise and the Oil and Gas Exploration Department.&#13;
&#13;
        Oil and Gas ExplorationDepartment This department has 1,800 employees with&#13;
        no specific tasks. There has beenno funding for field     services for about six years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Modifiedfrom Afghanistan: ManagingPublic Finances for Development,The World Bank,&#13;
December2005.&#13;
&#13;
                                                28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX 2: LETTEROF SECTOR DEVELOPMENT POLICY&#13;
&#13;
(in this appendix the term "MMI" and "Ministry of Mines and Industries" refers to the now&#13;
renamed `iZ.ioM" and "Ministry of Mines ")&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Islamic Republic of Afghanistan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            AFGHANISTAN'SMINERALS SECTOR:&#13;
                       LETTER OF SECTOR DEVELOPMENT POLICY&#13;
&#13;
                            Afghanistan Ministryo f Mines and Industries&#13;
                                       RevisedFebruary27,2006&#13;
&#13;
          The goal o f the Ministry o f Mines and Industries is ". ..to provide a transparent and&#13;
          efficient regulatory environment for Afghanistan's mineral, oil, gas, and industrial&#13;
          development that enables private-sector led investments, facilitates sustained&#13;
          economic growth, and increases revenues to the government."     '&#13;
The Afghanistan mineral sector consists o f five major commodity groups: (i)        hydrocarbons&#13;
(principally gas), (ii)  solid fossil fuels (principally coal), (iii) ferrous and precious&#13;
                                                                      base,&#13;
metals, (iv) construction materials (principally crushed stone and cement), and (v)&#13;
dimensional stone and gemstones. These industries were much more productive in the 1970s&#13;
and 1980s than they are today. The civil wars o f the 1980s and 1990s severely crippled&#13;
production and exploration. Existing mineral production is now limited to some natural gas&#13;
production in Sherbergan, small coal operations inBaghlan and Bamyan provinces, limestone&#13;
for two operating cement plants, construction materials (sand, gravel, crushed rock)&#13;
nationwide, and gemstones and dimensional stone from artisanal operations.&#13;
&#13;
Even though development o f a vibrant minerals sector has so far eluded Afghanistan, the&#13;
resource base and undeveloped potential is substantial. Development o f industrial mining&#13;
could substantially increase government revenues and export earnings as well as create new&#13;
job opportunities and downstream industries. Also, supply o f essential commodities such as&#13;
coal and industrial materials to local industries is critical. Attracting new investment to the&#13;
sector i s thus an essential element to help reduce poverty.&#13;
&#13;
For the past several decades the Ministry o f Mines and Industries (MMI), the government&#13;
 institution responsible for the mining sector, has been centered on extractive industries and&#13;
 associated heavy industries: (a) mining o f minerals and construction materials, (b) petroleum&#13;
 exploration and production, and (c) the operation o f downstream industries that utilize&#13;
 extractive industry outputs. Historically, MMI has operated as a vertically integrated&#13;
 extractive industry conglomerate with enterprises reporting to the center, but operating&#13;
 autonomously in terms o f budget planning and revenues management. However, the&#13;
 government has made the strategic policy decision that MMI should transform itself into a&#13;
 regulatory body to facilitate private sector investment rather than own and operate mines,&#13;
 industries, or other state-owned enterprises. The obstacles facing MMIto make this transition&#13;
 have been summarized in the IDA document "Mining As A Source o f Growth" (2004). The&#13;
 study concluded that MMI is not appropriately organized, staffed, and equipped to regulate&#13;
 the sector and stimulate new investment. With the addition of the light industries wing in&#13;
 early 2005, MMI added a cluster o f 10 textile-based enterprises. At this time approximately&#13;
&#13;
 'The  Ministryof MinesandIndustries(MMI)has sincebeenrenamedthe Ministryof Mines(MOM).&#13;
&#13;
                                                29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12,000 employees work for the Ministry and its various state-owned enterprises (SOEs),&#13;
including about 7,000 employees who work with the oil, gas, and minerals sectors. This&#13;
organizational structure does not reflect MMI's pending role as mineral sector regulator, and&#13;
concerted institutional strengthening and capacity building is needed. Moreover, due to the&#13;
political turbulence o f the past 30 years, MMI has lost much o f its institutional capacity to&#13;
supervise the sector. MMI will have to be significantly strengthened to meet the new&#13;
challenges o f developingthe country's mineral wealth.&#13;
&#13;
To this end, MOMacknowledges that (a) future resource development must be guided by&#13;
good governance policies, and (b) institutional strengthening and capacity building is needed&#13;
to ensure that the sector meets national objectives and benefits the people o f Afghanistan.&#13;
This letter buildson MMI's current Strategy for the Mineral Resources Sector o fAfghanistan&#13;
(April 28,2005, Revised January 29,2006).&#13;
&#13;
Good Governance Policies&#13;
&#13;
Within the InterimAfghanistanNational Development Strategy (I-ANDs),a) security; b)&#13;
governance, rule o f law, and humanrights, and c) economic and social development, are&#13;
deemed essential to consolidating peace and stability, reducing poverty, and achieving&#13;
prosperity through broad-based and equitable economic growth. Under the economic and&#13;
social development pillar, the government commits to a five-year strategic benchmark to&#13;
create an enabling regulatory environment and improved infrastructure for profitable&#13;
extraction o f Afghanistan's mineral and natural resources.&#13;
&#13;
The MMI acknowledges that development o f mineral resources will require investments in&#13;
excess o f government abilities and thus seeks to establish conditions and an enabling&#13;
environment to attract and retain investment by both private local and international groups. As&#13;
a first step, the ministryhas undertaken preparation and passage o f (i) Minerals Law (July&#13;
                                                                        the&#13;
2005) and (ii)    the Hydrocarbons (Exploration and Production) Law (December 2005). To&#13;
make these laws operational, MMI must now build institutional capacity to address&#13;
institutionalbarriers and increase administrative efficiency.&#13;
&#13;
To do so, MMIis developing a national minerals policy that reflects the strategic orientations&#13;
o f overall government policy as well as recognizing the complexities o f issues and challenges&#13;
facing the hydrocarbons and mineral industries. This policy includes the following main&#13;
elements.&#13;
&#13;
      Good Governance of Afghanistan's Mineral Resources.MMIwill:&#13;
      1. be guidedbyprinciples o f sustainability to define a national minerals development&#13;
          policy;&#13;
     2. exert central government sovereignty over mineral resources located throughout the&#13;
          national territory;&#13;
     3. stimulate and mobilize local and internationalprivate investment in minerals&#13;
          exploration and development;&#13;
     4. increase tax revenues to the central government from minerals production and ensure&#13;
          adequate disclosure thereof;&#13;
     5. strengthen government supervisory institutions to distinguish clearly between the&#13;
          roles and responsibilities o f the regulator and SOEs;&#13;
     6. promote the transition o f state-owned mineral resource enterprises to operate on a&#13;
          commercial basis;&#13;
     7. promote scientific and geological investigation into the nature and extent o f&#13;
          Afghanistan's mineral resources and to make such information available to the&#13;
          public andpotential investors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    Ensuring that Afghans Benefit from Production of Resources.MMI will&#13;
    1. seek to ensure that communities benefit from extractive industries and, where&#13;
        possible, link local economic development (small to medium enterprises) to the&#13;
        project;&#13;
    2. seek to ascertain broadsupport o f affected communities through informed&#13;
        consultation and capacity building at the local level;&#13;
&#13;
    AddressingEnvironmental and Social Issues. MMI will:&#13;
    1. ensure, in cooperation with the National Environment Protection Agency, that&#13;
        mining operations are conducted in an environmentally and socially sustainable&#13;
        manner through the enforcement o f legislation and creation o f an Environmental&#13;
        Protection Department, and that operators conduct proper environmental impact&#13;
        assessments and develop and implement environmental management plans;&#13;
    2. ensure adequate frameworks and capacity to implement mine closure/well&#13;
        rehabilitation and financial surety on project to do so;&#13;
    3.  undertake a rolling update o f technical guidelines usingaccepted best practices.&#13;
    4. begin to regularize small scale miningandprovide for adequate institutional and&#13;
        technical support o f these activities;&#13;
    5,   apply internationally accepted policies to safeguard social protection associated with&#13;
         mineral production; and&#13;
    6. seek to implement globally recognized voluntary principles on the use o f security&#13;
         forces.&#13;
&#13;
    Coordination between MMI, Other Government Ministries, and Donors. MMIwill&#13;
     1. coordinate donor programs andwork with other government ministries ina manner&#13;
         consistent with the ministry's policies and the broader objectives o f the government;&#13;
    2. develop a program management unit (PMU) for this purpose.&#13;
&#13;
InstitutionalStrengthening and CapacityBuilding&#13;
&#13;
As detailed in I-ANDs,the Government o f Afghanistan is putting into place a private-sector&#13;
led economic development model, with the Government divesting itself o f ownership o f the&#13;
means o f production, and instead carrying out policy making and regulatory functions. Based&#13;
on this model, the roles and responsibilities o f MMI will fall into the following three main&#13;
areas:  .        Setting Sector Policy. MMI will set and implement policies for the mining,&#13;
        hydrocarbon, and the industrial sectors. MMI will take the lead in formulating&#13;
        policies anddrafting laws, regulations, standards, andmodel contracts.&#13;
        .        Regulating natural resourceproduction and industrial activities. MMI will&#13;
        take the lead in (i) negotiating and issuing licenses and contracts, and (ii)   ensuring&#13;
        compliance with laws, regulations, licenses, contracts, and standards. Working&#13;
        closely with other ministries, MMI will also engage in economic regulation where&#13;
        there is a natural monopoly or little effective competition. Regulation requires that&#13;
        MMI be able to measure or verify production; calculate royalties, fees, and the&#13;
        Government's petroleum production share; and inspect and make the necessary&#13;
        measurements to check compliance with health, safety, and environmental standards.&#13;
        .        Moving to market- and private-finance based sectors. At present most&#13;
        activities in individual sectors are financed and managed by the Government. MMIis&#13;
        therefore both a regulator and an operator. In due course, the Government o f&#13;
        Afghanistan plans to privatize or liquidate most SOEs. MMI will maintain an up-to-&#13;
        date database on natural resources and production, provide vital data and information&#13;
        (such as production, sale, exports, imports, prices paid) to private sector participants&#13;
        andpromote the sectors to potential investors. Together with the Ministryo f Finance&#13;
        (MoF), MMI will lead this transition from government-owned and controlled&#13;
        operations to private-sector run operations inmining, hydrocarbons, and industry.&#13;
&#13;
                                                31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The transformation o f MMI to this regulatory role will require a number o f actions. These&#13;
include:.        Creating a Modern Legal and Regulatory Framework. The MMI has&#13;
        prepared new Minerals and Hydrocarbon (Exploration and Production) Laws, and&#13;
        both laws have now been passed by the Cabinet. They reflect international standards,&#13;
        apply to all investors local and foreign, and provide the basis for transparent&#13;
        allocation o f mineral and hydrocarbon rights to private entities. Terms o f reference&#13;
        have now been prepared to engage legal experts to help the Government draft mining&#13;
        regulations and a model contract.&#13;
        .        Implementing an Internationally Competitive Fiscal and Mining Taxation&#13;
        Package. The Income Tax Law o f 2005 provides internationally competitive fiscal&#13;
        terms for qualified extractive industry taxpayers. These provisions cover depreciation,&#13;
        amortization, loss carried forward, and stability.&#13;
        .        Building Strategic Planning and Technical Capacity. As an organization,&#13;
        MMI traditionally has had limited experience in formulating sector strategies and&#13;
        policies for private sector growth, or in interactingwith the public. MMIis organized&#13;
        differently from most Afghan ministries, because it has had limited direct contact&#13;
        with the public. Instead, its services were directed to the Government and to support&#13;
        o f its SOEs. Today, formulating strategies for the new MMI will require a better&#13;
        understanding o f factors that make sectors economic and efficient. It will also be&#13;
        important to understand the optimal sectoral structures and appropriate legal and&#13;
        contractual frameworks. Strategic planning also requires knowing how best to handle&#13;
        SOEs. The IDA and the Asian Development Bank are both working to build strategic&#13;
        planning and sectoral capacity within MMI. Further, the British Geological Survey&#13;
        andthe US Geological Survey have important programs targeted towards professional&#13;
        development within MMI,principally within Afghan Geological Survey.&#13;
        .        SOE Reform. The Ministry o f Finance is responsible for overseeing SOE&#13;
        reform. Its SOE department has already developed an approach to SOE reform and a&#13;
        preliminary classification o f SOEs. By recent Cabinet decision, privatization&#13;
        decisions now require joint actions by both a line ministry and MoF. The MMI is&#13;
        working with M o F on these issues to ensure that strategic considerations - such as the&#13;
        need to retain production o f certain essential commodities in the short term given the&#13;
        lack o f private sector investment and technical sectoral expertise - are fully taken into&#13;
        account inthe privatization strategy and its implementation.&#13;
        .        Regularizing the Informal Sector. This is needed to effectively regulate&#13;
        informal operations and to enforce legal, environmental, and social compliance.&#13;
&#13;
To achieve the above goals, MMI needs extensive capacity building and institutional&#13;
strengthening.&#13;
        Emphasis will be placed on professional development o f personnel through training&#13;
        andexposure to best international practices inthe mineral industries.&#13;
        Administrative unitddepartments will be given clear and consistent mandates and&#13;
        procedures will be established to enhance communication and coordination between&#13;
        them.&#13;
        Regional offices will be strengthened in order to reinforce links between the center&#13;
        and the outlying areas.&#13;
        Emphasis will be placed on transparency and good governance and specific&#13;
        procedures will be established inthis respect.&#13;
        Establish and, if necessary re-organize, departments to handle policy and&#13;
        administration, cadastre services, mines inspection, health and safety issues,&#13;
        environmental matters, commodity certification and quality control, and geological&#13;
&#13;
                                                32&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        survey and laboratory services. Develop programs for promotion o f the mining sector&#13;
        to local and foreign investors.&#13;
        Competitively tender mineral deposits internationally for which the government has&#13;
        detailed and complete geological information.&#13;
        Develop and implement plans for the rehabilitation and eventual liquidation/&#13;
        commercialization/privatizationo f SOEs.&#13;
        Establish a department to support small scale mining.&#13;
&#13;
FromPolicy to Action&#13;
&#13;
MMI seeks to build minerals sector governance to stimulate economic and social&#13;
development, bring stability to rural areas, fight poverty, and bring prosperity through broad-&#13;
based and equitable economic growth. Strategic investments are needed through a coordinated&#13;
multi-donor assistance program across several years. MMI invites the international&#13;
community, donors, bilateral agencies, and civil society to take a stake in the process and&#13;
ensure that the nation moves forward buildingupon a strong minerals sector. This letter is our&#13;
commitment to actions that will sustain the government and the people for years to come.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Eng.MirMohammed Ashan Sediq&#13;
Minister of Mines andIndustries&#13;
Government of Afghanistan&#13;
February 27,2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                33&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
.4&#13;
M&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
a,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          m&#13;
          v,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    ..&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
             ,i    x&#13;
                  3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Y&#13;
8&#13;
2 8&#13;
-8&#13;
? g&#13;
  .b&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Y&#13;
        8E&#13;
        e&#13;
        a2&#13;
&#13;
        bo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        x&#13;
        I&#13;
        m&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX 4: GOVERNANCE AND TRANSPARENCY INTHE NATURAL&#13;
RESOURCESSECTOR&#13;
&#13;
1.      The Afghan mineral sector offers a source o f economic growth, employment, and&#13;
export earnings. Worldwide experience shows, however, that resource-rich countries have&#13;
grown more slowly than resource-poor countries since the 1970s, and in the 1990s the&#13;
average per capita gross domestic product o f resource-poor countries surpassed that o f&#13;
resource-rich countries. This phenomenon has come to be known as the "resource curse."&#13;
Good governance is essential to avoid misallocation o f national resources that could lead to&#13;
increasedpoverty, corruption, and conflict.&#13;
&#13;
2.      To avoid unwanted outcomes, the government has prepared a policy letter to direct&#13;
orderly private-sector-led development o f national resources based on transparent,&#13;
competitive processes. The private sector is responding by expressing early interest in an&#13;
array o f mineral resources, including the initial competitive tender o f the Aynak copper&#13;
deposit and possibly exploration o f certain oil blocs. However, there is a danger that some&#13;
investors could seek to circumvent such good governance processes for both solid minerals&#13;
and hydrocarbons by exploiting capacity deficiencies in order to secure resources exclusivity&#13;
through non-competitive, non-transparent andpossibly corrupt means.&#13;
&#13;
3.       The government, through the project, will devise and implement a number o f&#13;
measures to ensure competition, transparency, and adherence to international best practices in&#13;
respect o f authorizing new investments in the sector. It is important to recognize that this&#13;
multi-layered approach puts into place transparency procedures at each key decision point in&#13;
terms o f (a) upstream issuance o f mine title and/or authorization o f investment agreements;&#13;
and (b) downstream management o f benefit streams through sound sector policy. As such, it&#13;
will provide the government and the international donor community with some comfort that&#13;
the bitter experience o f the resource curse in other countries will not be repeated in&#13;
Afghanistan.&#13;
&#13;
4.       The hndamental starting points to ensure good governance inthe sector have already&#13;
been established. The Minerals Law was gazetted by the government in 2005, providing for&#13;
 international standards to be applied to the investments in the sector. The Hydrocarbons&#13;
 (Petroleum and Gas) Law was approved by the Cabinet in December 2005. Regulations,&#13;
 administrative procedures, and guidelines will be prepared inthe initial months o f the project.&#13;
 This legislative framework for minerals andhydrocarbons will provide the basis for additional&#13;
 governance and transparency measures to be implemented as follows.&#13;
&#13;
          Sector Policy Advisors. In both sub-sectors, the project will fund sector policy&#13;
          advisors to the MOM.The advisors will provide, among other functions, advice to the&#13;
          MOMon international best practices concerning competitive bidding, governance and&#13;
          transparency measures, and management o fbenefits streams which are generally used&#13;
          inthe minerals andhydrocarbons sectors.&#13;
&#13;
     0    Technical assistance in cadastre management and mines inspection. The keystone&#13;
          of good governance in the sector is a properly functioning mine title and registration&#13;
          system together with precise procedures and guidelines for the issuance and&#13;
          maintenance o f titles (cadastre system). At present, MOMhas no experience with&#13;
          modem and sophisticated cadastre systems. Similarly, an effective mines inspection&#13;
          h c t i o n is essential to ensure compliance on the ground o f exploitation companies&#13;
          with applicable regulations and investment obligations. Because MOMlacks&#13;
          experience and capacity in both the cadastre and mines inspection functions, the&#13;
          project will fund significant technical assistance early on in the project to establish&#13;
          such systems within MOM.While a great deal o f effort will be made to train and build&#13;
          capacity o f MOMstaff, it i s recognized that this will take some time. Accordingly, a&#13;
          single large consultancy contract will be awarded for the duration o f the project to an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  39&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
international firm having expertise in cadastre management and mines inspection.&#13;
The terms o f reference for the consultant will provide for direct day-to-day&#13;
management of these functions in accordance with internationally accepted&#13;
procedures and guidelines. The terms o f reference will also provide for training,&#13;
capacity building and knowledge transfer for MOMstaff, with precise performance&#13;
indicators to assess how well this has been accomplished.&#13;
Mining Licensing Board. Review o f the cadastre, inspection, and environmental and&#13;
social safeguard functions related to the rights o f investors to operate in the sector&#13;
will be provided by a Mining Licensing Board. Similar to the practice in many&#13;
countries, the Board will be composed o f three senior department heads within MOM&#13;
supplemented by two representatives o f the consultancy firm responsible for&#13;
management o f the cadastre and mines inspectorate. The purpose o f the Board will be&#13;
to certify the compliance o f mine title, hydrocarbon license, and contract applications&#13;
with the regulations in force, specifically the conformity with applicable application&#13;
procedures, the financial and technical competencies o f the applicant, and the&#13;
compliance o f the proposed work program to established guidelines. The Board will&#13;
also review each renewal, cancellation, termination, and surrender case to ensure that&#13;
due procedures were followed. It will make recommendations to the Minister by&#13;
consensus decision based on these objective criteria. The Minister may not reject the&#13;
recommendations o f the Board except for materialbreaches.&#13;
International Advisoiy Council. Under the project, an advisory council will be&#13;
established, composed o f eminent international experts in mining and hydrocarbons&#13;
investments. The Minerals and Hydrocarbons Laws provide for contracts be approved&#13;
by an Inter-Ministerial Committee upon proposition o f the Minister for Mines and&#13;
Industries. The purpose o f the International Advisory Council will be to render an&#13;
opinion in respect o f 1) the procedures and processes used to negotiate such&#13;
agreements and contracts and, 2) the "fairness" o f the terms and conditions o f such&#13;
agreements and contracts. The Council will issue its opinions directly to the Minster&#13;
o f Mines with copy to the management committee o f the Afghanistan Reconstruction&#13;
Trust Fund. This will reassure the donor community that the government is granting&#13;
rights to develop the nation's natural resources in a transparent manner as well as&#13;
provide comfort that this development will be "fair" and consistent with best practice.&#13;
The Council will also conduct an annual audit o f cadastre functions and report to the&#13;
same two bodies.&#13;
Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative. Duringnegotiations it was agreed that&#13;
the Ministry o f Finance would publish its endorsement o f the principles o f the&#13;
Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative (EITI). Duringthe course o f the project&#13;
the government will implement the EITI with financial and technical assistance&#13;
provide by the project and the EITI trust funds. The EITI is under implementation&#13;
with the support o f a number o f governments (United Kingdom, Norway) and the&#13;
World Bank Group. The EITI is a process by which the government, private sector&#13;
companies operating in the extractive industries, and civil society groups discuss in a&#13;
structured fashion how to enhance reporting and disclosure o f revenues and benefits&#13;
 streams from extractive activities. The ultimate objective o f the EITI is to prepare a&#13;
template which will report on a regular basis the revenues paid by companies and&#13;
received by the government. The fundamental principles o f the EITI are available at:&#13;
www.eikansparencv.org,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        40&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX 5: PROCUREMENT ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
Country Context&#13;
&#13;
IDA has gained substantial experience and understanding of the procurement environment in&#13;
Afghanistan through its involvement in the interim procurement arrangements put in place&#13;
through the Emergency Public Administration Project as well as with the institutions with&#13;
current responsibility for those and the subsequent arrangements, namely Afghanistan&#13;
Reconstruction and Development Services (ARDS). As part o f the broader review o f&#13;
Afghanistan's Public Finance Management (PFM) system, IDA carried out an assessment o f&#13;
the procurement environment in the country based on the baseline andperformance indicators&#13;
developed by a group o f institutions led by the World Bank and the OECD Development&#13;
Assistance Committee.&#13;
&#13;
The first key issue identified through the procurement assessment was the need for ownership&#13;
and a champion in the Government for reform, deepening o f capacity, ensuring integrity in&#13;
the operation o f procurement systems, and promoting sound procurement among ministries.&#13;
&#13;
A new Procurement Law was adopted in November 2005 which radically transformed the&#13;
legal and regulatory framework. While the law provides a very modern legal system for&#13;
procurement, it may be difficult to implement in the current context. It relies, for example, on&#13;
the establishment o f a procurement policy unit to ensure implementation through the creation&#13;
o f secondary legislation, standardbiddingdocuments, provision o f advice, and creation o f the&#13;
necessary information systems for advertising and data collection. It further relies on the&#13;
development o f an independent complaints review mechanismto ensure enforcement. Neither&#13;
i s yet inplace.&#13;
&#13;
In the absence of adequate capacity to manage procurement activities effectively, a central&#13;
procurement facilitation service has been established. IDA and the Government has agreed on&#13;
a program for country-wide procurement reform and capacity building, leading to the&#13;
transition from centralized to decentralized procurement services. The IDA-funded Public&#13;
Administration Capacity Building (PACB) project is the primary instrument for implementing&#13;
the program to strengthen capacity o f the line ministries to manage public procurement in an&#13;
effective, transparent, and accountable manner. However, the implementation o f the&#13;
procurement capacity buildingstrategy has not made any significant progress yet due to a lack&#13;
o f coordination and delays indecision making within the Government. The radical changes to&#13;
the procurement environment brought about by the new Law also require the urgent&#13;
implementation o f a comprehensive capacity development program. The implementation o f&#13;
the procurement reform component o f the PACB project should be considered with due&#13;
priority to ensure that fiduciary standards are further enhanced and that capacity i s developed&#13;
 inthe Governmentto maintainthese standards.&#13;
&#13;
 PartA General&#13;
&#13;
 Procurement for the proposed project would be carried out in accordance with the World&#13;
 Bank's "Guidelines: Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" dated May 2004,&#13;
 "Guidelines: Selection and Employment o f Consultants by World Bank Borrowers" dated&#13;
 May 2004, and the provisions stipulated inthe Financing Agreement. The general description&#13;
 o f various items under different expenditure categories are describedbelow. For each contract&#13;
 to be financed by the Grant, the different procurement methods or consultant selection&#13;
 methods, the need for prequalification, estimated costs, prior review requirements, and time&#13;
 frame are agreed between the Grant Recipient and the IDA project team in the Procurement&#13;
 Plan. The Procurement Plan will be updated at least annually or as required to reflect the&#13;
 actual project implementation needs and improvements ininstitutional capacity.&#13;
&#13;
 Procurementof Works: Works procuredunder this project, would include office renovation.&#13;
 The procurement will be done using the World Bank Group's Standard Bidding Documents&#13;
&#13;
                                                41&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(SBD) for all I C B and National SBD agreed with (or satisfactory to) IDA for all NCB. Other&#13;
procurement method will be shopping and direct contracting. Threshold for N C B works will&#13;
be US$500,000 and for shopping will be US$lOO,OOO per contract.&#13;
&#13;
Procurement of Goods: Goods procured under this project would include: (1) vehicles, (2)&#13;
office equipment and software, (3) publications, (4) scientific/engineering equipment, (5)&#13;
consumables for operating equipment, vehicles, office equipment, etc. The procurement will&#13;
be done using World Bank Group's SBD for all ICB and National SBD agreed with (or&#13;
satisfactory to) IDA for all NCB. Other procurement method will be shopping. Threshold for&#13;
N C B goods will be US$200,000 and for shopping will be US$lOO,OOO per contract.&#13;
&#13;
Selection of Consultants: Consultancy Service procured under this project would&#13;
include: (1) 14 individual consultants hired for the Project Management Unit; (2) consultant&#13;
contract for legal, Cadastre, and Inspectorate; (3) consultant contract for small-scale mining&#13;
and extension services; (4) consultants contract for environmental and social protection; (5)&#13;
consultant contract for the Sector Policy and Private-Sector Promotion and Development&#13;
Unit; (6) consultant contract for the Afghanistan Geological Survey; (7) consultant contract&#13;
for strategic sector studies; and (8) consultant contract for auditors. The selection methods for&#13;
selection o f consultants will include QCBS, QBS, and individual consultant. Threshold for&#13;
CQS procedure willbe US$200,000 per contract.&#13;
&#13;
Short lists o f consultants for services estimated to cost less than US$50,000 equivalent per&#13;
contract may be composed entirely o f national consultants in accordance with the provisions&#13;
o fparagraph 2.7 o f the Consultant Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
Operational Costs which would be financed by the project would be procured using the&#13;
implementing agency's administrative procedures which were reviewed and found acceptable&#13;
to IDA.&#13;
&#13;
Part B Assessment of the agency's capacityto implementprocurement&#13;
&#13;
Procurement activities will be carried out by the P M U under the Ministry o f Mines. The&#13;
procurement in MOMwill initially be led by an international consultant and progressively&#13;
transferred to local staff. An assessment o f the capacity o f the ministry and the implementing&#13;
agency (Project Office) to implement the procurement actions under the project was carried&#13;
out in February 2006 by D. Kumar, Procurement Specialist, and Rahimulllah Wardak,&#13;
Procurement Analyst. The assessment reviewed the organizational structure and capacity o f&#13;
the MOM,largely because the P M U will be established as part o f the project itself. The P M U&#13;
will be responsible for day-to-day project management including procurement, financial&#13;
management, progress and fmancial reporting, staff appointment and management, and&#13;
project monitoring and evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
The Ministrycurrently procures items such as vehicles, generators, pumps, helmets, bearings,&#13;
ventilators, chemicals and drugs and weigh bridges using their own resources. They handle&#13;
about 20 to 30 procurement cases every year. The Deputy Ministers has delegated the&#13;
authority to approve procurements valued up to AF250,OOO (approximately US$ 5,000) and&#13;
the Minister o f Mines has delegated the authority to approve procurements valued up to&#13;
AF3,000,000 (US$60,000). For procurements o f complex nature and larger procurements,&#13;
they seek assistance from the Afghanistan Reconstruction and Development Services&#13;
Procurement Unit (ARDS-PU) which handles the procurement on the Ministry's behalf. At&#13;
present, ARDS-PU is handling procurement o f 147 items o f mining equipment, valued at&#13;
about US$ 4.7 million, financed by ADB. One official has attended a 15-day course on&#13;
ADB's procurement procedures and another official has taken a part-time course on World&#13;
Bank procedures.&#13;
&#13;
The Ministry has no experience in World Bank procurement procedures. The procurement&#13;
capacity within the Ministry for the project under consideration is weak and the procurement&#13;
&#13;
                                                42&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      risk is considered high. However, there is potential to develop capacity o f the Ministry&#13;
      officials through on-the-job training and guidance from ARDS-PU. It i s necessary to have a&#13;
      E&#13;
      capable and experienced Individual Procurement Consultant familiar with World Bank&#13;
      procedures inthe Ministry for the first 12 months, extended subsequently based on need. The&#13;
      Consultant will handle the procurement work and provide on-the-job training to the staff o f&#13;
      the Ministry.The following actionplanhas been agreed with the Ministry to mitigate the risk:&#13;
&#13;
        SI. No.              Action Plan                     Target             Responsibility&#13;
                  Selection o f an individual           June 30,2006     MOMwiththe helpof&#13;
                  Procurement Consultant to work                         ARDS-PU.&#13;
                  inthe Ministryfor the first 12                         7&#13;
                  months o f the project&#13;
                  On thejob training to the staff o f   Within 6 to 8    Procurement Consultant&#13;
                  the Ministry by the Procurement       months o f the&#13;
                   Consultant                           start o f the&#13;
                                                        project&#13;
                   Assistance from ARDS-PU              As andwhen&#13;
                                                        required&#13;
&#13;
      The overall procurement risk with the above measures is high.&#13;
&#13;
      PartC Procurement Plan&#13;
&#13;
      The Grant Recipient, at appraisal, developed a Procurement Plan for project implementation&#13;
      which provides the basis for the procurement methods. This planhas been agreedbetween the&#13;
      Grant Recipient and the Project Team on May 4, 2006 and is available at the offices o f the&#13;
      IDA in Kabul. I t will also be available in the Project's database and on the World Bank's&#13;
      external website. The Procurement Plan will be updated in agreement with the Project Team&#13;
       annually or as required to reflect the actual project implementation needs and improvements&#13;
       ininstitutionalcapacity.&#13;
&#13;
       PartD Frequencyof Procurement Supervision&#13;
&#13;
       Inaddition to the prior review supervision to be carried out fromWorldBank offices,&#13;
       the capacity assessment of the Implementing Agency has recommended two&#13;
       supervisions missions per year to visit the field to carry out post review of&#13;
       procurement actions.&#13;
&#13;
       Attachment 1&#13;
&#13;
       Details of the Procurement Arrangement involvingInternationalCompetition.&#13;
&#13;
       A        Goods andWorks andNon-ConsultingServices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1          2              3              4           5            6         7             8         9&#13;
Ref.  Contract       Estimated    Procurement      P-Q      Domestic     Review        Expected   Comments&#13;
No.  (Description)      Cost         Method                Preference    by IDA         Bid-&#13;
                                                             (yedno)   (Prior / Post)  Opening&#13;
                                                                                        Date&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 (b) ICB Contracts for works estimated to cost above US$500,000 equivalent per&#13;
                 contract, for goods above US$200,000 equivalent per contract and all Direct&#13;
                 contracting will be subject to prior review by IDA.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        43&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
          B       Consulting Services.&#13;
&#13;
                  (a) List of Consulting Assignments with short-list of international firms.&#13;
P-                                  2                            3                      5         6&#13;
Ref.No.     Iescription of Assignment                        Estimated             ieview     Expected&#13;
I---                                                         cost                  )y IDA     Proposal&#13;
                                                                         Method    Prior /    Submissi&#13;
&#13;
Contract 1  Mining &amp; Hydrocarbon Regulations                 F9,000,000  QCBS&#13;
              1   draft Mining &amp; Hydrocarbon regulations                                      30,2006&#13;
                  and amendments&#13;
            Yydrocarbon /Mining Cadastre&#13;
              1   Diagnostic &amp; design&#13;
              1   Cadastre implementation including&#13;
                  budget requirements, skills, operational&#13;
                  manual, andjob descriptions&#13;
f             Yydrocarbon/Mining Inspectorate&#13;
              1   Diagnostic &amp; design&#13;
              1   Draft Health &amp; Safety regulations&#13;
                  Inspectorateimplementation including&#13;
                  budget requirements, skills, operational&#13;
                  manual, andjob descriptions&#13;
Contract 2    YmallScale Mining /Extension Service Unit      $385,000     QCBS       Prior    Feb 30&#13;
              `ASM)                                                                           2007&#13;
                  Define a strategy, structure, and budget&#13;
                  for creation o fminerals section&#13;
              m   Createhmplementnew Minerals Section&#13;
              Environmental/Social Protection                $385,000     QCBS        Prior   Sept 30,&#13;
                  Define a strategy, structure, andbudget                                     2006&#13;
I-                for creation of minerals section&#13;
                  Draft environmental / social&#13;
                  administrative guidelines&#13;
                  CreatehmplementEnvironmental/Social&#13;
                  Protection Department&#13;
Contract 4    lmproving Internal Efficiencies                $1,300,000   QCBS        Prior   Oct 30,&#13;
                  Scopingfunctional review and staffing                                       2006&#13;
                  assessment / plans for all MOM&#13;
                  Assess Budget and Planning, Finance and&#13;
                  Accounting, Human Resources,&#13;
                  Information Technology capacitiesand&#13;
                  define a strategy for administrative&#13;
                  reform                                                                     I&#13;
                  Define structureand budgetrequirements,&#13;
I                 including job descriptions&#13;
                  Reform units&#13;
                  Implement new administrative/financial&#13;
                  management / HR, and IT systems&#13;
Contract 5    Sector Policy                                  $495,000     QCBS&#13;
                  Assess needs for a national sector policy&#13;
                  Draft national sector policy and assist&#13;
                  MOMinpassage/ implementation&#13;
              Private Sector Promotion and Development&#13;
              Office&#13;
                  Define a strategy, structure, andbudget&#13;
                  for creation of a private sector promotion&#13;
                  and business developmentoffice&#13;
                  Create / implement new office and&#13;
                  promotion plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            44&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
r&#13;
Contract 6    4fghan GeologicSurvey                         $1,848,000                      April 30,&#13;
              *   Technical assistanceto restoremineral                                     2007&#13;
                  collection&#13;
                  Establishpublic information center&#13;
                  Training in GIS and electronic data&#13;
                  mapping systems&#13;
                  Capacity building in geologic mapping,&#13;
                  mineral resourceassessment,district&#13;
                  studies&#13;
              Conduct strategic sector studies              $1,358,000                      March 30,&#13;
                  Develop sub-sector strategiesand develop                                  2007&#13;
                  an understandingof comparative&#13;
                  advantages, at aregional level, for SOEs&#13;
                  Conduct an inventory of extractive&#13;
                  industry SOEs, includingcurrent&#13;
                                                                         7&#13;
                  activities and estimatesof underlying&#13;
                  resources&#13;
              Auditors                                      $200,000                  Prior July 1,&#13;
                                                                                            2006&#13;
&#13;
                   (b) Consultancy services estimated to cost above US$ 200,000 or equivalents per&#13;
                   contract and all Single Source selection o f consultants (firms) and individual for&#13;
                   assignments will be subject to prior review by the IDA.&#13;
&#13;
                   (c) Short lists composed entirely of nationalconsultants: Short lists o f consultants&#13;
                   for services estimated to cost less than US$50,000 equivalent per contract, may be&#13;
                   composed entirely o f national consultants in accordance with the provisions o f&#13;
                   paragraph 2.7 o f the Consultant Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          ProcurementPlan&#13;
&#13;
          A        General&#13;
&#13;
           A1      Projectinformation:&#13;
           Country                   Afghanistan&#13;
           Borrower                  Islamic Republic o f Afghanistan&#13;
           Project Name      Sustainable Development o f Natural Resources Project&#13;
           Loadcredit No.&#13;
           Project Implementing Agency (PIA): Ministry o f Mines&#13;
&#13;
           A2      IDA'SapprovalDateof the procurementPlan:April 2006&#13;
&#13;
           A3      Date of GeneralProcurementNotice: TBD&#13;
&#13;
           A4      Periodcoveredby this procurement plan: 2 years&#13;
&#13;
           B        Goods andWorks and non-consultingservices.&#13;
&#13;
           B1       Prior Review Threshold:Procurement Decisions subject to Prior Review by IDA as&#13;
           stated inAppendix 1to the Guidelines for Procurement:&#13;
                             ProcurementMethod             I Prior Review Threshold 6) I   Comments    1&#13;
             1.     Goods                                    200,000 Equivalent or more&#13;
             2.     Works                                    500,000 Equivalent or more&#13;
             3.     Direct contracting (goods and works)     All&#13;
&#13;
           B2       Referenceto (if any) ProjectOperationaYProcurementManual: NONE.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          45&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       B3       Any Other Special Procurement Arrangements: [including advance procurement&#13;
       and retroactive financing, if applicable] : NONE.&#13;
&#13;
       B4       Procurement Packageswith Methods and Time Schedule&#13;
&#13;
                [List the Packages which require IDA'S prior review first and then the other&#13;
-&#13;
-1         -    pac&#13;
                                          4                            h           7         8          9&#13;
Ref.   Contract       Estimated Procurement           Pre-        Domestic    Review by Expected Comments&#13;
No.  (Description)      cost          Method       qualification Preference      IDA       Bid-&#13;
                        (US$)                       (yeslno)        (yeslno)   (Prior I  Opening&#13;
                                                                                Post)      Date&#13;
    Vehicles            200,000         NCB            No             No         Prior   Nov 06&#13;
     Vehicles           200,000         NCB            No             No         Prior   Apr 07&#13;
     Vehicles           400,000         ICB            No             No         Prior   JulO8&#13;
     Office             250,000         NCB            No             No         Post    Nov 06&#13;
     renovation&#13;
     Inspection          100,000      Shopping         No             No         Prior   Jun 07&#13;
     equipment&#13;
     Geological          100,000      Shopping         No             No         Prior   Jun 07&#13;
     equipment&#13;
     Office              150,000        NCB,           No             No          Post   Througho   Multiple&#13;
     equipment                        shopping                                           ut project packages&#13;
8    Software, and     1,140,000        NCB,           No             No          Post   Througho   Multiple&#13;
     publications                     shopping                                           ut project packages.&#13;
     [value for                                                                                     Publication&#13;
     NCB goods                                                                                      s include&#13;
     shall be below                                                                                 both&#13;
     $200,000 per                                                                                   publication&#13;
     contract, and                                                                                  by MOMof&#13;
     that for                                                                                       digital and&#13;
     shopping                                                                                       printed&#13;
     shall be below                                                                                 materials&#13;
     $100,000 per                                                                                   for&#13;
     contract]                                                                                      distribution&#13;
                                                                                                    to potential&#13;
                                                                                                    investors&#13;
                                                                                                    and&#13;
                                                                                                    purchase&#13;
                                                                                                    of books&#13;
                                                                                                    and&#13;
                                                                                                    journals in&#13;
                                                                                                    fiscal and&#13;
                                                                                                    technical&#13;
                                                                                                    areas.&#13;
&#13;
       C         Selectionof Consultants&#13;
&#13;
        C1       Prior Review Threshold: Selection decisions subject to Prior Review by IDA as&#13;
        stated inAppendix 1 to the Guidelines Selection and Employment o f Consultants:&#13;
&#13;
                           Selection Method              I    Prior Review Threshold   I Comments      1&#13;
                                                                      (US$)&#13;
          1.    Competitive Methods (Firms)               More than 200,000 Equivalent&#13;
          2.    Individual Consultant                     More than 50,000 Equivalent&#13;
          3.     Single Source (Firms)                    All&#13;
          4.     Single Source (Individual)               All&#13;
&#13;
        C2       Short list comprising entirely of national consultants:Short list o f consultants for&#13;
        services, estimated to cost less than US$50,000 equivalent per contract, may comprise&#13;
&#13;
                                                         46&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        entirely of national consultants in accordance with the provisions o f paragraph 2.7 o f the&#13;
        Consultant Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
        C3      Any Other Special Selection Arrangements: [including advance procurement and&#13;
        retroactive financing, if applicable]&#13;
&#13;
        C4       Consultancy Assignments with SelectionMethods and Time Schedule&#13;
&#13;
    1                     2                                A           5&#13;
tef. No.    Descriptionof Assignment       Estimated   selection   teview      Expected       Comments&#13;
                                           cost (US$)  rlethod     'y IDA      Proposals&#13;
                                                                   Prior I     Submission&#13;
                                                                   'ost)&#13;
:ontract    Mining &amp; Hydrocarbon           %9,000,000   QCBS         Prior&#13;
            Regulations&#13;
                draft Mining&amp;&#13;
                Hydrocarbon&#13;
                regulations and&#13;
                 amendments&#13;
            Hydrocarbon /Mining&#13;
            Cadastre&#13;
                 Diagnostic &amp; design&#13;
                 Cadastre&#13;
                 implementation&#13;
                 including budget&#13;
                 requirements, skills,&#13;
                 operational manual, and&#13;
                 job descriptions&#13;
            Hydrocarbon /Mining&#13;
            Inspectorate&#13;
                 Diagnostic &amp; design&#13;
                 Draft Health &amp; Safety&#13;
                 regulations&#13;
                 Inspectorate&#13;
                 implementation&#13;
                 including budget&#13;
                 requirements, skills,&#13;
                  operational manual, and&#13;
                 job descriptions&#13;
Contract    Small Scale Mining /           $385,000      QCBS         Prior    Feb 30 2007&#13;
2           Extension Service Unit&#13;
             (ASM)&#13;
                  Define a strategy,&#13;
                  structure, and budget&#13;
                  for creation of minerals&#13;
                  section&#13;
                  Createhmplement new&#13;
                  Minerals Section&#13;
Contract     Environmental/Social          $385,000      QCBS         Prior     Sept 30,2006&#13;
3            Protection&#13;
                  Define a strategy,&#13;
                  structure, and budget&#13;
                  for creation of minerals&#13;
                  section&#13;
                  Draft environmental /&#13;
                  social administrative&#13;
                  guidelines&#13;
                  Createiimplement&#13;
                  Environmental/Social&#13;
                  Protection Department&#13;
Contract     Improving Internal            $1,300,000    QCBS          Prior    Oct 30,2006&#13;
&#13;
                                                      47&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   1                                          1        4          5           6           7&#13;
Ref.No.  Descriptionof Assignment      Estimated    selection Zeview    Expected       Tomments&#13;
                                        cost (US$)  Method    )y IDA    Proposals&#13;
                                                              Prior I   Submission&#13;
                                                              'ost)     Date&#13;
1        Efficiencies&#13;
             Scopingfunctional&#13;
             review and staffing&#13;
             assessment / plans for&#13;
             all MOM&#13;
             Assess Budget and&#13;
              Planning, Finance and&#13;
              Accounting, Human&#13;
              Resources, Information&#13;
             Technology capacities&#13;
              and define a strategy for&#13;
              administrative reform&#13;
              Define structure and&#13;
              budget requirements,&#13;
              including job&#13;
              descriptions&#13;
              Reform units&#13;
              Implement new&#13;
              administrative/financial&#13;
              management/ HR, and&#13;
              IT systems&#13;
Contract Sector Policy                  $495,000     QCBS        Prior   Dec 21,2006&#13;
5             Assess needs for a&#13;
              national sector policy&#13;
              Draft national sector&#13;
              policy and assist MOM&#13;
              inpassage/&#13;
              implementation&#13;
         Private Sector Promotion&#13;
         and Development Office&#13;
              Define astrategy,&#13;
              structure, and budget&#13;
              for creationof a private&#13;
               sector promotion and&#13;
               business development&#13;
               office&#13;
               Create / implement new&#13;
               office and promotion&#13;
               plan&#13;
Contract Senior Industry Advisors       $972,000      QCBS        Prior  June 30,2006&#13;
6              Provide advice on&#13;
               MOMinvestor&#13;
               discussions&#13;
Contract Afghan Geologic Survey         1,848,000     QCBS        Prior  April 30, 2007&#13;
7              Technical assistanceto&#13;
               restoremineral&#13;
               collection&#13;
               Establishpublic&#13;
               information center&#13;
               Training in GIS and&#13;
               electronic data mapping&#13;
               systems&#13;
               Capacity building in&#13;
               geologic mapping,&#13;
               mineral resource&#13;
               assessment, district&#13;
               studies&#13;
&#13;
                                                   48&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   1                                                    A                        6            I&#13;
Ref. No. Descriptionof Assignment      Estimated    Selection  Review     Expected        Comments&#13;
                                       cost (US%)   Method     iy IDA     Proposals&#13;
                                                               :Prior/    Submission&#13;
                                                               Post)      Date&#13;
Contract Conduct strategic sectoral    $1,358,000   QCBS       ?rior      March 30,&#13;
8        studies                                                          2007&#13;
              Develop sub-sector&#13;
              strategies and develop&#13;
              an understandingof&#13;
              comparative&#13;
              advantages, at a&#13;
              regional level, for&#13;
              SOEs&#13;
              Conduct an inventory&#13;
              of extractive industry&#13;
              SOEs, includingcurrent&#13;
              activities and estimates&#13;
              of underlying resources&#13;
Contract Auditors                      $200,000        LCS         Prior  July 1, 2006&#13;
9&#13;
     10  Interim Project Preparation   $99,500          IC         Prior   Jan 2006       Hired under&#13;
         Specialist                                                                       PPF&#13;
     11  InterimProcurement            136,000          IC         Prior   Jan 2006       Hired under&#13;
         Specialist                                                                       PPF&#13;
     12  Interim                       70,000           IC         Prior   Jan 2006       Hired under&#13;
         EnvironmentaliSocial                                                             PPF&#13;
          Specialist&#13;
     13   International Director PMU   $8 10,000        IC         Prior   July 2006&#13;
          (4 years)&#13;
     14   Local Director PMU (5        $150,000         IC         Prior   Oct 2006&#13;
          years)&#13;
     15   Procurement Specialist (4    $570,000         IC         Prior   Jan 2007&#13;
          years)&#13;
     16   Accounting / Financial       $427,500         IC         Prior   July 2006&#13;
          ManagementSpecialist (3&#13;
          years)&#13;
     17   EITII Advisory Board         $345,000         IC        Prior    Dec 2006&#13;
          Secretariat(2 years)&#13;
     18   Local Staff PMU              $320,000          IC       Prior    Jan 2007&#13;
          Management(4 years)&#13;
     19   Interpreter (2 years)        20,000            IC        Pnst    Sept 2006&#13;
     20   Interpreter (2 years)        20.000            IC        Post    Dec 2006&#13;
     21   Translator (for documents,2                    IC        Post    Oct 2006&#13;
          years)&#13;
     22   Translator (for documents, 2 40,000            IC        Post    June 2007&#13;
          years)&#13;
&#13;
        D      Implementing Agency Capacity BuildingActivities with Time Schedule&#13;
&#13;
        D1     In this section the agreed Capacity BuildingActivities (some items could be from&#13;
        CPARrecommendation)are listedwith time schedule.NOTAPPLICABLE.&#13;
&#13;
            1No.          I&#13;
                          IExpectedoutcome/Activity I Estimated   IEstimated   IStart Date  I&#13;
                           Description               Icost        1Duration    I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   49&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
D2      Agreed Proceduresfor NationalCompetitive Bidding&#13;
        Inorder to ensure economy, efficiency, transparency and broad consistency with the&#13;
provisions of Section Iofthe Procurement Guidelines,the following criteria shall be followed&#13;
inprocurementunderNationalCompetitiveBiddingprocedures:&#13;
&#13;
               Standard bidding documents approved by the World Bank Group shall be&#13;
               used.&#13;
&#13;
               Invitations to bid shall be advertised in at least one (1) widely circulated&#13;
               national daily newspaper and bidding documents shall be made available to&#13;
               prospective bidders, at least twenty eight (28) days prior to the deadline for&#13;
               the submission ofbids.&#13;
&#13;
               Bids shall not be invited on the basis ofpercentage premium or discount over&#13;
               the estimated cost.&#13;
&#13;
               Bidding documents shall be made available, by mail or inperson, to all who&#13;
               are willing to pay the required fee.&#13;
&#13;
               Foreignbidders shall not beprecludedfrom bidding.&#13;
&#13;
                Qualification criteria (in case pre-qualifications were not carried out) shall be&#13;
                stated on the bidding documents, and if a registration process is required, a&#13;
                foreign firm determined to be the lowest evaluated bidder shall be given&#13;
                reasonable opportunity ofregistering, without any hindrance.&#13;
&#13;
                Bidders may deliver bids, at their option, either in person or by courier&#13;
                service or by mail.&#13;
&#13;
                All bidders shall provide bid security as indicated in the bidding documents.&#13;
                A bidder's bid security shall apply only to a specific bid.&#13;
&#13;
                Bids shall be opened in public in one place preferably immediately, but no&#13;
                later than one hour, after the deadlinefor submissionofbids.&#13;
&#13;
                Evaluation of bids shall be made in strict adherence to the criteria disclosed&#13;
                inthe bidding documents, ina format, andwithin the specifiedperiod, agreed&#13;
                with the Association.&#13;
&#13;
                Bids shall not be rejectedmerelyon the basis of a comparisonwith an official&#13;
                estimate without the prior concurrence ofthe IDA.&#13;
&#13;
                Split award or lottery in award of contracts shall not be carried out. When&#13;
                two (2) or morebidders quote the same price, an investigation shall be made&#13;
                to determine any evidence of collusion, following which: (A) if collusion is&#13;
                determined, theparties involved shall be disqualified and the award shall then&#13;
                be made to the next lowest evaluated and qualified bidder; and (B) if no&#13;
                evidence of collusion can be confirmed, then fresh bids shall be invited after&#13;
                receiving the concurrence of the IDA;&#13;
&#13;
                Contracts shall be awarded to the lowest evaluated bidders within the initial&#13;
                period of bid validity so that extensions are not necessary. Extension of bid&#13;
                validity may be sought only under exceptionalcircumstances.&#13;
&#13;
                Extension of bid validity shall not be allowed without the prior concurrence&#13;
                of the IDA (A) for the first request for extension if it is longer than eight (8)&#13;
                weeks, and (B) for all subsequent requests for extensions irrespective of the&#13;
                period.&#13;
&#13;
                                                50&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(xv)   Negotiations shall not be allowed with the lowest evaluated or any other&#13;
       bidders.&#13;
&#13;
(xvi)  Re-bidding shall not be carried out without the IDA'Sprior concurrence; and&#13;
&#13;
(xvii) All contractors or suppliers shallprovide performance security as indicated in&#13;
       the contract documents. A contractor's or a supplier's performance security&#13;
       shall apply to a specific contract under which it was furnished.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       51&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX 6: FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT ANNEX OF SUSTAINABLE&#13;
DEVELOPMENT OFNATURAL RESOURCESPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CountryIssues&#13;
&#13;
IDA has gained substantial experience and understanding o f the financial management (FM)&#13;
environment in Afghanistan through the large number o f projects under implementation over&#13;
the past four years. The Public Administration Capacity Building (PACB) project is the&#13;
primary instrument to continue and enhance the fiduciary measures put in place during the&#13;
past years to ensure transparency and accountability for the funding provided by IDA and&#13;
other donors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A PFM performance rating system using 28 high-level indicators developed by the Public&#13;
Expenditure and Financial Accountability (PEFA) multi-agency partnership program was&#13;
applied in Afghanistan in June 2005. The system is structured around six core dimensions o f&#13;
P F M performance (budget credibility; comprehensiveness and transparency; policy-based&#13;
budgeting; predictability and control in budget execution; accounting, recording, and&#13;
reporting; and external scrutiny and audit). This has been accomplished with very high levels&#13;
o f support from international firms. This assistance will continue to be needed inthe medium&#13;
term if these ratings are to be maintained. There is also much room for improvement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In spite o f undeniable gains made in reconstruction since the end o f 2001, the challenges&#13;
facing Afghanistan remain immense, not least because o f the tenuous security situation in the&#13;
region and continued prevalence o f a large illegal and illicit economy. The policy framework&#13;
benchmarks have not yet been costed and various priorities are funded through the annual&#13;
budgeting process. The rising costs o f the security sector constitute a major constraint on&#13;
attainment o f fiscal sustainability. The National Assembly will play an increasingly active&#13;
role with regard to executive oversight. The national strategy has created highexpectations o f&#13;
the executive which could prove to be quite difficult to meet.&#13;
&#13;
The public sector, in spite o f considerable efforts to reform its core functions, remains&#13;
 extremely weak outside o f Kabul. The lack o f qualified staff in the civil service and the&#13;
 absence o f qualified counterparts in the government after 30 years o f war and conflicts i s a&#13;
binding constraint. Delays in reforming the pay structure and grading o f civil servants have&#13;
 severely crippled the public administration o f the country. Domestic revenues lag behind&#13;
 expenditures by a factor o f ten to one. Large-scale corruption could emerge to undermine the&#13;
 government's efforts to enhance aid flows through national accounts. Capacities to track&#13;
 expenditures and monitor expenditure outcomes have improved, but they need rapid and&#13;
 substantial strengthening if progress toward the attainment o f national development targets is&#13;
 to be monitored. Currently, 75 percent o f external revenues bypass government appropriation&#13;
 systems.&#13;
&#13;
 An IDA project is currently financing a Financial Management Advisor to assist the Ministry&#13;
 o f Finance, an Audit Advisor to assist the Control and Audit Office, and a Procurement&#13;
 Advisor to assist in Procurement-related activities. Also an Internal Audit function is being&#13;
 developed with IDA financing. USAID, and earlier the IndianAid Assistance Programme, are&#13;
 also financing a team o f consultants and advisors to assist the D a Afghanistan Bank in local&#13;
 as well as foreign currency operations. The activities carried out under the existing Public&#13;
 Administration projects have helped the Government to ensure that appropriate fiduciary&#13;
 standards are maintained for public expenditures, including those supported by IDA and the&#13;
 donor community.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                52&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Progress has been slower than expected in shifting from operations support provided by the&#13;
Advisors to capacity development and knowledge transfer to the civil servants. Given this&#13;
situation, the use o f the Advisors is expected to continue to be required for the medium term.&#13;
Challenges still remain in attaining the agreed-upon fiduciary standards and also to further&#13;
enhance them. In the interim, the regulatory environment in Afghanistan has advanced&#13;
significantly. Unfortunately, even the mastery o f basic skills in the early environment does&#13;
not fully qualify the civil servants to work effectively inthe new emerging environment.&#13;
&#13;
Country systems that are in place for externally-aided projects will be used for all financial&#13;
management matters o f the project.&#13;
&#13;
RiskAssessment and Mitigation&#13;
&#13;
The table below identifies the key risks that the project may face and indicates how these risks&#13;
are to be addressed.&#13;
&#13;
 Pisk                             Risk      Risk Mitigation Measures&#13;
                                 Rating&#13;
 [nherentRisk                                                                    Residual risk&#13;
 zountry Inherent Risk              M       Source P F M study&#13;
                                                     -                           M&#13;
 ?roject Financial                  H       Ensure reasonableness o f advance    M&#13;
 Management Risk                            inthe designated account;&#13;
                                            maximize direct payments to&#13;
                                            consultants; all procurement&#13;
                                            through Procurement Advisor.&#13;
                                            Oversight by SDU with the&#13;
                                            support o f FMAdvisor to ensure&#13;
                                            timely acquittal o f cash advances&#13;
                                            under the project.&#13;
 Perceived Corruption                H       Government commitment,              S&#13;
                                             internal controls andnew internal&#13;
                                             audit unitwill all help reduce the&#13;
                                             highlevelofperceived&#13;
                                             corruption.&#13;
       Overall Inherent Risk          S                                          S&#13;
 ControlRisk&#13;
 1. Weak Implementing                H       Extremely weak FMcapacity in        S&#13;
 Entity                                      MOMwillbe supportedbya&#13;
                                             qualified FMconsultants' team&#13;
                                             hiredunder PPF to assess FM&#13;
                                             capacity and develop strategy for&#13;
                                             improvements. A financial&#13;
                                             management system (FMS) will&#13;
                                             be inplace inthe P M Ubefore&#13;
                                             IDA disbursements.&#13;
  2. FundsFlow                       M       Follows flow established in         M&#13;
                                             previous projects.&#13;
  3. Budgeting                        S       FMS and Head o f Development        M&#13;
                                              Budget will be responsible for&#13;
                                              this function.&#13;
  4. Accounting Policies and          M       Will follow international           M&#13;
  Procedures                                  standards with support from FM&#13;
                                                                ..&#13;
                                              Advisor.&#13;
  5. Internal Audit                   S       Internal audit department will      S&#13;
                                              review project internal control&#13;
                                              systems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  53&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16. External Audit                    S    1 Will be audited by CAO with            M&#13;
                                              support from Audit Advisor.&#13;
 7. Reporting and                     S       Strengthening the Special             S&#13;
 Monitoring                                   Disbursement Unit (SDU) is a&#13;
                                             priority under the new FM&#13;
                                              Advisor contract, to provide&#13;
                                              information that will comply with&#13;
                                              agreed format o f interim&#13;
                                              unaudited financial reports.&#13;
 OverallControlRisk                   S                                             S&#13;
 DetectionRisk                        L       Accounting/Recording/oversight        L&#13;
                                              by SDU-MOF o f all&#13;
                                           I  advances/M-16 supported by FM&#13;
                                              Advisor.&#13;
 Risk rating: H=high risk; S=substantial risk; M=modest risk; L-low risk&#13;
                                                                                                    I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 StrengthsandWeaknesses&#13;
&#13;
 Strengths&#13;
&#13;
 The main strength i s the Government's commitment to the PACB project's approach to&#13;
 ensure that capacity is inplace to strengthen accountability and transparency in its operations.&#13;
 PACB helps to strengthen the financial management in Treasury operations, internal audit,&#13;
 public procurement, and external audit under the Auditor General. This helps to provide&#13;
 assurance to IDA and other donors that the current measures designed to ensure appropriate&#13;
 utilization o f funds will not be circumvented.&#13;
&#13;
 A PMUwill be established to implement the project, with staffing to include a FMSpecialist.&#13;
 MOMhas initiated reforms ofthe ministry's administrative and financial functions. A Project&#13;
 Preparation Facility (PPF) has been approved which includes provision to put inplace a team&#13;
 o f four consultants (1 international consultant and 3 local consultants) to assess MOM'S&#13;
 financial management requirements and develop a strategy for improvement. Administration&#13;
 Department staff will be provided on-the-job training to process expenditures under the&#13;
 project in order to mainstream project financial management within MOM.&#13;
&#13;
 Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
 The main weakness in this project, as in many others in Afghanistan, is the ability to attract&#13;
 suitably qualified and experienced counterpart staff. A lack o f capacity inthe civil service has&#13;
 led to continued reliance on international firms to perform core government functions.&#13;
&#13;
 MOMhas not yet been involved in the management o f foreign grants thus the ministry's&#13;
 systems and staff lack the capacity to deal effectively with donor agencies. However, to&#13;
 address this weakness, MOMstaff will be involved at multiple levels infinancial management&#13;
 o f the project working closely with the FM consultants under PPF and with the FMS in the&#13;
 P M U.&#13;
&#13;
 ImplementingEntity&#13;
&#13;
 MOMis the implementing agency for this project. FMcapacity inMOMisextremely weak. It&#13;
  i s envisioned that capacity will be built first by way o f hiring a team o f consultants to assess&#13;
 FMcapacity and to prepare strategy for improvement. Second, an FMSwillbe inplace before&#13;
  the IDA project starts disbursements. Third, local counterpart staff will be recruited. Training&#13;
 will be imparted to existing MOMstaff in the Planning and Finance units o f the&#13;
 Administration Department for effective implementation o f the project. In addition to the&#13;
  Director o f Planning and Policy, the Vice President and Head o f Development Budget within&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   54&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the Planning and Policy unit will work closely with the FMSpecialist to facilitate day-to-day&#13;
FMoperations o fthe project, preparation ofM-16 forms, andoverall contract management.&#13;
&#13;
Budgeting&#13;
&#13;
Because there is limited capacity inmanaging external budget within MOM,the FMteam will&#13;
be responsible for ensuring that project expenditures envisaged to be expended ina fiscal year&#13;
are captured in the Governmental Development budget o f that fiscal year. It is to be ensured&#13;
that the project is included in the budget decree. However, in case it has not been included,&#13;
MOMmustobtain approval fromthe presidential office to be attachedto D1forms at the time&#13;
of requesting annual allotments for contracts under development project to avoid delays when&#13;
payments are processed.&#13;
&#13;
FundsFlow&#13;
&#13;
The standard mechanism o f flow o f finds employed in the other investment projects in&#13;
Afghanistan will be followed. Project funds will be deposited ina single Designated Account&#13;
(DA) to be opened and maintained at the Da Afghanistan Bank (DAB) or in a local&#13;
commercial bank. Capacity in terms o f delivery o f service and charges for the services will&#13;
have to be assessed by the Government (MOF) and arrangements formalized before moving&#13;
 from the existing practice o f placing this account in D a Afghanistan Bank (DAB).The DA, in&#13;
keeping with current practices for other projects in Afghanistan, will be operated by the&#13;
 Special Disbursement Unit (SDU) in the Treasury Department o f Ministry o f Finance.&#13;
 Requests for payments out o f DA finds will be made to the SDU by MOMand authorized by&#13;
 officials o f M O M .&#13;
&#13;
 In addition to payments out o f DA finds, MOMmay also request the SDU to make direct&#13;
 payments to third parties or request that that IDA issue special commitments for contracts&#13;
 covered by letters o f credit. Suchrequests will follow the World Bank Groupprocedures.&#13;
&#13;
 RetroactiveFinancing&#13;
&#13;
 No retroactive financing i s envisaged for this project.&#13;
&#13;
 Project Preparation Facility. An advance in the amount not exceeding US$1,550,000 has&#13;
 been provided to the Recipient for the preparation o f the project. The amount o f the Advance&#13;
 withdrawn, and the service charge incurred to the date o f repayment, shall be refinanced out&#13;
 of the Grant as soon as the Financing Agreement shall have become effective.&#13;
&#13;
  Accounting Policiesand Procedures.&#13;
&#13;
  Under the PPF, the FM consultant team will develop FM procedures including accounting&#13;
  policies and systems to be in place for effective project implementation. The Financial&#13;
  Management Specialist within the P M U will facilitate implementation o f suggestions by the&#13;
  team along with the local counterparts in MOM.The FMS will also: i)supervise preparation&#13;
  of supporting documents for expenditures, and payment orders (Form M16), ii)obtain&#13;
  approval for M-16 forms by the Minister/Deputy Minister depending on the payment amount,&#13;
  and iii)submit these forms to the Treasury Department in MOF which in turn will issue a&#13;
  check payable to the cash trustee by DAB after verification o f supporting documents and&#13;
  approvals on the form.&#13;
&#13;
  Currently, all records o f payments are maintained manually in files. It will be FMS'&#13;
  responsibility to establish accounting and reporting systems in the Planning unit and train&#13;
  existing staff with the support o f local counterpart to maintain financial data for the project. A&#13;
  FinancialManagementManualoutliningguidelinesand proceduresfor projectfinancial&#13;
  managementwill be developed by the FMS and the localstaff at MOM.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  55&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The FMS will establish project financial management in accordance with standard Afghan&#13;
government policies and procedures, including use o f the Chart o f Accounts developed by the&#13;
Financial Management Advisor to record project expenditures. The use o f these procedures&#13;
will enable adequate recording and reporting o f the project expenditures. Overall project&#13;
accounts will be maintained centrally in S D U which will be ultimately responsible for&#13;
accounting for all expenditures and receipts in the Government's accounting system.&#13;
Reconciliation o f project expenditure with M o F records will be carried out by Finance along&#13;
with Planning. This will be supported by the FMS who will ensure that monthly and yearly&#13;
reconciliation for project expenditures are carried out by MOMwith Treasury-MOF.&#13;
&#13;
The Financial Management Specialist and the local counterpart staff in Planning will be&#13;
responsible for coordinating FM activities o f the project with the SDU. Project accounts will&#13;
be consolidated centrally in the Ministry o f Finance, through the Special Disbursement Unit&#13;
in the Treasury supported by Financial Management Advisor. Consolidated Project Financial&#13;
Statements will be prepared for all sources anduses o fproject funds.&#13;
&#13;
Internal Audit&#13;
&#13;
The project financial management systems will be subject to review by the newly established&#13;
internal audit directorate o f the MOF, according to programs to be determined by the Director&#13;
o f Internal Audit. A risk-based approach will be applied to review project internal controls&#13;
and systems.&#13;
&#13;
ExternalAudit&#13;
&#13;
The accounts o f the project will be audited by the Auditor General, with the support o f the&#13;
Audit Advisor with terms o f reference satisfactory to the Association. The audit o f the project&#13;
accounts will include an assessment o f the: (a) adequacy of the accounting and internal&#13;
control systems; (b) ability to maintain adequate documentation for transactions; and (c)&#13;
eligibility o f incurred expenditures for Association financing. The audited annual project&#13;
financial statements will be submittedwithin 6 months o f the close o f fiscal year. All agencies&#13;
involved in implementation and holding records o f expenditures would need to retain these&#13;
records as per the IDA retentionpolicy.&#13;
&#13;
The following audit reports will be monitored in the Audit Reports Compliance System&#13;
(ARCS):&#13;
&#13;
~    ResponsibleAgency                      Audit                  Auditors            Date&#13;
 MOF, supported by Special SOE, Project Accounts and           Auditor General       Sep 22&#13;
      Disbursement Unit          Designated Account&#13;
&#13;
Reportingand Monitoring&#13;
&#13;
Interim unaudited fmancial reports will be used for project monitoring and supervision. Based&#13;
on the FMarrangements o f this project interim unaudited financial reports will be preparedby&#13;
the FMS with the help o f local counterparts inPlanning.These reports will be produced based&#13;
on records kept on Excel spread sheets or a simple data base.&#13;
&#13;
Quarterly interimunaudited financial reports will be produced showing: (i)      sources and uses&#13;
o f funds by disbursement category and project component; (ii)physical progress; and (iii)&#13;
 status o f procurement activities. The Ministry o f Mines will forward the relevant details to&#13;
DBER for consolidation, if any, with a copy to IDA within 45 days of the end o f the quarter.&#13;
The government andIDA have already agreed on aproforma format for all IDAprojects, and&#13;
the same format will be applicable for this project.&#13;
&#13;
Annual project accounts will be consolidated centrally in the Ministry o f Finance; in&#13;
particular, the Treasury Department, supported by the Financial Management Advisor, and&#13;
&#13;
                                                56&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
consolidated project financial statements will be prepared for all sources and uses o f project&#13;
funds.&#13;
&#13;
DisbursementArrangements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Expenditure Category                                      Amount              Financing&#13;
                                                                                            Percentage&#13;
               Consultancy services, goods,&#13;
               works, training, and operating                       US$28,450,000                 100&#13;
               costs                                                SDR 19,500,000&#13;
               Refund o f project preparation                        US$1,550,000        Amount payable&#13;
               advance                                              SDR 1,100,000        pursuantto Section&#13;
                                                                                         2.07 o f the General&#13;
                                                                                         Conditions&#13;
              ITotal                                                   %30.000.000                100&#13;
&#13;
Table A6-1 shows the allocation o f IDA proceeds. The table includes only 2 categories: (1) A&#13;
single category for "consultancy services, goods, works, training and operating costsg and (2)&#13;
Refind o f the PPF. The single category has been selected to facilitate preparation o f&#13;
disbursement applications and record-keeping. The project will be disbursed over a period o f&#13;
4 years. The closing date o f the project will be July 31, 2011, with a final disbursement&#13;
deadline four months after the closing date. During this additional 4-month period, project-&#13;
related expenditures incurred prior to the closing date are eligible for disbursement.&#13;
Disbursement estimates o f the IDA proceeds over the five year project are presented inTable&#13;
B3 in Schedule B.&#13;
&#13;
Disbursements procedures set out in the World Bank Group's "Disbursement Handbook for&#13;
World Bank Borrowers" (October 2005) are applicable to this project.&#13;
&#13;
DesignatedAccount&#13;
 The single designated account (DA) will be opened at D a Afghanistan Bank or in a local&#13;
 commercial bank in US dollars for a maximum amount o f US$2.5 million representing 3&#13;
 months o f estimated expenditures. The SDU in M o F will manage advances to this account&#13;
 and submit expenditure reporting on a monthly basis.&#13;
&#13;
 As authorized by Treasury and only where no other mechanism can be arranged and for&#13;
 amounts o f less than US$5000, cash advances may be taken from the DA and held and&#13;
 managed by MOM.This agency's controls as related to holding and accounting for cash,&#13;
 properly recording expenditures, and preparing statements o f expenditures, will need to be&#13;
 satisfactorily assessedbefore the Ministryo f Finance will release any cash advances to MOM.&#13;
 New cash advances will be made only when all other prior cash advances have been justified&#13;
 through submission o f statements o f expenditures to the SDU.&#13;
&#13;
 Expenditure reporting on payments made through the DA will be replenished on a monthly&#13;
 basis. Requests for advances may be made as often as needed.&#13;
&#13;
 DirectPayments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 9  "Operating   Costs'' means the Project-related incremental expenses incurred on account o f Project&#13;
 implementation support and management including the rental o f office space; the operation, maintenance, rental&#13;
 and insurance of vehicles; fuel; communications supplies and charges; advertisements; books and periodicals;&#13;
 office administration and maintenance costs; bank transaction charges; utility charges; domestic travel and per&#13;
 diem but excluding salaries o f officials and staff o f the Recipient's civil service.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             57&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Direct payments from IDA to vendors will be made for amounts exceeding 20%&#13;
(US$500,000) o f the advance inthe DA.All such payments require records (e.g.,invoices, fee&#13;
statements, consultants' statement of reimbursable expenses, and other records) that may be&#13;
identified by IDA as necessary to support disbursement.&#13;
&#13;
Preparationof Withdrawal Applications&#13;
The SDU will review quality o f withdrawal applications and ensure conformity to Treasury&#13;
procedures, and then obtain required signatures. Selected MOMfinance staff will become&#13;
registered users o f Client Connection and take an active role inmanaging disbursements.&#13;
&#13;
Summary Reports&#13;
Summary reports in the form o f Statements o f Expenditure will be used for expenditures on&#13;
contracts that are less than US$20,000.&#13;
&#13;
Records&#13;
All expenditures on contracts above US$20,000 will require submission o f records.&#13;
&#13;
Action Plan&#13;
&#13;
  Action                                            ResponsiblePerson          Target Date&#13;
                                                                                                     ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Appoint Financial Management Specialist in        MOM                        Before&#13;
  the P M U                                                                    disbursements&#13;
  FMconsultant team inplace                         MOM                        After PPF&#13;
                                                                               effectiveness&#13;
  Develop FMmanual and system                       FMS-MOM                    Before&#13;
                                                                               disbursements&#13;
&#13;
              .&#13;
Financial Management Covenants&#13;
&#13;
                 IRA shall submit audit financial statements within six months o f the end o f&#13;
                 each fiscal year. The audit report will cover the project financial statements,&#13;
              .  the project DA and statements o f expenditures, in accordance with terms o f&#13;
                 reference to be agreed with IDA.&#13;
                 Interim unaudited financial reports will be submitted o n a quarterly basis.&#13;
&#13;
Supervision Plan&#13;
&#13;
IRA shall submit audit financial statements within six months o f the end o f each fiscal year,&#13;
The audit report will cover the project financial statements, the project DA and Statements o f&#13;
Expenditures, inaccordance with terms of reference to be agreed with IDA.Interim unaudited&#13;
financial reports will be submitted on a quarterly basis.&#13;
&#13;
Supervision Plan&#13;
&#13;
During project implementation, IDA will supervise the project's financial management&#13;
arrangements. The team will review (i)      the project's quarterly interim unaudited financial&#13;
reports as well as the project's annual audited financial statements and auditor's management&#13;
 letter; (ii)&#13;
           project's financial management and disbursement arrangements (including a review&#13;
o f a sample o f Statements o f Expenditures and movements on the Designated Account) to&#13;
 ensure compliance with IDA'Sminimumrequirements and the FM Manual; and (iii)              status o f&#13;
 FMreforms inMOMunder component 1o fthe project.&#13;
&#13;
 Conclusion&#13;
&#13;
 The FMarrangements, including the systems, processes, procedures, internal controls, and&#13;
 staffing are adequate to support this project, subject to implementation o f the items listed in&#13;
 the action plan.&#13;
&#13;
                                                 58&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THIS PAGEINTENTIONALLY LEFT BLANK&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THIS PAGEINTENTIONALLYLEFTBLANK&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THIS PAGEINTENTIONALLY LEFT BLANK&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THIS PAGEINTENTIONALLYLEFTBLANK&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6827208">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/05/6827208/afghanistan-sustainable-development-natural-resources-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/05/6827208/afghanistan-sustainable-development-natural-resources-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2006/05/6827208/afghanistan-sustainable-development-natural-resources-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2006-08-16T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/06/01/000160016_20060601095503/Rendered/INDEX/T7673.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/06/01/000160016_20060601095503/Rendered/PDF/T7673.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2006-06-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2006-05-16T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Gray cover</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309938</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Afghanistan - Sustainable Development of
            Natural Resources Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Afghanistan Sustainable Development
            of Natural Resources Project aims to assist the Ministry of
            Mines in improving its capacity to effectively regulate
            Afghanistan's minerals and hydrocarbon resources sector
            in a transparent manner and foster private sector
            development. Among the benefits to Afghanistan of
            development of its mineral resources will be tax revenues,
            employment, rural development, and economic spin-offs. This
            project will support the Ministry of Mines to make the
            transition from being a producer of minerals and other
            commodities to a policy-making institution and regulator for
            the sector through capacity building and institutional
            strengthening across four components: (1) improving internal
            efficiencies of ministry departments, (2) developing
            regulatory capacity, (3) developing mineral resources, and
            (4) enhancing sector governance. Among the benefits to
            Afghanistan o f development of its mineral resources will be
            tax revenues, employment, rural development, and economic spin-offs.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Afghanistan - Sustainable Development of
            Natural Resources Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Afghanistan - Sustainable
            Development of Natural Resources Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2006/05/6827208/afghanistan-sustainable-development-natural-resources-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>AF-Sustainable Development Of Natural
            Resources -- P098118</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Oil Refining &amp; Gas Industry,Mining &amp; Extractive Industry (Non-Energy),National Governance,Energy Production and Transportation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Energy,Industry,Governance</teratopic>
        <count>Afghanistan</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20060601095503</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <subsc>Mining and other extractive</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Energy,Industry,Governance</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Energy and mining</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accountability, approach, asset management,
            authorization, cadastre, cement, cement industry, cement
            plants, citizens, coal, coal mines, coal mining, community
            development, Conceptual Framework, copper, corruption,
            crushed stone, decision-making, decision-making process,
            economic development, economic growth, EITI, electricity,
            employment, energy strategy, Environment Protection,
            environmental, environmental impact, environmental impact
            assessments, environmental issues, environmental management,
            environmental performance, Environmental Protection,
            Environmental Protection Agency, Expenditure, Expenditure
            Management, Extraction, Extractive Industries, Extractive
            Industries Transparency Initiative, ferrous metals,
            Financial management, foreign direct investment, fossil,
            fossil fuels, Gas, Gas Exploration, Gas Infrastructure, gas
            market, gas market development, gas pricing, gas pricing
            principles, gas processing, gas processing plants, gas
            production, gas production forecast, gas reserves, gas
            sector, gemstones, geological knowledge, Geological Survey,
            gold, gold mines, good governance, government authority,
            Government Institutions, government revenue, Government
            revenues, gravel, human resources, hydrocarbon exploration,
            hydrocarbons, Income, Income Tax, industrial minerals,
            industrial minerals production, informal sector,
            Institutional Arrangements, institutional capacity,
            institutional framework, internal audit, Investment Climate,
            iron, iron ore, large-scale mining, legal framework,
            legislation, license holders, limestone, Marble, metals,
            MINERAL, mineral production, mineral resource, mineral
            resources, mineral rights, MINERAL SECTOR, mineral sector
            development, mineral wealth, Minerals, Minerals Sector,
            Mines, mining activities, mining enterprises, Mining Policy,
            Mining Reform, mining regulations, mining sector, mining
            sector development, Mining Taxation, mining titles, natural
            gas, natural gas pipeline, NATURAL RESOURCES, occupational
            health, Oil, Oil and Gas, Outsourcing, petroleum, petroleum
            exploration, pipelines, political interference,
            post-conflict, power, power generation, power plant, private
            capital, private investment, private investors, private
            sector, private sector investment, private sector
            participation, Public Administration, Public Finance, public
            information, public institutions, public sector, refinery,
            regulatory agency, Regulatory Framework, regulatory regimes,
            Rehabilitation, resource base, revenues from oil, Royalty,
            sand, scientific knowledge, Small-scale, small-scale miners,
            Small-scale Mining, social obligations, Social Protection,
            solid minerals, stability agreements, State Gas Enterprise,
            State-owned enterprises, stream, sustainability, SUSTAINABLE
            DEVELOPMENT, tax laws, Tax Receipts, tax revenues, Taxation,
            Transparency, turbulence, vehicles
        </keywd>
        <owner>Oil, Gas and Mining (SEGOM)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Emergency Recovery Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T7673</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>EITI</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cadastre</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cadastre, Titling, Registry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inspectorate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative</ml:concept><ml:concept>Geological Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cadastre and Land Registration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Afghanistan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>