<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>FirstAnnual Forum of the BusinessAlliance for Food Fortification&#13;
&#13;
Public-Private Partnership Launched to&#13;
Improve Nutrition in Developing Countries&#13;
&#13;
Leading representatives of the global food industry, civil society, government and academic experts, gathered in Beijing,&#13;
China,on 22­23 October 2005,launched the BusinessAlliance for Food Fortification and discussed actions to reduce&#13;
the devastating effects of vitamin and mineral deficiencies and improve the health of the world's poorest peoples.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         he Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition                 · BAFF was formally launched as a private sec-&#13;
         (GAIN) and World Bank Institute (WBI)                        tor-led initiative facilitated by GAIN and&#13;
         brought together 150 decision makers for                     WBI. The launch was the culmination of a&#13;
the First Annual Forum of the Business Alliance                       process begun with a preliminary roundtable&#13;
for Food Fortification (BAFF) in Beijing, China,                      discussion of private sector roles in fighting&#13;
22­23 October 2005. Business leaders from the                         malnutrition hosted by the World Bank In-&#13;
length of the food production supply chain met                        stitute and GAIN in Washington, D.C., 16&#13;
with leaders from the Chinese government, civil                       November 2004. Participants were able to&#13;
society partners, and academic community for                          review progresses since 2004 and were proud&#13;
two days of discussion. Focusing initially on the                     to acknowledge that all goals set at the initial&#13;
structure and functioning of the BAFF, discussion                     roundtable were met over the subsequent year&#13;
broadened on the second day to consider how busi-                     and concluding with the Beijing forum. Offi-&#13;
ness can best support multisectoral efforts to in-                    cially launched in the presence of GAIN board&#13;
crease food fortification and so improve nutrition                    members, the BAFF is now fully integrated&#13;
globally and in China specifically. It was clear that                 into the broader GAIN Alliance of stakehold-&#13;
as socially responsible actors, businesses can play a                 ers committed to fighting malnutrition.&#13;
key role since in many cases companies already own                 · "Beijing Declaration on Food Fortification."&#13;
the right technology to make a difference as well                     Industry leaders and partners from across the&#13;
as the distribution channels and communication                        globe collectively expressed their commitment&#13;
networks. With the benefit of expert moderation                       to increase food fortification as a means to&#13;
by Robert Davies, CEO of the International Busi-                      reduce vitamin and mineral deficiencies and&#13;
ness Leaders Forum (IBLF), participants reached a                     therefore improve nutrition levels, particularly&#13;
number of important outcomes, including:                              among poor populations.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
           · Coca-Cola, Danone and Unilever agreed to&#13;
              become the first co-chairs of the BAFF. As&#13;
              agreed collectively by the company represen-&#13;
              tatives present, the co-chairs will work with&#13;
              their fellow BAFF members, GAIN, WBI,&#13;
              and leaders from government and civil society&#13;
              to identify projects for future collective action,&#13;
              and co-host the second Annual Forum.&#13;
           · China BAFF was formed by leading represen-&#13;
              tatives from China's business community, with&#13;
                                                                            The China BAFF is announced, to be co-chaired by the CEOs of the China&#13;
              the support of the Chinese Government. To be                  Grain Council and Qingdao Biomate Food Stuff Company.&#13;
&#13;
              chaired by Shijiazhuang Zhenji Brew Group&#13;
              Company and Qingdao Biomate Food Stuff                       The estimated 800 million children who suffer&#13;
              Company, the China BAFF will focus on scal-                  from malnutrition are at risk of severe physical and&#13;
              ing-up successful food fortification initiatives             cognitive debilitation. As highlighted during this&#13;
              and raising awareness of how to tackle vitamin               1st Annual Forum, some economists have ranked&#13;
              and mineral deficiencies through corporate ac-               micronutrient malnutrition reduction second only&#13;
              tion and multisectoral partnerships in China.                to HIV/AIDS control as the development invest-&#13;
              A first planning meeting of the Chinese BAFF                 ment with the greatest potential pay-offs.&#13;
              is schedule for December 2005.                                    The Business Alliance for Food Fortification&#13;
                                                                           (BAFF), together with leaders from government&#13;
        Key Objectives                                                     and civil society, will identify projects for future&#13;
        BAFF will promote business action to address the                   collective action and facilitate effective individual&#13;
        devastating effects of vitamin and mineral deficien-               corporate projects at country level in partnership&#13;
        cies in developing countries, a form of malnutri-                  with GAIN. BAFF will support innovation and&#13;
        tion that affects at least two billion people through-             project development as well as provide insights for&#13;
        out the world, and accounts for millions of dollars                effective implementation.&#13;
        in productivity losses and curative healthcare costs.                   BAFF members will demonstrate how they will&#13;
                                                                           increase vitamin and mineral coverage for poor&#13;
"The Beijing Declaration demonstrates that these companies are             populations through innovation and penetration&#13;
serious about helping to address vitamin and mineral deficien-&#13;
cies around the world. GAIN and its partners recognize that the            of new markets. Companies will report annually&#13;
private sector can play a critical role in ensuring the delivery of        on results.&#13;
fortified products to those that need it most.Vitamin and mineral&#13;
fortification is recognized as one of the most effective and simple&#13;
ways to improve the lives of vulnerable populations, and if we are         Priority Issues and Potential Topics&#13;
to achieve our goal of making a real difference, all stakeholders&#13;
need to play a part."                                                      for Future Collaboration&#13;
&#13;
                                                   --MarcVanAmeringen,     Over the course of the two days a number of is-&#13;
                                       Interim Executive Director of GAIN. sues came to the forefront as of real concern to the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
private sector and a range of stakeholders engaged     "BAFF is an exciting example of how business can become truly&#13;
                                                       engaged in providing solutions to important development chal-&#13;
with the fortification agenda. They included:         lenges for mutual benefit.The commitment to fighting malnu-&#13;
                                                       trition demonstrated here is inspiring.We must build on the&#13;
                                                       momentum generated.WBI and our colleagues across theWorld&#13;
 · Obtaining a level playing field for fortification,  Bank Group look forward to maximizing the learning for BAFF&#13;
    and the importance of government roles, for        members, and strengthening the capacity of BAFF to work with&#13;
                                                       the GAIN Alliance to increase coverage on the ground.The spirit&#13;
    example in ensuring adequate enforcement           from the Beijing launch is one of true partnership both within&#13;
 · Voluntary initiatives versus mandatory ap-          industry and across all sectors represented."&#13;
&#13;
    proaches--the need for flexibility                                                                        --Djordjija Petkoski,&#13;
                                                                                                                   Program Leader,&#13;
 · Innovative financing mechanisms for fortifica-                                       Business, Competitiveness &amp; Development,&#13;
                                                                                                              World Bank Institute&#13;
    tion initiatives&#13;
 · Education of consumers and social marketing&#13;
    campaigns                                             lations at risk of vitamin and mineral defi-&#13;
 · The appropriate role of the retail sector for          ciencies.&#13;
    fortified food products                           · BAFF to explore creation of further regional&#13;
 · Sharing information and best practices                 and country focused BAFF groups on the&#13;
 · Collective action benefit of BAFF--issues              model of China BAFF.&#13;
    that a single food company cannot resolve         · Create an information sharing platform for&#13;
    alone                                                 BAFF members, either through an indepen-&#13;
 · Costs of fortification in product markets where        dent       website&#13;
    margins are very slim                                 funded by BAFF&#13;
 · Need to facilitate innovation and experimen-           members or cre-&#13;
    tation                                                ationofpassword&#13;
 · Sustainable business models are vital to ensure        protected      areas&#13;
    continued corporate commitment and align              and    communi-&#13;
    fortification with corporate social responsibil-      ties of practice&#13;
    ity strategy                                          on the GAIN or&#13;
                                                          WBI websites.&#13;
Action Agenda forYear Ahead                           · Host        e-discus-&#13;
 · BAFF co-chairs to work with GAIN and WBI               sions and work-&#13;
    to formalize BAFF structure, decision-mak-            shops on priority&#13;
    ing framework and communication channels.             topics highlighted&#13;
    They will help build a common understand-             by BAFF mem-&#13;
    ing of the challenges around the fortification        bers,    including&#13;
    agenda and facilitate effective business en-          identifying indus-&#13;
    gagement.                                             try roles as advo-      PaulusVerschuren of Unilever and&#13;
                                                                                  Huaying Zhang of Coca Cola an-&#13;
 · BAFF members to identify business and part-            cates for the forti-    nounce that they will be co-chairs&#13;
                                                                                  of the BAFF together with Michael&#13;
    nership projects to extend coverage of popu-          fication agenda.        Infantes of Danone.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
· Development and dissemination of addi-                Contacts&#13;
  tional case studies of BAFF member proj-                · GAIN: Bérangère Magarinos, Business &amp;&#13;
  ects.                                                      Consumer Program (bmagarinos@gaingene&#13;
· Development of toolkit for BAFF members                    va.org)&#13;
  on the business case, models and action                 · World Bank Institute:Michael Jarvis, Busi-&#13;
  steps for fortification initiatives.                       ness, Competitiveness &amp; Development Pro-&#13;
                                                             gram (mjarvis@worldbank.org)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Mark your calendars: SecondAnnual Forum of the BAFF · Seattle · October 2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Beijing Declaration on Food Fortification&#13;
&#13;
 We, the charter members of the                      Commit ourselves to:&#13;
 GAIN Business Alliance for Food                     1. Seek and pursue opportunities to produce and&#13;
 Fortification, gathered in Beijing on                  distribute affordable fortified foods around the&#13;
 22­23 October 2005                                     world,and in the developing world particularly;&#13;
                                                     2. Explore and realize opportunities and partner-&#13;
 1. Motivated by the need to improve human              ships to more efficiently deliver affordable forti-&#13;
    health by improving nutrition and reducing          fied foods;&#13;
    global vitamin and mineral deficiency;          3.Advance the scientific knowledge and experi-&#13;
 2.Recognizing that food fortification is one of the    ence necessary to improve the production and&#13;
    most promising interventions for improving the      delivery of fortified foods to the consumers&#13;
    nutritional status of the world's poorest and       who need them most;&#13;
    should be the first area of focus;              4.Promote food fortification as an important and&#13;
 3. Recognizing that businesses, governments, non-      necessary element of global and local efforts&#13;
    governmental organizations and multi-lateral        to improve the health and well-being of the&#13;
    institutions can substantially contribute indi-     world populations at risk of vitamin and mineral&#13;
    vidually and jointly to combating vitamin and       deficiencies;and&#13;
    mineral deficiency around the world;             5. Work in cooperation and partnership with&#13;
 4. Acknowledging the progress to date and the          other relevant public and private institutions&#13;
    challenges and opportunities that lay ahead.        and organizations that can substantially contrib-&#13;
                                                        ute to reducing vitamin and mineral deficiency&#13;
                                                        around the world&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                  Company Participant List&#13;
                                       Beijing · 22­23, October 2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Ajinomoto Europe S.A.S                              International Life Sciences Institute Japan&#13;
            Akzo Nobel Chemicals Pte Ltd                  International Institute for Management Development, IMD&#13;
              Azko Nobel (Asia) Co. Ltd.                             International Business Leaders Forum&#13;
         August 1st Grain &amp; Cooking Oil Co.                                      Jilin Provincial&#13;
                         BASF                                                Kikkoman Corporation&#13;
                   Beidahuang Rice                          Kerry Oils &amp; Grains Business Development (KOGBD)&#13;
                 Beijing Air Caterers                                     Lanzhou Hongmei Milling&#13;
   Beijing Center for Disease Control &amp; Prevention                  Lombard Odeir Darier Hentsch &amp; Co.&#13;
           Beijing San Yuan Foods Co., Ltd                     Modern Flour Mills and Macaroni Factories Co.&#13;
           Beijing Tan Tan VITA Company                                    Ministry of Health, China&#13;
         Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation                 National Working Committee for Children and Women&#13;
               Capital Pediatric Institute                                            Nestlé&#13;
    Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention USA                                   Nestlé China&#13;
      Shijiazhuang Zhenji Brew Group Co., Ltd                            Ningxia Saibeizue Milling Co.&#13;
China Association of Bakery and Confectionery Industry                          Novartis­Gerber&#13;
      China Association of Women Entrepreneurs                                     Nutriblend&#13;
   China Center of Disease Control and Prevention                              Nutriblend China&#13;
       China Condiment Industrial Association                                 Oil Company Sengal&#13;
         China Dairy Industrial Association                  Center for Public Nutrition &amp; Development of China&#13;
         China Disabled Person's Federation                    Population Research Institute, Beijing University&#13;
        China Light-industry Publishing House                                  Snowwhite Milling&#13;
           China National Salt Corporation                    Southseas Oil &amp; Fats Industrial (Shanghai) Limited&#13;
         China Soybean Industry Association                              Soy Sauce Fortification Project&#13;
         Chinese Food Technology Association                                Strategy XXI Group Ltd&#13;
   Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference                             Suntory, LTD.&#13;
               City University London                                        Taiyo Kagaku Co., Ltd&#13;
                      Coca-Cola                                                     Tetra Pak&#13;
China National Cereals, Oils &amp; Foodstuffs Corporation                         The Academy of SGA&#13;
                      (COFCO)                                            The Micronutrient Initiative&#13;
                        Danone                             The State Council's Developing Office of Western China&#13;
               Danone Institute China                              The State Grain Administration of China&#13;
         Development Bank of South Africa                    ThinkTank Research Center for Health Development&#13;
Department of Disease Control, Ministry of Health, China           Tianjin Sihuang Nutritional Products, Ltd&#13;
Department of Health Legislation and Monitoring, China                      Tianshan Milling Group&#13;
         Department of Public Health, China                                  U.S. Wheat Association&#13;
                          DSM                                                    Ülker ­ Turkey&#13;
   Emory University, Rollins School of Public Health              United Nations Childrens Fund (UNICEF)&#13;
      Ferment Research Institute of Food Industry                               UNICEF China&#13;
                    Fortitech, Inc.                                                  Unilever&#13;
        Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition               United States Agency for International Development&#13;
                Guchuan Milling Co.                                                 (USAID)&#13;
                    H.J. Heinz Co.                                       WeiWei Food &amp; Beverage Ltd&#13;
        Hangzhou Beingmate Group Co., Ltd                                          World Bank&#13;
              HBT Foodchemical Corp.                                          World Bank Institute&#13;
                Hebei Provincial CDC                                        World Food Programme&#13;
                     Hoganas AB                                     Zheng Zhou Sanquan Foods, Co., Ltd&#13;
               Hoganas China Co., Ltd&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
            THE BUSINESS ALLIANCE FOR FOOD FORTIFICATION - BAFF&#13;
                                              GLOBAL LAUNCH&#13;
&#13;
                                       Beijing, China ­ 22 October 2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Audience:              Selected International Private Sector Representatives&#13;
&#13;
Objectives:            Confirm Companies' Commitment to the BAFF Initiative&#13;
                       Review Current Fortification Successes of BAFF Companies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1:30 ­ 2:00   REGISTRATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2:00 ­ 2:30   INTRODUCTION                                                        Mr. Robert Davies, CEO&#13;
              Participants Introductions                                          International Business Leaders Forum&#13;
              Meeting Objectives&#13;
&#13;
2:30 ­ 3:00   THE BAFF FRAMEWORK&#13;
              A key mechanism for the GAIN Alliance.                              Mr. Marc Van Ameringen&#13;
                                                                                  Interim Executive Director&#13;
                                                                                  Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition&#13;
              The contribution of the World Bank Institute.                       Dr. Djordjija Petkoski&#13;
                                                                                  Head of Private Sector Development&#13;
                                                                                  World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3:00 ­ 4:00   INDIVIDUAL ACTION&#13;
              Current Fortification Projects of the BAFF Companies:               Mr. Robert Davies&#13;
              Success Stories and Lessons Learned&#13;
&#13;
              Topics:                                                             Informal Input from Business Leaders&#13;
              How to improve existing projects?&#13;
              What are the principal barriers for doing more?&#13;
              What is the value added by partnership?&#13;
&#13;
4:00 ­ 4:30   Coffee Break&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4:30 ­ 6:00   COLLECTIVE ACTION&#13;
              Proposed areas for collaboration:&#13;
&#13;
              Sector Initiatives: Flour, Oil, Premix, Rice                        Dr. Glen Maberly&#13;
                                                                                  Flour Fortification Initiative Example&#13;
&#13;
              Corporate Support for the 10-Year Vitamin and Mineral               Mr. Rainer Gross, Chief of Nutrition&#13;
              Deficiencies Strategic Plan                                         UNICEF&#13;
&#13;
              The BAFF declaration                                                Ms Harriet Weiss, Strategy XXI&#13;
&#13;
              Other Suggestions from the Group&#13;
&#13;
              Discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6:00 ­ 6:30   NEXT STEPS&#13;
              Decisions and Conclusions                                           Mr. Robert Davies&#13;
&#13;
6:30 ­ 9:30   OFFICIAL BAFF LAUNCH                                                Mr. Jay Naidoo, Chairman of the Board&#13;
              Cocktail Reception and Dinner                                       Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  GAIN Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition Av. Giuseppe-Motta 52 Case postale 55 1211 Genève 20&#13;
                             T +41 22 749 18 50 F +41 22 749 18 51 www.gainhealth.org&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                       THE BUSINESS ALLIANCE FOR FOOD FORTIFICATION ­ BAFF&#13;
                 First Annual Forum: THE BUSINESS CASE FOR FOOD FORTIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
                                         Beijing, China - 23 October 2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Audience:     International and Chinese Private Sector, Chinese Government, Multilateral&#13;
              Agencies, Donor Agencies, Civil Society, Media, Academics, GAIN Board&#13;
&#13;
Objectives:   Discuss the Business Case for Food Fortification&#13;
              Identify Creative Solutions to Address the Cost of Fortification&#13;
              Recommend Approaches to Scale Up Food Fortification in China&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8:30 ­ 9:00  REGISTRATION&#13;
&#13;
9:00 ­ 10:00 OPENING REMARKS&#13;
              The Chinese Government's Agenda on Food Fortification          Dr. Longde Wang, China Vice Health&#13;
                                                                             Minister&#13;
                                                                             Mr. Li Shenglin, Deputy Director, NDRC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             The Global Vision of Food Fortification                         Mr. Jay Naidoo, Chairman of the Board&#13;
                                                                             Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition&#13;
&#13;
              Objectives of the First BAFF Annual Forum                      Mr. Robert Davies, CEO&#13;
                                                                             International Business Leaders Forum&#13;
&#13;
10:00 ­ 11:00 PLENARY SESSION: Setting the Scene for the BAFF&#13;
              Food Fortification, the Second Best Development Bet:           Dr. Harold Alderman&#13;
              An analysis by economists of the Copenhagen                    Lead Human Development Economist&#13;
              Consensus                                                      World Bank&#13;
&#13;
              Panel Presentations and Discussion:&#13;
&#13;
              Food Market Complexity and Food Industry Responsibility:       Dr. Michael Heasman, City University London&#13;
              Impact on the fortification agenda                             Co-Author of Food Wars:The Global Battle for Mouths, Minds and&#13;
                                                                             Markets&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Corporate Social Responsibility in the Food Industry:         Ms. Aileen Ionescu-Somers&#13;
              Can fortification become a CSR strategy?                      Forum, Corporate Sustainability Management&#13;
                                                                            Institute for Management and Development, IMD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11:00 - 11:15 BRIEFING: Three Breakout Roundtables&#13;
              In preliminary consultations, companies identified the cost    Moderators and Mr. Robert Davies&#13;
              of fortification as a major obstacle. What are the&#13;
              strategies to manage the cost?&#13;
              1. How to Finance Fortification Strategies?&#13;
              2. How to Integrate the Cost of Fortification Through the&#13;
                 Supply Chain?&#13;
              3. Is the Cost of Fortification a Policy Issue?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11:15 - 11:30 Coffee Break&#13;
&#13;
11:30 - 12:30 ROUNDTABLES: Parallel Discussions&#13;
              Sustainable Financing Strategies: Incentives on taxes and      Moderator: Mr. Admassu Tadesse&#13;
              tariffs, subsidies, growing new markets, working with vol-     Corporate Strategy&#13;
              umes, and grants                                               Development Bank of Southern Africa&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Sustainable Business Models: Analysis of effective fortifica-  Moderator: Dr. Djordjija Petkoski&#13;
              tion strategies through the supply chain ­ what can be         Head of Private Sector Development&#13;
              learned?                                                       World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Sustainable Policies: Analysis of the level playing field in-  Moderator: Dr. M.G. Venkatesh Mannar&#13;
              cluding regulation, quality control, consumer participation.   Executive Director, Micronutrient Initiative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              The Chinese Perspective: The three subjects will be dis-&#13;
              cussed by non-English speaking Chinese invitees                Moderator: Dr. Chen Junshi, CDC China&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12:30 - 2:00 LUNCH&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2:00 - 2:30  PLENARY SESSION: Breakout Roundtable Reports&#13;
             Two Key Recommendations and Two Action Points per              Moderators and Mr. Robert Davies&#13;
             group&#13;
&#13;
2:30 ­ 3:30  PLENARY SESSION: Current Vitamin and Mineral Defi-&#13;
             ciencies Situation in China: A public health perspective       Madame Chen Chunming, CDC-GAIN Board&#13;
&#13;
             Panel Presentations and Discussion: Three Chinese&#13;
             business cases&#13;
                 Salt Fortification (TBC)                                   Chinese Salt Company (TBC)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Soya Sauce Fortification                                   Zhang Lin, CEO of Shijiazhuang Zhenji Brew&#13;
                                                                            Group Co.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Flour Fortification                                        Mr. Zhou Baozhong, Chairman of the Board of&#13;
                                                                            Directors, Qingdao Biomate Food Stuff Co.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3:30 ­ 3:45  BRIEFING: Three Breakout Roundtables&#13;
             The three groups will develop actions points focusing on       Mr. Robert Davies&#13;
             future food fortification initiatives in China.&#13;
&#13;
3:45 ­ 4:15  Coffee Break&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4:15 ­ 5:15  ROUNDTABLES: Parallel Discussions&#13;
&#13;
             How to Accelerate and Scale Up Current Fortification           Moderator: Professor Yu Xiaodong,&#13;
             Projects in China?                                             PNDC and Chinese Participants&#13;
&#13;
             How to Accelerate and Scale Up Current Fortification           Moderator Ms. Harriet Weiss, Strategy XXI&#13;
             Projects in China?                                             with International Companies&#13;
&#13;
             The 10-Year Vitamin and Mineral Deficiencies Strategic         Moderator Mr. Rainer Gross,&#13;
             Plan: What approach for China?                                 Chief of Nutrition, UNICEF with&#13;
                                                                            Development Agencies&#13;
&#13;
5:15 ­ 6:00  PLENARY SESSION: Breakout Roundtable Reports&#13;
             Two Key Recommendations and Two Action Points per              Moderators and Mr. Robert Davies&#13;
             group&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6:00 ­ 6:30  CONCLUSIONS and NEXT STEPS                                     Mr. Robert Davies&#13;
                                                                            Mr. Marc Van Ameringen&#13;
                                                                            Interim Executive Director, GAIN&#13;
                                                                            Dr. Djordjija Petkoski&#13;
                                                                            Madame Chen Chunming, CDC-GAIN Board&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7:00 ­ 10:00 INAUGURAL DINNER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   GAIN Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition Av. Giuseppe-Motta 52 Case postale 55 1211 Genève 20&#13;
                                T +41 22 749 18 50 F +41 22 74918 51 www.gainhealth.org&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6857245">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/01/6857245/first-annual-forum-business-alliance-food-fortification
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/01/6857245/first-annual-forum-business-alliance-food-fortification</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2006/01/6857245/first-annual-forum-business-alliance-food-fortification</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2006-06-14T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/06/14/000160016_20060614171921/Rendered/INDEX/364800baff1report01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/06/14/000160016_20060614171921/Rendered/PDF/364800baff1report01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2006-06-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2006-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            First annual forum of The Business Alliance
            For Food Fortification
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Leading representatives of the global
            food industry, civil society, government and academic
            experts, gathered in Beijing, China, on 22-23 October 2005,
            to launch the Business Alliance for Food Fortification and
            discuss actions to reduce the devastating effects of vitamin
            and mineral deficiencies and improve the health of the
            world's poorest peoples.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            First annual forum of The Business Alliance
            For Food Fortification
        </docna>
        <display_title>First annual forum of The
            Business Alliance For Food Fortification</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2006/01/6857245/first-annual-forum-business-alliance-food-fortification</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Business Environment,Business in Development,Food &amp; Beverage Industry,Corporate Law</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Law and Development,Industry,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20060614171921</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Law and Development,Industry,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accounts, board members, business community,
            CEO, CEOs, Cereals, charter, Co. Ltd., collective,
            collective action, company, Confectionery, Confectionery
            Industry, Cooking, Corp., corporate social responsibility,
            Corporation, Fats, Flour, Flour Mills, Food Fortification,
            food industry, food production, food products, Food
            Technology, fortified foods, Health Legislation,
            International Business, Limited, Nutrition, nutritional
            status, Private Partnership, Public Health, quality control,
            Rice, social marketing, society, stakeholders, World Food Programme
        </keywd>
        <owner>Sustainable Development Division (WBISD)</owner>
        <repnb>36480</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disease Control &amp; Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Promotion, Disease Prevention and Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Models</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Food Fortification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Care Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Laws and Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Social Responsibility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Promotion and Disease Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Micronutrients</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications Organizational Design</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Fortification</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>