<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                              Documentof&#13;
                                            The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
                                     FOROFFICIAL USE ONLY&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             ReportNo. T7660-CI&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                     FORA PROPOSEDGRANT&#13;
&#13;
                             INTHE AMOUNT OF SDR 67.3 MILLION&#13;
                                 (vS$lOO MILLIONEQUIVALENT)&#13;
&#13;
                                               TO THE&#13;
&#13;
                                  REPUBLICOF COTED'IVOIRE&#13;
&#13;
              FORAN EMERGENCYDEMOBILIZATION, REINTEGRATION&#13;
&#13;
                        AND COMMUNITY REHABILITATIONPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             June 29,2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HumanDevelopment, Group I1&#13;
Africa Region&#13;
- -&#13;
This document has arestricted distribution andmaybe usedbyrecipients only inthe performance of&#13;
their official duties. Its contents may not otherwise be disclosed without World Bank authorization&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           CurrencyEquivalents&#13;
&#13;
                     Currency unit = CFA Franc (CFAF)&#13;
&#13;
                     US$l.OO = 519 (as o f June 9,2006)&#13;
&#13;
                                 FiscalYear&#13;
&#13;
                          January 1-December 31&#13;
&#13;
                  ACRONYMS ANDABBREVIATIONS&#13;
&#13;
BCEAO   Banque Centrale des Etats d 'Afrique de 1'Ouest (Central Bank o fthe West&#13;
        African States)&#13;
CDD     Community DrivenDevelopment&#13;
CFAA    Country Financial Accountability Assessment&#13;
CNDDR   Commission nationalepour le dksarmement, la de'mobilisation et la&#13;
        re'insertion (National Commission for Disarmament, Demobilization and&#13;
        Reintegration)&#13;
CQ      Consultant's Qualifications&#13;
CTO      Centre de Transit et d 'Orientation (Transit and Orientation Center)&#13;
DDR     Disarmament, Demobilization and Reintegration&#13;
DPKO    Department of Peace Keeping Operations&#13;
ECOWAS  Economic Community o f West African States&#13;
ERL     Emergency Recovery Loan&#13;
FA      Financial Agreement&#13;
FANCI   Forces Arme'es Nationales de Cdte d 'Ivoire (National Armed Forces o f&#13;
         CGte d'Ivoire)&#13;
FAFN    Forces Armkes des Forces Nouvelles (Armed Forces o fthe New Forces)&#13;
FDS     Forces de De'fence et de Se'curite'(Defense and Security Forces)&#13;
FMA      Fiduciary Management Agency&#13;
FMAM     Financial Management and Accounting Manual&#13;
FN      Forces Nouvelles (New Forces)&#13;
GTZ     Deutsche Gesellshaft fur Technishe Zusammenarbei (German Cooperation)&#13;
HIPC     HighlyIndebtedPoor Country&#13;
IAPSO    Inter-Agency Procurement Services Organization&#13;
ICB      International Competitive Bidding&#13;
ID      IdentityDocument&#13;
IDA      International Development Association&#13;
IDP      Internally Displaced Person&#13;
I O M    International Organization for Migration&#13;
ISN      InterimStrategy Note&#13;
MICECI  Mission de la CEDEAO en C6te d'lvoire (ECOWAS Mission inCGte d'Ivoire)&#13;
MINUCI   UnitedNations MissioninCGte d'Ivoire&#13;
MIS      Management Information System&#13;
N C B    National Competitive Bidding&#13;
ONUCI    Organisation des Nations Unies en C6te d 'Ivoire (UNDPKO Mission in&#13;
         CGte d'Ivoire)&#13;
PER      Public Expenditures Review&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PlM     Project ImplementationManual&#13;
PNDDR   Programme National de Dksarmement, Dkmobilisation et Reinsertion&#13;
        (National Program for Disarmament, Demobilization and Reintegration)&#13;
QCBS    Quality and Cost Based Selection&#13;
R C     Rkhabilitation Communautaire (Community Rehabilitation)&#13;
TSS     Transitional Safety Net&#13;
UEMOA   Union Economique et Monktaii-e OuestAfricaine (West African Economic&#13;
        and Monetary Union)&#13;
UNDP    UNDevelopmentProgram&#13;
UNICEF  UNChildren's Fund&#13;
UNHCR   UnitedNations HighCommission for Refugees&#13;
WFP     World FoodProgram&#13;
WHO     World Health Organization&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Vice President: Gobind T. Nankani&#13;
                    CountryDirector: MamadouDia&#13;
              Acting Sector Manager:  William Experton&#13;
                  Task Team Leader:   Maurizia Tovo&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                         Republicof CBted'Ivoire&#13;
        Demobilization.Reintegrationand CommunityRehabilitationProject&#13;
&#13;
                                                Table of Contents&#13;
&#13;
A.&#13;
  I Circumstancesoftheconflict..............................................................................&#13;
    BACKGROUND AND STRATEGY.........................................................................                                 5&#13;
                                                                                                                                     5&#13;
  I1     Humanitarian Impact              .......................................................................................... 5&#13;
  I11&#13;
   ...                                                                                                                               6&#13;
  IV.    Economic Impact ................................................................................................&#13;
         Government Response........................................................................................                 6&#13;
                                                                                                                                     7&#13;
B                                                                                                                                    8&#13;
                                                                                                                                     8&#13;
C.11DETAILED PROJECT DESCRIPTION..................................................................&#13;
 .V..&#13;
    .BANKRESPONSE AND STRATEGY.....................................................................&#13;
         InternationalResponse........................................................................................&#13;
&#13;
  I RationaleforBankAssistance............................................................................&#13;
         Elementsofthe BankResponse..........................................................................                        9&#13;
&#13;
  I.     Objectives .........................................................................................................        10&#13;
                                                                                                                                     10&#13;
  I1     DDRProgram Component................................................................................                        10&#13;
&#13;
D.I11INSTITUTIONAL&#13;
    ..   RC Program Component.,.................................................................................                     13&#13;
&#13;
  I                                                                                                                                  15&#13;
  I1     Implementing Mechanisms                   ...............................................................................   16&#13;
  I1&#13;
   ...   InstitutionalArrangements................................................................................&#13;
             . .             ARRANGEMENTSAND PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION.. 15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      ..............................................&#13;
  111.   Financial Management, Auditing and Reporting&#13;
         Procurement......................................................................................................           17&#13;
                                                                                                                                     20&#13;
  IV     Monitoring and Evaluation                 ...............................................................................   23&#13;
  IV  ..                                                                                                                             26&#13;
  V.     Project Sustainability........................................................................................&#13;
         Benefits   .............................................................................................................    26&#13;
  VI  .  Risks ..................................................................................................................    27&#13;
                                                                                                                                     28&#13;
E.VI1.&#13;
     FINANCIAL AND ECONOMIC JUSTIFICATION...............................................&#13;
         Environmental and Social Aspects ...................................................................&#13;
                                                                                                                                     29&#13;
F.   ACTION PLAN........................................................................................................             30&#13;
  I..    Action Plan for DDR Component.....................................................................&#13;
                                                           ........................................................................  30&#13;
&#13;
ATTACHMENTS .............................................................................................................&#13;
  I1     Action Planfor RC Component                                                                                                 31&#13;
                                                                                                                                     33&#13;
  Attachment 1 : Partial list of Documents inthe Project File ........................................                               33&#13;
&#13;
  Attachment 3 :Project Cost Summary..........................................................................&#13;
  Attachment 2 :Organigram of the NationalDDWRC Commission ............................                                              35&#13;
&#13;
  Attachment 4 : Criteria for RC Sub-projects ................................................................                       36&#13;
                                                                                                                                     38&#13;
  Attachment 5:Financial Management andDisbursements.,..........................................                                     42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Map IBRDNo33393&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                         A.      BACKGROUND AND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
I. Circumstancesoftheconflict&#13;
&#13;
1.       Though long presented as a development model, C8te d'Ivoire has been&#13;
undergoingpoliticaland social turmoil since the militarycoup of December 1999. A&#13;
ten-month military transition was characterized by a number o f mutinies and&#13;
destabilization attempts accompanied by social tensions andincreased insecurity. Despite&#13;
the Forum for National Reconciliation in 2001 and the establishment o f a Government of&#13;
National Union in August 2002, destabilization attempts persisted. In this context, the&#13;
militarycoup attempt o f September 19,2002 escalated into a full-blown rebellion,&#13;
&#13;
2.       Since September 2002, the country has been divided into two, with the&#13;
rebellious Forces Nouvelles (FN) holding the northern half and Government the&#13;
south. This de facto partition has had a serious economic, social, security and&#13;
humanitarian impact, including massive population displacements, many civilian and&#13;
military casualties, and the interruption o f the public administration and social services&#13;
delivery inthe north.&#13;
&#13;
3.       Responding to the crisis and increasingrisks of regionalspillover, intensive&#13;
diplomatic efforts have been deployed internationally and regionallyto resolve the&#13;
conflict. After West-Africa and French lead efforts, the Marcoussis Peace Accord&#13;
(January 2003) has provided a general framework for the resolution o f major issues of&#13;
contention, but implementation has been uneven and the new government o f national&#13;
reconciliation initial progress were faced with renewedpolitical tensions during 2003-04.&#13;
Mr. Mbeki, President of South Afiica, temporarily succeeded in getting the Ivorian&#13;
parties to agree on an action plan and a new timetable to implement the peace accords,&#13;
However, highlevels o f distrust between the two groups remained and timetables agreed&#13;
to were not adhered to. The peace process accelerated as o f October 2005 with the&#13;
adoption o f UNSecurity Council resolution 1633l delaying elections by a year (they are&#13;
now scheduled for end-October 2006) and establishing a new Transition Government&#13;
under Prime Minister Banny. These and other recent developments have given grounds&#13;
for renewed optimism and a credible peace process appears now to be underway.&#13;
&#13;
11.      HumanitarianImpact&#13;
&#13;
4.       Although large scale fighting lasted for only a short time, the social and&#13;
humanitarian impact has been severe, causing a prolonged and steady decline of&#13;
living conditions. Up to a million people were displaced (mostly women and children)&#13;
and poverty incidence i s estimated to have gone from 38% to 42-44%. Health, education&#13;
and agricultural services have been disrupted, although some improvement has been&#13;
registered inthe past year. Inparticular, health services inthe northern and western parts&#13;
of the country were reduced to minimal levels while schooling was intempted for over&#13;
half a million students and only resumed with NGOs support in February 2004. Food&#13;
'http://www.un.orglNewsPress/docs/2006/sc86&#13;
                                          19.doc.htm&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
production has decreased and cost o f transportation has risen substantially as a result o f&#13;
roadblocks. Human rights violations are common on both sides o f the confidence zone&#13;
and repeated concerns havebeenraised by ONUCI as well as human rights organizations.&#13;
&#13;
5.      The condition of children in particular raises serious concerns.NGOs have&#13;
identified many children who have been separated from their families as a result o f the&#13;
crisis, while the number o f child soldiers i s estimated to be at least 4,000. Since&#13;
September 2003, the armed forces o f the Forces Nouvelles (FAFN) have officially&#13;
banned the use and hrther recruitment o f minors, and agreed to start releasing those&#13;
identified by UNICEF. A similar process was initiated with militias inthe West, but the&#13;
resumption o f hostilities in November 2004 probably reversed the trend at least for a&#13;
while.&#13;
&#13;
111.    EconomicImpact&#13;
&#13;
6.      The economic impact of the conflict has been dramatic. Real output declined&#13;
by close to 2.5 percent over 2002-03. Some modest recovery has taken place since, with&#13;
real growth estimated at about 1.8 percent each year, mostly thanks to higher cocoa&#13;
exports and increased oil production. Since 2001, the last pre-crisis year, real GDP per&#13;
capita has fallen cumulatively by almost 10 percent. Transparency has deteriorated, the&#13;
fiscal situation i s strained, and internal and external arrears have substantially increased.&#13;
As there are still no regular fiscal flows across the demarcation lines, the country remains&#13;
de facto cut intwo.&#13;
&#13;
7.      With tightening and curtailment of bank lending and the prolonged&#13;
insecurity in many areas, the climate for private sector activity remains depressed.&#13;
Bankbranches inthe interior and inthe conflict zones have closed and lendingoperations&#13;
are being directed toward other UEMOA countries. Lingering insecurity, barriers to the&#13;
free flow o f goods across the national territory, and limited availability of bank credit to&#13;
the private sector make for a difficult climate for a quick resumption o f private activity.&#13;
The crisis inNovember 2004 had a very negative impact on industrial production and has&#13;
drastically reduced the government revenue base. External trade with the sub-region has&#13;
also been disrupted.&#13;
&#13;
IV.     GovernmentResponse&#13;
&#13;
8.      Humanitarian Response. According to the Ministry o f Solidarity and Social&#13;
Security, displaced persons have been registered at state-run social centers in areas under&#13;
government control, but only a very small fraction actually went to register. The Ministry&#13;
receives donations from institutions and individuals, and gives them to various structures&#13;
for distribution to internally displaced persons (IDPs). These structures include reception&#13;
centers, where some IDPs have been accommodated, and social centers, where they are&#13;
registered and given assistance. However, they do not assist the host families, which&#13;
carry the heaviest burden by providing food and shelter for the majority o f displaced&#13;
persons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9.      Disarmament, Demobilization and Reintegration. As soon as a formal and&#13;
effective cease fire was declared, the Government o f National Reconciliation undertook&#13;
the first initiatives to put into effect a program for the Disarmament, Demobilization and&#13;
Reintegration (DDR) o f ex-combatants, and asked for World Bank assistance. In May&#13;
2003, a workshop that included members from both sides, the government and&#13;
international experts resulted inan extensive outline or "road map" Cfeuille de route) for a&#13;
DDRprocess, which laidthe basis for further discussions that would eventually arrive at&#13;
a formal DDR program. The main principles and steps o f the actual disarmament,&#13;
demobilization and reintegration (DDR) have been agreed upon in a Joint Operations&#13;
Plan for DDR on January 9, 2004. The national program for the disarmament,&#13;
demobilization and reintegration o f ex-combatants and for community rehabilitation&#13;
(PNDDR/RC)         and a very detailed chronogram were agreed by the forces in&#13;
Yamoussoukro in M a y 2005. However, it has not been possible to launch the DDR&#13;
process as planned and it was only in May 2006, when the logistical details for the&#13;
parallel implementation o f the DDR and the national identification could be worked out,&#13;
that pre-cantonment was officially launched.&#13;
&#13;
10.     The national program for the disarmament, demobilization and&#13;
reintegration of ex-combatants and for community rehabilitation. A National&#13;
Program for the disarmament, demobilization and reintegration o f ex-combatants and for&#13;
community rehabilitation (known as the PNDDR/RC) has been developed to provide a&#13;
comprehensive approach, including links with the dismantling o f militias and the&#13;
restructuring o f the armed forces. Implementationresponsibility was initially given to the&#13;
National Commission for DDR (CNDDR), dissolved in June 2005. Presently, overall&#13;
implementation o f the PNDDWRC i s ensured by a technical entity with the same name&#13;
created by the Prime Minister inJune 2006 (see section D I1for more information).&#13;
&#13;
11,      Rehabilitation and Reconstruction.The lack o f coordination among ministries&#13;
and agencies concerned has been a serious obstacle to strategic planning for&#13;
reconstruction. The recently-established Ministry for Reintegration and Reconstruction i s&#13;
expected to provide unity and purpose to efforts inthis area. The PNDDR/RC adopted a&#13;
CDD approach in order to obtain quick results in the meantime, but the overwhelming&#13;
attention given to DDR and lack o f fundinghave limitedprogress.&#13;
&#13;
V.       InternationalResponse&#13;
&#13;
12.      The response of the internationalcommunity has focused on achieving and&#13;
maintaining peace. Given its strong links to C6te d'Ivoire and the presence o f large&#13;
numbers o f French citizens inthe country, the French Government was quick to mobilize&#13;
its troops and interpose them between the warring parties. The French military operation&#13;
(Licorne), numbering approximately 4,000             men, initially shared peace-keeping&#13;
responsibilities with MICECI. In February 2004, the United Nations approved the&#13;
deployment of 6,000 UNPeace Keeping Force (ONUCI) whose arrival inJune-July 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
greatly contributed to stabilize the situation. ONUCI will be a crucial partner to the DDR&#13;
process2.&#13;
&#13;
13.     Since the outbreak of the crisis, the United Nations agencies have had to&#13;
make a drastic shift from purely development programs to a rapid emergency&#13;
response mode. The agencies have reinforced their country teams with emergency&#13;
personnel and have gradually expanded programs to reach vulnerable populations in the&#13;
interior in collaboration with international and local NGOs. Emergency interventions&#13;
included: food aid, food-for-work and food-for-agriculture programs by WFP; various&#13;
education, health, nutrition, water and sanitation programs by UNICEF; and assistance to&#13;
third country nationals stranded as a result of the conflict by the International&#13;
Organization for Migration (IOM).             The strategy o f the UN Consolidated Appeals&#13;
Process (CAI?) for C8te d'Ivoire in 2004 was focusing on a "fragile consolidation o f&#13;
peace" with an estimated US$60 million necessary to respond to the urgent needs o f over&#13;
one million displaced people. In 2005, the CAP strategy was revised to "no war-no&#13;
peace" and called for US$36 million, but only 41% couldberaised. The request for 2006&#13;
i s $40 million to address the humanitarian needs o f over 3.5 million vulnerable persons,&#13;
with healthconcerns beingparamount.&#13;
&#13;
14.     The DDR process is supported by multi-lateral and bilateral donors. In&#13;
addition to supporting efforts to promote national reconciliation and social cohesion,&#13;
UNDP has provided funding and technical assistance to the PNDDR for a socio-&#13;
economic profiling o f ex-combatants, an ID system for ex-combatants, and mass-media&#13;
communication efforts. UNICEF has been active in the reintegration o f child soldiers,&#13;
having undertaken the delicate steps in collaboration with NGOs and the local authorities&#13;
to have the first 400 children released by the New Forces. The European Union i s&#13;
supporting sensitization and communication activities, the demobilization o f child&#13;
soldiers, the program for the militias and HIV/AIDS-related activities through UNFPA.&#13;
Japan and Belgium are providing support to pre-demobilization cantonment and&#13;
demobilization activities, including preparation and operation o f demobilization sites,&#13;
France, Sweden and Norway are supporting reinsertion and the gender dimension.&#13;
Denmark is contributing to the DDR process as well as to an effort against the&#13;
proliferation o f small arms. Total financing provided by donors is expected to be about&#13;
US$24 million (see Attachment 3 for details on donor contributions).&#13;
&#13;
                          B.        BANKRESPONSEAND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
I. RationaleforBankAssistance&#13;
&#13;
15.     Bank assistance would facilitate the stabilization of the situation in CBte&#13;
d'Ivoire, thereby helpingcreate conditionsunder which CBte d'Ivoire could resume&#13;
pro-poor social and economic development. Bank involvement would also play a&#13;
catalytic role for other donors to resume or step up assistance, and for the private sector&#13;
to restart key economic activities. Revitalizing economic activity and the improving&#13;
&#13;
  Subsequent authorizations to increase the size o f the ONUCI forces have brought their total to 9,228&#13;
(7,728 military and 1,182 police officers).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
living standards are key to the stabilization of Cbte d'Ivoire in the short and medium-&#13;
term.    In addition, implementation of the proposed project, as a part of the overall&#13;
emergency phase o f the Interim Strategy Note (ISN), is a requirement for the successful&#13;
resumption o f other projects inthe portfolio, as well as for IMF reengagement with a new&#13;
program.&#13;
&#13;
16.      The benefitsof peace andstabilityin C8te d'Ivoirewould extendwell beyond&#13;
its borders and would strengthen regional integration initiatives that have been&#13;
weakened by the crisis. Given the troubled history of West Africa and the pivotal role&#13;
played by Cbte d'Ivoire in the region, failure to reestablish a climate o f security and&#13;
confidence in Cbte d'Ivoire could jeopardize the fragile peace o f neighboring Sierra&#13;
Leone and Liberia, and ultimately destabilize the whole sub-region. The opposite i s also&#13;
true: if Cbte d'Ivoire i s helped in regaining economic momentum, it i s likely to become&#13;
again the growth engine o f the sub-region.&#13;
&#13;
17.      As shown by experienceelsewhere,the Bankhas a comparativeadvantagein&#13;
assisting Governmentsimplementdemobilizationand reintegrationprograms.DDR&#13;
i s a key element o f the peace agreement as well as a critical tool for bringingbelligerent&#13;
groups to the table and preventing a return to conflict. The Bank also has considerable&#13;
know-how on community driven development andproductive infrastructure rehabilitation&#13;
via social funds mechanisms and can bring the required level o f resources relatively&#13;
quickly under the emergency operation mode. It i s therefore uniquely positioned to&#13;
facilitate the transition from assistance to development in the shortest time possible,&#13;
which is crucial to give hope to people and avoid settling into a dependency mentality.&#13;
Experience o f similar situations has proven the interdependence o f DDR and CDD&#13;
approaches, focusing on the groups that are most likely to destabilize the situation as well&#13;
as on communities that have bothborn the efforts o f war andbeen ravagedby its effects.&#13;
&#13;
11.      Elementsof the BankResponse&#13;
&#13;
18.      The Bank's ISN focuses on limited, short-term objectives by promoting&#13;
macroeconomic stability and improving economic governance. It is envisaged to&#13;
cover a period o f about twelve months (July 2006-July 2007) and aims at addressing the&#13;
most urgentpost-conflict needs. To this end, the ISN i s built around three basic pillars: (i)&#13;
supporting the creation o f a security and institutional environment suitable for elections;&#13;
(ii) mitigating pressing economic and social costs resulting from the current crisis; and&#13;
(iii) safeguarding the economic fundamentals.&#13;
&#13;
19.      The Bank's support instruments during the emergency reengagementphase&#13;
will include a combination of new emergency projects, portfolio restructuring and&#13;
economic and sector work. New operations will amount to US$266 million and will&#13;
consist of:&#13;
     --  The present project (US$lOO million grant);&#13;
         An Emergency Economic Recovery Credit o f US$120 million to help finance the&#13;
         most pressing budgetary needs and initiating work on critical reconstruction&#13;
         needs;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    -   An HIVIAIDS project part of the World Bank multi-country AIDS program&#13;
&#13;
    -   (US$40million);&#13;
        LICUS grants to support governance, youth employment creation and the&#13;
        identification process (US$6 million).&#13;
&#13;
                         C.       DETAILEDPROJECTDESCRIPTION&#13;
&#13;
I. Objectives&#13;
&#13;
20.     The Project aims at: (i) enhancing the prospects for the stabilization and&#13;
recovery of C6te d'Ivoire by helping the country address its urgent post-conflict&#13;
challenges; and (ii)preparing the way for dealing adequately with medium and&#13;
longer-term reconstruction and development challenges. In particular, the Project&#13;
objectives are to (a) support the reinsertion and reintegration o f about 45,000 individuals&#13;
including ex-combatants, child soldiers and special groups3; (b) contribute to the&#13;
rehabilitation or reconstruction o f the social and economic infrastructure in the&#13;
communities most affected by the conflict; (c) assist vulnerable groups in (re)starting&#13;
economic activities; and (d) strengthen social capital throughout the country. This will&#13;
have a significant impact on reducing poverty and contributing to future economic&#13;
growth by encouraging IDPs and refugees to resume productive lives, improving access&#13;
to basic social services, investing in the human capital o f ex-combatants, and enhancing&#13;
the implementation capacity o fcommunity-based development organizations.&#13;
&#13;
21.     Project objectives will be pursued through three components: (a) a&#13;
demobilization, reinsertion and reintegration (DDR) component as provided for in the&#13;
Linas-Marcoussis Agreement; (b) a community rehabilitation (RC) component to help&#13;
build capacity and provide funding for community-based infrastructure, income&#13;
generation and reconciliation for the groups and localities most affected by the conflict;&#13;
and (c) an institution building and project management component to support project&#13;
implementation. It i s important to note that the World Bank project will not finance&#13;
either the disarmament or the demobilization.&#13;
&#13;
11.     DDR ProgramComponent&#13;
&#13;
22.     The National Program for the Disarmament, Demobilization and&#13;
Reintegration of ex-combatants and for Community Rehabilitation(PNDDWRC)&#13;
and World Bank Contribution. The DDR component will finance part o f a&#13;
comprehensive national DDR program (known as the PNDDR/RC), which has been&#13;
validated by representatives o f the belligerent parties. This program outlines all o f the&#13;
elements of the DDR process, starting with a substantial exercise in sensitizing all the&#13;
parties concerned by it (particularly the beneficiaries and the communities o f return), all&#13;
the way through to the social and economic reintegration of ex-combatants into their&#13;
communities. The World Bank will finance communication and sensitization activities,&#13;
as well as the reinsertion and reintegration of ex-combatants, including special programs&#13;
&#13;
 Estimatesare as follows: 4,000 child soldiers, 3,150 war widows and orphans, and 37,850 ex-combatants&#13;
(4,000 FDS, 2,000 militias, and 31,850 FAFN).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
for child soldiers and other vulnerable groups. Support for reinsertion will be provided&#13;
through a fast-disbursing mechanism whereby IDA finds will reimbursea positive list o f&#13;
imports for up to US$39.6 million equivalent (see Section D 11).&#13;
&#13;
23.     Sensitization and Communication. Prior to the launching o f the actual DDR&#13;
process, the PNDDR/RC will conduct a campaign to sensitize both the potential&#13;
beneficiaries (eligible combatants and special groups) and the communities to which they&#13;
will return as to the content and implications o f the program, to counter dangerous&#13;
rumors and secure heartfelt participation. Specific communication activities aimed at&#13;
reconciliation will be carried out in communities where the return o f ex-combatants may&#13;
cause tension or hostility. This sensitization and reconciliation service will continue&#13;
throughout the life o f the program as necessary.&#13;
&#13;
24.     Timing. The PNDDRwill cover the whole country. The presence o f over 10,000&#13;
internationalpeacekeeping forces will provide sufficient security to carry out the exercise&#13;
simultaneously throughout the country. The total time to complete pre-cantonment,&#13;
cantonment, disarmament and demobilization i s expected to be about three months,&#13;
assuming no unexpected delays.&#13;
&#13;
25.     Security. During the period o f pre-cantonment, cantonment, disarmament and&#13;
demobilization, all army personnel will be confined to barracks. In the areas formerly&#13;
held by government forces, the police and gendarmerie will be allowed to operate&#13;
normally and use "the weapons deemed adequate for the situation at hand". Inthe areas&#13;
formerly held by the FAFN and the "neutral zone", the bulk o f the security will be&#13;
undertaken by the impartial forces, which will also provide exclusive security for the&#13;
DDRprocess and sites. For more general civilian policing, contingencies havebeenmade&#13;
to use mixed patrols o f FANCI, FAFN and impartial forces. In addition, some 600&#13;
"police auxiliaries" were trained by ONUCI for deployment in the FN zone during the&#13;
disarmament and demobilization phase. The cost o f the impartial forces i s being and will&#13;
continue to be metby France and the contributors to the UNPeaceKeeping Operation.&#13;
&#13;
26.     Pre-cantonment and cantonment. This initial stage is crucial for confidence-&#13;
buildingmeasures as forces will exchange lists o f combatants and munitions. This period&#13;
will allow sufficient time for the identification process o f combatants to take place. After&#13;
status verification, each combatant will be registered and submitted to socioeconomic&#13;
profiling that will serve as baseline information for future re-integration activities. In&#13;
addition, medical teams will carry out medical screenings to identify serious diseases or&#13;
impairments that may affect ex-combatants' economic and social reintegration. Voluntary&#13;
counseling and testing for HIV/AIDS will also be offered. Cantonment sites will be&#13;
intermediate stops between the pre-cantonment and the disarmament sites, with the&#13;
purpose o fregulatingthe influx o f combatants into the disarmament sites.&#13;
&#13;
27.     Disarmament.Combatants will be called forward to the disarmament sites inunit&#13;
formation (11 in total) in batches o f more or less 150 per day, with their weapons (hand&#13;
held only). While the first two stages are under the responsibility o f the local forces,&#13;
starting with the disarmament phase the PNDDIURC will be in charge with ONUCI&#13;
providing support and oversight. Therefore the official registration o f armaments will&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
happen on disarmament sites under the supervision o f both PNDDR/RC and ONUCI.&#13;
Depending on their status and eligibility, combatants will then be transferred to&#13;
demobilization sites to be formally demobilized, to transit and orientation centers (CTOs)&#13;
ifthey areminors, andto armybarracks ifthey are ex-servicemen who want to remainin&#13;
the military.Combatants will be stationed indisarmament sites for one day.&#13;
&#13;
28.     Demobilization. Over a period o f about a week in specially prepared&#13;
demobilization sites, ex-combatants will receive a number o f services. These include the&#13;
following:&#13;
0   Formal demobilization and issuance o f a demobilization identity document (ID).&#13;
0   Pre-discharge orientation (counseling) to provide ex-combatants with critical&#13;
    information about project benefits, reintegration opportunities, health issues, civic&#13;
    rights and duties (including women's legal rights), etc. Special modules will be&#13;
    offered for female and disabled ex-soldiers targeting their special reintegration needs.&#13;
0   Transport organized by the PNDDWRC from the discharge centers to the regional&#13;
    DDRoffices inthe regiono ftheir choice.&#13;
&#13;
29.     Eligibility.All those requesting participation inthe IDA-fundedprogram will be&#13;
required to sign a declaration accepting the terms and conditions o f such participation.&#13;
The IDA funded re-insertion andre-integration program will be open to:&#13;
0   All those (male or female) recruited after September 19, 2002 into the fighting forces&#13;
    involved inthe Ivorian armed conflict;&#13;
0   All individuals under the age of 18 that are considered "child soldiers" as defined by&#13;
    the Cape Town Principles concerning child soldiers;&#13;
0   The widows and orphans o f combatants killedthe duringthe conflict.&#13;
&#13;
30,     Reinsertion. Transitional safety net assistance will be provided by the&#13;
Government to support ex-combatants for a limited period following their return to&#13;
civilian life. To support this effort, the Project will reimburse a positive list o f imports for&#13;
up to US$39.6 million equivalent. The transitional safety net has been calculated by the&#13;
Ivoirian government to be the cash equivalent o f a defined basket o f basic goods (e.g.,&#13;
household items, clothing and cooking utensils) and services (e.g., children's education)&#13;
enabling the beneficiary family unit to re-establish a civilian household. It has been set at&#13;
499,500 CFA (close to US$l,OOO equivalent per beneficiary). A first tranche equivalent&#13;
to 25 percent o f the total will be paid upon arrival at the regional DDR office,&#13;
immediately after discharge from the demobilization site, and two subsequent tranches&#13;
will bepaid 45 days and 90 days after the first tranche.&#13;
&#13;
31.     Reintegration.Economic and social reintegration assistance will be provided to&#13;
help ex-combatants establish sustainable livelihoods and encourage appropriate use o fthe&#13;
reinsertion assistance. The following guiding principles will apply: (a) minimize market&#13;
distortions and maximize beneficiary choice, (b) provide assistance that leads to&#13;
sustainable livelihoods, (c) involve communities o f settlement and foster reconciliation,&#13;
and (d) to the extent possible, benefit the wider community.&#13;
0   Economic reintegration. Ex-combatants will be equally eligible irrespective o f rank&#13;
    or former military affiliation and they will be allowed to choose their reintegration&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
     destination freely. Assistance will be offered in different forms, including:&#13;
     information, counseling and referral services; vocational training, apprenticeship&#13;
     schemes and educational opportunities; employment; provision o f seeds and tools.&#13;
0    Social reintegration. Specific activities will include: (a) information and sensitization&#13;
     o f ex-combatants, communities and society-at-large through outreach services,&#13;
     including training o f counselors, (b) specialized counseling, and (c) strengthening o f&#13;
     community services.&#13;
&#13;
32.      Special Groups for Reintegration. Three groups will receive particular&#13;
attention to facilitate their social and economic reintegration: female ex-combatants,&#13;
widows and orphans o f combatants, and combatants who have been disabled as a result&#13;
o f the conflict. A premise i s that these groups, and especially female ex-combatants, have&#13;
strengths and experiences that will help facilitate their reintegration into mainstream&#13;
social and economic life. The PNDDRRC also recognizes, however, the needfor special&#13;
support. This will include access to: (i)  specialized counseling; (ii) assistance to establish&#13;
peer-support groups; (iii)    medical treatment and rehabilitation; and (iv) support from&#13;
special programs inresponse to women's needs.&#13;
&#13;
33.      Child Soldiers4. Child ex-combatants among armed groups and forces are&#13;
estimated to be only about 4,000 but they will need priority assistance. The PNDDRRC&#13;
will work hand in hand with the relevant government ministries, UNICEF (as lead&#13;
agency) and specialized NGOs. The child soldier program has been established by&#13;
experts based on current best practice and has benefited from the experience o f a pilot&#13;
program financed by a Post-Conflict Fund grant. The guiding principle i s to secure the&#13;
release o f all children associatedwith the fighting forces and to promote as far as possible&#13;
their earliest re-unification with their families. Child soldiers will be separated from the&#13;
adults and the mainstream DDR program as soon as presented to the program. They will&#13;
be taken to special transit and orientation centers (CTOs) for children where experts will&#13;
assess their needs and define the best approach for re-integrating the child into society.&#13;
This may require lengthy detoxification and other psychological support, but the ultimate&#13;
goal i s to return the children to their family -- on no account are the CTOs to become&#13;
permanent orphanages. Tracing services will endeavor to find the child's family. Older&#13;
children may be suitable for independent group placement. Some may require support to&#13;
return to school, others may be more appropriately orientated towards vocational training,&#13;
or even directly into jobs.&#13;
&#13;
    111.    RC ProgramComponent&#13;
&#13;
34.      Overview. This component aims at meeting the short to medium-term needs of&#13;
returning rehgees/IDPs and the communities most affected by the conflict by using a&#13;
CDD approach. Its activities are meant to complement those financed by the restructured&#13;
projects in the Bank portfolio, and will be closely coordinated with such projects.&#13;
Through sub-project grants, the RC component will support the following activities: (a)&#13;
reconstruction, rehabilitation and re-equipment o f community level infrastructure, (b)&#13;
support to vulnerable groups (re)starting income generating activities, and (c) restoration&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 All individualswho havenotyet turned 18 onthe day the DDRprogramstarts are consideredas children.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
o f social capital at the community level. Implementation arrangements o f the RC&#13;
component draw extensively from best practices and lessons learned from similar&#13;
interventions in Sierra Leone, Ethiopia, Eritrea and Rwanda, as well as the cumulated&#13;
experience o f CDD-type operations. In addition, two pilot operations inthe center, north&#13;
and west financed by grants from the World Bank Post Conflict Fund have made it&#13;
possible to test and refine the proposed mechanisms.&#13;
&#13;
35.     Sub-projects qualifying for support under the R C component will be developed&#13;
and implemented inaccordance with the following principles (see also Attachment 4): (a)&#13;
enhance the opportunities for self-reliance o f displaced and rehgee populations, as well&#13;
as war-affected communities; (b) foster stabilization, equality, trust building and&#13;
reconciliation through a community-based approach; (c) strengthen local capacity to&#13;
implement and manage reconstruction, rehabilitation and development activities; (d)&#13;
promote awareness and sensitivity for gender equity and the protection o f the specially&#13;
disadvantaged (e.g., children, widows, the disabled and the elderly); (e) maximize&#13;
grassroots participation and input in the sub-project cycle; and (9 promote an integrated&#13;
approach to resettlement and rehabilitation.&#13;
&#13;
36.     Sub-component 1: Reconstruction and rehabilitation of community&#13;
infrastructure. Infrastructure damaged or looted during the conflict will be rebuilt,&#13;
repaired and refurbishedin accordance with the preferences expressed by the community,&#13;
usinga CDD approach. This means that communities will be responsible for all stages o f&#13;
sub-project implementation, with support from NGOs or other specialized entities as&#13;
needed. As the experience o f conflict i s often accompanied by feelings o f powerlessness&#13;
and confusion, allowing beneficiaries to have as much control as possible over their sub-&#13;
projects will contribute to the healing process. Sub-projects may include rehabilitating or&#13;
equipping collective infrastructure such as schools, health centers, bridges, markets, and&#13;
water supply systems inthe communities hardest hitby the conflict.&#13;
&#13;
37.     Sub-component2: Supportto incomegeneratingactivities.The primary target&#13;
o f this sub-component will be vulnerable groups such as female-headed households,&#13;
youth at risk, and IDPshefugees willing and able to go back to their communities o f&#13;
origin. Services provided will be geared toward puttinghouseholds and individuals back&#13;
on their feet through the provision o f small grants for, among others, equipment and&#13;
training to restart pre-war activities, and in certain cases initiate new income-generating&#13;
activities. Support to these groups will be channeled primarily through the community,&#13;
andtechnical support agencies will provide supervision and assistance.&#13;
&#13;
38.     Sub-component 3: Restorationof social capital at the community level. This&#13;
sub-component will aim at developing self-reliance and social capital within a spirit o f&#13;
stabilization and reconciliation. It will include a wide range o f activities proposed by&#13;
actors within or outside the community and its implementation will be sub-contracted to&#13;
NGOs. The activities to be financed under this sub-component will revolve around&#13;
communication for social cohesion and the promotion o f solidarity and reconciliation&#13;
through public events and group activities such as village theatre, traditional dancing,&#13;
sport events, inter-communal meetings and radio programs. A pilot project implemented&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
by the US-based NGO Search for Common Ground and financed by the World Bank&#13;
Post-Conflict Fundwill guide implementationo f this sub-component.&#13;
&#13;
   IV. InstitutionBuildingandProjectAdministrationComponent&#13;
&#13;
39.      Institutional support and capacity building. Staff development at the central&#13;
and local levels i s critical for effective program implementation. Therefore, while a&#13;
competitive hiringprocess should result inthe selection o f high-quality personnel, staff at&#13;
all levels will undergo training as necessary. The Project will also support targeted&#13;
capacity-building o f partner              organizations,      including     local    governments         and&#13;
communities, as required to attain the objectives o f the project. In addition, local and/or&#13;
expatriate technical assistance and consultancies will be financed throughout&#13;
implementation, including for external audits and independent evaluations.&#13;
&#13;
40.      Support to Project Administration.Project implementation will be supported&#13;
by financing: (a) most o f the operating costs of the PNDDRRC and a fiduciary&#13;
management agency; (b) equipment and vehicles; and (c) rehabilitation o f office space.&#13;
&#13;
  D.        INSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTSAND PROJECTIMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
I. InstitutionalArrangements&#13;
&#13;
41.      The Prime Minister is responsible for the implementation of the DDR&#13;
process and of all other emergency programs. The institutional framework, mandate,&#13;
organization and functioning o f the PNDDR/RC are established in a decree (arr&amp;e?&#13;
signed by the Prime Minister on June 1, 2006. The program is headed by a Coordinator&#13;
with a ministerial rank, nominated by a presidential decree and reporting directly to the&#13;
Prime Minister, while an Inter-ministerial Coordination Committee exercises general&#13;
oversight functions5. Responsibility for day-to-day operations rests with a General&#13;
Secretary, who supervises three operational units: the DDR unit in charge o f&#13;
disarmament, demobilization, reinsertion and reintegration o f ex-combatants; the unit in&#13;
charge o f dismantling and disarming militias; and the R C unit in charge o f community&#13;
rehabilitation. It should be noted that IDA financing will only contribute to the activities&#13;
carried out in the context of the reinsertion and reintegration o f ex-combatants and&#13;
community rehabilitation, as well as general fiduciary responsibilities.&#13;
&#13;
42.      Based on experience from other post-conflictprojectsin Africa, management&#13;
of the DDR and RC components will be kept separate, with separate designated&#13;
accounts and separate componentcoordinators.However, close links will be retained&#13;
to ensure consistent and complementary approaches. General services, such as&#13;
communication and general support services, will be common to both components, and&#13;
will be placed directly under the General Secretary. Financial management, accounting,&#13;
&#13;
  The Inter-ministerial Coordination Committee comprises: the Prime Minister (President of the&#13;
Committee), the Minister in charge of the Reconstruction and Reinsertion Program, the Minister o f&#13;
Defense, the Minister o f Interior, the Minister of national Reconciliation and Relations with Institutions, the&#13;
delegate Minister in charge of Economy and Finance, and the Director of Cabinet of the Prime Minister&#13;
(Secretary).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
and procurement will be delegated to an independent fiduciary management agency that&#13;
will report to the Coordinator for day-to-day transactions and to the Ministryof Finance&#13;
for overall use o f donor and Government counterpart funds under its management. The&#13;
PNDDWRC will have an accountant who will be responsible for communication and&#13;
coordination between the PNDDWRC and the fiduciary agency.&#13;
&#13;
43.     Regional offices will be established for both components for more efficient&#13;
implementation and greater proximityto beneficiaries.The number of DDR and RC&#13;
regional offices will be finalized depending on implementation needs, but the original&#13;
assumptions indicate the immediate need for six regional DDR offices and eight regional&#13;
R C offices (see organigram in Attachment 2). Each regional DDR or RC office will be&#13;
headed by a Regional DDR or RC Coordinator. Day-to-day administration will be&#13;
provided by staff selected ina competitive manner on technical grounds. The selection o f&#13;
key contractual staff will be submittedto IDA for prior review. Policies and procedures&#13;
relative to financial management, administration, and the execution o f the two&#13;
components will be set forth in the Project Implementation Manual (PIM) and will be&#13;
supported by a modular management information system.&#13;
&#13;
11.     ImplementationMechanisms&#13;
&#13;
DDRimplementationmechanisms&#13;
&#13;
44.     The implementationmechanisms for the DDR component are outlinedin the&#13;
PNDDWRC and detailedin the PIM.The management o fthe DDRprogramwill come&#13;
under a specialized unit that will carry overall responsibility for all aspects o f the DDR&#13;
process, It should be noted, however, that the pre-cantonment and cantonment exercises,&#13;
though planned and overseen by members o f the PNDDR/RC with assistance from&#13;
impartial forces, will actually be carried out largely by the forces themselves; in addition,&#13;
GTZ has been contracted by the PNDDRRC to provide logistical support. Inparticular,&#13;
the PNDDFVRC will be responsible for: (i)       developing and maintaining the information&#13;
system that will store and transfer relevant program data (and keep it confidential); (ii)&#13;
organizing the payments o f the safety net allowance; (iii)  providing, in conjunction with&#13;
UNICEF and other specialized agencies, child protection services for child soldiers; and&#13;
(iv) providing tailored services for special groups.&#13;
&#13;
45.     Reintegration services, such as training or employment initiatives, will be&#13;
providedby suitableentities identifiedand sub-contractedby the PNDDWRC.Such&#13;
entities will be selected with a transparent process on a competitive basis and according&#13;
to the criteria set forth in the DDR part o f the PIM. They may be private or public, local&#13;
or international. To promote a responsible use o f the funds made available, ex-&#13;
combatants will be requested to sign a "contract" with the PNDDRRC and the service&#13;
provider. DDR regional offices and district program officers will be responsible for&#13;
identifying partners that can assist with training or employment opportunities and for&#13;
orienting ex-combatants towards appropriate reintegration initiatives. Regional and&#13;
district DDR staff will also play a key role in monitoring the successful social re-&#13;
integration o f ex-combatants into the community, paying particular attention to known&#13;
vulnerable individuals.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RCimplementationmechanisms&#13;
&#13;
46.     For the implementation of the RC component, the PNDDWRC will rely on&#13;
Regional RC Offices and will subcontract technical support agencies (NGOs and&#13;
other private agencies). These technical support agencies will be selected following a&#13;
Request o f Expression of Interest published in local and international media (e.g.,&#13;
Development Business), and a subsequent Requestfor Proposals. They will presentrecent&#13;
audit reports and will submit themselves to auditing during the course o f project&#13;
implementation. At the community level, implementation arrangements will be based on&#13;
best practice from social fund-type projects and operate according to CDD principles,&#13;
with technical support agencies providing support as needed (see Attachment 4). To&#13;
ensure consistency, build confidence, and promote transparency and accountability, all&#13;
aspects o f the sub-project cycle will be described in the PIM in a section specific to the&#13;
RC component, which will be accessible to the general public. A simplified version will&#13;
also be produced for disseminationto beneficiaries.&#13;
&#13;
47.     For sub-components 1and 2, sub-projectimplementationwill be entrustedto&#13;
direct beneficiaries or community-basedorganizations. For this reason, procedures&#13;
will be kept simple and flexible, with an eye to minimizingpaperwork and the need for&#13;
community implementers to travel. In particular, procedures for community-based&#13;
procurement and financial management will be followed. RC Regional Coordinators will&#13;
not be expected to be directly involved inimplementation, but rather to concentrate on (a)&#13;
review o f sub-project planning processes (for conformity to the procedures set in the&#13;
PIM) and technical soundness; and (b) monitoring and evaluation of the activities o f&#13;
technical support agencies and communities. Sub-component 3 will be implemented by&#13;
the NGOs whose proposals will have been selected inaccordance with the procedures set&#13;
forth in the PIM. Further details on implementation mechanisms can be found in&#13;
Attachment 4.&#13;
&#13;
111.    FinancialManagement,Auditing andReporting&#13;
&#13;
48.     Overall Program Accounting and Reporting. A Fiduciary Management&#13;
Agency (FMA) will have the overall responsibility for Project accounting and reporting.&#13;
Thus, while the PNDDWRC will be responsible for the physical implementation o f the&#13;
program, the FMA will be responsible for financial management and procurement,&#13;
maintaining IDA resources' budget and accounts. To that end, the FMA will use the&#13;
existing PNDDRRC computerized and integrated financial management system&#13;
appropriate to the scale and nature o f the program and capable of recording and reporting&#13;
in a timely manner the program operations by origin o f funds, by regions, components,&#13;
activities and expenditure categories. The computerized financial management system i s&#13;
multi-currency, multi-location, multi-donor and include, among others, the following&#13;
modules: general accounting, cost accounting, budgeting, assets management, contract&#13;
management, preparation o f withdrawal applications and tracking o f disbursements by&#13;
donors, reports generating, including quarterly financial monitoring reports and semi-&#13;
annual financial statements. The financial management specialist o fthe P N D D W C will&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
be responsible for coordination and communication with the FMA to ensure timely and&#13;
acceptable consolidated financial statements o f all Program's activities including IDA,&#13;
Government and other donors.&#13;
&#13;
49.     As part o f the PIM, a Financial and Accounting Procedures Manual will be&#13;
developed and will include a description o f salient features o f the financial management&#13;
system and financial policies and procedures. It will describe: (i) the overall organization&#13;
o f the program including an organizational diagram andjob description o f the accounting&#13;
and financial staff; (ii) the accounting system to be used: chart o f accounts, budget&#13;
coding, accounting standards; (iii)the main transactions cycles; (iv) internal control&#13;
procedures; and (iv) a summary o f the various operational procedures related to budget&#13;
management (planning, execution and monitoring) and management o f assets,&#13;
procurement o f works, goods and services, and disbursements, which are detailed in the&#13;
PIM.&#13;
&#13;
50.     Financial Management Risks. The financial management risks are expected to&#13;
behigh for the followingreasons: (i)governance and transparency deteriorated duringthe&#13;
conflict; (ii)it i s a complex and relatively large project; (iii)the PNDDRRC has&#13;
practically no experience with Bank procedures; and (iv) the control environment i s&#13;
generally weak in a post conflict country. However, this risk will be mitigated by&#13;
enhancing the control environment. This will include (a) recruiting an independent FMA&#13;
that will report directly to the Coordinator; and (b) putting in place an independent&#13;
internal audit function. Semi-annual technical and financial audits including an opinion&#13;
on the project's performance during the first year will also provide an early feedback on&#13;
the project and on the FMA's performance.&#13;
&#13;
51.     Staffing.A qualified financial management specialist with relevant experience in&#13;
donor funded projects will be responsible for coordination between the PNDDRRC and&#13;
the FMA to ensure accurate and timely consolidated financial statements. The FMA will&#13;
have staff inthe regional offices.&#13;
&#13;
52.     Reporting.      Financial reports will provide information to monitor the&#13;
achievement o f the program development objectives. They should therefore capture all&#13;
sources o f funding, with sufficient segregation o f data to permit identification o f&#13;
individual sources (including counterpart funds) and disbursements on major program&#13;
activities or types o f expenditure, as well as any balance(s) o f funds. Financial reports&#13;
should cover the needs o f all donors and consist o f a Cash Flow Statement together with&#13;
accompanying notes. Quarterly financial monitoring reports will be prepared and&#13;
submitted to the Bank 45 days after the closing o f the quarter following the date o f&#13;
effectiveness. The financial monitoring reports will be based on Annex A, Sample I11o f&#13;
the Bank's Guidelines on financial monitoring reports or on any other report acceptable&#13;
by the Bank that will include financial, physical progress and procurement information.&#13;
The information contained in the quarterly reports should be sufficient to establish&#13;
whether: (i)funds disbursedto the project are being used for the intendedpurposes; (ii)&#13;
project implementation i s on track; and (iii) budgeted costs will not be exceeded. The&#13;
financial reports should be prepared in a structure and detail that facilitate comparison&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
with physical progress. Annual audit o f financial statements are required and will&#13;
comprise but will not be limitedto: (i) Statement o f Source and Application o f Funds&#13;
                                         the&#13;
for the Program during the current financial year, and cumulatively since the start o f the&#13;
Program; (ii)the statement o f expenditures (SOEs); (iii)the Designated Account&#13;
StatementReconciliation; and (iv) the Project Account StatementReconciliation and any&#13;
other financial report deemed necessary and relevant. As an additional safeguard, the first&#13;
year semi annual technical and financial audits will be conducted.&#13;
&#13;
53.      Flow of Funds. The Project will have two Designated Accounts, one covering&#13;
expenditures related to the DDRcomponent (excluding the transitional safety net) as well&#13;
as general project management expenditures, and the other covering expenditures related&#13;
to the R C component. Both Designated Accounts will be located at the Central Bank o f&#13;
West African States (BCEAO) and will have advance accounts ina commercial bankthat&#13;
will be managed by the FMA in accordance with Bank guidelines. In addition, two&#13;
separate accounts will be established at the BCEAO for the project's quick disbursing&#13;
component, and the government counterpart funds. To facilitate quick disbursements, the&#13;
Bank has agreed with the Government on a special procedure for emergency projects that&#13;
allows project funds to by-pass the cumbersome regular national procedures. Should it&#13;
become necessary to establish regional sub-accounts (30 days advance), an effort will be&#13;
made to accommodate such need, provided the Bank approves o f the accounting system&#13;
put in place. The PNDDRRC will coordinate all withdrawals and replenishment of the&#13;
DesignatedAccounts with the FMA.&#13;
&#13;
54.      Quick DisbursingMechanism.The timely availability and flow o f fundingwill&#13;
be critical to enable the Government to implement the DDR process within the planned&#13;
timeframe.     The Project will therefore use a quick disbursement mechanism in&#13;
accordance with Bank's guidelines for Emergency Recovery Credits. Under this&#13;
provision, the Government will be eligible for reimbursement o f up to a total o f&#13;
US$39.6 million equivalent against a positive list o f imports. Retroactive financing will&#13;
be possible for expenses that have been incurred up to four months prior to the expected&#13;
date o f signature o f the Financing Agreement. A joint Governmenth3an.k team will be&#13;
formed to compile and review the list o f positive imports and related procurement&#13;
documentation. The first payment against a positive list o f imports will consist o f&#13;
US$10 million equivalent and will be made at effectiveness so as to help cover&#13;
expenditures for the first tranche o f the transitional safety net for ex-combatants. The&#13;
second payment o f US$10 million equivalent will be made when the Beneficiary&#13;
furnishes to IDA evidence in form and substance satisfactory to IDA showing that a&#13;
random sample o f at least five percent o f the demobilized combatants have received the&#13;
first tranche o f the transitional safety net with less than a 5% error. The third and last&#13;
payment o f US$19.6 million will be made when the Beneficiary furnishes to IDA&#13;
evidence in form and substance satisfactory to IDA showing that a random sample o f at&#13;
least five percent o f the demobilized combatants have received the second tranche o f the&#13;
transitional safety net with less than a 5% error.&#13;
&#13;
55.      Safeguards to ensure the proper use of funds. Safeguards will be built into the&#13;
program to ensure that funds are utilized for the purposes intended:&#13;
   (a) Disbursements will be linked to project implementation progress;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   (b) A fiduciary management agency will be recruited 'for all financial transactions,&#13;
         accounting and procurement purposes;&#13;
   (c) External financial audits will be undertaken at least annually to verify the&#13;
         appropriate use o f funds, and every six months for the first year;&#13;
   (d) A non-transferable photograph ID will be provided to each ex-combatant (this&#13;
         should be used to verify ex-combatants' eligibility for assistance), and lists o f&#13;
        beneficiaries will be kept at the regional offices;&#13;
   (e) A management information system will be established to allow for close&#13;
        monitoring o fproject implementation at central and local levels;&#13;
   ( f ) Regular surveys o f a representative subset o f beneficiaries will track program&#13;
         delivery and use of funds by ex-combatants; and&#13;
   (g) Regular supervision missions will be carried out in collaboration with national&#13;
         authorities.&#13;
&#13;
56.      Audit Requirements. The financial statements of the program will be audited&#13;
semi-annually for the first year and annually thereafter by an independent auditor&#13;
acceptable to the Bank in accordance with international auditing standards. Audit reports&#13;
o f such scope and detail agreed by IDA would be submitted to the Bank within 60 days&#13;
after the end o f the audit period. The auditor will provide a separate opinion on each: (i)&#13;
the program financial statements (Statement o f Source and Application o f Funds,&#13;
explanatory notes, etc.); (ii)the Statement o f Expenditures; and (iii)the Designated&#13;
Account. In addition, technical audits carried out in parallel with financial audits will&#13;
provide opinions on program performance, that is, project progress and timeliness in&#13;
relation to progress milestones and objectives stated in the Technical Annex, as well as&#13;
the economy and efficiency with which the progradproject is being implemented. The&#13;
financial auditor will also provide a management letter on the internal control procedures&#13;
outlining any recommendations for improving the control system, the accounting and&#13;
financial procedures as a result o f the financial statements audit.&#13;
&#13;
111.      Procurement&#13;
&#13;
57.       General. Procurement arrangements and procedures have been devised to be&#13;
commensurate with the emergency nature o f the project. Also, the need has been&#13;
recognized for simple mechanisms to facilitate the procurement or contracting o f various&#13;
reintegration assistance packages for ex-combatants. Therefore, the arrangements&#13;
envisaged are aimed at maximizing efficiency and flexibility, mixing procurement on the&#13;
local market in the conflict affected areas with procurement and distribution from&#13;
regional, national and international levels. NGOs will be involved inthe implementation&#13;
of the project, particularly for community-based actions. Procurement procedures under&#13;
the project will be prepared by the Beneficiary and included in the PIM that will be&#13;
submitted for IDA approval. For the project implementation, IDAprocurement guidelines&#13;
and policies will be followed. The FMA will be responsible for procurement as well as&#13;
financial management.&#13;
&#13;
58.      Procurement Planning. Relevant IDA guidelines and procedures will operate&#13;
for goods, works and services. Procurement plans will be prepared and will provide the&#13;
basis for agreement with IDA on the proposed packaging and the optimal methods o f&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
procurement.    A general procurement plan for the entire duration of project&#13;
implementation will be included in the PIM. A detailed procurement plan has been&#13;
prepared for the duration o f the project. Both general and detailed procurement plan&#13;
prepared by the Beneficiary have beenfinalized duringnegotiations. The agreed plan will&#13;
be updated on a yearly basis and sent to IDA for approval. Community sub-projects will&#13;
not need to be included in the procurement plan because their demand-driven nature&#13;
makes it difficult to finalize procurement plans in advance. However, the agreement&#13;
document o f each approved sub-project will include a procurement schedule for&#13;
completing the sub-project.&#13;
&#13;
59.    InstitutionalArrangementsfor Procurement. Procurement will be done at two&#13;
levels: (a) national level by the FMA; and (b) local level by community-based&#13;
organizations and NGOs. The FMA procurement staff should be familiar with World&#13;
Bank's procurement procedures and will have the following responsibilities: (i)&#13;
procurement o f all major items under ICB, N C B and all consulting services (including&#13;
NGOs); (ii)  monitoring all procurement activities o f the Project at all levels; and (iii)&#13;
building capacity o f NGOs and others partners as needed. Procurement for community&#13;
sub-projects will generally be carried out by the communities themselves with the&#13;
technical support o fNGOs and consultants,&#13;
&#13;
60.    ProcurementProcedures. Simplifiedprocedures for emergency projects will be&#13;
usedwherever needed. Procurement o f civil works, goods and consultants will be carried&#13;
out in accordance with the World Bank's "Guidelines: Procurement under IBRD Loans&#13;
and IDA Credits" dated May 2004 and "Guidelines: Selection and Employment o f&#13;
Consultants by World Bank's Borrowers" dated May 2004. Bank's Standard bidding&#13;
documents and evaluation forms will be used. Procurement for the community sub-&#13;
projects will be processed in accordance with paragraph 3.15 o f the Bank's procurement&#13;
guidelines (Community Participation in Procurement) and the Bank's Guidelines for&#13;
Simpliped Procurement and Disbursementfor Community-Based Investments (February&#13;
1998). The PIM would describe in detail the specific procurement arrangements o f the&#13;
community-based component.&#13;
&#13;
61.    Procurementof ConsultantServices&#13;
    0  Firms: Consultant services will be procured on the basis of: (i)  Quality-and-Cost-&#13;
       Based Selection (QCBS) by evaluating the quality ofproposals by qualified short-&#13;
       listed firms before comparing the cost o f services to be provided; and (ii)  Least&#13;
       Cost Selection, for the project's financial audits. Contracts less than US$lOO,OOO&#13;
       each for firms could be contracted on the basis o f CQ or may be awarded on a&#13;
       Single Source basis only in exceptional circumstances as stipulated in the&#13;
       Consultants Guidelines (items 3.9 to 3.1l), adequate justification and prior&#13;
                                                     after&#13;
       review by IDA.&#13;
    0  Individual Consultants: Individual Consultants will be selected under the&#13;
       provisions for the Selection o f Individual Consultants described in section V o f&#13;
       IDA'SConsultant Guidelines, Le., in essence through the comparison of the&#13;
       curriculum vitae o f at least three qualified individuals. Most o f the individual&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        consultant contracts worth less than US$50,000 may be awarded on a single&#13;
        source basis with IDA's prior review&#13;
&#13;
62.     To ensure that priority is given to national consultants, shortlists for contracts&#13;
estimated to cost under US$200,000 may be comprised entirely o f national consultants&#13;
(in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 2.7 o f Consultant Guidelines) if a&#13;
sufficient number o f qualified consultants are available at competitive costs. However, if&#13;
foreign firms have expressed interest, they will not be excluded.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    0   Procurement of goods. Individual contracts worth US$250,000 equivalent or&#13;
        above (excluding gasoline) will be awarded on the basis o f ICB. Individual&#13;
        contracts worth less than US$250,000 equivalent or contracts for gasoline&#13;
        estimated above $50,000 each will be awarded on the basis o f NCB. Contracts&#13;
       worth less than US$50,000 each may be awarded through National Shopping&#13;
       using approved procedures in accordance with IDA Guidelines and the June 9,&#13;
        2000, Memorandum `Guidance on Shopping' issued by the Bank.                   Direct&#13;
        contracting may be utilized only whenjustified in accordance with the Guidelines&#13;
        and only after prior review from IDA. Specific goods, such as vehicles and&#13;
       motorcycles, may be grouped and procured through IAPSO, in accordance with&#13;
        the provisions o f paragraph 3.9 o f the Guidelines.       The lists o f goods to be&#13;
       procured under this method will need to be included in the procurement plan&#13;
        which will receive IDA'snon-objection.&#13;
&#13;
    0   Procurementof works. Civilworks contracts will bevery limitedinnumber and&#13;
        in value. Hence, neither ICB nor NCB are foreseen under the project. Small&#13;
       refection and rehabilitation o f facilities estimated at less than US$50,000&#13;
        equivalent per contract may be procured under lump-sum, fixed-price contracts&#13;
        awarded on the basis o f quotations obtained from not less than three (3) qualified&#13;
        domestic contractors (preferably more inorder to obtain at least three comparable&#13;
        offers) invited inwriting to bid.&#13;
&#13;
63.     Prior Review Thresholds. Contracts for goods estimated to costs US$200,000&#13;
or more will require prior review by IDA. All single source contracts and the first two&#13;
contracts related to sub-projects per region will also be submitted to IDA's prior review.&#13;
IDA will review the selection process proposed by the Beneficiary for hiringconsultants,&#13;
but prior review will not be requiredfor contracts worth less than US$lOO,OOO for firms&#13;
and contracts worth less than US$50,000 for individuals. These thresholds may be&#13;
updated after the first year o f the project, based on project performance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                    Thresholds for ProcurementMethodsand PriorReview&#13;
&#13;
Expenditure Category       ContractValue       Procurement       Contracts Subjectto&#13;
                           Threshold (US$)     Method            Prior Review&#13;
&#13;
1.Works                    &lt;50,000             Quotation         Postreview&#13;
&#13;
2. Goods&#13;
                           &gt;250,000            ICB               All contracts&#13;
                           250,000-200,000     NCB               Prior review&#13;
                           ~200,000            NCB               Postreview&#13;
                           &lt; 50,000            Shopping          Postreview&#13;
                                               Directcontracting All contracts&#13;
&#13;
     Specificgoods         All values         IIAPSO             Prior review&#13;
&#13;
3. ConsultingServices      1&#13;
Firms                      &gt; 100,000           QCBS              All contracts&#13;
                           &lt; 100,000           QCBSICQSILCS      Postreview&#13;
                                               sss               All contracts&#13;
&#13;
Individuals                &gt; 50,000            3 cv              All contracts&#13;
                           &lt; 50,000            3 cv              Postreview&#13;
                                               sss               All contracts&#13;
&#13;
4. Sub-projects                                                  the first two (2) contracts relatedtc&#13;
                                                                 sub-projectsineachregion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  64.     RiskAssessment. Theprocurement capacity assessmentcannot be done since the&#13;
  entity that will run procurement i s not yet on board. Due to the country post-conflict&#13;
  environment and delays in implementing the procurement reform6, the procurement risk&#13;
  has been set as high and prior review thresholds fixed consequently. To mitigate&#13;
 procurement risks, the following actions have been recommended : (i)               selection of an&#13;
  independent Fiduciary Management Agency (FMA) with international experience and&#13;
  solid knowledge in Bank procurement; (ii)          use of Bank Standard Bidding Documents;&#13;
  (iii)effective internal control assured by PNDDR/RC staff (not by the FMA's staff );&#13;
  (iv) if needed, strengthening o f NGOs capacity by the FMA to help them better support&#13;
 communities-based procurement; (v) use o f the PIM approved by the Bank; (vi) quarterly&#13;
 Bank supervision; and (vii) an annual special procurement supervision for post review.&#13;
&#13;
     IV. MonitoringandEvaluation&#13;
&#13;
 65.      General. Project monitoring and evaluation will draw upon a comprehensive&#13;
 Management Information System (MIS) that will combine ina modular fashion databases&#13;
 relative to (a) individual ex-combatants information; (b) payments o f transitional safety&#13;
 net allowances; (c) employers, training providers, and consultants inprinciple accessible&#13;
&#13;
   The CPAR was been completedin2004. So far, there is no major progress in the implementationof the&#13;
 actionplandue to the countryvolatile situation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
to ex-combatants; (d) technical support agencies and prospective technical support&#13;
agencies to be sub-contracted for the RC component; (e) physical implementation o f&#13;
community sub-projects, by sub-project type; and (f)              accounting and financial&#13;
management information. Regional offices will have access to the M I S and will be&#13;
connected to the PNDDRRC headquarters via satellite, thus allowing for the timely&#13;
exchange o f information. In addition to the daily routine, ad hoc studies will be carried&#13;
out as needed. These will include a formal evaluation o f the demobilization process as&#13;
well as regular beneficiary assessments, combining both quantitative and qualitative&#13;
methods. A mid-term review will be carried out by the government and the Bank. An&#13;
implementation completion report will be prepared within six months o f the Grant&#13;
closing, with the government o f C8te d'Ivoire's contribution included.&#13;
&#13;
66.     The Monitoring and Evaluation Unit will ensure that information is provided and&#13;
sharedregularly, so as to be an effective tool for project management. The Unit will also&#13;
be responsible for measuring project performance against the agreed performance&#13;
indicators specified below. Specifically, the Unit will (a) monitor the hnctioning and&#13;
effective utilization o f the MIS; (b) organize and supervise ad hoc evaluation studies; (c)&#13;
provide timely feedback to management; and (d) prepare regular reports for the&#13;
Coordinator, the Inter-ministerial Coordination Committee and donors.&#13;
&#13;
67.     DDR Component. Monitoring of the DDR component aims at ensuring that&#13;
project benefits are provided in a timely and effective manner and that leakages are&#13;
minimal. Information on beneficiaries will be registered into the M I S during the pre-&#13;
cantonment, disarmament and demobilization phase and transmitted to the relevant&#13;
regional DDR office so as to allow individualized follow-up. At the same time, a robust&#13;
system o f non-transferable picture ID will deter misuse and make forgery difficult.&#13;
Regional offices will be expected to update information on each beneficiary promptly,&#13;
and transmit it to the PNDDWRC headquarters. At any point during project&#13;
implementation, therefore, the MIS should provide a comprehensive and detailed picture&#13;
of the status o f reintegration for each ex-combatant. Information on child soldiers will be&#13;
sent by the CTOs to the closest regional DDR office on a monthly basis (the CTOs will&#13;
not have direct access to the MIS), and the office will enter it into the system.&#13;
&#13;
68.     A strong local presence through the regional offices and, especially, the regular&#13;
visits o f "district monitors" will make it possible to follow project execution closely. In&#13;
addition, for the first year o f project implementation, each regional DDR office will have&#13;
a special liaison officer who will answer beneficiary concerns and take stock o f the&#13;
problems encountered.        The liaison officer will also make visits to a sample o f&#13;
combatants intheir community o f settlement with the purpose o f assessing the success o f&#13;
reintegration efforts and provide feedback to the program on a regular basis. Child&#13;
soldiers will be visited regularly by UNICEF teams and a Child Soldier Specialist from&#13;
the PNDDR/RC central office.&#13;
&#13;
69.     RC Component. Monitoring will be an integral part o f each sub-project&#13;
implementation, as disbursements o f tranches to each technical support agency and for&#13;
each community sub-project will be contingent on performance monitoring --by R C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Regional staff and by the technical support agencies, respectively. Monitoring and&#13;
evaluation mechanisms will be built into the RC information system, which will use a&#13;
software especially designed for social funds and adapted to the specific needs o f the R C&#13;
component. Data on key indicators (in terms o f both process and outputs) will be&#13;
generated quarterly andreviewedbyproject and Bank staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      ProgramPhase                       Key ProgramPerformanceIndicators&#13;
DDR&amp; RC: General            I e  Timely disbursement o f counterpart funds.&#13;
&#13;
information                      timely manner and inaccordance with the PIM, DDRpart.&#13;
DDR:Reinsertion               e  First reinsertionpayment to all demobilized ex-combatants made&#13;
                                 upon arrival at regional DDR offices.&#13;
                              e  Second and thirdreinsertion payments made ina timely manner&#13;
                                 and no later than six months after the previous payment, and in&#13;
                                 accordance with the PIM, DDR section.&#13;
                              e  Less than 5% error (double or incorrect payments) made in&#13;
                                 reinsertion payments, based o n a random sample.&#13;
DDR: Reintegration            e  70 % o f demobilizedex-combatants engaged insome type o f&#13;
                                 economic reintegration activity (training, small business&#13;
                                 assistance, agriculture activities, etc) within 6 months o f receiving&#13;
                                 last reinsertion payment.&#13;
                              e  Active program for female ex-combatants within 4 months o f end&#13;
                                 o f demobilization process.&#13;
                              e  70% of demobilized ex-combatants engaged inproductive&#13;
                                 economic activities (or schooling) 6 months after reintegration&#13;
                                 support is completed.&#13;
RC                            e  All RegionalCommunity RehabilitationCommittees inplace&#13;
                                 within 4 months o fproject effectiveness.&#13;
                              e  450 infrastructure sub-projects financed byproject end.&#13;
                              0   150 sub-projects supporting income-generation activities or&#13;
                                 employment creation financed by project end.&#13;
                              e  Monthly radio programs for social cohesion produced and aired in&#13;
                                 at least two local languages and French within 6 months o f project&#13;
                                 effectiveness.&#13;
                              e   100 community or inter-community solidarity events financed by&#13;
                                 project end.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IV.     ProjectSustainability&#13;
&#13;
71.     Emergency interventions such as the present one are intended to provide&#13;
immediate relief rather than promotingsustainable changes. Some o f the activities&#13;
financed by the project, therefore, are not meant to be sustainable, as they will not be&#13;
needed in a peaceful environment. Nevertheless, the project endeavors to provide a&#13;
bridge between humanitarian assistance and damage control on the one hand, and long-&#13;
term development on the other. The project has been designedina collaborative fashion,&#13;
by building on reviews and assessments of key socio-economic and other factors that&#13;
have andwill influence the emergency situation, with the aim o f laying the conditions for&#13;
sustainable recovery. Inparticular:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    0   The DDR component will support the sustainable reintegration of ex-&#13;
        combatants and child soldiers into civilian life with a view to becoming&#13;
        productivecitizens. The initial transition period, whereby adults will receive a&#13;
        reinsertion allowance and children will receive specialized services in CTOs, will&#13;
        provide an opportunity for beneficiaries to reenter into mainstream social and&#13;
        economic life in a gradual manner, while communication and mediation efforts&#13;
        with receiving communities and families should facilitate the process. Services&#13;
        offered as part o f the reintegration effort will provide beneficiaries with skills that&#13;
        will help them find sustainable economic activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    0   All three sub-components of the RC component have been designed in a way&#13;
        that maximizessustainability.Steps taken include: (a) community participation&#13;
        to ensure local ownership as well as motivation to maintain and operate assets&#13;
        created with project support; (b) community investments in sub-projects, and&#13;
        contracts on their maintenance responsibilities; (c) where applicable, prior&#13;
        commitment from the relevant government agency to support recurrent&#13;
        expenditures; (d) activities to strengthen social capital to promote community&#13;
        solidarity and continued cooperation;         and (e) community micro-planning&#13;
        exercises to encourage attention to sub-project sustainability in the medium and&#13;
        long-term.&#13;
&#13;
V.      Benefits&#13;
&#13;
72.     The key benefit of Bank assistance would be to acceleratethe stabilization of&#13;
the situation in C6te d'Ivoire, thereby helping create conditions under which CGte&#13;
d'Ivoire could resume pro-poor social and economic development. Stability and rule o f&#13;
law would help prevent the extension o f the conflict and its multi-faceted impacts to its&#13;
fragile neighbors; it would also facilitate the regional fight against epidemic diseases. The&#13;
conflict in CGte d'Ivoire has overflowed to jeopardize development and even security in&#13;
neighboringcountries; stability could return this well-endowed country to its role as an&#13;
engine o f growth for the sub-region.&#13;
&#13;
73.     Immediate assistance is also essential for the sake of C6te d'Ivoire's&#13;
seventeen million people. Humanitarian assistance on an extended basis breeds&#13;
dependence rather than self-reliance, grievance rather than acceptance and moving on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               26&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CBte d'Ivoire needs to re-launch development activities at the local, sector and national&#13;
levels. This project would provide resources to move from assistance to development and&#13;
pave the way for restructured and new projects inthe Bank portfolio. Inaddition, support&#13;
by the Bank would contribute to a comprehensive framework for other donors, thus&#13;
laying the grounds for a concerted effort towards sustainable reconstruction and the&#13;
returnto normal andproductive lives.&#13;
&#13;
VI.     Risks&#13;
&#13;
74.     The Bank's active engagement in Cate d'Ivoire during this period of crisis is&#13;
a high-risk, high-profile and potentially high-gain enterprise. The greatest risk,&#13;
however, i s failing to support the nascent normalization process and missing a window o f&#13;
opportunity for stabilizing a key country in an unstable region. Thus, while there i s no&#13;
guarantee that civil war will not erupt again or that the process o f inter-Ivorian dialogue&#13;
will not lead to a Government that has limitedcommitment to development, the risks o f&#13;
doing nothing are much greater. O f course, the risks associated with actively engaging in&#13;
an uncertain environment must be carehlly considered.            In this sense, the Interim&#13;
Strategy Note (ISN) identifies the main risks associated with a Bank presence in CBte&#13;
d'Ivoire and suggests mitigating responses. More specific risks associated with the&#13;
proposed operation are explored below.&#13;
&#13;
    e   Insuficient political commitment to peace and reconciliation. While there has&#13;
        been significant progress toward the implementation o f the Linas-Marcoussis&#13;
        Agreement, and more in general toward a return to normalcy, the path has been&#13;
        far from smooth. Leaders on both sides have at times behaved in a way that cast&#13;
        serious doubts over their true commitment to peace, and it i s clear that not all&#13;
        stakeholders are equally supportive o f a negotiated solution. Yet, there are strong&#13;
        internal and external forces pushing toward peace. Many religious groups,&#13;
        community associations andjust ordinary citizens continue to play a conciliatory&#13;
        role while regional leaders and the whole o f the international community have&#13;
        repeatedly called on the two sides to make a serious effort for the implementation&#13;
        of the peace agreements. The World Bank, as a member o f the International&#13;
        Working Group established to monitor and facilitate the implementation o f peace&#13;
        agreements, has the opportunity to support the stabilization process in a very&#13;
        effective manner.&#13;
&#13;
        Reversal of the peace process and resumption of hostilities. Many observers&#13;
        agree that sustainable peace will not be secured until the DDR and national&#13;
        identification processes are completed, the militias are disarmed and dismantled,&#13;
        and free and fair elections are held. The intervention o f peacekeeping forces has&#13;
        proved crucial in restoring order on a number o f occasions and their presence i s&#13;
        expected to last until the situation i s less fragile. The efforts o f the international&#13;
        community, combining soft diplomacy with more assertive stances (UN&#13;
        sanctions), have also been effective in keeping the peace process moving. In&#13;
        particular, careful monitoring o f the arms embargo has discouraged continued&#13;
        armament on both sides o f the confidence zone.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   0   Destabilization and absence of security. The militias (mostly inthe West but also&#13;
       in Abidjan) can play a significant destabilizing role. As stated in the Pretoria&#13;
       agreement, they should be disarmed and dismantled in parallel to the DDR&#13;
       process. In addition, the circulation o f large numbers o f light weapons may result&#13;
       in increased criminality, especially in the immediate post-disarmament period.&#13;
       Thus, after the beginningo fthe DDR,the capacity anddeployment o fthe security&#13;
       forces will be crucial to the sustainability o f the disarmament o f various groups.&#13;
       Therefore a solid and feasible restructuring o f the security sector i s also critical.&#13;
       The successful implementation of the security plan for Abidjan and the recent&#13;
       launching o f a national program against the proliferation o f light weapons could&#13;
       be an important contribution to improved security.&#13;
&#13;
       Insufficient implementation capacity. Both public and private sector capacity in&#13;
       CGte d'Ivoire have been weakened by administrative and educational crises and&#13;
       governance problems, while the massive displacements caused by the conflict&#13;
       may result in an uneven distribution o f skills and limit needed labor mobility.&#13;
       This situation may prove particularly problematic in view o f the decentralized&#13;
       nature o f the project, which will require the presence o f competent and dynamic&#13;
       individuals throughout the country both in regional DDR and RC offices and as&#13;
       implementing partners. The project will select staff and implementingpartners on&#13;
       a competitive and transparent basis, but also make technical assistance available if&#13;
       needed. The monitoring &amp; evaluation system will facilitate careful monitoring o f&#13;
       implementation progress, so as to be able to spot and address problems as they&#13;
       arise. In addition, the community approach adopted for many o f the project&#13;
       activities has proven effective in situations where capacity was arguably lower&#13;
       than inCGte d'Ivoire.&#13;
&#13;
VII.   EnvironmentalandSocialAspects&#13;
&#13;
75.    The reintegration of around 45,000 ex-combatants and special groups into&#13;
civilian life and support to receiving communities and other war-affected&#13;
communitiesis expectedto be environmentallyneutral. Inparticular:&#13;
   0   Under the DDR component, the reinsertion and reintegration activities are&#13;
       designed to develop the financial self-sufficiency o f ex-combatants' households&#13;
       primarily through transitional safety nets, training and counseling; and&#13;
   0   Under the RC component, community infrastructure sub-projects will consist o f&#13;
       re-equipment,    rehabilitation and reconstruction o f pre-existing structures&#13;
       (fortunately,  the level     o f physical destruction --and consequently the&#13;
       reconstruction needed-- i s quite low, as most physical damage appears to have&#13;
       beencaused by looting andneglect).&#13;
&#13;
76.    However, the project i s classified as environmental category B because of&#13;
potential, but not significant, adverse environmental effects associated with the&#13;
rehabilitationof community infrastructureas well as with economic activitiesto be&#13;
supported under both components. An Integrated Safeguards Data Sheet outlines&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
measures to be taken under the project to avoid or mitigate any negative impact on the&#13;
environment. Activities financed under the project will be screened using a standardized&#13;
approach based on an adaptation o f the tools developed by the Multi-country&#13;
Demobilization and Reintegration Program in collaboration with the Afiica Safeguards&#13;
Policy Enhancement initiative. The screening form for ex-combatants' income generating&#13;
activities and community sub-projects will be customized for C8te d'Ivoire, and applied&#13;
by all implementing partners under the project. Any rehabilitation and reintegration&#13;
activities including community driven projects will be implemented using the required&#13;
technical expertise and following standard World Bank procedure for Community Driven&#13;
Projects. On-going independenttechnical supervision i s provided for under the project.&#13;
&#13;
77.      The process envisaged for environmental and social screening of project&#13;
activities will involve three steps: (1) an initial checklist will be used for a pre-&#13;
screening to exclude (a) activities expected to have an harmful environmental or social&#13;
impact, and (b) activities that have no environmental or social implications whatsoever;&#13;
(2) an additional checklist will be used for detailed screening o f sub-projects; and (3)&#13;
standard technical guidelines and/or mitigation measures by area o f potential sub-project&#13;
(e.g., construction and rehabilitation o f buildings, water supply and sanitation, etc.) will&#13;
guide project staff in assessingpossible social and environmental impacts and identifying&#13;
appropriate measures. The PNDDRRC will be responsible to ensure the design,&#13;
dissemination and adequate use o f the environmental and social screening tool required at&#13;
all levels o f stakeholders consultations.&#13;
&#13;
                  E.     FINANCIAL AND ECONOMIC JUSTIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
78.      Overall Justification. Quick, tangible improvements in living conditions and the&#13;
returnto normal life are paramount for the resumption o f growth. Duringthe immediate&#13;
post conflict period o f two to three years, rapid progress on economic recovery and&#13;
reconstruction will be essential to the long-term economic development o f C8te d'Ivoire.&#13;
Luckily, the conflict has been relatively short-lived and therefore adjustment to a normal&#13;
way o f life should not pose major problems. Inparticular, displacedpopulations have not&#13;
had the time to develop the dependent mentality typical o f long-term residents o f refugee&#13;
camps and transitional shelters. Similarly, many combatants have been recruited fairly&#13;
recently and therefore their return to civilian life should not be very problematic.&#13;
Experience from post-conflict situations throughout the world suggests that the most&#13;
effective way to encourage the quick resumption o f peaceful social and economic&#13;
activities, and therefore o f the development process, i s through emergency D D R R C&#13;
projects, which deal with the most visible and disturbing aspects o f conflict - large&#13;
numbers o f armed personnel and extensive movements o f population fleeing from&#13;
violence.&#13;
&#13;
79.     Analysis of Alternatives. The project design reflects the accumulated wisdom o f&#13;
previous post-conflict operations. The underlyingproject concept o f providing assistance&#13;
to the internally displaced, refugees and ex-combatants, as well as to the receiving&#13;
communities, i s based on best practices and experiences gained in similar IDA member&#13;
countries and post-conflict situations, and it is deemed appropriate for achieving the&#13;
development objective o f the project. The training and employment efforts directed at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ex-combatants are also based on successful Bank and other donor agency experiences in&#13;
numerous countries, while the RC component draws on experience with social funds,&#13;
CDD and natural disaster reconstruction projects. Inaddition, the pilot activities financed&#13;
bythe Post Conflict Fundhave provided crucial context-specific information.&#13;
&#13;
80.      Cost Analysis. It was not possible, nor is it required, to conduct a cost-benefit&#13;
analysis for this project. The project design, therefore, i s based on cost-effectiveness,&#13;
attempting to minimize costs without forfeiting quality. Whenever possible, existing&#13;
structures will be used rather than buildingup parallel systems; for example, payments of&#13;
reinsertion allowances will be done through existing financial institutions at the local&#13;
level and PNDDWRC regional offices will be housed in government buildings.&#13;
Administrative costs have been contained by limiting the number o f Project staff and&#13;
relying on NGOs and other private and public agencies that already have a field presence&#13;
inthe target zones. Inaddition, economies of scale will be realized by having a number&#13;
o f services shared by both components (procurement,                      financial management,&#13;
communication, monitoring and evaluation), while preserving the needed independence&#13;
o f the DDR and R C activities.&#13;
&#13;
                                          F.      ACTION PLAN&#13;
&#13;
I. ActionPlanforDDRComponent&#13;
                                  Issue                                    Action/     Completion&#13;
                                                                       Responsibility     date&#13;
&#13;
 Demobilization*&#13;
 Specify technical criteria for Demobilization and                    FANCIIFAFN and Done&#13;
 ReinsertiodReintegration                                             PNDDWRC&#13;
 Confirm roles and responsibilities o f relevant stakeholders inthe   FANCUFAFN,       Done&#13;
 demobilizationprocess, especially o f the Armed Forces               ImpartialForces&#13;
                                                                      and PNDDWRC&#13;
 Identify and assess suggested Demobilization Centers                 FANCUFAFN,       Done&#13;
                                                                      ImpartialForces&#13;
                                                                      and PNDDIURC&#13;
 Provide informationand seek agreement on (i)     STIIHIVIAIDS        Technical Team / Done&#13;
 counseling model and health kits; (ii)  IDandMIS systems; (iii) IDA&#13;
 financial management and TSS payment systems; (iv) socio-&#13;
 economic questionnaire; (vi) TOR for monitoringand evaluation&#13;
 system&#13;
&#13;
 Carry out informationand sensitizationcampaign with combatants, ex- P N D W R C with  Ongoing&#13;
 combatants and communities                                           help from&#13;
                                                                      FANCUFAFN&#13;
 Establish and staff Regional Offices                                 PNDDWRC          Ongoing&#13;
 Set up ID and MIS systems                                            PNDDWRC          Ongoing&#13;
 Finalize detailed demobilization plan and sub-components (ID, socio- PNDDR/RC with    Done&#13;
 economic profile, health screening and counseling orientation)       Impartial Forces&#13;
 EstablishDemobilization Centers (rehabilitate, equip, staff)         PNDDIURC         Ongoing&#13;
&#13;
 Pre-cantonment                                                       FANCIIFAFN       Ongoing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Demobilization                                                             IPNDDRRC       August 2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Develop reinsertion payment mechanism and logistics to deliver TSS         PNDDWRC       Ongoing&#13;
payments&#13;
&#13;
Provide first TSS payment inregions o f return                              PNDDRRC       September 2006&#13;
&#13;
Reintegration&#13;
EstablishRegional DDR Offices                                               PNDDRRC       Ongoing&#13;
&#13;
Recruit experts for preparatory studies o freintegration options (labor     PNDDRRC       Done&#13;
markets, vocational training, credit markets)&#13;
Finalize regional reintegration assistance strategies                       PNDDRRC       Ongoing&#13;
&#13;
Initiate economic reintegration assistance                                  PNDDWRC       October 2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Issue                                      Action/    Completion&#13;
                                                                            Responsibility    date&#13;
First draft of ProjectImplementationManual, RC Component                    PNDDRRC, CARE Done&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Finalization of draft ProjectImplementationManual, RC Component             PNDDRRC       Done&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Expressionof Interestfor technical support agenciesinlocal mediaandthe      PNDDRRC       August 2006&#13;
DevelopmentBusiness&#13;
&#13;
RecruitmentofRC Coordinator                                                 PNDDRRC       Done&#13;
&#13;
Workshop for validation ofProjectImplementationManual, RC Component         PNDDRRC       Done&#13;
&#13;
Recruitmentof RC Unit Staff Abidjan                                         PNDDRRC       Ongoing&#13;
&#13;
Completionof MISdesign for RC                                               PNDDRRC       Ongoing&#13;
Finalizationof ProjectImplementationManual, RC Component                    PNDDRRC, IDA  Done&#13;
&#13;
Finalization o f detailedTOR for Request for proposalsfor technical support PNDDRRC       September 2006&#13;
agencies&#13;
&#13;
Requestfor proposalsfor technical support agencies: launching               PNDDRRC       September 20061&#13;
Recruitmentof RegionalCoordinators in 8 regions                             PNDDRRC       Ongoing&#13;
&#13;
Requestfor proposalsfor technicalsupport agencies: receptionofproposals                   October 2006&#13;
&#13;
Finalizationof agreements with selectedtechnicalsupport agencies            PNDDRRC       November2006&#13;
&#13;
First tranche disbursedto all technical support agencies                    PNDDRRC       January 2007&#13;
&#13;
Settingup of RegionalCommunityRehabilitationCommittees                      PNDDRRC       Ongoing&#13;
List of priority zones ineach region                                        CRR, PNDDRRC  February2007&#13;
&#13;
First disbursementsfor sub-projectimplementation                            PNDDR/RC      April 2007&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      G.      CONDITIONS FORBOARD PRESENTATIONAND EFFECTIVESS&#13;
&#13;
81.     Conditionsfor BoardPresentation.The only condition for Boardpresentation&#13;
is clearance o f Bank arrears. By June 30, 2006 arrears are estimated to amount to&#13;
US$322 million.&#13;
&#13;
82.     Conditionsfor Effectiveness. Giventhe emergency nature o fthe project,&#13;
conditions have beenkept to a minimum. They are as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      0 A PIM satisfactory to the Bank hasbeen adopted;&#13;
      0 An account has been established by the government for purposes o f holding the&#13;
        contribution o f counterpart funds to project costs, and an initial deposit o f CFAF&#13;
        500 million has beenmade therein;&#13;
      0 An account has been established for receiving the three tranches o f&#13;
        reimbursement o f eligible imports, which will be used by the government to&#13;
        finance the transitional safety net for ex-combatants;&#13;
      0 An external auditor with qualifications, experience and terms o f reference&#13;
        satisfactory to the Bank, has been recruited in compliance with the Bank&#13;
        procurement guidelines;&#13;
      0 A FiduciaryManagement Agency with terms ofreference satisfactory to the Bank&#13;
        has been recruited incompliance with Bank procurement guidelines; and&#13;
      0 A project coordinator with qualifications, experience and terms o f reference&#13;
        satisfactory to the Bank has been appointed, and a DDR coordinator and a RC&#13;
        coordinator with qualifications, experience and terms o f reference satisfactory to&#13;
        the Bank havebeenrecruited incompliance with Bank procurement guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              32&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ATTACHMENTS&#13;
&#13;
              Attachment1: Partiallistof Documentsinthe ProjectFile&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A. Government&#13;
&#13;
1. Linas-Marcoussis Agreement, 23 January 2003.&#13;
2. Programme National de Dksarmement, Dkmobilisation et Reinsertion et de&#13;
   Rkhabilitation Communautaire (PNDDFVRC or National Program for Disarmament,&#13;
   Demobilization and Reintegration and for Community Rehabilitation).&#13;
3. Feuille de route (((Roadmap to the disarmament and demobilization process)&#13;
                                  ))&#13;
4. Arrgtks no.65, 85, portant cre'ation et mode defonctionnement de la CNDDR&#13;
   (Ministerial decrees establishing the National DDFVRC Commission and its&#13;
   fonctioning, 2003).&#13;
5. Plan conjoint des opkrations (Joint Operations Plan).&#13;
6. Accra I11Agreement, 31July 2004&#13;
7. Pretoria Agreement, 6 April 2005&#13;
8. UNResolutions 1643 (2005), 1633 (2005), 1603(2005) 1572 (2004), 1528 (2004),&#13;
   1479 (2003)&#13;
9. Arrgte' no. 153,Jixant le cadre institutionnel, les attributions, 1'organisation et le&#13;
  fonctionnement du Programme National de Dksarmement, de De'mobilisation, de&#13;
   Rkinsertion et de Re'habilitation Communautaire (Ministerial decree establishing the&#13;
   PNDDWRC and its fonctioning), June 1, 2006.&#13;
&#13;
B. BankStaffAssessments&#13;
&#13;
1. Aide-MCmoire, Post Conflict Mission, July 2003 and September2003.&#13;
2. Aide-MCmoire, Preparationof the Demobilization, Reintegration and Reconstruction&#13;
   Project, December 2003.&#13;
3. Aide-MCmoire, Appraisal of the Demobilization, Reintegrationand Reconstruction&#13;
   Project, February 2004.&#13;
4. Aide-MCmoire, Post-Appraisal o f the Demobilization, Reintegrationand&#13;
   ReconstructionProject, June 2004.&#13;
5. Aide-MCmoire, Pre-Negotiations mission o fthe Demobilization, Reintegration and&#13;
   ReconstructionProject, January 2005.&#13;
6. Aide-MCmoire, Follow-up o fthe Demobilization, Reintegrationand Community&#13;
   ReconstructionProgram and supervision o f Post-Conflict Fundgrants, March-May&#13;
   2006.&#13;
&#13;
C.Studies and Reports&#13;
&#13;
1. Terms o fReference for study on reintegration opportunities for ex-combatants.&#13;
2. Terms of Reference for study on the needs and preferences o f the most vulnerable&#13;
   groups inthe post-conflict period.&#13;
3. Consultant report on implementation instruments for a program for retrenched&#13;
   personnel insupport o f the armed forces, August 2003.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             33&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4. Reports of activities of pilot project for reconstruction, rehabilitation and&#13;
    reconciliation inthe Bouake area, December 2003 (fundedby Post Conflict Fund,&#13;
    implemented by CARE Intl.).&#13;
5. Report o f study on the needs and preferences of the most vulnerable groups inthe&#13;
    post-conflict period, 2004.&#13;
6. Terms o f reference for study on ReconstructingSocial Capital, Rehabilitation and&#13;
    Reconciliation Projects inBouake.&#13;
7. Report o f study on Reconstructing Social Capital, Rehabilitation andReconciliation&#13;
   Projects inBouakC, April 2004.&#13;
8. Consultancyreport on Management Information System, January 2004 andMay&#13;
    2004.&#13;
9. Survey on the needs and reintegrationaspirations o fnew recruits inthe Security and&#13;
   Defense Forces.&#13;
10. Real Time Evaluation o f pilot project for reconstruction, rehabilitation and&#13;
   reconciliation inthe BouakC area, September 2004 (funded by Post Conflict Fund,&#13;
    implemented by CARE Intl.).&#13;
11.Evaluation o fPost Conflict Fundgrant to UNICEF for pilot reintegrationo f child&#13;
    soldiers (inFrench), May 2006.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              34&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 2: InstitutionalArrangements for the PNDDWRC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  internal Audit&#13;
     Fiduciary Agency       .______ GeneralSecretariat&#13;
                                   Administrative &amp; Finances&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Reintegration&#13;
Reintegration.B Reinsertion        Community infrastrutures&#13;
      Chiid soldiers              income Generation activities&#13;
     Special Groups                Social capital development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     DDR Regional                        CR Regional&#13;
&#13;
     Abidjan, Bouak4,                    BouakB, Man,&#13;
     Man, San-Pedro,                  San-Pedro, Bouna,&#13;
                                       Korhogo, Daloa,&#13;
       Bondoukou                          Bondougou,&#13;
                                        Yamoussoukro&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
N.B.:Shadedareais notcoveredbyProjectfunding&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     35&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                    Attachment3: ProjectCost Summary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A -NationalProgram:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Cated'IvOire&#13;
                                                             DDRmRNfltional~zoM#w)9&#13;
                                                                   TotalcostandFhlKhg&#13;
                                                                        rn&#13;
                                                                                          FhlKhg&#13;
                                                                                                              lotal&#13;
                                                                                                  otha      - F i l m i n g&#13;
Conponents                                                   Totalcost G o v m t       IDA       Donors     Available      cep&#13;
l.lhDWStion,ReirSertiOnardRantegratlOn                        $1041        $17.8       $57.6       $25.0      $100.4       $3.7&#13;
2Rflmmua'on,rehabilitationardqmofcormKdfies                   $31.8        $24         $29.4       $0.0       $31.8        $0.0&#13;
3. program-                                                   S3.6         $18.1       $13.0       $0.4       $31.5        $2.1&#13;
  Totalprogramcost                                            $169.5       w.3         $100.0      $25.4      $163.7       $5.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             French                   Belgian&#13;
                             Coope-                   Coope-&#13;
   UNDP           EU          ration       Japan      ration   Norway Denmark Sweden                   Total&#13;
&#13;
     1.3          11.8         2.0          2.7        2.4        0.1          3.9        1.2          25.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B- IDA-financedProject:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A-               I &amp; i m l f h a n d ~ a l&#13;
   Sasitiratia7ardCamudcaticn                                 0.2   20.0    0.7    80.0                 0.8   0.8        -    0.7 0.1&#13;
                                                              1.5   28     53.3    97.2                 54.9 50.6    39.6   15.3  0.0&#13;
   ~         ~      f        w        ~       c       n       0.8   17.3    3.6    827                  4.4   4.0      0.0    3.8 0.6&#13;
                                                              25    4.1    57.6    95.9     ----   ---- 60.1 55.4     39.6  19.7  0.7&#13;
FLWDI&amp;dh&amp;-&#13;
s u J t o t d D a m b* i l i saa bn ~d~~0 0 a n d ~ 0 0&#13;
                      .   .              a l c f d l i e 5&#13;
   carmrdty%~ects                                             24    7.3    29.3    90.0   0.9    27     326 30.0         -  326     -&#13;
CIhjeCtAhhiShb'00&#13;
   wid-            cn                                         27    17.2   13.0    828       -     -    15.8 14.5      23   11.2  23&#13;
                                                              7.5   7.0   100.0    922    0.9    0.8 lB.4 100.0       41.9  63.5   3.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            36&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                         a t e d'Ivoire&#13;
                                                                   Post-Conflict Rehabilitation&#13;
                                                               ExpenditureAccountsbyFinanciers&#13;
                                                                         (US$ Million)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             Local&#13;
                                          The Government    IDA      Beneficiaries        Total     For. (Excl. Duties&amp;&#13;
                                           Amount Yo Amount YO Amount % Amount YO                   Exch. Taxes) Taxes&#13;
&#13;
I.InvestmentCosts&#13;
 A. PositiveList of Imports                           -   39.6 100.0      -             39.6   37.2  39.6        -&#13;
 C.Equipement                                 0.2  18.4    0.8  81.6               --     1.0   0.9   0.2      0.6   0.2&#13;
 D.ServicedeConsultants&#13;
    1. Servicede Consultant international&#13;
                           -                  0.2  10.0    1.8  90.0      -               2.0   1.9   1.6      0.4&#13;
   2. Servicede Consultant - national      -----------&#13;
                                              0.9  19.2    3.7  80.8                      4.6   4.3     -      3.8   0.8&#13;
 SubtotalServicedeConsultants                 1.1  16.4    5.5  83.6                      6.6   6.2   1.6      4.2   0.8&#13;
 E.Formation                                               0.2 100.0      -        ----   0.2   0.2   0.1      0.2&#13;
 F. Sous-Projet                                           40.4  95.3    2.0      4.7    42.4   39.8           42.4&#13;
 G.PPF                                     --------------  0.6  100.0              -      0.6   0.5     --     0.6&#13;
TotalInvestment Costs                         1.3   1.4   87.1  96.4    2.0      2.2    90.4   84.9  41.5     47.9   1.0&#13;
II.RecurrentCosts&#13;
 A.Personnel contractuel                      1.3  20.0    5.4  80.0      -               6.7   6.3            5.5   1.2&#13;
 B.Operationet Entretien                      1.8  20.0    7.0  80.0                      8.8   8.3            7.2   1.6&#13;
 C. Supervision et Voyages Administratifs  -----------&#13;
                                              0.1  20.0    0.5   80.0                     0.6   0.6            0.5   0.1&#13;
TotalRecurrentCosts                        -----------&#13;
                                              3.2  20.0   12.9   80.0              ----  16.1   15.1     ----  13.2  2.9&#13;
TotalPROJECTCOSTS                             4.5   4.2   100.0  93.9   2.0       1.9   106.5  100.0 41.5      61.1  3.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      37&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
               Attachment4: DetailedDescriptionof RC Component&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MainActors andtheir Role&#13;
  0  RC Regional OfJices: They will be headed by a Regional Coordinator and be&#13;
     responsible for supervisingthe work o f technical support agencies, monitoring on&#13;
      a sample basis the work o f beneficiary communities, keeping the Regional&#13;
      Community Rehabilitaation Committee informed o f implementation progress,&#13;
      ensuring that sub-projects are prepared, processed and executed in accordance&#13;
     with the PIM.&#13;
  0  Regional Community Rehabilitation Committees: They will be ad hoc&#13;
      committees comprising traditional authorities and representatives o f the main&#13;
      confessional groups and technical ministries at the regional level. They will be in&#13;
      charge o f selecting the communities that will receive funds for sub-projects under&#13;
      sub-components 1 and 2. This selection will be guided by a set o f criteria set&#13;
      forth in the PIM. The Regional Community Rehabilitation Committees will be&#13;
      updated regularly o f the progress o f the sub-projects in their region and will in&#13;
      particular review progress reports producedby the RC Regional Office.&#13;
  0   Technical support agencies: They can be NGOs or other private entities to be&#13;
      selected on a competitive basis (procurement process carried out by the FMA).&#13;
      The PNDDRiRC will subcontract to them the following activities: (i)&#13;
      implementation o f the micro-planning processes at the community level,&#13;
      including the identification o f potential beneficiaries o f sub-component 2, in the&#13;
      communities selected by the Regional Community Rehabilitation Committee; (ii)&#13;
      capacity building in favor o f communities; and (iii)the assistance for and&#13;
      supervision o f sub-project implementationby the Community Committees, andby&#13;
      beneficiary groups inthe case o f income-generating sub-projects. Criteria for their&#13;
      selection and their responsibilities are described in the PIM. Their activities will&#13;
      be monitored by the PNDDR/RC Regional Office for RC, as well as well as by&#13;
      the RC Coordinator and the Monitoring and Evaluation Unit.&#13;
  0   Communities: Communities will establish themselves as associations duly&#13;
      registered at the relevant Prefecture. Membership in the association will be open&#13;
      inprinciple to all community members, while the composition oftheir governing&#13;
      body will be specified in the PIM as well as in the association by-laws. In cases&#13;
      where the community already has a representative association duly registered&#13;
      (e.g., a Parents Teacher Association), there may be no need to create a parallel&#13;
      structure. The community association will receive the funds for the selected sub-&#13;
      project and be in charge o f its implementation, with helphpervision from a&#13;
      technical support agency provided by the PNDDIURC.&#13;
&#13;
ProjectCoverageAreas&#13;
  0   Sub-component I and 2: All regions affected by the conflict and where major&#13;
      displacement (in and out) has taken place (a list i s provided inthe PIM, R C part).&#13;
  0   Sub-component 3: All regions o f C8te d'Ivoire.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           38&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Targeting&#13;
   0   Sub-component I and 2: The Regional Community Rehabilitation Committees&#13;
       are responsible for selecting the communities where investments under sub-&#13;
       component 1 and 2 will be made. A basic community unit for the RC i s the&#13;
       "village-center"  (or ``pays rural") in rural areas and the neighborhood (or&#13;
       "quartier urbain") in urban areas. Both "pays ruraZ" and "quartier urbain" are&#13;
       economic and planning tools, with clear geographic boundaries. In order to&#13;
       determine the exact list o f communities, the Regional Community Rehabilitation&#13;
       Committees will use the following criteria: (a) level o f damage to infrastructure;&#13;
       (b) displacement and return flows; (c) percentage o f vulnerable individuals (e.g.,&#13;
       households headed by minors or disabled adults); and (d) level o f social cohesion&#13;
       (e.g., existance o f conflicts in the community). The list will have to be approved&#13;
       by the Regional Community Rehabilitation Committees by consensus and will&#13;
       constitute the list o f priority communities to be targeted for assistance by&#13;
       technical support agencies.&#13;
   0   Sub-component 3: While this sub-component will be implementedthroughout the&#13;
       country, particular emphasis will be placed on areas particularly prone to conflict&#13;
       and on communities where sub-component 1and 2 are active.&#13;
&#13;
Eligible Groups of Direct Beneficiaries&#13;
   0   Sub-component I: Are eligible all communities which (i)are included in the&#13;
       priority list established by the Regional Community Rehabilitation Committees;&#13;
       and (ii) have established themselves as associations in accordance with the PIM&#13;
       andunderthe guidance o f a technical support agency.&#13;
   0   Sub-component 2: Are eligible all groups that (i) at least 6 members, and at&#13;
                                                           have&#13;
       least two thirds o f them considered particularly vulnerable according to the&#13;
       criteria provided in the PIM (e.g., female-headed households, displaced or&#13;
       refugees returning to their communities); and (ii)have been approved by the&#13;
       community association.&#13;
   0   Sub-component 3: National coverage.&#13;
&#13;
Typology of Sub-projects&#13;
   0   Sub-component I: Eligible infrastructure sub-projects include: rehabilitation,&#13;
       extention or re-equipment o f existing elementary schools; rehabilitation and&#13;
       refurbishment o f existing health centers; water pumps repair; rehabilitation o f&#13;
       small access roads; construction o f latrines; repair o f bridges, markets, etc. The&#13;
       following infrastructure sub-projects are not eligible: electrification; construction&#13;
       o f new schools or new health centers, unless already planned by the respective&#13;
       ministries and duly staffed; construction or rehabilitation o f individual dwellings;&#13;
       asphalted roads.&#13;
   0   Sub-component 2: I s eligible any type o f income-generating activity that has been&#13;
       determined acceptable upon applying a social and environmental screening&#13;
       checklist (see Section D VII). Priority will be given to activities interruptedby the&#13;
       conflict and to be restarted, but eligible groups may also express the intention to&#13;
       explore new activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              39&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
     Sub-component 3: Activities financed under this component may be o f very&#13;
     different nature and include radio programs in different languages (e.g., call-in&#13;
     magazines, soap-operas, round tables) as well as inter-communal and community&#13;
     events ("reconciliation days", sport events, singing contests, inter-active theatre).&#13;
     The intention i s to find creative ways to communicate and to influence behavior,&#13;
     so the only common denominator o f activites to be financed i s that they all&#13;
     contribute to the restoration of social capital at the community level.&#13;
&#13;
Budgetsand Contributions&#13;
  0  Sub-component I:Grants for sub-projects will have a maximumbudget o f about&#13;
     US$ 20,000. The community should contribute 10% o f this amount either in cash&#13;
     or in kind (labor, time invested in sub-project implementation and monitoring,&#13;
     etc.).&#13;
  0  Sub-component 2: Grants for sub-projects will be o f a maximum o f about&#13;
     US$4,000. Given that recipients will be selected among the most vulnerable&#13;
     people in the community, no formal contribution will be required. Communities,&#13;
     however, will be encouraged to agree on symbolic contributions so as to preserve&#13;
     the beneficiaries' dignity and limitjealousy.&#13;
  0  Sub-component 3: Activities will be sub-contracted on a competitive basis to&#13;
     private entities with a proven record o f effective communication for conflict&#13;
     prevention and resolution. Budgetswill be negotiated case by case.&#13;
&#13;
Implementationmechanisms&#13;
  0  Sub-component I:Technical support agencies will be contracted to assist eligible&#13;
     communities in a given geographic area incarrying out a micro-planning exercise&#13;
     to identify priority needs and select a sub-project for funding (the content,&#13;
     procedures and output o f a micro-planning exercise are described in the PIM).&#13;
     Sub-project proposals will be reviewed by the R C Regional Office, who will&#13;
     check their compliance with the eligibility criteria set forth inthe PIM (e.g., type&#13;
     of sub-project, absence o f alternative financing sources, consistency with&#13;
     applicable national standards, clearly identified community contribution) as well&#13;
     as the technical soundness, and inform the Regional Community Rehabilitation&#13;
     Committee. Upon approval, funds will be made available to the community&#13;
     committee, who will implement the sub-project with help/supervision from&#13;
     technical support agencies (NGOs) financed by the project.&#13;
  0  Sub-component 2: With assistance from a technical support agency sub-&#13;
     contracted by the project, the community will identify who should be the&#13;
     beneficiaries within the community itself in accordance with criteria set forth in&#13;
     the PIM. Groups o f beneficiaries will elaborate proposals for income-generating&#13;
     activities with the assistance o f the technical support agency. After approval from&#13;
     the community committee, proposals will be submitted to the R C Regional Office&#13;
     for funding (all procedures and criteria for this process will be detailed in PIM).&#13;
     The community committee will receive the funds, but the contract will state&#13;
     clearly that the funds are to be retro-ceded to the beneficiary group, and two&#13;
     representatives o f the beneficiary group will co-sign the contract. The technical&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             40&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  support agency will ensure that intendedbeneficiaries received their money, and&#13;
  will provide assistance/supervision to beneficiaries.&#13;
0 Sub-component 3: The RC national coordination will issue Requests for&#13;
  Proposals specifying the type o f activities to be financed in accordance with the&#13;
  PIM. The project will contract selected organizations to implement regional or&#13;
  inter-regional programs, and will inform the concerned Regional Community&#13;
  Rehabilitation Committees.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       41&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
               Attachment5: FinancialManagementAssessmentReport&#13;
&#13;
ExecutiveSummary&#13;
&#13;
As part of the preparation of the Emergency Demobilization, Reintegration and&#13;
Community Rehabilitation Project, a full financial management assessment has been&#13;
carried out in accordance with the Financial Management Practices Manual issuedby the&#13;
Financial Management Sector Board on November 3, 2005. The main objectives o f the&#13;
assessment were to determine whether: (a) the PNDDR/RC has adequate financial&#13;
management arrangements to ensure that project funds will be used for the intended&#13;
purposes in an efficient and economical way; and (b) PNDDRRC financial reports will&#13;
beprepared inan accurate, reliable and timelymanner; and (c) PNDDRRC assets will be&#13;
safeguarded.&#13;
&#13;
A Country Financial Accountability Assessment (CFAA) has not yet been conducted in&#13;
C6te d'Ivoire because the country has been undergoing a prolonged period o f political&#13;
instability, which began with the military coup in December 1999 and precipitated with&#13;
the conflict that started on September 19, 2002. This situation has had a severe&#13;
economical and political impact inthe country.&#13;
&#13;
A Public Expenditure Review (PER) was conducted in 2003 and has concluded that&#13;
budget preparation was relatively strong but improvements were needed to ensure&#13;
consistency among projections usedby various ministries and agencies. There is no clear&#13;
link between policies and resource allocation. According to the PER, the implementation&#13;
o f the integrated financial management system called SIGFIP has provided some&#13;
significant benefits in terms o f budget expenditure monitoring and control, inclusion o f&#13;
donor activities, and strengthened capacity for execution. The SIGFIP system, however,&#13;
due to its numerous steps, slows down the entire process unduly. Donor funds are&#13;
reported in the budget, but because o f the war situation, expenditures often deviate&#13;
significantly from the amounts budgeted with the government giving priority to the&#13;
payment o f military wages, security equipments, etc. There are also significant payment&#13;
arrears. The Bank will conduct an integrated PER and CFAA to be started inFY07 and&#13;
finalized inFY08.&#13;
&#13;
Disbursement of external assistance has been slow.           Bank projects experienced a&#13;
disbursement rate averaging only about 12% over the past five years before suspension,&#13;
compared to an average Sub-Saharan Africa rate o f about 22%. In part this reflects a&#13;
difficult, conflict-affected environment, but it i s also a result o f weaknesses in public&#13;
expenditure management and controls.&#13;
&#13;
The conclusion o f the financial management assessment is that financial management&#13;
arrangements have an overall risk rating o f high and do not satisfy all the requirements&#13;
under OPh3P10.2.&#13;
&#13;
To mitigate the country and project risk, a Fiduciary Management Agency (FMA) will be&#13;
selected to ensure that sound financial management and procurement will be maintained&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            42&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
throughout the life o f the project. This FMA will be staffed by experienced and qualified&#13;
personnelwith relevant background indonor-funded projects. The FMAwill be equipped&#13;
with a software appropriate to the scale and nature o fthe emergency program, integrated&#13;
into the project M I S in a modular way. The project will have similar book accounts to&#13;
those for other IDA-funded projects.&#13;
&#13;
The project internal controls will be documented in the Financial and Accounting&#13;
Manual, which will be part o f the Project hplementation Manual. This manual will be a&#13;
living document to be updated during the whole life o f the project in response to&#13;
changing situations and implementation experience. The annual financial statements&#13;
should reflect all Program activities, including those financed by other donors and the&#13;
Government. The first year, a semi-annual technical and financial audit o f the Program&#13;
will be conducted. Subsequently, financial audit reports will be submitted to the Bank&#13;
within the six months after the end o f each financial year since it's expected that previous&#13;
technical audit would have helped PNDDIURC have enough acquaintance with the&#13;
monitoring o f the physical and financial progress o fthe Program.&#13;
&#13;
SummaryProjectDescription&#13;
&#13;
The project will be implemented via three components: (a) demobilization, reinsertion&#13;
andreintegration (DDR) o f ex-combatants; (b) community rehabilitation (RC) to provide&#13;
funding for community-based infrastructure, income generation and reconciliation for the&#13;
groups and localities most affected by the conflict, and (c) an institution building and&#13;
project management to support project implementation.&#13;
&#13;
Inparticular, the Project objectivesareto:&#13;
s Support the reinsertion and reintegration of about 45,000 individuals including ex-&#13;
    combatants, child soldiers and special groups;&#13;
3 Contribute to the rehabilitation or reconstruction of the social and economic&#13;
    infrastructure inthe communities most affectedby the conflict;&#13;
3 Assist vulnerablegroupsin(re)starting economicactivities;&#13;
3 Strengthensocialcapitalthroughoutthecountry.&#13;
&#13;
Bank's resources will not finance either the disarmament or the demobilization.&#13;
&#13;
CountryIssues&#13;
&#13;
Governance and transparency deteriorated during the conflict. This was especially true&#13;
with respect to the cocodcoffee sector, contracts between the public and private sectors,&#13;
and management o f petroleum. Since June 2004, C6te d'Ivoire has accumulated&#13;
significant arrears on its debt obligations towards the Bank, and on November 1, 2004, it&#13;
fell into non-accrual status. The authorities have remained current on their obligations to&#13;
the Fund. They have accumulated about $300 million in arrears to the World Bank as o f&#13;
June 1, 2006. However, the government is seeking to rapidly enhance the financial&#13;
accountability framework in order to: reimburse arrears, mitigate fiduciary risk inpublic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             43&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
expenditure management; achieve economy, efficiency and effectiveness in the use o f&#13;
public funds; enhance transparency and accountability.&#13;
&#13;
Riskassessmentandmitigation&#13;
&#13;
The objectives o f the project's financial management systemare to:&#13;
0   Ensure that funds are used only for their intended purposes in an efficient and&#13;
    economical way;&#13;
0   Ensure that funds are properly managed and flow smoothly, adequately, regularly and&#13;
    predictably inorder to meet the objectives o f the project;&#13;
0   Enable the preparationo f accurate and timely financial reports;&#13;
0   Enable project management to monitor the efficient implementation o f the project;&#13;
    and&#13;
0   Safeguard the project assets and resources.&#13;
&#13;
Moreover, the following features are recommended for a strong financial management&#13;
system:&#13;
0   The PNDDR/RC should have an adequate number and mix o f skilled and experienced&#13;
    staff both at the central and the decentralized levels (Regional Offices);&#13;
0   The internal control system should ensure the conduct o f an orderly and efficient&#13;
    payment and procurement process, and proper recording and safeguarding o f assets&#13;
    and resources;&#13;
0   The accounting system should support the Program requests for funding and meet its&#13;
    reporting obligations to fund providers including The Government o f CGte d'Ivoire,&#13;
    IDA, other donors, andlocal communities;&#13;
0   The system should be capable o f providing financial data to measure performance&#13;
    linked to the output o f the project;&#13;
0   An independent, qualified auditor should be appointed to review the Program's&#13;
    financial statements and internal controls;&#13;
0   The first year, semi annual technical and financial audits will be conducted to ensure&#13;
    coherence between the physical and the financial implementation o f the Program; and&#13;
0   An independent qualified Fiduciary Management Agency should be selected through&#13;
    a transparent process to ensure sound FMsystem.&#13;
&#13;
The table below shows the results o f the risk assessment from the Risk Rating Summary.&#13;
It identifies the key risks PNDDWRC management may face in achieving project&#13;
objectives and provides a basis for determining how management should address these&#13;
risks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             44&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  Country Level  H  National elections are scheduled for&#13;
                    October 2006.                                    -_&#13;
                    Once the elections have taken place,&#13;
                    an integrated CFAA and PER will&#13;
                    be conducted -plannedfor FY&#13;
                    2007.&#13;
&#13;
 IProjectLevel  H   A FMA will be selectedto ensure     The launching o f the hiring&#13;
                    sound Financial Management          process was a condition o f&#13;
                    System (disbursement, procurement negotiations,      while   the&#13;
                    and FM).                            recruitment o f the FMA i s&#13;
                                                        a        condition        o f&#13;
                                                        effectiveness.&#13;
ControlRisk&#13;
  Budgeting          s mentioned, budget preparation i&#13;
~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     weak part of the budget proces                  --&#13;
                     he Bank team and project sta&#13;
                      ve worked closely to put in pl&#13;
                       comprehensive budget for&#13;
                     hole life o f the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 IAccounting                                                         --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 IInternal&#13;
  Control            nancial        management                        _ _&#13;
                        ounting procedures that sh&#13;
                        igate the weak internal contr&#13;
                         DWRC. PNDDWRC will ha&#13;
                         ternal auditor within its team.&#13;
&#13;
 IFundsFlow                                                             --&#13;
                           ted financial management&#13;
                            tion system called SIGFIP.&#13;
                         special procedure has been&#13;
                        wed     for    emergency     IDA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Financial&#13;
  Reporting&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    45&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W  Auditing            M       $raft TOR adapted as appropriate toThe hiring o f the external&#13;
                               identified project risks have beenauditors i s a condition o f&#13;
                               prepared. An integrated technicaleffectiveness.&#13;
&#13;
                               conducted.&#13;
                               and    financial  audit   will   be&#13;
&#13;
                               Technically     competent       and&#13;
                               independent external auditor will be&#13;
                               selected.&#13;
&#13;
   OverallRisk         H&#13;
  Rating&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Weaknesses of financialmanagementsystems (FMS)&#13;
&#13;
The project FMS i s weakened by the following salient features:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
0 The accounting personnelhave been selected but they needadditional training on Bank&#13;
  fiduciary procedures.&#13;
0 Internal auditing arrangements are not yet adequate and severe internal controls issues&#13;
  have been raised by an external audit in 2005. The Financial Management and&#13;
  Accounting Manual should be amended to take into account the suggestions o f this&#13;
  2005 financial audit and the decision to hirean FMA.&#13;
0 Funds flow arrangements are not fully adequate because the banking system has been&#13;
  affected by this crisis (there are no banking facilities presently operating in the zone&#13;
  controlled by the FN).&#13;
0 There i s not a good understanding o f the Financial Reporting requirements given that&#13;
  the Project Accountant has not yet implemented World Bank projects before and has&#13;
  not had training in Financial Management and Disbursement Guidelines for the World&#13;
  Bank.&#13;
&#13;
Institutionalandimplementationarrangements&#13;
&#13;
The PNDDRRC will be responsible for the overall implementation o f the project. A&#13;
Fiduciary Agency will be selected to manage World Bank funds. Based on experience&#13;
from other post-conflict projects inAfiica, management o f the DDR and R C components&#13;
will be kept separate, with separate Designated Accounts and separate component&#13;
coordinators.&#13;
&#13;
The objectives o fthe FMA are to:&#13;
0   Ensure that funds are used only for their intended purposes in an efficient and&#13;
    economical way;&#13;
0   Ensurethat funds are properly managedand flow smoothly, adequately, regularlyand&#13;
    predictably inorder to meet the objectives o fthe project;&#13;
0   Enable the preparation of accurate and timely financial reports;&#13;
0   Enable project management to monitor the efficient implementation o f the project;&#13;
    and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             46&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
0    Manage procurement, including purchases o f goods, works, and consulting services;&#13;
&#13;
Regional offices will be established for both components for more efficient&#13;
implementation. A good financial management system will be put in place at the&#13;
decentralized level to ensure sound management o fproject funds.&#13;
&#13;
AccountingArrangements andInformationSystem&#13;
&#13;
For IDA resources, the FMA will maintain books o f accounts in accordance with&#13;
accounting standards acceptable to the Bank. The books o f account to be maintained&#13;
should include: a Cash Book, ledgers, journal vouchers, fixed asset register and a&#13;
contracts registers. The books o f accounts will be maintained on a computerized system.&#13;
A list o f accounts codes (Chart of Account) for the project should be drawn up and&#13;
should match the classification o f expenditures and sources and application o f funds&#13;
indicated in the Financing Agreement. The Chart o f accounts should be developed in a&#13;
way that allows project costs to be directly related to specific work activities and outputs&#13;
o f the project.&#13;
&#13;
Concerning the overall Program, the PNDDRRC will maintainbooks o f accounts for the&#13;
activities financed by the Government and the other donors in a format, content and&#13;
periodicity that will ensure provide qualitative and timely consolidated financial&#13;
statements to be audited. The audited consolidated financial statements submitted to the&#13;
Bankshould reflect all project activities, including those financedbyother donors andthe&#13;
Government.&#13;
&#13;
Books o f Accounts to be used for the Program will be opened and a Chart o f Accounts&#13;
will be completed inaccordance with the requirement inthe FinancingAgreement.&#13;
&#13;
Staffingarrangements&#13;
&#13;
The FMA will be staffed by experienced and qualified personnel with relevant&#13;
background in donor-funded projects. It has been agreed that the staff will comprise o f&#13;
one senior financial management specialist, one accountant, one senior procurement&#13;
specialist and hidher assistant. At the decentralized level, FMA will be represented inthe&#13;
nine RC regional offices will berepresented byone accountant for eachregion, including&#13;
the office in the District o f Abidjan. The regional accountants will maintain books o f&#13;
accounts for IDA resources. Regional accountants could be used for cross support in&#13;
different regional offices if deemed necessary due to Program's cycle and/or activities. A&#13;
financial management specialist will be appointed at the PNDDRRC as a focal point to&#13;
help inmaintaining the information link between the FMA and the PNDDRRC. He/She&#13;
will be responsible for consolidating the Program's financial statements&#13;
&#13;
FMA staff as well as PNDDWRC staff will be trained as appropriate in the following&#13;
areas (i)Financial Management including internal controls, information system and&#13;
computer applications; (ii) disbursementprocedures; and (iii)   procurement guidelines and&#13;
procedures. This can be arranged in consultation with the Senior Financial Management&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             47&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
specialist and the Senior Procurement Specialist based respectively in Abidjan and&#13;
Ouagadougou during the implementation period o f the project.&#13;
&#13;
To make sure that the project i s effectively implemented, the FMA and PNDDR/RC will&#13;
ensure that appropriate staffing arrangements are maintained throughout the life o f the&#13;
project.&#13;
&#13;
InformationSystem andAccounting&#13;
&#13;
The FMA will maintain a consolidated budget and accounting system for the duration o f&#13;
the project including all sources o f funds. To that end, the PNDDR/RC i s already will be&#13;
equippedwith a computerized and integrated financial management system appropriate to&#13;
the scale and nature o f the emergency program and capable o f recording and reporting in&#13;
a timely manner the project operations.&#13;
&#13;
InternalControlandFinancialManagementManual&#13;
&#13;
The project internal controls (including processes for recording and safeguarding fixed&#13;
assets) are documented in the Financial Management and Accounting Manual (FMAM)&#13;
o f the PNDDR/RC. A supplemental Financial Management Manual will have to be&#13;
preparedto take into consideration the specific concerns o f regional offices. The FMAM&#13;
should be a living document that can be updated to strengthen the internal control system&#13;
during the whole life o f the project. The procedures used by the project to maintain its&#13;
records at all levels o f implementation will be documented in the FMAM. These will&#13;
include the requirement for cross references to supporting documentation in the SOE&#13;
supporting schedules in order to facilitate the inspection o f these schedules and improve&#13;
the maintenance o fthe project's records.&#13;
&#13;
The FMAM describes the accounting system: major transaction cycles o f the project,&#13;
funds flow processes, the accounting records, supporting documents, computer files and&#13;
specific accounts in financial statements involved in the processing o f transactions. The&#13;
FMAM also includes the financial reporting process, project budgeting procedures,&#13;
procedures to be used for the replenishment o f the Designated Account and auditing&#13;
arrangements.&#13;
&#13;
The FMA will ensure that an adequate internal control system is in place at the central&#13;
and regional levels. The project will have an internal audit unit which will be headed by&#13;
an internal auditor who has already been selected on a competitive basis and in&#13;
conformity with Bank procurement procedures. The role o f the internal auditor is clearly&#13;
spelt out in the terms o f reference used for the selection. His role will include ensuring&#13;
that the FMA i s executing all its activities in accordance with the relevant TORSand&#13;
contract.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              48&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
DisbursementArrangements/ Flow of Funds&#13;
&#13;
Flow of Funds. The Project will have two Designated Accounts, one covering&#13;
expenditures related to the DDR component (excluding the transitional safety net) as well&#13;
as general project management expenditures, and the other covering expenditures related&#13;
to the R C component. Both Designated Accounts will be located at the BCEAO and will&#13;
have advance accounts in a Commercial Bank that will be managed by the FMA in&#13;
accordance with Bank operational guidelines. Furthermore two separate accounts will be&#13;
established at the BCEAO for the project's quick disbursing component, and the&#13;
government counterpart funds. The IDA funds will only transit in the BCEAO&#13;
DesignatedAccounts and will be immediately transferred by the Treasurer to the FMA in&#13;
advance accounts opened in commercial banks, acceptable by the Bank and the&#13;
Government. The government has agreed to use this special procedure for PNDDRRC to&#13;
allows project funds to by-pass several steps o f the cumbersome regular national&#13;
procedures .&#13;
&#13;
FMA will transmit withdrawal applications to the Directorate o f Public Debt for&#13;
submission to IDA. Withdrawal applications will be submitted along with statements o f&#13;
commercial Banks and Designated Accounts opened at the Central Bank. All&#13;
disbursements will be initially transaction based and given the large size o f the&#13;
Designated Accounts, namely CFAF 1.6 billion and CFAF 1.5 billion for the above&#13;
captioned components, respectively, there will be a minimum application size o f USD&#13;
550,000 equivalent for any payment other thanDedicated Account replenishments.&#13;
&#13;
Should it become necessary to establish regional sub-accounts (30 days advance), an&#13;
effort will be made to accommodate such need, provided that the Bank approves the&#13;
accounting system put in place for such accounts. The PNDDWRC will coordinate all&#13;
withdrawals and replenishment o f the Designated Accounts with the FMA. Funds Flow&#13;
arrangements will be as follow:&#13;
    (i)    IDAwill make an initialadvance disbursement fkom the proceeds o fthe Grant&#13;
           by depositing into the Government o f CGte d'Ivoire operated Designated&#13;
           Accounts held at the reliable commercial bank inU S dollars;&#13;
    (ii)   Actual expenditures will be reimbursed through submission o f Withdrawal&#13;
           Applications and against Statements o f Expenditure that will be approved in&#13;
           accordance with internal control measures inthe FMAM; and&#13;
    (iii)  All expenditures o fBank's funds will bepaidbyFMA inaccordance with the&#13;
           approval mechanism documented inthe FMAM.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           49&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
            IDA andCounterpartFundsFlow Chart for Paymentsthrough&#13;
                                Advances/Reimbursements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                ','.'. '.                Withdrawal&#13;
                                                                         '.'.            applications&#13;
                                                                             ',&#13;
                                                                               ','.&#13;
                                                                                   ','.'.'.'.&#13;
                                   BCEAO                                                      ', '. '.&#13;
                   1. DesignatedAccount                                                               '.&#13;
                                                                                                        ',&#13;
                      Component DDR&#13;
                   2. DesignatedAccount&#13;
                          Component RC                                     I    Directorateof PublicDebt&#13;
                   3. DedicatedAccount (positive list)&#13;
                      Component DDR&#13;
                   4. Governmentcounterpart                                                   1.11.1&#13;
                                                                                                   I&#13;
                                                                                                          Withdrawal&#13;
                                                                                                         applications&#13;
&#13;
1                                                                                          I.I&#13;
                                   I                                                                         I&#13;
&#13;
 Government's                              FiduciaryAgency (in commercialbanks)&#13;
&#13;
 CommercialBank                           1. DesignatedAccount Component DDR&#13;
&#13;
 (counterpart funds)                     2. DesignatedAccount Component R C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The timely availability o f funds and the smooth flow o f funding will be critical elements&#13;
for the government to implement the DDR process within the planned timeframe. The&#13;
Project will therefore use a quick disbursement mechanism in accordance with Bank's&#13;
guidelines for Emergency Recovery Operations. Under this provision, the government&#13;
will be eligible for reimbursement o fup to a total o fUS$39.6 million equivalent against a&#13;
positive list o f imports. Retroactive financing will be possible for expenditures that have&#13;
been incurred up to four months prior to the expected date o f signature o f the financing&#13;
agreement. A joint GovernmentBanks team will be formed to compile and review the list&#13;
of positive imports and related procurement documentation. The first payment against a&#13;
positive list o f imports will consist o f US$10 million equivalent and will be made at&#13;
effectiveness so as to help cover expenditures for the first tranches o f the transitional&#13;
safety net for ex-combatants. The second payment of US$10million equivalent will be&#13;
made when the Government furnishes to IDA evidence inform and substance satisfactory&#13;
to IDA showing that a random sample o f at least five percent o f the demobilized&#13;
combatants have received the first tranche o f the transitional safety net with less that a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              50&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5% error. The third and last payment o f US$19.6 million will be made when the&#13;
Government furnishes evidence in form and substance satisfactory to IDA showing that a&#13;
random sample o f at least five percent o f the demobilized combatants have received the&#13;
second tranche o fthe transitional safety net with less than a 5% error.&#13;
&#13;
FinancialReportingArrangements&#13;
&#13;
The PNDDR/RC will produce quarterly Financial Monitoring Reports (FMRs) and will&#13;
submit the FMRs to IDA within 45 days after the end o f each quarter. The FMRs will&#13;
include financial reports, physical progress and procurement information. At a minimum,&#13;
the financial reports must include the sources and uses o f funds, expenditures by main&#13;
expenditure classifications, beginning and ending cash balances and other supporting&#13;
schedules.&#13;
&#13;
The financial reports should be prepared in a structure and detail that facilitate&#13;
comparison with physical progress. The semi-annual financial statements will comprise&#13;
but will not be limited to: (i) Statement o f Source and Application o f Funds for the&#13;
                               the&#13;
Program during the current financial year, and cumulatively since the start o f the&#13;
Program; (ii)the statement o f expenditures (SOEs); (iii)the Dedicated Account&#13;
StatementReconciliation; and (iv) the Project Account StatementReconciliation and any&#13;
other financial report deemed necessary and relevant.&#13;
&#13;
ExternalAuditing&#13;
&#13;
The audit report should reflect all the activities o f the Program, including those financed&#13;
by other donors and the Government, and must be submitted to IDA within six months&#13;
after the end o f each financial year. The arrangements for the external audit o f the&#13;
financial statements o f the Program should be communicated to IDA through agreed&#13;
terms o f reference. Appropriate terms o f reference for the external auditor must be&#13;
developed and agreed within six months o f Grant Effectiveness.&#13;
&#13;
For the first year, a financial and technical audit will be conducted semi-annually to&#13;
ensure consistency betweenthe physical and the financial implementation o f the Program&#13;
and provide opinion on Program's performance. Thereafter, it's assumed that PNDDR&#13;
will have in place adequate mechanisms to monitor and control physical and financial&#13;
implementation o f the Program; therefore financial audit will be conducted. Audits will&#13;
be conducted by independent auditors acceptable to the Bank in accordance with&#13;
international auditing standards. Audit reports o f such scope and detail agreed by IDA&#13;
would be submitted to the Bank within 6 months after the end o f the audit period. The&#13;
auditor will provide a separate opinion on each: (i)    the Program financial statements, (ii)&#13;
the statement o f expenditure (iii) Designated Accounts. The auditor will also provide&#13;
                                   the&#13;
a management letter on the internal control procedures outlining recommendations for&#13;
improving the control system, the accounting and financial procedures as a result o f the&#13;
audit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              51&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Supervision Plan&#13;
&#13;
A supervision mission will be conducted at least twice every year based on the risk&#13;
assessment of the project. The mission's objectives will include ensuring that strong&#13;
financial management systems are maintained for the project throughout its life. An SOE&#13;
review will be carried out regularly to ensure that expenditures incurred by the project&#13;
remain eligible for IDA funding. The Implementation Status Report will include&#13;
financial management rating for the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Table C:Allocation of GrantProceeds&#13;
&#13;
                                        C8te d'Ivoire&#13;
         Emergency Demobilization, Reintegration and Community Rehabilitation Project&#13;
                                  Disbursement Schedule&#13;
                                       (US$Million)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         IDA&#13;
                                                                               Percentage&#13;
DisbursementCategory                                         Amount             financing&#13;
                                                          (US$million)&#13;
&#13;
 1. DRR - Eligible Imports                                      39.6               100%&#13;
2. DRR - Reintegration                                          12.0               100%&#13;
 3. DRR -Other activities and Project Administration            15.4               80%&#13;
4. RC Component                                                 25.0              100%&#13;
 5. PPF                                                         0.6               100%&#13;
 6. Non-Allocated                                               7.4&#13;
&#13;
Total                                                          100.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            52&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                 8W           To               7W                              6W                                5W                        4W                       3W&#13;
                                             Bamako                                                          To&#13;
                                                       MALI                                                                                                                                                          CTE D'IVOIRE&#13;
                                                                                                           Sikasso&#13;
                                                                                                                                                        BURKINA&#13;
                                                                        Tengrel&#13;
                                                                                                                                           To&#13;
                                                                                                                                     Bobo Dioulasso          FASO&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                To&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               Kampti                                                DEPARTMENT CAPITALS*&#13;
               10N                                                                        Bago                                                                                                             10N&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     REGION CAPITALS&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             To                                      NATIONAL CAPITAL&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                            Batie&#13;
&#13;
                                     Odienne                                    Boundiali                                         Ferkessedougou                                                                                     RIVERS&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      Korhogo                                                                                                                        MAIN ROADS&#13;
&#13;
                            To                                                                                                                                         Komo         Bouna                                           RAILROADS&#13;
                           Beyla                                                                 Bou&#13;
&#13;
               9N                                                                                                                                                                                                                   DEPARTMENT BOUNDARIES&#13;
&#13;
                                                               K O R H O G O                                                                                                                                                         REGION BOUNDARIES&#13;
&#13;
               GUINEA                                  Sassandra                                                     BandamaBlanc                                                                      To&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      Bole&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                              9N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Nzi                                                                                          INTERNATIONAL BOUNDARIES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Touba                                           Maraou                                                    Dabakala&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 *Departments have the same&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     B O U A K E&#13;
                                                                  Seguela                                                                                                                                                        name as their capital.&#13;
               8N                                                                              Mankono                             Katiola                                           Bondoukou               8N&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                       To&#13;
                      To                                                                                                                                                                             Wenchi&#13;
                   Nzerekore                                                                                                                                                     Tanda&#13;
                                             Biankouma                                                          Boumi&#13;
                                                                                                                Boumi                Bouak&#13;
                                                                                                                                      Bouak&#13;
                                     M A N                                                          Lac de&#13;
                         Mont Nimba                                                                Kossou       Sakassou                                M'Bahiakro&#13;
                         (1,752 m)                                    Vavoua         Zuenoula&#13;
                                             Man                                                                                                                                                 To&#13;
                                Danane                                      Lobo                                 Tiebissou                                                                    Sunyani&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Bocanda                   Agnibilkrou&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                        Agnibilkrou&#13;
               7N                               Bangolo                                           Bouafle                                               Daoukro                                              7N&#13;
                                                                       Daloa&#13;
                                                   Duekoue                                       YAMOUSSOUKRO                                                    Abengourou                   GHANA&#13;
                                                                                                     Sinfra                         Dimbokro&#13;
                                        Guiglo                     D A L O A                                                                       Bongouanou&#13;
                         Toulepleu                                                                                                    Toumodi&#13;
                                                                       Issia&#13;
                 To                                                                                          Oum&#13;
                                                                                                             Oum                               A B I D J A N                                                                                 CTE D'IVOIRE&#13;
               Monrovia&#13;
                                                                                           Gagnoa&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    Adzope&#13;
               6N                                                                                                                                                                                            6N&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       Lakota                      Tiassale        Agboville&#13;
                                                                   Soubr&#13;
                                                                   Soubr                                         Divo&#13;
&#13;
                      LIBERIA                                                  Sassandra          Davo&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Nzi                            Komo&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                            Alepe&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                       Aboisso&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      Dabou&#13;
                                                                                                                   Grand-Lahou                                   Abidjan&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                 Adiake&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   Jacqueville   Grand-                               To&#13;
               5N                                                                                                                                               Bassam                             Prestea   5N&#13;
                                                                                                  Sassandra&#13;
&#13;
SEPTEMBER                                                                  San-Pedro                                                                             0          40       80      120 Kilometers                                                                              IBRD&#13;
                                       To                                                                                                                                                                            This map was produced by the Map Design Unit of The World Bank.&#13;
                                     Monrovia                                                         Gulf of Guinea                                                                                                 The boundaries, colors, denominations and any other information&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     shown on this map do not imply, on the part of The World Bank&#13;
                                                   Tabou                                                                                                         0      20       40     60      80 Miles                                                                                     33393&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     Group, any judgment on the legal status of any territory, or any&#13;
         2004                                                                                                                                                                                                        endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
                                 8W                            7W                              6W                                5W                        4W                       3W&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="6913176">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/06/6913176/cote-divoire-emergency-demobilization-reintegration-community-rehabilitation-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/06/6913176/cote-divoire-emergency-demobilization-reintegration-community-rehabilitation-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2006/06/6913176/cote-divoire-emergency-demobilization-reintegration-community-rehabilitation-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2007-01-26T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/07/11/000090341_20060711085040/Rendered/INDEX/T7660.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/07/11/000090341_20060711085040/Rendered/PDF/T7660.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>Q402</credit_no>
        <datestored>2006-07-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2006-06-29T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Cote D'Ivoire - Emergency
            Demobilization, Reintegration and Community Rehabilitation Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Emergency Demobilization,
            Reintegration and Community Rehaibilitation Project for Cote
            D'Ivoire aims at providing needed immediate support
            for: (a) demobilizing and reintegrating about 45,000
            individuals including ex-combatants, child soldiers and
            special groups, (b) rehabilitating or reconstructing social
            and economic infrastructure in the communities most affected
            by conflict, (c) restarting of economic activities by
            vulnerable groups, and (d) strengthening social capital
            throughout the country. The Project includes a quick
            disbursing mechanism that uses a positive list of imports to
            generate counterpart funds to finance rapid project implementation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Cote D'Ivoire - Emergency
            Demobilization, Reintegration and Community Rehabilitation Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Cote D'Ivoire - Emergency
            Demobilization, Reintegration and Community Rehabilitation Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2006/06/6913176/cote-divoire-emergency-demobilization-reintegration-community-rehabilitation-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>CI-Emergency Post-Conflict Assistance
            Project -- P082817</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Transport Economics Policy &amp; Planning,Community Development and Empowerment,Post Conflict Reintegration,Population Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Transport,Health, Nutrition and Population,Social Development</teratopic>
        <count>Cote d'Ivoire</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>West Africa!$!80474</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20060711085040</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other social services</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Transport,Health, Nutrition and Population,Social Development</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Health and other social services</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Accountability, Accounting, Accounting
            Procedures, accounting standards, armed conflict, Auditing,
            audits, Bank branches, basic social services, CAP, capacity
            building, child soldiers, citizens, communication efforts,
            communities, community infrastructure, community services,
            consolidated financial statements, consolidation,
            development activities, development objectives, development
            organizations, Disarmament, diseases, dissemination,
            economic growth, economic reintegration, education, elderly,
            elections, emergency response, employment, employment
            creation, employment opportunities, ex-combatants,
            excombatants, family unit, Financial Management, financial
            policies, gender equity, Government Response, Health, health
            centers, health services, human capital, Human Development,
            Human rights, Human rights violations, income-generating
            activities, industrial production, Information System,
            infrastructure rehabilitation, institutional framework,
            international community, International Organization for
            Migration, International Response, legal rights, lessons
            learned, living conditions, living standards, local
            authorities, local capacity, local governments,
            macroeconomic stability, medical treatment, military
            casualties, nationals, nutrition, operating costs, orphans,
            outreach, Peace, Peace Keeping, Peace Keeping Operations,
            peacekeeping, police, presidential decree, Procurement,
            progress, project grants, Project Implementation,
            psychological support, Public Expenditures, radio,
            Reconciliation, Reconstruction, referral services, Refugees,
            REHABILITATION, rights organizations, road, route, Safety,
            safety net, sanitation, security, Security Forces,
            segregation, self-reliance, service provider, social, social
            capital, social cohesion, social funds, social
            reintegration, Social Security, social services, social
            tensions, spillover, strategic planning, supply systems,
            technical assistance, Transit, Transparency, Transport,
            transportation, true, UNFPA, vocational training, vulnerable
            groups, vulnerable populations, war, water supply, World
            Health Organization
        </keywd>
        <owner>AFT: Human Development 2 (AFTH2)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Emergency Recovery Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>West Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF056705-POST-CONFLICT RECOVERY PLANNING
            AND TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE, AND ECONOMIC</trustfund>
        <repnb>T7660</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets and Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Safety Nets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Funds and Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Zero Pillar</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Research and Surveys for Public Contracts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Combatants</ml:concept><ml:concept>DDR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tracking Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Conflict, Crisis and Fragility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Cohesion and Violence Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Very Vulnerable Groups (disability, orphans, children and youth)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Rights</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Soldiers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Militia</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disarmament, Demobilization, Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disarmament, Demobilization, Reintegration </ml:concept><ml:concept>Reconciliation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Cohesion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vulnerable Groups</ml:concept><ml:concept>Orphans</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Cte dIvoire</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>