<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>19268&#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
'MMe No. 179                                                                                   April IMS&#13;
Regulation in New Natural Gas Markets-&#13;
The Northern Ireland Experience&#13;
Peter Lehbnann    So far gas market liberalization has generally occurred in mature markets-particularly where&#13;
much of the pipeline system has already been laid, as in Argentina, Britain, and the United States.&#13;
In these cases a competitive structure is appropriate. In new markets, however, it may be difficult&#13;
to introduce a competitive regime from the outset, and a different approach and form of&#13;
regulation, such as a period of exclusive licenses, may be needed.' In 1997 the Northern Ireland&#13;
authorities awarded Phoenix Natural Gas an exclusive license for a limited period to develop a&#13;
new gas market from scratch in the greater Belfast area. This Note explains the rationale for a&#13;
period of exclusivity and describes Northern Ireland's approach to gas market regulation.&#13;
The Northern Ireland authorities hacl been eager   The economics of supplying gas to areas outside&#13;
to develop a natural gas market, both for envi-   Belfast are difficult, though better opportunities&#13;
ronmen-tal reasons and to make the province  imiay develop. Indeed, in a ncw gas industry it&#13;
mtore attractive to foreign investors. Their effort  can be argued that the initial development&#13;
was triggered by the conversion to natural gas of  license should be granted only for part of a&#13;
a power plant in Northlern Ireland, wvith coIll-  region or country. In that case it may be best to&#13;
missioning in 1996. The plant wTas owned by   develop the network as a series of regional fran-&#13;
British Gas (nov BG), and the gas is transportecl  clhises. That way. two or more licensees wlill be&#13;
from Britain by a subsea pipeline. This pipeline   well placed to compete in each other's areas&#13;
provided an opportunity to deliver natural gas to   once the industry matures.&#13;
homes and irdustry.&#13;
Monopoly in transportation&#13;
To take up this opportunity, a license for nauiral&#13;
gas for the greater Belfast area was granted to   The authorities accepted British Gas/Phoenix's&#13;
Phoenix Natural Gas in a tender limited to only   argument that a long (twenty-year) transporration&#13;
one other candidate. Phoenix was originally a 100   monopoly period was needed to attract an&#13;
percent 5uLbsidiary ofBG, thougl Kevspan Energy   investor into the markct. The necessary invest-&#13;
now has a 24.5 percent shareholding. Phoenix   mnents appeared to British Gas/Phoenix to be&#13;
was granted a combined license for transport and   fairly marginal. Major marketing risks stemmed&#13;
supply, but cliffcrent approachcs were used for   from having to displace coal, liquefied petroleuLml&#13;
the two activities. An exclusive transport license   gas. and oil in the residential market and from the&#13;
lasts twenty years, but competition in supply wrill  dependence of Phoenix on the decisions of a&#13;
be allowed after only two to eight years.   single body, the Northern Ireland Housing&#13;
Executive, the public housing authority that owns&#13;
Northern Ireland contains 600000 householdls.   more than a quarter of the houses in greater&#13;
with just over 250,000 in the greater Belfast area.   Belfast. There were also substantial technical and&#13;
T The World Bank Group * Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Regulation in New Natural Gas Markets-The Northern Ireland Experience&#13;
financial risks. The autlhorities decided that all   If Phoenix does not meet its obligations, it will&#13;
these risks would be compounded if multiple   lose its exclusive license in the districts where it&#13;
infrastructture licenses were granted.            fails. Thuls other companies couldl then he&#13;
granted transportation licenses.&#13;
Thle autlhorities also agreed with British Gas/&#13;
Phoenix that a single license wouldl have other   Transportation charges&#13;
advantages. A single cleveloper is inore likely to&#13;
clevelop an optimal, well-designed "backbone"    From the outset P'hoenix has maintainecd separate&#13;
network (avoiding, for example, multiple pipes    charges for the use of tlhe transport network hy&#13;
and wires running down the same street). And a    gas suppliers and for the supply of gas to final&#13;
single developer is easier to deal with in terms    customers. Until competition is introdtuced, the&#13;
of granting approvals, planning traffic, making    transport charge will simply he a transfer price&#13;
contingency plans, and providing local authlority    between  Phoenix's  distribution  ancd  sIpply&#13;
support services.                                 btusinesses.&#13;
Development obligations                           Both Phoenix and the authorities recognized that&#13;
the price to final customers wxouldl have to he&#13;
One of the authorities' primary goals was to    kept lowv for many years to persuade ctistomers&#13;
secure the construction of an extensive natural   to switch to gas and that the overall costs of sUp-&#13;
gas pipeline system in Belfast. Thtis investment   plying gas wouIld be dominated by the transport&#13;
obligations were a key part of the license. Several   charges. Thus the debate over pricing focuLsed on&#13;
challenges arise when an investment program is   the transport charges; the supply prices were less&#13;
expected of an exclusive licensee: how to ensure    contentious.&#13;
that the investment takes place, what sanctions&#13;
to put in place if it does not, and how to deal   Standard  approaches  to  setting  transport&#13;
witlh unforeseen circumstances.                   charges are not appropriate for a new industry.&#13;
The regulatory asset base starts fromii zero,&#13;
The license requires Phoenix to complete its net-   changes rapidly, and is Unpredictable. If charges&#13;
work in twelve years and to perform the wxork in   are based on a return on assets, they wxould he&#13;
each of Belfast's twelve districts in a specific order,   exceptionally high at the outset (because of low&#13;
withlin a specified timeframe. Moreover, a pipeline    utilization) and would change sharply fi-om year&#13;
must nLn *xithin 50 meters of 90 percent of the    to ycar. Thus it was decided to set transport&#13;
homes in each clistrict. This was a much more    charges at a level that is expected to provicle an&#13;
cletailed blueprint than Plhoenix would have liked.   8.5 percent real pretax return on cash flows over&#13;
Phloenix argued that it already hacl major sunk    txxernty years, with calculations based on fore-&#13;
investments-in  medium-  and  high-pressure    cast capital and operating costs, sales levels, and&#13;
pipelines-and so hacd the necessary' commercial   mix of sales. Phoenix consideredi this return&#13;
incentives to connect up the maximum load. The    rather low  given the risks involved in the&#13;
detailed blueprint created a risk that Phoenix will   project. But there was some upside from  the&#13;
fail to meet its obligations. TWo safegtiards for   prospect of acdditional transport revenue after&#13;
Plhoenix redluce but do not eliminate the risk:  the initial txventy-year license period. The big&#13;
* The regulator can agree to changes in the   qcuestion mark was the enormous uncertainty&#13;
order and dates of pipeline construction if   about all the forecasts. To address this uncer-&#13;
there are good reasons for doing so.            tainty, it was agreed that there would be a&#13;
* Plhoenix does not have to lay pipes past hous-   reforecast every five years, with one possible&#13;
ing that the Northern Ireland Housing Executive    additional forecast in the initial five-year period.&#13;
hacl not converted to. and does not intencl to    Uncler these reforecasts the previous five years&#13;
convert to, natural gas.                        will be "'water tinder the bridge"-that is,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Phoenix wvill retain any gains and bear any    The scope for competition may be limited given&#13;
losses if developments differ from what vas   the small or nonexistent margins betwZeen trans-&#13;
forecast. Thus there are incentives for efficient   port and supply charges for many years. Still,&#13;
and rapid market development. However, prices   Phoenix wanted an initial exclusivity period. The&#13;
for the remaining period of the license wouild be    company was concerned that potential competi-&#13;
adjusted in light of changes in the forecasts so   tors would protest and that the authorities would&#13;
that the net present value over the remaining   take action if competition did not develop wlhen&#13;
period, given the new forecasts, would be the   it was permitted on paper. In the end the exclu-&#13;
same as in the original net present value    sivity periods agreed on were quite short-partly&#13;
calculations.                                   because the rest of the United Kingdom has com&#13;
petitive gas markets.&#13;
One of the most controversial issues in the nego-&#13;
tiations over transport charges was how to deal   Prices to final customers&#13;
with changes in the distribution of gas sales&#13;
among market segments and wvith the effects of   A key challenge for the new gas industry is to&#13;
such changes on costs and average prices. In    win customers who are using competing fuels.&#13;
addressing these matters the authorities wantcdl   The gas industry sometimes argues that it needs&#13;
to prevent excessive profits for Phoenix, but also    neither regulation nor gas-to-gas competition&#13;
to provide incentives for rapid development of   because there is strong competition between&#13;
the network and market.                         fuels. In a mature market vith many gas cus-&#13;
tomers, interfuel competition may need to be&#13;
Competition in supply                           supplemented, especially in the residential mar-&#13;
ket. But where a gas industry is being estab-&#13;
In a mature utility industry it is generally desir-   lished, the industrv's argument is valid.&#13;
able to separate the transport business and the&#13;
supply business, as there is different scope for   Thus in Northern Ireland there is no regulation&#13;
competition and different competitors in the twxo    of gas prices to consumers, other than rules bar-&#13;
sectors. In a developing industry, however, too    ring discrimination, for the first five years of the&#13;
strict a separation is undesirable. For example.   license. After that the regulator can introduce a&#13;
the transport arm and the supply arm should   price formula if he decides that customers' inter-&#13;
plan an integrated rollout of the network to avoid   csts are not adequately protected by competition&#13;
major cost inefficiencies. That process involves   between fuels or within the gas market. This reg-&#13;
information sharing and cooperation that might   ulation applies only to consumers using less than&#13;
be unacceptable in a mature industry. Moreover,   2.2 million kilowatt-hours a year; larger industrial&#13;
the cost allocations between infrastructure and    customers are not subject to regulation of final&#13;
marketing are blurred in the early days of a new    prices.&#13;
industry.&#13;
The license sets out extremely broad principles&#13;
Phoenix will face competition in supply in domes-   for determining prices to customers if and when&#13;
tic and small industry markets (less than 2.2 mil-   regulation is introduced. Moreover, there is a pro-&#13;
lion kilowatt-hours a year) in late 2004. Given that   vision for a ruling by the Monopolies and Mergers&#13;
customers are being connected gradually over the    Commission if the regulator and licensee cannot&#13;
eight-year exclusive license period, the average    agree on prices.&#13;
monopoly supply period for these customers will&#13;
be four to five years. The monopoly period is   Cooperative approach to regulation&#13;
shorter for larger industrial customers-from twro&#13;
to three years, with each district opening up to    The former regulator for electricity in Northern&#13;
competition on a rolling basis.                 Ireland has become the joint gas and electricity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Regulation in New Natural Gas Markets-The Northern Ireland Experience&#13;
regulator. But for several reasons the common                 than was expected. There has .tlso heen a sholt-&#13;
adversarial approach to regulation is inappropri-             age of appliance retailers and, more important,&#13;
ate in the new  gas market. The uncertainty and               qualified installers.&#13;
pace of change mean that the grounci rles wS;ill&#13;
clhange rapidly-both  sides need  to recognize                It is still early days. but so far it has heen the mar-&#13;
this. The lack of an asset hase and the absence               ket rather than regulation that has had the m ajor&#13;
of  entrenched" high operating costs will also                impact on  the  dcevelopment of the  Northern&#13;
affect the regulator-'s approach. In any case the             Irelanid gas industry.&#13;
normal regulatory battle-where the regulator&#13;
wants loxw prices and the company wants higlh    Ihis NIL' htu Ibeen pric Wxit i                 .le p h v (,ol cxroid Luine. (In,&#13;
profits-wvill likely be replaced in tlhe early years           lUrlrrv. ndi Mtiilin i'Inkelt of (vnlr i . I need Kingdoin.&#13;
hy a major shared  objective: both  sides want                   Tie inpaik   s, icc wni t h    inI pon uids pri hip ruling&#13;
rapi(l penetration of the market. Furtlhermore, at               mg nurkets mognweC his.&#13;
the initial stages the fledgling industry will he a&#13;
small or medium-size company and shouldl not                  PeterLemanan  (alllehmann.demon.co.lD,&#13;
he  hurdened  Isy  unnecessarily  hig7h  costs  of            until 1998, Commercial Director' Centrica,&#13;
funding the regulator's office, staffing a hig reg-           now Chairmnan, Enerqy Saving Trtst. t, Cited&#13;
tulator;' affairs team, ancd funding inquiries from           Kinzgdlom&#13;
the Monopolies ancl Mergers Commission.&#13;
Viewpoint is an open     Conclusion&#13;
forum intended to&#13;
oncourage dissemination&#13;
of and debate on ideas,  A lack of good precedents and credible compet-&#13;
innovations, and best    ing offers made negotiations over the gals license&#13;
practices for expanding  unusually difficult in Nortlhern Ireland. For good&#13;
the private sector The&#13;
views published are      reasons, the  approach  taken  to  choosing  thie&#13;
those of the authors and  licensee vwas partly hut not fully competitive. In&#13;
should rot be attributed  some circUmstances a more competitive process&#13;
tc the World Bank or any&#13;
ol its affiliated organize-  might he [letter. Still, the license that emerged&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the  may he useful for anyone vxorking on the regu-&#13;
conclusions represent    lation of newv gas industries.&#13;
official policy of the&#13;
World Bank or of its&#13;
Executive Directors or   In the two years since license discussions   'ere&#13;
the countries they       concluded, Phoenix  has completed  the  initial&#13;
present.                 clevelopment of its network, meeting all regula-&#13;
To order additional      tory targets and overcoming some inevitable clif-&#13;
copies please call       ficulties. Moreover, Phoenix's gas prices have&#13;
202 458 11 11 or contact&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,   been lo.er than was anticipated.&#13;
Room FlItK-208,&#13;
The World Bank,          Still, the maarket has posed some tough challenges.&#13;
tift H Street, NW,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 2W3,    Competing fuel prices have heen low  (especially&#13;
or Internet address      for oil), and threatened competitors, especially in&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.   residential markets, haxve fought back. The North-&#13;
The serion in a no&#13;
available on-ine nrn Ireland Housing Executive, which had necdecd&#13;
(www.worldbank.org/      to demonstrate impartiality hetwveen fuel stuppli&#13;
html/fpd/notest/         ers, has only recently announcccl that natural gas&#13;
® Printed or recycled   iS the preferred fuieL. As a result fewer of the exec-&#13;
paper                    utive's properties have been refurbished with gas&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="692837">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/04/692837/regulation-new-natural-gas-markets-northern-ireland-experience
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/04/692837/regulation-new-natural-gas-markets-northern-ireland-experience</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/04/692837/regulation-new-natural-gas-markets-northern-ireland-experience</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/11/17/000094946_00110805321680/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/11/17/000094946_00110805321680/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2000-11-17T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Regulation of new natural gas markets - the
            Northern Ireland experience
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            So far gas market liberalization has
            generally occurred in mature markets-particularly where much
            of the pipeline system has already been laid, as in
            Argentina, Britain, and the United States. In these cases a
            competitive structure is appropriate. In new markets,
            however, it may be difficult to introduce a competitive
            regime from the outset, and a different approach and form of
            regulation, such as a period of exclusive licenses, may be
            needed. In 1997 the Northern Ireland authorities awarded
            Phoenix Natural Gas an exclusive license for a limited
            period to develop a new gas market from scratch in the
            greater Belfast area. This Note explains the rationale for a
            period of exclusivity and describes Northern Ireland's
            approach to gas market regulation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Regulation of new natural gas markets - the
            Northern Ireland experience
        </docna>
        <display_title>Regulation of new natural gas
            markets - the Northern Ireland experience</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1999/04/692837/regulation-new-natural-gas-markets-northern-ireland-experience</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Oil Refining &amp; Gas Industry,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Oil &amp; Gas,Carbon Policy and Trading,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Energy,Industry,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>United Kingdom</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Lehmann, Peter</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_00110805321680</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Fuels</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 179</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Energy,Industry,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Oil &amp; Gas</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Natural gas; Market liberalization; Northern
            Ireland; Gas market; Regulatory framework; Gas pipeline;
            Pipeline transport; Transport costs; Gas supply;
            Competitiveness; Gas prices; Gas industry; Residential areas
            coal,construction,fuel,fuel
            prices,fuels,gas,gas and electricity,gas industries,gas
            industry,gas market,gas market liberalization,gas market
            regulation,gas markets,gas pipeline,gas prices,gas sales,gas
            suppliers,Monopolies,natural gas,natural gas
            markets,oil,pipeline,pipeline construction,pipeline
            system,pipelines,pipes,present value
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>19268</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competitiveness and Competition Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Microeconomic and Market Reforms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Servers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Switches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oil Refining &amp; Gas Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Support Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competition Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Network Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>United Kingdom</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>