<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
THE WORLD BANK&#13;
Report No. 16098-TO&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
August 13, 1997&#13;
Technical Agriculture 3&#13;
Country Department 13&#13;
Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Currency unit    CFA Franc (CFAF)&#13;
US$1.00 = 509 CFAF (as of March26, 1996)&#13;
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES&#13;
Metric system&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
AfDB         African Development Bank&#13;
BCEAO        Banque Centrale des Etats de I'Afrique Occidentale (Central Bank of Western African&#13;
Countries)&#13;
BIE          Public Investment Budget (Budget d Invesiissement de l 'Etat)&#13;
CAA          Agricultural Apprenticeship Center&#13;
CAS          Country Assistance Strategy&#13;
CCS          Coordination and Monitoring Committee (Comite de Coordination et de Suivi)&#13;
CFAF         Franc of the Central African Monetary Union&#13;
CFD          Caisse Fran,aise de De'veloppement (French Development Bank)&#13;
CNCA         National Bank for Agricultural Credit (Caisse Nationale de Credit Agricole)&#13;
COOPEC       Savings and Loans Cooperatives (Cooperative d'Epargne et de Credit)&#13;
CRAP         Regional Agricultural Research Center&#13;
DAF          Directorate of Administration and Finance (Direction Administrative et Financiere)&#13;
DMN          Directorate of National Meteorology (Direction de la Mietiorologie Nationale)&#13;
DNRA         National Directorate for Agricultural Research (Direction Nationale de la Recherche&#13;
Agricole)&#13;
DPDR         Prefectural Division for Rural Development Division (Division Prefectorale du&#13;
Developpement Rural)&#13;
DRDR         Regional Directorate for Rural Development (Direction Regionale du Developpement&#13;
Rural)&#13;
EDI          Economic Development Institute&#13;
ERAC         Economic Recovery and Adjustment Credit&#13;
ERR          Economic Rate of Return&#13;
ESA          Institute of Higher Studies in Agronomy&#13;
EU           European Union&#13;
FAC          Fond d'Aide et de Coope'ration (French Aid and Cooperation Fund)&#13;
FINSAC       Financial Sector Adjustment Credit&#13;
FONGTO       Togolese Federation of NGOs (Fede'ration des ONG du Togo)&#13;
FUCEC        National Union of Saving and Loans Cooperation of Togo (Federation des Unions des&#13;
Cooperatives dE'pargne et de Credit)&#13;
ICAT         Technical Assistance and Support Institute (Institut de Conseil et d'Appui Technique)&#13;
IFAD         International Fund for Agricultural Development&#13;
INCV         National Food Crops Institute (Institut National des Cultures Vivrieres)&#13;
INS          National Soils Institute (Institut National des Sols)&#13;
INTA         Food Processing Technology Institute (Institut National des Technologies Agricoles)&#13;
INZ          Animal Husbandry Institute (Institut National de Zoonology)&#13;
Vice-President:        Jean-Louis Sarbib, AFRVP&#13;
Country Director:      Theodore Ahlers, AFC13&#13;
Technical Manager:     Jean-Paul Chausse, AFTA3&#13;
Task Team Leader:      Christian Fauliau, AFTA3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IRCC         Coffee and Cocoa Research Institute (Institut de Recherche Cafi Cacao)&#13;
IRCT         Textile Crops Research Institute (Institut de Recherche sur les Cultures Textiles)&#13;
ITRA         Togolese Agricultural Research Institute (Institut Togolais de Recherche Agricole)&#13;
LDPA         Letter of Agricultural Development Policy&#13;
MAEP         Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock and Fisheries (Ministere de I 'Agriculture, de&#13;
l 'Elevage et de la Peche)&#13;
MEF          Ministry of Economy and Finance&#13;
NGO          Non-Governmental Organization&#13;
NPV          Net Present Value&#13;
OPAT         Togolese Agency for Agricultural Products (Office des Produits Agricoles Togolais)&#13;
OPEA         Professional Agricultural Organizations (Organisations Professionnelles Economiques&#13;
Agricoles)&#13;
PERP         Public Enterprise Restructuring Project&#13;
PFP          Policy Framework Paper&#13;
PIP          Public Investment Program (Programme d 'Investissement Public)&#13;
PNASA        National Agricultural Services Project (Projet National d'Appui aux Services Agricoles)&#13;
PNPE         National Small Ruminant Project (Projet National d'Appui au Petit Elevage)&#13;
OP           Observation Points&#13;
PSM          Public Sector Management&#13;
PVA          Agricultural Extension Project (Projet de Vulgarisation Agricole)&#13;
RMFI         Rural and Microfinance Institutions&#13;
S&amp;C          Savings and Credit&#13;
SAFFIC       Coffee-Cocoa Support Agency (Societt Nationale d'Appui a la Filiere Cafe-Cacao)&#13;
SARS         Farming System Research Support Sites (Site d'Appui a la Recherche Systeme)&#13;
STN          National Technical Secreteriat (Secreteriat National Technical)&#13;
SOE          Statement of Expenditures&#13;
SONAPH       National Palm Oil Company (Societe Nationale du Palmier a Huile)&#13;
SOTOCO       Togolese Cotton Company (Societe Togolaise du Coton)&#13;
STER         Togolese Rural Extension System (Systeme Togolais d'Encadrement Rural)&#13;
T&amp;V          Training and Visit&#13;
TOGOGRAIN Togolese Cereal Bank (Etablissement d'Etat de stockage des cereales)&#13;
UEMOA        West African Economic and Monetary Union (Union Economique et Monitaire&#13;
d'Afrique de l 'Ouest)&#13;
UNDP         United Nations Development Program&#13;
USAID        United States Agency for International Development&#13;
VB           Field Extensionist (Vulgarisateur de Base)&#13;
VDF          Village Development Fund&#13;
WFP          World Food Program&#13;
GOVERNMENT FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January 1 - December 31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
1. SOCIO-ECONOMIC BACKGROUND .................................................................1I&#13;
A. BACKGROUND ........................................................................1I&#13;
B. RECENT DEVELOPMENTS .........................................................................1&#13;
II. AGRICULTURAL  SECTORAL  BACKGROUND  ..................................................................2&#13;
A. FARMING  SYSTEMS AND  PRODUCTION  .........................................................................                                   2&#13;
Agro-ecological Zones .................................................................2&#13;
Production  Potential ..................................................................2&#13;
Main  Products and  Productivity ..................................................................3&#13;
Rural Natural Resources ..................................................................4&#13;
B. AGRICULTURAL  INSTITUTIONS .........................................................................5&#13;
Ministry of Rural Development and Village Water Resources (MAEP) ..............................5&#13;
Agricultural Services ..................................................................6&#13;
Training in Agriculture ..................................................................7&#13;
Non-Governmental Organizations (NGOs) ............................................................... ...7&#13;
Credit to  Agriculture ..................................................................7&#13;
Other Institutions Operating  in Rural Areas ...............................................................8...&#13;
Trading of Agricultural Inputs ..................................................................9&#13;
Rural Investments:  Current Projects ...........................                                 ......................................9&#13;
C. THE  GOVERNMENT'S  SECTORAL  STRATEGY ........................................................................ 10&#13;
Role of Agriculture  in the Economy ...........................                                 ...................................... 10&#13;
D. SECTORAL STRATEGY AND WORLD BANK PROGRAMS IN TOGO ..................................... 10&#13;
E. LESSONS LEARNED FROM THE EXPERIENCE OF THE WORLD BANK AND OTHER&#13;
DONORS ........                 ................................................................ II&#13;
III. THE PROJECT .................................................................                                                                   12&#13;
A. PROJECT  OBJECTIVES AND  STRATEGY ........................................................................                                     12&#13;
B. SUMMARY DESCRIPTION ........................................................................                                                 13&#13;
C. DETAILED  PROJECT  DESCRIPTION ........................................................................                                      14&#13;
Restructuring  of and  Support to  Extension  Services ........................................................... 14&#13;
Support to  Agricultural Research ......................                                ........................................... 15&#13;
Support to  Pilot Agricultural Credit Operations ................................................................. 15&#13;
Pilot VDF  ................................................................. 16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Support to the MAEP ........................................ 16&#13;
IV. PROJECT COSTS AND FINANCING ............................................. 17&#13;
A. PROJECT COSTS .............................................                                           17&#13;
B. PROJECT FINANCING .............................................                                       18&#13;
C. PROCUREMENT .............................................                                            21&#13;
D. DISBURSEMENTS .............................................                                           24&#13;
E. ACCOUNTING, FINANCIAL REPORTS, AND AUDITS .............................................               25&#13;
Financial Management and Accounting .............................................                    25&#13;
Budgeting ............................................. 26&#13;
Auditing .............................................                                               26&#13;
V. PROJECT ORGANIZATION AND IMPLEMENTATION .............................................  27&#13;
A. PROJECT MANAGEMENT AND CRITICAL STEPS .............................................                   27&#13;
Pre-implementation phase ............................................. 27&#13;
Project Implementation ............................................. 27&#13;
Monitoring, Evaluation and Reporting ............................................. 28&#13;
VI. PROJECT ECONOMIC ANALYSIS ............................................. 29&#13;
A. CURRENT AND POTENTIAL YIELDS .............................................                            29&#13;
Project Interventions ............................................. 29&#13;
B. ESTIMATING FARM-LEVEL BENEFITS AND COSTS .............................................                30&#13;
Input and Output Markets ............................................. 30&#13;
Farm  Budgets ............................................. 31&#13;
C. PROJECT ECONOMIC VIABILITY .............................................                              32&#13;
VII. BENEFITS AND RISKS ............................................. 33&#13;
A. BENEFITS .............................................                                                33&#13;
Direct Project Benefits ............................................. 33&#13;
Indirect Benefits ............................................. 34&#13;
B. PROJECT RISKS .............................................                                           35&#13;
Quantifiable risks ............................................. 35&#13;
Non-quantifiable Risks .............................................                                 35&#13;
C. FISCAL BURDEN OF THE PROJECT ON THE BORROWER .............................................             38&#13;
D. PROJECT IMPACTS ..................................................                                    39&#13;
VIII. ASSURANCES AND RECOMMENDATIONS .............................................                          39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
1.    Detailed Project Description&#13;
2.    OED Recommendations and PNASA Responses&#13;
3.    Economic Analysis&#13;
4.    ICAT Organigramme&#13;
5.    MAEP Organigramme&#13;
6.    ITRA Organigramme&#13;
7.    Budget Impact&#13;
8.    M &amp; E Indicators in Relation to Main Objectives&#13;
9.    Project Objectives and Key Performance Indicators&#13;
10.   Schedule of Liquidation, Privatization and Legal Framework Improvement&#13;
11.   Terms of Reference for Mid-Term Review&#13;
12.   IFAD's Review and Recommendations: Summary&#13;
13.   Project Documentation&#13;
MAP: IBRD No. 27983&#13;
This report is based on the findings of Bank appraisal mission carried out in Togo in March&#13;
1996, consisting of Mr. C Fauliau (mission leader), Mr. K. Egbeto (financial analyst), and Mr.&#13;
R. Poison (economist). The preparation of the project was supported by Mr. Noel Chabeuf,&#13;
(livestock specialist), Mr. Harry Palmier (SPAAR, agriculture research specialist), Mr. J.&#13;
Weetjens (extension specialist) and a team of FAO/CP. Secretarial support was provided by&#13;
Mme. W. Sajous. The project's lead advisor, Mr. J. Baah-Dwomoh and peer reviewers,&#13;
Messrs.. F. Schorosch and C. de Haan have reviewed the project from the Initial Executive&#13;
Project Summary. The Negotiations were completed on May 30, 1997. Mr. T. Ahlers is the&#13;
Country Department Director and Mr. J.P. Chausse the Technical Manager of the Agriculture&#13;
Group responsible for this operation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
Credit and Project Summary&#13;
Borrower:         Government of Togo&#13;
Beneficiaries     Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock and Fisheries (MAEP),&#13;
Technical Assistance and Support Institute,&#13;
Togolese Agricultural Research Institute,&#13;
Savings and Credit Cooperatives,&#13;
Professional Agricultural Organizations, and&#13;
Village Communities&#13;
Credit Amount     SDR 19.2 million (equivalent to US$26.2 million)&#13;
Terms:            Standard IDA terms, with 40 years maturity and 10 year grace period&#13;
Project Descriotior   The National Agricultural Services Support Project (PNASA) aims to&#13;
increase standards of living in rural areas by improving agricultural&#13;
productivity, production and incomes. It supports the restructuring and&#13;
strengthening of Togo's institutions responsible for providing core&#13;
agricultural services to farmers and the emergence of strong and viable&#13;
agricultural producer associations.  The project would: (a) enhance&#13;
participation of farmers in the programming, management and financing of&#13;
agricultural services (adaptive research, extension, Professional&#13;
Agricultural Organizations - OPEAs); (b) strengthen MAEP's sectoral&#13;
policy formulation implementation and monitoring capabilities (including&#13;
agricultural statistics); (c) increase agricultural productivity by&#13;
strengthening the agricultural research system to better meet farmers'&#13;
needs, placing greater emphasis on protection of the environment and&#13;
integrating it more closely into regional and international networks; (d)&#13;
facilitate a progressive transfer of import supply and marketing activities&#13;
to OPEAs and the private sector; and (f) foster the development of&#13;
selected financial intermediation institutions in pilot areas.&#13;
The project includes five components:&#13;
(a)         Agricultural Services.  The project would support the creation of a&#13;
decentralized, semi-private and autonomous Technical Assistance and&#13;
Support Institute (ICAT), with farmers' participation, which would&#13;
consolidate and replace existing governmental or parastatal extension&#13;
services and retrain their staff, and would be responsible for providing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
improved extension services to farmers and support to farmer&#13;
organizations;&#13;
(b)         Agricultural Research. The project would strengthen Togo's agricultural&#13;
research system by consolidating all existing research institutions into a&#13;
new decentralized, semi-private and autonomous Togolese Agricultural&#13;
Research Institute (ITRA), with farmers' participation;&#13;
(c)         Agricultural Credit. The project would include two pilot rural finance&#13;
schemes: (i) grassroot savings and loans operations through selected&#13;
existing non-governmental organizations, to test a successful approach for&#13;
ensuring accessibility to agriculture credit by small producers, including&#13;
women, to these essential services;&#13;
(d)         Village Development Fund. A Village Development Fund to support&#13;
demand-driven small rural infrastructure at the community level;&#13;
(e)         Ministri of Agriculture. Livestock and Fisheries (MAEP). The project&#13;
would provide assistance for the reorganization of MAEP, and to build up&#13;
its capacity in policy design, planning, programming and program&#13;
evaluation.&#13;
Benefits and Risks:  By increasing agricultural productivity, the project would help Togo meet&#13;
its goal of alleviating rural poverty and achieve its strategic objectives of&#13;
national food security and increased exports. In the short term, improved&#13;
cultivation techniques would result both in increased production and better&#13;
environmental protection. Streamlining MAEP and reinforcing its policy&#13;
making and monitoring abilities would result in a policy and institutional&#13;
framework that would be more responsive to priorities and constraints in&#13;
the country.&#13;
Other important benefits of the project would come through its impact on&#13;
institutional capacity-building, good governance and coordination of&#13;
donor operations. The main agencies, ITRA and ICAT, would be&#13;
managed as private enterprises with effective participation of beneficiaries&#13;
to ensure transparency and demand-driven management.  Farmers'&#13;
organizations would be strengthened and encouraged to play a much&#13;
increased role in the management of the sector.&#13;
The main project risks, which affect all projects in Togo, are that: (i) the&#13;
Government may "backtrack" on its decisions to decentralize services and&#13;
bestow increased autonomy and responsibility to local institutions and (ii)&#13;
the country's severe fiscal constraints may curtail its capacity to&#13;
satisfactorily fund project activities. However, government commitment&#13;
to decentralization and empowerment is strong, and increasingly assertive&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iii -&#13;
farmers organizations supported by donors, limit greatly any possibility of&#13;
backtracking. The financing by beneficiaries, through their associations,&#13;
of a large share of agricultural service institutions would mitigate the risk&#13;
of critical funding shortages, even after the end of external financial&#13;
support.&#13;
Economic Rate of&#13;
Return:             21.3 percent, with a net present value of CFAF 9,987 million.&#13;
Poverty Category    Program of Targeted Interventions&#13;
Environmental&#13;
Category.           C&#13;
Man:                IBRD No. 27983&#13;
Estimated Costs and Financing Plan&#13;
Project Costs&#13;
(US$ million)&#13;
Expenditures Categories Costs   Local   Foreign    Total    % Total   % Foreign&#13;
Costs    Costs                Cost    Exchange&#13;
- Civil Works                   4.3      3.1       7.4        14          42&#13;
- Goods and Equipment           1.4       5.8      7.2        14          81&#13;
- Vehicles                      4.8       5.7      10.5       20          54&#13;
- Consulting Services, Studies,&#13;
and Training                   6.5      2.7       9.2        17          29&#13;
- Social Capital                0.1                0.1        --&#13;
- Operating Costs              11.9       3.2      15.0       29          21&#13;
- Severance Pay                 1.7                 1.7        3&#13;
- PPF Refinancing               0.3       1.2       1.5        3          80&#13;
TOTAL                          30.9      21.7      52.6       100         41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iv -&#13;
Financing Plan&#13;
(US$ million)&#13;
ICAT      ITRA     Institutional   Pilot Rural   VDF   PPF  TOTAL&#13;
Strengthening    Finance&#13;
IDA             9.2       7.0         7.6          0.9                1.5    26.2&#13;
IFAD            3.9       2.1         3.1           0.6       0.3            10.0&#13;
Other Donors    0.5       0.5         0.5                                     1.5&#13;
OPEAs            1.6       1.0                                                2.6&#13;
Government      2.4       2.4         7.0          0.4                       12.2&#13;
Total           17.6      13.0        18.2          1.9       0.3    1.5    52.6&#13;
Numbers may not add up due to rounding.&#13;
Estimated Disbursements of IDA Credit&#13;
(US$ million)&#13;
FY98        FY99       FY2000      FY2001      FY2002      FY2003&#13;
Annual         3.5          6.5         5.7         6.0         3.0          1.5&#13;
Cumulative     3.5         10.0        15.7        21.7         24.7        26.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
I.    SOCIO-ECONOMIC BACKGROUND&#13;
A. BACKGROUND&#13;
1.1   At the beginning of the 1980s, after a decade of high growth and heavy external&#13;
borrowing to finance an ambitious public investment program, Togo failed to adjust to a sharp&#13;
decline in the international prices of its major exports (phosphate, coffee and cocoa). Its&#13;
financial situation worsened significantly and it quickly found itself saddled with severe&#13;
macroeconomic imbalances and high external indebtedness. Stabilization and adjustment&#13;
programs implemented between 1985 and 1989, with the support of the Bretton Woods&#13;
institutions and other donors, helped the country achieve a substantial liberalization of its&#13;
economy and led to a resumption of growth despite a less favorable external environment, with&#13;
commodity prices far below the peak level reached in 1980.&#13;
1.2   The Togolese reform process, which began in 1985, was centered on: (a) reducing&#13;
unsustainable public sector deficits; and (b) liberalizing the economy. The structural reform&#13;
program achieved significant progress in dealing with severe problems in all areas of economic&#13;
activity: agricultural pricing and marketing; restructuring of the public enterprise sector; public&#13;
resource allocation and efficiency; domestic and external trade taxation; and the incentive&#13;
framework for non-agricultural sectors. Real GDP growth averaged 3.4 percent a year between&#13;
1984 and 1989 (with real annual growth of cash crops output averaging 11 percent and&#13;
manufacturing 6 percent).&#13;
B.   RECENT DEVELOPMENTS&#13;
1.3   Political Developments. By the end of the 1980s the Government came under increasing&#13;
pressure to establish a multi-party system. A period of political crisis ensued, marred by violent&#13;
street riots and mass civil disobedience. A national conference, convened in July 1991, led to the&#13;
formation of a one-year transition government. Parliamentary and presidential elections were&#13;
scheduled for July 1992, but political violence disturbed the electoral calendar and paralyzed&#13;
economic activity from November 1992 through July 1993. The political situation improved&#13;
during the second half of 1993. In August 1993, President Eyadema was re-elected for a five-&#13;
year term and legislative elections were completed in March 1994.&#13;
1.4   Economic Developments. The combination of socio-political turmoil and reduction of&#13;
government expenditures, exacerbated by the drying up of foreign aid, led to a severe contraction&#13;
of the economy. During 1991-93, GDP fell by 21 percent, fiscal revenues dropped by a&#13;
cumulative 52 percent and, by the end of 1993, the overall fiscal deficit widened to 15 percent of&#13;
GDP. The government accumulated substantial domestic payment arrears amounting to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2 -&#13;
equivalent of 8 percent in 1993, with more than half representing unpaid salaries and social&#13;
security contributions. Exports and imports contracted sharply. The substantial drop in net&#13;
foreign financing led to a marked deterioration in the balance of payments.&#13;
1.5   Post-Devaluation Developments. Following the devaluation of the CFA Franc (CFAF)&#13;
in January 1994, the return to political stability and the resumption of structural reforms, the&#13;
economy showed clear signs of recovery. Real growth reached 14 percent in 1994 and 8 percent&#13;
in 1995, reflecting a solid recovery from the depressed levels of 1992 and 1993. In line with&#13;
program targets, consumer prices rose by about 35 percent on average in 1994. The relatively&#13;
high inflation in 1994, similar to that in several other CFA countries, reflected a variety of&#13;
factors, including the effects of the devaluation on the prices of imported goods and services,&#13;
large inflows of capital, Togo's strong economic recovery and a drop in the supply of food crops&#13;
during the second half of the year. Inflationary pressures have abated since then; the average CPI&#13;
increase was 7 percent in 1995 and is estimated at about 5 percent in 1996. Despite a sharp drop&#13;
in cotton production during the 1995/96 crop season, the economic recovery remains robust and&#13;
real GDP growth is estimated at 6 percent in 1996, as the decline in cotton output was&#13;
compensated by buoyant trade and mining activity.&#13;
II. AGRICULTURAL SECTORAL BACKGROUND&#13;
A.   FARMING SYSTEMS AND PRODUCTION&#13;
Agro-ecological Zones&#13;
2.1   Togo has six agro-ecological zones, running from north to south (a) the dry inland&#13;
savannah zone in the north, with high rural population density and farming systems based on&#13;
millet, sorghum, cowpeas, peanuts and cotton; (b) the Oti River hydromorphological system with&#13;
low rural population density and the domain of sorghum, fonio, cowpeas, peanuts and irrigated&#13;
rice as the main crops; (c) the dry mountainous northern Atacora zone, with low rural population&#13;
density in the west, higher in the east, dominated by sorghum, yams, peanuts and cotton; (d) the&#13;
middle and southern Atacora mountainous and sub-humid zone, with average rural population&#13;
density and a diversified agriculture based on maize, sorghum, yams and peanuts in the north&#13;
(Sokode), and maize, cassava, coffee, cocoa and oil palm in the southeast (Kpalime); (e) the&#13;
Mono river basin, with low to average rural population density, and planted in maize, yams, rain-&#13;
fed rice, cowpeas and cotton; and (f) the dry coastal and precoastal zone, with a dense rural&#13;
population and maize, cotton, cassava, peanuts and oil palm as the main crops.&#13;
Production Potential&#13;
2.2   Soil Potential. Togo is relatively rich in arable land, but the distribution of good land is&#13;
uneven. The coastal and savannah regions run the greatest risk of soil deterioration. Their&#13;
current semi-intensive cropping systems will shortly be unable to satisfy the food needs of the&#13;
population, and soil fertility decline--already started due to intensified cropping--will accelerate&#13;
unless radical steps are taken. The three central regions-Plateau, Center and Kara-have good&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
potential and will be able to meet the needs of their projected populations, even with the current&#13;
farmning systems, well beyond the coming decade.&#13;
2.3   Production Systems. Togo's main farming systems are the pastoral, agro-pastoral and&#13;
agricultural systems. The scope for development of pastoral and agro-pastoral systems, in which&#13;
livestock predominates, is constrained by limited grazing potential and animal health and water&#13;
problems. In systems where crops predominate, herding and farming are often separate, but they&#13;
are beginning to be integrated with the development of animal traction. Productivity increases of&#13;
the main farming systems face several constraints: (a) the state of natural resources (poor&#13;
chemical characteristics of many soils, deterioration caused by climatic changes and human&#13;
population pressures); (b) the rudimentary technological level of farmers (cotton farmers being&#13;
an exception); (c) population pressures, migration problems and land tenure issues; (d)&#13;
inadequate marketing systems resulting in high prices for inputs and low prices of marketed&#13;
products; and (e) inefficiency of public services.&#13;
2.4   Farm Structure. Farms vary a great deal in terms of the area under cultivation and the&#13;
type of equipment used. The cultivated area varies from less than two hectares in the more&#13;
populous zones of the southern and northern prefectures to more than 10 hectares in the center.&#13;
Per capita cultivated area ranges from less than 0.10 hectare for lands farmed manually to more&#13;
than 1.5 hectare in the cotton growing areas, where draft animals are used. At present 1.6 to 2.0&#13;
million people are working in farming. The number of rural families now exceeds 400,000.&#13;
Main Products and Productivity&#13;
2.5   Agriculture.  The last agricultural census was taken in 1981.  Since that time&#13;
extrapolations have been carried out using quick surveys (which were disrupted, however, by the&#13;
socio-political crisis). Except for cash crops like cotton, coffee and cocoa, for which figures can&#13;
be supplied by marketing companies, the statistical data presented in this report should be used&#13;
with caution. Togo's main food crops are cassava (411,000 tons annually), yams (364,000 tons),&#13;
maize in the south (251,000 tons) and millet and sorghum in the north (123,000 tons). Rice&#13;
production (38,000 tons of paddy rice) is growing rapidly but does not meet the needs of&#13;
domestic consumption (28,000 metric tons of rice imported in 1994). Togo has the potential of&#13;
being self-sufficient in food, but per capita production of foodcrops over the whole period 1984-&#13;
1994 declined, despite an increase in absolute terms in production of maize and rice.&#13;
Table 2.1 Trend in the per capita production of foodstuffs&#13;
Average 1978/82   Average 1983/87      1994&#13;
(kg/inhabitant)   (kg/inhabitant)   (kg/inhabitant)&#13;
Total cereals          110                121              111&#13;
Total roots/tubers     336               251               210&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4 -&#13;
2.6   The chief export crops are cocoa (5,000 tons in 1994, down from 14,000 tons in 1985),&#13;
coffee (17,000 tons in 1994) and cotton (130,000 tons in 1994). The production of cotton has&#13;
soared (an annual increase of nearly 12 percent between 1986 and 1991) and today almost&#13;
200,000 small farmers, about half of the farming population, are involved in this activity. Coffee&#13;
production improved markedly between 1984 and 1989 after the introduction of new varieties of&#13;
Robusta. The export crop base is still relatively narrow. However, the devaluation of the CFAF&#13;
in January 1994, combined with a rise in world market prices, has given new life to the&#13;
production of export crops. A private contract-farming program of aromatic plant production for&#13;
export has initiated diversification of agricultural operations, employing more than 600 persons.&#13;
2.7   Livestock. In 1993, Togo counted about 240,000 cattle, 2.4 million small ruminants&#13;
(sheep and goats), 248,000 pigs and 5.2 million poultry. The importance of beef in the diet of&#13;
the population has been steadily declining, whereas that of small ruminants (assisted by an IFAD&#13;
project administered by IDA) and poultry is increasing rapidly. In the region of Lome, about ten&#13;
modem, private poultry production facilities have been established. This development is taking&#13;
place without Government assistance, and at times under severe constraints such as the difficulty&#13;
of obtaining bank loans for these modem facilities (the largest has 10,000 laying hens).&#13;
2.8   Ocean and Inland Fishing. The country's fish production potential is rather limited.&#13;
The potential of the coastal zone under traditional use is estimated at about 8,000 tons per year.&#13;
The lagoon area covers some 6,500 hectares-lakes Vogan, Aneho and Togo-and is heavily&#13;
exploited, supplying around 2,500 tons of fish yearly. The inland resources include the Mono,&#13;
Oti and Kara rivers and a few aquaculture facilities. Little is known about them, despite the fact&#13;
that more than 50 percent of the population's protein needs is met by fish production.&#13;
Consumption of fish varies between 8 and 13 kg per capita (more than 50 kg in fishing villages).&#13;
National production of fish has remained unchanged for years, in the range of 15,000 tons yearly,&#13;
while consumption is 37,000 tons per year (22,000 tons imported).&#13;
2.9  Inputs and Technology. The use of improved agricultural technologies and inputs&#13;
(animal traction, selected seeds, fertilizers, pesticides, etc.) is still limited. Cotton production is&#13;
an exception. In other crops, only 12 percent of the areas are planted with improved varieties.&#13;
The total consumption of fertilizer rose from 5,000 tons in 1978 to 29,000 tons in 1993. Yet,&#13;
overall, still only 15 percent of cultivated land is fertilized, mainly for cotton. Improved&#13;
agricultural technologies are available, but they are poorly disseminated because of the&#13;
dysfunctional relationship between agricultural research and extension services.   The&#13;
technologies available from research include improved husbandry methods, improvement in soil&#13;
fertility and in natural pastures, agro-forestry, reforestation, watershed management and anti-&#13;
erosion techniques. Nevertheless, these technologies often need to be adapted to the resources&#13;
and requirements of the small farms, and systematically disseminated.&#13;
Rural Natural Resources&#13;
2.10  On the whole, the natural resources of Togo (water, soil, vegetation) are still sufficient to&#13;
meet the current needs of the country. By a conservative estimate, arable land of good or average&#13;
quality exceeds 3.1 million hectares, compared to about 1 million hectares cultivated annually.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
However, this potential is not evenly distributed over the country and in large areas there is an&#13;
alarming increase in the degradation of natural resources, chiefly due to population pressures and&#13;
the mining of soil fertility. The main detrimental resource-use practices include deforestation (up&#13;
to 15,000 hectares per year), cultivation of marginal soils in the hilly areas and the race to&#13;
cultivate forest galleries and wooded savannahs. Forests and woodlots are being replaced by&#13;
bush savannah with slight, and in some areas non-existent, agricultural potential. Given the&#13;
importance of forests for conserving soil and water, this degradation induces accelerated soil&#13;
erosion, blanketing of alluvial areas by coarse materials, siltation of rivers, lakes and dams, and a&#13;
noticeable decline in ground water levels. The most critical situations can be seen in the densely&#13;
populated coastal and central areas. The poorest segment of the population, which lacks the&#13;
financial resources to use improved techniques or acquire alternative heating material to&#13;
firewood, is at the same time the chief victim of this environmental degradation and one of its&#13;
promoters. Togo has no significant remaining forest resources. In the plateau and central&#13;
regions, where rainfall exceeds 1,200 mm/year, there is a significant reforestation potential on&#13;
marginal land, estimated at 40 percent of the country's area. Despite efforts in this area during&#13;
the period 1986-1990 (15,000 hectares of reforesting and 1,000 hectares of teak plantations),&#13;
there is a continual and alarming deterioration of natural resources (6,000 to 15,000 hectares of&#13;
land cleared yearly) as the last stands of forest are replaced by bush savannah.&#13;
B.   AGRICULTURAL INSTITUTIONS&#13;
Ministry of Rural Development and Village Water Resources (MAEP)&#13;
2.11  The decree Law 90/91 of April 3, 1991, reorganized the Ministry of Agriculture,&#13;
Livestock and Fisheries (MAEP) and the decrees 01-02-03 of July 14, 1994, specified the tasks,&#13;
structure and operations of its three Directorates namely: (a) the National Directorate of&#13;
Agricultural Research, including two technical departments and six institutes; (b) the General&#13;
Directorate for Rural Development, including nine technical departments at the national level&#13;
and five Regional Directorates for Rural Development (DRDRs); and (c) the Directorate of&#13;
Administration and Finance (DAF).&#13;
2.12 In practice, however, the Ministry is composed at the central level of 21 departments and&#13;
43 divisions, services and sections; this is the result of the accumulation of structures that have&#13;
followed successive ministerial reorganizations. The same proliferation of structures can be&#13;
found at the regional level. This has led to fragmentationand dispersion of responsibilities,as well&#13;
as to serious communication and coordination problems. Excessive centralization has also resulted&#13;
in removing responsibilities from local directorates and field services, lengthening the decision-&#13;
making process, and rendering decisions inappropriate because the decision makers are far removed&#13;
from local realities. Human resource management at the MAEP (more than 4,400 agents, of&#13;
which 2,000 at headquarters) is far from rigorous: an exhaustive inquiry carried out by the&#13;
TCP/FAO project indicated that it is difficult to reconcile the situation -on the ground with&#13;
MAEP's staffing records. Some categories of staff are without legal standing (temporary&#13;
personnel, training and employment staff, and contractors for projects, some of whom maintain&#13;
their positions after termination of the projects).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
2.13 Some departments of the MAEP are engaged in commercial activities. DAF is involved&#13;
in the marketing of inputs, and the Rural Transport Development Service with warehousing and&#13;
distribution of foodstuffs. Other units carry out activities in construction and make purchases&#13;
and sales of veterinary and phytosanitary products. DRDRs are also involved in carrying out&#13;
commercial activities often without adequate management and financial controls. Such practices&#13;
divert the MAEP from its mission to promote rural development through the efficient provision&#13;
of essential public agricultural services to resource-poor rural populations.&#13;
Agricultural Services&#13;
2.14 Extension Services. In 1986 the Government adopted a new strategy for agricultural&#13;
extension services, set forth in the document "Togolese Rural Extension System" (STER), aimed&#13;
at identifying the needs of the farmers and forging a strong link between agricultural research and&#13;
extension services. The operations of the public extension service are based on the main&#13;
principles of the T&amp;V system. At the national level, however, the extension service has&#13;
encountered difficulties due to the multiplicity of approaches and goals pursued by the various&#13;
rural operators: DRDRs aiming to provide integrated advice to smallholders, the Togolese Cotton&#13;
Company (Socidtt Togolaise du Coton -SOTOCO) focusing on cotton production, and the&#13;
Coffee-Cocoa Support Agency (Societe Nationale d'Appui ai la Filiere Cafe-Cacao - SAFICC)&#13;
aiming at supporting coffee and cocoa producers (but at present essentially non-functional). The&#13;
Agricultural Extension Project (funded by the World Bank), prematurely closed in June 1994,&#13;
attempted to support the efficient operation of STER. However, it was impeded in its efforts by&#13;
the social unrest in 1991-1992, the extremely difficult budgetary situation of the country, which&#13;
nearly eliminated any financial participation by the Government, an inadequate management&#13;
structure and poor linkages with research.&#13;
2.15  Agricultural Research. Agricultural research in Togo is characterized by: (a) a strong&#13;
concentration of research centers and human resources in the southern part of the country (59&#13;
researchers out of a total of 84, chiefly in Lome); (b) inadequate researchers' skills (the majority&#13;
of researchers possessing the education level of "agricultural engineer"; (c) lack of prioritization&#13;
and non-participatory planning; (d) poor access to scientific literature and links with regional&#13;
research; (e) insufficient operating resources; and (f) very weak links with extension agents and&#13;
producers. Only two specialized institutes are connected to regional and international networks&#13;
affording exchanges of technology and plant material: the Textile Crops Research Institute&#13;
(IRCT) for cotton farming in Correkape, the plateau region, and the Coffee and Cocoa Research&#13;
Institute (IRCC) for coffee and cocoa in Tove, the western plateau region. However, these&#13;
institutes have had little or no involvement in other crops (food crops) or in production systems.&#13;
The research system also includes, the National Food Crops Institute (INCV) in Ativeme-Lom6,&#13;
the Animal Husbandry Institute (INZ) in Avetonou, in the plateau region, specializing in animal&#13;
husbandry, the National Soil Institute (INS) for soil research, the Food Processing Technology&#13;
Institute (INTA) for food processing technology and the Directorate for National Meteorology&#13;
(DMN) for meteorology. To a varying but significant degree, these institutes are weak and do&#13;
not address the pressing needs of Togo's agriculture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
2.16 Professional Agricultural Associations. The number of Professional Agricultural&#13;
Associations (OPEAs) is estimated at more than 2,500. Many are exclusively woman groups and&#13;
some are particularly active. These OPEAs are organized around primary economic activities or&#13;
social issues. Until about three years ago, producers in the coffee, cocoa and cotton sectors were&#13;
not organized. Now, they are actively involved in the collection of cotton seed and participate in&#13;
the management of the committee charged with coordinating activities in the liberalized coffee&#13;
and cocoa sub-sectors. Moreover, they are keen to play a much increased role in the supply of&#13;
agricultural inputs and the marketing of products. This will require, however, that assistance be&#13;
given to strengthen their institutional and operational capacities.&#13;
Training in Agriculture&#13;
2.17  There are three levels of training for agriculture: (a) basic training for extension agents at&#13;
the Agricultural Apprenticeship Center (CAA) of the National Agricultural Training Institute in&#13;
Tove; (b) mid-level field managers' training provided by the School for Agricultural Technicians&#13;
also in Tove; and (c) (since 1981-82) advanced training for agricultural engineers offered by the&#13;
Institute for Higher Studies in Agronomy (ESA) in Lome. During the period from 1986 to 1991,&#13;
the CAA retrained 750 extension officers. The Tove Training Center is currently closed because&#13;
of a lack of financial resources, and only the ESA is in operation. Training of extension officers&#13;
and of sector and subsector chiefs is provided by technicians specializing in extension activities.&#13;
There is an urgent need to restructure agricultural training at all levels, to make it relevant to the&#13;
changing needs of farmers, but also of all the other public rural development institutions, whose&#13;
missions have changed dramatically and now focus on efficiently meeting the needs of farmers&#13;
for a widening range of agricultural services and advice.&#13;
Non-Governmental Organizations (NGOs)&#13;
2.18  The in-depth study of NGOs carried out during the preparation of the project revealed&#13;
that about sixty NGOs, organized in a national federation (Togolese Federation of NGOs -&#13;
FONGTO), are presently active in rural areas. The number of NGOs has increased significantly&#13;
in recent years with the economic and political crisis. Within this group there is a majority of&#13;
organizations whose main objective is to provide services on a commercial basis rather than&#13;
assisting rural populations. Most NGOs work closely with donors, at times subcontracting and&#13;
carrying out components of investment projects on the same footing as private companies. As&#13;
NGO activities have thus far been poorly regulated, they are doing so in unfair competition with&#13;
the private sector. The study revealed that many NGOs-without supervision or evaluation-&#13;
tend to impose their own priorities on farmers with little element of participation involved. The&#13;
quality and professional ability of these organizations also vary greatly. The pre-appraisal&#13;
mission identified five NGOs, which have taken an active part in the preparation of the project,&#13;
and with whom the project intends to maintain contractual agreements.&#13;
Credit to Agriculture&#13;
2.19 Following the liquidation of the National Bank for Agricultural Credit (CNCA) at the end&#13;
of 1988, Togo has had no public rural credit institution. Private banks have not taken up the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8 -&#13;
slack, refusing to lend to this sector without guarantees. Members of farmers' associations in the&#13;
cotton zone have access to crop credits administered by SOTOCO. The traditional mechanisms&#13;
of the "tontine" and loans granted by traders remain the most common forms of credit. A recent&#13;
survey of rural credit by the World Council of Credit Unions and USAID in the Kara River&#13;
region revealed that about 40 percent of families had recourse to this form of borrowing, but that&#13;
usually these credits are not for production purposes. The National Union of Savings and Loan&#13;
Cooperatives of Togo (FUCEC) covers the entire country, but its activities in rural regions are&#13;
limited. The Savings and Loans Cooperative (COOPECs), which operate under the aegis of&#13;
FUCEC, follow a cooperative model based on accrued savings prior to the awarding of credit.&#13;
Other associations attempt to reproduce the Grameen Bank model or base their approach on&#13;
mutualist practices (SYNORSEC, SOCODEVI, etc.). In 1995, the National Assembly adopted a&#13;
law, enacted by the Central Bank, regulating Rural and Microfinance Institutions (RMFIs) under&#13;
the aegis of the Ministry of Economy and Finance (MEF). The proliferation of very small, local-&#13;
-and often unreliable--financial organizations masks the extreme difficulty for most small&#13;
farmers of obtaining access to credit for agricultural and livestock operations.&#13;
Other Institutions Operating in Rural Areas&#13;
2.20  SOTOCO, SAFICC and, to a lesser degree, the National Palm Oil Company (Societe&#13;
Nationale du Palmier a Huile, SONAPH) provide support services to agricultural producers.&#13;
SOTOCO was created in 1974 as a public enterprise. It serves 13 rural development sectors (one&#13;
third of the national total) and has an integrated approach, working upstream and downstream&#13;
from cotton production by providing in kind credit to farmers for inputs and undertaking all&#13;
purchases of seed cotton from producers, and providing for transportation, processing and&#13;
delivery of cotton fiber to the port. SOTOCO has also been entrusted with extension services&#13;
related to cotton and food crops, as well as with adaptive research, the production of seeds for&#13;
food crops, the promotion of farmers' associations and the creation of rural infrastructure. For its&#13;
extension activities alone, SOTOCO has 883 employees, of which 587 are field extensionists.&#13;
With the aid of the World Bank-supported Third Cotton Project (Cr. 1929-TO) and the Caisse&#13;
Francaise de Developpement (CFD), SOTOCO is presently undergoing restructuring to clearly&#13;
separate its processing and marketing activities, which would be privatized, from its agricultural&#13;
support activities. SAFICC was created in 1992 for providing extension services in the coffee&#13;
and cocoa region (three sectors) in cooperation with IRCC, which is responsible for coffee and&#13;
cocoa research. SAFICC currently employs 123 agents (including three sector chiefs and 20&#13;
local advisors) for extension services, and 62 organizational staff. It doesn't have an operating&#13;
budget and producers are considering it not efficient. It would be liquidated as a condition of&#13;
Board Presentation of the proposed project (para. 8.3 (a)). SONAPH's mandate is to develop&#13;
industrial and village oil palm plantations, manage the processing plants and market the oil.&#13;
However, support to palm plantations is inefficient and would be assumed by ICAT. Plantations&#13;
would be leased or sold to private farmers. Oil palm processing, now very inefficient, would be&#13;
privatized. The Togolese Cereal Bank (TOGOGRAIN), active in grain marketing, does a poor&#13;
job of managing buffer stocks and its elimination has been contemplated several times, but not&#13;
yet implemented. Its liquidation would be a condition of Board Presentation (para. 8.3 (a)).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9 -&#13;
Trading of Agricultural Inputs&#13;
2.21  The distribution of agricultural inputs is still dominated by an inefficient public sector.&#13;
Trading of fertilizers and pesticides outside the cotton sector is handled by the MAEP through its&#13;
DAF and the Directorate of Market and Production Support (DMMP), in a clearly inefficient&#13;
fashion. The private sector only takes care of the transportation from the port to the regional&#13;
MAEP warehouses. SOTOCO has warehouses and trucks to deal with fertilizers and pesticides&#13;
for cotton cultivation which is the main consumer of modem inputs. Production of basic seeds&#13;
by the INCV has been hampered by administrative and budgetary constraints. This context&#13;
weakens the farmers' chances to get good and timely agricultural inputs. The public service is&#13;
not only inefficient but it also unfairly competes against the private sector, making the latter's&#13;
growth impossible. Only three private import firms, with a small financial capacity, have been&#13;
able to survive by providing services to SOTOCO and DMMP. However, during the last five&#13;
years, farmers' organizations, collaborating with each other, have increased their ability to deal&#13;
with the local distribution of fertilizers, particularly in the cotton area and could provide viable&#13;
partners to an emerging private sector role in the distribution of inputs.&#13;
Rural Investments: Current Projects&#13;
2.22 The Public Investment Program (PIP) for 1995 totaled CFAF 34,102 million (US$70.3&#13;
million) of which only 10 percent in support of the agricultural sector. Although some of the&#13;
public investments in other sectors (e.g., those appearing under the headings "Infrastructure" and&#13;
"Socio-Cultural Investments") will benefit the rural sector, this share seems small in relation to&#13;
the importance of the rural sector in the GDP, the work force employed in the sector, and the&#13;
Government's declarations concerning the key role of agriculture in the country's development.&#13;
Ongoing investment projects in the agricultural sector are numerous despite the withdrawal of&#13;
most official assistance to Togo during recent years. The most important projects are: (a) the&#13;
Third Cotton Development Project, funded jointly by the World Bank (Cr. 1929-TO), the Caisse&#13;
Francaise de Developpement (CFD) and the Government of Togo; (b) "FED-Savane," an&#13;
integrated rural development project financed by the European Union (EU); (c) the "micro-&#13;
projects" program, focused chiefly on the development of bottomlands, financed by the EU; (d)&#13;
the "PAIDB" program (Grassroots Development Project) financed by the World Bank; (e) the&#13;
National Small Livestock Project (PNPE) financed by IFAD and administered by the World&#13;
Bank; (f) the Support to Village Groups in the Eastern Savannah Region Project, cofunded by&#13;
IFAD, UNDP and UNCDF; (g) the project "Support for Women's Associations in the Savannah&#13;
Regions," undertaken by the NGO "Islands of Peace"; (h) the "Forest Development and&#13;
Protection of the Environment Project," project financed by the WFP; and (i) the "Northern Togo&#13;
Agro-forestry Development and Model Plantations Project," financed by Care International.&#13;
Many of these projects operate outside public institutions and their capacity-building impact is&#13;
limited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10-&#13;
C.   THE GOVERNMENT'S SECTORAL STRATEGY&#13;
Role of Agriculture in the Economy&#13;
2.23  Agriculture occupies a critical position in the Togolese economy. It employs about 77&#13;
percent of the active population and accounts for about 35 percent of GDP (its share even&#13;
reached 45 percent in 1993 as the result of the downturn in the other sectors). It is strongly&#13;
oriented toward the production of food crops, which contribute about two thirds of sectoral GDP.&#13;
Livestock ranks second (15 percent) followed by cash crops (about 10 percent of GDP). Cash&#13;
crops and phosphates account for 27 percent and 34 percent of export revenues respectively. In&#13;
1995, however, receipts from cotton exceeded those from phosphates for the first time. The&#13;
majority of poor people live in rural areas. The lack of development in rural areas draws young&#13;
Togolese towards the cities, where they join a fast expanding poor, urban population. The&#13;
importance of economic growth in the agricultural sector is not only in its role in reducing rural&#13;
poverty, but also as an essential component of social stability.&#13;
2.24 The main constraints to accelerated agricultural growth are summed up in the conclusions&#13;
of the general review of the rural sector carried out in 1992 by the Government of (National&#13;
Meeting on Agriculture and Land Issues): (a) the services provided to farmers and livestock&#13;
producers are inadequate; (b) agronomic research is ill-adapted to the actual problems of the&#13;
sector; (c) farm credit is insufficient; (d) agricultural land titles are insecure; (e) transportation&#13;
and storage infrastructure is lacking; and (f) water management needs to be greatly improved.&#13;
2.25 As a first step in re-designing its agricultural growth strategy, the Government has&#13;
outlined four principal goals: (a) intensify and diversify production to enhance food security,&#13;
improve the population's nutritional balance, provide substitutes for imports and increase&#13;
exports; (b) reduce rural poverty by increasing rural productivity, employment and incomes; (c)&#13;
develop agriculture within an environmentally sustainable framework; and (d) develop human&#13;
resources in the agricultural sector. Government's broad strategy to achieve these objectives&#13;
embodied in a Letter of Agricultural Development Policy (LDPA) has been provided to the Bank&#13;
in November 1996 (para. 8.1 (a)). The general policies advocated in the LPDA are to: (a)&#13;
complete the liberalization of trade and prices; (b) redefine the functions of the various rural&#13;
actors by restructuring public services, organizing rural society and giving farmers, in particular&#13;
women and young producers, adequate representation in the institutions falling under MAEP; (c)&#13;
guarantee access to land via land reform (the agricultural land reforms of 1974 and associated&#13;
implementation decrees are to be reviewed and amended); (d) improve agricultural productivity&#13;
while preserving natural resources; (e) establish a decentralized system of agricultural credit&#13;
based on cooperative savings and loan principles; and (f) professionalize technicians and&#13;
producers through training.&#13;
D.  SECTORAL STRATEGY AND WORLD BANK PROGRAMS IN TOGO&#13;
2.26  Agricultural-led rural development is at the core of the Bank's Country Assistance&#13;
Strategy (CAS) for Togo. The CAS aims to promote a policy and institutional framework that&#13;
favors private initiative and eliminates obstacles to agricultural investments, production and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
exports. The on-going Economic Recovery and Adjustment Credit (ERAC) supports important&#13;
agricultural sector reforms, notably the elimination of public monopolies in processing,&#13;
marketing and exporting of cash crops. As a first step, the transfer of the marketing and&#13;
exporting of cotton from OPAT to SOTOCO has just been completed. Progressive privatization&#13;
of cotton transportation implemented under the Third Cotton Project has also already permitted a&#13;
substantial decrease in transportation costs. A study is currently being carried out to define an&#13;
overall strategy for the liberalization and privatization of the cotton sector. Coffee and cocoa&#13;
marketing have been liberalized in 1996. Finally, other studies have been undertaken to design a&#13;
strategy for the privatization of the agricultural parastatal SONAPH.&#13;
2.27  Following the closing of the credit for the Agricultural Extension Project in 1994, there is&#13;
only one remaining IDA-funded operation in support of Togo's agricultural sector: the Cotton&#13;
III Project (Cr. 1929-TO), which is supporting the development and rationalizing of cotton&#13;
production. IDA is also the executing agency for the IFAD-funded PNPE which supports the&#13;
growth and reorganization of small ruminant production. IFAD's assistance to Togo started in&#13;
1983 with the financing of the Notse Rural Development Project and has been primarily aimed at&#13;
promoting crop intensification and diversification among smallholders, with particular emphasis&#13;
on food crops and small livestock development. IFAD has been supporting a policy of reduced&#13;
State intervention and increased reliance on grass roots institutions. There are presently three&#13;
IFAD-financed projects under implementation: (a) PNPE (approved in 1987), (b) the Support to&#13;
Village Groups in the Eastern Savannah Region Project (approved in 1990); and (c) the Village&#13;
Organization and Development Project (approved in 1995).&#13;
E.   LESSONS LEARNED FROM THE EXPERIENCE OF THE WORLD BANK AND&#13;
OTHER DONORS&#13;
2.28 The experience of the World Bank (see also para. 2.14), IFAD and other donors in project&#13;
implementation in Togo highlights the following lessons: (i) agricultural sector growth requires&#13;
that Government define and implement a clear and supportive agricultural policy and&#13;
institutional framework; (ii) while growth must be private sector-led the State has a central role&#13;
to play in ensuring adequate access of all farmers, and in particular the poorest among them, to&#13;
the basic agricultural services and rural infrastructure that are beyond the power of local&#13;
communities and/or the market to deliver; (iii) sustained growth in agricultural production and&#13;
incomes requires improvements in productivity and technical innovations that must be adapted to&#13;
local circumstances and disseminated by a well functioning and closely collaborating research&#13;
and extension system; (iv) the continuing relevance of extension services critically hinges on a&#13;
continuous flow of technologies from research well suited to farmers' technical, financial and&#13;
managerial abilities, and to their market opportunities; (v) given Government's budgetary&#13;
constraints, it is desirable to move, when possible, towards the recovery of part of the cost of&#13;
delivering basic services and maintaining infrastructure, to ensure their long-term viability; and&#13;
(vi) even if these basic services must be financed by the Government, it has been unable to&#13;
provide these services efficiently in the past; they may be more efficiently delivered by non-&#13;
government institutions and beneficiaries must play a leading role in their definition and quality&#13;
control if they are to be relevant and efficiently delivered. These lessons, and lessons from&#13;
operations in other countries and OED's findings and recommendations with respect to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
agricultural services, extension in particular, have been fully incorporated in the design of the&#13;
proposed operation.&#13;
III. THE PROJECT&#13;
A.   PROJECT OBJECTIVES AND STRATEGY&#13;
3.1   Objectives. The project's central objective is to improve living standards of farm&#13;
households by increasing agricultural productivity and income, while placing greater emphasis&#13;
on protection of the environment. It would install and strengthen a national institutional&#13;
framework designed to upgrade the performance of agriculture and stimulate development of&#13;
OPEAs and the private sector. More specifically, the project would: (a) boost participation of&#13;
farmers in the programming, management and financing of agricultural services (adaptive&#13;
research, extension and support for OPEAs); (b) strengthen the MAEP's sectoral policy&#13;
formulation, implementation and monitoring capabilities (including agricultural statistics); (c)&#13;
increase agricultural productivity by strengthening the agricultural research system to better meet&#13;
farmers' needs, placing greater emphasis on protection of the environment and integrating it more&#13;
closely into the regional and international networks; (d) facilitate a progressive transfer of import&#13;
supply and marketing activities to OPEAs and the private sector; and (e) foster the development&#13;
of three Saving and Credit institutions in pilot areas.&#13;
3.2   Project strategy. Implementation of the PNASA would be preceded by a preliminary&#13;
phase of restructuring of the MAEP and of the public agencies involved in direct support to&#13;
farmers. The restructuring process would concern about 4,400 staff (including 600 staff working&#13;
in different agricultural projects). After restructuring, about 2,760 agents would have been&#13;
redeployed in the four new agencies: (a) MAEP with about 1,000 staff; (b) a Technical&#13;
Assistance and Support Institute (ICAT) in charge of national extension services with about&#13;
1,350 staff; (c) a Togolese Agricultural Research Institute (ITRA), whose permanent core staff&#13;
would not exceed 260; and (d) SOTOCO, which would as part of the restructuring focus on&#13;
cotton processing and marketing activities, would retain 150 extension staff dealing with&#13;
linkages with ICAT and ITRA. Redundant staff would thus amount to about 1,700 employees.&#13;
Taking into account 550 retirements, about 1,250 would have to be laid off. These numbers are&#13;
indicative. A detailed staff assessment is currently being carried out that would identify staff that&#13;
would be retained/laid off. Government would provide terminated employees with a severance&#13;
payment in accordance with the law in effect at the time of termination. The timing of the&#13;
selection of staff to be retained/terminated, as well as the payment of severance entitlements has&#13;
been agreed upon during negotiations, as part of the detailed action plan for the restructuring of&#13;
MAEP (see para. 5.2).&#13;
3.3   A Consultation and Monitoring Committee (CCS), chaired by the Minister of MAEP and&#13;
composed of representatives of the Ministries of Planning, Public Service, Finance and State-&#13;
Owned Companies, was established on January 31, 1995 by the Government to supervise the&#13;
restructuring phase before the start-up of the project. A National Technical Secretariat (STN)&#13;
was also set up within MAEP on January 27, 1995, to plan and coordinate the implementation of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
the restructuring activities to be completed prior to the start-up of the PNASA. The STN is&#13;
currently receiving assistance from an Ivorian consulting firm, specialized in human resource&#13;
development which provided assistance to similar restructuring operations in C6te d'Ivoire&#13;
(including staff terminations). Key activities that have been undertaken over the past 2 years are&#13;
described in paragraph 5.1.&#13;
3.4   During negotiations, agreement was reached that MAEP's current activities which are&#13;
unrelated to its core public service functions would be transferred to private operators and&#13;
OPEAs (production, processing and marketing activities: ranches, inputs, seed production&#13;
nurseries and plantations, maintenance, rural works, etc.; (para. 8.2(a), see also Annex 10,&#13;
including timetable). In addition, the liquidation of SAFICC and TOGOGRAIN was adopted by&#13;
the Government as a condition of Board Presentation (para 8.3(a)).&#13;
B.  SUMMARY DESCRIPTION&#13;
3.5   The project has five main components:&#13;
(a)   Agricultural Services. The project would support the creation of a decentralized,&#13;
autonomous, semi-private, Technical Assistance and Support Institute (ICAT)--&#13;
consolidating existing governmental or parastatal extension services, appointing&#13;
and retraining their best staff-- responsible for providing improved extension&#13;
services to farmers and support to farmer organizations;&#13;
(b)   Agricultural Research. The project would strengthen Togo's agricultural research&#13;
system by merging all existing research institutions into a newly created,&#13;
decentralized, autonomous, semi-private, Togolese Agricultural Research Institute&#13;
(ITRA);&#13;
(c)   Agricultural Credit. The project would provide assistance to implement two pilot&#13;
rural finance activities (i) grassroot savings and loans operations through selected&#13;
existing non-governmental agricultural organizations, to test a successful&#13;
approach for ensuring accessibility for small producers, including women, to these&#13;
essential services; and&#13;
(d)   Village Development Fund: To support demand-driven small rural infrastructure&#13;
at community level (funded by IFAD);&#13;
(e)   Ministrv of Agriculture. Livestock and Fisheries (MAEP). The project would&#13;
provide assistance for the reorganization of MAEP, to build up its capacity in&#13;
policy design, planning, programming, monitoring, control and program&#13;
evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
C.   DETAILED PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
3.6   The project would be implemented over a five-year period. Its detailed description and&#13;
implementation arrangements are presented in Annex 1. At the end of the second year of&#13;
implementation, an in-depth mid-term review would be carried out to assess progress and issues&#13;
in implementation, as well as its impact on beneficiaries and institutional capacity-building (see&#13;
also para. 5.9).&#13;
Restructuring of and Support to Extension Services (US$17.6 million)&#13;
3.7   The project would support the merging of the existing MAEP and SOTOCO extension&#13;
services into a new institute: ICAT. This institute would have as its mandate the provision of&#13;
agricultural extension to all farmers as well as assistance for the establishment and strengthening&#13;
of OPEAs. It would be a semi-private company (societe d'economie mixte), with full financial&#13;
and management autonomy, in which Government would have a minority share (40 percent), 10&#13;
percent from SOTOCO, 5 percent from ITRA, 5 percent from private sector and farmers through&#13;
their OPEAs will have (40 percent). ICAT's capital would be set at CFAF 200 million, allowing&#13;
easy access to OPEAs. ICAT's operating costs would be financed in the same proportion by&#13;
Government, through annual budget transfers, and OPEAs, through voluntary contributions from&#13;
the primary marketing of cash crops (it is estimated that about 80 percent of all farmers are&#13;
members of OPEAs handling cotton, coffee and/or cocoa marketing and would therefore&#13;
contribute to ICAT financing). Farmers' representatives would therefore have a dominant voice&#13;
in defining ICAT's policies, programs and budgets.&#13;
3.8  ICAT's management would be decentralized. In each of its five regional directorates, it&#13;
would establish a Regional Orientation Council (ROC) to reflect farmer's concerns in work&#13;
programs and management. ROCs would have an adequate representation of all small farmers,&#13;
including food crop producers and women. Agricultural extension services would be organized&#13;
according to STER, which is based on the Training and Visit (T&amp;V) system adapted to Togo's&#13;
particular circumstances. ICAT would establish contractual links with research, focusing on&#13;
adaptive research programs, based on participatory farming system assessments and executed&#13;
with the effective participation of farmers in the planning, implementation and monitoring of&#13;
research activities. Particular attention would be given to improving the productivity of crops&#13;
produced by the poor, in particular food crops. ICAT support to OPEAs would aim at&#13;
strengthening their financial and institutional viability, and implementing appropriate financial&#13;
management (including accounting) principles.  The financing of Management Advisers&#13;
(Conseillers de gestion), initially appointed and financed by ICAT, would be progressively taken&#13;
over by individual OPEAs. Finally, ICAT would design and operate a Farmers Information&#13;
System to disseminate through mass media (bulletins, regular radio and TV programs) relevant&#13;
information on technologies, production issues, plant and animal protection problems, marketing&#13;
and price conditions and other relevant inforrnation on farmners' technical and economic&#13;
envirornment. ICAT's staff would be selected from existing MAEP, and SOTOCO personnel,&#13;
and employed on a contractual basis. From the start of the project, they would receive intensive&#13;
training in relevant technical and managerial skills.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
3.9   The project would finance ICAT's non-salary operating costs (on a declining basis).&#13;
Government and OPEAs would finance the balance of these costs as well as 100 percent of&#13;
salary costs from the start (see also para. 4.5). The project would also finance, equipment,&#13;
limited civil works to rehabilitate ICAT's essential premises, training programs, and technical&#13;
assistance. IFAD, one of the project's co-financiers, would also contribute part (50 percent) of&#13;
OPEAs' initial contribution to ICAT's share capital.&#13;
Support to Agricultural Research (US$13.0 million)&#13;
3.10  The project would support the merging of the current agricultural research institutions&#13;
(DNRA and other institutes) into a new institute: ITRA. Like ICAT, ITRA would be a semi-&#13;
private company (Societe d'economie mixte), with financial and management autonomy, and&#13;
with share capital contributed 40 percent directly by Government, 10 percent by SOTOCO, 5&#13;
percent by ICAT, 5 percent by the private sector and 40 percent by producers through OPEAs.&#13;
ITRA's main objectives would be to implement priority research programs (crop and animal&#13;
husbandry, improved planting material, soil and water conservation, post-harvest storage and&#13;
processing) designed in collaboration with ICAT, OPEAs (representing smallholders) and private&#13;
partners on the basis of priority needs of farming systems in each one of Togo's main agro-&#13;
ecological zones. During the first year of project implementation, ITRA, together with ICAT&#13;
and MAEP would undertake a detailed review of farming systems with a focus on smallholders'&#13;
production possibilities and constraints, the technologies available to meet their specific needs&#13;
and the priority areas to be addressed by research programs. ITRA would also play an important&#13;
role in the training of ICAT's extension staff. Its programs would be implemented largely on&#13;
contract (with ICAT and other partners) through four Regional Agricultural Research Centers&#13;
(CRAPs). Its permanent staff wouldn't exceed 260, including 50 researchers, with the possibility&#13;
of using additional staff on limited-duration contracts for implementing specific research&#13;
programs contracted by third parties (private companies, OPEAs, NGOs).&#13;
3.11  The project would finance ITRA's non-salary operating costs (on a declining basis).&#13;
Government and OPEAs would finance the balance of these costs as well as 100 percent of&#13;
salary costs from the start (see also para. 4.5). Income would also be derived from contracts with&#13;
third parties. The project would furthermore finance the rehabilitation and equipment of ITRA's&#13;
offices and research centers, the training of staff and limited technical assistance. IFAD would&#13;
contribute part (50 percent) of OPEAs' initial contribution to ITRA's initial share capital.&#13;
Support to Pilot Agricultural Credit Operations (US$ 3.2 million)&#13;
3.12  The project would include a pilot program to increase savings and develop credit to&#13;
agriculture; this program would support the expansion of promising operations for three existing&#13;
Savings and Credit (S&amp;C) institutions (supported by reputable NGOs) --Mutuelle Adzedzi,&#13;
Caisse Rurale de Nyelle and the COOPECs -- in pilot areas. The operations and performance of&#13;
these three S&amp;C grassroots institutions would be backstopped and closely monitored by the&#13;
Rural Credit Monitoring and Evaluation Unit in MAEP. This unit would review their operating&#13;
policies and human resource development plans. In accordance with the new law regulating&#13;
RMFIs, their financial and prudential management as well as their annual audits will be closely&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16-&#13;
monitored by the unit in charge of Rural and Microfinance supervision in the MEF. The&#13;
component would help promote the establishment of branches for three viable grass-roots&#13;
institutions addressing the needs in agricultural credit, with an emphasis on small farmers, and in&#13;
particular female producers. It would contribute to expand the outreach of Togo's financial&#13;
system and thus be complimentary to the activities of the Financial Sector Adjustment Credit&#13;
(FINSAC) currently in preparation with IDA support. The project would finance the initial&#13;
investments required for the establishment of new branches (during the first three years of project&#13;
implementation), the training of their staff and their operating costs (on a declining basis over a&#13;
period of three years), including annual audits, on the basis of approved annual operating&#13;
budgets, the assistance provided by NGOs (on the basis of negotiated contracts) and the salary&#13;
and operating expenses of the component's coordinator to be recruited on a contractual basis by&#13;
NGOs Rural Credit Committee. Staff of the World Bank's Africa Region financial sector cluster&#13;
will be closely involved with the supervision of this component and will be part of the&#13;
supervision team.&#13;
Pilot VDF (US$0.6 million)&#13;
3.13  The project will also support the establishment of a pilot VDF. Through matching grant&#13;
arrangements this pilot will allow the establishment, in selected villages, of a fund to finance&#13;
community-based infrastructure (schools, health posts, village marketing facilities, water supply,&#13;
bottomland development) on a demand basis. The fund would have a Board of Directors&#13;
comprised of local representative of the administration officials and representatives of the local&#13;
community, and be managed --on the basis of operating policies and procedures including&#13;
eligibility criteria adopted by the Board-- by a manager recruited on contract by the Board.&#13;
Beneficiaries would contribute to the investment costs through cash or labor, and be responsible&#13;
for their execution within the framework of contractual arrangements with NGOs or private&#13;
entrepreneurs. The project (IFAD) would finance the matching grant element of the investment&#13;
costs, the operating cost of the VDF managers (on a declining basis, the balance being financed&#13;
by a fee on the fund turn-over) and the initial training of VDF's board members.&#13;
Support to the MAEP (US$18.2 million)&#13;
3.14  The project would support, as part of the overall public sector reform process, the&#13;
refocusing of MAEP's responsibilities and operations on the definition and monitoring of&#13;
Government's rural development policies and strategies. The main thrust of the reorganization is&#13;
to build the capacity of MAEP to deliver Government's core functions (policy-making and&#13;
provision of essential services), decentralize its activities and establish more efficient planning,&#13;
budgeting and monitoring procedures. The project would in particular support: (i) the&#13;
strengthening of MAEP's policy and monitoring capacities, including essential statistics&#13;
collection and analysis; (ii) the review of its planning and budgeting process, and the&#13;
implementation of annual public expenditure reviews; and (iii) the redeployment of existing&#13;
MAEP staff within the Ministry's new structure or ICAT/ITRA, and comprehensive staff&#13;
training programs. MAEP has already prepared a proposal outlining its main responsibilities and&#13;
proposed organization, including a detailed job description and skills profile for each key&#13;
position. MAEP's proposed institutional structure is presented in Annex 5. It is currently&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17-&#13;
carrying out a full skills gap analysis to define the required human resource development&#13;
program. During negotiations, agreement was reached on a detailed and time bound action plan&#13;
for each of the activities related to the restructuring of MAEP, including the completion of&#13;
severance payments to redundant staff in accordance with Togolese law (para. 8.2 (b)). The&#13;
action plan was adopted by the Government as a condition of Board Presentation (para. 8.3 (b)).&#13;
The restructuring of MAEP and the signature of Multi-year Program Agreements for ICAT and&#13;
ITRA would be a condition of credit effectiveness (para. 8.4 (a) and (b)).&#13;
3.15 PNASA would improve the framework of the agricultural sector. In addition, the Prime&#13;
Minister and the Minister of MAEP have stressed the need to quickly implement a rural&#13;
investment program. To undertake the preparation of this program, the MAEP, together with all&#13;
rural development partners, has launched a program of economic sector work to thoroughly&#13;
analyze the growth potential in the agricultural sector. This regionalized investment program&#13;
would aim: (i) to implement a "gestion de terroir" approach; (ii) to finance small rural&#13;
investments requested by producers; (iii) to implement a rural land tenure pilot approach, (iv) to&#13;
support rural community radio programs in rural areas. A detailed proposal for studies, including&#13;
terms of reference, would be prepared as part of the project's first year's annual work program&#13;
and budget (see also para. 5.7).&#13;
3.16  The project would finance the rehabilitation of MAEP's essential facilities at the&#13;
headquarters and regional levels, basic office equipment, a limited number of vehicles,&#13;
incremental non-salary operating costs (on a declining basis), training and technical assistance.&#13;
The refinancing of the project's PPF has been considered as part of this project component.&#13;
IV. PROJECT COSTS AND FINANCING&#13;
A.   PROJECT COSTS&#13;
4.1   The total cost of the project is presented in Table 4.1. Over the five-year investment&#13;
period, it is estimated at US$52.6 million. Of this amount, about US$21.7 million, or 41 percent,&#13;
is in foreign exchange, and US$4.6 million in taxes and duties. Physical contingencies are&#13;
estimated at US$3.7 million and price contingencies at US$4.0 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18-&#13;
Table 4.1: FinancingPlan by Project Expenditure Category&#13;
(US$ million)&#13;
Expenditures Categories Costs   Local   Foreign    Total    % Total   % Foreign&#13;
Costs    Costs                Cost      Exchange&#13;
- Civil Works                   4.3       3.1       7.4        14          42&#13;
- Goods and Equipment           1.4       5.8       7.2        14          81&#13;
- Vehicles                      4.8       5.7       10.5       20          54&#13;
- Consulting Services, Studies,&#13;
and Training                    6.5       2.7       9.2        17          29&#13;
- Social Capital                0.1                 0.1        --&#13;
- Operating Costs               11.9      3.2       15.0       29          21&#13;
- Severance Pay                 1.7                 1.7        3&#13;
- PPF Refinancing               0.3       1.2       1.5        3           80&#13;
TOTAL                           30.9     21.7      52.6        100         41&#13;
B.  PROJECT FINANCING&#13;
4.2    The respective shares of the Government of Togo, OPEAs and external donors are&#13;
presented in Table 4.2 below.&#13;
Table 4.2: Summary Project Costs by Component and Financier&#13;
(IUS$ million)&#13;
ICAT     ITRA    Institutional.  Pilot Rural   VDF   PPF  TOTAL&#13;
Strengthening    Finance&#13;
IDA             9.2       7.0         7.6          0.9               1.5    26.2&#13;
IFAD            3.9       2.1        3.1           0.6       0.3            10.0&#13;
Other Donors    0.5       0.5         0.5                                    1.5&#13;
OPEAs           1.6       1.0                                                2.6&#13;
Government      2.4       2.4         7.0          0.4                      12.2&#13;
Total           17.6      13.0       18.2          1.9       0.3    1.5    52.6&#13;
4.3    Government and the beneficiaries, through their OPEAs, would respectively contribute&#13;
US$ 12.2 million equivalent (23 percent of total cost)' and US$2.4 million equivalent (5 percent)&#13;
towards the total cost of the project. IDA would contribute US$26.2 million (48 percent), IFAD&#13;
US$10.0 million (20 percent) and the Japanese Government, which would finance the purchase&#13;
of computers for MAEP, ICAT and ITRA (US$1.5 million, 5 percent).&#13;
Of this amount, US$1.6 million is incremental financing and US$10.5 million represents present financing for&#13;
staff salaries and other operating and investment costs. (see paras. 7.14 and 7.17).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
4.4  IFAD would contribute to the financing of all project components. In particular, it would&#13;
finance part of OPEAs' contribution to ICAT's and ITRA's initial share capital and the VDF.&#13;
IFAD's support to the project would be conditional upon the preparation by the Government of&#13;
an Action Plan covering the first two years of project implementation and detailing the measures&#13;
and activities specifically targeted at ensuring the adequate access of the poorest segments of the&#13;
rural population, in particular women, who are the main target group of IFAD's assistance, to the&#13;
services provided under the project. At the end of this two-year period, a detailed mid-term&#13;
review (para. 5.9) would (i) assess the performance of implementing agencies in carrying out the&#13;
Action Plan and reaching the target group; and (ii) propose, if need be, changes in approaches&#13;
and design necessary to better meet project's development objectives.&#13;
4.5   As agreed at negotiations, the Government would finance (i) from the start, 100 percent&#13;
of MAEP's staff salary cost and 40 percent of ICAT's and ITRA's salary costs; and (ii) an&#13;
increasing proportion (up to 40 percent after the third year of the project) of ICAT's and ITRA's&#13;
non-salary operating costs. OPEAs private sector and agro-industries would finance (i) their&#13;
share (the balance after IFAD contribution) of ICAT's and ITRA's initial share capital; (ii) 60&#13;
percent of ICAT's and ITRA's salary costs; and (iii) an increasing proportion (up to 60 percent&#13;
after the third year of project implementation) of these institutions' non-salary operating costs&#13;
(para. 8.2 (c)). The IDA credit would finance all investment costs and 100 percent of non-salary&#13;
operating costs during the first three years of the project and 50 percent thereafter.&#13;
4.6   A programming and budget meeting will be held annually at the end of August to plan&#13;
ICAT and ITRA resources. After analyzing results and budget execution for the previous year,&#13;
ICAT and ITRA will present their program for the following year, along with the resources&#13;
needed. After deducting the Government's share (to be included in the Finance Law) and&#13;
resources provided by certain external assistance programs, the subsectoral contributions and&#13;
their respective allocation will be determined.  This meeting will be organized by the&#13;
Supervisory Board/General Meeting of each company (ICAT/ITRA), represented by their Board&#13;
of Directors.&#13;
4.7  In each company, a Supervisory Board that would take on the role of a General Meeting&#13;
would oversee the Board of Directors, whose members it would appoint. The Supervisory Board&#13;
will consist of the ministers responsible for macroeconomic management and the agriculture&#13;
sector, or their representatives, the coffee, cocoa and cotton exporters involved in the operations&#13;
of ICAT and ITRA, and the presidents of the coffee, cocoa and cotton cooperatives and the other&#13;
organized subsectors. This Supervisory Board/General Meeting will hold a regular meeting at&#13;
least once a year.&#13;
4.8   Financing from the subsectors will be provided as follows: after the annual programming&#13;
and budget meeting has determined the resources required, the amount per kilo of product will be&#13;
established (it will not be fixed, but may vary in light of expected production volumes, the level&#13;
of complementary external assistance, etc.). Initially the cotton, coffee and cocoa exporters (later&#13;
the system may be extended to other organized subsectors) will withhold the agreed amounts.&#13;
They will then deposit them in the ICAT, ITRA and coffee/cocoa OPEA support project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
accounts. Copies of the deposit statements will be systematically sent to the appropriate&#13;
administrative departments. Oversight will be exercised via export volumes. Only after the&#13;
exporters have deposited their contributions to the ICAT and ITRA accounts will exportation be&#13;
authorized.&#13;
4.9   On the Boards of Directors of ICAT and ITRA interested parties will be represented as&#13;
follows:&#13;
Government                     4           Cotton industry                I&#13;
Coffee/cocoa exporters         I           Companies supplying inputs     I&#13;
ICAT/ITRA (cross-representation)  1        Agricultural producers         5&#13;
Producers will be represented as follows: 1 per region/subsector, i.e. 1 representative for cotton,&#13;
1 for coffee/cocoa, 1 for stockraising,. 1 for fisheries, and 1 for market gardening (who must be a&#13;
woman). The two delegations agreed that this proposal for the representation of producers is an&#13;
interim one designed to meet a temporary situation. It will be part of ICAT's mandate from its&#13;
first year to inform and to train the trade organizations in all lines of production regarding the&#13;
system of representation and its financial implications. After two years, at the mid-term review,&#13;
the provisional representation of producers will be replaced by a system of representation chosen&#13;
and organized by the producers themselves.&#13;
Table 4.3: Financing of ICAT and ITRA&#13;
(as percentage of operating costs)&#13;
Govemnment     OPEAs/Private Sector and          IDA&#13;
Agro-industries&#13;
Project Year   Salaries   Other   Salaries    Other      Salaries     Other&#13;
1          40        0        60           0           0          100&#13;
2          40        0        60           0           0          100&#13;
3          40        0        60           0           0          100&#13;
4          40       20        60           30          0           50&#13;
5          40       20        60          30           0           50&#13;
Post-project    40       40        60          60           0            0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
C. PROCUREMENT&#13;
4.10 All goods and civil works financed under the IDA Credit would be procured in&#13;
accordance with the Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits, dated&#13;
January 1995 (rev. In January and August 1996). All procurement of consulting services will be&#13;
guided by the Guidelines for the Selection and Employment of Consultants by World Bank&#13;
Borrowers dated January 1997. For initial contracts to supply goods and equipment, vehicles,&#13;
and civil engineering services, the MAEP's, DAF will provide its support to ICAT and ITRA.&#13;
Present procurement capacity is weak and MAEP staff responsible for procurement therefore&#13;
underwent procurement training in 1996. ICAT and ITRA staff would undergo procurement&#13;
training during the first year of project implementation (para. 4.10 and 5.3). Procurement plan&#13;
and bidding documents for the first project year have been submitted to IDA (para. 8.3 (c)). Use&#13;
of the Bank's standard bid documents would be mandatory. Agreement on the use of Bank&#13;
procurementprocedureswas reached during negotiations(para. 8.2 (d)). The project's procurement&#13;
arrangements are shown in Table 4.4 below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Table 4.4: Procurement Arrangements&#13;
(US$ million equivalent)&#13;
Procurement Method&#13;
Procurement            ICB        NCB       Other    NBF'/          Total&#13;
Arrangement&#13;
Civil Works                    1.3       2.9                  3.2           7.4&#13;
of which IDA                  (1.2)      (2.5)                             (3.7)&#13;
IFAD                                             |   (2.6)        (2.6)&#13;
Goods and equipment           1.6         0.8       0.8       4.0          7.2&#13;
of which IDA                  (1.5)      (0.7)     (0.7)                   (2.9)&#13;
IFAD                                                  (2.4)        (2.4)&#13;
Vehicles                      5.5         1.9                 3.1          10.5&#13;
of which IDA                  (5.0)      (1.7)                             (6.7)&#13;
IFAD                                                  (1.1)        (1.1)&#13;
Consultant Services, Studies                        4.6       4.6          9.2&#13;
and Training&#13;
of which IDA                                       (4.6)                   (4.6)&#13;
IFAD                                                  (1.6)        (1.6)&#13;
Operating Costs                                     8.3       6.7          15.0&#13;
of which IDA                                       (6.8)                   (6.8)&#13;
IFAD                                                  (2.2)        (2.2)&#13;
Social Capital                                                0.1          0.1&#13;
of which IDA&#13;
IFAD                                                  (0.1)        (0. 1)&#13;
Severance Pay                                                 1.7          1.7&#13;
of which IDA                                                               (0.0)&#13;
IFAD                                                               (0.0)&#13;
Refinancing of PPF                                  1.5                    1.5&#13;
of which IDA                                       (1.5)                   (1.5)&#13;
IFAD                                                               (0.0)&#13;
Total                         8.4         5.6      15.2       23.4         52.6&#13;
of which IDA                  (7.7)      (4.9)    (13.6)                  (26.2)&#13;
IFAD                                                 (10.0)       (10.0)&#13;
* Figures may not add up due to rounding off.&#13;
4.11  Contracts for vehicles, goods and equipment would be grouped by lots. All lots valued&#13;
at more than US$150,000 would be procured using International Competitive Bidding (ICB)&#13;
procedures and contracts from US$50,000 to US$150,000 using National Competitive Bidding&#13;
(NCB) procedures. Contracts estimated to cost less than US$50,000, but more than US$35,000&#13;
may be procured using international shopping and contracts of less than US$35,000 may be&#13;
2   Figures in parenthesis indicate IDA and IFAD share of financing. Numbers may not add up due to rounding.&#13;
2/  Not Bank-Financed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
procured using national shopping procedures. All laboratory equipment for ITRA costing less&#13;
than US$50,000 may be procured using international shopping procedures. For all national and&#13;
international shopping, at least three price quotations should be obtained for comparison. The&#13;
aggregate value is expected not to exceed US$0.7 million during the life of the project. All&#13;
contracts for goods and works equivalent to US$150,000 or more would be subject to the Banks&#13;
prior review. For all contracts not subject to prior review, all pertinent documentation would be&#13;
kept by the agency responsible for the procurement (MAEP, ICAT and ITRA) for review by the&#13;
auditors and Bank supervision missions.&#13;
4.12  Contracts for civil works.  The contract to rebuild MAEP, estimated to cost&#13;
approximately US$1.3 million, would be procured through ICB.  Other contracts for&#13;
rehabilitation and maintenance of regional and local offices, usually not exceeding US$20,000&#13;
for each contract aggregating not more than US$2.5 million during the life of the project, would&#13;
be procured under NCB, using national procedures acceptable to the Bank. These works are&#13;
scattered over the country and are not expected to attract foreign firms. However, they would be&#13;
allowed to bid, if they wish.&#13;
4.13  Contracts for technical assistance, studies and training. The project would not&#13;
finance long-term expatriate technical assistance. Consultant services on a short-term basis&#13;
would be procured from local or international firms. The majority of the contracts will be based&#13;
on Quality and Cost Based Selection (QCBS) procedures. The project will also employ non-&#13;
QCBS procedures as follows: (a) Fixed Budget for less than $50,000; (b)&#13;
Consultants'Qualifications, less than $20,000 for individuals and less than $50,000 for firms; (c)&#13;
Single Source for less than $20,000 for individuals, and less then $50,000 for firms (subject to&#13;
Bank approval); and (d) Selection of Individual Consultants according to section 5 of the&#13;
guidelines. All consultant contracts with firms, estimated to cost more than US$30,000&#13;
equivalent, including amendments and extensions, and with individual consultants, estimated to&#13;
cost more than US$10,000, would be subject to IDA's prior review. All terms of reference for&#13;
individual consultants and sole source contracts, regardless of the amount of the contract, would&#13;
be subject to IDA's prior review.&#13;
4.14 Monitoring of contracts. A team in the MAEP would provide support to ICAT and&#13;
ITRA in preparing the first set of draft contracts. During the first year of the project all contracts&#13;
would be followed-up by this team. Training for ICAT and ITRA staff would be organized&#13;
during the first year of the project. DAF of MAEP, ICAT, and ITRA, together with the financial&#13;
administrator of the credit component, would set up, and keep up to date at all times, a&#13;
computerized data base for monitoring project procurement contracts.  A contract status&#13;
statement for each project component would be a mandatory part of the progress report submitted&#13;
to IDA two weeks prior to each half-yearly supervision mission. Component contract managers&#13;
would be invited to take part in the technical training sessions regularly organized by the World&#13;
Bank for the benefit of the subregion. The expenses involved would be eligible for inclusion as&#13;
project costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24 -&#13;
D.    DISBURSEMENTS&#13;
4.15  The proposed disbursement by category are shown in table 4.5 below. Disbursement&#13;
percentages are relatively low for several categories because IFAD is co-financing these&#13;
expenditures with IDA.&#13;
Table 4.5: Disbursements by Category&#13;
Amounts              Financed by IDA&#13;
(US$                     (%)&#13;
million)&#13;
1. Civilworks                   3.5                  50% Foreign4&#13;
45% Local&#13;
2. Goods and Equipment           2.5                  60% Foreign&#13;
(except computers)3                                 45% Local&#13;
3. Vehicles                     6.0                  75% Foreign&#13;
70% Local&#13;
4. Consultant Services,         4.2                60% Foreign exp.&#13;
Studies and Training&#13;
5. Operating Costs              6.0          70% up to July 1, 2000 and 35%&#13;
thereafter&#13;
6. Refinancing of PPF            1.5&#13;
7. Unallocated                  2.5&#13;
TOTAL                           26.2&#13;
4.16 To facilitate project implementation, the Government would open three Special Accounts,&#13;
benefiting respectively MAEP, ICAT and ITRA, in the arnount of CFAF 250 million&#13;
(US$500,000 equivalent) each, at a local commercial bank on terns and conditions acceptable to&#13;
IDA. Agreement on this was reached during negotiations (para. 8.2 (e)). Activities planned&#13;
under the Pilot Rural Finance Operations component would be supported through the MAEP&#13;
special account. Upon effectiveness of the Credit, an aggregate amount of CFAF 175 million&#13;
(equivalent to US$350,000) would be deposited in these Special Accounts. This amount would&#13;
3  Provided by the Japanese Government&#13;
4  The percentage is based on the without price taxes. Precision conceming the percentage of taxes on civil works would be provided by&#13;
Togolese representatives during negotiations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
be increased to the authorized amount of the Special Accounts when cumulative disbursements&#13;
reach the equivalent of SDR 1.5 million. The Special Accounts would be replenished on a&#13;
monthly basis or when the total of incurred expenditures reach one third of the total authorized&#13;
allocation of the respective Special Account. The Borrower would be permitted to submit&#13;
withdrawal applications on the basis of Statement of Expenditure (SOEs) for contracts for the&#13;
procurement of goods below the equivalent of US$50,000 and for services below the equivalent&#13;
of US$50,000 for firms and US$20,000 for individual consultants. The invoices and related&#13;
documentation for claims submitted on the basis of SOEs would be kept at the project&#13;
coordination office for review by IDA supervision missions and independent auditors. All&#13;
withdrawals for contracts and expenditure above these thresholds would be submitted to IDA&#13;
with full documentation.&#13;
4.17 In addition to the Special Accounts, project accounts would be set up for ICAT and&#13;
ITRA. The Government would deposit its share of funding in these accounts. As part of its first&#13;
year's funding of ICAT and ITRA's work program, Government, as a condition for&#13;
effectiveness, would make an initial deposit in the amount of CFAF 490 million for ICAT and&#13;
CFAF 350 million for ITRA, representing salaries for six months, in the project accounts (para.&#13;
8.4 (d)). Procedures for transfer of funds to ICAT and ITRA and for financial control were&#13;
agreed upon at negotiations (para. 8.2 (g)). Quarterly deposits would be due for ICAT and&#13;
ITRA. Failure to adhere to the quarterly deposit schedule would be treated as a cause for&#13;
suspension of disbursements by IDA. The timing and size of these deposits would be reviewed&#13;
'annually as part of the annual work program and budgets (para. 5.7). The timing of the initial&#13;
deposits was defined in the action plan for the restructuring of MAEP and the creation of ICAT&#13;
and ITRA (para. 5.2) and agreed upon during negotiations (para. 8.2 (f)).&#13;
E.   ACCOUNTING, FINANCIAL REPORTS, AND AUDITS&#13;
Financial Management and Accounting&#13;
4.18 The restructured MAEP, ICAT and ITRA would each keep their own accounts. MAEP&#13;
would only keep Project accounts accounting, including specific accounts covering its Special&#13;
Account and Statements of Expenses (SOEs). ICAT's and ITRA's accounting would cover their&#13;
respective Operating costs, Project accounts, Special account and SOEs. Financial management&#13;
at MAEP is presently weak, while ICAT and ITRA, as newly created institutions, have no track&#13;
record in financial management. The restructured MAEP, ICAT and ITRA, would, therefore, put&#13;
in place appropriate accounting procedures and computerized financial management systems,&#13;
acceptable to the Bank, with the support of an accounting firm. After installation of the&#13;
computerized system, the accounting firm would maintain the accounts for a period of six&#13;
months, while selected staff from DAF (MAEP), and the financial and administrative divisions&#13;
of ICAT and ITRA, would undergo intensive and hands-on training in the use of the system and&#13;
the accounting procedures. After the initial training, timely short-term assistance would be&#13;
provided to: (a) review adherence to the accounting procedures and quality of data entry; and (b)&#13;
give refresher training. The quality of the financial management systems and eventual corrective&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-26 -&#13;
actions would be assessed as part of the annual audits (see para. 4.15). Agreement on these&#13;
arrangements and their timing was obtained at negotiations (para. 8.2 (h)).&#13;
4.19 The accounts would be kept in accordance with internationally accepted accounting&#13;
principles and with practices acceptable to IDA. Agreement on this was reached during&#13;
negotiations (para. 8.2 (i)). They would be expected to produce interim and annual financial&#13;
statements.&#13;
Budgeting&#13;
4.20 At least four months prior to the start of each fiscal year MAEP, ICAT and ITRA would&#13;
submit annual budgetary projections for approval by the Project Management. The presentatibn&#13;
of annual Budgets would follow the accounting plan retained for each of the three Project&#13;
executing agencies. MAEP, ICAT and ITRA would submit these Budgets for IDA's review and&#13;
comment no later than three months prior to the start of each fiscal year. Agreement on this has&#13;
been reached at negotiations.&#13;
Auditing&#13;
4.21  All project and operating accounts, special accounts, Statements of Expenses (SOE) and&#13;
voucher documentation would be audited once a year by an independent audit firm acceptable to&#13;
IDA. Annual audit reports would include the auditors' findings on the management and&#13;
reliability of the Special accounts and on the reliability of withdrawal applications submitted on&#13;
the basis of SOEs. They should also indicate whether reported expenditures on goods supplied&#13;
and services rendered are eligible for financing under the IDA Credit and state whether such&#13;
goods and services appear to have been used for project purposes. Furthermore, the audit reports&#13;
should assess the validity of the procedures and internal control mechanisms in place, and&#13;
include proposals for their improvement (see also para. 4.14). Terms of reference and audit&#13;
reports would be mandatorily reviewed by IDA. Certified copies of the audit reports would be&#13;
submitted to the Finance Ministry, MAEP, and IDA within six months of each fiscal year's&#13;
closing dates. Assurances concening these audit procedures was provided during negotiations&#13;
(para. 8.2 (j)). Appointment of an audit firm acceptable to the Bank was agreed during&#13;
negotiations The supervision mission following the receipt of an audit report would arrange a&#13;
working meeting attended by representatives of MAEP, MEF and Civil Service Ministry, the&#13;
executing agency concerned, the audit firm, and the World Bank to discuss the report and agree&#13;
on a plan of action to rectify any problems identified.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27 -&#13;
V.   PROJECT ORGANIZATION AND IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
A.   PROJECT MANAGEMENT AND CRITICAL STEPS&#13;
Pre-implementation phase&#13;
5.1   The CCS established under the terms of an Interministerial Order dated January 31, 1995,&#13;
and the STN, established within MAEP in January 1995, are currently in charge of the design&#13;
and implementation of the proposed institutional restructuring program (para 3.3).  The&#13;
following critical actions, needed to establish the desired institutional structure before the proper&#13;
project is launched, are presently underway:&#13;
(a) preselection of appointees to managerial positions in the newly organized entities&#13;
(recruitment drives, both public and among former managers; job announcements via the&#13;
usual media). Listing of to-be-abolishedjob positions, and computation of severance rights;&#13;
(b) planning for civil service staff transfers to the new MAEP with support from the same&#13;
consulting firm; and&#13;
(c) selection of OPEAs to be ICAT and ITRA shareholders;&#13;
Project Implementation&#13;
5.2   The details of project implementation are presented in the Project's Implementation Plan,&#13;
which was prepared during appraisal and approved at negotiations (para. 8.2 (k)). At the national&#13;
level, leadership and guidance would be provided by the CCS already set-up by Government&#13;
(para 3.3). The secretary general of MAEP for the support to MAEP component; ICAT and&#13;
ITRA managing directors for these two components respectively, and the coordinator recruited&#13;
by the NGO committee would manage the financial aspects of the pilot rural finance component.&#13;
A proposal concerning the statutes of MAEP, ICAT, and ITRA including job descriptions for&#13;
key positions in MAEP, ICAT, and ITRA was submitted to the Bank before negotiations (8.1 (b)&#13;
and (c)).&#13;
5.3   Training. Implementation of the training plan would begin as soon as the project is&#13;
launched. The first staff to be trained would be the financial officers, and senior and mid-level&#13;
executives of ICAT, ITRA and MAEP. Country-wide coordination of training activities would&#13;
be the responsibility of MAEP's newly organized Directorate of Training, in close cooperation&#13;
with the human resources management staff of ICAT and ITRA. The Directorate's specific&#13;
responsibilities would be to: (a) compile comprehensive qualitative and quantitative data on&#13;
training supply and demand; (b) centralize (and have available to users) the findings of the&#13;
monitoring and evaluation divisions of the Human Resources Units of the two institutes (ICAT,&#13;
ITRA); (c) keep up-to-date records on individual employees' training history so that the most&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-28 -&#13;
effective use can be made of available know-how; and (d) provide orientation, advice, and&#13;
support in the realm of teaching for all training instructors.&#13;
5.4   Technical Assistance. It is estimated that 96 person-months of specialist assistance and&#13;
consulting would be needed to help implement the project, including 31 months of international&#13;
expertise. Most of this assistance would support training activities, in the fonn of instructional&#13;
modules to be delivered in Togo (10 months of services from international specialists and 63&#13;
months from local institutions to adjust the existing training module to present needs).&#13;
Monitoring, Evaluation and Reporting&#13;
5.5   Each component would have its specific monitoring and evaluation arrangements to track&#13;
achievement of the performance indicators listed in Annexes 8 and 9. For the purpose of impa't/&#13;
development evaluation, indicators have been developed for overall goals and production and&#13;
institutional objectives.  Monitoring indicators (input, process, output) include detailed,&#13;
quantitatively measurable targets and financial performance gauges of the project and the units&#13;
assisted by it. The project performance criteria in Annexes 8 and 9 were approved by the&#13;
Government and IDA during negotiations (para. 8.2(1)). Under the supervision of the director of&#13;
each institution concerned, the monitoring and evaluation process would include semi-annual&#13;
meetings to review work programs and adjust operating plans where this is necessary to ensure&#13;
that goals can be achieved. To facilitate evaluation of project impact, a base-line survey was&#13;
started during the latter part of 1996 and will be completed before mid-1997 and beneficiaries&#13;
survey would be carried out every year.&#13;
5.6   The private sector technical cluster of the Africa Region will be closely associated with&#13;
the implementation of the Agriculture Finance component of this project. Specifically staff of the&#13;
financial sector cluster in AFTP1 will be part of the supervision team. The objective is to ensure&#13;
that the national agricultural credit policy will be developed jointly with the MEF and will fit&#13;
with the national rural and microfinance policy under preparation under the FINSAC.&#13;
5.7   The program-budgets for the various project components would be combined into a&#13;
global annual work plan and budget for the entire project. These would be reviewed by IDA for&#13;
no-objection during the mandatorily scheduled supervision missions each year in October.&#13;
Considering the special objectives of the project regarding rural poor, particular attention would&#13;
be given to detailed activities targeted at the rural poor and to tracking project's performance in&#13;
this area. Agreement on timing and scope of the work prograns and budgets was reached during&#13;
negotiations (para. 8.2 (m)).&#13;
5.8   Half-yearly reports to the Government and IDA covering all project components would&#13;
be required, covering: (a) the current implementation status (institutions, budget, procurement);&#13;
and (b) project impact on quality of agricultural services, on agricultural production, and on&#13;
farmers' standard of living, particularly on women and youth. This documentation would&#13;
provide the basis for the work of supervision missions and the mid-term review team.&#13;
Agreement on the submission of these reports was agreed during negotiations (para. 8.2 (n)).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29 -&#13;
5.9   After two years, a mid-tern project review mission by representatives of IDA and the&#13;
other donors would join with the Togolese authorities to evaluate the achievements up to that&#13;
point. Close attention would be paid to the overall implementation and impact of the two-year&#13;
"Pro-poor" Action Plan and to the financing arrangements that support the agencies targeted by&#13;
the project, particularly the flow of contributions from their beneficiaries (see Annex 11). The&#13;
tenrs of reference for the mid-term review were approved during negotiations (para. 8.2(o)). At&#13;
the end of the project, an implementation completion report would be prepared, (before six&#13;
months, after the end of the project), basing the findings on the development and performance&#13;
indicators to be agreed with the Government.  Agreement on the preparation of the&#13;
implementation completion report and its contents was reached during negotiations (para. 8.2&#13;
(p)).&#13;
VI. PROJECT ECONOMIC ANALYSIS&#13;
A.   CURRENT AND POTENTIAL YIELDS&#13;
6.1   Togo shares many attributes of subsistence production characteristic of sub-Saharan&#13;
Africa: crop yields are below their agronomic potential, and the growth in food output is largely&#13;
from area expansion rather than through intensification. Low soil productivity, itinerant rainfall&#13;
and low levels of technologies are the fundamental constraints to increased productivity. The&#13;
traditional farming methods of alternating slash-bum accelerate loss of soil organic matter,&#13;
resulting in rapid oxidation of inherent soil nutrients. Use of chemical fertilizer, which is needed&#13;
to restore soil integrity, is suboptimal and confined largely to the export crop subsector. Only an&#13;
estimated 15 percent of Togo's total cultivated area benefit directly from fertilizer use of any&#13;
kind. The use of farm yard manure is not widespread and is largely concentrated in the Kara and&#13;
Savanes Regions.&#13;
Project Interventions&#13;
6.2   The project would support structural realignment and institutional strengthening of&#13;
MAEP, ICAT and ITRA to enable these institutions to accelerate the process of technology&#13;
development, testing and dissemination to increase productivity of smallholders, the latter being&#13;
fully involved in all stages of this process. The major crops that would be promoted are shown&#13;
in Table 6.1 below:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Table 6.1: Selected Food Crop Varieties and their Yield Potentials (kg/ha)&#13;
On-Station   Demonstration   On-Farm   Farmer  Yield Difference:&#13;
Variety                          Plots        Trials    Fields  Farmer Fields vs.&#13;
On-Farm Trials&#13;
(%)&#13;
Maize:&#13;
Pool 16 SR      4,300          3,691        2,912     1,210         58&#13;
Rice:&#13;
ITA 212         5,500          4,574        3,532     2,054         42&#13;
Cassava:&#13;
TMS 30574       22,000         20,860       21,360    9,934          54&#13;
Cowpeas&#13;
IT 82 E          1,537         1,106         733       360           51&#13;
Groundnut&#13;
73-33            3,273         1,432           -       762           47&#13;
Yam&#13;
Brutani         25,000           -          13,800    10,313        25&#13;
Source: Direction de la Vulgarisation Agricole, MAEP.&#13;
B.   ESTIMATING FARM-LEVEL BENEFITS AND COSTS&#13;
Input and Output Markets&#13;
6.3   Input Markets.  Input markets, especially for fertilizer and farm chemicals, are&#13;
dominated by the large agricultural parastatals that provide inputs, including credit, directly to&#13;
cash crop producers. Recent economic reforms have helped to liberalize domestic marketing of&#13;
inputs and to provide an enabling environment for expanded private sector participation. The&#13;
procurement and distribution of fertilizer is still dominated by SOTOCO, SAFICC, and the&#13;
fertilizer procurement agency within MAEP. In the past, SOTOCO has relied on the government&#13;
phosphate monopoly, OTP, to procure fertilizer for use in the cotton subsector. SOTOCO takes&#13;
delivery of these inputs at the port, and transports them to regional warehouses, from where they&#13;
are distributed to farmers. Under the proposed liberalization of internal markets, the project&#13;
would gradually, but strongly support the development of village-level institutions (farmer&#13;
associations, cooperatives and women and youth groups) to handle the distribution of fertilizer to&#13;
farmers. For cocoa and coffee, the collapse of the rural credit system has led to serious problems&#13;
in SAFICC's efforts to supply inputs to farmers, and many of them have resorted to the open&#13;
market for these inputs.&#13;
6.4   Output Markets. Food crop markets are generally competitive in Togo; they are&#13;
characterized by numerous small traders and limited government intervention. The inefficient&#13;
government food crop sector parastatal, TOGOGRAIN, which has operated for nearly two&#13;
decades and whose functions have been limited to procuring about 12,000 MT of grains annually&#13;
as security stock, will be dissolved (see also paras. 2.20 and 3.4). The marketing of food crops is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
dominated by women, but the relatively underdeveloped rural infrastructure network and post-&#13;
harvest processing and storage facilities contribute to seasonal price variations in rural markets.&#13;
Marketing of cotton, cocoa and coffee was, until recently, controlled by the parastatal OPAT.&#13;
Under OPAT, there was heavy implicit taxation of export crop producers, with producer prices&#13;
kept as low as one third of the world market price. The net effect of these policies was a huge&#13;
cash surplus for the monopolist: in 1980, for example, OPAT contributed 10 percent of total&#13;
government revenue. Between 1983 and 1987, and as a result of measures introduced under the&#13;
structural adjustrnent programs, the price of coffee, cocoa and cotton increased in real terms by&#13;
29, 20, and 25 percent, respectively. From 1988 onwards, government adopted a policy to make&#13;
the producer price of export crops more responsive to world market signals, with an announced&#13;
indicative floor price, and supplemental transfers to producers based on the actual world market&#13;
price that prevailed during the year. Under recent reforms, the export of cash crops has been&#13;
liberalized and since 1996 the internal marketing of coffee and cocoa has been liberalized.&#13;
6.5   Prices. Financial and economic prices of inputs and outputs are in Annex 3. Financial&#13;
prices are based on first quarter 1996. All output prices are average annual farmgate prices&#13;
received by producers. The financial price of fertilizer is based on prices paid by fanners for&#13;
these inputs to the major parastatals. Import parity prices were calculated for all tradables. For&#13;
all non-tradables, a standard conversion factor (SCF) of 0.8 was used to convert financial prices&#13;
to economic values. The daily wage paid during first quarter 1996 was estimated at CFAF 750&#13;
per day for the food crop sector; it is higher for export crops, averaging about CFAF 1,200 per&#13;
'day. The price of urea, the most common fertilizer used on food crops, was estimated at CFAF&#13;
125 /kg or CFAF 6,250 per 50-kg bag. This compares to its economic price of CFAF 153 per kg&#13;
or 7,650 per 50-kg bag, reflecting a subsidy element received by farmers linked to the parastatals.&#13;
Given Togo's geography, calculation of economic prices was referenced on three major&#13;
production centers in order to fully account for differences in transport costs - Lome, for the&#13;
South, Sokode, for the Central, and Mango, for the Savannah North. The cost of intrastate&#13;
transport of inputs to these major centers was provided by SOTOCO.&#13;
Farm Budgets&#13;
6.6   Financial budgets.5  Farm budgets (per ha) were estimated for main food and export&#13;
crops. The farm budgets were based on conservative yield estimates (details are in the&#13;
Implementation Manual). Labor use was adjusted to reflect differences in technical requirements&#13;
between traditional and improved farming systems for some activities, such as weeding and&#13;
harvesting. Overall, farm budgets showed that the adoption of improved technologies would be&#13;
financially profitable for smallholders. The average returns to farm household (in CFAFIha)&#13;
typically exceeded the rural wage of CFAF 750 per day for food crops and CFAF 1,200 per day&#13;
for export crops. These returns were higher for the export crop sector, ranging between CFAF&#13;
2,500 to 5,500 per day (Table 6.2).&#13;
s  Detailed financial budgets for individual crops are in the Working Paper&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
6&#13;
6.7   Economic budgets The impact of the adoption of improved varieties was also assessed&#13;
using the economic prices estimated for inputs and outputs, including the economic opportunity&#13;
cost of farm labor. They include benefit-cost ratios, based on the opportunity costs of farm labor,&#13;
and the benefit-cost ratios that take into account the economic costs of all inputs. These&#13;
estimates are also in Table 6.2. The benefit-cost ratios for all crops exceeded unity, indicating&#13;
that economic returns from adopting these technologies in traditional farming systems would&#13;
more than offset the invested resources. Benefit-cost ratios were, in general, higher for cash&#13;
crops, followed by cereals, and by roots and tuber crops. The lowest benefit-cost ratio was for&#13;
cowpea, reflecting both the underdeveloped research for this crop, its low yields, and the high&#13;
postharvest losses caused by insect pests.&#13;
Table 6.2: Summary of Financial Returns and Economic Impact of Improved Technologies.&#13;
Benefit-Cost Ratios&#13;
Incremental Returns (Financial)      (Economic terms)&#13;
Per Ha         Non-labor Inputs&#13;
Crop             (CFAF/HA)           (CFAF/HA)        Labor    All Costs&#13;
Cereals&#13;
Maize            65,327               92,972           4.0       2.4&#13;
Rice              80,040              61,301           5.8      2.3&#13;
Root and&#13;
Tubers&#13;
Cassava          148,800             143,200           3.2      2.9&#13;
Yam              141,600             115,475           2.7       1.8&#13;
Legumes&#13;
Cowpea           121,000              73,775           3.5       1.5&#13;
Groundnut         58,771              32,646           1.4       0.9&#13;
Export Crops&#13;
Cotton           253,885             225,629           9.0      5.5&#13;
Cocoa            375,211             540,575          6.3        5.4&#13;
Coffee           580,255             966,380           4.5   1   4.4&#13;
C.    PROJECT,ECONOMIC VIABILITY.&#13;
6.8   Based on projections of the crop area that would be impacted by extension services&#13;
annually, the economic budgets were aggregated to estimate the project's overall Economic Rate&#13;
of Return (ERR). The estimation was based on the following assumptions: (a) a project life of&#13;
20 years, commencing in mid-1997, with a one year lag for the accrual of benefits; (b) an&#13;
investment period of five years; (c) an opportunity cost of capital of 12 percent; (d) all prices in&#13;
constant 1996 values; and (e) incremental output to come from the adoption of improved&#13;
varieties and management practices for food and cash crops. Although the project would impact&#13;
6  Details of economic budgets are in the Working Paper&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
on the livestock sector, estimation of economic returns focused primarily on food and cash crops.&#13;
These two subsectors account for nearly 75 percent of agricultural GDP, with fisheries, livestock&#13;
and hunting accounting for the remainder. Based on these assumptions, the project economic&#13;
rate of return (ERR) was estimated at 21.3 percent with a net present value (NPV) of CFAF&#13;
9,787 million.&#13;
VII. BENEFITS AND RISKS&#13;
A.   BENEFITS&#13;
Direct Project Benefits&#13;
7.1   Direct project benefits would be: (a) increased productivity of traditional farming&#13;
systems; (b) increased farm incomes; and (c) increased efficiency of research and extension&#13;
management through the restructuring of MAEP, ICAT and ITRA.&#13;
7.2   Increased productivity. The project would strengthen the national agricultural research&#13;
and extension systems, resulting in increased productivity of traditional farming systems. The&#13;
testing, selection, dissemination and adoption of improved varieties and management practices&#13;
would increase yields of poor farmers, resulting in higher food output for both household&#13;
consumption and markets. Yields of the major cereals, maize and rice, would increase by 112&#13;
and 100 percent, respectively on farmers' fields by the end of the project. The yield of&#13;
leguminous crops, such as cowpea, would also nearly double under farmers' conditions,&#13;
compared to the current yield of 450 kg per ha for traditional varieties. Farmers in the cash crop&#13;
subsector (cotton, cocoa, and coffee) are expected to benefit even more, from higher output.&#13;
Overall, an estimated incremental 54,900 tons of maize and 7,000 tons of rice would be&#13;
produced annually at full implementation. The estimated incremental output of cassava and yam&#13;
would be about 94,970 and 31,730 tons (fresh tuber weight) per annum, respectively. The&#13;
average returns to farm families producing these crops would be about twice the existing rural&#13;
wage rate of CFAF 750 per day.&#13;
7.3   Increased incomes. The project would lead to increased incomes for farmers from the&#13;
sale of marketable surpluses, both to the domestic markets and for exports. The liberalization of&#13;
internal marketing of cash crops, in particular, would benefit farmers who would receive an&#13;
increasingly higher share of world market prices. Strengthened OPEAs would permit farmers to&#13;
have better and low price access to various markets due to economies of scale in marketing.&#13;
OPEAs would also permit farmers to have ready access to cash as part of the trading benefit that&#13;
would accrue to them as members of the cooperative. Given the concentration of poverty in&#13;
Togo's rural areas, the impact of increased farm incomes would have a direct, positive impact on&#13;
the farmers, providing them with greater flexibility in consumption decisions.&#13;
7.4   Efficient management of research and extension. The project would lead to increased&#13;
efficiency in the delivery of research and extension services to beneficiaries through the&#13;
establishment of ICAT and ITRA. The measures that would be undertaken, including the semi-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
privatization of agricultural services would, through training and better incentives, lead to&#13;
improved services to farmers. Efficiency gains would be realized in terms of: (a) cost-&#13;
effectiveness of extension; (b) frequency of field visits; (c) diversity of improved packages for&#13;
farmers; and (d) a pool of better trained and motivated extension staff. The strengthening of the&#13;
central implementation unit, MAEP, and the research and extension systems would provide&#13;
improved capacity for effective management of research and extension in terms of better&#13;
planning, priority setting, and policy formulation.&#13;
Indirect Benefits&#13;
7.5   Indirect project benefits would be: (a) improved food security and nutritional status; (b)&#13;
human resource and institutional development; and (c) creation of an enabling environment for&#13;
sustainable agriculture development (due to policy measures initiated under the ERAC and to be&#13;
monitored under the project).&#13;
7.6   Improved Food Security. The improved crop varieties and management practices&#13;
promoted under the project would increase the productivity of traditional farming systems,&#13;
resulting in increased food production, which is essential for food security. Increasing the&#13;
availability and diversity of basic food supplies is essential for reducing poverty and increasing&#13;
household nutritional status. Food security would also be enhanced through the incomes that&#13;
farmers would earn from marketing surplus production, thereby empowering them to purchase&#13;
food during the lean periods of the rainy season.&#13;
7.7   Human Resources and Institutional Development.  In addition to the physical&#13;
infrastructure, the project would train both front-line extension and research staff, including&#13;
subject matter specialists. Training of ICAT and ITRA personnel would be complemented by&#13;
enhanced capacity building within MAEP for sector policy formulation and for monitoring and&#13;
evaluation of agricultural projects' impact. Capacity development within MAEP will include&#13;
strengthening capacity for the provision of market information to farmers (especially for export&#13;
crops) and for standardization and quality control of cocoa, coffee and cotton.&#13;
7.8   Enabling Policy Environment for Agriculture. The policy measures that would be&#13;
supported under the project, for example, the liberalization of input and output markets, would&#13;
provide an enabling environment for private sector participation in agriculture development,&#13;
which is essential for sustainable sector growth. In particular, the involvement of farmers&#13;
organizations in setting research and extension policies and- priorities would broaden the&#13;
decision-making process of agricultural development.  Farmer organizations would also&#13;
participate in the marketing of inputs at the farm-level, gradually taking over the roles currently&#13;
played by the key parastatals, SOTOCO and SAFICC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
B.    PROJECT RISKS&#13;
Quantifiable risks&#13;
7.9   Quantifiable project risks are as follows: (a) input price risks due, for example, to an&#13;
increase in the rural wage or increase in the price of purchased inputs, notably fertilizer as a&#13;
result of ongoing or planned liberalization; (b) output price risks, which may occur due to a fall&#13;
in the world price of Togo's primary export crops (cotton, cocoa and coffee) or through price&#13;
discounts that may be caused by lower quality of exports as a result of the liberalization of&#13;
export marketing. For these risks, sensitivity analyses were used to determine the impact of&#13;
these changes on the overall economic viability of the project, and switching values calculated to&#13;
determine the magnitude of the change required in each of these variables to make the project&#13;
change from being economically viable to unviable.&#13;
7.10  An additional risk results from the major organizational changes supported by the project&#13;
and the potential delays linked to the tight timetable to implement these. This risk will be&#13;
reduced by the requirements that key personnel for the new or reorganized units be selected on a&#13;
competitive basis and that the supporting finances are available on time. The effect of the&#13;
potential delay in this respect is presented in Table 7.1.&#13;
7.11   Sensitivity Analysis. Results of the sensitivity analysis are summarized below. They&#13;
show that the project's NPV is quite robust to wide shifts in input and output prices. However,&#13;
depressed food crop prices would affect project viability; a 20 percent reduction in food crop&#13;
prices would reduce the NPV by nearly 50 percent while, from the switching value estimated, a&#13;
50 percent reduction in food crop prices would render the project economically unviable. A 20&#13;
percent increase in the rural wage rate or a similar increase in fertilizer price would have no&#13;
perceptible impact on project viability. While labor is the most binding constraint, some of the&#13;
improved management methods for weed control and integrated pest management require less&#13;
labor input. Similarly, fertilizer use at the farm-level is still low and farmers would typically not&#13;
apply the recommended dosage, but would cut back on use if prices were to increase.&#13;
Non-quantifiable Risks&#13;
7.12 The main non-quantifiable project risks are: (a) political instability; (b) inadequate&#13;
counterpart funding; (c) inability of the OPEAs to contribute to ICAT and ITRA; and (d) lower-&#13;
than-expected adoption rates. For these risks, the approach used was to explain the nature of the&#13;
risk, assess the likely impact on the project, assign a subjective probability as to its likely&#13;
occurrence based on field experience and views of sector officials, and recommend mitigation&#13;
measures to minimize these risks (Table 7.2)&#13;
7.13  Political instability. In Togo, a renewal of political unrest would directly affect the&#13;
attainment of project objectives. Depending on the degree of instability, it may lead to&#13;
contraction of staff, reduced supervision, or at the extreme, project closure. The key intervention&#13;
is for the main donors to continue the reform dialogue with the government. It is also expected&#13;
that recent reforms that are being put into place to help restore macroeconomic stability may also&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
translate into some measure of political stability as the economy expands and jobs are created&#13;
and new opportunities are opened to the unemployed.&#13;
7.14  Counterpart funds. While Borrower's incremental contribution to project costs is low&#13;
(about US$7.6 million over five years, excluding duties and taxes), there is a low real risk that&#13;
project implementation delays may occur due to inadequate counterpart funding.  The&#13;
rationalization of government expenditures, which is currently underway, would help to improve&#13;
expenditure programming and introduce greater transparency in the budget process. An&#13;
important step in minimizing this risk is continuation of the current reform agenda and the&#13;
institutional strengthening within MEF. An important part of this process is to provide a regular&#13;
and advance notice to government of counterpart fund requirements that will come due during&#13;
the year. An appropriate forum for this would be the annual CPPR and supervision missions.&#13;
7.15 Contribution from the OPEAs. Under the project, OPEAs are expected to contribute a&#13;
share of the recurrent expenditures of ICAT and ITRA. However, there is the risk that the actual&#13;
annual contribution may be affected by changes in market conditions, such as a fall in the price&#13;
of export and/or food crops. The associated risk can be minimized by (a) clearly stating the&#13;
institutional mechanism and the procedures by which the transfer between the OPEAs and ITRA&#13;
and ICAT would be effected; (b) educating member associations (a process that is already&#13;
underway); and (c) providing a fall-back arrangement, such as through the EU-funded STABEX,&#13;
for keeping funding at optimal levels in the event of low crop prices.&#13;
7.16 Lower-than-expected yields. The risks of lower-than-expected yields can be minimized&#13;
with adequate logistics to front-line extension staff, and increased efficiency of dissemination,&#13;
including a defined menu of technologies and target farmer groups. Monitorable indicators&#13;
under the project, which would be reviewed periodically during implementation (supervisions&#13;
and project mid-term review), may help to reduce this risk.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-37 -&#13;
Table 7.1: Non-quantifiable Project Risks and Mitigation Measures&#13;
Risk Factor     Likely Impact    Probability    Mitigatory Measures    Time Frame&#13;
(a) Political   Project           Medium-to-    Maintain policy       Continuous; IDA,&#13;
Instability    implementation     high          dialogue and increased   CFD, other&#13;
delayed or made    probability.    donor monitoring may   donors.&#13;
impossible due to               help.&#13;
renewed civil&#13;
unrest.&#13;
(b) Inadequate  Project objectives   Medium     Better budgetary      Continuous; IDA,&#13;
Counterpart    delayed or not met; probability  programming and       IMF, Togo&#13;
Funding         project costs     given country  transparency;        Country Team.&#13;
increased due to    experience and  continued&#13;
implementation    resource      implementation of&#13;
delays.           scarcity.     reforms to increase&#13;
fiscal accountability&#13;
and transparency;&#13;
annual dialogue&#13;
(CPPR, SIR).&#13;
(c) Inadequate  Inefficient       The           Clearly define        Throughout&#13;
OPEAs           extension and     probability of   mechanisms for     project life.&#13;
Contribution    research services   this occurring   beneficiary      (MAEP/ICAT/IT&#13;
may result if    is low-to-     contribution; educate    RA)&#13;
private agents    medium for    OPEAs (underway) and&#13;
(OPEAs) do not    cash crop     strengthen their&#13;
pay expected share  producers, but  capacity to implement&#13;
of recurrent costs   higher for food  this task.&#13;
in a timely      crop farmers.&#13;
manner; inefficient&#13;
extension may&#13;
result.&#13;
(d) Lower-      Lower benefits    Medium        Sensitivity analysis of   Throughout&#13;
than-Expected   than used in      probability, but project benefits;  project life;&#13;
Adoption        estimating project  impact on   Provide logistics and    MAEP/Task&#13;
ERR; lower        project is high  incentives to extension; Manager.&#13;
impact.          if this risk   increase number and&#13;
materializes.   quality of extension;&#13;
Regular monitoring&#13;
through SPNs and&#13;
MTR.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
C.   FISCAL BURDEN OF THE PROJECT ON THE BORROWER&#13;
7.17 The total government public investment program (PIP) for the three-year rolling plan is&#13;
estimated at US$269.4 million, of which agriculture and rural development would account for&#13;
US$36.2 million (13.4 percent). Of this amount, the government would contribute about US$2.3&#13;
million over the next three years, with donors providing the balance. Based on PIP estimates, the&#13;
government would contribute US$0.5 million to agriculture and rural development in 1996,&#13;
US$1.0 million in 1997 and US$0.8 million in 1998, or a total of US$2.3 million over the three&#13;
year period. Total incremental counterpart funding required under the project is estimated at&#13;
US$12.2 million (US$4.6 million excluding duties and taxes, see footnote 3 para. 4.3). With the&#13;
project, government's commitments would increase to US$0.78 million in 1996, US$1.28&#13;
million in 1997, and US$1.08 million in 1998, indicating an increase of 56, 28 and 35 percent&#13;
respectively of the initial allocations for agriculture and rural development (Table 7.2).&#13;
Table 7.2: Fiscal Impact of Project on 3-Year Public Investment Program.&#13;
1997     1998    1999&#13;
Without Project (US$ million):&#13;
Total Annual PIP                                75.4     90.0    104.0&#13;
Of which, Agriculture and Rural Development.    10.4      12.4     13.4&#13;
Agriculture Share of PIP (%)                    13.8      13.8     12.9&#13;
Government Contribution to Agriculture           0.5       1.0      0.8&#13;
With Project (US$ million):&#13;
Annual Counterpart Funds (excluding duties and  0.28      0.28     0.28&#13;
taxes) (a)&#13;
Agriculture share of PIP with Project (US$ million)  14.08  14.08    13.18&#13;
Revised Govt. Contribution to Agriculture US$ million)  0.78  1.28    1.08&#13;
Increase in Fiscal Burden in Agricultural Sector (%)  2.0  2.0     7.0&#13;
Note: only. The increase in fiscal burden shows the percent increase in current commitments for&#13;
agriculture and rural development due to the project.&#13;
(a) Assuming that counterpart funds are evenly distributed over the project life.&#13;
Source: Mission estimates.&#13;
7.18  The increased financial burden under the project has been kept to a minimum, given the&#13;
adverse economic conditions in the Borrower's country. Most of the recurrent expenditures&#13;
would be met by donors, including IFAD, Government of Japan and UNDP. However, the&#13;
following factors, which are built into the project, would also help ensure that government's&#13;
capacity to contribute this amount is not affected: (a) the project would rationalize the civil&#13;
service in agriculture, and the staff reductions envisaged would lead to reduced government&#13;
expenditures and savings; (b) OPEAs would contribute a share of recurrent expenditures for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
research and extension, freeing off government resources; (c) restructuring parastatals in the&#13;
export crop sector would lead to efficiency gains and cost savings, and less drain on public&#13;
resources; and (d) institutional strengthening efforts currently underway would introduce greater&#13;
transparency in public finance that would assist govermment to meet counterpart fund obligations&#13;
in a timely manner.&#13;
D.   PROJECT IMPACTS&#13;
7.19 Impact on Women. The reorientation of the country's agricultural services, which will&#13;
become demand-oriented and participatory, will help to bring these services (in particular,&#13;
extension advice and research) to female producers and to respond better to their specific needs.&#13;
Through their statutory representation in decision-making bodies, rural women will be able to&#13;
influence strategic and policy decisions and adapt national programs to their demands and&#13;
capabilities. Women will benefit from the Program's training activities, in particular, from the&#13;
functional literacy classes, and get priority access to the resources of the VDF.&#13;
7.20 Impact on Youths: The disengagement of the State, provided for under PNASA, will&#13;
open up a number of opportunities in the fields of input supply, transport, and other rural&#13;
services. Young people in rural areas will have the opportunity to form OPEAs and benefit from&#13;
the Programn's training, extension and financing facilities. This will enable them to fill the gaps&#13;
created by the withdrawal of the public and semi-public enterprises and undertake income-&#13;
generating group activities in the fields of commerce, processing, transport of water, inputs and&#13;
products, etc. Young smallholders will have an important role to play as counterparts to the new&#13;
research structure (ITRA), participating in the identification and testing of research needs and&#13;
messages.&#13;
7.21 Impact on the Environment: PNASA will facilitate the introduction of improved&#13;
cultivation techniques aimed at environmental sustainability. By consolidating crop production&#13;
and animal husbandry related research, it will promote the development and introduction of soil&#13;
conservation and restoration techniques, permitting to prevent or halt over-exploitation and&#13;
degradation of natural resources. Crop diversification and promotion of other economic activities&#13;
(through the improved access to training and credit) will reduce the negative effects of mono-&#13;
cropping and the pressure on limited land resources, in general. Project proposals submitted for&#13;
financing from VDF or credit resources will be screened as to their environmental impact.&#13;
VIII. ASSURANCES AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
8.1   Conditions for negotiations completed:&#13;
(a)   a Letter of Agricultural Development Policy available for Bank comments (para.&#13;
2.25);&#13;
(b)   a proposal, in a form acceptable to the World Bank, of statutes to govern the&#13;
organization of MAEP, ICAT, and ITRA (para. 5.2); and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40 -&#13;
(c)   detailed proposals for all job positions for each of the functions of MAEP, ICAT,&#13;
ITRA, and the agricultural services side of SOTOCO (para. 5.2).&#13;
8.2   Assurances obtained during negotiations:&#13;
(a)   transfer of MAEP's current activities, unrelated to its core public service functions&#13;
to private sector operators and OPEAs (para. 3.4);&#13;
(b)   detailed and time-bound action plan for the restructuring of MAEP and the&#13;
establishment of ICAT and ITRA (para. 3.14);&#13;
(c)   OPEAs would contribute to financing of ICAT and ITRA and would mobilize&#13;
needed funds through voluntary contributions from the primary marketing of&#13;
cocoa, coffee and cotton (paras. 4.5-4.8);&#13;
(d)   Acceptance of Bank procurement procedures (para. 4. 10);&#13;
(e)   opening of three special accounts, one each for MAEP, ICAT and ITRA (para.&#13;
4.16);&#13;
(f)   opening project accounts benefiting ICAT and ITRA and make quarterly&#13;
government deposits (para. 4.17);&#13;
(g)   agreement on the administrative and financial procedures for transfer of funds to&#13;
ICAT and ITRA, and on financial control procedures (para. 4.17).&#13;
(h)   installation of computerized financial management system  and adoption of&#13;
appropriate accounting procedures at MAEP, ICAT and ITRA, satisfactory to the&#13;
Bank (paras. 4.18-4.19)&#13;
(i)   operation of special accounts in accordance with internationally accepted&#13;
principles and with practices acceptable to IDA (para. 4.19)&#13;
(j)   agreement on terms of reference for annual audits and submission of audit reports&#13;
within 6 months of close of fiscal year (para. 4.21);&#13;
(k)   agreement on Project Implementation Plan (para. 5.2)&#13;
(l)   agreement on key project performance indicators (para. 5.5);&#13;
(m)  agreement on timing and scope of work programs and budget (para 5.7);&#13;
(n)   agreement on content of half-yearly progress reports (para. 5.8);&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
(o)   agreement on arrangements for mid-term review (para. 5.9);&#13;
(p)   agreement on the preparation of the implementation completion report by the&#13;
Borrower within 6 months of the credit's closing date (para. 5.9)&#13;
8.3   The following conditions for presentation to the Board have been complied with:&#13;
(a)   approval by the Council of Ministers of a decree sanctioning the liquidation of&#13;
SAFICC and TOGOGRAIN (paras. 2.20 and 3.4);&#13;
(b)   adoption of decrees for the restructuring of MAEP and the establishment of ICAT&#13;
and ITRA, by the Government (paras. 3.14); and&#13;
(c)   submission to IDA of a procurement plan and bidding documents for the first year&#13;
of the project (para. 4. 10).&#13;
8.4   Conditions for Credit effectiveness:&#13;
(a)   ICAT and ITRA have been established, and the boards of directors of ICAT and&#13;
ITRA, respectively, have had their first meeting;&#13;
(b)   a Multi-year Program agreement has been signed for each of the two agencies&#13;
(para. 3.14);&#13;
(c)   MAEP has been restructured, and MAEP's staff not retained for employment in&#13;
either ICAT, ITRA or the restructured MAEP, have received severance payments&#13;
in accordance with the relevant laws of the Borrower (para. 3.14); and&#13;
(d)   the Borrower has deposited CFAF 490 million and CFA 350 million in the project&#13;
accounts for ICAT and ITRA respectively (para. 4.17).&#13;
8.5   Recommendation. With the above assurances and conditions, the project would be suitable for&#13;
an IDA Credit of US$ 26.2 million, on standard IDA terms with 40 years of maturity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42-                                   Annex I&#13;
Page 1 of 9&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
DETAILED PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
A.    Support for basic agriculturalservices: TechnicalAssistance and Support Institute (ICAT)&#13;
1.           ICAT would be created on the basis of the MAEP's, SAFIC and SOTOCO existing&#13;
extension services. It would focus its efforts on support to farmers and OPEAs in coordination with&#13;
other entities operating in the rural areas, by systematically seeking contractual relationships. ICAT is&#13;
intended to lead rural producers, through their economic professional organizations, in sharing with the&#13;
Government technical and financial responsibilities for efficient adaptive research, extension and OPEA&#13;
support services. ICAT would have the status of a semi-private company. Its initial corporate capital&#13;
could be distributed as follows: public shareholders (Government) 40 percent, and private shareholders&#13;
(OPEAs, employees, SOTOCO traders of agricultural inputs and agricultural products) 60 percent. The&#13;
corporate capital would be limited to FCFA200 million, allowing easy access by the OPEAs. The&#13;
Government would be able either to keep the assets used by ICAT in the public domain and make them&#13;
available for use or provide the corresponding subsidies in kind. The choice would be done during the&#13;
negotiation. The seats on ICAT's management board would be distributed as the paticipation in the&#13;
corporate capital.&#13;
2.           Extension and adaptive research. ICAT's function is to provide technical support to&#13;
agricultural producers in order to enhance their use of technical practices to increase their production and&#13;
improve their productivity in the long terrn. Farming systems would be a basis for the messages to be&#13;
disseminated through the extension method. However, specific product approach would not be given up,&#13;
but it would be integrated in the farming system context. Consequently, adaptive research and extension&#13;
staff would have to promote coffee, cocoa and cotton cultivation as well as food crop production and&#13;
livestock as important targets&#13;
3.           The extension services would be provided under the new Togolese Rural Extension System&#13;
(STER) based on the "Training and Visit" system, adapted to socioeconomic conditions in Togo. This&#13;
system represents a continuation and adaptation of the first STER, drawn up by the Agricultural Extension&#13;
Project (PVA), under which the MAEP's extension services were partly restructured. On the basis of&#13;
experience with the PVA, SOTOCO's agricultural extension services and other projects in Togo, the second&#13;
STER, Guide to Extension in Togo (Guide de la Vulgarisation au Togo) was prepared with World Bank&#13;
assistance during the agricultural extension workshop held in April 1995. The extension programs would&#13;
be designed and structured as a dynamic participatoryprocess (producers, extension agents, researchers and&#13;
other rural partners). The producers would be visited regularly by extension agents (agricultural advisers)&#13;
supported by technical specialists and monitored by zone chief. The extension services would need to&#13;
gather, discuss and analyze experiences, promote their exchange among regional institutions and make the&#13;
available technologies accessible to the producers. Adaptive research would be responsible for carrying out&#13;
tests of adaptation and adoption of the technologies by the producers through the observation points (POs)&#13;
and the Site to Support Agricultural Research System (SARSs) and for disseminatingfarmer know-how and&#13;
technical improvements. It would take part (the main participants would be the producers) in on-farm&#13;
demonstrationsof the new technologies. Special attention would be given to crops grown by women and to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43-                                   Annex 1&#13;
Page 2 of 9&#13;
the difficulties faced by young people in getting started in business and by the most disadvantaged farmers.&#13;
Identification of their problems, together with the solutions proposed and their disseminated through&#13;
extension, would be included in the project monitoring criteria (see Annex 9). This adaptive research,&#13;
corresponding to pre-extension, would be ICAT's responsibility and would be carried out in collaboration&#13;
with ITRA. ICAT would be able to entrust multi-site trials to ITRA, which would bear scientific&#13;
responsibilityfor them, ICAT continuing to be responsible for monitoring and evaluation.&#13;
4.            Support for the professional agricultural economic organizations (OPEAs). This would&#13;
comprise providing the farmers with the necessary assistance to enable them to set up and consolidate&#13;
farner groups through technical assistance activities designed to promote and strengthen organizational&#13;
structuring in the rural areas in order to set up economically and financially viable economic and&#13;
commercial units with coordination interlinkages. In addition to strengthening the basic groups, the&#13;
objective is to support the creation of higher-level agricultural professional organizations in the form of&#13;
unions and federations in specific fields. Involvement of women in the farmer associations would be&#13;
achievedboth by helping set up women's associationsand by integratingthem more firmly into the existing&#13;
professional organizations. The functions in which they traditionally excel (management, business, etc.)&#13;
would be developed through adapted training activities. The technical support measures would be geared to&#13;
the following activities: (a) analysis of the situation of the existing groups; (b) continuation of the process&#13;
of identifying and assessing the farmers' organizational needs; (c) assistance in setting up farmer groups&#13;
(providing statutes, helping formulate internal regulations, etc.); (d) training of managers and management&#13;
advisers, and (e) advisory assistance on rural credit, getting products to markets, marketing, processing and&#13;
artisan skills.&#13;
5.            The general strategy of this component would be based on two lines of action: (a) training&#13;
of OPEA technical specialists as true cooperative management and organization advisers, and (b) rapid&#13;
integration of these management advisers into cooperative unions intended progressively to take over total&#13;
responsibility for them. Training would be provided concerning participatory diagnosis and regulation of&#13;
the OPEAs and for management advisers (CGs) at private economic entities. Private-sector professionals&#13;
would take part in this training, particularly concerning trade in inputs. The work program of these CGs,&#13;
complete with quantifiable objectives, would be drawn up in collaboration with and approved by the&#13;
cooperativesand the unions with which they would be working. For the specific subsectors--coffee,cocoa,&#13;
cotton--specific, quantifiable programs would be prepared which would be dovetailed into the general&#13;
strategy but planned and negotiated each year by the various partners. Since CG assistance is deemed to be&#13;
a service that must be remunerated by the cooperative unions, a pragmatic analysis would be performed&#13;
after the first two years of the project to determine objectively the tempo at which the unions have to&#13;
assume total financial responsibility for these management advisers. The project would finance training of&#13;
the management advisers and their necessary operating and travel facilities.&#13;
6.            Human resources management and training. ICAT's would have a specific directorate&#13;
dedicated to have a permanent human resources development through on-the-job training for all staff. In&#13;
close collaboration with the technical manager of adaptive research, extension and support to OPEAs,&#13;
this Directorate would permanently assess the staff efficiency and would organize training&#13;
complementation to improve their operational skills. The training would be given by private-sector,&#13;
public sector and NGOs specialists. The project would finance training sessions, mission fees and travel&#13;
means for trainers, international and national consultant costs to support national trainers.&#13;
7.            Farmers information support. Broadcastingof information concerning agricultural product&#13;
prices and location is a key element for good marketing. Extension, adaptive research and OPEA support's&#13;
staff need also to have access to a broad forecasting system. An agricultural information unit would be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-44-                                   Annex I&#13;
Page 3 of 9&#13;
linked with the General Directorate of the ICAT. In close coordination with the ITRA and the MAEP this&#13;
unit would plan the broadcasting of agricultural infornation. This unit would not disseminate information&#13;
which would remain the task of TV, radio and newspapers. The unit would operate on the basis of contracts&#13;
with the news media. The contracts would be financed by the project through ICAT. To be eligible for&#13;
project financingthe annual contractswould also be agreed with IDA.&#13;
8.           ICAT's five regional directorates would be supported at the national level by the National&#13;
Directorate, comprising a General Directorate, an Administrative and Financial Directorate, three technical&#13;
directorates (Extension and Adaptive Research, Human Resources and Training, and Support for OPEAs)&#13;
and three units (Monitoring and Evaluation, Internal Auditing, and Farmers Information). ICAT's total staff&#13;
is projected to be 1,298: 120 upper-level managers, 287 middle managers and 891 operatives (including&#13;
618 agricultural advisers). At headquarters there would be 42 staff (15 grade A, 7 grade B and 20 grade&#13;
C/D operatives and contractual staff). Each regional directorate would have a staff of 50 (15 grade A, 12&#13;
grade B and 23 operatives), giving a total of 250 for the five regions. The local sections would have a total&#13;
staff of 1,006 (30 grade A, 220 B and 756 operatives).&#13;
9.           ICAT's staff would be selected from the MAEP's current personnel, chiefly that of the&#13;
extension services, which would supply the greater part of its employees, and staff of SOTOCO (following&#13;
reorganization of the company) and SAFICC (following its liquidation). This staff would consist&#13;
essentially of contractual personnel. Civil servants can be seconded during the first two years; thereafter&#13;
they would have to choose between private status and re-entry into the civil service.&#13;
10.          ICAT's resources would comprise: (a) the shareholder's capital subscriptions; (b) public&#13;
resources in the form of an annual allocation to fund salaries and part of operating expenses, which would&#13;
decrease as and when the time comes for them to be defrayed by private operators or agricultural&#13;
professional organization contributions; (c) contracts with the agricultural professional organizations&#13;
through voluntary levy requested by the producers and effected for cotton, coffee and cocoa by the export&#13;
firms. These sums would then be passed on to ICAT and ITRA in accordancewith a technical and financial&#13;
agreement concluded each year. This agreement would be drawn up by a committee on which the&#13;
producers would hold the majority of the seats; these levies on the purchase price of the products would be&#13;
instead of the current financial withholdings to finance services or taxes; (iv) contracts with agricultural&#13;
equipment and input vendors (inputs promotion), and (v) donations and legacies.&#13;
11.          The project provides for:&#13;
(a)    access to all agricultural data and a possibility for different interest groups to be involved in&#13;
the contracts which would be a condition for project financing;&#13;
(b)    accommodation of ICAT's National Directorate headquarters in the current premises of the&#13;
plant Protection Directorate, which are in good condition. They comprise a single-story&#13;
building with a site area of 600 m2, adequate to house ICAT and ITRA, which would&#13;
maintain a permanent contractual relationship,within a single site at Lome' Cacavelli;&#13;
(c)   installation of ICATs regional directorates in:&#13;
(i)   the PROPTA Project buildings at Atakpame, to be rehabilitated, and annexes to the&#13;
buildings of the Sokode, Kara and Dapaong DRDRs;&#13;
(ii)    a building to be constructed at Tsevie, where there is no infrastructure; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-45-                                   Annex 1&#13;
Page 4 of 9&#13;
(d)   redesign and rehabilitation of the existing infrastructures at the section and subsection&#13;
levels for the offices of ICAT.&#13;
The project would finance:&#13;
(a)   the necessary building rehabilitation or construction works;&#13;
(b)   the necessary office equipment and materials, means of transportation (6 passenger cars, 6&#13;
ATVs, 12 pickups, 286 motor cycles and 601 motorized bicycles), and training and mission&#13;
fees.&#13;
B      Support for agricultural research (Togolese AgriculturalResearch Institute--ITRA)&#13;
12.          The agricultural research component would comprise activities aimed at promoting&#13;
agricultural development in the areas of plant, animal, fishery and forest products, the environment, and&#13;
post-harvest, food and agroindustrialtechnologies. To that end it would support a scientific program based&#13;
on: (a) Togo's priority development concerns, defined by the MAEP and ICAT on the basis of the&#13;
producers' real needs both at the national level and that of each agro-ecological zone; (b) protection of the&#13;
environment; (c) post-harvest, agro-food and agroindustrial technologies; (d) development of land&#13;
resources; (e) production of basic seed for the major crops cultivated in Togo. The improved seed would be&#13;
propagated by a network of private producers, mainly seed farmers (a reconversion opportunity for laid-off&#13;
staff), who would sell it directly to individual farmers or OPEAs (this seeds privatization program would be&#13;
supported by the NGO IFDC), and (f) development and distribution to the extension services of a&#13;
technological data package tailored to farmers needs.&#13;
13.          The current agricultural research system (DNRA and institutes) would be replaced by a&#13;
Togolese Agricultural Research Institute (ITRA). ITRA's functions would be to (a) serve as a national&#13;
frame of reference in the area of agricultural research, however, without seeking to monopolize this activity;&#13;
(b) provide training for researchers and technicians, and also, at the request of ICAT, technicians for&#13;
agricultural extension; (c) collect, process and disseminate scientific and technological data in the areas of&#13;
the agricultural and basic sciences; (d) advise the government authorities on the availability of technology&#13;
with the object of raising agricultural production, consolidating national food security and protecting the&#13;
environment, and (e) contribute, within its areas of responsibility, to the formulation of Togo's national&#13;
agricultural development policy. ITRA's status would be similar to that of ICAT (a semi-private company&#13;
with private capital partners). It would possessjuridical personalityand autonomy in administrationand in&#13;
technical, financial and human resources management. Its headquarters would be at Lome. It would&#13;
comprise a General Directorate and four polyvalent regional agricultural research centers with management&#13;
autonomy.&#13;
14.   The General Directorate would comprise a Director General (DG), to be selected chiefly for his&#13;
management skills, assisted by a Scientific Director (DS), an Administrative and Financial Director (DAF)&#13;
and a Support Services Director (DSA). The DS would be assisted by four scientific coordinators in the&#13;
following fields: (a) plant products and post-harvest technologies; (b) animal and fishery products; (c)&#13;
forest products and management of agricultural natural resources, and (d) production systems and&#13;
application of agricultural research findings. The DSA would have five agencies: (a) Scientific and&#13;
Technical Information; (b) Biometrics and Data Processing; (c) Agricultural Meteorology; (e) National&#13;
Soils Service (Lome), which would provide its rural development services through contracts with a Land&#13;
Development Support Unit which is about to be privatized, and (f) National Food Technologies Service&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46-                                 Annex 1&#13;
Page 5 of 9&#13;
(Lome), which would similarly provide its development services through contacts with an Agricultural&#13;
Food Product and Agroindustrial Technologies Support Unit (studies contracts) which could also be&#13;
privatized.&#13;
15.          ITRA would have four regional polyvalent agricultural research centers (CRAPs). They&#13;
would be located in the main agro-ecologicalregions, at:&#13;
(a)     Kara (Abouda), for the dry savannahs of northern Togo;&#13;
(b)      Tove (former IRCC station), for the sub-humid mountainous region of middle and southern&#13;
Atacora; IRCC's old coffee/cocoa research programs would be expanded to include:&#13;
production systems, food crops and post-harvest techniques, environment and animal&#13;
products;&#13;
(c)     Kolokope (former IRCT) for the moist savannah, where the old cotton research programs&#13;
would be expanded as for the IRCC;&#13;
(d)      Davie, for southem Togo.&#13;
16.          The centers would specialize in certain fields for which they are best suited (for example:&#13;
Kara, millet/sorghum; Tove, coffee/cocoa; Carr6kape, cotton; Tsevie, maize/yam), at the national and&#13;
regional levels. Agreements could be signed for this purpose with regional (western African) and&#13;
international research centers. The ability of the research system to cater for the specific problems of&#13;
women and young people would form part of the criteria for measuring the success of the project. (See&#13;
Annex 8).&#13;
17.          The permanent "core" staff of agricultural research would not exceed 260, including 50&#13;
researchers. They would be selected through open competition. In cases of comparable qualifications,&#13;
preference would be given to current personnel of DNRA and the institutes. ITRA would use temporary&#13;
personnel as needed in light of the research contracts awarded to it. This contract research would not,&#13;
however, generate any additional recurrent costs for ITRA after completion of the work.&#13;
18.   The project would provide for:&#13;
(a)   redesign of the premises of INCV and DNRA (800 m2) and rebuilding of the premises of&#13;
INTA (800 m2) and INS (700 m m2) to accommodate ITRA's director's office and&#13;
laboratories;&#13;
(b)   rehabilitationof the existing premises for offices and housing (250 m2) and constructionof&#13;
150 m2 of new offices for the Davie SRAP;&#13;
(c)   rehabilitation of office infrastructures(200 m2) for the KpalimelTove SRAP;&#13;
(d)   rehabilitationof 500 m2 of housing for the Atakpam6/KolokopeSRAP;&#13;
(e)   rehabilitationoflaboratories(120 m2), offices (500 m2) and housing(500 m2) at&#13;
Abouda/Kara;&#13;
(f)   electrification of the Abouda and Kolokope centers;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47-                                  Annex I&#13;
Page 6 of 9&#13;
(g)    provision of additional scientific equipment for the laboratories;&#13;
(h)    provision of means of transport for researchers and support personnel;&#13;
(i)   financing of inter-countryresearch agreements within the subregion.&#13;
C.    Pilot Agricultural Credit&#13;
19.          The purposes of the rural credit savings and loan component are to: (a) test the setting up&#13;
of a three rural S&amp;L institutions frame of reference based on the existing structures; (b) finance the&#13;
development of agricultural production in order to enhance food security and upgrade rural living&#13;
conditions; (c) support efforts by farmers to better organize themselves for the purposes of production,&#13;
marketing, product processing, and management of their farms and of their finances; (d) make the OPEAs&#13;
more efficient in this field; and (e) improve the rural framework for facilitatingthe liberalization process of&#13;
the whole agricultural sector. These credit operations would make it possible to use the extension services&#13;
for individual farmers and groups of farmers to better advantage. This component implemented through&#13;
three selectedNGOs would be based on: (a) good managementability; (b) credit reimbursementrate higher&#13;
than 95 percent during the last four years; (c) interest rate similar to the national financial market; (d) no&#13;
direct credit subsidies. However, during the implementation phase, not exceeding four years, grants to&#13;
support salaries and capacity building for credit managers in the field is acceptable (OD 8.30 para, 29); (f)&#13;
sound accounting, legal, and regulatory infrastructure system (OD 8.30 para.36, 37); (g) self-sustaining&#13;
resource mobilization after the implementation period (OD 8.30 para.70); (h) independence of decision&#13;
making for the credit managers (OD 8.30 para.71). The project would not change the NGOs' strategies,&#13;
which have already yielded positive results in the field, but it would provide support to consolidate the gains&#13;
and extend the experiments.&#13;
20.          The project would hence provide support for: (a) three NGOs (SYNORSEC, SOCODEVI&#13;
and FUCEC) in setting up new S&amp;L branches to widen acces to saving and develop credit to agriculture in&#13;
predetermined pilot areas; (b) a Coordination Committee; and (c) a technical M&amp;E unit to implement for&#13;
this component within the MAEP. The component will be complimentary to the activities of the Financial&#13;
Sector Adjustment Credit (FINSAC) and therefore will entail close collaboration between the different&#13;
projects' units during implementation.&#13;
21.          Through the three NGOs the project would finance the setting up of 10 new rural S&amp;L&#13;
institutionsand strengtheningofthe Nyile S&amp;L (SYNORSEC: six new rural S&amp;Ls and strengtheningof the&#13;
Nyile S&amp;L; SOCODEVI: four new S&amp;L institutions, FUCEC: will provide training). The project would&#13;
bear the infrastructure expenses (vehicles, data processing equipment, office furniture and materials) and&#13;
personnel training, salary and travel costs during the period until the S&amp;Ls that are to become self-financing&#13;
reach break-even point in 4 to 5 years.&#13;
22.          Technical coordination of this pilot operation would be assured by a Coordination&#13;
Committee. The Committee would have eight members (NGOs-two each, MAEP-one, Finance Ministry-&#13;
one) and its chairmanship would rotate every six months. It would be responsible chiefly for organizing a&#13;
three-day discussion workshop every six months. The workshop would bring together entities involved in&#13;
credit to agriculture in Togo. The three NGOs would present their results, their problems and their tools&#13;
and strategies at this workshop. This would give the other operators an opportunity to note and apply the&#13;
information or even to strengthen the tools and strategies utilized through constructive criticism. The&#13;
project would bear the costs of these workshops.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-48-                                  Annex 1&#13;
Page 7 of 9&#13;
23.          A Rural Credit Technical Monitoring and Evaluation Unit would be set up in the MAEP.&#13;
Its functions will be to: (a) review the operating policies of the three pilot schemes and human resource&#13;
development plans; (b) assess the validity of the personnel positions and profiles of each of the pilot rural&#13;
scheme; (c) assess the pilots' economic impact on productivity and production in the selected regions; (d)&#13;
evaluate the training activities carried out; and (e) review the annual audits of the pilots.&#13;
24.          The financial manager for this component would be recruited on a contractual basis, using&#13;
a competitive method and terms of reference approved by the World Bank. The costs of this manager, who&#13;
would have no jurisdiction over the technical side of the component, would be borne by the project.&#13;
25.          The Agricultural Finance component of this project would complement actions to&#13;
be taken under the FINSAC and the Public Enterprise Restructuring Project (PERP) to ensure&#13;
strengthening of the overall Rural and Microfinance sector in Togo. Actions supported by the FINSAC&#13;
and the PERP will consist in : (a) supporting the Unit in charge of the supervision of rural and&#13;
microfinance institutions in the MEF, (b) providing the Network of RMFIs with regular technical&#13;
training sessions, broad exposure to international best practices and technical assistance to expand and&#13;
organize the network activities and communication, (c) assisting the public/private joint committee in&#13;
elaborating a National Rural and Microfinance strategy for Togo, and (d) providing FUCEC with&#13;
Technical Assistance in institution building and financial management.&#13;
26.          Therefore, the Technical Assistance activities regarding agricultural finance in the&#13;
present project will be organized in coordination with the Implementation Unit of the PERP and&#13;
FINSAC projects: (a) semi annual workshops (mentioned in paragraph 22) will be designed jointly; (b)&#13;
during implementation the Unit in MAEP will work closely with the MEF in charge of supervision of all&#13;
Rural and Microfinance Institutions, to review the financial and prudential management of the three pilots&#13;
as well as their M&amp;E procedures; (c) while the PERP will bear the initial cost of setting up and training&#13;
the Unit in MEF, the present project will bear the additional cost related to agricultural credit; and (d) the&#13;
national agricultural credit policy will be gradually developped under the framework of the rural and&#13;
microfinance policy.&#13;
27.          The support component (equipment, training) of this lending is regarded as an investrnent&#13;
by the Government in the agricultural sector to set up the necessary professional human resources network&#13;
for establishment of a rural S&amp;L system. The funds derived from repayment of the loans by the NGOs&#13;
would go to fund the regional S&amp;L institutions in order to boost lending capacity and expand the system.&#13;
An external audit of the development and use of the funds would be performed each year, by private&#13;
auditors, and transmitted to the MAEP, the Ministry of Finance and IDA. Future management procedures&#13;
would be determined in light of the findings of the mid-term review.&#13;
D.    Support for the MAEP&#13;
28.          The Ministry of Rural Development (MAEP) would refocus its attention on its functions of&#13;
formulating and implementingthe Government's agricultural policy. Prior to start-up of the project, the job&#13;
descriptions and personnel profiles for each position would be redefined, the headquarters directorates and&#13;
services restructured and reduced in number, and their staffs redeployed in the regions and prefectures.&#13;
With ICAT taking over the agricultural services responsibilities in the regions, the staff of the regional&#13;
apparatus would be reduced from 1,736 to 765 and that of the headquarters services at Lome from 989 to&#13;
178.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49-                                  Annex 1&#13;
Page 8 of 9&#13;
29.   The Terms of Reference of the MAEP and its Regional Directorates during the first two years of&#13;
the project would be to: (a) complete the liberalization process for coffee, cocoa and pursue it for cotton; (b)&#13;
complete an annual agricultural public expenditures review; (c) update the agricultural sector review with&#13;
participating regional directors; (d) implement instruments for managing its functions both at the regional&#13;
and national levels. The appraisal mission would finalize these TORs and propose financial covenants for&#13;
the CreditAgreementaccordingto the targets of planned operations. The mid-term review would assess the&#13;
results and propose a reviewed plan for the last three years of the project.&#13;
30.          The new MAEP would comprise, at the national level, an office of the minister and&#13;
secretariat, with a secretary general coordinating the activities of six directorates: Administration and&#13;
Finance; Planning, Programming and Statistics; Farming, Livestock and Fishing; Natural Resources&#13;
Management, and Promotion of Rural Legislation. These directorates would be divided into 20 agencies&#13;
(services), as detailed in the organizational chart (see Annex 5). The permanent staff complement would\&#13;
not exceed 68 of grades Al and A2, 39 of grade B and 41 of grades C/D, plus 30 permanent operational&#13;
staff. At Lome these agencies would be grouped together in a single building. The costs of rehabilitation,&#13;
furniture, data processing equipment and office equipment (50 percent would be renovated old equipment)&#13;
would be borne by the project.&#13;
31.          In the five regions, the government's role would be limited to: (a) identifying and studying&#13;
agricultural constraints and potentials and drawing up regional agricultural policies; (b) helping to program&#13;
projects within the framework of national policy; (c) assessing the impact of the projects and programs; (d)&#13;
systematically gathering the necessary data on the rural world and, in particular, keeping the agricultural&#13;
statistics; (e) overseeing compliance with the animal health, plant health and land tenure regulations and the&#13;
establishment of OPEAs, and (f) evaluating natural resources and drawing up rural land use and&#13;
development plans. Each regional directorate would have five divisions: (a) Administration and Finance;&#13;
(b) Programming and Statistics; (c) Natural Resources Management; (d) Animal and Plant Health Control,&#13;
and (e) Land Tenure Affairs and Rural Institutions. The regional directorate would have a staff of 75 : 20 of&#13;
grades Al/A2, 19 of grade B and 36 operational staff. The five regions would hence have a total staff of&#13;
375.&#13;
32.          A Prefecture Rural Development Division (DPDR) would be set up in each of the 30&#13;
prefectures, with responsibility for applying the animal and plant health regulations, gathering statistics and&#13;
overseeing natural resource conservation. It would be headed by a division chief and would comprise three&#13;
offices: (a) Natural Resources; (b) Statistics, and (c) Animal and Plant Health Control. Each prefecture&#13;
would have 1 grade B and 12 grade C/D staff members, giving a total staff of 390 for the whole of the&#13;
country.&#13;
33.          The project would finance: (a) rehabilitation of the DRDR's premises at Atakpame,&#13;
Sokode, Kara and Dapaong (a total area of 2,910 m2). For the maritime DRDR, which would be moved&#13;
from Lome to Tsevie, it is planned that the premises of the regional planning directorate (400 m2) be&#13;
renovated and that they be rehabilitated and supplemented by a new 250-m2 office building; (b) renovation&#13;
at the level of the 30 prefectures of the offices of the rural development prefectoral divisions (DPDRs), i.e.,&#13;
4,500 m2 to be renovated in the existing infrastructures at the section level, and (c) rehabilitation and&#13;
construction works for the buildings of the MAEP's headquarters services at Lome and rehabilitation of a&#13;
330m2 single-story building, and construction of a second 500-m2 single-story building nearby. This&#13;
solution brings the Minister'soffice and all the directoratestogetheron the DGDR site.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-50-&#13;
Annex 1&#13;
Page 9 of 9&#13;
34.           The project would also finance office equipment and materials, up to 50 percent of existing&#13;
inventory, vehicles (II passenger cars, 7 ATVs, 100 motor cycles and 120 motorized bicycles) and their&#13;
operating costs.&#13;
35.           Other financing would have to be raised prior to start-up of the project in order to settle the&#13;
MAEP's debts and pay the severance allowances of the staff not retained in the new structure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-51-                                Annex 2&#13;
Page 1 of 2&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
OED RECOMMENDATIONS AND PNASA RESPONSES&#13;
Extension principle      Recommendations of OED                      Response&#13;
Programming of        To be maintained, but program to be    The program is determined after&#13;
activities            determined according to the needs of    participative diagnosis in accordance&#13;
the farmer group (as agreed with them)  with farmers requests. Specific&#13;
as well as the availability and    training of Field Extension Workers&#13;
appropriate timing for treatment of  (FEW) and Subject Matter Specialist&#13;
specific technologies.             (SMSs) on participative diagnosis is&#13;
planned.&#13;
Fixed visits schedule    To be maintained, but in accordance  The periodicity of visits will be&#13;
with a schedule agreed as appropriate   planned with farmer contact groups on&#13;
between farmers, field staff and   a regular schedule. Exceptions can be&#13;
supervisor, rather than as a general  accepted if the farmer so wishes.&#13;
standard of fortnightly visits.&#13;
Supervision           Maintain, but with more emphasis on    Regular visit schedules will be&#13;
assessing reactions of farmer clientele   maintained in accordance with farmers'&#13;
than on the mechanics of the visit  requests. Training for FEW and&#13;
schedule.                          supervisor to improve capacity to&#13;
assess reactions of farmers is planned&#13;
at the beginning of the project.&#13;
Single line of command  To be maintained (but not as an   Farmers are to be selected/appointed to&#13;
essential requirement), but develop and  the Board of ICAT. They are in the&#13;
understanding that the extension staff   regional planning and assessment&#13;
must be responsive to the needs of the   committee. ICAT's staff is managed&#13;
farmer clientele whose reactions would  under semi-private rule not as civil&#13;
be monitored by supervisory staff as    servants. They are accountable to&#13;
measure of staff performance.      farmers.&#13;
Concentration on ex-    To be maintained, but not to the  According to the project preparation,&#13;
tension technology    exclusion of facilitating the provision    NGOs (Sassakawa 2000, SOCODEVI,&#13;
of services by other agencies (private   IFDC etc ... ) support complementary&#13;
and public) to meet the needs of the  pilot credit operation, seeds, fertilizer&#13;
farming communities being attended,   and post harvest privatization.&#13;
nor of assisting farmers to develop a    Supported by the project OPEAs would&#13;
self-help capacity (e.g., seedling  be more efficient participating in&#13;
production, group marketing)       processing storage and marketing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-52-                               Annex 2&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
Technical content and   To be maintained, timely training  Training sessions would be planned&#13;
training              sessions for field staff geared to  from the SEW requests which would be&#13;
subjects of proximate visits, but not as  established from farmers needs. The&#13;
district-wide general recommendations  presence of different SMS would allow&#13;
associated with dominant commodities; that and, if necessary, specific support&#13;
the widely applicable recommendations would be requested from research.&#13;
would be taken into account by training&#13;
officers, but training would be adapted&#13;
and incorporated where possible into&#13;
the solutions to the problems identified&#13;
with farmer groups.&#13;
Use of Contact Farmers  A concept to be adopted that identifies  That is exactly the project strategy and&#13;
or Farmer Groups for   existing groups of farmers with similar  SEW would receive training to&#13;
visits and            resource circumstances, problems and   implement it.&#13;
demonstrations        attitudes as the medium for interaction&#13;
with the extension staff (as groups or&#13;
subgroups in the recipient community),&#13;
uses these groups to define major&#13;
constraints, analyzes the relevance of&#13;
technological solutions, and assumes&#13;
ownership of demonstrations.&#13;
Research-extension    To be maintained and expanded with    The farming system approach is basic&#13;
linkage               an emphasis on enduring relevance in   for the project. SEW are polyvalent&#13;
applied/adaptive research; this implies  (agro, livestock and forestry).&#13;
a farming system perspective in both    Adaptive/research would work directly&#13;
research and extension, which would   into the farmers exploitation to&#13;
benefit by joint farming system    experiment proposals for the extension.&#13;
diagnostic surveys.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 3&#13;
Page I of 2&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
ECONOMIC ANALYSIS: CURRENT AND POTENTIAL YIELDS&#13;
1.    Maize. In Togo, technology packages have been more effective for maize than for most&#13;
food crops, given the high response of maize to nitrogen fertilizer. Maize improvement programs&#13;
have concentrated on the rapid development and dissemination of open-pollinated varieties from&#13;
which farmers can save seeds for planting in subsequent seasons. Several improved varieties of&#13;
maize are now commonplace in Togo's farming systems; notably the Ikenne and Pool 16SR&#13;
varieties. While high yields (upwards of 2.9 tons/ha) have been obtained during on-farm trails,&#13;
realization of full yield potential under farmers' conditions is constrained by low inherent soil&#13;
fertility, poor management, and striga infestation. Project interventions will address these&#13;
constraints with the objective of raising on-farm yields closer to those realized under research-&#13;
managed conditions and increasing farmers' yields which, at a high of about 1.2 tons/ha, is still&#13;
58 percent below that of on-station yields.&#13;
2.    Rice. The presence of hydromorphic soils and fertile valley bottoms make rice&#13;
cultivation highly successful in the south-central areas of Togo. Despite this potential, rice has&#13;
remained an under-exploited crop. Water remains a major constraint, given the erratic rainfall&#13;
patterns in most parts of the country. Improved rice varieties have been imported from the&#13;
regional research centers, such as IITA, but yields on farners' fields are still about 42 Rercent&#13;
below that of on-farm trials. The project would support the multiplication and dissemination of&#13;
improved rice varieties, as well as provide recommendations for improved input use and&#13;
management practices, including optimal plant population, spacing and timely weeding and&#13;
application of chemicals. Regional directorates of the restructured MAEP would identifyand&#13;
plan suitable investment projects to support irrigation improvements. NGOs and bilateral donors&#13;
would be able to finance these well-planned projects more easily.&#13;
3.    Yams. Yam cultivation has benefited from the minister technology for multiplying yam&#13;
seedlings for planting. However, this technology is not widely used by farmners. The relative ease&#13;
of producing seed yams, and the high yield of this crop in Togo, provide substantial scope for&#13;
increasing national production. It is estimated that Togo's current national crop can be increased&#13;
by 25 percent over the project period with widespread adoption of minisett technology,&#13;
combined with improved management practices. The project would support the dissemination of&#13;
improved yams seed technology (minisett) to farmers as well as disease and pest control&#13;
interventions.&#13;
4.    Cassava. While yields of traditional cassava are currently low, about 8 to 10 tons/ha,&#13;
there are improved varieties whose adoption can impact farm-level production dramatically. The&#13;
most popular varieties are the tropical manihot series (TMS) 30572 and TMS 30555, both of&#13;
which are in high demand due to processed quality. The project would support ITRA's&#13;
multiplication and on-station trials to select new cultivars for their tolerance to local diseases and&#13;
pests. It will also support ICAT dissemination of these cultivars to smallholders.&#13;
5.    Cowpea. Yields of beans are low in Togo, about 360 kg/ha, due to the prevalence of&#13;
insect pests that wreck havoc in farmers' fields. The use of insecticides provides some degree of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5 4-                             Annex 3&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
relief, but the high costs of these chemicals prevent farmers from using them on a wide scale.&#13;
Newer varieties of beans, such as IT 82 E 18, and IT82 E 16 have on-station yields exceeding I&#13;
ton/ha. The project would support the multiplication of these new varieties and their&#13;
intercropping into existing farming systems, an integrated pest management strategy that would&#13;
further help to reduce insect infestation.&#13;
6.    Groundnuts. Groundnut has a high potential as an economic crop in Togo, but&#13;
realization of this potential is constrained by diseases, poor agronomic practices, and limited use&#13;
of fertilizer by farmers. With stable rainfall and the use of modem inputs, groundnut yield can be&#13;
as high as 1.2 tons/ha on-station. Under farmers' conditions and management practices,&#13;
groundnut yields are often as low as only 0.7 tons/ha. Improved groundnut varieties, such as&#13;
RAP 12 and TS 32-1, would be multiplied by ITRA and disseminated by ICAT for traditional&#13;
farming systems.&#13;
7.    Export crops. In the past, the export crop sector received extension services directly&#13;
from the parastatals (SAFIC, SOTOCO). Under the project, extension services would be&#13;
rationalized, with resources pooled for more effective coverage. Support would be provided for&#13;
management of existing crops, replanting with improved cultivars, and the development of new&#13;
areas. In particular, ITRA would work on research on export crops, while ICAT would provide&#13;
extension assistance to farmers on disease and pest control and management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-55-                                    Annex 4&#13;
Page I of I&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
Institut de Conseil et d'Appui Technique (ICAT)&#13;
ORGANIGRAMME&#13;
D'ADMINISTRATION&#13;
FerineD                      O               rClue Ifrv.natiqEauet&#13;
Serv. A                GENERALE&#13;
uditDG/DGA                                          e E&#13;
COORDINATION NATIONAF                                 CORINTO NATINAL&#13;
| VULGARISATION   1                                  ORIAOPNATINL&#13;
|Serv. Adrnin. &amp; Finncsa|REIONLEt8&#13;
I&#13;
|  CS  |     | ~CS  |       |CHEF DE SECTEUR ||CS  ||CS|&#13;
Unite Techniciens &#13;
alis6s TS                   T&#13;
CA A_Consciller C                        A&#13;
L   5   LL 1              ~~~~~~~~~Agricole CAL        IL               J&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ORGANIGRAMME DU MINISTERE DU DEVELOPPEMENT RURAL(MAEP)&#13;
| MINISTRE DU     |&#13;
DEVELOPPEMENTRUAL&#13;
CABIINET MAEP~&#13;
|Etablissements Publics .  .............-SECRETAR IAT *-                                   Societes&#13;
GENERAL&#13;
D DA    l  l      DEP       l    l     DAF        l     _      DPRH                    DRNA                   DSID&#13;
4Div. P F V      DFiv. P E                                      -l jDiv. A P    _|Div. Planif.  Div. A R          Div. Staistique&#13;
4Div. PA-I         4Div. P PA             Div. BCAI            jDiv.P&amp;I I                 Div. CAGRNA  |         Div. Informatiq&#13;
Div. C.Phyto       Div LHASPV          4Div. MPL                Div. S&amp;E                 Div.AA-F              - Div. DIA&#13;
Div. Juridique  |Div. GRHII&#13;
Div. E F A&#13;
aDiv. IR|&#13;
Etablissements Publics |-I-------| DIRDECTOPPN               E REGIONALE               .      . -Societes&#13;
|    Div. PE S  l  l    DivRNA      l                 |    Div. A F             Div. C V            Div. C Phyto&#13;
DIVISION PREFECTORALE                                                                                  o U|n&#13;
DU DEVELOPPEMENT RURAL                                                                                   eh&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SIGNIFICATION DES SIGLES&#13;
DA                         Direction de I'Agriculture&#13;
Div. PFV                   Division de la Promotion des Filieres Vivrieres&#13;
Div. PA-I                  Division de la Promotion des Filieres Agro-Industrielles&#13;
Div. C. Phyto              Division du Contr6le Phytosanitaire&#13;
DEP                        Direction de I'Elevage et des Peches&#13;
Div. PE             Division de la Promotion de I'Elevage&#13;
Div. PPA                   Division de la Promotion des Peches et Aquaculture&#13;
Div. LHASPV                Division de la Legislation, de l'Hygiene Alimentaire et de la Sante&#13;
DAF                        Direction de I'Administration et des Finances&#13;
Div. AP                    Division de I'Administration et du Personnel&#13;
Div. BCAI                  Division du Budget, de la Comptabilite et de l'Audit Interne&#13;
Div. MPL                   Division de la Maintenance,du Patrimoine et de la Logistique&#13;
Div. Juridiq.              Division Juridique&#13;
DPRH                       Direction de la Planification et des Ressources Humaines&#13;
Div. Planif.               Division de la Planification&#13;
Div. P&amp;I                   Division Programme et Investissement&#13;
Div. S&amp;E                   Division Suivi et Evaluation&#13;
Div.GRH                    Division Gestion des Ressources Humaines&#13;
Div.EFA                    Division de i'Enseignement et de la Formation Agricoles&#13;
Div.IR                     Division Institutions Rurales&#13;
DRNA                       Direction des Ressources Naturelles Agricoles&#13;
Div. AR                    Division Amdnagement Rural&#13;
Div. CAGRNA                Division du Contr6le des Amenagement et Gestion des Ressources Naturelles Agricoles&#13;
Div. AA-F                  Division des Affaires Agro-foncieres&#13;
x&#13;
0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
DSID                       Direction des Statistiques, de l'Informatique et de la Documentation&#13;
Div. Statistique           Division des statistiques&#13;
Div. Informatiq.                  Division de l'Informatique&#13;
Div. DIA                   Division de la Documentation et de l'Information Agricole&#13;
DIRECTION REGIONALE DU DEVELOPPEMENT RURAL&#13;
Div. PFS                   Division de la Planification, de la Formantion et des Statistiques&#13;
Div. RNA                   Division des Ressources Naturelles Agricoles&#13;
Div. AF                    Division de I'Administration et des Finances&#13;
Div. CV                           Division du Contr6le Vterinaire&#13;
Div. C. Phyto              Division du Controle Phytosanitaire&#13;
DIRECTION PREFECTORALE DU DEVELOPPEMENT RURAL&#13;
Bur. des Statistiques      Bureau des Statistiques&#13;
Bur. des Res. Nat. Agr.    Bureau des Ressources Naturelles Agricoles&#13;
Bur. Contr6le Veterinaire  Bureau du Contr6le Veterinaire&#13;
Bur. Contr6le Phytosan. Bureau du Controle Phytosanitaire                                                                          u'&#13;
GQ~&#13;
(DU&#13;
hU'&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC Oi TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
Institut Togolais de Reclierche Agronomique (ITRA)&#13;
ORGANIGRAMME&#13;
DARS:  Dispositif d'Appui a la Recherche-Systeme&#13;
IST:    Information Scientifique et Technique&#13;
CONSEIL&#13;
D'ADMINISTRATION&#13;
DIRECC1ION&#13;
GENERALE&#13;
|DIRECTION DES LABORATOIRES                                                                      DRCOODRETNADI XNITATIOE&amp; &#13;
SCIENTIFIQUE   |DlES PROOGRAMMES |                FINANCIERE  &#13;
q   Lao Micelvaleur des teffes  |S4ervicelIST                                           Product. aiiniales     IS {iice Finaiicier&#13;
Lnbo N%tiitioll ctTcchiil.Aliilcoui. |IiixleB                                          l Irodkct. vegetae   |nCoptabilile&#13;
Labo Res.Genetiq BiAtecl.&amp;RS                                                                                              istique&#13;
jDocumentation  | st Ress. Natur.- |      Conlr8le         &#13;
.                   q~~~~~~~Serv. Admin. et tetRs.Hm &#13;
|   CRA/L                                            CRA/F                                       r       CRAtSIL                                    CRAtSS        |           O&#13;
|   (DAVIE)                                              (  TOVE)                                            (KOLOKOPE)      ll                        (BUA            f* &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-60-                              Annex 7&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
LES COUTS DES STRUCTURES&#13;
GESTION 1996&#13;
(en million FCFA)&#13;
Personnel   Fonctionnement   Investissement&#13;
1   SAFICC                            105         358                 25&#13;
2    TOGOGRAIN                         20           88                405&#13;
3  OPAT                               NC           NC                 NC&#13;
4    SOTOCO Enc                       121     _&#13;
5    MAEP Central                   1.868         1.677&#13;
6    DRDR                             992          180&#13;
7    Projet ANANAS                     19             1                18&#13;
8    PNPE                                                         105.000&#13;
9    IRCT                              58           51                 51&#13;
10  IRCC                               50           59                122&#13;
11   SOGVERS                          NC           NC             107.286&#13;
12   Projet TRYPANOSOMIASE             10          NC                 27&#13;
13  RANCH ADELE                        37           56&#13;
14   Projet NAMIELE                    13           10                72&#13;
15   PROPTA                           24           NC                 NC&#13;
Source: DAF&#13;
NC:  donnees non communiquees&#13;
4:    il s'agit seulement du personnel pris en charge sur le budget de l'Etat. La&#13;
SOTOCO paie les salaires et le fonctionnement de plus de 600 agents sur la filiere&#13;
coton.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-61-                           Annex 7&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
Impact du Projet sur le Financement&#13;
au titre des filieres agricoles&#13;
Annee 1    Annee 2    Annee 3    Annee 4    Annee 5&#13;
ICAT + ITRA&#13;
Salaires            960         960         960        960         960&#13;
Fonctionnement                                          600        600&#13;
Total         960         960        960         1560        1560&#13;
N.B. Une partie des financements de fonctionnement pourront etre pris en charge par&#13;
des programmes d'appui bi ou multilateraux en particulier pour les annees 4 et 5 apres&#13;
la reprise de toute la cooperation intemationale au Togo. Dans ce cas les charges a&#13;
supporter par les filieres pourraient 8tre encore diminuees.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Impact sur le budget&#13;
(million FCFA)&#13;
Annde 1            Annee 2              Annee 3             Annee 4            Annee 5&#13;
R        I         R         I         R          I         R         I        R         I&#13;
MAEP&#13;
* Salaires                  1000                1000                1000                 1000               1000&#13;
t Frais de Fonctionnement                                                                          395                395&#13;
ICA + ITRA&#13;
* Salaires                  640                 640                 640                 640                 640&#13;
* Frais de Fonctionnement                                                                         414                414&#13;
Total                  1640                1640                1640                1640      809       1640      809&#13;
Total par an                1640               1640                 1640               2449                2449&#13;
R: Reallocation des fonds actuellement utifises par le budget courant.&#13;
I: Depenses supplementaires dues a 1'execution du projet.&#13;
x&#13;
0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
MONITORING AND EVALUATION (M&amp;E) INDICATORS IN RELATION TO MAIN OBJECTIVES&#13;
Narrative Summary                                             Obiectively Verifiable Indicators&#13;
(Actual v. Target)&#13;
Goals&#13;
1. Increase living standards of farm household                1. % rise in average household net incomes*&#13;
2. Increase labour efficiency                                 2. % rise in return per person day of farm labour&#13;
3. Reduce household food scarcity                             3. % fall in food scarce HHs&#13;
4. Improve nutrition                                          4. % decrease in malnourished children &lt; 5 yrs (in close collaboration with the&#13;
Ministry of Health&#13;
Purpose and objectives&#13;
A. Production&#13;
a'&#13;
1. Increased yield of main crops                              1. Average kgs/ha yield increases on main crops&#13;
2. Increased area and output from main crops                  2. % increase in area and output from main crops&#13;
3. Increased food availability from own production            3. Proportion of food from farm consumed by HH*&#13;
4. Area under improved seeds                                  4. % increase under improved seed for main crops*&#13;
5. Adoption of agro-forestry                                  5. % increase in farmers using agro-forestry*&#13;
6. Adoption of improved cultivation practices                 6. % increase in farmers using improved practices*&#13;
7. Adoption of soil/water conservation technics               7. % increase in farmers adopting conserve. practices*&#13;
8. Increase labour productivity of female farmers             8. % of productivity increase of F farmers&#13;
9. Increase cash income from livestock                        9. % of HH income derived from livestock&#13;
B. Institutional&#13;
1. More cost-effective extension                              1. % rise in number of mini-plots/meetings/FA unit cost&#13;
2. Improved dissemination capacity                            2. % rise in farmer understanding/awareness ext&#13;
3. Improved relevance of extension messages                   3. % rise in farmers adopting recommendations&#13;
4. Upgrading management/supervisory skills                    4. Staff assessment/job evaluations/reporting&#13;
5. Increased efficiency and effect of research                5. Cost of research/increase of production from research&#13;
6. Cost Accounting Systems operating                          6. Funds disbursed and accounts produced&#13;
7. Efficiency of Agency management                            7. Farmers participation in decisions (national and regional)&#13;
8. Improved acccess to agriculture credit                     8. % farmers participating in rural credit and efficiency of rural credit program                (D J&#13;
9. Improved economic farmers empowerment                      9. % of farmers involved in cooperatives increase incomes of farmers through cooperatives  x&#13;
(D&#13;
o x&#13;
Fh C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
PROJECT OBJECTIVES AND DETAILED SCHEDULE OF IMPLEMENTATION INDICATORS&#13;
.jProject Component    C  ompoetsObjctve                                           Cri t 20: ical.....      .......... Steps Inica0;i;;0;tor       Da0 i:tes&#13;
Restructuring         Create and implement&#13;
Process               ICAT and ITRA and           *   Completion of the staff census                                                                4/96(C)&#13;
MAEP                  strengthen the MAEP         0   Selection of specialized private firms for staff evaluation and preparation of staff selection  4/96(C)&#13;
ICAT                                              *   Creation of ICAT and ITRA                                                                     7/97&#13;
ITRA                                              *   Completion of job description of all staff concerned                                          2/97(C)&#13;
*   Completion of staff selection                                                              10/7/97&#13;
*   Recruitment and start-up of training of the Heads of the training and Human Resources         8/97&#13;
Management Departments of ICAT, ITRA, and MAEP at both central and regional level&#13;
*   Lay-off of contractual staff who are not selected                                             9/97&#13;
*   Completion of the identification of staff's training needs and the project's training program  8/97&#13;
*   Final selection of the Director General of the ICAT and the ITRA                              8/97&#13;
*   Final selection of the ICAT and ITRA national directors                                       8/97&#13;
TOGOGRAIN?                 *   Appointment of a liquidator SAFIC                                                              7/97&#13;
*   Audit of 1996 accounts and evaluation of assets of MAEP, DRDR Research Institutes             7/97&#13;
*   Allocation of assets to the ICAT and the ITRA                                                 8/97&#13;
*   Ministerial decree to reorganize the MAEP's services                                       10/7/97&#13;
ICAT-                 Improve organization and    *   Elimination of duplication of extension services                                             10/97&#13;
Extension             management of               *   Multidisciplinarity of the extension service                                                 10/97&#13;
extension services         *   Establishment of working program for extension staff on all levels                             1/98&#13;
*   Regular supervision of extension staff on all levels                                       Permanent&#13;
*   Regular Training for all staff                                                             Permanent&#13;
*   Appropriate logistic support for field and central staff                                   Permanent&#13;
Improve farmers' know-how   *   Regular fortnightly visits to farmer contact groups                                        Permanent&#13;
and knowledge to increase    *   Installation of demonstration plots in farmers' fields                                    Permanent&#13;
their productivity and     *   Repetition of demonstration plots by all interested farmers in their own fields             Permanent&#13;
income;&#13;
(C) Completed&#13;
oQ&#13;
ID&#13;
0&#13;
U,h&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Project Objectives and Detailed Schedule of Implementation Indicators&#13;
Project Component     Component's Objectives                                     Critical Steps - Indicators                                  Evaluation&#13;
Dates&#13;
cont. ICAT' - Ext.    Make the existing farm     *   Development of new technical messages                                                      Permanent&#13;
management systems more    *   Focus on the farm as a whole                                                               Permanent&#13;
productive, stable and     *   Special emphasis on agro-forestry and improved fallow                                      Permanent&#13;
environmentally&#13;
sustainable&#13;
ICAT -                Elaborate technical        *   Establishment of one Systematic Research Adaptation Site (SARS) in each region -- as much as  6/98&#13;
Adaptive Research     messages, based on a           possible in the immediate surroundings of the observation plots to facilitate management and to&#13;
thorough understanding of      diminish costs -- to bridge the gap between research results, both systematic and thematic,&#13;
existing farming               on the one hand, and technical messages, adoptable by farmers, on the other hand&#13;
practices, permitting&#13;
farmers -- in particular&#13;
women and youth -- to      *   Establishment of one Observation Plot in each region to serve as multi-local trial sites for  6/98&#13;
increase their revenue and     thematic research programs to undertake varietal tests&#13;
productivity through&#13;
intensification of&#13;
cropping practices and     *   Installation of On Farm Trials to test varieties, selected through the observation plots, in  6/98&#13;
diversification into           farmers' own fields&#13;
profitable and&#13;
environmental sustainable&#13;
activities&#13;
Improve research - farmer    *   Organization of Monthly Technical Review Meetings with SMSs, thematic and systematic       3/98&#13;
extension linkages             researchers and SARs staff&#13;
*   Participation of the ICAT (Directorate for Support to Adaptive Research/Service for          1/98&#13;
Technical Programs of Research/Development Support) in elaboration of research programs&#13;
9/97&#13;
ICAT - Support        Promote and strengthen     *   Recruitment of Farmer Organizations Specialists (FOSs)&#13;
to Farmer's          farmer's organizations      *   Regular meetings of FOSs and about 20 farmers' organization each to train and advise          3/98&#13;
Organizations                                        participants on creation of farmers' organizations purchasing of inputs, rural credit, processing&#13;
of agricultural production, marketing and relations with other organizations in agri-business&#13;
*   Stremaline OPEA's support strategy                                                           3/98&#13;
*   Creation of tolls to support OPEA                                                            3/98&#13;
*   Training of FOS to master strategy and tolls                                                 3/98&#13;
*   Improve cooperator's incomes                                                                 6/99&#13;
*   Improved fertilizer management                                                               6/99&#13;
Improve and promote        *   Close collaboration between the ICAT and different Professional Organizations                6/98&#13;
coordination among             Project which focuses on the creation of second and third - level organizations&#13;
farmers' organization&#13;
support&#13;
CD &gt;&#13;
ox&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Project Objectives and Detailed Schedule of Implementation Indicators&#13;
Projectg componen:t  :Component's Objectives                                     Cical Steps in Indcators.                                    Evaluation&#13;
ICAT-                                            *   Monitoring of quality and regularity of training                                             6/98&#13;
Monitoring and                                   *   Monitoring of cost effectiveness of ratios                                                   12/98&#13;
Evaluation&#13;
*   Budgetary control                                                                            12/98&#13;
Monitoring and evaluation    *   Monitoring of variations in farmers' revenues                                              6/99&#13;
of the quality and impact  *   Monitoring of women farmers' revenues                                                        6/99&#13;
of the ICAT field work     *   Monitoring of farmers' reactions to technical themes                                         6/99&#13;
*   Monitoring of adoption rates                                                                 6/99&#13;
*   Monitoring of commercial performance                                                         6/99&#13;
*   Monitoring of benefits increase of farmers' organizations                                    6/99&#13;
MAEP - ICAT - ITRA   Create, within the ICAT     *   Completion of training of Human Resources Managers and Training Managers                     12/98&#13;
Training and Human    ITRA and MAEP, the         *   Assurance of external supervision of trainers                                                12/98&#13;
Resources             capacity to conceive and&#13;
Management            organize training programs&#13;
Help staff adapt to new    *   Completion of first training of all staff on job description                                 12/98&#13;
task descriptions          *   Completion of initial technical training for all staff                                       12/98&#13;
Improve technical, manage-   *   Provision of continious training for all staff                                             6/99&#13;
rial and orginizational skills   .&#13;
Assure efficient human     *   Adaptation of training programs to staff performance                                         6/99&#13;
resource mamagement                                                                                                                            ON&#13;
MAEP - ICAT - ITRA   Assure accountability       *   Preparation of annual budgets                                                                12/98&#13;
Administration                                   *   Assure general and analytical accountability                                                 12/98&#13;
and Finance                                      *   Assure budgetary control                                                                     12/98&#13;
12/98&#13;
Manage goods and           *   Supervision of the accountability at the regional level                                      12/98&#13;
equipment                  *   Goods process in purchasing goods and services                                               12/98&#13;
*   Supervision of logistical management at the regional level&#13;
Assure the administrative  *   Assure supervision of regional administrative human resources management                     6/99&#13;
aspects of human resources&#13;
management&#13;
ITRA                  Provide adapted            *   % of themes which adapted to the farmers context                                             12/99&#13;
themes to SARS             *   Increase of farmers' production                                                              12/99&#13;
*   Increase of farmers' productivity                                                            12/99&#13;
l    Decrease of farming system risks                                                            12/99&#13;
oD&#13;
o x&#13;
U,h&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Project Objectives and Detailed Schedule of Implementation Indicators&#13;
Project Component                                                                                                                             Evaltation&#13;
Component's Objective                                     Critical Steps - Indicators                                    Dates&#13;
cont. ITRA            Capacity building of       *   Staff training                                                                               12/99&#13;
extension staff            *   Improvement of services from researchers to extension staff                                  12/99&#13;
Capacity building          *   Result of training in work performance                                                       12/99&#13;
of research staff          *   Incentives to the researchers to promote adaptive research                                   12/99&#13;
Regional and intemational    *   Impact of the Regional Network participation in planning, finance and results in the field  12/99&#13;
networks participation     *   Impact of the Intemational Network participation in planning, finance and results in the field  12/99&#13;
Institutional         Financial                  *   Implementation of new procedures                                                             12/98&#13;
Strengthening of                                 *   Implementation of tools and human resources training for an annual agricultural public       12/98&#13;
MAEP                                                 expenditure review (regional and national)&#13;
*   First Agricultural public expenditure review                                                 12/98&#13;
*   Annual Agricultural expenditures review                                                      12/99&#13;
Planning and Financial     *   Implementation of tools and human resources training of the annual investment planning (regional  12/98&#13;
and national)&#13;
*   First annual planning of agricultural investments (regional and annual)                      12/98&#13;
*   Annual planning of agricultural investments (regional and national)                          12/98&#13;
Planning                   *   Participation of regional and national planning service in Agricultural project preparation planning  12/98&#13;
Monitoring                 *   Effectiveness of S/E of Agricultural project (regional and national) and impact of the S/E   12/99&#13;
Technical efficiency       *   Task definition for each services, working plan, monitoring or results                       12/98&#13;
of each regional service   *   Implementation of reliable agricultural statistics at regional and national levels           12/98&#13;
Stregthening of MAEP's     *   Retrenchment of all activities related to direct support to cooperatives and training of farmers  12/98&#13;
Cooperative Support        *   Enacting revised cooperative legislation to make it more simple and operational              12/98&#13;
*   Monitoring of policy implementation and enforcement of regulations                           12/99&#13;
Strengthening of MAEP's    *   Effeciency of Regional Directorates: (a) development of regional agricultural                12/99&#13;
Regional Directorates          policies; (b) monitoring and evaluation of policy implementation; (c) enforcement of regulations;&#13;
and (d) collection and processing of statistics&#13;
Strengthening of MAEP's    *   Land tenure legislation improvement                                                          12/00&#13;
policy making              *   Rural NGO's framework improvement                                                            12/99&#13;
*   Rural credit framework proposal                                                              12/99&#13;
*   Food crops policy support                                                                    12/98&#13;
&gt;D&#13;
OQ&#13;
o x&#13;
U,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Project Objectives and Detailed Schedule of Implementation Indicators&#13;
Evaluation&#13;
Project Component      Component's Objectives                                     Critical0 Steps -Indicators                                      Dates&#13;
Agriculture Credit    Implementation of cluster   *   Composition of the cluster                                                                    12/97&#13;
managing the credit        *   Definition of rules                                                                            12/97&#13;
component                  *   limplementation of rules                                                                       6/98&#13;
Mutual rural credit        *   Nb. of "caisse", Nb of credits, amounts, % of reimbursement                                    12/99&#13;
implementation&#13;
Impact of credit to        *   Impact in production and productivity increase                                                 12/99&#13;
agriculture&#13;
*   Impact in living standards                                                                    12/99&#13;
Exchange of information    *   Effectiveness of the semestiral workshops, participants and working plan issued                12/99&#13;
MAEP and MEF               *   Training of human resources, improvement and implentation of S/E tools, quality of             12/99&#13;
capacity building              recommendations for the national strategy&#13;
co&#13;
o0&#13;
&gt;&#13;
(D&#13;
LJ1&gt;&#13;
o x&#13;
U,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-69-                                   Annex 10&#13;
Page 1 of I&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
SCHEDULE FOR LIQUIDATION, PRIVATIZATION AND LEGAL FRAMEWORK&#13;
IMPROVEMENT&#13;
TOGOGRAIN            Liquidation before board&#13;
SAFICC               Liquidation before board&#13;
SEEDS&#13;
i)    Privatization&#13;
Farm of Sotoboua:    privatization        12/99&#13;
ii)    Quality Control&#13;
Legal Aspect                               6/98&#13;
Set up                                     6/98&#13;
iii)   Importation&#13;
Legal Aspect                               6/98&#13;
FERTILIZER&#13;
i)    Import Liberalization&#13;
Legal Aspect                              completed&#13;
ii)    Quality Control&#13;
Legal Aspect                               6/98&#13;
Set up                                     6/98&#13;
iii)    Cancellation of Food crop Fertilizer subsidies  12/98&#13;
VETERINARY PRODUCTS&#13;
i)    Import Liberalization                             completed&#13;
ii)    Quality Control&#13;
Legal Aspect                               6/98&#13;
Set up                                     6/98&#13;
PESTICIDES&#13;
i)    Import Liberalization                             completed&#13;
ii)    Quality Control&#13;
Legal Aspect                               6/98&#13;
Set up                                     6/98&#13;
AGRICULTURAL TOOLS&#13;
i)    UPROMA liquidation                                12/98&#13;
ii)    Import Liberalization, Legal Aspect              completed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 1 1&#13;
Page 1 of 4&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCE FOR THE PROJECT MID-TERM REVIEW&#13;
The Mid-Term Review would take stock of progress and formulate recommendations with regard to appropriate actions to be&#13;
taken in the area of project activity in the table below:&#13;
Proiect Activity                                          Recommendation&#13;
1. The Restructuring Process MAEP. ICAT and ITRA:&#13;
-to what extent the restructuring process of the MAEP and the&#13;
creation of the ICAT and ITRA has been completed successfully;&#13;
-the possibility and appropriateness of further adjustment;&#13;
to what extent both the MAEP and the ICAT and ITRA are    -improve staffing&#13;
properly staffed;&#13;
-the budgetary impact of the restructuring process;       -further increase financial sustainability&#13;
2. The ICAT:&#13;
-the participation of the different partners in the capital structure   -the possibilities to increase the private sector's and in particular&#13;
farmers' organizations-participation in the capital;&#13;
-the private sector's capacities and interest to further assume  -ways and means to increase the private sector's participation;&#13;
responsibility for agricultural services;&#13;
-the efficiency of the ICAT's management structure, the extent of  -increase efficiency of management and farmers' participation in&#13;
decentralization, and the importance of farmer's participation in   the management of the ICAT&#13;
the decision making process&#13;
-the number of women working in the ICAT                  -increase the number of female staff;&#13;
-the cost effectiveness of the ICAT with regard to use of  -increase the cost effectiveness; and&#13;
equipment and vehicles; and the mission fees;&#13;
-availability of counterpart funds;                       -counterpart funds allocation and release.&#13;
(a) Extension and adawtive research:&#13;
-the impact of the principal technical themes with regard to  -improve relevance of technical themes;&#13;
agriculture, livestock and agro-forestry, on production and&#13;
farmers' revenue;&#13;
-the cost effectiveness of the ratios applied by the ICAT and by  -improve ratios&#13;
other extension organizations.&#13;
-the number of demonstration plots per contact group and per  -increase the visibility of the extension activities; the number of&#13;
technical theme, and the number of farmers participating in the  farmers adopting one or more technical themes; improve&#13;
encounters with the FEWs                                  understanding of reasons for non-adoption.&#13;
-farmers', researchers' and extension agents' participation in  -improve research - farmers - extension linkages;&#13;
Systemic Research Adaptation Sites;&#13;
-the efficiency and regularity of monthly extension workshops;    -improve the process of monthly review and fine-tuning of&#13;
technical                                                 technical themes;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-71-                                              Annex ll&#13;
Page 2 of 4&#13;
-the efficiency, relevance and environmental impact of technical    -improve technical messages;&#13;
messages;&#13;
-the relevance of technical messages for special interest groups  -improve technical messages;&#13;
such as women and youth;&#13;
(b) Farmer Organizations&#13;
-the number and quality of newly created first -, second-, and  -improve conditions for the creation and promotion of farmers'&#13;
third- level farmer organizations;                             organization;&#13;
-the financial management of farmer organizations in terms of  -improve management practices;&#13;
turnover, benefits and economic investments;&#13;
-the number of Farmer Organizations Specialists transferred from    -strengthen cooperative unions so as to enhance their managerial&#13;
the ICAT to farmers' cooperative unions;                       and financial responsibility for Farmers' Organization Specialists;&#13;
-the possibility for farmer organizations to take direct and full  -extend Farmer's Organization economic activities&#13;
responsibility for price setting, marketing and exportation of&#13;
cotton, coffee, cocoa etc.;&#13;
-the efficiency and relevance of the ICAT's activities with regard&#13;
to strengthening of farmers' organizations, making the ICAT's&#13;
farmers' organizations activities more demand-drive.&#13;
(c) Farmer and trader Information&#13;
fthe involvement of different professionals                    -improve the variety of information broadcasting&#13;
the relevence of information&#13;
the efficeincy of informarion broadcasting&#13;
3. The ITRA&#13;
-the participation of the different partners in the capital structure    -the possibilities to increase the private sector's and in particular&#13;
farmer organizations-participation in the capital;&#13;
-the private sector's capacities and interest to further assume  -ways and means to increase the private sector's participation;&#13;
responsibility for research services;&#13;
-the efficiency of the ITRA's management structure, the extent of   -increase efficiency of management and farmers' participation in&#13;
decentralization, and the importance of farmers' participation in    the management of the ITRA&#13;
the decision making process&#13;
-the number of women working in the ITRA                       -increase the number of female staff;&#13;
-the cost effectiveness of the ITRA with regard to use of      -increase the cost effectiveness&#13;
equipment and vehicles; and the mission fees&#13;
-availability of counterpart funds;                           -counterpart funds allocation and release.&#13;
-themes provided to the extension, themes used by extensionist,    -improve relevance of technical themes&#13;
and themes adopted by farmers;&#13;
-the cost effectiveness of research actions;&#13;
-impact of researches in capacity building of extension staff and&#13;
OPA leaders;&#13;
-impact of the project in capacity building of researchers;&#13;
-relevant relationship between national, regional and international&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-72-                                               Annex I I&#13;
Page 3 of 4&#13;
agricultural research network&#13;
-effectiveness of incentives to have results in the field rather than&#13;
academic reports.&#13;
4. The MAEP:&#13;
-the planning directorate's capacities to prepare and program  -strengthen the directorates' staff through appropriate training and&#13;
agricultural policy, annual investment budgets, and studies;    other means;&#13;
-the cooperative directorate's capacities to prepare policy and  -strengthen the directorates' staff through appropriate training and&#13;
legislation and to enforce regulations with regard to cooperatives    other means;.&#13;
-the regularity and reliability of statistical reports;        -strengthen the directorate's staff through appropriate training&#13;
and other means;&#13;
-the regional directorates' capacity to develop regional        -strengthen the directorates' staff through appropriate training and&#13;
agricultural policies, monitor and evaluate policy implementation,   other means;&#13;
enforce regulations and produce reliable statistics;&#13;
-the autonomy of regional directorates with regard to budgetary  -appropriateness to increase regional directorate's budgetary&#13;
planning;                                                       autonomy.&#13;
5. Credit to Aericulture&#13;
-the efficiency of credits to agriculture: number of credit increase,  -to improve strategy and tools;&#13;
amounts, % of recovery;&#13;
-the impact of credits in production increase and productivity  -to focus strategy;&#13;
improvement;&#13;
-the relevance of national policy proposed;                     -to decide extension or not of the pilot operations.&#13;
6. Training&#13;
-the quality, relevance and cost of initial training of all staff;  -improve the cost effectiveness of the training;&#13;
-the appropriateness and possibilities to improve initial&#13;
agricultural training programs;&#13;
-the regularity and relevance of continuous training of all staff;  increase training's efficiency and relevance;&#13;
-the efficiency of collaboration between the ICAT, ITRA, MAEP    ways and means to improve and expand collaboration with o-ther&#13;
and other training organizations;                               training organizations.&#13;
7. Administration and Finance&#13;
-the maintaining of records and accounts reflecting adequately  -improvements to the accounting procedures;&#13;
operations and financial conditions;&#13;
-the timely availability of certified copies of accounts as well as of  -respect of delays for transmission of such accounts and audit&#13;
the annual audit report;                                       reports;&#13;
-the respect of Bank's procedures with regards to procurement and  -appropriate training to increase staff's capacities with regard to&#13;
disbursement;                                                   procurement and disbursement;&#13;
-the eligibility of payments made under the special account;    -proper use of special accounts;&#13;
-the efficiency of financial and administrative procedures;     -improve such procedures;&#13;
-efficiency of the budgeting process and the responsibility of both   -increasing financial responsibility at the regional level;&#13;
the regional and national level for ICAT, ITRA and MAEP;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-73-&#13;
Annex 11&#13;
Page 4 of 4&#13;
-the availability of counterpart funds,                   -timely release of these funds.&#13;
8. MonitoringlEvaluation of ICAT. ITRA. MAEP and rural credit&#13;
-the relevance of the indicators used by the M/E system;  -improve the M/E system and training of M/F staff;&#13;
-the reliability of information;                          -procedures of data collecting and processing;&#13;
-the availability on the appropriate levels of M/E reports;  -the production and distribution of M/E reports.&#13;
9 Revised estimate of the proiect impact during the first two years&#13;
10 Economic analysis of the proiect and second phase&#13;
-adequacy of data to prepare an economic analysis         -based on data collected during the first phase of the project, an&#13;
economic analysis to be prepared/updated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 12&#13;
Page 1 of 5&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
SUMMARY OF IFAD'S REVIEW AND STRATEGIES&#13;
PRINCIPALES CARACTERISTIQUES DU FONDS DE DEVELOPPEMENT&#13;
VILLAGEOIS (FDV)&#13;
I. CONTEXTE&#13;
Le Projet national d'appui aux services agricoles (PNASA) du Togo a ete prepare par ia&#13;
Banque mondiale depuis janvier 1995. II vise, a travers une meilleure organisation des&#13;
producteurs et des groupes sociaux, une amelioration de la foumiture de services et intrants et&#13;
l'incitation pour une meilleure commercialisation, a l'augmentation de la productivite des&#13;
exploitations agricoles, F'amelioration des conditions de vie et la reduction de la pauvrete en&#13;
milieu rural.&#13;
Ces objectifs generaux devraient etre atteints grace a la mise en oeuvre de quatres&#13;
composantes principales:&#13;
i)    Appui aux services agricoles;&#13;
ii)    Renforcement de la recherche agricole;&#13;
iii)    Operations pilotes de credit rural; et&#13;
iv)    Assistance au Ministere du developpement rural.&#13;
Le cout total du Projet est evalue a 50,9 millions d'USD pour une periode de 5 ans. La&#13;
Banque mondiale, en tant que Chef de file, finance 25,0 millions d'USD, alors que la part du&#13;
Gouvernement s'eleve a 7,4 millions d'USD. Une partie des formations (1,2 million d'USD) est&#13;
supportee par le PNUD, tandis que la participation des organisations professionnelles&#13;
economiques agricoles (OPEA) couvrira 2,4 millions d'USD. Le reste devra etre finance par&#13;
d'autres bailleurs de fonds interesses, japonais (1,5 million d'USD).&#13;
Le FIDA propose de participer a ce Projet en financant 20% des couts de toutes les&#13;
composantes, avec l'objectif principal d'orienter l'appui du Projet vers le groupe cible de petits&#13;
producteurs, les femmes, les jeunes et les ruraux pauvres. Afin d'atteindre cet objectif, qui&#13;
correspond parfaitement a la politique du Gouvernement togolais et a la nouvelle strategie de la&#13;
Banque mondiale (qui cible sa plus grande implication dans la lutte contre la pauvrete rurale),&#13;
des missions d'appuis r6guliers d'un(e) consultant(e) en "Agriculture familiale et allegement de&#13;
la pauvretd rurale", specifiquement orientees vers ces aspects, ont et inclues parmi les activites&#13;
du Projet. Dans le meme but, le PNASA financera les parts des groupes cibles au capital social&#13;
de l'Institution de conseil et d'appui technique (ICAT) et l'Institut togolais de recherche agricole&#13;
(ITRA) pour que les groupes economiquement les plus faibles bien que les plus nombreux&#13;
puissent representer leurs interets dans la gestion et la programmation des deux institutions.&#13;
Enfin, un Fonds de developpement villageois (FDV) sera initie en faveur des groupes de petits&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-75-                                 Annex 12&#13;
Page 2 of 5&#13;
producteurs, des femmes et des jeunes, principalement dans les villages hors cultures de rente,&#13;
pour financer des amrnagements et infrastructures communautaires.&#13;
L'objectif de la presente Annexe est de donner les principales caracteristiques du Fonds&#13;
de developpement villageois (FDV) pour lequel le PNASA contribuera a son initiation avec un&#13;
montant de 220 000 USD et qui sera ouvert A toutes autres contributions nationales et/ou&#13;
etrangeres. Ce document devra servir de base pour l'elaboration (avec un appui exterieur si&#13;
necessaire) du manuel de procedures par l'ONG choisie pour la gestion du Fonds pendant une&#13;
periode interimaire de deux ans.&#13;
II. PRINCIPALES CARACTERISTIQUES DU FONDS&#13;
L'objectif du Fonds sera: (a) d'atteindre les communautes de petits producteurs hors&#13;
culture de rente, les femmes, les jeunes et les pauvres; (b) r6pondre A des besoins reels&#13;
d'investissements communautaires exprimes par les groupes sociaux vises; (c) contribuer A&#13;
I'am6lioration de leur niveau de vie; et (d) faciliter les actions de vulgarisation agricole.&#13;
Les domaines d'investissement prevus (liste non exhaustive) seront lies A: (a) la&#13;
gestion rationnelle et durable des terroirs: realisation de plans d'amenagement de terroirs,&#13;
amenagement de bas-fonds et de mares, protection des ressources naturelles communales,&#13;
pepinieres de reboisement villageois; et (b) I'amelioration des infrastructures communes:&#13;
magasins de stockage d'intrants, greniers villageois, salles d'alphabetisation, cases de sante,&#13;
petits ouvrages de desenclavement, puits/forages, amenagement des marches villageois.&#13;
Les activites du Fonds debuteront par une campagne d'information sur: (a) les&#13;
objectifs du Fonds; (b) les possibilites d'acceder au Fonds (seules les organisations villageoises&#13;
regroupant les groupes cibles ou une majorite de populations cibles pourront y acceder pour la&#13;
r6alisation d'investissements d'inter8t commun); (b) les criteres de selection des participants&#13;
(adhesion aux conditions du FDV, organisation dynamique du groupe, volontge exprime par la&#13;
majorite du groupe, pas de conflits majeurs entre les groupes au niveau du village, etc.); (c) la&#13;
prdsentation des propositions sur des formulaires prepares a cet effet par le FDV; et (d) les&#13;
possibilites d'appui (ONG, ICAT, ITRA, etc.) dans ce domaine.&#13;
La selection des demandes de participation aux actions du Fonds se fera des procedures&#13;
transparentes, simples et decentralisees au niveau des regions avec la participation des OPEA des&#13;
groupes cibles prioritaires. Pour les actions choisies, l'ICAT (I'ONG, l'OPEA) aidera les&#13;
villages (organisations villageoises) dans l'elaboration d'un document simple de faisabilite de&#13;
l'action selon une procedure d6finie dans le manuel de procedures.&#13;
La mise en oeuvre des actions sera participative, les collectivites devront decider du&#13;
choix des investissements A realiser, des technologies utilisees, des modalites de realisation des&#13;
travaux (par contrat avec de tacherons, des ONG ou autres entrepreneurs prives) et du suivi des&#13;
travaux. La gestion et l'entretien des infrastructures seront a la charge des communautes&#13;
villageoises. Un cahier de charge precisera les modalit6s de gestion et d'acces aux installations&#13;
communautaires realisees au moyen du FDV.&#13;
Les cofits des investissements prevus seront partages entre la participation propre des&#13;
beneficiaires de 30% en monnaie, materiaux de construction, batiments et/ou main-d'oeuvre et&#13;
70% qui seront couverts par le Fonds (subventions). Ce partage des contributions pourra etre&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-76-&#13;
Annex 12&#13;
Page 3 of 5&#13;
modifie de commun accord avec les beneficiaires et d'autres bailleurs de fonds travaillant selon&#13;
une approche semblable dans la zone et assurant dans tous les cas une participation minimum des&#13;
beneficiaires.&#13;
Le deboursement du Fonds sera decentralise au niveau des regions. Pour la realisation&#13;
des actions concretes au niveau des villages, des contrats seront signes entre le Fonds et une&#13;
association (groupement, organisation economique ou sociale) pour preciser les modalites et les&#13;
conditions de mise en oeuvre et de d6boursement des tranches successives des montants&#13;
accordes. Un compte sera ouvert a la banque la plus proche au nom de l'association pour la&#13;
realisation de l'investissement. Pour chaque tranche successive de financement, le suivi devra&#13;
evaluer l'avancement des travaux en accord avec les termes du contrat; l'ordre de deboursement&#13;
devra etre contre-signe par deux personnes autorisees dont une, representera la communaute.&#13;
Les redevances et une eventuelle contribution des beneficiaires pour la maintenance et le&#13;
renouvellement des investissements seront versees sur un compte ouvert au nom d'une&#13;
organisation villageoise et constituant un fonds de roulement villageois pour aider i la&#13;
perennisation des investissements.&#13;
La gestion du Fonds sera initiee par une ONG, puis apres une periode interimaire de&#13;
deux ans sera transferee aux organisations sociales etlou socioprofessionelles (OPEA)&#13;
regroupant les petits producteurs hors cultures de rente, les femmes et les jeunes. Pendant cette&#13;
periode interimaire aura lieu la consolidation, le renforcement et la formation des organisations&#13;
ciblees par les activites du Fonds; elles seront aussi initiees a la mise en oeuvre des&#13;
investissements et la gestion du Fonds.&#13;
L'ONG devra repondre a un certain nombre de criteres: (a) travailler au moins 5 ans au&#13;
Togo dans l'appui au developpement rural; (b) avoir une experience dans la formation et la mise&#13;
en oeuvre des micro-r6alisations en milieu rural; (c) avoir une experience dans la gestion&#13;
financiere et la tenue des cahiers des charges; et (d) avoir actuellement des activites au Togo&#13;
pour diminuer le cofit de l'assistance au FDV. Sur la base du present document le MAEP fera un&#13;
premier choix de trois ONG repondant le mieux a la realisation des objectifs du Fonds. Une&#13;
ONG sera selectionnee avec I'aide de l'ICAT et de l'ITRA et du (de la) consultant(e) en&#13;
"Agriculture familiale et allegement de la pauvrete rurale". Elle devra preparer (avec un appui&#13;
exterieur si n6cessaire) dans un d6lai de deux mois la version provisoire du manuel de&#13;
procedures qui sera envoy6 aux bailleurs de fonds (IDA et FIDA) pour commentaires avant la&#13;
finalisation. Le document sera finalise lors de la seconde mission d'appui technique avec le(a)&#13;
consultant(e) en "Agriculture familiale et all6gement de la pauvrete rurale".  La version&#13;
definitive, y inclus la proposition de couts de gestion de l'ONG pour la periode interimaire et le&#13;
programme pour la premiere annee, sera envoyee pour approbation a l'IDA et au FIDA deux&#13;
mois plus tard. DMs l'approbation du FIDA, la premiere tranche sera versee sur un compte&#13;
bancaire. Le FDV devrait 8tre operationnel en seconde annee du PNASA.&#13;
Durant la periode de 3 ans de la mise en oeuvre des actions financees par le FDV, le&#13;
FIDA et le cas echeant, d'autres contribuables (bailleurs de fonds bi et multi-lateraux desireux de&#13;
contribuer aux investissements de base en milieu rural) au financement du fonds recevront des&#13;
rapports semi-annuals d'activites.  Les activit6s seront aussi suivies et 6valuees par le(a)&#13;
consultant(e) qui formnulera durant ses mission au Togo (apres discussions avec l'ONG et les&#13;
OPEA) des recommandations pour la poursuite des activites du Fonds. L'Unite de suivi et&#13;
evaluation de l'ICAT et des representants des groupes sociaux concernes, seront aussi impliques&#13;
dans le processus.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-77-                               Annex 12&#13;
Page 4 of 5&#13;
III. PREPARATION DU MANUEL DE PROCEDURES DU FONDS DE&#13;
DEVELOPPEMENT VILLAGEOIS (FDV)&#13;
Le manuel de procedures du Fonds devra contenir:&#13;
A.    Description des informations sur le Fonds, destinees a une large diffusion a&#13;
travers les services d'appui au monde rural et les media:&#13;
*     Objectifs du Fonds&#13;
*     Domaines d'investissement possible&#13;
*     Principes de financement (couit minimum/maximum, participation&#13;
villageoise, subvention du PNASA)&#13;
*     Conditions de participation&#13;
*     Presentation de candidatures&#13;
*     Selection des candidatures&#13;
*     Preparation de la documentation pour des actions (investissements)&#13;
*     Gestion des realisations&#13;
B.    Domaines d'investissement:&#13;
* Gestion rationnelle et durable des terroirs villageois: plans&#13;
d'amenagement de terroirs, amenagement de bas-fonds et de mares,&#13;
protection des ressources communales, amenagement des espaces&#13;
intervillageois, pepinieres de reboisement villageois, etc.&#13;
*     Amdlioration des infrastructures communes: magasins de stockage&#13;
d'intrants, greniers villageois, salles d'alphabetisation, cases de sante,&#13;
petits ouvrages de desenclavement, puits/forages, amenagement des&#13;
marches villageois, etc.&#13;
C.    Principes de financement des investissements:&#13;
*     Financement minimum et maximum&#13;
*     Participation villageoise: monnaie, materiaux de construction, main-&#13;
d'oeuvre, transport&#13;
*     Subvention du projet&#13;
D.    Conditions de participation:&#13;
Appartenance a un groupe cible (petits producteurs, femmes, jeunes,&#13;
ruraux pauvres, hors culture de rente)&#13;
Adhesion volontaire aux conditions du FDV&#13;
Organisation dynamique du(des) groupe(s) cible(s)&#13;
Pas de conflits majeurs entre les groupes et les autres villageois&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-78-&#13;
Annex 12&#13;
Page 5 of 5&#13;
E.    Presentation et selection des candidatures:&#13;
*     Demande par ecrit en fran9ais ou en langue nationale sur imprime&#13;
prepare a cet occasion par le Fonds&#13;
*     Investissement prioritaire pour le groupe&#13;
*     Attestation d'un agent de vulgarisation sur la validite de la demande&#13;
*     Correspondance avec les conditions d'adhesion&#13;
F.    Preparation de la documentation pour les actions (investissements):&#13;
*     Document simplifie de faisabilite selon modele prepare a cet effet par le&#13;
fonds&#13;
*     Possibilite d'appui de la part de l'ICAT, de l'ITRA, des ONG&#13;
G.    Approche (participative) pour le choix des actions, des technologies et de la mise&#13;
en oeuvre:&#13;
*     Choix des actions (investissement)&#13;
*     Choix des technologies adaptdes&#13;
*     Modalitds de mise en oeuvre&#13;
H.    Contrat entre le Fonds et les communautes pour un investissement, sur imprime&#13;
prepare ia cet effet par le Fonds&#13;
1.    Contrat pour la realisation des travaux entre la Communaute, les services prives,&#13;
ONG, etc., sur imprime prepare a cet effet par le Fonds&#13;
J.    Deboursements des fonds par le Projet&#13;
K.    Deboursement des fonds pour les investissements villageois&#13;
L.    Suivi et evaluation des investissements villageois:&#13;
-     OPEA et ONG (pour la periode interimaire)&#13;
*     Groupes cibles concernes&#13;
M.    Fonds de roulement villageois:&#13;
*     Entretien des investisssements&#13;
*     Renouvellement des investissements&#13;
N.    Financement et gestion du FDV&#13;
0.    Suivi et evaluation du FDV&#13;
*     LePNASA&#13;
*     L'ICAT&#13;
*     Le MAEP&#13;
P.    Rapports&#13;
R.    Litiges.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-79-&#13;
Annex 13&#13;
Page I of I&#13;
REPUBLIC OF TOGO&#13;
NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SERVICES SUPPORT PROJECT&#13;
PROJECT DOCUMENTATION&#13;
PREPARATORY STUDIES:&#13;
1. FAO, 1994/1995: Preparation du Plan de restructuration des institutions rurales (PRIR) (Projet FAO/TCP/TOG/4.)&#13;
2. MAEPET, FAO, mars 1995: Proposition de politique agricole.&#13;
3. Banque Mondiale/ MAEPET (P. Debouvry), 1995: Etude du dispositif de formation agricole.&#13;
4. MAEPET, BM, PVA (Mme. A. J. Atchikiti et Mme. E.V.Womitso); mai 1994: Role des femmes et les moyens de leur&#13;
intdgration dans les services de vulgarisation.&#13;
5. FAO/CP, Banque Mondiale, mars 1995: (ICR). Agricultural Extension project (cr. 1808-TO&#13;
6. MAEPET/DVA, avril 1995: Guide de la vulgarisation au Togo. (Atakpame avril 1995).&#13;
7. ISNAR, mai 1995: Diagnostic de la recherche agricole.&#13;
8. MAEPET, juin 1995: Declaration de politique de la recherche agricole.&#13;
9. Direction de la recherche agricole, octobre 1995: Preparation de la composante Recherche agricole (version provisoire).&#13;
10. SAFECO, avril 1995: Inventaire et diagnostic des institutions financieres en milieu rural.&#13;
11. SOCODEVI, SYNORSEC et FUCEC, octobre 1995: Propositions pour la composante de credit mutuel rural.&#13;
12. CESAO/FONGTO, avril 1995: Evaluation de la capacite institutionnelle des ONG en milieu rural.&#13;
13. MAEPET/ Banque Mondiale (J.P. Koffi et M. Foli), juin 1995: problemes fonciers en milieu rural au Togo.&#13;
14. Analyse de la ldgislation cooperative.&#13;
15. (IFDC) le systeme de vente des intrants et les propositions de privatisation.&#13;
16. Le ddsengagement de l'Etat de 1'exdcution des infrastructures.&#13;
17. Les contraintes a l'extension de la traction animale et propositions operationnelles.&#13;
18. Les strategies paysannes dans l'Ouest Togo.&#13;
19. Le processus de privation des ranchs.et de la fonction veterinaire.&#13;
20. L'amelioration de la transformation des produits agricoles.&#13;
WORKING PAPER:&#13;
1. Vulgarisation agricole&#13;
2. Crddit rural mutuel&#13;
3. Ressources humaines&#13;
4. Mise en oeuvre du Projet national d'appui aux services agricoles&#13;
5. Gestion&#13;
6. Aspectsjuridiques et institutionnels&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-  BURKINA FASO                       .r                               MALI&#13;
A'                       C                      ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~NIGER&#13;
-11B                     7'-t       -                                                    ,&gt;&lt;  _, K                 &#13;
T NE- ,N                                                                j&#13;
DAANy?EN'B0N                                                             URKINA       X&lt;&#13;
.       $                 M&gt;AonW o CtJ' .D AAFASO                                                \   &gt;&#13;
r ,T4     N      D j o  c' 5 R  E   9---=-? ---   -  $7&#13;
I., Tandjouareo*; ., ;             I -t                  Jv-~-.y t                                 BENIN7&#13;
*N\.    w;);~    1t __     _ i                                               S              1'   '       NIGERIA&#13;
C N           N A  r !  A               B  E  N   I N             ,     /  GHANA  I&#13;
Of T 1 TGoo   i    N                                    0&gt;                0 L&#13;
'L,                                                           .0g  )     ,!         o i=          \&#13;
I ,(1 SOn),,J ,A,  &lt;c  i  H 0 f =                             - to'-&#13;
.~ ~~~~~/ N2   .N                                              /    'cWfa0_  ;X gff Gwneoy                ~~~&#13;
10~~~~~~~~~~~~~~N&#13;
I      KERANT$  , K                                    2-&#13;
GHANA                                                                                     T /  K,     OGO&#13;
.ANK?E             O?UrrirOLcB,3rN        NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL SUPPORT&#13;
G .. Gueri+wUNAO-                o  I              SERVICES PROJECT (PNASA)&#13;
\   1   . Y'  b  _ rt.SNch   iPROJET NATIONAL D'APPUI AUX&#13;
}  p- 7"9-,SA R ARAIKOy4A   $ z                                SERVICES AGRICOLES&#13;
&gt; AiSA                           IMPLANTATION OF THE ICAT&#13;
'T h00 ,,2.iS$AR    !  ) '--- o   - ,.IMPLANTATION DE L'ICAT&#13;
oBASSAR    _    550t1             o&#13;
C ___ ci 9 ~ 5,$sor ,.e *      K                          -                           &lt;, t,, &lt;JO =A. MAIN ROADS&#13;
N  '  o'~~~~~'~~   (/~~ \~~~~N' ~ROUTES PRINCI PALES&#13;
_,                                         N . g    N    /  X   /     .-   \  -_   - SELECTED SECONDARY ROADS  9'&#13;
- 9' i   &lt;- 2)  (  ( / f r ' | SOKODE-   hombu )                 ROUTES SECONDAIRES CHOISIES&#13;
9~~~~~~~~~~~~~                                              ( ~       &lt;~zMAIN RIVERS                       r&#13;
TCi  OUDJG .  /   '  \   /  .COURS D'EAU IMPORTANTS                   |&#13;
ooo   9  -- - ISOHYETS IN MILLIMETERS&#13;
-/iS   {    4  . ' i--  j  T C -IA M B A !  fSOHYETES EN MILLIMETRES&#13;
o    SELECTED TOWNS&#13;
/ \  io                                   K A  , (  \_&lt;  i  !  T0   VILLES CHOISIES&#13;
1          TQ{Q[4otouBo CA-E N T IIA L    -                *    SECTOR CAPITALS&#13;
N /':-'         .\                 (Sohoboua  &gt;            1". &lt;                CHEFS-LIEUX DE SECTEUR&#13;
,&gt;                                              Sotoolooo  5           'N \, iREGION CAPITALS&#13;
/ -   0 1  g    oA   |   '     CHEFS-UEUX DE REGION&#13;
y --                   =! o'~~~- 1__                __ z- =-.L   *3 NATIONAL CAPITAL j&#13;
&gt;   ,    v )   l BliHaR             '          I) i              ~~~~~~~      ~      ~     ~~~~~~~CAPITALE  &#13;
SECTOR BOUNDARIES&#13;
C               \r       Rt BDJTTA J         EST-MONO)                 &#133; LIMITES DE SECTEURS           ?&#13;
LoJ9obo &lt;,           QihN5 8aagBISk   g                     | -REGION BOUNDARIES&#13;
_83i                                                     &lt;s.           *'t,"~ \   .    *t  \ _1 p    j   iMITES DE REGIONS&#13;
k E '&lt;  ,m  j ' c &gt;   -  &lt;S Efvooooooo   y0i,     ----INTERNATIONAL BOUNDARIES&#13;
y  (,'&gt;                                 \ r                     I A  ,FRONTitRES INTERNATIONALES&#13;
e     ,-  Nje -N                                                "                                               \.     7 ''--  ''  '  --' iA&#13;
500                                                                      ..d -yN                -&#13;
&gt;       /       'G A    WAWA            'r&#13;
-0-~~~~~~~0,'~~~~~~~N  -T,  _- ~ ~ ~     ~     ~     ~     ~    ~     -y 1  /- ht-0&#13;
&lt;N   NN&gt;         ,,  2                          ed   1i0-ATAKPAME   Nohr iofotmotion,Imdcowo &#13;
N C   &gt;                       AmIW&lt;   N                 Kl        /N                oot\ehismorodonot   &#13;
N_.              l      7   Iw TEAL Uj                    '  j               mkgtPY.oN#oyp, f,&#13;
D-oyi-Ap6yoie  A                                                  orooyoodorsomoet &#13;
4=S^;-\~~ ~ ~~                        ~~~~      IQFA                       ot-to' territory,t /i   h  &#13;
7" 0                                                                                                               7' \ ,'('--}-  r  I   &gt;&#13;
&lt;i--'-N -            /  +/  ti '   _-i,'-t 0 25 SO 75  1  OO -,  .  1500,&lt;X_&lt;  21    5        7 t      1&#13;
7~~~~~~~ ,_,0  T:.j&#13;
150  1    11 - -     ',                       I        II                 I  /&#13;
I                  ~~~~~~~KILOMETERS&#13;
00  A~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
7 ~~~~~~%7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IMAGING&#13;
Report No.:          16098   TO&#13;
Type:       A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="694635">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/08/694635/togo-national-agricultural-services-support-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/08/694635/togo-national-agricultural-services-support-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/08/694635/togo-national-agricultural-services-support-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1997/08/13/000009265_3971104184223/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1997/08/13/000009265_3971104184223/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>P897;2990</credit_no>
        <datestored>2001-04-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1997-08-13T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Togo - National Agricultural Services
            Support Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The National Agricultural Services
            Support Project's central objective is to improve
            living standards of farm households in Togo by increasing
            agricultural productivity and income, while placing greater
            emphasis on environmental protection. The project has five
            main components: 1) Agricultural services -the creation of a
            technical assistance and support institute responsible for
            providing improved extension services to farmers and support
            to farmer organizations; 2) Agricultural research -merging
            all existing research institutions into a newly-created,
            decentralized, autonomous, semi-private agricultural
            research institute; 3) Agricultural credit -implementing
            pilot grassroots savings and loans operations through
            selected nongovernmental organizations to test an approach
            for ensuring accessibility for small producers, including
            women; 4) Agricultural credit -a village development fund to
            finance small rural infrastructure; and 5) The Ministry of
            Agriculture, Livestock, and Fisheries (MAEP) -reorganizing
            this agency to build up its capacity in policy design,
            planning, programming, monitoring, control, and program evaluation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Togo - National Agricultural Services
            Support Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Togo - National Agricultural
            Services Support Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1997/08/694635/togo-national-agricultural-services-support-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>TG-Nat.Agriculture Serv -- P002891</projn>
        <docty>Staff Appraisal Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Agricultural Research,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Agriculture</teratopic>
        <count>Togo</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>West Africa!$!80474</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3971104184223</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Agricultural extension and research,Central government administration,Micro- and SME finance</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1997-2</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Agriculture</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agrarian structure; Agricultural credit;
            Agricultural income; Agricultural productivity; Agricultural
            research; Agricultural societies; Civil works; Environmental
            protection; Extension services; Institution building;
            Monitoring; Nongovernmental organizations; Producers;
            Project evaluation; Quality of life; Rural infrastructure;
            Savings &amp; loan associations; Technical assistance;
            Villages; Women in agriculture
            access to credit,AfDB,African Development
            Bank,Agricultural Development,Agricultural
            Extension,agricultural extension services,Agricultural
            Inputs,agricultural productivity,Agricultural
            Products,Agricultural Research,agricultural
            systems,agricultural technologies,Agricultural
            Training,Agriculture,Agronomy,animal health,Animal
            Husbandry,animals,aquaculture,arable land,AUDITS,balance of
            payments,bank loans,beef,Cacao,cash
            crops,cassava,cattle,Central
            Bank,cereals,Cocoa,Coffee,Coffee
            production,commodity,Cooperatives,Cotton,cotton
            cultivation,cotton growing,cotton production,cotton
            sector,cotton zone,cowpeas,CPI,crop,cropping,cropping
            systems,Crops,cultivated land,cultivation,cultivation
            techniques,decentralization,deforestation,Devaluation,diet,diversified
            agriculture,ecological Zones,economic activity,ECONOMIC
            ANALYSIS,Economic Development,Economic Rate of
            Return,employment,environmental degradation,environmental
            protection,Equipment,Expenditures,export
            crops,exports,Extension
            Services,extensionists,FARM,farmer,farmer
            organizations,farmers,farmers organizations,Farming,FARMING
            SYSTEMS,Farms,fertilizer,fertilizers,Financial
            Management,financial resources,Financial Sector,fish,fish
            production,Fisheries,Fishing,Food Crops,food needs,Food
            Processing,food
            security,foodcrops,forestry,Forests,goats,government
            expenditures,grain,grazing,hectares of land,Human resource
            management,IFAD,imports,incomes,inefficiency,inflation,International
            Fund for Agricultural
            Development,lands,Livestock,maize,market
            prices,marketing,Microfinance,millet,natural
            pastures,Natural Resources,NGOs,oil palm,paddy,Palm
            Oil,pastures,peanuts,pesticides,plant
            production,plantations,population pressures,POTENTIAL
            YIELDS,poultry,poultry production,Present Value,private
            sector,production of cotton,Production Systems,Productivity
            increases,public services,Real GDP,Regional Agricultural
            Research,research centers,resource allocation,rice,Rice
            production,Rural Development,rural infrastructure,rural
            population,rural poverty,Savings,seed,seed
            cotton,seeds,sheep,small farmers,small producers,small
            ruminants,soil erosion,soil fertility,soil
            research,Soils,sorghum,SPAAR,statistical data,T&amp;V
            system,taxation,Technical Assistance,Textiles,UNDP,unfair
            competition,United Nations,United States Agency for
            International Development,USAID,vegetation,Village
            Communities,violence,Water Resources,watershed,watershed management,yams
        </keywd>
        <owner>AFT: ESSD 2 (AFTS2)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>West Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF040384-TOGO - NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL
            SERVICES PROJECT - RESTRUCTURATION OF PNA-,TF040383-TOGO - NATIONAL AGRICULTURAL
            SERVICES PROJECT - RESTRUCTURATION OF PNAS,TF039806-TOGO - RURAL DEVELOPMENT
            STRATEGY (PNASA)</trustfund>
        <repnb>16098</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Togo</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>