<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. T-7117-GZ&#13;
WEST BANK AND GAZA&#13;
PALESTINIAN EXPATRIATE PROFESSIONAL PROGRAM&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
May 14, 1997&#13;
Private Sector Development and Infrastructure Division&#13;
Country Department II&#13;
Middle East and North Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
(as of May 1997)&#13;
Currency Unit: New Israeli Sheqalim (NIS)&#13;
US$1.0 = NIS 3.35&#13;
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES&#13;
1 meter (m)        =   1.09 yards (yd)&#13;
1 m2               =   10.76 square feet&#13;
1 kilometer (km)    =   0.62 miles (mi)&#13;
1 km2              =   0.38 square miles&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
CBJ       =    Central Bank of Jordan&#13;
CG        =    Consultative Group&#13;
EAP       =    Emergency Assistance Program&#13;
EHRP      =    Education and Health Rehabilitation Project&#13;
ERP       =    Emergency Rehabilitation Project&#13;
GOI       =    Government of Israel&#13;
HF        =    Holst Fund&#13;
IDA       =    International Development Association&#13;
MOET      =    Ministry of Economy and Trade&#13;
MOF       =    Ministry of Finance&#13;
MOPIC    =    Ministry of Planning and International Cooperation&#13;
PA        =    Palestinian Authority&#13;
PECDAR  =    Palestinian Economic Council for Development and Reconstruction&#13;
PEPP      =    Palestinian Expatriate Professional Program&#13;
PLO       =    Palestine Liberation Organization&#13;
PMA       =    Palestine Monetary Authority&#13;
SC        =    Steering Committee&#13;
TA        =    Technical Assistance&#13;
TATF      =    Technical Assistance Trust Fund&#13;
TFGWB   =    Trust Fund for Gaza and West Bank&#13;
TOKTEN  =    Transfer of Knowledge through Expatriate Nationals&#13;
TS        =    Technical Secretariat&#13;
UNDP      =    United Nations Development Programme&#13;
WBG       =    West Bank and Gaza&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January 1 - December 31&#13;
Regional Vice President:          Kemal Dervi5, MNAVP&#13;
Program Manager:                  Odin Knudsen, MNCWG&#13;
Manager:                          Nigel Roberts, MNCWG&#13;
Division Chief:                   Alastair J. McKechnie, MN2PI&#13;
Task Manager:                     Robert A. Mertz, MN2PI&#13;
Peer Reviewer:                    Nimrod Raphaeli, OPRPG&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WEST BANK AND GAZA&#13;
PALESTINIAN EXPATRIATE PROFESSIONAL PROGRAM&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.  DETAILED PROJECT DESCRIPTION   ................................. 1&#13;
A. Origin of the PEPP Project Concept ................................. 1&#13;
B.  Institutional Setting  ................................. 2&#13;
C.  Project Objectives  ................................  2&#13;
D. Project Cost and Financing ................................. 3&#13;
E.  Main Conditions of the Trust Fund Credit ............................. 6&#13;
F.  Risks and Risk Alleviation Measures  ................................ 6&#13;
11. PROJECT ADMINISTRATION AND IMPLEMENTATION .                            .                  8&#13;
A. Project Management and Organization.                                                  8&#13;
B. Procurement .10&#13;
C. Disbursement .10&#13;
D. Accounts and Auditing .11&#13;
E. Monitoring and Evaluation .11&#13;
F. Project Supervision Plan .11&#13;
Appendix I. Key Performance Indicators .13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WEST BANK AND GAZA&#13;
PALESTINIAN EXPATRIATE PROFESSIONAL PROGRAM&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
I. DETAILED PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
A.    Origin of the PEPP Project Concept&#13;
1.1   Since the beginning of the technical assistance (TA) program funded by the Technical Assistance&#13;
Trust Fund (TATF) in early 1994, Palestinian ministries and agencies have frequently requested financial&#13;
support to bring expatriate Palestinian professionals from a broad range of specializations to assist various&#13;
government departments. To meet this need in the case of one key economic agency, a small amount&#13;
of TATF funds were allocated in 1995 to provide relocation allowances for Jordanians of Palestinian&#13;
origin who were being seconded by the Central Bank of Jordan to work with the Palestine Monetary&#13;
Authority (PMA) for a period of one or two years as departmental managers or senior technical experts&#13;
in bank supervision. Knowledge of this pilot program for the PMA quickly elicited requests from the&#13;
Ministry of Finance (MOF) and other ministries for similar support.&#13;
1.2   Several dozen other Palestinian expatriates have come to the WBG on short-term advisory&#13;
assignments through the Transfer Of Knowledge Through Expatriate Nationals (TOKTEN) program,&#13;
managed by the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) and the Ministry of Planning and&#13;
International Cooperation (MOPIC). Frequently the sponsoring agency has asked the individual to stay&#13;
for a longer period to manage and build the department or program which he/she has designed. Since&#13;
these agencies usually do not have dedicated project resources (and wish to save the time involved in&#13;
preparing discrete project proposals), they have frequently asked the Bank for access to TATF funds to&#13;
cover the cost of longer term contracts for "graduates" of the TOKTEN program.&#13;
1.3    All of these requests had to be turned down for three reasons. First, TATF funds were&#13;
insufficient for this purpose and unsuited to this usage. Second, based on experience with the PMA and&#13;
TOKTEN, it was obvious that such a program would need to be professionally designed and managed,&#13;
with substantial, up-front institutional analysis, an institution-building orientation, an international,&#13;
competitive search process to identify the most suitable Palestinian candidates irrespective of their&#13;
location, and a competitive compensation program that could accommodate Palestinians coming from&#13;
moderate and higher income countries. Third, and most important, to be successful and to attract&#13;
external funding, such a program would have to be shielded effectively from the pressures surrounding&#13;
personnel recruitment. From experience, this would happen only if the project was professionally&#13;
managed by a qualified, independent company of recognized international stature, responsive to a multi-&#13;
ministerial body rather than to a single ministry or agency, and with independent oversight. Hence the&#13;
Palestinian Expatriate Professional Program (PEPP), as described in this annex, was developed gradually,&#13;
as a result of the lessons learned from the TATF and TOKTEN programs and in an effort to&#13;
accommodate the unpredictable and evolving operating environment.&#13;
1.4   The PEPP project concept was originally discussed in 1995 with the Palestinian Authority (PA)&#13;
and with the Palestinian private sector sponsors, a group of prominent Palestinian businessmen, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2                                                                         Technical Annex&#13;
Palestinian-Jordanian Follow Up Committee, who had become concerned about the need to strengthen&#13;
the professional capacity of Palestinian government agencies. It was quickly agreed to join forces to&#13;
prepare the project and the Follow-Up Commnittee pledged their financial support for the project in&#13;
September 1995. Since then, a representative of the Palestinian private sector has participated at every&#13;
significant step in project preparation, including pre-qualification of potential consulting firms to provide&#13;
project management, evaluation of the proposals received, and discussions with Dutch and Israeli&#13;
government representatives and the PA.&#13;
1.5   Subsequently, a project concept note was prepared and the project was included in the Core&#13;
Investment Program of the PA and presented to the Consultative Group (CG) for the WBG which met&#13;
in Paris in November 1995. However, beginning immediately after the CG meeting, there was a rapid&#13;
downward spiral in the political and security situation in the WBG, resulting in extremely tight travel&#13;
restrictions on movement between Gaza and the West Bank. This closure policy demonstrated that&#13;
agreements would be needed with the Government of Israel to ensure the free mobility of PEPP program&#13;
participants, or the effectiveness of the PEPP program would be compromised.&#13;
B.    Institutional Setting&#13;
1.6   The institutions to be assisted under this project are the ministries and agencies of the PA. The&#13;
PA encompasses 24 ministries and 21 autonomous agencies. By agreement, the project will focus during&#13;
the pilot phase on four or five key economic ministries and agencies, including the Ministries of Finance&#13;
(MOF), Planning and International Cooperation (MOPIC), Economy and Trade (MOET), Education&#13;
(MOE) and Health (MOH) and the Palestine Monetary Authority (PMA). In principle, the PEPP will&#13;
gradually expand its scope to include most ministries and agencies. The PEPP project will, however,&#13;
concentrate on high priority economic and financial management positions, specialized technical functions&#13;
and policy making units in each agency and only upon the senior management and technical positions in&#13;
those agencies. The ministries and agencies to be assisted by the project, and the priority positions to&#13;
be filled during each three-month period, will be identified in a rolling quarterly work plan which will&#13;
be prepared each quarter by the Technical Secretariat (TS).&#13;
C.    Project Objectives&#13;
1.7   The PEPP project is designed to achieve the following objectives: (i) institutional development:&#13;
(a) to strengthen the management and technical capabilities of ministries and agencies of the Palestinian&#13;
Authority; (b) for organizational units where the PEPP will recruit managers and senior technical&#13;
personnel, to advise on the appropriate organizational structure and the qualifications of the personnel&#13;
to be recruited; (c) to identify and recruit the most qualified Palestinian expatriate professionals to fill&#13;
targeted positions; (d) to establish and utilize a professional, transparent, competitive, international&#13;
recruitment process for such persons; and (e) to establish and apply an objective, transparent and fair&#13;
methodology for the payment of relocation allowances; (ii) capacity building: (a) to ensure that suitably&#13;
qualified individuals are identified and trained, primarily on-the-job, to take over the positions of the&#13;
PEPP program participants so that there is minimal disruption when they return to their countries of&#13;
domicile; and (b) to build a data base of Palestinian expatriates which can be used to recruit professionals&#13;
under the program and that can be used to maintain contact with the Palestinian diaspora once the project&#13;
has been completed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Technical Annex                                                                             3&#13;
1.8   It is important to place the objectives of the project in the broader context of the establishment&#13;
of a Palestinian government after 30 years of occupation. The project focuses on filling imnmediate gaps&#13;
in senior management and technical positions in the PA by recruiting skilled Palestinians from outside&#13;
the WBG. The project will seek to minimize the potential disruption from the departure of PEPP&#13;
participants, by seeking to ensure that trainable permanent WBG residents, with appropriate background&#13;
and skills, are identified to work with each new PEPP participant, learning on the job, with the possibility&#13;
of some short-term training.&#13;
D.    Project Cost and Einancing&#13;
1.9    Project Costs. The estimated cost of this project is US$9 million over a three-year period, as&#13;
summarized in the following table:&#13;
Foreign        Local&#13;
Component                                    Costs          Costs         Total&#13;
--------------- US$ Million -----------&#13;
Local salaries to PEPP personnel                           -0-            3.0           3.0&#13;
Relocation allowances to PEPP personnel                    4.5           -0-           4.5&#13;
Project management                                         1.5           -0-            1.5&#13;
Total                                              6.0             3.0          9.0&#13;
1.10   Local Salaries and Relocation Allowances. The cost of local salaries and hypothetical relocation&#13;
allowances is based on the actual salaries and relocation allowances currently being paid to senior&#13;
Jordanian personnel seconded to the PMA by the Central Bank of Jordan (CBJ). For budgeting purposes,&#13;
we have assumed that the average person engaged under the project would be paid an annual salary of&#13;
$20,000 and an annual relocation allowance of $30,000, slightly above the current level of salary and&#13;
relocation allowances being paid.' However, these levels would probably not be adequate to attract&#13;
individuals in higher paid positions and from higher income countries.&#13;
1.11   Table 1 shows an indicative range of relocation allowances which might apply to PEPP program&#13;
participants, calculated on the basis of a local senior management government salary in the WBG (first&#13;
column @ $18,000) and on the basis of "take-home" income in the present country of residence (columns&#13;
two, three and four). These allowances have been calculated on the basis of the World Bank's current&#13;
methodology for staff sent on overseas assignments. During the pilot phase the TS will assess the&#13;
methodologies utilized for relocation allowances by other international companies and institutions and will&#13;
develop a methodology that can be applied in a transparent and effective manner to Palestinian expatriates&#13;
coming from a large number of countries:&#13;
I/     Palestinian expatriates from Jordan currently seconded to the PMA as senior technical specialists, managers&#13;
and directors are being paid an annual salary of about $18,000 (which is about the same as their Jordanian&#13;
salaries) and an annual relocation allowance, calculated on international norms, of between $18,000 and&#13;
$24,000, a total of about $36,000 - $42,000. This is much less than foreign consultants are paid to work&#13;
in Palestine. The relocation allowance for Palestinians coming from higher wage areas, such as Western&#13;
Europe, North America and the Gulf, would probably be tied more to their opportunity cost (net take home&#13;
pay or some other comparator) and not to their governmental salary.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4                                                                      Technical Annex&#13;
Table 1: Calculation of Hypothetical Relocation Allowances&#13;
(US$)&#13;
Annual Salary **             $18,000      $50,000      $75,000     $100,000&#13;
Post Allowance&#13;
Assignment Allowance*       $2,500       $2,500       $2,500       $2,500&#13;
Hardship Allowance (15%)    $2,700       $7,500      $11,250      $15,000&#13;
Cost of Living (16.25%)     $2,925       $8,125      $12,188      $16,250&#13;
Subtotal                  $8,125      $18,125      $25,938      $33,750&#13;
Housing Allowance            $12,000      $12,000      $15,000      $15,000&#13;
Installation Expenses&#13;
Settling-in Grant*          $1,038       $2,885       $4,327       $5,769&#13;
Return to HQ grant*           $692       $1,923       $2,885       $3,846&#13;
Subtotal                  $1,731       $4,808       $7,212       $9,615&#13;
Grand Total - Individual     $21,856      $34,933      $48,150      $58,365&#13;
Family Allowance              $4,231       $7,308       $9,712      $12,115&#13;
Grand Total - Family        $26,087      $42,241      $57,862       $70,480&#13;
* family allowance would be double&#13;
** the three higher salary levels are assumed to be net of income tax in the country of current residence.&#13;
1.12  Proiect Management. The estimated cost of establishing and operating the TS over a three-year&#13;
period is US$1.5 million. Arthur Andersen subrnitted the winning proposal with a price of $2.0 million&#13;
over two years. The initial project proposal was based on a six-person international team, resident in&#13;
the WBG, with offices in Gaza and the West Bank managing a far larger program. However, the&#13;
operating environment has changed considerably from mid-1996 and the World Bank and other agencies&#13;
have encountered considerable operating difficulties, not to mention the substantial hardship imposed on&#13;
Palestinian individuals and organizations by the Israeli closures. Thus, the Bank, in December 1996,&#13;
redefined the project concept and requested that Arthur Andersen present a modified proposal based on&#13;
a smaller and non-resident professional team in order to substantially reduce the fixed costs and the use&#13;
of resident expatriate personnel. Instead the program will operate initially from abroad with a substantial&#13;
presence in the WBG whenever needed during the initial one-year pilot period. The cost of project&#13;
management for this phase is about $500,000, plus a 20 percent contingency. If all forty positions&#13;
targeted for the first year are filled, the cost per recruitment will be about $12,500 (excluding the&#13;
contingency), or about 25 percent of the average annual cash compensation. This amount is somewhat&#13;
below the normal cost of international recruitment (about one-third of the first year's cash compensation).&#13;
The unit cost is expected to decline somewhat in subsequent years since the intensive work required to&#13;
establish the operating policies and procedures and get the program going will not need to be repeated,&#13;
project management and the Steering Committee will have moved up the learning curve, and most of the&#13;
first year's recruits are expected to remain for a second year with little input from the TS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Technical Annex                                                                       5&#13;
1.13   Toward the end of the pilot period the effectiveness of the project will be reassessed and a basis&#13;
agreed for subsequent operation of the program. Given the risks inherent in the project, continued&#13;
operation is expected to be based on an approach that minimizes fixed costs and keeps expatriate&#13;
management personnel to the minimum required for efficient project management. The contract for the&#13;
remaining two-year period of the project will be negotiated at the end of the pilot phase, based on&#13;
adjustments to the project concept and operating policies and procedures which result from the first twelve&#13;
months of operations. It is anticipated that the project will be carried out with a lean team and with&#13;
continued attention to cost-effective implementation. The salaries of international and local staff are based&#13;
on current private sector salary levels and are expected to remain constant over the life of the project.&#13;
1.14   Financing Plan. Project funds are being provided by the Palestinian Authority, the Palestinian&#13;
private sector through the Welfare Association, a private, charitable NGO headquartered in&#13;
Geneva, Switzerland, and the IDA. The Palestinian private sector sponsors informed the World&#13;
Bank in September 1995 through the Jordanian-Palestinian Follow-Up Committee that they would provide&#13;
$4-5 million to the project on a grant basis. This commitment has been reconfirmed. A first tranche of&#13;
US$3 million will be contributed to the project at the outset. These funds will be administered by IDA.&#13;
The balance of the funds (US$1-2 million) would be contributed to match an equivalent amount of funds&#13;
from donors or the IDA if the project operates successfully and if additional funds are required to expand&#13;
or extend the project. One possible source of additional funds is the Dutch Government. A meeting is&#13;
scheduled at the end of May 1997 to consider a Dutch government funding commitment for the project.&#13;
In the event that additional donor funds are contributed to the project, the Palestinian Authority has&#13;
confirmed that it will contribute additional funds up to at least US$3 million to cover the local salaries&#13;
of the additional PEPP program participants. The PA would pay the local salaries of PEPP program&#13;
participants during the period of their contract. External funds would cover the cost of the relocation&#13;
allowances and the management contract with Arthur Andersen acting as the TS.&#13;
1.15  IDA funding would amount to US$3 million, one-third of the total project cost. IDA will finance&#13;
the management contract with Arthur Andersen during the pilot phase in order to reduce the risk to the&#13;
cofinanciers that their funds would not be put to productive use if the project did not go forward.&#13;
Palestinian private sector funds would finance relocation allowances only during the pilot phase.&#13;
Assuming successful extension of the contract to the full three-year project period, funding of the&#13;
management contract and relocation allowances would shift to a pari passu basis between the Welfare&#13;
Association and the IDA at that point so that equal disbursement of both funding sources is achieved and&#13;
maintained.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6                                                                        Technical Annex&#13;
Table 2: Project Costs and Financing Plan by Component&#13;
Foreign       Local       Total&#13;
Component                         Costs        Costs     Costs/Funding&#13;
---------------- (US$million) -------------------&#13;
Local Salaries                     0.0           3.0        3.0&#13;
-PA                                -             3.0        3.0&#13;
Relocation Allowances              4.5           -          4.5&#13;
-IDA                               1.9           -          1.9&#13;
-Welfare Association               2.6           -          2.6&#13;
Project Management                 1.5           -          1.5&#13;
-IDA                               1.1           -          1.1&#13;
-Welfare Association               0.4           -          0.4&#13;
Total Project Cost and Funding     6.0           3.0        9.0&#13;
-PA                                0.0           3.0        3.0&#13;
-IDA                               3.0           -          3.0&#13;
-Welfare Association*              3.0           -          3.0&#13;
* IDA-administered&#13;
E.    Main Conditions of the Trust Fund Credit&#13;
1.16   The Trust Fund Credit would be extended for a period of 40 years, with 10 years' grace, under&#13;
standard IDA terms. The following conditions of board presentation have been met: (a) negotiation of&#13;
the project management agreement for the pilot period between the PA Ministry of Finance and Arthur&#13;
Andersen; and (b) negotiation of a Trust Fund Contribution Agreement between the Palestinian private&#13;
sector sponsors (represented by the Welfare Association) and IDA as Administrator of such funds. The&#13;
Contribution Agreement will be signed once the Board of the Welfare Association has given its approval,&#13;
expected at their next Board meeting on May 25, 1997.&#13;
F.    Risks and Risk Alleviation Measures&#13;
1.17   Risks. There are substantial political and operational risks which the project design has tried to&#13;
address. These risks include: (a) continuation of severe Israeli travel restrictions on Palestinian residents&#13;
and expatriates, particularly concerning travel between the West Bank and Gaza, thereby limiting their&#13;
mobility and effectiveness and discouraging their continued employment; (b) pressures to deviate from&#13;
what is intended to be an independent and transparent recruitment process; and (c) high turnover among&#13;
recruited expatriate professionals because of difficult living and working conditions, especially in Gaza.&#13;
These risks and the project's proposed methods of risk minimization are described in the following&#13;
paragraphs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Technical Annex                                                                       7&#13;
1.18  Mobility and Effectiveness. The political environment for the proposed PEPP program has been&#13;
uncertain, especially since late 1995. Palestinians seconded to the PMA and financed under the TATF&#13;
have continued to encounter serious obstacles to their freedom of movement which have negatively&#13;
impacted their overall effectiveness. Under such circumstances, the World Bank and the other sponsors&#13;
of the PEPP have questioned whether or not we could establish a sufficient basis to proceed with this&#13;
program without explicit assurances of travel mobility in advance from the GOI. Following recent&#13;
conversations with our fellow sponsors, senior officials of the PA and senior representatives of the GOI,&#13;
we have decided that the need for the managerial expertise and experience which the PEPP program is&#13;
intended to provide is so critical that we must move ahead, even if we cannot obtain ironclad assurances&#13;
in advance that participants will have the mobility necessary to be fully effective in their work. We have&#13;
been informed by officials of the GOI that they will provide multiple entry visas and travel permits&#13;
ensuring free mobility between the West Bank and Gaza for PEPP program participant during the period&#13;
of their contract (including extension of that contract) so long as they can be assured by the PA that the&#13;
individuals in the program will abide by the terms of their visas. Mutually acceptable commitments and&#13;
detailed operating policies and procedures will be worked out during the pilot phase.&#13;
1.19   Fixed Cost Risk Minimization - Pilot Phase. Rather than waiting for the current uncertainty&#13;
in the West Bank/Gaza to be resolved before moving ahead with the project, we think it prudent to adopt&#13;
a flexible approach and start the PEPP program on a pilot basis. Rather than undertaking considerable&#13;
fixed costs at the beginning by moving expatriate consultants to the WBG, it seems more cost-effective&#13;
to operate initially from abroad. This would get the program going but minimize the possible financial&#13;
risks of substantial fixed costs in the event that the operating environment proved to be unsustainable.&#13;
Such an approach seems likely to reduce the substantial, up-front overheads embedded in the original&#13;
project design and project proposal when an improving political environment was anticipated. At the&#13;
Bank's request, the consultants prepared a revised proposal planning to start the project with a one-year&#13;
long pilot period during which the consultants would work largely from abroad. The project manager&#13;
and other professional staff would make periodic visits to carry out the work required on the ground.&#13;
Recruitment and other activities could be implemented largely outside the WBG. Back-stopping support&#13;
would be provided by the consultants' local offices.&#13;
1.20   During the pilot phase, the consultants would focus on recruiting persons to fill a first batch of&#13;
25-40 key positions in a small number of key economic ministries (the Ministries of Finance, Economy&#13;
and Trade, Planning and International Cooperation, Education, Health and the Palestine Monetary&#13;
Authority). These individuals would constitute a test group to establish the internal operating systems&#13;
and procedures of the PEPP program and the operating modalities of visas and travel permission with&#13;
the GOI. We plan an operational review toward the end of the pilot phase to determine what changes&#13;
might be required to adapt to the lessons learned in those first few months. If the operating environment&#13;
turns out to be unfavorable, we would make whatever adjustments were deemed necessary, including -&#13;
in the extreme - shutting down the program.&#13;
1.21  Independent Recruitment Process. In the highly charged atmosphere of the WBG, it will be&#13;
difficult to set up and operate a project to recruit managers and technical specialists for the government&#13;
in a transparent, independent and apolitical manner. This has made it difficult to identify any one&#13;
counterpart agency for the project which will satisfy other beneficiary agencies. However, the sponsors&#13;
agree that unless the recruitment process is insulated from politics, the risks are high that political&#13;
considerations will subvert the process. They have said that they would be unwilling to use their funds&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8                                                                       Technical Annex&#13;
unless the independence and integrity of the process is assured. The acceptance by the Palestinian&#13;
Authority of the project concept and the proposed independent operating structure being established, as&#13;
described in the Memorandum of the President and the Technical Annex, was confirmed during&#13;
negotiations. The commitment of the PA to the principle of independent project operation has also been&#13;
confirmed in a letter to IDA from the Minister of Finance on behalf of the PA. We will also rely on the&#13;
SC and the project manager (the TS) to remain apolitical and to maintain the integrity of the recruitment&#13;
process. Finally, IDA will conduct thorough due diligence in monitoring project implementation at key&#13;
points as outlined in paragraph 14 of the Memorandum of the President.&#13;
1.22  "Interference." in Domestic Affairs. There may be concerns that an independent recruitment&#13;
process and close supervision of the consultant selection process by IDA could constitute interference in&#13;
the selection of senior Palestinian government officials. There may also be concerns that relocation&#13;
allowances give the providers of those funds a call on the loyalty of those individuals. This risk gives&#13;
added strength to the importance of a transparent and professional recruitment and selection process&#13;
insulated from politics, to the need for an explicit endorsement of the project concept and approach from&#13;
the PA prior to Board presentation, and to close monitoring of implementation by IDA. The fact that&#13;
the final choice of the individual to be contracted will, in all cases, rest solely with the Minister of the&#13;
specific Ministry should reduce this concern.&#13;
II. PROJECT ADMINISTRATION AND IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
A.    Project Management and Organization&#13;
2.1   The project would be implemented by the Ministry of Finance on behalf of the PA. A Steering&#13;
Committee, chaired by the Minister of Finance, and consisting of the Ministers of Economy and Trade,&#13;
and Planning and International Cooperation, and two non-governmental representatives, will be&#13;
established to supervise project implementation. At least one representative of the Palestinian private&#13;
sector would participate in the project as a member of the Steering Committee. The SC is expected to&#13;
meet monthly to review project progress against the quarterly work plans, to recommend modifications&#13;
or technical improvements in design and implementation, to give the SC's approval of the prequalified&#13;
candidates and those selected by the ministries, and to approve the new quarterly work plan.&#13;
2.2    Day-to-day project management would be contracted to Arthur Andersen on behalf of the Steering&#13;
Committee. This management consulting firm would act as the Technical Secretariat (TS) for the project,&#13;
with the responsibility of establishing and operating a transparent, independent process to identify and&#13;
recruit well qualified Palestinian expatriate professionals to fill specific senior positions. The operations&#13;
of the TS have been thoroughly described in paragraph 9 of the Memorandum of the President.&#13;
2.3   The PA would be responsible for all matters regarding the contracting of the individual PEPP&#13;
participants and payment for their services. Funds would be transferred by the Bank to the PA for&#13;
payments on a three-month advance basis, subject to confirmation that the individual was performing&#13;
satisfactorily. Timely payment of local salaries and relocation allowances, bookkeeping and related&#13;
administrative tasks would be the responsibility of the Ministry of Finance. Agreement to these&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Technical Annex                                                                       9&#13;
arrangements was confirmed at negotiations. The MOF will appoint an individual to assume these&#13;
responsibilities as the Ministry's project manager and counterpart to the TS.&#13;
2.4   Suitable office space and secretarial support for the TS will be provided, at cost, in the local&#13;
offices of Arthur Andersen in Gaza and the West Bank. The Arthur Andersen team consists of employees&#13;
from their Washington, D.C., Saudi Arabian and Jordanian offices. One specialist from Public&#13;
Administration Associates, a Washington-based firm specializing in public administration development&#13;
in developing countries, is also a member of the core team of the project. For the pilot period, these&#13;
individuals will travel to the WBG as needed. A data base manager will be hired locally. Should these&#13;
project management arrangements prove to be inadequate at the time of the performance review toward&#13;
the end of the pilot phase, the PA would take such measures as may be agreed with Arthur Andersen and&#13;
IDA to adjust project management satisfactorily. In addition, the following actions were agreed at&#13;
negotiations:&#13;
(a)   the PA confirmed its commitment to maintain the management contract with Arthur&#13;
Andersen on a mutually satisfactory basis between the parties during the project period&#13;
and will agree with IDA in case of any significant changes in the organization, staffing&#13;
and responsibilities of the TS; and&#13;
(b)    operating policies and procedures covering international recruitment, the methodology for&#13;
calculating and paying relocation allowances, and day-to-day management of the project&#13;
will be recommended by the TS during the pilot phase and agreed by the Steering&#13;
Committee and IDA. Financial procedures to be followed by the PA in utilizing and&#13;
auditing project funds, acceptable to IDA, will be adopted by the PA by the end of&#13;
August 1997.&#13;
2.5    At negotiations, the PA confirmed that:&#13;
(a)   the TS will prepare a quarterly work plan for each three-month period indicating which&#13;
ministries are to be assisted and which positions are to be filled, and the expected method&#13;
of recruitment. Each work plan will be agreed by the Steering Committee and IDA;&#13;
(b)    a suitably qualified local counterpart would be designated for each Palestinian expatriate&#13;
professional engaged under the program;&#13;
(c)   the TS would produce summary quarterly progress reports covering the work done in the&#13;
previous quarter, appointments and cancellations of contracts, and disbursements of&#13;
funds, as part of report containing the quarterly work plan; and&#13;
(d)   the work plan to recruit the first 10-15 candidates for the key ministries to be covered&#13;
by the first quarterly work plan during the period July 15 - October 15, 1997 will be&#13;
prepared within one month of project start-up (i.e., by target date August 15, 1997).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10                                                                       Technical Annex&#13;
B.    Procurement&#13;
2.6    All Trust Fund Credit funds and IDA-administered donor funds (a total of US$6 million) would&#13;
be used for consulting services. Both the project management contract and the payment of relocation&#13;
allowances to PEPP program participants are considered payments for consulting services because of the&#13;
nature of the work being done and the selection process which will be used. A very limited amount of&#13;
equipment may be purchased under this project as part of the contract with Arthur Andersen.&#13;
2.7   Procurement of all consulting services financed by the Trust Fund Credit funds and IDA-&#13;
administered donor funds under this project would be according to IDA guidelines for the selection of&#13;
consultants. The management company providing project management services as Technical Secretariat&#13;
to the project has been selected on the basis of an internationally diversified, competitive process. The&#13;
individual PEPP program participants will be recruited by the TS on behalf of the client ministries on the&#13;
basis of a transparent international search, using advertisements, direct contacts and other standard&#13;
recruitment techniques. Non-competitive, single source appointment of individuals will not be authorized.&#13;
2.8   The principal burden of procurement would rest on the TS, although the ministries and agencies&#13;
would have the sole responsibility to choose among the candidates identified for each position. As lender&#13;
and administrator of trust funds, IDA would act in its normal capacity to monitor project implementation&#13;
at key points. Because this is a time-consuming process, substantial staff time has been budgeted for&#13;
procurement-related issues in the supervision plan (see para. 2.17). In order to reduce the burden on staff&#13;
time, standard contracts for the relocation allowances would be used.&#13;
2.9   Schedule B of the Memorandum of the President summarizes the cost of items to be financed by&#13;
the project and the expected procurement methods for each.&#13;
C.    Disbursement&#13;
2.10   The project is expected to disburse fully over a three-year period. The Trust Fund Credit would&#13;
finance up to 100% of the cost of the project management and relocation allowances. Since the relocation&#13;
allowances will consist of many small amounts, almost all disbursements are expected to be through two&#13;
Special Accounts (SA) established for the purpose of the project. Supporting documentation in respect&#13;
of all payments would be retained by the MOF for a period of not less than two years for review by IDA&#13;
supervision missions and independent auditors, acceptable to IDA. Disbursement would be according&#13;
to the standard terms specified in the Disbursement Handbook published by the World Bank and dated&#13;
1986, as may be amended from time to time.&#13;
2.11   During the pilot phase, the Trust Fund Credit alone will fund the management contract; IDA-&#13;
administered funds from the Welfare Association will fund relocation allowances. Following completion&#13;
of the pilot phase and signature of an extension contract covering the full project period, funding of the&#13;
management contract and relocation allowances will be shared equally by the Trust Fund Credit and the&#13;
Welfare Association. Should additional external funding be received, disbursements between external&#13;
funding agencies would be expected to be proportional to maintain parity between these sources.&#13;
2.12   To expedite implementation, the MOF would establish two Special Accounts at a commercial&#13;
bank acceptable to IDA, to be operated as revolving funds for the Trust Fund Credit and the IDA-&#13;
administered contribution of the private sector to the project. These accounts would each be funded with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Technical Annex                                                                      11&#13;
an initial deposit of US$300,000 and would be replenished as and when needed upon presentation of a&#13;
withdrawal application.  The target would be to provide liquidity sufficient to cover quarterly&#13;
disbursements from each SA. The Minister of Finance and one other signatory would be authorized to&#13;
operate each SA, as well as to sign the withdrawal applications under the project. Approval of&#13;
disbursements to the Special Accounts would be contingent on continuing satisfactory performance of the&#13;
project.&#13;
D.    Accounts and Auditing&#13;
2.13   The accounts of all project funds, including the Special Accounts, would be audited annually by&#13;
independent auditors acceptable to IDA.&#13;
E.    Monitorin2 and Evaluation&#13;
2.14   A rolling work plan and budget for each quarter would be prepared by the TS and agreed with&#13;
the Steering Committee and with IDA. Implementation of these quarterly work plans would be monitored&#13;
through quarterly progress reports prepared by the TS. The content of the quarterly reports was agreed&#13;
at negotiations. The TS will furnish to the SC and IDA a work plan for the July-October 1997 period&#13;
at the end of the first month of operations. The first quarterly progress report (for the July-October 1997&#13;
quarter) would be prepared by October 15, 1997, and at quarterly intervals thereafter. To facilitate&#13;
project management and review, the quarterly progress report and forward-looking quarterly work plan&#13;
will be combined as separate sections in one document to be presented simultaneously in advance to the&#13;
SC and IDA for review and agreement.&#13;
2.15   The PA and IDA would carry out a joint review of progress in implementing the project during&#13;
the pilot period on the basis of performance indicators which were agreed at negotiations and which are&#13;
contained in Appendix 1 to this document. Key indicators would include progress, acceptable to IDA,&#13;
in recruiting the first 25-40 professionals, arrangements by the GOI to provide free mobility and full&#13;
effectiveness of PEPP program participants, and a transparent, professional and competitive selection&#13;
process.&#13;
F.    Proiect Supervision Plan&#13;
2.16   Because of the labor-intensive nature of consultant selection, IDA staff supervision of the project&#13;
is expected to require considerable effort and attention. However, the presence of a high quality TS&#13;
should enable IDA to focus on the quarterly work plans and the pre-qualification of candidates and not&#13;
to get involved in day-to-day issues of project management. The Bank's Resident Mission is expected&#13;
to be responsible for day-to-day monitoring of project activities with little need for headquarters input.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12                                                                       - Technical Annex&#13;
2.17   The table below gives the estimated staff-weeks for supervision of the project during the FY98-&#13;
FY00 period:&#13;
Supervision Plan&#13;
Fiscal Year                              FY 1998  FY 1999 FY 2000&#13;
1. Project management issues                13       12         10&#13;
2. Procurement issues                        2         1         1&#13;
Total staff-weeks                       15        13        11&#13;
The cost of IDA supervision has been calculated at $153,500 (39 staff/weeks at an average cost of&#13;
US$3,750 and US$17,000 for travel). This level of resources should be feasible. IDA is expected to&#13;
receive about US$60,000 in administrative fees on US$3 million of donor funds under Trust Fund&#13;
arrangements, calculated at two percent of the amount of funds contributed by external sources.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Technical Annex                                                                             13&#13;
APPENDIX 1&#13;
Key Performance Indicators&#13;
A. Institutional Development Objectives:                        FY 1998   FY 1999   FY 2000&#13;
- number of positions targeted for recruitment in              40         30         30&#13;
each annual period (does not include contract extensions)&#13;
- number of professionals recruited in each annual period      30         40         30&#13;
- number of professionals recruited who fulfill the full period  27       36         27&#13;
of their contract (does not include contract extensions)&#13;
- number of professionals recruited who are offered and         --        20         30&#13;
accept a second year of employment&#13;
percentage of professionals recruited who are               75%        75%        75%&#13;
considered to have performed in the first or&#13;
second tranche of performance categories&#13;
(highest = 1 and lowest = 5)&#13;
- independence, quality and transparency of the               75%        75%        75%&#13;
international recruitment process followed (rate&#13;
on the basis of the number of top-ranked candidates selected)&#13;
B. Capacity Building:&#13;
- number of individuals appointed to act as full-time deputies  30        40         30&#13;
to the expatriate professionals recruited&#13;
- number of appointed individuals who replace PEPP             n.a.       24         32&#13;
participant on his departure&#13;
- establishment and operation of the data base on expatriate  1,000      5,000     15,000&#13;
Palestinian professionals (number of individuals included)&#13;
C. Proiect Management:&#13;
- number of individual participants granted full travel and work  100%   100%       100%&#13;
permits and mobility consistent with their contracts&#13;
- quality of the methodology used to calculate and            66%       80% &lt;      80% &lt;&#13;
pay relocation allowances (proportion of appointments&#13;
without disputes over level of compensation percentage)&#13;
- management of project financial operations and Special Account    1 or 2  1 or 2  1 or 2&#13;
(highest = 1 and lowest = 5)&#13;
- actual disbursement of funds against projected disbursements  60% &lt;   75% &lt;      85% &lt;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="694797">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/05/694797/west-bank-gaza-palestinian-expatriate-professional-program-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/05/694797/west-bank-gaza-palestinian-expatriate-professional-program-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/05/694797/west-bank-gaza-palestinian-expatriate-professional-program-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1997/05/14/000009265_3980313101828/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1997/05/14/000009265_3980313101828/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-05-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1997-05-14T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            West Bank and Gaza - Palestinian Expatriate
            Professional Program Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objectives of the Palestinian
            Expatriate Professional Program Project are to: (1) attract
            skilled and experienced managers and senior technical
            specialists from the Palestinian diaspora to fill management
            and technical positions in key Palestinian ministries and
            agencies; (2) establish a transparent, independent, and
            international recruitment process to fill these positions;
            and (3) help establish compensation practices based on
            objective criteria and a transparent methodology. This
            project supports the Bank's overall objective of
            building policy-making and institutional capacity within the
            Palestinian government. The project will finance relocation
            allowances and local government salaries for Palestinian
            expatriates and a contract with a leading international
            management consulting firm to implement the project.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            West Bank and Gaza - Palestinian Expatriate
            Professional Program Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>West Bank and Gaza - Palestinian
            Expatriate Professional Program Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1997/05/694797/west-bank-gaza-palestinian-expatriate-professional-program-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>GZ-Palestinian Expatriate Professional
            Project -- P049708</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems,Business in Development,National Governance,Economic Adjustment and Lending</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>West Bank and Gaza</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Middle East!$!80463</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980313101828</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other social services,Central government administration</subsc>
        <admreg>Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1998-1</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Education</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Civil servants; Expatriate management;
            Experts; Foreign workers; Industrial relocation; Institution
            building; Management contracts; Palestinians; Recruitment; Wages
            Account,Accounts,administrative
            fees,advertisements,Auditing,auditors,Authority,bookkeeping,budgeting,commitment,commitments,counterpart,Disbursement,disbursements,donor
            funds,employment,equipment,extension,financial
            management,financial risks,financial support,FISCAL,fixed
            costs,funding agencies,funding sources,government
            agencies,government departments,government
            funding,government officials,government
            representatives,Housing,institutional analysis,institutional
            development,lender,Liberation,managers,Ministers,Ministries
            of Finance,Ministry of Finance,Nationals,Nations,Private
            Sector,private sector sponsors,Procurement,Public
            Administration,Rehabilitation,revolving
            funds,tranche,transparency,trust funds,working conditions
        </keywd>
        <owner>West Bank and Gaza (MNC04)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Middle East</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF027041-PALESTINIAN EXPATRIATE
            PROFESSIONAL PROGRAM (PEPP),TF026042-PALESTINIAN EXPATRIATE
            PROFFESSIONALS PROGRAM</trustfund>
        <repnb>T7117</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing for Results</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outcomes Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Drivers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Results Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Allowance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Allowance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>