<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
THE WORLD BANK&#13;
Report No. 15448-ME&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
FEDERAL ROADS MODERNIZATION PROJECT&#13;
June 6, 1997&#13;
Mexico Country Department&#13;
Sector Leadership Group&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRFNCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Currency 11nit             -               New Peso (NS)&#13;
US$1.00                               N$7.9 (May 27. 1997)&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January I to December 31&#13;
UTNITS OF WEIGHTS AND] MEASURES&#13;
Metric                                    Bitish/US Equivalent&#13;
1 kilometer (kmi)                         0.62 mile (mi)&#13;
I meter (m)                               3.28 feet (ft)&#13;
I gram (g)                               0.0022 pound (lb)&#13;
I kilogram (kg)                           2.20 pounds (lb)&#13;
I ton                                     2,205 pounds&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
AADT                           Annual Average Daily Traffic&#13;
BANOBRAS                       National Bank for P'ublic Works and Services (Banco Nacional de Obras y Servicios Ptblicos)&#13;
CAPUFE                         Federal Road and Bnidge Toll Authonity (Caminos y Puentes Federales de&#13;
Ingresos y Servicios Conexos)&#13;
CGP                            General Coordination for Planning (Coordinacion General de Planeaci6n)&#13;
CVSA                           North-American Commercial Vehicle Safety Alliance&#13;
DGCC                           Generai Directorate for Maintenance (Dirccci6n General de Construccion y&#13;
Conscrvaci6n) of scr&#13;
DGCF                           General Directorate for Federal Elighways (Direccion General de Carreteras&#13;
Federales) of SCT&#13;
DGCS                           General Directorate for Training (Direccion General de Capacitacion Sectorial) of SCT&#13;
DGMNPT                         General Directorate for Preventive Medicine in Transportation (Direcci6n&#13;
General de Medicina Preventiva en el Transporte) of SCT&#13;
DGP                            General Directorate for Ports (Direcci6n General de Puertos)&#13;
DGPI                           General l&gt;irectorate for Planning (Direcci6n General de Planeaci6n) of SCT&#13;
DGTR                           General Directorate of Toll Roads&#13;
DGTT                           General Directorate for Land Transport (Direccion General de Transporte&#13;
Terrestre) of SCT&#13;
DPE                            Directorate for Programming and Evaluation (Direcci6n de Programaci6n y&#13;
Evaluaci6n) of DGCCOP&#13;
ERR                            Economic Rate of Return&#13;
FHN                            Federal Highway Network&#13;
FNM                            Mexican Railways (Ferrocarriles Nacionales de Mexico)&#13;
GDP                            Gross D)omeastic Product&#13;
GDTR                           General Directorate of Toll Roads&#13;
HDM                  :         Highway Design Model&#13;
HRR-M                          Highway Rehabilitation, Resurfacing and Maintenance&#13;
ICB                            Intemational Competitivc Bidding&#13;
IDB                            Interamerican Development Bank&#13;
UNIT                           Mexican Transport Institute (Instituto Mexicano de Transporte)&#13;
KPH                            Kilometers per hour (Kilometros por horas)&#13;
NAFTA                          North American Free Trade Agreement&#13;
NCB                            National Contpetitive Bidding&#13;
NBF                            Not Bank Financed&#13;
PFCP                           Federal Hlighway and Port Patrol (Policia Federal de Caminos y Puertos)&#13;
SCT                            Secretanat for Communications and Transport (Secretaria de Comunicaciones y Transportes)&#13;
SECOGEF                        General Secretanat of the Comptroller of the Federation (Seeretaria de la&#13;
Contraloria General de la Federacion)&#13;
SEDESOL                        Secretariat for Social l)evelopment (Secretaria de Desarrollo Social)&#13;
SEDUE                          Secretariat for Urban Development and Ecology (Secretaria de Desarrollo Urbano y Ecologia)&#13;
SHCP                           Secretariat for Finanze and Public Credit (Secretaria de Hacienda y Credito&#13;
Publico)&#13;
SICC                           Highway Maintenance Management System&#13;
SIMAP                          Mexican Model for Highway Project Analyses&#13;
SIPUMEX              :         Mexican Model for Bridge Management Systeni&#13;
SISTER                         Simulation Model of Highway Maintenance Strategies (Simulation de&#13;
Strategies d'Entretien Routier)&#13;
SPP                            Secretariat for Programming and Budgeting (Secretaria de Programaci6n y&#13;
Presupuesto I&#13;
VOC                            Vehicle Operating Costs&#13;
Regaional Vice! President                 -                    Javed Husain Burki&#13;
Country Director                          -                    Olivier Lafourcade&#13;
Acting Sector Leader                      -                    Richard Clifford&#13;
Task Manauzer                             -                    Peter Gyamfi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
FEDERAL ROADS MODERNIZATION PROJECT&#13;
Loan and Project Summary&#13;
Borrower:                  Banco de Obras y Servicios Publicos (BANOBRAS).&#13;
Guarantor:                 United Mexican States.&#13;
Executing Agency:          Secretaria de Comunicaciones y&#13;
Transportes (SCT).&#13;
Beneficiary:               Not Applicable.&#13;
Poverty Category:          Not Applicable.&#13;
Amount:                    US$475 million.&#13;
Terms:                      Libor-based single currency loan (US Dollars) with repayment&#13;
in 15 years, including 5 years of grace.&#13;
Commitment Fee:            0.75% on undisbursed loan balances, beginning 60 days after&#13;
signing, less any waiver.&#13;
Financing Plan:            See para. 15.&#13;
Net Present Value and&#13;
Economic Returns:          NPV is US$983 million equivalent discounted at 12% and&#13;
ERR is&#13;
18.9% for the whole road program.&#13;
Staff Appraisal Report:    Report No. 15448, dated May 27, 1997&#13;
Map:                       IBRD No. 28418&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
FEDERAL ROADS MODERNIZATION PROJECT&#13;
Appraisal Report&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page&#13;
1. THE TRANSPORT SECTOR .....................................................1&#13;
A. The Economy and the Transport Sector .....................................................1&#13;
B. Institutional Framework and Sectoral Planning .....................................................2&#13;
C. Government's Transport Sector Policy ......................                         ...............................3&#13;
D. The Bank's Experience and Lessons Learned in the Sector ....................                          ....................4&#13;
E. Rationale for Bank Involvement .....................................................6&#13;
2. THE  HIGHWAY  SECTOR  ........7.............................................7&#13;
A. The Highway Network ......................................................7&#13;
B. Administration of the Primary Highway Network ....................................................9&#13;
C. Highway Maintenance ..........1........................................... 1&#13;
D. Sector Issues ..................................................... 11&#13;
3. THE PROJECT .....................................................                                                                 16&#13;
A.  Project Origin .....................................................                                                   16&#13;
B.  Project Objectives ..................................................... 16&#13;
C. Project Description ..................................................... 16&#13;
D. Project Cost and Financing ..................................................... 22&#13;
E. Sustainability .....................................................                                                    22&#13;
4. PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION .....................................................                                                      25&#13;
A. Sub-project Selection, Preparation and Evaluation ................................................. 25&#13;
B. Conditions and Procedures for Procurement of Sub-projects ..................................... 25&#13;
C. Implementation and Monitoring .....................................................                                     27&#13;
D. Accounts and Audits ..................................................... 30&#13;
E. Disbursements .....................................................                                                     30&#13;
F. Economic Evaluation .....................................................                                               32&#13;
G. Environmental AND  SOCIAL  aspects .....................................................                                32&#13;
H. Project Objective Category  ..................................................... 33&#13;
I. Project Benefits .....................................................                                                  33&#13;
J.  Project Risks .....................................................                                                    34&#13;
This report is based on the findings of an appraisal mission that visited Mexico from February 7 to 21,&#13;
1996. The mission members were Messrs. Peter Gyamfi (Task Manager), Gustavo Unda (Transport&#13;
Engineer) and Rodrigo Archondo-Callao (System Specialist). Mr. Gordon Bodley and Mrs. Monica&#13;
DuQuesnay (Consultants) assisted in the financial and economic analysis of the project. Messrs. Olivier&#13;
Lafourcade, Richard Clifford and Martin Stabb assited in the quality enhancement and control of the&#13;
project preparation and appraisal. Mr. Juan Carlos Mendoza assisted in the production of this report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5. AGREEMENTS TO BE REACHED AND RECOMMENDATIONS ............             ....................... 35&#13;
Annexes&#13;
Annex A Rehabilitation and Maintenance of the Federal Road Network ......... ................. 36&#13;
Annex B Training Program ......................................................... 41&#13;
Annex C Performance Monitoring Indicators ......................................................... 43&#13;
Annex D Economic and Financial Analysis of the Project Roads ............ ....................... 46&#13;
ITEMS IN THE PROJECT FILE&#13;
1.    PROGRAMA DE DESARROLLO DEL SECTOR COMUNICACIONES Y TRANSPORTE (1995-2000)&#13;
2.    PROGRAMA DE TRABAJO EN EL SECTOR COMUNICACIONES Y TRANSPORTES (1996)&#13;
3.    INFRAESTRUCTURA CARRETERA: DIAGN6STICO, OBJETIVOS Y LiNEAS DE AccION&#13;
4.    PROGRAMA DE MODERNIZACI6N DE LA RED CARRETERA (1996-2002)&#13;
5.    PROGRAMA NACIONAL DE CONSERVACI6N DE CARRETERAS (1996)&#13;
6.    RED CARRETERA FEDERAL: ESTRATEGIAS DE CONSERVACI6N (1996)&#13;
7.    AUTOPISTA SAN Luis PoTosi - SALTILLO: ANALISIS DE ALTERNATIVAS&#13;
8.    MODERNIZACION DE LA CARRETERA TAMPICO - LINARES&#13;
9.    APLICACION EN LA SCT DEL MODELO DE EVALUACI6N DE IMPACTO AMBIENTAL&#13;
10.   SisTEMA DE SIMuLAcI6N A DIFERENTES ESCENARIOS PARA LA MATRIZ DE ESTADO DE IMPACTO&#13;
AMBIENTAL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
FEDERAL ROADS MODERNIZATION PROJECT&#13;
THE TRANSPORT SECTOR&#13;
A. THE ECONOMY AND THE TRANSPORT SECTOR&#13;
1.1   Mexico restored economic growth by substantially restructuring its economy in the&#13;
mid 1980s, including privatizing a large number of state-owned enterprises, opening the&#13;
economy to foreign competition, expanding the role of market forces in resource&#13;
allocation and adhering to a policy of fiscal restraint. This growth has been interrupted by&#13;
a large current account deficit which resulted in a major devaluation at the end of 1994,&#13;
from which the country is still recovering. In order to restore trust in the economy, the&#13;
Government launched an economic austerity program in March 1995 aimed at: (a)&#13;
achieving a budget surplus of 4.4% of Gross Domestic Product (GDP) in 1995; (b)&#13;
limiting net domestic credit creation to a maximum of N$10 billion for 1995; (c) achieving&#13;
equilibrium in the balance of payments; and (d) restructuring N$65 billion of outstanding&#13;
debt of the private sector. The Government's medium to long term objective, however,&#13;
remains restructuring of the economy.&#13;
1.2   Fiscal restraint has meant a drastic decline in public sector investments, including&#13;
the transport sector (an average decline of about 7.5% per year), during the first half of&#13;
the 1990s. To increase funding to the transport sector, the Government has been&#13;
encouraging increased private sector participation in the provision of facilities and&#13;
services. Most of the Government's success in this area has occurred in (a) the highways&#13;
sub-sector, where about 5,000 km of high standard federal roads have been built by&#13;
private concessions at a cost of more that US$10 billion; and (b) the ports sub-sector,&#13;
where over 80 port terminal concessions have been granted, mostly to the sole users of&#13;
specialized terminals.&#13;
1.3   The transport sector in Mexico accounts for about 6 % of the government's capital&#13;
expenditures, a figure which has been declining in recent years due mainly to the increased&#13;
relative importance of private investment. In terms of GDP, the transport sector in&#13;
Mexico accounts for almost 10%, up from just over 7% in 1986, reflecting the growth in&#13;
transport activity as a result of the Government's new economic policy. Mexico's&#13;
economic growth depends critically on the development of its external trade and, for&#13;
growth in this area to be sustained, transport infrastructure and services are crucial.&#13;
1.4   An expected impact of the North America Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) on&#13;
Mexico's transport sector is an increase in the annual growth rate in trade between the&#13;
U.S. and Mexico from the current 10% per annum to about 15% per annum, by about the&#13;
next two years. The impact on transport demand in ton-km will be even greater as the&#13;
advantages of "maquiladora" industries locating near the border are eliminated and new&#13;
growth occurs in the industrial centers of Mexico at longer distances from the US. The&#13;
increased trade and associated high traffic growth will require significant modernization of&#13;
Mexico's transport infrastructure along the trade corridors, inter-modal facilities such as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2&#13;
storage facilities, services such as cargo identification and documentation and electronic&#13;
data interchange systems. The Government's transport policy is aimed at encouraging the&#13;
private sector to supply these facilities and services and for the Government to provide&#13;
only those, which though economically justifiable, are not financially attractive to the&#13;
private sector under a concession scheme. The proposed project would help to modernize&#13;
federal roads which fall into the latter category.&#13;
B. INSTITUTIONAL FRAMEWORK AND SECTORAL PLANNING&#13;
1.5   The Secretaria de Comunicaciones y Transportes (SCT) is responsible for&#13;
managing the transport sector and its agencies through its Sub-secretariat for&#13;
Infrastructure, which handles almost all public road transport infrastructure development,&#13;
and its Sub-secretariat for Transport which is responsible for operational, regulatory and&#13;
tariff matters. The biggest challenge currently facing SCT is the need to adapt to its&#13;
changing role: (a) from a builder, operator and provider of services to a manager,&#13;
promoter and regulator of the sector; and (b) from an agency with jurisdiction over almost&#13;
all roads in the country to one that is decentralizing and that has transferred considerable&#13;
responsibilities for road construction and maintenance to the state governments. SCT is&#13;
already undertaking the first steps in this transformation process, but the path for future&#13;
ones and the details of how the new institutions will function remain to be defined. The&#13;
proposed project would provide technical assistance to SCT in the highway sub-sector to&#13;
help it move further in the desired direction. In the case of airports and railways, the Bank-&#13;
financed Infrastructure Privatization Technical Assistance Project (Loan 3937-ME, FY96)&#13;
provides assistance, inter alia, to study suitable organizational structures for managing the&#13;
concessions and for regulating the sub-sectors.&#13;
1.6   Responsibility for planning in the transport sector has been divided among the&#13;
modal agencies upon whose expertise SCT largely relies for the technical assessment of&#13;
projects: the Direcci6n General de Puertos (DGP) for ports, the Ferrocarriles Nacionales&#13;
de Mexico (FNM) for railways and the Direcci6n General de Servicios Tecnicos for roads.&#13;
The General Directorate for Planning (DGPI), within SCT, is responsible for coordinating&#13;
and formulating the modal plans into an overall sector plan. Sector planning is carried out&#13;
in close cooperation with relevant national and regional authorities, the private sector and&#13;
other interested parties. In addition to strengthening project evaluation and planning&#13;
capacity, for which the DGPI is receiving assistance under the ongoing Highways&#13;
Rehabilitation and Traffic Safety Project (HRTS; Loan 3628-ME, FY93), DGPI needs to&#13;
develop a comprehensive highway resources allocation model to help in efficiently&#13;
distributing SCT's limited road budget among competing road activities. The proposed&#13;
project would provide for the development of such a model.&#13;
1.7   Public participation in the development of SCT's program is required by law. The&#13;
SCT has been calling public meetings in a number of cities to discuss transport&#13;
modernization. Participants, totaling over 8,000, have included public servants from the&#13;
federal, state, and local levels, as well as users of all modes of transportation, chambers of&#13;
commerce, equipment and vehicle manufacturers, labor unions, and professional&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3&#13;
associations. The conclusions of the meetings and over 6,000 proposals submitted by&#13;
participants and interested groups have been reflected, to the extent possible, in the&#13;
formulation of the National Program for Transport Modernization. SCT periodically&#13;
evaluates the results of its efforts, using the program as a guide. Based on this evaluation,&#13;
SCT reports its progress to the Congress as required in the Planning Law.&#13;
1.8   The SCT is gradually addressing planning deficiencies related to identifying,&#13;
selecting and programming investments. In early 1991, SCT started to strengthen its&#13;
planning unit and gave it a greater role in the analysis and selection of priorities. The&#13;
General Coordination for Planning (CGP) was created to supervise all planning within&#13;
SCT, including the DGPl and the Sector Planning Committee. CGP's functions and&#13;
responsibilities were revised to enhance its coordinating role and an Environmental Affairs&#13;
Unit was established to oversee environmental affairs in the transport sector and to factor&#13;
environmental impact and its mitigation at the planning stage. Also in 1991, the&#13;
Secretariat for Programming and Budgeting (SPP), which approves the proposed sector&#13;
investment and operating budgets, established an investment unit to review all major&#13;
investments in the sector and to make modal planning more consistent. These functions&#13;
are now being carried out by the Secretariat of Finance and Public Credit (SHCP). One of&#13;
the most beneficial effects of these efforts is that planning transport facilities is being&#13;
looked at increasingly from an inter-modal and transport corridor basis.&#13;
C. GOVERNMENT'S TRANSPORT SECTOR POLICY&#13;
1.9   The Government's transport policy, outlined in its Plan Nacional de Modernizaci6n&#13;
del Sector Transporte, emphasizes: (a) increased private sector participation in the&#13;
provision, operation and maintenance of transport facilities; (b) deregulation of the&#13;
transport sector; (c) public provision of those facilities and services which, though&#13;
economically justified, are not financially attractive to private investors; (d) SCT's&#13;
changing role in the sector from operational to normative and promotional functions; (e)&#13;
changes in the organizational and legal structure of the sector; and (f) the transfer of road&#13;
responsibilities to the state governments. The Government is steadily, but cautiously&#13;
implementing this policy. About 5,000 km of high standard roads have been built by&#13;
concession and facilities at some 80 ports have been concessioned. The Government has&#13;
also called for bids for cargo handling on the four most important ports: Veracruz and&#13;
Tampico on the Atlantic/Gulf Coast and Manzanillo and Lazaro Cardenas on the Pacific&#13;
Coast. In the aviation sub-sector, the airline deregulation of 1989 has permitted direct&#13;
service between the US and many Mexican tourist destinations and now the Government&#13;
is seriously considering concessioning the airports. In the case of railways, the&#13;
Government is undertaking a major restructuring program aimed at both reducing the high&#13;
annual deficits of the FNM and also laying the ground for increased private sector&#13;
participation. The program includes dividing the railways into three regions, and&#13;
concessioning their operations to the private sector. The Bank is supporting all these&#13;
activities through the Infrastructure Privatization Technical Assistance Project (Loan&#13;
3937-ME, FY96) approved in August 1995.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4&#13;
1.10  As part of its economic restructuring program and to attract private sector&#13;
participation, the Government has also substantially deregulated the transport sector and&#13;
significantly reduced the Government's direct involvement in operating facilities and in&#13;
controlling pricing. Both trucking and inter-urban bus tariffs were deregulated in 1989,&#13;
while wharfage and cargo handling charges are increasingly being determined at the level&#13;
of the individual ports. FNM has been granted considerable freedom in setting its own&#13;
tariffs and in adjusting them to reflect market conditions. Lastly, entry restrictions to the&#13;
inter-modal transport industry, previously limited to one monopoly operator, have been&#13;
removed with the effect that there are now more than 30 firms competing to the benefit of&#13;
users.&#13;
1.11   The areas of policy reform in which further changes and progress are required&#13;
include: (a) establishing a regulatory framework for managing competition; (b) completing&#13;
the restructuring and privatization of the railway, ports and airports; (c) stimulating multi-&#13;
modal transport; and (d) establishing institutional responsibilities in the SCT that reflect&#13;
the changed role of Government.&#13;
D. THE BANK'S EXPERIENCE AND LESSONS LEARNED IN THE SECTOR&#13;
1 .12   General. The Bank has been involved with the Mexican Highway Sector since&#13;
1960 with twelve loans for the federal highway system, the first seven of which were&#13;
regular project investment loans whereas the last four were sector investment loans. In&#13;
addition, the Bank made a loan to improve the rural roads system in the state of Chiapas&#13;
and a Road Transport and Telecommunications Sector Adjustment Project which&#13;
supported, on the transport side, Mexico's policy of deregulating highway transport&#13;
services.&#13;
1.13  Although the projects were implemented under diverse economic, inflationary and&#13;
exchange rate conditions, they all shared common implementation results: they achieved&#13;
their physical goals, albeit with considerable time and cost overruns, but had rather modest&#13;
impact on institutional strengthening, except for the two most recent projects. The lessons&#13;
learned from this implementation experience have been increasingly incorporated in the&#13;
last two road projects as well as the proposed one.&#13;
1.14  Physical Implementation of the Projects. Practically all the projects were&#13;
designed to be completed in four years from loan signature. None achieved this objective&#13;
and there was no indication of consistent improvement up to 1990. The First Highway&#13;
Project was completed 3-1/2 years behind schedule and the Second Highway Sector&#13;
Project ended three years late. The PCRs and Audit Reports have consistently attributed&#13;
the implementation delays to slow counterpart allocations and the cost overruns to&#13;
insufficient detailed engineering, changes in the scope of works, delays during&#13;
construction and unexpectedly-high inflation.&#13;
1.15  With regards to the implementation delays, these were significantly reduced when&#13;
the new administration decided in 1990 to condition budgetary allocations to the SCT on&#13;
the progress in the execution of Bank-financed projects. This decision resulted in the last&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5&#13;
50% of the disbursement under the Second Highway Sector Project, which was then three&#13;
years behind schedule, being made in the last two years of project implementation and the&#13;
Highway Maintenance Project, which also had significant delays when the new&#13;
disbursement policy was introduced, being completed according to schedule.&#13;
1.16  With regards to cost overruns, the Third Highway Project was the only one of the&#13;
seven investment loans that achieved some success in reducing cost overruns because the&#13;
Bank insisted that detailed engineering had to be completed before loan negotiations. The&#13;
Second Highway Sector, the Highway Maintenance Project and the ongoing Highway&#13;
Rehabilitation and Traffic Safety Project (HRTS) drew on this experience, with the result&#13;
that the cost overruns of these were substantially less than in previous projects.&#13;
1.17  The main lessons drawn from the physical implementation of the projects show the&#13;
need for: (a) the Government to continue to give SCT an incentive to speed up&#13;
implementation by linking the disbursements of the Bank loan proceeds and the execution&#13;
of the SCT's budget; (b) the Bank and the Government holding annual meetings on SCT's&#13;
road budget to ensure adequate provision of funds for ongoing projects; and (c) ensuring&#13;
that detailed engineering of a substantial part of the project is completed before loan&#13;
negotiations. The proposed project design draws from these lessons by incorporating the&#13;
actions under (a) through (c) above in the project design and implementation.&#13;
1.18  Institutional Strengthening and Policy Reforms. Although the Bank's sector&#13;
reviews from 1964 to 1974 all emphasized institutional and regulatory problems, the&#13;
Bank's lending for the first six road projects focused rather narrowly on construction; loan&#13;
conditionality was mainly designed to deal with assurances about the implementation of&#13;
civil works. Improvement in institutional strengthening therefore was minimal. Starting&#13;
with the Seventh Project, the Bank corrected this shortcoming by shifting its focus to&#13;
transport sector economics, planning and transport regulatory issues. Success in achieving&#13;
institutional strengthening and policy reform objectives have been mixed, as outlined&#13;
below. The lessons to be learned from these projects are that: (a) institutional&#13;
strengthening and policy reforms take a long time and steady effort to accomplish; (b) the&#13;
Government's sense of ownership is indispensable to success and therefore Government&#13;
officials should be closely involved in choosing the measures to be included under the&#13;
projects and in designing their implementation; and (c) clear up-front loan conditionality&#13;
on the important measures should be included under the projects.&#13;
1.19  The main institutional strengthening and policy reform achievements from the&#13;
Bank's lending to the sector include: (a) improving planning and budgetary coordination&#13;
(the First Highway Sector Loan); (b) initiating an increase in highway maintenance&#13;
expenditures at the expense of construction, encouraging the SCT to improve work&#13;
programming and preparation of multi-annual budgets, revising and introducing more&#13;
efficient procurement practices and tying SCT's budgetary disbursements on the progress&#13;
in implementing externally-funded projects (the Second Highway Sector Project); (c)&#13;
introducing the concepts of highway and bridge maintenance systems, providing for&#13;
greater participation of the private sector in carrying out maintenance and introducing&#13;
better allocation of road funds to all of SCT's road activities (the Highway Maintenance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6&#13;
Project); and (d) deregulating the road transport industry (the Sector Adjustment Project).&#13;
The deregulation of trucking had arguably the greatest positive impact of all these&#13;
reforms: more than 44,000 new truckers entered the industry within the first two years of&#13;
deregulation, tariffs for trucking services fell by about 25% and services improved&#13;
markedly.&#13;
E. RATIONALE FOR BANK INVOLVEMENT&#13;
1.20  The Bank's current Country Assistance Strategy (CAS) for Mexico, discussed at&#13;
the Board on December 17, 1996 stresses: (a) growth with stability by supporting sound&#13;
macro-economic management througii enhanced monitoring and closer dialogue,&#13;
especially on structural and micro underpinnings of macro policy, and ensuring sound&#13;
financial and capital marked development; (b) social development through improving the&#13;
efficiency and quality of social sector spending and making a dent in regional&#13;
concentrations of poverty through the planned Southern States Initiative; (c)&#13;
modernization of the State through improving the regulatory framework to facilitate&#13;
private enterprise and to foster competition and supporting an orderly and efficient&#13;
process of fiscal and administrative decentralization. The proposed project fits into the&#13;
above strategy by: (a) reducing existing and potential constraints to economnic growth&#13;
caused by inefficient and costly transportation in Mexico; and (b) facilitating the orderly&#13;
and efficient decentralization of the administration of about half of the federal network to&#13;
the states by strengthening the state road agencies.&#13;
1.21  The Bank has been extensively involved in Mexico's highway sector since 1960&#13;
with 12 loans. After 10 highway investment loans, the Bank has focused the two most&#13;
recent loans, the Highway Maintenance Project, Loan 2876-ME, and the BRTS, Loan&#13;
3628-ME, on addressing the need for maintenance and rehabilitation of the federal&#13;
network. The proposed project, which would address the need for additional capacity, is&#13;
therefore a logical follow-up and complement to the maintenance and rehabilitation&#13;
projects and the highway concession program. Modernizing road transport on the federal&#13;
network also requires improving SCT's road management systems and procedures, multi-&#13;
modal transport operations, vehicle weight and dimension enforcement, road safety as well&#13;
as environmental impact assessment and mitigation. The Government accords high&#13;
priority to further improvement in these matters which, together with the physical&#13;
improvements mentioned above, would greatly reduce the cost of transport and thereby&#13;
enhance its competitive position vis a vis its NAFTA partners. The Bank is providing&#13;
assistance to improve these areas under the ongoing HRTS; the proposed project would&#13;
deepen and expand that assistance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7&#13;
THE HIGHWAY SECTOR&#13;
A. THE HIGHWAY NETWORK&#13;
2.1    Road transport in Mexico is the major mode for both passengers and freight,&#13;
accounting for about 99% of intercity passenger movement and about 89% of cargo&#13;
movement by land. Road traffic generally grew by 10% per annum in the 1970s and by&#13;
about 5% per annum in the 1980s (Table 2-1). Traffic growth occurred despite the&#13;
economic recession and substantial real price increases for road freight. Within the context&#13;
of NAFTA, traffic growth on the major road corridors, currently estimated at about 10%&#13;
annually, is expected to increase to about 15% per annum starting in 1998.&#13;
2.2   The 302,000 km of interurban roads in Mexico, of which about 93,000 km are&#13;
paved, are classified as federal, toll, state and rural roads in accordance with the source of&#13;
funds for the various road programs. The states have jurisdictional responsibility for some&#13;
83,000 km of roads. The Government, through SCT, has primary responsibility for the&#13;
49,000 km of federal and toll highways. Control and responsibility for the approximately&#13;
170,000 km of rural roads is shared by local governments, the states and the federal&#13;
government (Table 2-2). The Government is transferring responsibility for rural roads to&#13;
the states and local governments. The Federal Highway Network (FHN) has evolved&#13;
rapidly, as has the rest of Mexico's road system. In 1952, there were only 27,000 km of&#13;
roads, 16,000 km of which were paved. By 1995, the road system had grown to over&#13;
302,000 km, about 93,000 km of which were paved (including 6,000 km with four or&#13;
more lanes). The system's annual rate of growth has slowed from 8.7% per year from&#13;
1952-1975 to 1.7% per year from 1975 to 1991, a sign that the network has reached&#13;
relative maturity and that, except for a few areas, the primary network is in place. In the&#13;
past ten years, road investment has shifted from extension of the trunk network to&#13;
construction of rural access roads and, more recently, to maintaining and widening&#13;
existing trunk roads in response to increased travel demand.&#13;
2.3   The recently-concluded inventory of the federal road network shows that about 50% of&#13;
the network is in poor condition, 35% in fair condition and the remaining 15% in good&#13;
condition. Although there is much variance between regions, average conditions on SCT's&#13;
federal highways appear to have worsened in the 1980s due mainly to the decline in real terms&#13;
of the highway rehabilitation and road maintenance budgets (HRRM) budgets, from about&#13;
US$230 million in 1983 to US$120 million in 1989. Because it has had to operate with low&#13;
budgets for several years, SCT generally limited maintenance to emergency and repair works.&#13;
Conditions on the toll roads are better than on the federal highways. The Federal Toll Roads&#13;
and Bridges Authority (CAPUFE), which has higher financial resources per km, has been able&#13;
to maintain its toll roads in a very satisfactory manner. The condition of the federal network is&#13;
being improved significantly through the HRTS Project which is addressing the budget&#13;
problems and increasing SCT's efficiency in using available maintenance funds through staff&#13;
training and the introduction of modern maintenance management systems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
Table 2-1: Indicators of Highway Demand&#13;
Average Annual Growt&#13;
Growth Rate&#13;
(Percent)         1975      1980     1985      1990          1975-     1980-     1985-&#13;
1980      1985      1990&#13;
Population (thousands)    60,150   69,655    77,938    86,150        4.0        2.3       2.0&#13;
GDP (Billion 1980          3,171    4,470     4,920    5,236         7.1        1.9       1.3&#13;
pesos)&#13;
PerCapitaGDP              52,718    64,173    63,127   60,778        4.0       -0.3      -0.8&#13;
(1980 pesos)&#13;
Vehicles in Circulation    3,340    5,828    6,932    9,741          11.8       3.5       7.0&#13;
(thousands)&#13;
Automobiles                2,401    4,255     4,921    6,754         12.1       3.0       6.5&#13;
(thousands)&#13;
Trucks (thousands)          888     1,489     1,917    2,893         10.9       5.2       8.6&#13;
Buses (thousands)            51        84        94       94         10.5       2.3       0.0&#13;
Gasoline Consumption      10,865    18,316   25,217     N.A.         11.0       6.6      N.A&#13;
by Road Vehicles&#13;
(million liters)&#13;
Diesel Consumption         5,499    8,215    12,922     N.A.         8.4       9.5       N.A&#13;
by Road Vehicles&#13;
(million liters)&#13;
Passenger Cars/              40        63        63       78          8.4       0.0       6.7&#13;
1000 Inhabitants&#13;
Road Network (km)        186,218   212,626   224,255   239,235        2.7       1.0       1.5&#13;
Federal Highways (km)     38,292   42,521    44,359   45,743         2.2        0.8       0.6&#13;
Source: Asociaci6n Mexicana de la Industria Automotriz, "La Industria Automotriz de Mexico&#13;
en Cifras", SCT, SPP. November 1991&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9&#13;
Table 2-2: Classification of Highways (Length in Km as of 1996)&#13;
Jurisdiction&#13;
Mexican Classification  Approximate Function    Federal    State    Local&#13;
- Federal Highways      Primary (arterials)    42,000*&#13;
- Toll Highways         Primary (arterials)     6,200&#13;
- State Highways        Secondary (collectors)    -       83,000&#13;
- Rural Roads           Tertiary (local)              170,000&#13;
*    tAbout 15,000 km of these roads are in the priority network, 13,000 km in the basic network and&#13;
17,800 km are of low priority. Lengths are given in two-lane highway equivalent km&#13;
B. ADMINISTRATION OF THE PRIMARY HIGHWAY NETWORK&#13;
2.4    SCT's two Sub-secretariats divide highway related tasks between them. The Sub-&#13;
secretariat for Infrastructure has jurisdiction over the General Directorate for Federal&#13;
Roads, the General Directorate of Toll Roads (GDTR), the General Directorate for&#13;
Technical Services, and the General Directorate for Maintenance (DGCC). These four&#13;
directorates have primary responsibility for the planning/design, toll roads management,&#13;
construction and maintenance respectively of roads under federal jurisdiction. The Sub-&#13;
secretariat for Transport includes the General Directorates for Tariffs, Land Transport,&#13;
and Preventive Medicine in Transportation and the Federal Highway Patrol, which are&#13;
responsible for transport services including vehicle regulation, safety and police functions.&#13;
SCT also maintains a fully staffed and equipped unit (SCT Regional Center) in each state&#13;
to carry out regional construction, maintenance and operations.&#13;
2.5    Before 1989, SCT constructed some 950 km of toll roads and 32 bridges.&#13;
CAPUFE is responsible for their operation and maintenance. Since 1989, most new toll&#13;
roads have been built by private sector companies, which also operate and maintain them&#13;
(para. 2.13).&#13;
2.6    SCT's General Directorate for Federal Highways (DGCF) designs most of the&#13;
federal highways and bridges in house, employing modern techniques; the criteria and&#13;
standards used (Table 2-3) are adequate. Most of the construction work is done by&#13;
DGCF through contracting, but some modernization (widening) works are handled by&#13;
DGCC using the same standards. There are several Mexican consulting firms engaged in&#13;
highway and bridge design, and SCT is increasingly using them to prepare the engineering&#13;
of major works.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10&#13;
Table 2-3: Federal Highway Design Criteria and Standards&#13;
CLASS                   E          D         C          B           A2          A4           A4S&#13;
Less&#13;
ITEM                    than 100   100-500   500-1500   1500-3000   3000-5000   5000-20000   5000-20000&#13;
AADT a/  AADT        AADT      AADT         AADT       AADT b/    AADT b/&#13;
Design Speed (KPH)&#13;
Flat terrain                 50-70      50-70     70-100    80-100         90-110     90-110       90-110&#13;
Rolling terrain              40-60      40-60      50-80     60-90         70-110     70-110       70-110&#13;
Mountainous terrain          30-40      30-40      40-60     50-70         60-80      60-80        60-80&#13;
Radius (M)&#13;
Flat terrain                 70-150    70-150    150-350   210-420       270-420    270-420       270-420&#13;
Rolling terrain              40-105    40-105      70-210    105-270     150-350     150-350      150-350&#13;
Mountainous terrain          20-40      20-40      40-105    70-150       105-210    105-210      105-210&#13;
Maximum Grade (%)&#13;
Flat terrain                 7.0        .0        5.0        4.0         4.0         4.0          4.0&#13;
Rolling terrain              I0.0       9.0       7.0        6.0         5.0         5.0          5.0&#13;
Mountainous terrain           13.0      12.0      8.0        7.0         6.0         6.0          6.0&#13;
Roadway Standards&#13;
Roadway Width (M)            4.0        6.0       7.0        9.0          12.0       22.0          2 x 11.0&#13;
Pavement Width (M)           4.0        6.0       6.0        7.0         8.0         2 x 7.0       2 x 7.0&#13;
Shoulder Width (M)           -          -         0.5        1.0         2.5         3.0          3.0&#13;
Super-elevation (MIM)                -     -    -0.10 Max.&#13;
Cross-slope (%)              3          3         2          2           2           2            2&#13;
Width of Median (M)          -          -         -          -           -           1.0          8.0&#13;
Minimum Sight Distance (M)&#13;
Stopping&#13;
Flat terrain                 55-95      55-95     95-155    115-175       135-175    135-175      135-175&#13;
Rolling terrain              40-75      40-75     55-115     75-135        95-155     95-155       95-155&#13;
Mountainous terrain          30-40      30-40     40-75       55-95       75-115      75-115       75-115&#13;
Passing&#13;
Flat terrain                 -          255-315   315-450   380-485      405-495     405-495      405-495&#13;
Rolling terrain              -          100-270   225-380   270-405      315-450     315-450      315-450&#13;
Mountainous terrain          -          135-100   180-270   225-315      270-380    270-380       270-380&#13;
Bridge Design Standards        -                                      HS20&#13;
(AASHTO) c/&#13;
a/   AADT = Annual Average Daily Traffic.&#13;
b/   Separated Roadways.&#13;
c/   American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials.&#13;
Note:   Ranges shown are from "Minimum" to "Desirable".&#13;
Source: SCT - Dec. 1995&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I1&#13;
2.7   After over 30 years of road construction in Mexico, many experienced and well&#13;
equipped road construction contractors have emerged. Domestic firms must register&#13;
annually, providing detailed data on their operations. There is a wide range of capacity&#13;
among them, with emphasis on medium-sized firms able to undertake typical highway&#13;
contracts. Mexican firms win most international competitive bidding (ICB) contracts.&#13;
SCT personnel supervise construction but private consultants are increasingly being used&#13;
for this activity. The Government has reduced its once-dominant role in implementing&#13;
highway rehabilitation and resurfacing works and the private sector's involvement in these&#13;
activities is resulting in a more efficient implementation of the budget. About 70% of&#13;
SCT's highway rehabilitation works is being carried out by contract.&#13;
C. HIGHWAY MAINTENANCE&#13;
2.8   SCT, through DGCC, is responsible for maintaining the 42,182 km of the toll-free&#13;
portion of the federal network. CAPUFE, private concessionaires and the state&#13;
governments maintain about 1,420 km, 3,167 km and 1,096 km of expressways&#13;
respectively on concession with SCT. The toll roads are adequately maintained. DGCC&#13;
has also significantly improved its maintenance over the past three years under its&#13;
Highway Rehabilitation, Resurfacing and Maintenance Program (HRRM), being financed&#13;
under the HRTS, by: (a) introducing modern road and bridges maintenance management&#13;
systems; (b) contracting about 70% of its maintenance to the private sector; (c) training&#13;
staff; and (d) increasing significantly its spending on maintenance. SCT's spending on&#13;
maintenance and rehabilitation accounts for over 60% of its road budget. The result is that&#13;
during the past three years, DGCC has rehabilitated about 5,060 km, resurfaced about&#13;
18,700 km and annually maintained about 44,000 km. These achievements exceed the&#13;
HRRM's program targets by over 20%.&#13;
2.9   The Government's impact objective with the HRRM: is to bring the condition of at&#13;
least 50% of the federal road network to "good" condition and the rest to at least a "fair"&#13;
condition by the year 2007. To ensure that the modernization program does not shift funds&#13;
from road maintenance and compromise this objective, the Government committed itself,&#13;
during the mid-term review of the HRTS in March 1996, to: (a) spend at least US$300&#13;
million annually, in real terms, on rehabilitating and maintaining the federal road network&#13;
under SCT's responsibility in order to achieve the program's goals, and (b) present to the&#13;
Bank, by October 31 of each year during project implementation starting in 1997, its draft&#13;
road program for the subsequent fiscal year and, by April 30 each year starting in 1998, its&#13;
actual road program as updated to fully use the budget approved by the Legislature.&#13;
Annex A presents the objectives, progress and future direction of the HRRM.&#13;
D. SECTOR ISSUES&#13;
2.10  This section discusses the main issues in the highway sub-sector and how they are&#13;
being and would be resolved by the ongoing HRTS Project and the proposed project. The&#13;
issues cover SCT's future role in the highway sub-sector and the organizational changes it&#13;
needs, its institutional capacity, the toll road system, highway sector planning and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12&#13;
financing, truck size and weight limits, traffic safety and procedures for managing&#13;
environmental impact assessment.&#13;
2.11   SCT's Role and Organization. The Government needs to review SCT's evolving&#13;
role and organization to reflect two confluent developments: (a) the increasing&#13;
participation of the private sector in building and operating toll roads and in carrying out&#13;
road maintenance and (b) the Government's ongoing decentralization of road&#13;
administration to the states and its plans to transfer about half of the federal road network&#13;
to the states. Over the past five years, the private sector has helped to build about 5,000&#13;
km of high-standard federal roads which it is operating as toll roads and is considering&#13;
another 1,400 km over the next five years. Also, almost 70% of the maintenance of&#13;
federal roads is now being executed by private contractors. These developments,&#13;
combined with the rapidly-increasing use of consultants in all phases of project planning,&#13;
design and construction supervision, are moving SCT progressively into a role of manager&#13;
rather than operator in the sub-sector. This would require training of the remaining staff&#13;
to play the management role. Decentralization of road administration has been going on&#13;
for some time now in the SCT, but the emphasis so far has been on shifting responsibilities&#13;
and associated accountability from headquarters to SCT's centers in the states. The&#13;
planned transfer of road administration of about half of the federal network would require:&#13;
(a) a further review of the role, function, organization and size of the SCT centers and (b)&#13;
a review of the technical, administrative and financial capacity of each receiving state in&#13;
order to implement a realistic schedule of transfer and provide the necessary funds for the&#13;
transferred roads for a realistic time period. The proposed project includes a study on&#13;
SCT's future organization, staffing and a training program for staff (para. 3.7 (b)).&#13;
2.12 SCT's Institutional Capacity. Modernization of the physical infrastructure of the&#13;
federal road system alone would be insufficient to achieve the transport efficiency aimed at&#13;
by SCT. SCT needs to increase its institutional capacity. The Government, through the&#13;
ongoing HRTS Project is implementing an extensive institutional strengthening program,&#13;
comprising: (a) strengthening the capacity of SCT's Planning Coordination Office; (b)&#13;
completing the reorganization of the road maintenance directorate; (c) developing and&#13;
implementing highway maintenance management systems; (d) continuing the review of&#13;
highway cost recovery; (e) implementing revised vehicle size and weight regulations; (f)&#13;
implementing a detailed staff training program and (g) strengthening the administration of&#13;
traffic safety. Satisfactory progress has been made on items (b) and (c), but the rest of the&#13;
program has been slowed down due mostly to delays in hiring consultants or, in the case&#13;
of the training component, instructors. Moreover, past experience in Mexico has&#13;
demonstrated that effective institutional strengthening in the areas being covered under the&#13;
HRTS would require more time and effort than can be covered under the ongoing project.&#13;
The proposed project would therefore include resources for continuing and deepening the&#13;
institutional strengthening of the SCT (para 3.7).&#13;
2.13  The Private Toll Road Concession Program. An issue with which the toll road&#13;
concession program has had to grapple with is the high tolls the concessionaires have had&#13;
to charge to recuperate both their investment and operating costs. This has led to most&#13;
potential users preferring to use alternative, unimproved, but toll-free roads, causing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13&#13;
concessionaires to raise their tolls even higher. The need to charge high tolls arises from&#13;
the fact that the original concession proposals were evaluated on the basis of how fast the&#13;
roads would revert to Government's ownership (i.e., the length of the concession&#13;
contract). Consequently, bidders had an incentive to offer unrealistically short concession&#13;
periods. The problem was further exacerbated by the high initial construction costs due to&#13;
concessionaires being restricted to a set design by SCT. Over the past two years, SCT has&#13;
being working with the concessionaires on pilot reduced tolls to stimulate traffic and&#13;
therefore overall incomes to the concessionaires. The experiment has proved successful&#13;
and the concessionaires have agreed to reduce their toll levels by an average of 60% from&#13;
January 1, 1996. To avoid the same problems for the 1,400 km of toll concessions&#13;
expected to be awarded from 1996 to 2000, the SCT has revised and improved the&#13;
conditions under which the concessions are evaluated and granted. The changes include:&#13;
(a) using the lowest required toll, with a pre-determined concession period, as the criterion&#13;
to award concessions; (b) leaving the detailed designs to the bidder, with SCT only&#13;
stipulating the design parameters; (c) eliminating the arrangement of a guaranteed financial&#13;
rate of return; and (d) increasing the concessionaires equity contribution, thereby reducing&#13;
the debt component to acceptable levels.&#13;
2.14  Planning of Federal Road Activities. Planning of activities on the federal road&#13;
network is dispersed among various entities of the SCT. Planning at the project concept&#13;
and feasibility stage for construction is done within the Directorate General of Toll Roads&#13;
using an HDM-type life-cycle analysis model. Planning of maintenance and rehabilitation&#13;
works is carried out by the Direccion de Conservaci6n using a "more user-friendly"&#13;
version of the HDM III model known as SISTER. The Direcci6n General de Carreteras&#13;
Federales also has its own model for conducting economic analysis. The Direccion&#13;
General de Planeaci6n integrates the results of these activities into the federal highway&#13;
program. The system, in practice, has two significant drawbacks: (a) the lack of&#13;
coordination among the various directorates which leads to a duplication of efforts on data&#13;
collection and analysis and (b) the absence of an overall priority ranking of all the&#13;
individual activities so that they can compete for the scarce resources. The proposed&#13;
project would provide technical assistance to review current road planning processes&#13;
within the SCT and modify them to ensure efficient sharing of results from the different&#13;
agencies and establish integrated planning procedures (para. 3.7 (a)).&#13;
2.15  Highway Financing and Cost Recovery. The Government needs to establish a&#13;
financing mechanism to ensure adequate and timely financing of the federal network. In&#13;
spite of a major contribution from the private sector (an estimated US$7 billion to build&#13;
high-standard toll roads), financing for the federal road network still falls below needs to&#13;
restore, maintain and expand it. The Government has been spending about US$300&#13;
million annually on maintenance and rehabilitation to restore the network to an acceptable&#13;
standard by the year 2008. An increase in spending of US$400 annually would achieve&#13;
that goal in the year 2003. Moreover, the modernization of the existing network would&#13;
require an additional US$240 million a year of public funds over the next five years, in&#13;
addition to an expected private sector contribution of about US$4 billion from the private&#13;
sector for more toll roads. Under the ongoing HRTS, the Government is undertaking a&#13;
study of various alternative financing mechanisms for the highway sector to ensure its&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14&#13;
adequate funding. The HRTS is also providing technical assistance to the Government to&#13;
implement the study's recommendations on establishing an adequate and reliable&#13;
mechanism.&#13;
2.16  The bulk of federal highway expenditures over the past five years has been mostly&#13;
for road rehabilitation and maintenance (about 60% of the total US$520 million annual&#13;
outlays). With the start of the modernization program, there is going to be a strong&#13;
competition between maintenance and improvement for scarce resources. The&#13;
comprehensive planning model mentioned in para 3.7 would help in allocating available&#13;
funds efficiently to SCT's various road activities. In addition, at negotiations the&#13;
Government agreed to present to the dank during the joint annual project implementation&#13;
review meetings for the proposed project and for the HRTS Project its financing plan for&#13;
SCT's road activities for that year. This would enable adjusting the allocations to ensure&#13;
that the maintenance commitments are met.&#13;
2.17  Revenues to the highway sector come from road-user fees, private-sector financing&#13;
of toll road concessions, voluntary contributions from the trucking industry and loans from&#13;
international agencies. Road-user fees, mostly fuel taxes, license fees and tolls, estimated&#13;
at about US$2,300 million annually, cover adequately the sector's needs. However,&#13;
automobiles subsidize heavy vehicles. The Government has undertaken studies to&#13;
determine the exact imbalance between automobile and truck charges with a view to&#13;
reduce it.&#13;
2.18  Vehicle Weights and Dimensions. The Government issued revised regulations&#13;
on vehicle weights and dimensions in January 1994 to meet agreed standards under&#13;
NAFTA. Consultants, hired under the ongoing Highway Rehabilitation and Traffic Safety&#13;
Project have submitted their recommendations to SCT on the type and location of the&#13;
weigh bridges to be purchased and implementation is expected to start during the second&#13;
half of this year. The SCT is reviewing the pros and cons of the private sector playing a&#13;
role in operating the system either as a concession or a management contract.&#13;
2.19  Traffic Safety. SCT is now implementing its road safety program very&#13;
vigorously. The program has been included as an important objective of both SCT's 1990-&#13;
1994 and 1995-2000 National Programs for Transport Modernization. Very significant&#13;
progress has been made in improving vehicle inspection, driver training and licensing and&#13;
in the removal of hazardous locations. As a member of the North American Commercial&#13;
Vehicle Safety Alliance (CVSA), Mexico is under pressure to improve its traffic safety&#13;
measures. The proposed project would provide for additional resources to continue the&#13;
improvement of road safety.&#13;
2.20 Environmental Impact of Highway Projects. Existing Mexican laws provide&#13;
for adequate safeguards against adverse environmental impacts from road activities. The&#13;
SCT also has the necessary organizational set-up to comply with the laws and has&#13;
developed tools which should help to better coordinate the collection and use of data&#13;
during the different stages of project development, and internal communication on&#13;
environmental issues. Article 27 of the Mexican Constitution establishes the Federal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15&#13;
Government's obligation to conserve the nation's natural resources. The General Law on&#13;
Ecological Balance and Protection of the Environment, enacted in March 1988,&#13;
constitutes the present legal framework to deal with transport environmental issues.&#13;
Under this law, the Government must (a) establish federal environmental standards; (b)&#13;
evaluate the environmental impact of major projects; (c) carry out environmental&#13;
protection actions in areas under federal jurisdiction; and (d) create and manage federal&#13;
natural protected areas. In addition, Articles 19 and 20 of the 1993 Procurement and&#13;
Public Works Law and Article 12 of its regulation require that the environmental impact&#13;
of public works be studied, and that environmental conditions be preserved wherever&#13;
public works are carried out. Shortly after the General Ecology Law went into effect the&#13;
Secretariat of Urban Development and Ecology, SEDUE (recently transformed into&#13;
SEDESOL), published a regulation on environmental impact assessments, which defined&#13;
specific conditions for mandatory SEDESOL review of an impact assessment, procedures&#13;
for preparing and presenting impact assessments, and sanctions for failure to comply with&#13;
the regulations. In order to coordinate the execution of environmental impact assessment&#13;
of transport projects with SEDESOL, SCT's Environmental Affairs Unit (EAU) within the&#13;
General Coordination of Planning has been strengthened to six full-time staff and is&#13;
receiving technical assistance under the HRTS Project to introduce models to facilitate&#13;
environmental assessments. The project would provide for improved coordination among&#13;
EAU and other SCT directorates which are also independently carrying out their own&#13;
environmental assessments, with consultants assistance, and to disseminate the results of&#13;
EAU's results in improving environmental assessments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16&#13;
THE PROJECT&#13;
A. PROJECT ORIGIN&#13;
3.1   Preparation of the proposed project started in August 1995 following a request&#13;
from the Government for Bank assistance in modernizing the federal highway network.&#13;
The project's design and scope resulted from discussions between the Bank, SCT,&#13;
BANOBRAS and SHCP during several project preparation missions to Mexico between&#13;
August and December 1995. The project was appraised in February 1996 and&#13;
negotiations started in Washington in May 1996. Negotiations were suspended because&#13;
the Bank and the Government failed to reach agreement on the framework for the&#13;
resettlement documents to be prepared for the road modernization sub-projects.&#13;
Following protracted discussions, negotiations were resumed on May 15, 1997 and&#13;
completed on May 29, 1997. The Government has submitted a Project Implementation Plan,&#13;
outlining the project's objectives, scope and composition, estimated costs and financing plan&#13;
and the arrangements for project implementation.&#13;
B. PROJECT OBJECTIVES&#13;
3.2   The project would have two broad objectives. The first would be to help meet the&#13;
expected traffic growth on the federal road network and to reduce road transport system&#13;
costs. This would be achieved by: (a) improving the capacity and thereby the service&#13;
quality of the federal road network and (b) farther improving the safety on the network.&#13;
The second objective would be to improve the institutional capacity to manage the road&#13;
network by: (a) strengthening SCT's capacity to formulate work programs, efficiently&#13;
allocate highway funds among road activities and to manage environmental impact&#13;
assessment and mitigation and (b) increasing the capacity of selected states to manage&#13;
their road networks.&#13;
C. PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
3.3   The project, which would finance a time slice (1998 to 2002) of SCT's Federal&#13;
Roads Modernization Program (FRMP), would consist of: (1) civil works to increase the&#13;
capacity and traffic safety of the federal network (about US$800 million equivalent),&#13;
including providing additional lanes on some road sections, building climbing lanes on&#13;
others, improving horizontal and vertical alignments, providing adequate road shoulders&#13;
and curbs and removing hazardous spots; (2) institutional strengthening (US$61 million)&#13;
directed at SCT and selected state highway organizations for improving management&#13;
systems and procedures, training staff and reviewing the role and needs of the SCT centers&#13;
in the states; (3) further support to SCT to implement actions on road sector financing, to&#13;
improve multi-modal transport operations, to continue improving road safety and&#13;
environmental impact assessment and mitigation measures in the planning, construction&#13;
and operation of transport facilities (US$2 million).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17&#13;
Federal Highway Modernization Program&#13;
3.4   SCT's FRMP is based on the results of a series of analyses conducted by the SCT&#13;
covering: (a) road surface conditions, (b) pavement bearing capacity for current and future&#13;
traffic, (c) levels of service; (d) safety, and (e) the attractiveness of proposed&#13;
improvements to potential private concessionaires. SCT selected about 2,016 km of the&#13;
highest priority roads for modernization over the period 1996 to 2002 using public funds.&#13;
The roads selected for 1996, about 158 km, have been modernized by SCT using its own&#13;
funds; those for 1997, about 122 km, have been contracted out and will be financed&#13;
retroactively by the Bank. The selected road sections for the indicative program have high&#13;
economic returns, serve important export/import corridors and/or regional integration, are&#13;
close to saturation, have poor safety and would not be attractive to potential private&#13;
investors. In addition, the project would provide for the improvement of about 200&#13;
hazardous road locations (mostly intersections and sharp curves). SCT's findings and&#13;
conclusions from these analyses are presented in a report entitled "Programa de&#13;
Modernizaci6n de la Red Carretera 1996-2002" which is included in the Project File. The&#13;
indicative list of roads, with the current and planned future design standards, is presented&#13;
in Table 3.1.&#13;
3.5   The SCT also selected two road stretches totaling about 324 km to make up the&#13;
1997 and 1998 program (Table 3.2). The Bank has reviewed the feasibility studies,&#13;
detailed engineering, environmental impact assessments and socio-economic studies&#13;
carried out with consultants' assistance for these roads, and found them acceptable. The&#13;
1997 and 1998 road sections were selected using the same criteria to be used for the&#13;
remaining project roads during implementation (para.4. 1). During negotiations, the&#13;
Government confirmed the composition and scope of the 1997 and 1998 program.&#13;
3.6   The works under the program, which are aimed at increasing capacity and&#13;
improving safety, would include: (a) eliminating bottlenecks such as narrow bridges and&#13;
dangerous intersections; (b) widening and/or adding lanes, building climbing lanes,&#13;
improving horizontal and vertical alignment and adding road shoulders; (c) expanding&#13;
some of the most saturated lanes from two to four lanes; (d) upgrading and modernizing&#13;
road signalization and; (e) removing hazardous spots.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18&#13;
Table 3-1:&#13;
Indicative Modernization Program and Characteristics - Civil Works&#13;
Subproject                   Section                           Length   Upgrading&#13;
Beginning at         Ending at       (km)   From  To&#13;
San Luis Potosi - Puerto Mexico                                          236&#13;
Huizache              Matehuala          34        A2    A4&#13;
Matehuala             San Roberto          129     A2    A4&#13;
San Roberto           Pto. Mexico          73      B2    A4&#13;
Tampico - Linares                                                          198&#13;
Cuauhtemoc            Est.Manuel           18      B2    A2&#13;
Est.Goni..alez        Est.Zaragoza         61      B2    A2&#13;
Barretal              Tomasenio            39      B2    A2&#13;
Escobedo              Linares              62      B2    A2&#13;
Fresnillo-Torreon-Cuencame                                                 148&#13;
Rio Grande            Cuencame             148      C     A2&#13;
Tampico-Veracruz                                                           328&#13;
Cardel                Gpe. Victoria        131     B2    A2&#13;
Tuxpan                Tampico              197     B2    A2&#13;
Villahermosa-Merida                                                        490&#13;
Villahermosa          Cd. del Carmen       168     A2    A4&#13;
Cd. del Carmen        Champoton            149     A2    A4&#13;
Camipeche             Bord.                110     A2    A4&#13;
Camp. /Yuc.&#13;
Border Camp./Yuc.    Merida                65      A2    A4&#13;
Saltillo-Monclova                                                          21&#13;
Ramal La Muralla      Toward P. Negras    10      Realigmnent&#13;
Castaiios             La Gloria            11      A2    A4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
19&#13;
Table 3-2: Project Data and Status of Preparation for 1997 and 1998 Roads&#13;
LENGTH       BASIC       FINAL    RIGHT OF    ENVIRONMENTAL           SOCIOLOGIC&#13;
FEDERAL ROAD                        ROAD SUBPROJECT                              STUDIES   DESIGN       WAY ()          IMPACT (*)          STUDY(.)&#13;
KMS.         (%)         (%)        (%)               (%)                (%)&#13;
PROGRAM FOR 1997&#13;
SAN LUIS POTOSI - SALTILLO&#13;
HUIZACHE - MATEHUALA                        83          100        100         100              100                 100&#13;
TAMPICO - LINARES&#13;
BARRETAL - TOMASENO                         39          100        100         100              100                 100&#13;
PROGRAM FOR 1998&#13;
SAN LUIS POTOSI-SALTILLO              MATEHUALA-SAN ROBERTO                       129          100        100         100              100                 100&#13;
SAN ROBERTO-PTO. MEXICO                     73          100        100         100              100                 100&#13;
TOTAL KILOMETERS TO BE                                                            324&#13;
MODERNIZED IN1997 AND 1998&#13;
() Existing right of way, except in the case of new by-passes&#13;
()  To be prepared by environmetal experts&#13;
(-) To be prepared by a sociologist&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20&#13;
Institutional Strengthening Component&#13;
3.7   The institutional strengthening component would continue, reinforce and expand&#13;
actions being undertaken under the ongoing Highway Rehabilitation and Traffic Safety&#13;
Project. Specific areas to be covered, proposed by SCT at the start of project preparation,&#13;
include the following:&#13;
Highway Sub-sector Planning and Resource Allocation. Under the HRTS, the&#13;
SCT's Planning Coordination Office has been established and is being&#13;
provided technical assistance to prepare project planning and evaluation&#13;
manuals. In addition, SCT needs a comprehensive highway planning&#13;
resource allocation model to efficiently distribute its limited budget among&#13;
competing highway activities. The proposed project would provide technical&#13;
assistance to CGP to develop the model and train higher-level staff to use it.&#13;
The scope and terms of reference for consulting services for preparing the&#13;
model were reviewed and agreed during project preparation. The agreement&#13;
was confirmed during negotiations;&#13;
Review of SCT's Role and Organization. SCT's ongoing decentralization of&#13;
road administration and its increasing normative role requires reviewing its&#13;
role in the road sector and re-organizing it accordingly. The project would&#13;
provide for technical assistance to carry out the review and to assist in&#13;
implementing the recommendations. The project would also provide for&#13;
assistance to the road agencies in selected states to improve their&#13;
organizations and train staff Terms of reference for the consultants services&#13;
were confirmed at negotiations;&#13;
Road Traffic Safety. The HRTS is improving road safety through: (a) improving&#13;
driver behavior and increasing public road traffic safety awareness, (b)&#13;
training inspectors, supervisors and examiners of truck drivers, and (c)&#13;
providing technical assistance for research on road safety, conducting&#13;
information campaigns, preparing programs to eliminate about 300&#13;
hazardous highway locations, and updating vehicle safety standards. The&#13;
proposed project would continue the technical assistance for road safety,&#13;
especially preparing programs for removing additional hazardous spots.&#13;
Improvement in Environmental Control. SCT's Environmental Affairs Unit&#13;
(EAU) is being strengthened under the HRTS. To comply with&#13;
environmental requirements, SCT has revised its work specifications for&#13;
HRRM works and improved those parts related to the coverage of cultural&#13;
patrimony, the managing of quarries and pollution control of construction&#13;
equipment. These revisions have been included in the bidding documents&#13;
for construction of civil works and are adequate. EAU has developed and&#13;
is calibrating a simulation model for assessing environmental impacts of&#13;
transport facilities throughout Mexico. EAU is currently working in&#13;
relative isolation from SCT's other directorates involved in road planning,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21&#13;
construction and maintenance. The proposed project would provide&#13;
technical assistance to SCT to review its procedures for managing&#13;
environmental impact assessments in order to avoid duplication of efforts&#13;
and lack of coordination; and.&#13;
Facilitation and Improvement of Inter-Modal Transport. The project would&#13;
provide consulting services to review and analyze inter-modal transport in&#13;
Mexico, including the regulatory framework thereof and recommend&#13;
actions for its improvement.&#13;
Consultancy Services&#13;
3.8   The project would provide for consultant services for assisting:&#13;
the general directorate of Toll Roads (GDTR) in the preparation of the traffic and&#13;
economic and financial feasibility studies required to identify and select&#13;
sub-projects to be included in the program (para. 4.8 (a)); and&#13;
DGCF in the preparation of environmental, social and engineering studies,&#13;
supervision of construction; and the coordination of the program (para. 4.8&#13;
3.9   The project would provide for the improvement of about 200 hazardous road&#13;
locations (mostly intersections and sharp curves). These would be in addition to those&#13;
included in the works under the 950 km of road sections and the locations being improved&#13;
under the HRTS. The works would be undertaken by contract. These improvements&#13;
would be based on a master list of hazardous road sections prepared from a combination&#13;
of accident statistics developed by DGTT and the Federal Highway Patrol, and from field&#13;
visits. Each year, SCT , with consultants assistance, would select the locations it plans to&#13;
improve and submit a report to the Bank justifying each improvement, both technically&#13;
and economically. The project would also provide for consultant services for detailed&#13;
preparation of the program and for supervision of the works.&#13;
3.10  Staff Training. The ongoing HRTS includes a sizable staff training program for&#13;
the SCT (Annex B). The proposed project provides for deepening the training to SCT in&#13;
areas such as bidding and contract administration, budgetary and resource allocation&#13;
among road activities and project evaluation techniques and assessment of environmental&#13;
impacts and designing mitigation plans. The project would also include training for new&#13;
areas such as inter-modal transport and electronic data interchange systems, transport&#13;
corridor analysis and planning and highway financing. Lastly, the project would provide&#13;
for a parallel training program to the ongoing one under the HRTS for four selected states&#13;
in Mexico. Training to be included in the project would also address the highway sector&#13;
entities at states' level. At negotiations, the scope for the training component was agreed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22&#13;
D. PROJECT COST AND FINANCING&#13;
3.11   The total cost of the project is estimated at about US$ 865 million equivalent with&#13;
a foreign exchange component of about US$375 million based on March 1996 prices and&#13;
including physical and price contingencies. Identifiable taxes and duties are about US$120&#13;
million and the total project cost, net of taxes, is US$743 million equivalent. The cost&#13;
estimates for the civil works are based upon detailed estimates prepared by the Direcci6n&#13;
General de Carreteras Federales (DGCF), with the assistance of consultants, and are&#13;
similar to those obtained in recent contracts. The costs of the highway safety training and&#13;
technical assistance components were estimated in accordance with prevailing costs of&#13;
materials and services. The estimated man-month rate for local consultants varies between&#13;
US$4,000 and US$7,000 and for expatriate consultants, between US$10,000 and&#13;
US$15,000. The proposed loan of US$475 million would finance 55% of the total project&#13;
cost. The Government would finance the remaining US$388 million equivalent. SCT's&#13;
budget for 1997 provides a sufficient amount to cover the project's first year program up&#13;
to December 31, 1997, the end of Mexico's fiscal year. A summary of project cost&#13;
estimates and financing plan is presented in Tables 3.3 and 3.4.&#13;
E. SUSTAINABILITY&#13;
3.12  The sustainability of the project would be determined by: (a) adequate maintenance&#13;
of the project roads after their improvement; (b) better traffic management to ensure that&#13;
the expected levels of service are attained; (c) improvement in traffic policing, as a&#13;
complement to removing physical road hazards, in order to ensure the expected&#13;
improvement in traffic safety; and (d) the ability of SCT to more efficiently allocate&#13;
available highway funds among activities on the federal road network. The&#13;
implementation of the maintenance management system, developed under the HRTS, and&#13;
the adoption of a proposed road maintenance fund being addressed under the HRTS,&#13;
financed from road-user charges would help to insure a stable source of funding for road&#13;
maintenance. The proposed project would further help to improve highway signs,&#13;
introduce measures to reduce roadside friction and improve the capacity of the Federal&#13;
Highway Police to remove incapacitated vehicles. Assistance for highway safety, being&#13;
covered under the ongoing HRTS, would be continued and strengthened under the&#13;
proposed project. Lastly, efficient systems of allocating highway funds among different&#13;
road activities, already introduced successfully in other countries with the Bank's&#13;
assistance, would be introduced in SCT to help ensure that available funds are spent on&#13;
the highest priority activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
23&#13;
Table 3-3: Summary of Project Cost and Financing Plan&#13;
(US$ Million)&#13;
A. Estimated Project Costs:                           Local   Foreign    Total a/&#13;
(US$ Million)&#13;
FRM Program                               408.2      272.2      680.4&#13;
Consultants Services                        6.8       45.5       52.3&#13;
Training                                    0.1        0.9        1.0&#13;
Total Base Costs                     415.2      318.5      733.7&#13;
Contingencies&#13;
Physical                              41.5      31.9        73.4&#13;
Price                                 31.7      24.4        56.1&#13;
Total Contingencies                   73.3      56.2       129.5&#13;
Total Project Costs                       488.5      374.7      863.2&#13;
B. Financing Plan:&#13;
Government of Mexico                      388.2        ----     388.2&#13;
IBRD (multiple currency)                   100.3     374.7      475.0&#13;
Total Financing                           488.5      374.7      863.2&#13;
a/ Totals may not add up due to rounding&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24&#13;
Table 3-4: Project Costs and Annual Expenditures (US$ Million)&#13;
PROJECT COMPONENT                       ANNUAL EXPENDITURES ()--- ---  TOTAL()&#13;
1998     1999    2000      2001     2002&#13;
A.CIVIL WORKS (Indicative)&#13;
HUIZACHE-MATEHUALA                          21.56    21.56                                  43.13&#13;
MATEHUALA-SAN ROBERTO                       43.13    28.75                                  71.88&#13;
SAN ROBERTO-PTO. MEXICO                              28.75    28.75                         57.50&#13;
LA MURALLA                                                     8.34                          8.34&#13;
CASTANOS-LA GLORIA                                    3.59                                   3.59&#13;
CUENCAME-RIO GRANDE                         20.41    20.41                                  40.83&#13;
VILLAHERMOSA-CD. DEL CARMEN                 24.15    24.15                                  48.30&#13;
BORD STATES CAMP./YUC.-MERIDA                        18.69                                  18.69&#13;
CUAUHTEMOC-EST. MANUEL                       7.91                                            7.91&#13;
GONZALEZ-ZARAGOZA                           17.25                                           17.25&#13;
BARRETAL-TOMASENO                           10.78                                           10.78&#13;
ESCOBEDO-LINARES                            12.22                                           12.22&#13;
CARDEL-GUADALUPE VICTORIA                                              32.99    32.99       65.98&#13;
CAMPECHE-LIM.EDOS.CAMP.NYUC                                            21.08    10.54       31.63&#13;
CD. DEL CARMEN-CHAMPOTON                                      21.28    21.28                42.55&#13;
EST. MANUEL-MATAMOROS                                         32.58    16.29                48.88&#13;
SOTO LA MARINA-MATAMOROS                                    50.3125    50.31    50.31      150.94&#13;
SUBTOTAL: A                                157.41   145.91   141.26   141.95    93.84     680.37&#13;
B. CONSULTANTS SERVICES&#13;
(a) INSTITUTIONAL STRENGTHENING&#13;
BUDGET ALLOCATION IMPROV.                             0.21     0.21                          0.42&#13;
NATIONAL AND STATE PLANNING                  0.50     0.50     0.25                          1.25&#13;
HIGHWAY DECENTRALIZATION                     0.52     0.50     0.50                          1.52&#13;
INTERMODAL TRANSPORT                                  0.22                                   0.22&#13;
HIGHWAY MAINTENANCE FINANCING                         0.21     0.21                          0.42&#13;
(b) STUDIES AND SUPERVISION&#13;
STUDIES (*-..)                                        4.38     4.24     4.26     1.58       14.45&#13;
SUPERVISION                                  7.87     7.30     7.06     7.10     4.69       34.02&#13;
SUBTOTAL: B                                  8.89    13.31    12.47    11.36     6.27       52.30&#13;
C. TRAINING                                           0.25     0.25     0.25     0.25        1.00&#13;
SUBTOTAL: C                                           0.25     0.25     0.25     0.25        1.00&#13;
TOTAL COSTO BASE                           166.30   159.47   153.98   153.56   100.36      733.67&#13;
D. CONTINGENCIES&#13;
PHYSICAL (10%)                              16.63    15.95    15.40    15.36    10.04       73.37&#13;
PRICE (---)                                  4.39     8.52    12.49    16.81    13.90       56.11&#13;
SUBTOTAL: D                                 21.02    24.47    27.89    32.16    23.94      129.48&#13;
TOTAL: PROJECT COST                        187.32   183.94   181.87   185.72   124.30      863.14&#13;
Cost estimates include taxes amounting to 15%&#13;
Based on the project implementation schedule&#13;
) 2.4% per year from 1998 onwards&#13;
(**) Final engineering studies for the 1998 program have been completed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
A. SUB-PROJECT SELECTION, PREPARATION AND EVALUATION&#13;
4.1    The investment sub-projects to be implemented during 1997 and 1998 were selected&#13;
during appraisal and agreed at negotiations. The sub-projects to be executed each year&#13;
thereafter would be selected and submitted to the Bank for its review by October 31 of the year&#13;
preceding the year of implementation. The submissions would be supported by detailed&#13;
reports on the economic, financial, environmental, social and technical studies for the selected&#13;
sub-projects. These studies would be carried out by consultants/experts acceptable to the&#13;
Bank. Each investment sub-project will meet the following criteria:&#13;
have a positive NPV and an ERR, calculated in accordance with a method&#13;
satisfactory to the Bank, of at least 12%;-&#13;
have a detailed financial analysis of each sub-project demonstrating that they are&#13;
not attractive for private concession;&#13;
not involve negative environmental impacts for which satisfactory mitigation&#13;
measures have not been clearly defined through acceptable environmental&#13;
assessment;,&#13;
have resettlement documents acceptable to the Bank for projects involving&#13;
resettlement;&#13;
have a structural design life, in the case of roads, of at least 20 years (unless a&#13;
technical study demonstrates that a shorter design life is appropriate).&#13;
The above procedures and criteria were confirmed at negotiations.&#13;
4.2    For studies, technical assistance and training, the following would be required to be&#13;
submitted to the Bank before the annual review:&#13;
for studies and technical assistance, detailed terms of reference, manpower&#13;
requirements, cost estimates and implementation schedule; and&#13;
for training courses, seminars and workshops, the specific objectives, trainers' CVs&#13;
and fees, number of participants by agency, duration and detailed cost&#13;
estimates.&#13;
The above requirements were confirmed at negotiations.&#13;
B. CONDITIONS AND PROCEDURES FOR PROCUREMENT OF SUB-PROJECTS&#13;
4.3    The Bank loan would help to finance only contracts related to project components&#13;
selected according to the criteria outlined in para. 4.1 and that the tendering is in&#13;
accordance with procedures and design standards agreed with the Bank. SCT would be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26&#13;
directly responsible for the procurement of items under the project. SCT has the capacity&#13;
to carry out the procurement program under the project.&#13;
4.4   All project components financed under the proposed Bank loan would be procured&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's Guidelines for Procurement (January 1995). Procurement&#13;
procedures would be as follows:&#13;
a) to the extent practicable, contracts for works shall be grouped into bid packages&#13;
estimated to cost the equivalent of US$10 million or more each and would be awarded&#13;
through international competitive bidding (ICB) and prequalification procedures, using&#13;
standard documents agreed with the Bank. Civil works valued at less than US$10&#13;
million equivalent, up to an aggregate of US$200.1 million, would be procured&#13;
through national competitive bidding procedures (NCB), using standard documents&#13;
agreed with the Bank, and where foreign bidders would have the opportunity to&#13;
compete. All bidding documents would include specifications to safeguard the&#13;
environment during construction. It is not foreseen that there would be any&#13;
procurement of goods in this project.&#13;
b) Consultants for studies, supervision, and technical assistance would be selected and&#13;
engaged following the Bank's Guidelines for the Use of Consultants (August 1981).&#13;
The cost of these services are expected to aggregate to US$61.5 million. For complex&#13;
time-based assignments, Bank-issued standard forms of contract would be used.&#13;
Where no relevant standard contract documents have been issued by the Bank, other&#13;
standard forms acceptable to the Bank shall be used.&#13;
4.5   All contracts for civil works estimated to cost US$10 million equivalent or more&#13;
would be subject to the Bank's prior review of the procurement documentation&#13;
(advertising, bidding documents, bid evaluation, and contract award). The total value of&#13;
these contracts would be US$600.3 million and would represent about 75% of all Bank-&#13;
financed civil works. Prior review would also be required for the first two contracts for&#13;
civil works to be awarded under NCB procedure, and for all contracts for consulting&#13;
services valued at US$100,000 equivalent or more for consulting firms, and of more than&#13;
US$50,000 equivalent for individuals. The provisions of the Guidelines requiring prior&#13;
Bank review or approval of budgets, short lists selection procedures, letters of invitation,&#13;
proposals, evaluation reports and contract, would not apply to contracts for the&#13;
employment of consulting firms valued at less than US$100,000 equivalent each, and to&#13;
contracts for the employment of individuals estimated to cost less than US$50,000&#13;
equivalent each. However, said exceptions to Bank prior review would not be applicable&#13;
to: (i) the terms of reference for such contracts, (ii) single-source selection of consulting&#13;
firms; (iii) assignments of critical nature as reasonably determined by the Bank; (iv)&#13;
amendments to contracts for the employment of consulting firms raising the contract value&#13;
to US$100,000 equivalent or more; and (v) amendments to contracts for the employment&#13;
of individual consultants raising the value of the contract to US$50,000 equivalent or&#13;
more. The financing for training would be based on a detailed program to be submitted to&#13;
the Bank for approval.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27&#13;
4.6   Project cost breakdown by procurement method is presented in Table 4-1; the amounts&#13;
in parenthesis show allocations of loan proceeds. Procurement arrangements were confirmed&#13;
at negotiations.&#13;
C. IMPLEMENTATION AND MONITORING&#13;
4.7   BANOBRAS will be the Borrower and will on-lend the loan proceeds to the&#13;
Government (for SCT) under the same terms and conditions as the Bank loan, with&#13;
Government bearing the foreign exchange and interest rate risks. It will be a condition of&#13;
loan effectiveness that Borrower and the Guarantor enter into contractual arrangements&#13;
satisfactory to the Bank for the transfer of loan funds.&#13;
4.8   SCT would be responsible for the preparation/execution of most of the project&#13;
components through its various Directorates, as follows:&#13;
DGTR for identifying the sub-projects for the annual programs and canrying out&#13;
the feasibility, social and financial studies and for technology transfer to the&#13;
states;&#13;
DGPI for preparing the annual highway budget and for transferring highway&#13;
planning capabilities to the states road agencies and for organizing and&#13;
making operational the entity that would administer the funds generated&#13;
through the road users' charges;&#13;
DGCF for preparing the final engineering and environmental and social impact&#13;
assessments for the sub-projects to be included in the annual program, for&#13;
managing the execution of the civil works and for implementing the&#13;
resettlement documents;&#13;
DGMPT for implementing the assistance for traffic safety; and&#13;
DGTT for implementing the staff training components of the project, including&#13;
supporting the training of the states highway staff.&#13;
The social impact analysis to determine the need for involuntary resettlement and to design&#13;
the resettlement documents will be carried out by qualified social scientists under terms of&#13;
reference satisfactory to the Bank. SCT will be responsible for implementing resettlement&#13;
actions arising from the project. SCT has been using both state and municipal level&#13;
entities to assist it in carrying out resettlement actions depending upon each particular&#13;
case. SCT will use mechanisms acceptable to the Bank to carry out resettlement cases&#13;
under the proposed project. During negotiations it was agreed that institutional measures&#13;
acceptable to the Bank for carrying out remedial measures in accordance with the&#13;
resettlement framework shall be in place and to be fully operational prior to the time that&#13;
any such remedial measures are required and, in any event, that they shall be in place and&#13;
operational not later than one year after the date of the Loan Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28&#13;
4.9     Project supervision is expected to take place at least three times during the first&#13;
year of project implementation and at least twice a year to monitor progress of the&#13;
proposed project. Supervision missions at the appropriate point of the annual budget&#13;
cycle would seek assurance of the adequacy of the funding required for the annual&#13;
modernization programs. Because of the country-wide nature of the project, supervision&#13;
requirements are expected to be about 20 staff weeks per year.&#13;
Table 4-1: Procurement Methods and Disbursements (US$ Million)&#13;
I. Procurement&#13;
Procurement Method&#13;
ITEM                     DESCRIPTION                     ICB     NCB   Other a/ TOTAL&#13;
Civil Works    Highway Modernization&#13;
Contracts over US$ 10 million               600.3                      600.3&#13;
(Bank financing)               (315.3)                    (315.3)&#13;
Contracts under US$ 10 million                      200.1              200.1&#13;
(Bank financing)                       (105.1)           (105.1)&#13;
Subtotal: Civil Works                    600.3   200.1              800.4&#13;
(Bank financing)               (315.3)  (105.1)          (420.5)&#13;
Consultants&#13;
Services       (a) Institutional Strengthening                                    4.5       4.5&#13;
(Bank financing)                                  (3.9)     (3.9)&#13;
(b) Other Consultants Services                                   57.0      57.0&#13;
(Bank financing)                                 (49.6)    (49.6)&#13;
Subtotal: Consultants Services                  61.5      61.5&#13;
(Bank financing)                                 (53.5)    (53.5)&#13;
Training       Courses and Seminars                                               1.2       1.2&#13;
(Bank financing)                                  (1.0)     (1.0)&#13;
Subtotal:Training                                         1.2       1.2&#13;
(Bank financing)                                  (1.0)     (1.0)&#13;
TOTAL (*)                                      600.3   200.1    62.7    863.1&#13;
(Bank financing)               (315.3)  (105.1)  (54.5)   (475.0)&#13;
(*) Totals include taxes and duties and may not add up due to rounding&#13;
al "Other" includes direct contracting, and the Bank's consultants selection procedures&#13;
Figures in parenthesis are the respective amnounts financed by the Bank loan and include contingencies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
29&#13;
II. Disbursements&#13;
% of net&#13;
Amounts             Expenditures&#13;
Category                                     To be Financed&#13;
(1) Civil Works                        357.4                 53%&#13;
(3) Services                           45.5                  100%&#13;
(4) Training                            0.9                  100%&#13;
(5) Unallocated                        71.2&#13;
Total                                  475.0&#13;
FY1 998   FY1999   FY2000   FY2001   FY2002   FY2003   FY2004&#13;
Annual        80.0      80.0     80.0     90.0     75.0      50.0     20.0&#13;
Cummulative   80.0    160.0    240.0    330.0    405.0    455.0    475.0&#13;
a/ "Other" includes direct contracting and the Bank's consultant selection procedures.&#13;
4.10   Semestral reviews, in April and October of each year, and coinciding with those of&#13;
the ongoing HRTS project, would be held to review the progress in project&#13;
implementation and to agree on the program for the current year. The reviews would&#13;
focus on:&#13;
(a)    the progress against the previous annual project implementation schedule;&#13;
(b)    the level and composition of SCT's road budget for the fiscal year in which&#13;
the review takes place;&#13;
(c)    the performance against the project monitoring indicators; and&#13;
(d)    the finalization of the selection of sub-projects for the current year, taking&#13;
into consideration the balance in SCT's road budget.&#13;
SCT would provide a report on progress of each component of the project, at least one&#13;
month before the date fixed for the annual review.&#13;
4.11 In April 2000, the Government and the Bank would conduct a mid-term review of&#13;
progress in project implementation, which in addition to items covered in the annual&#13;
reviews, would focus on:&#13;
the adequacy of funding for activities in the federal road network, including that&#13;
for the ongoing project;&#13;
the progress made on the institutional aspects being supported under the loan;&#13;
the implementation road improvements included in the project;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30&#13;
the progress in the commitments and disbursements of loan funds, to be assessed&#13;
on the basis of the summary expenditures and on the physical progress of&#13;
all eligible sub-projects;&#13;
the progress in the training program, including the number of staff successfully&#13;
trained and the impact of the training on SCT's capacity;&#13;
the progress made in bringing the federal network to good condition; and&#13;
the future direction of the project, including any necessary changes in objectives&#13;
and scope.&#13;
4.12  In addition to the above, during negotiations, agreement was reached with the&#13;
Government that the SCT would provide: (a) every six months, progress reports to the&#13;
Bank for monitoring purposes, on the basis of a format and methodology acceptable to the&#13;
Bank; and (b) within six months of the closing date, an input to the Project&#13;
Implementation Completion Report.&#13;
D. ACCOUNTS AND AUDITS&#13;
4.13  Agreement was reached during negotiations that BANOBRAS will: (i) maintain&#13;
and cause to be maintained the records and accounts adequate to reflect its operations and&#13;
financial position; and (ii) have the records of the project accounts audited in line with the&#13;
standing arrangements between BANOBRAS and the Bank and that the use of statement&#13;
of expenditures and the special account (para. 4.16) would be subject to a separate&#13;
opinion in the audit report.&#13;
E. DISBURSEMENTS&#13;
4.14  Standard disbursements profiles prepared by the Bank for the LAC region, and in&#13;
particular for Mexico, indicate that a seven year period is required to obtain full&#13;
disbursements for this type of project. The disbursement period has accordingly been&#13;
estimated at seven years and the closing date on June 30, 2004 (Table 4-2). However, if&#13;
SCT decides to accelerate project execution and SHCP agrees to provide the funds&#13;
required to match the loan funds necessary, the project could be completed in about four&#13;
years. The initial allocations of loan proceeds and the corresponding percentage to be&#13;
disbursed by category are shown in Table 4-1. Disbursement would be made on the&#13;
following basis: (a) 53% of the expenditures on civil works; (b) 100% of total&#13;
expenditures on consultant services; and (c) 100% of total expenditures on training.&#13;
4.15  Disbursements under the project will be made against full documentation of&#13;
expenditures except for the following items, for which disbursement would be on the basis&#13;
of statement of expenditures (SOEs): (a) civil contracts costing less than US$10 million&#13;
equivalent; (b) consultant contracts with firms estimated to cost less than US$100,000&#13;
equivalent and with individuals costing less than US$50,000 equivalent; and (c) training.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
31&#13;
SOE records will be made available to Bank staff as required for inspection during&#13;
supervision.&#13;
4.16   To expedite project execution, a Special Account would be opened in the Central&#13;
Bank, with an authorized allocation of US$25 million equivalent. The first advances from&#13;
this account will be limited to US$15 million equivalent until the aggregate amount of&#13;
withdrawals from the loan account plus the total amount of all outstanding special&#13;
commitments have reached US$75 million equivalent. Retroactive financing of US$ 30&#13;
million equivalent (about 6% of the loan) was agreed at negotiations for expenditures&#13;
incurred on works and consulting services initiated between June 30, 1996 and the loan&#13;
signature date. These arrangements were confirmed at negotiations.&#13;
Table 4-2&#13;
SCHEDULE OF ESTIMATED DISBURSEMENTS&#13;
(US$ Million)&#13;
IBRD Fiscal Year     Disbursements       Cummulative      Cummulative&#13;
per quarter      Disbursement       Percentage&#13;
1998 September 30, 1997        35.0&#13;
December 31, 1997         15.0               50.0&#13;
March 31, 1998            15.0&#13;
June 30, 1998             15.0               80.0            16.8%&#13;
1999 September 30, 1998        20.0&#13;
December 31, 1998         20.0              120.0&#13;
March 31, 1999            20.0&#13;
June 30, 1999             20.0              160.0            33.7%&#13;
2000 September 30, 1999        20.0&#13;
December 31, 1999         20.0              200.0&#13;
March 31, 2000            20.0&#13;
June 30, 2000             20.0              240.0            50.5%&#13;
2001 September 30, 2000        20.0&#13;
December 31, 2000         20.0              280.0&#13;
March 31, 2001            25.0&#13;
June 30, 2001             25.0              330.0            69.5%&#13;
2002 September 30, 2001        20.0&#13;
December 31, 2001         20.0              370.0&#13;
March 31, 2002            20.0&#13;
June 30, 2002             15.0              405.0            85.3%&#13;
2003 September 30, 2002        15.0&#13;
December 31, 2002         15.0              435.0&#13;
March 31, 2003            10.0&#13;
June 30, 2003             10.0              455.0            95.8%&#13;
2004 September 30, 2003         10.0&#13;
December 31, 2003         10.0              475.0           100.0%&#13;
Assumptions:&#13;
Loan Signing Date:           July, 1997&#13;
Loan Effectiveness:          September, 1997&#13;
Project Completion:    December 31, 2003&#13;
Loan Closing Date:           June 30, 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
32&#13;
F. ECONOMIC EVALUATION&#13;
4.17  The economic analysis has been carried out for the physical component of the&#13;
project, except the removal of hazardous spots for which an economic analysis would be&#13;
carried out as the spots are studied and selected during project implementation. The&#13;
activities captured by the analysis cover about 90% of total project base cost. The&#13;
economic benefits from improving SCT and the state road agencies' capacity, even though&#13;
expected to be substantial, are not quantified. The estimated combined economic rates of&#13;
return (ERR) for the indicative federal road program for 1997 to 2002 is about 18.9%,&#13;
with a net present value discounted at 12% of US$983 million.&#13;
4.18  In addition to the ERRs, the selection of the individual road sections to be included&#13;
in the highway modernization program took into consideration the importance of the&#13;
roads in the external trade transport and in regional integration and accident reduction.&#13;
For the economic analysis of the selected roads, a modified version of the Bank's HDM III&#13;
model, the HDM-Q, which takes into consideration road congestion and capacity&#13;
constraints as well as roadside friction, was used. The model predicts the life-cycle cost of&#13;
different modernization and subsequent pavement management options and selects the&#13;
combination with the minimum life-cycle costs, including the cost to road users and the&#13;
SCT. The life-cycle costs of road modernization include: road construction and&#13;
maintenance costs, vehicle operating costs, cost of time and accident costs. The accident&#13;
costs were put in the model as an exogenous variable. The traffic on the project roads&#13;
ranges between 2,100 and 31,000 vehicles per day. The value oftime used in the analysis&#13;
is based on only work-related trips and estimated as the frill value of the salary of heavy&#13;
vehicle drivers and 50% of the value of earnings for those traveling in private cars. Annex&#13;
D outlines the economic analysis for a typical road section, the San Roberto - Puerto&#13;
Mexico road (80 km). The full analysis is included in the Project File.&#13;
4.19  A sensitivity test of the variation in the ERRs against possible 20% changes in&#13;
construction costs and benefits as well as excluding the savings in time shows that all&#13;
project roads still yield ERRs of at least 12% and positive NPVs. An analysis performed&#13;
to test the effects (risk) of postponing the modernization of the typical road, San Roberto&#13;
- Puerto Mexico, shows that the net benefits are reduced if the investment is postponed by&#13;
two or three years. This postponement would, however, not make the modernization&#13;
economically non-feasible.&#13;
G. ENVIRONMENTAL AND SOCIAL ASPECTS&#13;
4.20  The road improvement activities under the project might, in some cases, result in&#13;
negative environmental impacts. All road improvement would, therefore, be subjected to&#13;
an environmental impact assessment (EIA). For all sub-components identified for&#13;
implementation during the first year, EIAs have been carried out, reviewed by the Bank&#13;
and found satisfactory. For the remaining components, which would be selected in&#13;
subsequent years, the EIAs would be carried out before the approval of the sub-&#13;
component for inclusion in that year's program. SCT's environmental affairs unit (EAU)&#13;
is being strengthened under the HRTS. Moreover, to comply with environmental&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
33&#13;
requirements, SCT has revised its work specifications and improved those parts related to&#13;
the coverage of cultural patrimony, the management of quarries and borrow pits, pollution&#13;
control of construction equipment and work crews and disposal of waste materials. These&#13;
revisions are included in the bidding documents for civil works construction and are&#13;
adequate. SCT is also taking steps to improve the coordination among EAU and other&#13;
directorates of SCT carrying out their own environmental assessment in order to eliminate&#13;
duplication.&#13;
4.21   Since the proposed project is a time-slice operation and the social impacts,&#13;
including involuntary resettlement, of the civil works sub-projects to be carried out beyond&#13;
1998 are not yet known, agreement was reached at negotiations on a framework for&#13;
preparing resettlement documents, should they be necessary. The roads being modernized&#13;
in 1997 and those selected for 1998 were studied by a qualified sociologist and found not&#13;
to cause any need for involuntary resettlement. In order to ensure that any involuntary&#13;
resettlement caused by modernization of other roads or complementary works, such as by-&#13;
passes and junctions, which may not be part of the project, but connected with the project&#13;
roads, are adequately handled, it was agreed at negotiations that such complementary&#13;
works would also be subject to the resettlement framework mentioned above. In the&#13;
event of the need for involuntary resettlement in either of the above cases, it was agreed at&#13;
negotiations that the Borrower shall: (a) prepare and furnish to the Bank satisfactory&#13;
resettlement documents for such affected persons or families not later than the date on&#13;
which it submits the road sections or complementary works for the Bank's review and&#13;
approval; and (b) thereafter carry out the actions recommended by the resettlement&#13;
documents in accordance with their terms.&#13;
H. PROGRAM OBJECTIVE CATEGORY&#13;
4.22  The applicable categories for this project are Environmentally Sustainable&#13;
Development (80%) and Economic Management (20%).&#13;
I. PROJECT BENEFITS&#13;
4.23  The project would increase transport efficiency and reduce costs on the federal&#13;
road network, particularly along the major export transport corridors, and enhance the&#13;
country's competitive advantage in its external trade. It would help in accommodating the&#13;
rapid road traffic growth, estimated at about 10% per annum, on the major corridors&#13;
which will result from the NAFTA agreement. Given the free competition in Mexico's&#13;
trucking industry, the savings in vehicle operating costs would be passed on eventually to&#13;
consumers and the general population including the low income sector. Significant, but&#13;
non-quantifiable benefits would also accrue from the institutional strengthening and&#13;
training components. The improvement in allocating funds to highway activities would&#13;
ensure that benefits are maximized. Strengthening SCT and its regional centers would&#13;
help increase implementation efficiency and reduce delays. Finally, the improvement in&#13;
environmental and social awareness and the capacity to incorporate environmental and&#13;
social factors into road planning and the execution of road projects would prevent damage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
34&#13;
to the country's natural resources and would adequately compensate persons adversely&#13;
affected by the projects.&#13;
J. PROJECT RISKS&#13;
4.24  The main project risks include: (a) Reduction of Maintenance Efforts on Road&#13;
Network. For the last several years, the Government, with the Bank's assistance, has&#13;
concentrated its efforts on rehabilitating and maintaining the federal road network. This&#13;
strategy has worked well. However, the country has reached a point where it now needs&#13;
to expand road capacity as well. It must do this in a balanced way so as not to jeopardize&#13;
what has been gained in terms of maintaining the existing system. There is, however, the&#13;
risk that with the modernization program, insufficient resources will be allocated to road&#13;
maintenance. The risk would be significantly reduced by SCT's ongoing effort to redefine&#13;
the federal road program to make it about half of its current size. Also, the introduction&#13;
of the proposed road maintenance fund and more efficient systems for allocating funds&#13;
among all road activities should help to ensure that economic priorities are reflected in&#13;
SCT's use of funds. Lastly, the pace of implementation of the modernization program&#13;
would be tailored to the availability of funds to implement a balanced road budget for the&#13;
STC. (b) Delays in Complementary Action to Modernize the Federal Road System. SCT&#13;
recognizes that modernizing the federal road network also includes complementary actions&#13;
to improve safety, traffic flow management, policing and vehicle weight and dimension&#13;
control. SCT's achievements on these would be discussed at annual review meetings&#13;
which would also agree on the composition and size of the annual programs. (c)&#13;
Environmental and Social Risks. Possible negative environmental and social impacts from&#13;
the project would be mitigated through the environmental safeguards built into SCT's&#13;
bidding documents, the strict requirements for environmental impact assessment in the&#13;
project and close monitoring of resettlement and their implementation of the resettlement&#13;
documents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
35&#13;
AGREEMENTS REACHED AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
5.1   During negotiations, agreement was reached on the following:&#13;
as a condition of loan effectiveness, the Guarantor and the Borrower would enter&#13;
into contractual agreements, satisfactory to the Bank, for the transfer of the&#13;
loan funds (para. 4.1);&#13;
SCT would present to the Bank, by October 31 each year during project&#13;
implementation starting in 1998, its draft road program on the federal&#13;
network for the subse(cuent fiscal year and by April 30, each year starting in&#13;
1998, its actual road program as updated to use fully the budget approved&#13;
by the Legislature (para. 2.9);&#13;
the composition and scope of the first and second year road programs (para. 3.5);&#13;
the scope and terms of reference of the technical assistance and implementation&#13;
schedules for: (i) reviewing the role and organization of the SCT; (ii)&#13;
developing the comprehensive road planning model and (iii) reviewing&#13;
inter-modal transport (para. 3.7);&#13;
the scope of the staff training program (para. 3.10);&#13;
the arrangements, eligibility, criteria and documentation for sub-project selection&#13;
(paras. 4.1 and 4.2);&#13;
procurement procedures (paras. 4.4 - 4.6);&#13;
the scope and content of the semestral and mid-term project implementation&#13;
reviews (paras. 4.9 - 4. 10);&#13;
performance and impact monitoring indicators for the project (para. 4.10)&#13;
the auditing of the project account would be in line with standing arrangements&#13;
between BANOBRAS and the Bank, and that the use of statement of&#13;
expenditures and the special account would be subject to a separate&#13;
opinion in the audit reports (para. 4.13);&#13;
procedures for environmental reviews and a framework for preparing resettlement&#13;
documents for subprojects (paras. 4.20-4.21); and&#13;
the loan disbursement arrangements, including the establishment of a Special&#13;
Account (paras. 4.14-4.16).&#13;
5.2   With the above agreements, the project is suitable for a Bank Libor-based single&#13;
currency loan of US$475 million for a period of 15 years, including five years of grace.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
36&#13;
Table A-1: Highway Rehabilitation, Resurfacing, and Maintenance Program 1993-1996&#13;
DGCC Budget Requirements, Physical Targets and Accomplishements&#13;
1993             1994             1995         1996        Total 93 - 96   |&#13;
Target  Actual  Target  Actual  Target   Actual   Actual   Target (T)  Actual (A)   A/T&#13;
I. Financial Targets&#13;
(1993 Mexican N$ Million)&#13;
Total                1000.2  1330.5  1065.0  1086.7  1125.9   765.5   1298.0    3191.1    3182.8    99.7&#13;
(a) Pavements                      833.2  1156.4   866.4   953.0   941.2   712.7   1118.2    2640.8    2822.1   106.9&#13;
Rehabilitation                   284.0   407.6   444.6   344.1   608.3   224.3    729.5    1336.9         976.0    73.0&#13;
Resurfacing 1/                   341.7   158.9   246.0   320.9   165.8   209.7    201.9        753.5      689.5    91.5&#13;
Routine Maintenance &amp; Equipm. If    207.5   589.9   175.8   288.0   167.1   278.7    186.8     550.4    1156.6   210.1&#13;
(b) Bridges&#13;
Rehabilitation/Improvement        50.0    70.9    69.5    56.4    68.4    49.6        69.3     187.9      176.9    94.1&#13;
(c) Miscellaneous                  117.0   103.2   129.1    77.3   116.3       3.3    110.5      362.4      183.8    50.7&#13;
II. Physical Targets&#13;
(a) Pavements&#13;
Rehabilitation   KM. 4/          722.0  2375.0  1151.0  1097.2  1745.0  1590.5   1625.0    3618.0    5062.7   139.9&#13;
Resurfacing       KM. 4/        7661.0  5863.0  5543.0  7580.0  4187.0  5245.6   4463.0   17391.0   18688.6   107.5&#13;
Routine Maintenance KM. 4J    33600.0 46000.0 35790.0  46183.7  35790.0 41774.0  35790.0  105180.0  133957.7   127.4&#13;
(b) Bridges&#13;
Rehabilitation/lImprovement UNITS  76.0   120.0    45.0   102.0    85.0   102.0       74.0     206.0      324.0   157.3&#13;
i1. Impact Indicators&#13;
(a) Highway Pavements: % of&#13;
Highway length in fair to good&#13;
condition&#13;
Strategy 88 (basic strategy)     40.0    27.0    36.0    43.0    35.0    50.0        39.0&#13;
Strategy 87                      39.0    27.0    41.0    43.0    40.0    50.0        44.0&#13;
Strategy 13                      38.0    27.0    44.0    43.0    52.0    50.0        50.0&#13;
(b) Bridges: units in need of repair 2/&#13;
Alarm                            66.0    80.0    32.0    60.0       0.0    30.0       0.0&#13;
Urgent                          214.0   213.0   181.0   245.0   168.0   260.0        83.0&#13;
Less urgent                     265.0   316.0   256.0   620.0   256.0   920.0    256.0&#13;
14- Noviembre - 1995&#13;
11 Fuente: Reporte de las Residencias Generales en Metas Financiadas Actuales&#13;
2/ Las Metas del Programa Presupuesto fueron estimadas en base a Inspecci6n de 821 Puentes: sin embargo durante 1994 y 1995 se complemento la&#13;
inspeccion de los 6346 Puentes existentes en la red federal&#13;
3/ Estimado&#13;
4/ Las Cantidades fisicas mostradas como actuales (Realizados) provienen de los informes de la Residencia General y en muchos casos incluye obra&#13;
realizada con un partida presupuestal diferente&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
37                          Annex A&#13;
Table A-2&#13;
Table A-2: Highway Rehabilitation, Resurfacing and Maintenance Program&#13;
Estimated DGCC Budget Needs and Physical Targets (1996 - 2000)&#13;
1996    1997    1998    1999   2000&#13;
Target  Target  Target  Target  Target&#13;
1. Financial Targets&#13;
1996 Mexican N$ Million&#13;
Total           2,143.5 3,000.0  2,878.0  3,170.0  3,151.0&#13;
(a) Pavements                 1,790.1  2,585.2  2,443.1  2,782.1  2,815.2&#13;
Rehabilitation               907.8  1,723.1  1,801.1 2,159.1 2,165.1&#13;
Resurfacing                  406.9  415.1   156.0   152.0   155.1&#13;
Routine Maintenance &amp;        475.4   447.0   486.0   471.0   495.0&#13;
Equipm.&#13;
(b) Bridges&#13;
Rehabilitation/Improvement   113.3   145.0   150.0   138.0   135.0&#13;
(c) Miscellaneous              240.0   270.0   285.0   250.0   201.0&#13;
11. Physical Targets&#13;
(a) Pavements&#13;
Rehabilitation   km        1,549.1  2,655.1   2,642  3,287.1  3,643.1&#13;
Periodic Maintenance km    3,714.2  5,691.1  2,159.1  1,762.0  2,114.0&#13;
Routine Maintenance km    42,085.0 38,139.0 38,870.0 38,224.0 39,091.0&#13;
(b) Bridges&#13;
Rehabilitation/Improvement    127     132     137     126     123&#13;
units&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1: Projected Plhysical Conditioni of the Federal Road Network&#13;
(Assuming Expenditures of US$ 300 Million per Year)&#13;
40000                                                                                . _  ......&#13;
37500&#13;
35000 - - ----&#13;
32500 -&#13;
30000 - -&#13;
27500 -&#13;
25000       _                                                  ;&#13;
E    22500 -,&#13;
20000       .                             . .: ;&#13;
17500-                                                    :    :           :  :             :               X&#13;
15000 - - ----&#13;
12500                              -                                :.&#13;
10000   -.......&#13;
7500 -..&#13;
5000&#13;
2500&#13;
O  ------,-                        ,|,                          ,,I'I'&#13;
1996 1997 1998 1999 2000 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010&#13;
IEn    Good         Fair   El Bad         g   V. Bad |        Year&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
39                            Annex A&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
FEDERAL ROADS MODERNIZATION PROJECT&#13;
Rehabilitation and Maintenance of the Federal Road Network&#13;
A. Institutional Arrangements&#13;
1.    The Secretarfa de Comunicaciones y Transporte (SCT), through its Direcci6n&#13;
General de Conservaci6n de Carreteras (DGCC), is responsible for maintaining the un-&#13;
tolled portion of the federal road network, about 42,182 km. CAPUFE, private&#13;
concessionaires and the state governments are responsible for 1,420 km, 3,167 km and&#13;
1,096 km respectively on concession with SCT. Since the beginning of 1997, SCT has&#13;
been negotiating with the states to take over about half the federal road network.&#13;
2.    Maintenance of the expressways by CAPUFE, the private concessionaires and&#13;
the states, financed out of the tolls collected by these entities, is adequate. DGCC has&#13;
over the past three years significantly improved its maintenance performance through:&#13;
(a) introducing modern road and bridge maintenance management systems; (b)&#13;
contracting about 70% of of its maintenance to the private sector; (c) training its staff;&#13;
and (d) increasing significantly its spending on maintenance and rehabilitation, which&#13;
accounts for over 60% of SCT's road budget.&#13;
B.   Government's Objectives with HRRM&#13;
4.    To restore the federal network, the Government embarked on a Highway&#13;
Rehabilitation, Resurfacing and Maintenance Program (HRRM). The Government's&#13;
objective under the program, being financed with the Bank's assistance under the&#13;
HRTS, was to bring the condition of all SCT-maintained roads in the federal network&#13;
(about 42,833 km) to at least a "fair" classification and no highways in poor condition&#13;
by the year 2008.&#13;
C.   Program Implementation&#13;
5.    The program's physical and institutional strengthening performance has been&#13;
fairly good; each year about 44,000 km have received routine maintenance, about&#13;
6,200 km resurfacing and about 1,700 km rehabilitation or reconstruction under the&#13;
program. On the institutional side, an operational, modern maintenance management&#13;
system has been put in place in DGCC with the assistance of consultants (BCEOM,&#13;
France). The system has permitted more rational selection, budgeting and monitoring&#13;
of rehabilitation and maintenance activities as well as the revision of the program to&#13;
reflect changing road conditions and availability of funds.&#13;
6.    The Government's performance in meeting the program's financial&#13;
requirements and its commitments under the HRTS project has been satisfactory on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
40                            Annex A&#13;
average: spending was above commitments for 1993 and 1994 and below for 1995. The&#13;
total spending for the first 3 years of the program have been equal to the commitments&#13;
undertaken under the HRTS (see Table A-1). These commitments were, however,&#13;
themselves only about 70% of the sums required to implement an optimum&#13;
maintenance program, i.e. one that would maximize the net present value to society.&#13;
They were considered acceptable to the Bank, however, in view of the difficult&#13;
financial situation the Government was going through then.&#13;
7.    An analysis of the physical work done since the start of the program in 1993&#13;
shows that the rhythm is acceptable. All roads in the federal network which are not&#13;
slated for resurfacing, rehabilitation or periodic maintenance receive adequate routine&#13;
maintenance each year. At the rate of 7,900 km of rehabilitation and periodic&#13;
maintenance per year, all roads in the network would be covered by these operations&#13;
within the next six years, compared to the cycle of 6 to 8 years traditionally considered&#13;
adequate, depending on traffic volumes.&#13;
D.   Revised Program Objectives.&#13;
8.    DGC has carried out an analysis of condition of the federal network based upon&#13;
more recent, detailed and reliable road condition inventory and assuming different&#13;
alternative levels of financing, using its maintenance management system, SISTER.&#13;
The results, presented in Figure 1, show that, should the annual allocation in real terms&#13;
be retained at US$300 million equivalent, the 1996 level, at least 50% of the network&#13;
would be brought to "good" condition and the remaining 50% to "fair" condition, the&#13;
original program objective, in the year 2008 compared to 2007. On the other hand,&#13;
funding the program at N$3.0 billion or US$400 million equivalent would accomplish&#13;
that goal in the year 2003.&#13;
9.    During the Mid-Term Review of Implementation of the HRTS in 1996, the&#13;
Government agreed to increase the funding for the HRTS to at least US$300 million&#13;
equivalent per year starting January 1997. The 1997 maintenance budget was actually&#13;
slightly higher than US$300 million and, if maintained, would permit achieving the&#13;
original program's goals by the year 2008. Should the Government's financial&#13;
situation improve, the Government undertook to increase the annual expenditures to&#13;
attain the goal in the year 2003. The revised financial and physical targets for the&#13;
program are presented in Table A-2.&#13;
10.   A detailed presentation of alternative funding scenarios and the corresponding&#13;
network conditions is included in the Project File.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
41                               Annex B&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
FEDERAL ROADS MODERNIZATION PROJECT&#13;
TRAINING PROGRAM&#13;
A Introduction&#13;
SCT HAS EMBARKED ON A VERY SIGNIFICANT STAFF TRAINING PROGRAM UNDER THE&#13;
ONGOING HIGHWAY REHABILITATION AND TRAFFIC SSAFETY PROJECT (HRTS). HRTS'&#13;
TRAINING PROGRAM AIMS AT:&#13;
(a) strengthening SCT, both at headquarters and in the regional units (Centros, SCT), in&#13;
all areas of highway rehabilitation and maintenance;&#13;
(b) improving SCT's performance in all areas of transport planning, contract&#13;
administration, works supervision and quality control;&#13;
(c) strengthening SCT in administering driver licensing, and vehicle inspection; and&#13;
(d) equipping the training centers at SCT's regional centers with basic training facilities.&#13;
2.    The detailed list of training areas and the number of staff expected to benefit are&#13;
included in Table B-i. Progress in implementing the program has been considerably delayed&#13;
due to delays in recruiting instructors.  It is now estimated that the program would be&#13;
completed by the year 1999 to 2000, instead of the original completion date of 1996. It was&#13;
therefore decided that the training program under the proposed Federal Roads Modernization&#13;
Program (FRM) be kept to a minimum in order not to overload SCT.&#13;
B. The Training Program under the FRM Project.&#13;
3.    The FRM would provide for deepening the above training in areas such as: (a) bidding&#13;
and contract administration (beneficiary, DGCF); (b) budgetary and resource allocation among&#13;
road activities(beneficiary, Oficiria Mayor); (c) project evaluation techniques (beneficiary,&#13;
DGP); and (d) the assessment of environmental social and economic impacts and designing&#13;
mitigation/compensation plans (beneficiaries, DGCF, DGST and CGP). The training would&#13;
also finance training in new areas such as: (a) inter-modal transport and electronic data&#13;
interchange systems (beneficiary, DGTT); (b) transport corridor analysis and planning&#13;
(beneficiary, DGP); and (c) highway financing (beneficiary, DGP). Lastly, the project would&#13;
provide for a parallel training program to the ongoing one under the HRTS for four selected&#13;
states in Mexico.&#13;
4   The proposed program under the project, to be carried from 1998 to 2001, would reach&#13;
about 780 participants over the 4-year period as shown in the table below. A more in-depth&#13;
training program would be developed following the re-organization study for the SCT.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
42                               Annex B&#13;
Table B-1 Training Program (1998-2001)&#13;
Number of Participants and Estimated Costs&#13;
Beneficiarie  1998  1999  2000  2001       Total       Total&#13;
s                                    (1998-       (U$&#13;
2001)      Thous.)&#13;
DGCF           80   120   120    80            400         500&#13;
DGP             10    20    20    10            60         100&#13;
DGTT            10    20    20    10            60         100&#13;
DGE            40    50    50    40            180         100&#13;
DGST           20    20    20    20             80         200&#13;
Totals        160   230   230   160            780       1,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
43                                Annex C&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
FEDERAL ROADS MODERNIZATION PROJECT&#13;
Performance Monitoring Indicators&#13;
A. Indicators&#13;
1.    The indicators to be monitored for measuring the project's performance are grouped&#13;
into five: (a) input indicators, which measure the efficiency in the delivery of inputs to the&#13;
project; (b) output indicators, which measure the efficiency of the implementing agency in&#13;
executing the project; (c) outcome indicators, which provide an indication of the sucess in&#13;
achieving the project's objectives; (d) impact indicators, which measure the degree of&#13;
attainment of the project's broad objectives; and (e) sustainability impact, which indicates the&#13;
degree to which the main factors/conditions needed for the project's sustainability are being&#13;
ffilled. A list of these indicators and the agreed benchmarks are presented in Table C-1.&#13;
B. Organizational Arrangements for Monitoring&#13;
2.    SCT would be responsible for measuring the project's performance. SCT would be&#13;
assisted by the Instituto Mexicano de Transporte (IMT) and consultants, as necessary, with&#13;
financing under the project. To permit a "before" and "after" project comparison, benchmark&#13;
measurements would be made, for those outcome and impact indicators to which they are&#13;
applicable, before project implementation starts. The results of the performance monitoring&#13;
would be discussed during the annual review of project implementation and would be an&#13;
important input into the project Implementation Report after loan closure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
44                                Annex C&#13;
Table C-1: Performance Monitoring Indicators&#13;
Indicators                                     Benchmark&#13;
1998     1999     20004    2001      2002&#13;
Input Indicators&#13;
Counterpart Funds US$ m    25.0     65.9      112.4    107.0    89.7&#13;
Bank Loan Funds US$ m      25.0     65.9      112.4    107.0    89.7&#13;
Output Indicators&#13;
Km of Highways             160      265       255      195      70&#13;
Modernized&#13;
% of Contracts Completed    60      70        80       85       90&#13;
on Time&#13;
No. of Staff Receiving              160       230      230       160&#13;
Training                   _ _ :&#13;
Outcome Indicators&#13;
% of Completed Roads with  100      100       100      100       100&#13;
targeted improved capacity&#13;
Ratio of actual and projected  90   90        90       90        90&#13;
time savings for completed&#13;
roads&#13;
Ratio of Actual and        80       80        80       80        80&#13;
Projected Vehicle Operation&#13;
Cost Savings for Completed&#13;
Roads&#13;
Impact Indicators&#13;
% Decrease in Transport    20       20       20        20       20&#13;
Costs on Completed Roads&#13;
% Reduction in Serious     10       15       20        20       20&#13;
Accidents&#13;
%:Reduction in No. of All   5       10        10       15        15&#13;
Accidents on Completed&#13;
Roads&#13;
Sustainability Indicators&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
45                                Annex C&#13;
Km of Federal Roads        2110      2264     2745      3096      1633&#13;
Rehab./Recons.&#13;
Km of Federal Roads        1764      2275     995       1000      1000&#13;
Receiving Periodic&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Km of Federal Roads        39277    39277    39277    39277    39277&#13;
Receiving Routine&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Funds Spent on Maintenance  3170     3151     3200      3321     3450&#13;
(N$ Million)                       I         I        I         I        I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
46                                Annex D&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
FEDERAL ROADS MODERNIZATION PROJECT&#13;
Economic and Financial Analysis of the Project Roads&#13;
l. Economic Analysis&#13;
A. Methodology&#13;
1.    SCT used economic tests, Net Present Value and Economic Rates of Return, to pre-&#13;
select the roads to be included in its federal roads modernization program. SCT then prepared&#13;
in-depth economic analysis on about 2016 km of roads to be modernized in years 1997-2002&#13;
using the HDM -Q model. The model measures the benefits from the road investments in the&#13;
form of vehicle operating cost savings and time savings to the economy against the cost of the&#13;
investments and subsequent maintenance of the road over the 25-year life of the&#13;
investments.The HDM-Q is the modified form of the HDM III model which can take into&#13;
consideration congestion effects. The model predicts the life-cycle costs of different&#13;
modernization and subsequent pavement management options and selects the combination with&#13;
the minimum life-cycle costs to society, including the cost to road users and the SCT. The&#13;
model computes, for a given road and traffic, first the free-flow speeds and then adjusts these&#13;
speeds to take into account the congestion level. The resulting speeds are then used to compute&#13;
the vehicle operating and travel time savings. Although accident savings are expected to be&#13;
considerable, it is difficult to quantify them to any reliable degree. The estimates for these&#13;
savings are therefore not included in the best estimate analysis of the roads, but have only been&#13;
added to the benefits in the case of the sensitivity analysis. A sample of the economic analysis,&#13;
using the San Roberto - Puerto Mexico Road (80 km), one of the first-year roads is presented&#13;
below.&#13;
Traffic&#13;
2.    The San Roberto - Puerto Mexico (SR-PM) road section forms part of the most&#13;
important road axis in Mexico, the Mexico - Nuevo Laredo road which carries over 9,000&#13;
vehicles per day (vpd) of which more than 60 % are trucks. The SR-PM road section carries&#13;
about 7,958 vpd of which 46% are passenger vehicles, 2% buses and 52% heavy vehicles.&#13;
Based on historic traffic growth and future projects of economic growth, the rate of growth of&#13;
traffic has been estimated at a modest 2% per year for all vehicle types. This a conservative&#13;
assumption since the current average annual growth is between 5 % to 7 %. Therefore, in the&#13;
sensitivity analysis an average annual growth of 5% has also been tested. Because a financial&#13;
analysis of toll alternatives to the proposed investments has shown them financially&#13;
unattractive, it has been assumed that there will be no traffic diversion from the project road.&#13;
Vehicle Operating Costs (voc)&#13;
3.    The vocs used in the model are those incorporated in the HDM model modified to&#13;
reflect unit costs in Mexico. The benefits from reduced vehicle operating costs arise from both&#13;
the better riding surface after modernization and the reduction in roadside friction from&#13;
increased road capacity. The initial roughness has been measured at 5.3 IRI (international&#13;
roughness index) and the final, after the road investment, estimated at 2.1 from experience in&#13;
Mexico with similar works. The vocs with and without the project are shown in Table D-1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
47                                Annex D&#13;
Time Savings&#13;
4.    The time savings from the investments represent the differential in average travel times&#13;
between the existing nearly congested roads and those on the improved roads which would&#13;
permit a level of service of at least "B". The HDM Q model estimates these time savings&#13;
automatically based on traffic levels and composition and the geometrical design standards of&#13;
the existing and improved roads.&#13;
5.    The value of time is quantified separately for truck and bus drivers and their mates -&#13;
for whom the average full value of wages and compensation is used - and for private car&#13;
drivers and their passengers - for whom the value of time is discounted.&#13;
Investment Costs&#13;
6.    The modernization of the road, which comprises road widening and provision of wider&#13;
shoulders as well as overlaying the surface, is estimated to occur in 1998 with an overlay in&#13;
the year 2016. Annual routine maintenance and resealing, when the damaged area reaches&#13;
50%, would be carried out each both in the 'with"and "without"project cases, but, in the&#13;
without case, there would also be an overlay in the year 2007. The investment costs used in the&#13;
analysis are estimates based on unit prices in recently received bids for similar works. The&#13;
economic costs for both benefits and agency costs have been calculated as total costs minus&#13;
taxes. No shadow prices have been used since the valuation of cost and benefit inputs is&#13;
undistorted market prices.&#13;
B. Summary Results&#13;
7.    The costs and benefit streams during the life-cycle of the San Roberto - Puerto Mexico&#13;
Road, and the results of the economic analysis are shown in Tables D-1 and D-2. The&#13;
proposed modernization of the San Roberto - Puerto Mexico road section would yield a Net&#13;
Present Value of US$40.9 million, discounted at 12%. The corresponding economic rate of&#13;
return would be 25.2%. The 1997-2002 indicative program would yield an NPV of about&#13;
US$983 million and an economic rate of return of 18.9%.&#13;
C. Sensitivity Analysis&#13;
8.    A sensitivity analysis, assuming reasonably likely variations in costs and benefits,&#13;
shows for the SR-PM road section that, with a combined increase of 20% and a decrease in&#13;
benefits of 20%, the ERR falls to 21.5 % (Table E-3). The IRR increases to 28.5% if a traffic&#13;
growth rate of 5% p.a. is assumed. For all the project's civil works combined, the NPV&#13;
discounted at 12% would be US$920 million, and the economic rate of return 19.4%. These&#13;
figures are, however, only indicative -since the current list of roads in the program is very&#13;
tentative. For the whole project, a 20% increase in investment costs would reduce the ERR to&#13;
14.9% while a decrease in benefits of 20% would reduce it to 14.3% The NPV would still be&#13;
positive in all cases.&#13;
II. Financial Analysis&#13;
9.    The financial analysis of the Tampico - Linares road, one of the roads in the second&#13;
year program, is presented here as an illustration of the analysis to determine if an alternative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
48                                 Annex D&#13;
road financed by the private sector and operated as a toll road would be attractive to the private&#13;
sector under reasonable assumptions of toll levels and length of concession period. The&#13;
objective is to ensure that public funds are not substituted for would-be private funds in&#13;
improving public infrastructure. Using private funds would release public funds for other uses&#13;
and would lead to more efficient use of resources since, in the toll road case, the public would&#13;
be given the option to pay tolls for an improved level of service over a long period of time.&#13;
On the other hand, the private sector would only undertake to finance the alternative roads if&#13;
the potential return on capital exceeds that from available opportunities in Mexico.&#13;
A. The Analysis&#13;
10.   The existing road in the modernization program is made up as follows (see Figure 1):&#13;
Tampico - Altamira&#13;
Altamira - Est. Manuel&#13;
Est. Manuel - Gonzalez.&#13;
Gonzalez - Llera de Canales&#13;
Llera de Canales - Cd. Victoria&#13;
Cd. Victoria - Barretal&#13;
Barretal - Lim. Edos. Tam/Nuevo Leon&#13;
11.   The sections of the road with inadequate capacity and therefore requiring urgent&#13;
attention are:&#13;
Entronque Llera - Ciudad Victoria    - 58.0 km, ADT 4,350 with 15% trucks; and;&#13;
El Barretal - Linares  -116.0 km, ADT 2,858, with 16% trucks.&#13;
Economic rates of return for the two sections, calculated using the same methodology as the&#13;
San Luis Potosi - Huizache road above, yield economic returns of 17.8% and 14.8%&#13;
respectively.&#13;
12.   The tolled alternative would consist of:&#13;
Alt. A: Cuauhtemoc - Ciudad Victoria - 156 km, ADT 1,416; and&#13;
Ciudad Victoria - Linares   153 km, ADT 2,448.&#13;
13.   Under the alternative of a toll road, the existing road would need to be maintained in a&#13;
reasonable shape to provide a free alternative to users, as required by Mexican Law. The main&#13;
variables used in the toll alternative analysis are as discussed below.&#13;
Traffic&#13;
14.   The traffic data, collected by consultants in their feasibility studies, gave the following&#13;
results:&#13;
(a)    Base year daily volumes are cars 1,416 and 2,448 respectively, as shown&#13;
above;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
49                                Annex D&#13;
(b)    A uniform growth of 2.5% was predicted by the consultants, except in the&#13;
initial years of the toll operation. It was assumed that there would be a drop of&#13;
10% in traffic immediately following the introduction of tolls. This would be&#13;
followed by a period of growth so that, by the 10th year, the traffic would be&#13;
equal to that predicted originally assuming the 2.5% annual growth. Traffic&#13;
beyond year 10 is projected to continue its 2.5% annual growth.&#13;
Construction Costs&#13;
15.   The construction costs of the toll road alternative are estimated at US$282 million or&#13;
US$912,223 per km, based upon the experience of SCT. Overlays, at a cost of US$129,809&#13;
per km are expected to be applied to the road every - years. Routine maintenance has been&#13;
estimated at US$1,481 per km per year. A physical contingency of 20% has been applied to&#13;
all costs.&#13;
Financing Conditions&#13;
16.   Based on the results of SCT's studies, the concessionaire can obtain financing for 40%&#13;
of the initial outlays, with the remaining 60% coming from reserves or a call on shareholders&#13;
capital. The loan conditions would be as follows:&#13;
(a)    A loan of 40% of initial construction cost would be obtained with a two-year&#13;
grace period. During construction, interest is added to the loan principal.&#13;
Amortization of capital and principal would be over 7 years with equal annual&#13;
installments. Interest is calculated over the outstanding balance at the end of&#13;
each year; and&#13;
(b)    The interest rate would be 11 % per year. The corresponding interest payments&#13;
are included as an operating cost to be offset against revenue since the loan is&#13;
intended to lever up the return on shareholders capital.&#13;
Toll Administration Costs&#13;
17.   The cost of collecting tolls and administering the system are estimated to be 10% of&#13;
gross revenue.&#13;
Concession Life&#13;
18.   To avoid the problems which have plagued the private toll roads program due to the&#13;
short concession period, SCT intends to grant the concessionaires a period of 30 years for the&#13;
new concessions.&#13;
Toll Rates&#13;
19.   The toll rates are estimated as 85% of the expected reduction in costs to road users in&#13;
the fifth year following the inauguration of the new road. These rates which compare&#13;
reasonably with CAPUFE's rates are: US cents 1.72 for cars, US cents 3.44 for buses and US&#13;
cents 5.16 for trucks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
50                                 Annex D&#13;
II. Results&#13;
20.   The flows of revenue and costs are shown in Table D-3. The estimated rate of return&#13;
on share capital would be -6.9% which is unattractive to the private sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
51                                            Annex D&#13;
Table D-1: Economic Analysis of San Roberto - Puerto Mexico Road&#13;
Cost and Benefit Streams (US$ millions)&#13;
Road Length = 80 km&#13;
Without Project                                                         With Project&#13;
Year    Traffic   Type of Work  ERI  Agency  Vehicle Op. Accident  Total    Traffic   Type of  IRI    Agency   Vehicle Op. Accident    Total&#13;
(ADT)                mm/m   Costs       Costs      Costs   Costs   (ADT)    Work   mm/m    Costs           Costs      Costs'      Costs&#13;
(VOC)&#13;
1998     6353       Overlay     3.6  5.26       98.6S   0.00      103.94      6353    Modern.  3.6       49.90      98.68       0.00    148.58&#13;
1999     6511                  3.7  0.10        89.11    0.38     89.59       6511    Conaerv.  2.1      0.10       81.39       0.00   81.49&#13;
2000     6674                   3.9  0.10        92.17    0.46    92.73       6674               2.2      0.10      83.48       0.00   83.58&#13;
2001     6841                   4.0  0.10        95.39   0.54    96.03        6841               2.3      0.10      85.61       0.00   85.71&#13;
2002     7012                   4.2  0.10        98.76   0.6      99.46       7012               2.3      0.10      87.79       0.00   87.89&#13;
2003     7187                   4.3  0.10       102.49   0.64    103.23       7187               2.5      0.10      90.03       0.00   90.13&#13;
2004     7367                   4.5  0.10       106.54   0.ou     107.32      7367               2.5      0.10      92.34       0.00   92.44&#13;
2005     7551                   4.7  0.10       111.03   0.71     11-1,84     7551               2.6      0.10      94.71       0.00   94.81&#13;
2006     7740                   5.0  0.10       115.52   0.74     116.36      7740               2.7      0.10      97.16       0.00   97.26&#13;
2007     7934       Overlay     2.9  5.25       120.86   0.76     126.87      7934               2.8      0.10      99.69       0.00   99.79&#13;
2008     8132                   3.0  0.10       113.68   0.76     114.54      8132               3.0      0.10      102.31      0.00   102.41&#13;
2009     8335                   3.1  0.10       118.48   0.76     119.34      8335               3.2      0.10      105.38      0.00   105.48&#13;
2010     8544                   3.3  0.10       122.37   0.76    123.23       8544               3.4      0.11      109.01      0.00   109.12&#13;
2011     8757                   3.4  0.10       126.44   0.76    127.3        8757               3.6      0.12      112.93      0.00   113.05&#13;
2012     8976                   3.5  0.10       130.73   0.76     131.59      8976               3.8      0.12      116.94      0.00   117.06&#13;
2013     9201                   3.7  0.10       135.28   0.76    136.14       9201               4.0      0.12      121.04      0.00   121.16&#13;
2014     9431                   3.8  0.10       140.16   0.76    141.02       9431               4.2      0.12      125.24      0.00   125.36&#13;
2015     9667                   4.0  0.10       145.43   0.76     146.29      9667               4.4      0.12      129.52      0.00   129.64&#13;
Avg.                            3.4                                                              3.2&#13;
Economic Comparisons&#13;
Without Accident Savings                    Without Accident Savings&#13;
Year     Decreased   Decreased     Net    Decreased  Decreased    Accident       Net&#13;
Agency       User      Benefits   Agenry     User    Cost Savings   Benefits&#13;
Costs      Costa                  Costa     Costs&#13;
1998     -44.64       0.00      -44.64    -44.64      0.00         0.00       -44.64&#13;
1999      0.00        7.72       7.72       0.00      7.72         0.38        8.10&#13;
2000      0.00        8.69       8.69       0.00       8.69        0.46        9.15&#13;
2001      0.00        9.78        9.78      0.00       9.78        0.54        10.32&#13;
2002      0.00        10.97      10.97      0.00      10.97        0.60        11.57&#13;
2003      0.00        12.46      12.46      0.00      12.46        0.64        13.10&#13;
2004      0.00        14.20      14.20      0.00      14.20        0.68        14.88&#13;
2005      0.00        16.32      16.32      0.00      16.32        0.71        17.03&#13;
2006      0.00        18.36      18.36      0.00      18.36        0.74        19.10&#13;
2007      5.15        21.17      26.32      5.15      21.17        0.76        27.08&#13;
2008      0.00        11.37      11.37      0.00      11.37        0.76        12.13&#13;
2009      0.00        13.10      13.10      0.00      13.10        0.76        13.86&#13;
2010      -0.01       13.36      13.35     -0.01      13.36        0.76        14.11&#13;
2011     -0.02        13.51      13.49      -0.02     13.51        0.76        14.25&#13;
2012      -0.02       13.79      13.77     -0.02      13.79        0.76        14.53&#13;
2013     -0.02        14.24      14.22     -0.02      14.24        0.76        14.98&#13;
2014      -0.02       14.92      14.90     -0.02      14.92        0.76        15.66&#13;
2015      -0.02       15.91      15.89     -0.02      15.91        0.76        16.65&#13;
ERR= 25.2%                                ERR =26.3%&#13;
NPV = 40.9                                NPV = 44.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
52                                Annex D&#13;
Table D-2: Economic Analysis of Roads&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis Results&#13;
(US$ millions)&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis Results&#13;
Scenarios            San  Roberto  - Whole&#13;
Pto. Mexico      Project&#13;
1. Base Case                          25.2          19.4&#13;
2. Cost Increased by 20%              26.1          14.1&#13;
3. Benefits Decreased by 20%          26.6          14.3&#13;
4. Excluding Accident Benefits        25.7          15.5&#13;
5. Costs Decreased by 20%             21.5          12.3&#13;
and Benefits Decreased by 20%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
53                                                                    Annex D&#13;
Table D-3: Financial Analysis of Tampico - Linares Road&#13;
Estimation of Financial Returns&#13;
(US$)&#13;
Estimate of Financial Returns      1             2            3             4            5             6             7            8             9             10&#13;
Revenues                         -7,974,366   -32,456,587   -30,794,934   -25,518,468   -20,241,271    -1,541,667    -9,686,101    -4,952,074    -4,430,648    -4,382,883&#13;
Depreciation and Amortization     1,346,090    5,476,963     5,957,098     5,957,098    5,957,098     5,957,098    5,957,098     5,957,098     6,244,212   465,193,807&#13;
Investments                      92,185,933&#13;
Available Credit                 63,398,368&#13;
Debt Service                                   5,283,197    10,566,395    10,566,395    10,566,395    10,566,395    10,566,395   5,283,197&#13;
Cash Flow                       -35,415,841   -32,262,822   -35,404,231   -30,127,765   -24,850,568   -19,573,782   -14,295,398    -4,278,173  1,813,564     1,861,329&#13;
Accum. Cash Flow                -35,415,841   -67,678,663  -103,082,893  -133,210,658  -158,061,226  -177,635,008  -191,930,406  -196,208,579  -194,395,014  -192,533,685&#13;
11           12            13            14           15            16           17            18            19           20&#13;
Revenues                         -3,659,847    -2,937,086    -2,886,946    -2,834,432    -2,779,909    -3,262,483    -3,206,271    -3,149,190    -3,089,598    -3,030,143&#13;
Depreciation and Amortization     5,570,311    4,896,411     4,896,411     4,896,411    4,896,411     5,433,189    5,433,189     5,433,189     5,433,189      543,319&#13;
Investments&#13;
Available Credit&#13;
Debt Service&#13;
Cash Flow                         1,910,464     1,959,325    2,009,465     2,061,979    2,116,502     2,170,706    2,226,919     2,283,999     2,343,591     2,403,046&#13;
Accum. Cash Flow               -190,623,221  -188,663,896  -186,654,431  -184,592,452  -182,475,950  -180,305,245  -178,078,326  -175,794,327  -173,450,736  -171,047,690&#13;
21           22            23           24            25            26           27            28            29           30&#13;
Revenues                         -2,776,807     1,703,772    2,129,716     2,658,128    2,725,118     2,795,030    2,866,814     2,938,873     3,014,447     3,089,794&#13;
Depreciation and Amortization     5,241,135      823,893       461,879&#13;
Investments&#13;
Available Credit&#13;
Debt Service&#13;
Cash Flow                         2,464,328    2,527,665     2,591,595     2,658,128    2,725,118     2,795,030    2,866,814     2,938,873     3,014,447     3,089,794&#13;
Accum. Cash Flow               -168,583,361  -166,055,697  -163,464,102  -160,805,974  -158,080,857  -155,285,827  -152,419,012  -149,480,140  -146,465,692  -143,375,899&#13;
Return on Capital = -6.9%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IBRD 28418&#13;
Tij..o.                                                      10&#13;
'~~~~~~~~~~~'&#13;
a  Cs  S O { N  O ( R A j  C\H I H  A H U A                                                                                                               FEDERAL ROAD&#13;
1g   - H rmosills _   [   &lt;  \    &lt;    ..   /   Cd. Acufio                                                                             M E X I C O~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ E   IC &#13;
1         ~~~                   ~~0 -&gt;h. (    S gOuhoL.p P.d.Nors                                                                             /                        FEDERAL ROADS                                                  -&#13;
MODERNIZATION PROJECT -&#13;
flia Boalta   ~  i.dod ObtaElS..&#13;
Eod. H U.......T  ,/                                                             -     FEDERAL ROADS TO BE MODERNIZED&#13;
!    ,  oAXA  o  Ua'ojooa  '9           Porrol I    _                   M  iclona  nro0   -~     n-                                                             DIVIDED HIGHWAYS&#13;
m  C.,tanl.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~SELECTED MAIN ROADS&#13;
CSeLIFO2%A 0                       )&lt;&gt;e l_ 2 \ &lt; &gt; giG:orio) / N_\l ~ RIVERS&#13;
S,3U R             L., machi                                                                                                                                        0 ntjrr  ntanoro.  0   SELECTED CrTIES AND TOWNS&#13;
10  STATE CAPITALS&#13;
* NATIONAL CAPITAL&#13;
X  +\\Cu1i\s6n  DURANGO 0  t   t.  ,26  P.uerrtLInuEes    -/.                                                --~  STATE BOUNDARIES&#13;
La&gt;How Pa0                                               C)nncon~ej            DuWt%ZrE~Coo                                   G                               ---INTERNATIONAL BOUNDARIES&#13;
oL     100      200     300      400     500 KILOMETERS&#13;
C.    S.. L..                                                  WV .-I                                                                                D0         100          200           3     MILES&#13;
N   ARIT  ,A-  Cd V.11       P-                                                                                          'Pt..~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'t&#13;
AgydT".]                                                               A9W G  ulI f  o f  M  e x i c o            Progreso            TiaimT    Ju6r&#13;
P-P A C I F I C   O C E A N  1  J:rv u x p                                                                                        Merido                      C&#13;
P                                                                                                                     YUC BAT  yaIi P&#13;
-20.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        Ta..1G.dlj,I.lo-,2&#13;
(cI CASTANOS LA GLORIA                                               -e                                                             .JIP                                                                     NTA, *&#13;
VILLAHERMOSA-CD.DEL CARMEN                                  -\                Ut)~o Pa                                TCA          JBaP            y  a    Nam Pe Che&#13;
CUAUHTEMOC-EST MANUEL                                   Maon               ,qzno0            CAChatu,na&#13;
( MATEHUALA-SAN ROBERTO                                                                                          OR t                                                                       CAM PECHE7&#13;
( SAN ROBERTO-PUERTO MEXICO                                          Lo- rIS                                                                                   TAB A       4_&#13;
CUENCAME-RIO GRANDE                                                   L.  rnad-na                   -- &#13;
( GONZALEZ-ZARAGCZA                                                                 ZC_P&#13;
Acop   t  O   A  )(  &lt;   C   A t_         i       L ~~~~~~~~CH IA Aee S 1           BEIZ&#13;
( ESCOBEDO-LINARES                                                                                                            0    CA.&#13;
~~~~~~~ C~ A                              /i          . Mloo_tln_ ttna  &#13;
Thimp .np  pdodaond by tn Map O.aig. Unit F Tha W BrmL                                                                                                                 - P.,t E.                                                                /&#13;
Th. bo-nndri., coon, d-omninaolo and o,ef,m im.na-e..,                                                                                                                                                                 GUATEMALA&#13;
Ahon on -hi, mop oo not .ply, on f, pate  Th. World 8ank Ctnp,&#13;
any jdg.at on- . lgol .enaofanyb n y j-mtnYi a any an-n                                                                                                                                                                                    (  HONDURAS&#13;
100-                                                                                      90pac,erlo&#13;
MAY 1997&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IMAGING&#13;
Report No.:         15448   ME&#13;
Type:     SAR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="694717">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/06/694717/mexico-federal-roads-modernization-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/06/694717/mexico-federal-roads-modernization-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/06/694717/mexico-federal-roads-modernization-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1997/06/06/000009265_3980420170634/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1997/06/06/000009265_3980420170634/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>4206</loan_no>
        <datestored>2001-04-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1997-06-06T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Mexico - Federal Roads Modernization Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Federal Roads Modernization Project
            (FRMP) has two broad objectives: to help meet the expected
            traffic growth on the federal road network and to reduce
            road transport system costs; and to improve the
            institutional capacity to manage the road network. The
            project, designed to finance a time slice (1998 to 2002) of
            the FRMP, consists of: (1) civil works to increase the
            capacity and traffic safety of the federal network,
            including providing additional lanes on some road sections,
            building climbing lanes on others, improving horizontal and
            vertical alignments, providing adequate road shoulders and
            curbs and removing hazardous spots; (2) institutional
            strengthening directed at the Secretariat for Communications
            and Transport (SCT) and selected state highway organizations
            for improving management systems and procedures, training
            staff and reviewing the role and needs of the SCT centers in
            the states; and (3) further support to SCT to implement
            actions on road sector financing, to improve multi-modal
            transport operations, and to continue improving road safety
            and environmental impact assessment and mitigation measures
            in the planning, construction, and operation of transport facilities.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Mexico - Federal Roads Modernization Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Mexico - Federal Roads
            Modernization Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1997/06/694717/mexico-federal-roads-modernization-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>MX-Federal Roads Modztn -- P043163</projn>
        <docty>Staff Appraisal Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Urban Transport,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Airports and Air Services,Roads &amp; Highways,Public Sector Economics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Transport</teratopic>
        <count>Mexico</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>North America!$!80465</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980420170634</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Roads and highways,Central government administration</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1997-2</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Transport</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Transportation</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Civil works; Climbing lanes; Finance;
            Institution building; Management; Road &amp; highway
            engineering; Road &amp; highway networks; Road &amp; highway
            planning; Road &amp; highway safety; Traffic control;
            Training; Transport costs
            access
            roads,accountability,accounting,airline,airline
            deregulation,airports,Audits,Automobiles,Average Daily
            Traffic,aviation,Bridge,bridge design,Bridges,budget
            surplus,Buses,capital expenditures,cargo,cargo
            handling,civil works,concession contract,concession
            period,concession
            scheme,concessions,construction,construction
            contractors,construction supervision,construction
            work,corridor,Daily
            Traffic,debt,decentralization,deficits,Design Speed,economic
            analysis,economic growth,expressways,Financial
            Analysis,FISCAL YEAR,Framework,freight,Grade,Gross Domestic
            Product,HDM III,Highway,Highway Design,Highway
            Maintenance,highways,inflation,inventory,Kilometers per
            hour,labor unions,Land Transport,lanes,local
            governments,maintenance,modal transport,Net Present
            Value,operation and maintenance,passenger,passenger
            movement,passengers,Pavement,Pavement
            Width,police,Ports,private sector,private sector
            participation,Privatization,public sector,public sector
            investments,public servants,Railways,range,Rate of
            Return,regulatory framework,reorganization,resource
            allocation,Resurfacing,road construction,road corridors,road
            funds,road investment,road maintenance,road management,Road
            Network,road safety,road system,Road traffic,road
            transport,road transport industry,Roads,Roadways,rural
            roads,Safety Project,shifting responsibilities,Sight
            Distance,speed,structures,technical
            assistance,Telecommunications,terminal,terminals,terrain,Toll
            Roads,tolls,traffic growth,Traffic Safety,transport
            infrastructure,transport policy,TRANSPORT
            SECTOR,Transportation,trucking,Trucks,trunk roads,urban
            bus,Urban Development,Vehicle Operating Costs,Vehicle Safety,Vehicles
        </keywd>
        <owner>Fin, Private Sec &amp; Infrastructur (LCSFP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>North America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>15448</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health and Traffic Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Traffic Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highway Tolls</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Pricing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road User Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Toll Roads</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Free Trade Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Preferential Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>WTO Accession</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport in Urban Areas</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Transit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Tolls</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Agreements and Negotiations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Traffic and Road Safety</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Roads</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Mexico</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>