<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
THE WORLD BANK&#13;
Report No. 16384-MAU&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
ISLAMIC REPUBLIC OF MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
May 22, 1997&#13;
Technical Agriculture 3&#13;
Country Department 15&#13;
Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENT&#13;
Currency Unit   =    Ouguiya (UM)&#13;
USSI.00          =    UM  142 (January 1997)&#13;
SDR              =    US$1.3637&#13;
SYSTEM OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES: METRIC&#13;
Metric System&#13;
FISCAL YEAR OF BORROWER&#13;
January I - December 31&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS'&#13;
ADC           Association de Developpement Communautaire (Community development association)&#13;
AEA           (Projet d') Approvisionnement en Eau Aftout (Aflout water supply)&#13;
AfDB          African Development Bank&#13;
AMM           Association des maires de Mauritanie (Mauritanian mayors' association)&#13;
AP            Association pastorale (Pastoral Cooperative Association, PCA)&#13;
AVB           Agent de vulgarisation de base (Field extension agent, Ag. Services project)&#13;
BOP           Bureau des organisations paysannes&#13;
(Rural organization office, in wilayas' MDRE Delegations)&#13;
BVT           (Projet de la) Barriere Verte du Trarza (Trarza green belt)&#13;
BTU           British Thermal Unit&#13;
CAIE          Centrale d'Approvisionnement en Intrants d'Elevage (vet. medicine supply organization)&#13;
CA            Compte d'Avance (Advance Account)&#13;
CAS           Country Assistance Strategy&#13;
CESP          Country environmental strategy paper&#13;
CLD           Comite local de developpement (District development committee, at Moughataa level)&#13;
CNERV         Centre national d 'etudes et de recherche veterinaire (National center of veterinary research)&#13;
CP            Comite de Pilotage (Project steering committe)&#13;
CPR           Charge de Programme Regional (Regional Program Assistant)&#13;
CRD           Comite Regional de Developpement (Regional Developpement committee, at wilaya level)&#13;
CRP           Coordinateur Regional de Projet (Regional Project Coordinator)&#13;
CS            Conseil de surveillance (Project Control Committee)&#13;
CVN           (Projet de la) Ceinture verte de Nouakchott (Nouakchott green belt project)&#13;
DAP           Direction des Affaires Politiques et des Libertes Publiques&#13;
(Political Affairs and Public Liberties Directorate of MIPT)&#13;
DATAR         Direction de l'Amenagement du Territoire (National land use planning, Min. of Interior)&#13;
DEAR          Direction de l 'Environnement et de I 'Amenagement Rural (Environment directorate, MDRE)&#13;
DRAP          Direction des Ressources Agricoles et Pastorales (Directorate of crops and livestock, MDRE)&#13;
DRFV          Direction de la Recherche, de la Formation et de la Vulgarisation&#13;
(Research, education and extension directorate, MDRE)&#13;
ECPG          Equipe centrale de planification et de gestion (Project's central planning and implementation team)&#13;
EMAT          Equipe mobile d'appui technique (Project's technical support team)&#13;
ESMAP         Energy Sector Management Assistance Program&#13;
In order to avoid confusion, the text uses French acronyms exclusively, except in the case of international institutions&#13;
and Bank procedures.&#13;
Vice-President:       Jean-Louis Sarbib&#13;
Country Director:    Hasan Tuluy&#13;
Technical Manager:  Jean-Paul Chausse&#13;
Task Team Leader:  John Hall&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FNAEM         Federation Nationale des Agriculteurs et Eleveurs de Mauritanie&#13;
(Mauritanian national federation of livestock raisers)&#13;
FNEM          Federation Nationale de Eleveurs de Mauritanie (Mauritanian federation of livestock raisers)&#13;
GIRNEM        (Projet de) Gestion des Ressources Naturelles de l 'Est Mauritanien&#13;
(East Mauritania natural resource management project)&#13;
GNAP          Groupement National des Associations Pastorales (Pastoral associations national group)&#13;
GRN           Gestion des ressources naturelles( Natural Resource Management, NRM)&#13;
GTC           Groupement Technique Communautaire (Community technical group)&#13;
GTIV          Groupes techniques inter-villageois (Local technical committees)&#13;
HRM           Holistic resources management&#13;
HVPSE         (Projet d') Hydraulique Villageoise et Pastorale du Sud-Est (Southwestern pastoral and&#13;
water supply project)&#13;
IDB           Islamic Development Bank&#13;
MP            Manuel de Procedures (Implementation Manual)&#13;
MARP          Methode acceleree de recherche participative (Participative rural appraisal, PRA)&#13;
MDRE          Ministere du developpement rural et de 1 'environnement&#13;
(Ministry of Rural Development and Environment)&#13;
MHE           Ministere de l 'Hydraulique et de l 'Energie (Ministry of energy and water resources)&#13;
MIPT          Ministere de I 'Interieur, des postes et des telecommunications&#13;
(Ministry of Interior, Post and Telecommunications)&#13;
NBP           National bidding procedures&#13;
NEAP          National Environmental Action Program&#13;
ONS           Office National des Statistiques (National Statistical Institute)&#13;
PAC           Plan d'Amenagement Communautaire (Community management plan)&#13;
PAFT          Plan d'action desforets tropicales (FAO's Tropical Forest Action Plan)&#13;
PAN           (Projet de) Protection de I 'Aeroport de Nema (Nema Airport protection project)&#13;
PDIAIM        Projet de developpement integre de I 'agriculture irriguee de Mauritanie&#13;
(Mauritanian Integrated Development Program of Irrigated Agriculture)&#13;
PDLCD         Programme de lutte contre la desertification (Program of desertification control)&#13;
PETF          Plan d 'Execution Technique et Financiere (Technical and financial action plan)&#13;
PIC           Plan d'Investissement Communautaire (Community investment plan)&#13;
PLEMVASP   Projet de Lutte contre l 'Ensablement (sand dune protection project)&#13;
PMLCD         Plan Mauritanien de Lutte Contre la Desertification (Mauritanian plan to check desertification)&#13;
POV           Projet Operations Villageoises (Village operations project)&#13;
PRADER        Projet Regional d'Appui au Developpement Rural (Regional rural development support project)&#13;
PRASRE        Projet de Reboisement d'Agglomerations sur la Route de l 'Espoir&#13;
(Tree plantation project south of "Route de l'espoir")&#13;
PSA           Projet des Services Agricoles (Ag. services project)&#13;
RPTES         Review of Policies of Traditional Energy Strategy&#13;
SAC           Schema d'Amenagement Communautaire (Community land use master plan)&#13;
SED           Strategie Energie Domestique (Domestic energy strategy)&#13;
SOE           Statements of Expenditure&#13;
SONADER    Societe Nationale de developpement et d'equipement rural&#13;
(National society of rural equipment and development)&#13;
UE            Union Europeenne (European Union)&#13;
UICN          Union Internationale pour la conservation de la nature&#13;
(International union for the conservation of nature)&#13;
UNCACEM    Union Nationale des Caisses de Credit et d 'Epargne Mutuels&#13;
(National union of savings and loan organizations)&#13;
UNDP          United Nations Development Program&#13;
UNSO          United Nations Sudano-Sahelian Office&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ISLAMIC REPUBLIC OF MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No&#13;
I.    BACKGROUND ...........................................I&#13;
A. The Country ...........................................               .1&#13;
B. The Economy ...........................................I&#13;
C. The Rural Sector ............................................2&#13;
D. The Environment ............................................5&#13;
E. Institutions ............................................6&#13;
F. Sectoral Issues and Strategy ............................................8&#13;
II.   THE PROJECT ............................................11&#13;
A. Rationale and Objectives ...........................................1  I&#13;
B. Summary Description ...........................................                                                                14&#13;
C. Detailed Features ...........................................                                                                  14&#13;
D. Project Costs ...........................................            .                                                         19&#13;
E. Financing Plan ...........................................                                                                     20&#13;
F. Procurement ...........................................                                                                       21&#13;
G. Disbursement ...........................................             .                                                        24&#13;
iiI.   PROJECT ORGANIZATION AND MANAGEMENT                                                      ....................................... 26&#13;
A. Project Organization ............................................                                                             26&#13;
B. Project Implementation ...........................................                                                            29&#13;
C. Monitoring and Evaluation ...........................................                                                         30&#13;
D. Financial Management, Accounting and Auditing                                      ..................................... 30&#13;
E. Reporting, Supervision and Mid-Term  Review  ...........................................                                      32&#13;
F. Environmental and Social Impacts ...........................................                                                  33&#13;
IV.   PROJECT BENEFITS, RISKS AND SUSTAINABILITY ...........................................                                                35&#13;
A. Project Benefits ...........................................                                                                   35&#13;
B. Project Risks ...........................................                                                                     37&#13;
C. Fiscal Impact of the Project ...........................................                                                       38&#13;
D. Project Sustainability ...........................................                                                            38&#13;
V.    AGREEMENTS REACHED AND RECOMMENDATIONS ...........................................                                                        39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
1.    List of Projects Related to Natural Resource Management, and Lessons Learned&#13;
2.    Implementation of Project's Activities&#13;
3.    Anticipated Cost of Activities&#13;
4.    Project Cost Summary&#13;
5.    Estimated Schedule of Disbursements of IDA Credit&#13;
6.    Project Institutional Set-Up&#13;
7.    Selection Criteria of Participating Communities&#13;
8.    Investment Choices and Economic Justification&#13;
9.    Project Implementation Schedule&#13;
10.   Project Logical Framework&#13;
11.   Key Performances Indicators&#13;
12.   Nature and Source of Consultant Services&#13;
13.   Map IBRD. 28452&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ISLAMIC REPUBLIC OF MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Credit and Program Summary&#13;
Borrower:             Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Implementing Agency:   Ministry of Rural Development and Environment (MDRE)&#13;
Beneficiaries:        Farmers and herders (approximately 75,000 inhabitants) from 250&#13;
villages located in the rainfed area of 9 of Mauritania's 13 Regions.&#13;
Povertv:              Program of Targeted Interventions&#13;
Credit Amount:        SDR 13.2 million (US$18.0 million equivalent)&#13;
Terms:                Standard IDA terms, with 40 years' maturity and 10 years grace&#13;
period&#13;
Project Description   The project would be the first five-year time slice of a long term (20-&#13;
year) natural resource management program. The project has three&#13;
components: (i) allocation of funds for community investments; (ii)&#13;
provision of technical support and strengthening of the institutional&#13;
environment; and (iii) establishment of a comprehensive training&#13;
program.  The result of the implementation of these three&#13;
components is expected to be: (a) the empowerment of organized&#13;
rural communities; and (b) the creation of an enabling institutional&#13;
framework. These results are, in turn, expected to have a positive&#13;
impact on two major development-related phenomena, namely: (i)&#13;
the rehabilitation of land, water and vegetation; and, consequently&#13;
(ii) improved production, increased income and a better quality of&#13;
life for communities participating in the program.&#13;
Economic Rate of Return: Investment scenarios expected to provide 12%, 13% and 14% ERR&#13;
for pastoral, agro-pastoral and agro-sylvo-pastoral systems,&#13;
respectively.&#13;
Benefits:             The proposed project contains features that would increase crop and&#13;
livestock production, in addition to laying the groundwork for solving&#13;
other, more persistent, social and environmental problems in the rural&#13;
sector. At the village level, the project would: (i) preserve village&#13;
habitat; (ii) improve subsistence production; and (iii) increase&#13;
beneficiary revenues. At the national level, the project would help to&#13;
(i) retain people on the land, thus reducing rural outmigration; (ii)&#13;
reduce environmental degradation over the medium to long terrn; (iii)&#13;
improve the institutional environment, thus reducing social conflicts;&#13;
and (iv) ensure more sustainable maintenance of rural infrastructures.&#13;
Risks:                Risk factors which could hamper project implementation are: (i) the&#13;
administration's ability to implement this project; (ii) conflicts arising&#13;
among potential beneficiaries; (iii) the availability of relevant&#13;
technologies to be disseminated; and (iv) natural conditions (rainfall)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
which could prevent environmental rehabilitation from taking place.&#13;
Finally, risks associated with the project's ability to reduce poverty&#13;
overall include the persistence of traditional forms of social&#13;
organization which could prevent the equitable distribution of project&#13;
benefits to all segments of the population. Each of these issues has&#13;
been addressed by, respectively, (i) designing an effective&#13;
institutional setup for the project; (ii) taking full advantage of the&#13;
existing legal framework; (iii) facilitating the exchange and extension&#13;
of appropriate technologies; and (iv) establishing drought&#13;
preparedness contingency plans.&#13;
Project Financing Plan:&#13;
Contributors               US$ million           UM million                   °&#13;
IDA                            18.0                 2,556                     69&#13;
Beneficiaries                   7.5                 1,065                     29&#13;
Govemment                       0.4                   57                       2&#13;
Total                          25.9                 3,678                     100&#13;
Estimated IDA Disbursements:&#13;
US$million&#13;
FY98         FY99        FY2000        FY2001        FY2002        FY2003&#13;
Annual           1.9          2.3          2.6           4.6           6.1          0.5&#13;
Cumulative       1.9          4.2          6.8          11.4          17.5          18.0&#13;
Map: No. IBRD 28452&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ISLAMIC REPUBLIC OF MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
I.    BACKGROUND&#13;
A. THE COUNTRY&#13;
1.01        The Islamic Republic of Mauritania covers a territory in the Western Sahara of&#13;
over one million km2, and consists largely of desert, except for its southern fringe. Its&#13;
population of 2.3 million, which is growing at an annual rate of 2.5 %, depends to a great extent&#13;
on agriculture and stockraising for its livelihood. The prolonged droughts of the 1970s and early&#13;
1980s have caused great social upheaval: the population, about two-thirds of which was&#13;
nomadic in 1965, has become largely sedentary and/or has moved to urban centers. More than&#13;
half the population now lives in cities (compared to 5% in 1960) and Mauritania has one of the&#13;
world's highest urban growth rates (6.9 % annually). In the countryside, the rural population has&#13;
mainly settled in the Senegal Valley (which is now home to about 30% of the total) and in the&#13;
rainfed zone adjoining it to the north (15% of the total). Only 10 % of the total population&#13;
remains nomadic. These large population shifts have put great stress on the limited land, other&#13;
natural resources and on Government services. This was a factor in the political unrest that&#13;
occurred in the 1989-1992 period.&#13;
B. THE ECONOMY&#13;
1.02        Mauritania is a low-income country, with a per capita GNP estimated at US$460&#13;
equivalent in 1995. Over two-thirds of the population depends on agriculture, livestock and&#13;
fishing for a living; together, these activities account for about one third of GDP. Mauritania is&#13;
also an important iron ore producer and has rich fishing grounds; iron ore and fish products are&#13;
the mainstay (over 90%) of its exports.&#13;
1.03        Mauritania's economic development through the mid-1980s was uneven and&#13;
marked by major financial imbalances and highly interventionist government policies. Despite&#13;
investment rates as high as 36% of GDP in the early 1980s, the long-term rate of growth&#13;
averaged only 2%, which was slower than that of the population. Faced with a deepening crisis,&#13;
the Govemment adopted an economic adjustment program in 1985, which improved macro-&#13;
economic performance considerably: from 1985 to 1989, real GDP growth was 3.4%. During&#13;
this period, key reforms were enacted: price liberalization, abolishment of all import licenses and&#13;
quotas, and privatization of rice processing and marketing. From 1989 to 1992, however, the&#13;
country suffered a series of intemal shocks (unfavorable weather, institutional bottlenecks, the&#13;
Senegal-Mauritania crisis of 1989, and the Persian Gulf crisis of 1990-91), which had a severe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2 -&#13;
impact on economic and financial performance. Real GDP growth fell to 1.7% in 1992, and the&#13;
public sector deficit (excluding grants and restructuring operations) doubled from 1.6% to 3.1%&#13;
of GDP. To counteract these trends, the Government launched in 1992 a renewed adjustment&#13;
program that provided for a 27% devaluation of the Ouguiya (UM); liberalization of foreign&#13;
exchange; reduction of inflation (from 10% in 1992 to 4.7% in 1996); and a reduction in the&#13;
fiscal deficit (from over 3.1% in 1992 to 0.8% in 1995.) This has resulted in an annual GDP&#13;
growth rate of 4.9% over the past four years (1993-96), a remarkable recovery from the&#13;
stagnation of the three preceding years. The underlying strategy of the adjustment program, to&#13;
which the Government fully subscribes, has been (i) to create an environment conducive to&#13;
private sector development as a basis for economic growth; (ii) to check public sector deficits&#13;
through structural reform of public enterprises; and (iii) to increase public sector efficiency&#13;
through more decentralized decision-making and increased institutional capacity.&#13;
C. THE RURAL SECTOR&#13;
1.04        In an arid country where nearly 90% of the land area is desert (i.e., receives less&#13;
than 150 mm of rainfall annually), the raising of drought-tolerant livestock (cattle, sheep, goats&#13;
and camels) is the activity best suited for survival. In Mauritania, it is the most important&#13;
agricultural occupation, accounting for about 80% of agricultural GDP. This percentage has&#13;
remained remarkably stable: during the drought years, when large numbers of animals died or&#13;
were slaughtered for lack of fodder, it declined to 74%, only to rise again to 81% in the better&#13;
rainfall years after 1985. By contrast, crop production contributes less than 20% to agricultural&#13;
GDP and fluctuates more, since it depends on rainfall. Over the past ten years, it has increased&#13;
overall by only 0.6% per year, while ranging in individual years from a 41.3% decline (1990) to&#13;
37.0% growth (1993) over the preceding year. Until the late 1970s, the country was self-&#13;
sufficient in cereals and milk and a net exporter of meat. Subsequent droughts, as well as a shift&#13;
in demand by an increasingly urban populace towards wheat and rice at the expense of sorghum&#13;
and millet, have made the country more dependent on food imports, including a declining&#13;
proportion of food aid.&#13;
The Resource Base&#13;
1.05        Cropping. The availability of water is the main determinant of agricultural&#13;
production in Mauritania. This factor limits the cultivable land area to about 0.5% of the total.&#13;
Table 1 shows land potential, as distinct from its actual utilization. Only in the southeast of the&#13;
country (Guidimaka and Hodh regions) is rainfall sufficient (450 - 550 mm. annually) to allow&#13;
rainfed cropping; on average, about 120,000 ha are cropped here annually. Everywhere else,&#13;
cropping depends on supplementary water supplies. The latter are used most extensively in flood&#13;
recession cropping (on residual soil moisture after flood waters have receded), which is practiced&#13;
in the Senegal River Valley on about 35,000 ha, and water harvesting (on some 30,000 ha in&#13;
bottomlands and behind retention dikes) in the area north of the Senegal Valley but south of the&#13;
"Route de I 'Espoir", where rainfall ranges from 150 mm to 400 mm. annually. In all of these&#13;
systems, sorghum and millet, sometimes in rotation with cowpeas, are the main crops. Finally,&#13;
the Senegal Valley has some 19,000 fully irrigated hectares, almost all under rice. The area&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3 -&#13;
under irrigation has been increasing since private irrigation development was permitted four&#13;
years ago.&#13;
1.06        Annual consumption of grains, the basis of the Mauritanian diet, is around&#13;
300,000 tons a year. Of this, about 200,000 tons can be supplied by domestic producers in a&#13;
good year: some 150,000 tons in the form of sorghum and millet, which are subsistence crops&#13;
mainly consumed on the farm; and about 50,000 tons as paddy, a cash crop sold in urban&#13;
markets.&#13;
1.07        Livestock raising. Mauritania's livestock herd is large, and grazes on almost 14&#13;
million ha of sylvo-pastoral land, or 14% of the country's area (Table 1). The livestock&#13;
population breaks down into approximately eight million sheep and goats, 1.4 million cattle and&#13;
one million camels. Annual meat production, which satisfies domestic demand, is estimated at&#13;
60,000 tons per year, of which 50% is sheep and goat meat, 35% beef and 15% camel meat.&#13;
Milk production does not currently meet the country's needs. Veterinary services are generally&#13;
available, but animal husbandry is largely traditional and productivity is low, since pasturelands&#13;
have been stagnating in productivity and declining in quality.&#13;
Table 1: Land potential in Mauritania (' 000 Ha)&#13;
Potential     Potential as %    Actual Usage&#13;
of total&#13;
Cultivable land&#13;
&#149; under rainfed conditions       220              0.20          120&#13;
. flood recession/harvesting     139              0.15           65&#13;
. oases                            6               --&#13;
. irrigable area                 137              0.15           1 9&#13;
Subtotal cultivable land       502             0.5           204&#13;
Rangelands              13,800            13.40&#13;
Forest lands (gazetted)         48             --&#13;
Desert                88,719            86.10&#13;
Total land area          103,069           100.0&#13;
1.08        The livestock industry has been undergoing great changes which, although&#13;
painful, have laid the groundwork for higher productivity growth and better security against&#13;
droughts.  First, the drought years have largely eliminated the purely nomadic system of&#13;
transhumance (except for camel herds), and those pastoralists who did not become city dwellers&#13;
have largely settled in the southern fringe of the country, in or near the Senegal Valley. They are&#13;
now more likely to grow crops, and in the dry season will only trek short distances with their&#13;
animals to watering points in the area. With increased settlement density in the southern areas,&#13;
the competition for water resources and good pasture and cropland has increased. Thus, there is&#13;
a more widely felt need for broader application of irrigation and water harvesting techniques for&#13;
cropping, better maintenance of watering points, and pasture improvement technologies.&#13;
Second, demographic shifts within the country have created an important urban market for meat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4 -&#13;
and milk where little or none existed before. Hence, while livestock raising was largely for&#13;
subsistence in the past (with some live cattle exports to neighboring countries),  it has&#13;
increasingly become a commercial undertaking which is spurring the demand for productivity-&#13;
and quality-improving technologies, as well as for more efficient marketing circuits.&#13;
1.09        Fuelwood Production.  As the prime source of household energy, fuelwood is&#13;
important in the Mauritanian economy, even in urban centers. Total wood resources, primarily&#13;
in the sylvo-pastoral steppes in the south and in the Senegal Valley, were tentatively estimated in&#13;
1991 at 700,000 m3 per year, of which some 10% to 20% was considered accessible for cutting.&#13;
1.10        Several developments have put a severe strain on wood supplies. Successive&#13;
droughts have retarded growth, and even destroyed part of the resource. Increased cropping and&#13;
grazing in the area where most of the forest and bush are found have further exacerbated this&#13;
trend. Most importantly, the explosive growth of cities has pushed the demand for charcoal to&#13;
such levels that forests (including gazetted forests closer to cities) have become depleted. The&#13;
supply response to this growth in demand has consisted of little more than accelerated cutting of&#13;
existing wood resources. Forest protection measures by the Government (in gazetted forests)&#13;
have been relatively ineffective, and reforestation has so far been insignificant. Under the&#13;
Domestic Energy Strategy (SED) launched by Government in 1990, incentives were created to&#13;
substitute gas for fuelwood. This policy has been relatively successful, with gas consumption&#13;
increasing from 9,000 tons in 1991 to 14,000 tons in 1995. But gas is considerably more&#13;
expensive than charcoal per BTU, so the gas market will be limited to affluent urban consumers&#13;
for a long time to come. Therefore, this policy has not really been able to substantially reduce&#13;
charcoal consumption or halt environmental degradation. In fact, the major charcoal-producing&#13;
areas shifted from Rosso (200 km east of Nouakchott) during the 1980s, to Kaedi (450 km east of&#13;
Nouakchott) during the early 1 990s, finally ending up in Selibabi (600 km east of Nouakchott) at&#13;
present.&#13;
1.11        An important obstacle thus far to the development of a wood supply strategy has&#13;
been that forest and bush areas are considered "open" territory, where cutting, grazing and&#13;
clearance for cropping can be carried out without interference. Typically, charcoal makers need&#13;
only a permit from the Regional Governor to cut wood, and villages with wood resources have&#13;
had little or no say in the exploitation of that resource.  Under such conditions, there is no&#13;
incentive to maintain or replant wood: charcoalers will simply move to other areas after&#13;
depletion of the forest. It is now acknowledged that villagers should have a greater say in the&#13;
exploitation of their wood resources. A legal framework exists for such a shift (para. 1.25), and&#13;
they should be helped to arrive at agreements with charcoalers ("contrats participatifs") in the&#13;
interest of more rational forest exploitation and the creation of rural wood markets.&#13;
Production Systems&#13;
1.12        Farming systems in Mauritania typically embrace each of the above-mentioned&#13;
activities (livestock raising, cropping and wood gathering), but their interdependence varies&#13;
according to rainfall. In the drier areas of the rainfed zone, a pastoral production system will&#13;
predominate, in which stockraising provides the bulk of subsistence and monetary income, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5 -&#13;
cropping is marginal. Transhumance is still necessary under this system to provide sufficient&#13;
feed for the herd. In areas with somewhat more rainfall, agro-pastoral production systems are&#13;
found, in which cropping is more important (although seldom predominant). They have a higher&#13;
degree of sedentarization, and transhumance is practiced only over short distances. Finally, in&#13;
the most humid areas, where wood resources are still fairly abundant, a2ro-sylvo-pastoral&#13;
production systems predominate. These are usually well integrated, as in flood-recession areas&#13;
where dry season pastures are among the richest in the country. Even here, however, cropping&#13;
seldom predominates unless full-scale irrigation is practiced (as in the Senegal Valley).&#13;
1.13        In addition to the poor natural endowment of the rural sector and the harsh&#13;
climatic conditions, the constraints common to all production systems are: (i) the low level of&#13;
empowerment and the inadequate application of the existing legal framework, which prevent&#13;
rural communities from dealing effectively with the increased competition for land and water&#13;
resulting from population shifts; (ii) poor technical knowledge, on the part of both rural&#13;
populations and technical services, of relevant natural resource management technologies&#13;
(especially in rangeland management) which would be economically replicable and technically&#13;
sustainable; and (iii) the fact that, even when the institutional environment is not an issue and the&#13;
technology is available, these cannot be implemented for want of the required financial&#13;
resources.&#13;
D. THE ENVIRONMENT&#13;
1.14        Fragmentary data on natural resources exists in Mauritania, but it is currently&#13;
scattered among various ministries, project management units and NGOs, in addition to being of&#13;
variable quality and reliability. There is considerable redundancy and confusion between the&#13;
data produced by different agencies. Topographic maps are often outdated or unavailable, and&#13;
some thematic maps are imprecise or inconsistent in their use of geographic place namnes. Also,&#13;
there is a general lack of circulation and exchange of information at all levels in Mauritania, a&#13;
problem that severely compromises the quality of planning, monitoring and evaluation of&#13;
environment-related activities.&#13;
1.15        Land degradation is considered the major challenge to Mauritania's future. The&#13;
stages in the fight against desertification are closely linked to international and regional&#13;
initiatives. Landmark documents and activities include: (i) the adoption of the PDLCD (French&#13;
acronym of the Program of Desertification Control) by the Council of Ministers in 1987; (ii) the&#13;
preparation, with support from ESMAP (Energy Sector Management Assistance Programn), of a&#13;
domestic energy strategy (1990); (iii) the preparation of a Tropical Forest Action Plan (PAFT -&#13;
1990); (iv) the preparation of the PMLCD, or Multisectoral Desertification Control Program,&#13;
based on the  PAFT and the PDLCD (1991); (v) the Mauritanian Country Environmental&#13;
Strategy Paper (CESP), which identified major problem areas; (vi) Government's signature of&#13;
the Convention on Desertification (1994); and (vii) the preparation of a National Environmental&#13;
Action Program (NEAP), begun in March 1995 and due to be finalized by the end of 1997.&#13;
1.16        The Country Environmental Strategy Paper of 1994 identified three major&#13;
problem areas: (i) the absence of sustainable, equitable and efficient management of natural&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6 -&#13;
resources; (ii) the overfishing of coastal waters, which is depleting a formerly rich resource base;&#13;
and (iii) the rapid emergence of water supply and sanitation problems in urban areas. It cites four&#13;
natural resource management issues: the development of irrigation in the Senegal River Valley;&#13;
land degradation in the rainfed zone, especially sand dune encroachment and deforestation;&#13;
problems associated with pastoralism; and overexploitation of water in the oases of the desert&#13;
zone.&#13;
1.17        To a large extent, the natural resource management issues developed in the CESP&#13;
correspond to the analysis and issues outlined in the preceding paragraphs. Increasingly,&#13;
however, it is possible to discern strategies that would help alleviate these problems and diminish&#13;
their impact over the medium to long term. Land degradation could be addressed by better&#13;
resource management using the "gestion de terroir" or community-based natural resource&#13;
management approach, which is one of the goals of the proposed project as far as the rainfed&#13;
zone is concerned. Similarly, techniques exist to improve pasture management even under&#13;
conditions of intense grazing pressure. Such techniques have been successfully tried in other&#13;
parts of the Sahel and would be introduced into Mauritania under the proposed project. Finally,&#13;
participatory approaches to forest exploitation, also to be introduced under the project, would&#13;
create incentives for better preservation of existing wood resources, permitting their exploitation&#13;
at sustainable levels.&#13;
E. INSTITUTIONS&#13;
Territorial Organization&#13;
1.18        Administratively, Mauritania is divided into: (i) 13 regions (wilaya), each of&#13;
which is under the authority of a governor (wali) assisted by two or three assistant governors&#13;
(wali moucaid); (ii) 53 districts (moughataa) directed by a prefect (hakem); (iii) 205&#13;
municipalities (communes), of which 163 are rural. The mandate and attributions of the&#13;
territorial administration are defined by order No. 90.002 of January 31, 1990. This whole set-up&#13;
is under the purview of the Ministry of the Interior, Post and Telecommunications (MIPT) and in&#13;
particular of its directorates: Regional Planning and Interventions (DATAR), Local&#13;
Communities, and Political Affairs and Public Liberties. Civil society, on the other hand, is&#13;
organized at the municipal level, where each commune (including village communities within&#13;
their boundaries) has the status of a decentralized territorial collectivity with its administration&#13;
and local management under the responsibility of an elected mayor. Municipal management&#13;
involves local fiscal revenues and budgeting under the control of the Ministry of Finance, but&#13;
human and material resources are extremely scarce in rural communes.&#13;
Government Services in the Rural Sector&#13;
1.19        The Ministry of Rural Development and Environment (MDRE) is the agency&#13;
responsible for the development of livestock and agriculture, as well as for environmental&#13;
protection. The MDRE was reorganized in March 1993 by decree No. 22-93 so as to better use&#13;
its resources at field level. It now has three technical directorates: DRAP (agriculture and&#13;
livestock), DRFV (research education and extension) and DEAR (forestry and environment),&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7 -&#13;
together with a Planning Unit (Cellule de Planification) at cabinet level. In the field, Regional&#13;
Delegations of the MDRE have been established in each wilaya, under the authority of the wali.&#13;
Taken together, the public structures dealing with rural development, excluding SONADER,&#13;
employed nearly 1,200 agents by late 1993, of which 176 were senior staff and technicians, and&#13;
700 lower-level staff divided amongst the regional delegations. Aside from the Banc D'Arguin&#13;
National Park, a public entity under the Govermment's General Secretariat, the MDRE&#13;
supervises public entities (in particular SONADER, CNERV and the Diawling National Park) as&#13;
well as two semi-public enterprises: UNCACEM and CAIE.&#13;
1.20        MDRE's operations are hampered by: (i) the inadequate number of qualified field&#13;
staff; (ii) an operating budget that has been stagnant since 1988, with only 60% of the Ministry's&#13;
resources funneled to the regions; and (iii) difficulties in personnel management when it comes&#13;
to responding to demands from the rural sector.&#13;
Producer's Groups. Associations and Coops&#13;
1.21        Rural entities wishing to organize themselves in Mauritania have two options: (i)&#13;
cooperative association under the Cooperative Law of January 1993, and under the authority of&#13;
the Agriculture and Livestock Directory (DRAP) of the Ministry of Rural Development&#13;
(MDRE); and (ii) community association under the Law of June 1964, and under the authority of&#13;
the Directorate of Political Affairs and Public Liberties of the Ministry of Interior.&#13;
1.22        Thirty-nine pastoral "cooperative associations" (APs) have been established under&#13;
the IDA-funded Livestock II project in the 8 wilayas south of the "Route de l'Espoir." These&#13;
APs formally represent 660,000 people living in 1,100 villages. Although the new Law has&#13;
boosted the number of rural coops, they have not been very effective so far and, according to a&#13;
survey performed during this project's preparation, village investments carried out by now-&#13;
completed projects have shown a poor level of sustainability. The reasons for such poor&#13;
performance include: (i) the weak skills of the organizations' leaders, which prevent them from&#13;
managing funds properly and from diversifying activities (input supply and marketing of&#13;
production); and (ii) the organizations' lack of access, even when they enjoy legal recognition, to&#13;
the financial resources required to start a new activity. Three major agriculture and herders'&#13;
associations are represented at the national level: the GNAP (representing pastoral cooperative&#13;
associations), the FNAEM, and the FNEM.&#13;
1.23        Because it is not of a sectoral nature and can cover different types of activities, the&#13;
"community association" option has been chosen by many programs dealing with agricultural&#13;
and non-agricultural activities, such as the management of solar pumps (UE), the construction of&#13;
classrooms (IDA), rural pharmacies, transportation, etc. In addition, when such associations are&#13;
awarded the "public interest" status (reconnaissance d'interet public), they may manage public&#13;
funds and can be granted some authority in managing and protecting Government-owned&#13;
resources (water points, forests). Since they are managed under the Ministry of Interior, such&#13;
types of organizations have better access to regional and local administrations, and are better&#13;
suited to dealing with community-based natural resource management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8 -&#13;
Land Tenure&#13;
1.24         The current land tenure legislation has emerged mainly in response to conditions&#13;
specific to the irrigated areas (Senegal River Valley), and needs further refinement and official&#13;
mechanisms (i.e., decrees) providing for its application to rainfed areas. It offers some scope for&#13;
ensuring secure tenure for the affected communities: the concept of harim. or vital space,&#13;
borrowed from Islamic law (sharia), was introduced under the law dealing with settlements. It&#13;
has already been broadened by the addition of the notion of land reserve, which is used in tenure&#13;
regularization efforts in the Senegal River Valley (Trarza). The notion of the indivisibilitv of&#13;
collective rights in a cooperative context opens up another possible avenue for the devolution of&#13;
state-held land rights, according to which these collective rights would be acknowledged as&#13;
belonging exclusively to a defined group, without there being a possibility (for ecological or&#13;
social reasons) of a drift towards the regime of concession rurale, or private property. The&#13;
State's option to grant leases of public lands and publicly created infrastructures offers another&#13;
possibility for the devolution of public lands to local communities, cooperatives or associations.&#13;
1.25         A study was carried out during project preparation to assess the relevance of the&#13;
legislative framework. Its conclusions, which were confirmed by the Government, were that the&#13;
project could be implemented under the existing legal framework, namely: (i) the Ordinance of&#13;
June 5, 1983, and its Decree of Application of January 31, 1990 concerning the private allocation&#13;
of agricultural lands; (ii) the Water Code of July 4, 1985 stating that under certain circumstances&#13;
private entities might be granted exclusive rights over water resources outside privately owned&#13;
land; (iii) the Forestry Code of December 15, 1982 acknowledging the rights of some private&#13;
users to manage gazetted forests; and (iv) the Ordinance of June 5, 1983 authorizing the State to&#13;
grant exclusive grazing rights to a given group of users.&#13;
F. SECTORAL ISSUES AND STRATEGY&#13;
Lessons Learned with IDA Lending&#13;
1.26         The World Bank Group has been involved in Mauritania's agricultural sector&#13;
since 1971, mainly in support of investments in irrigation, livestock development and anti-&#13;
desertification efforts.  Several projects, either completed, under implementation or under&#13;
preparation, are relevant to the sector (see Annex 1). A substantial store of experience is&#13;
therefore available to help identify and overcome strategic difficulties encountered in: (i) rural&#13;
development projects; (ii) the agricultural sector at large; and (iii) the policy environment for&#13;
agriculture.&#13;
1.27         Past projects in the rural sector have encountered such obstacles as: (i) generally&#13;
inappropriate top-down desIns that preclude sustainability and a sense of ownership; (ii) poor&#13;
financial manag'ement resulting in extensive implementation delays; (iii) len2tgrv procurement&#13;
processes ; (iv) ineffective field services, which have often been unresponsive to beneficiaries'&#13;
demands; and (v) lack of counterpart funding due to budgetary problems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9-&#13;
1.28        In addition, Mauritanian agriculture is hobbled by four factors that can only be&#13;
overcome in the long run. First the poor level of natural resource endowment demands&#13;
familiarity with, and application of, relevant technologies in order to put production on secure&#13;
footing and attain acceptable levels of productivity. In certain fields such as water harvesting,&#13;
technologies are already well developed. In others, however, such as pasture management,&#13;
animal fodder production and storage, there is a great need for improvement and adaptation to&#13;
local ecological conditions. Second, rural communities lack the institutional capacity to reverse&#13;
the current trend toward impoverishment. They are insufficiently organized, they lack the&#13;
authority to steer Government technical services toward their needs and, until recently, the legal&#13;
and regulatory framework did not support their empowerment. Tbird, rural communities' low&#13;
level of market integration into the monetary economy causes a critical shortage of savings and&#13;
investment instruments (credits, grants, etc. ). Fourth, most resources (human and financial)&#13;
have been allocated to irrigation, while rainfed agriculture has been neglected.&#13;
Main Conclusions of Economic and Sector Work&#13;
1.29        Recently completed economic and sector work, subsequent discussion of its&#13;
conclusions with Government, and the results of ongoing adjustment programs have all pointed&#13;
the way to a comprehensive development strategy for the sector at large. These ESW products&#13;
are described below.&#13;
1.30        The Country Assistance Strategy. The 1994 CAS, as well as the 1997 draft CAS,&#13;
set forth a comprehensive development strategy for Mauritania, including: (i) human resource&#13;
development and poverty reduction to develop the skills of rural communities, create conditions&#13;
conducive to their empowerment, and improve the quality of life of rainfed farmers; (ii) private&#13;
sector development, including decentralization of civil works, services and input supply to&#13;
provide incentives to local contractors rather than to businesses based in Nouakchott; (iii)&#13;
development of the agricultural sector along participatory lines, in the interest of a stronger&#13;
economy; (iv) economic management and capacity building; and (v) environmental protection&#13;
and rehabilitation.&#13;
1.31        The Country Environmental Strategy Paper (1994) identified three major&#13;
challenges: the unsustainable, inequitable and inefficient management of natural resources; the&#13;
overexploitation of fisheries; and urban expansion. The CESP proposed three degrees of priority&#13;
for the problems at hand: (i) due to their great ecological and socio-economic value, a high level&#13;
of priority would go to the sustainable development of the Senegal River Valley, the sustainable&#13;
use of fishing grounds, the management of fuelwood supply and demand, and control of the&#13;
salinization of aquifers; (ii) medium priority would be accorded to the control of sand dune&#13;
encroachment, soil erosion and fertility loss, solid waste disposal, and the overuse of aquifers in&#13;
oases, given their ecological and socio-economic importance; and (iii) a lesser degree of priority&#13;
would go to urban wastewater disposal and pollution control, biodiversity, environmental impact&#13;
of mining, and coastal pollution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
1.32        The povertv alleviation strategy (1994) acknowledges that the incidence of&#13;
poverty in the rainfed (East and Center) rural areas of the country is between 62% and 75%, a&#13;
rate which is among the highest in the country (as against 40% in urban areas and 57% for&#13;
Mauritania as a whole). The strategy laid out in this document, which recommends assisting the&#13;
most vulnerable segments of the population, cites six major priorities to be included in any rural-&#13;
oriented development strategy: (i) promotion of producers' organizations; (ii) effective&#13;
management of land and water; (iii) protection against desertification; (iv) land tenure security;&#13;
(v) establishment of local micro-financing schemes; and (vi) skills development among rural&#13;
dwellers.&#13;
1.33        The agricultural development strategv agreed upon in 1995 with the Government&#13;
would be pursued through (i) active participation of villagers in the design and implementation&#13;
of agricultural policies for which incentives would be provided; (ii) improved technical support&#13;
to help villagers increase and diversify production; (iii) rehabilitation of existing irrigated&#13;
perimeters rather than the creation of new ones; (iv) establishment of a national NRM program&#13;
and of a legal and institutional framework giving local communities greater authority and&#13;
responsibility; and (v) adoption of reforms to help streamline services and intensify production&#13;
through appropriate policies on land use, extension and improved competitiveness of local&#13;
products.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
II.   THE PROJECT&#13;
A. RATIONALE AND OBJECTIVES&#13;
Sector Development. Objectives and Strategv&#13;
2.01        The proposed operation would capitalize on steps that Government has already&#13;
taken to: (a) improve the policy environment with greater empowerment of local rural&#13;
communities and the decentralization of MDRE's services; (b) implement the CESP's&#13;
environmental recommendation concerning more efficient management of natural resources; and&#13;
(c) strengthen oneoin2' operations by coordinating with existing extension services, devising a&#13;
domestic energy strategy, and liaising with the PDIAIM project now under preparation.&#13;
Rationale and value-added of IDA involvement&#13;
2.02        IDA should be involved because the proposed project would: (i) help the country&#13;
to implement its development strategy; (ii) link macropolicy measures supported by IDA and&#13;
investment/capacity building; (iii) promote the emergence of coherent rural sector development&#13;
programs by coordinating operations currently under implementation (such as the PSA) or under&#13;
preparation (such as the PDIAIM); (iv) exploit lessons learned under earlier projects; (v) bring&#13;
IDA's NRM experience in other countries to bear in Mauritania; (vi) pursue the household&#13;
energy strategy agreed upon in 1990; and (vii) promote donor coordination.&#13;
Logical Framework&#13;
2.03        The project would be the first five-year time slice of a long-term (20-year) natural&#13;
resource management program that would cover the whole rainfed zone of Mauritania. As&#13;
shown in the logical framework (Annex 10), the project has been designed as follows:&#13;
(a)   The Proiect's overall objective would be to control and, hopefully, reduce, the&#13;
spiral of poverty so well illustrated in this part of the world by the confluence of&#13;
population growth, environmental degradation and reduced agricultural&#13;
production.&#13;
(b)   Project's expected impact. In order to break the poverty spiral, the project is&#13;
expected to improve the basic ecological functions (water and mineral cycles,&#13;
ecological succession) through resource management, thus bringing about&#13;
sustainable yield increases (in crops and livestock) and increased incomes for&#13;
participating communities.&#13;
(c)   Proiect's expected outcome. The project's impact (described in (b) above)&#13;
depends upon two conditions, which are the project's expected outcome: (i) the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
empowerment of rural communities, i.e., the provision of skills to organize, to&#13;
manage common resources and obtain access to financing; and (ii) an improved&#13;
institutional environment in the rural sector, including secure access to natural&#13;
resources.&#13;
(d)   Proiect's output. The project is expected to produce three major outputs, which&#13;
would be required in order for the project's outcome above to take place: (i) an&#13;
improved basis for sustainable production, with well chosen and well managed&#13;
village investments; (ii) stronger technical services to the community; and (iii) the&#13;
generation and dissemination of appropriate technologies, and the development of&#13;
required skills.&#13;
(e)   Components. In order to produce the above output, the project would implement&#13;
three components: (i) village investments; (ii) strengthening of government&#13;
services; and (iii) skills development.&#13;
Project Scope&#13;
2.04        As a first five-year slice of a long-term program, the Project would intervene in&#13;
nine regions or wilayas, out of the 13 existing in Mauritania. As for the rest of the national&#13;
territory, it is recommended that consultations with other donors involved in similar activities&#13;
(Germany, European Union, IFAD) be pursued with a view to harmonizing approaches and&#13;
coordinating field interventions. Within the nine selected regions, the project would concentrate&#13;
on approximately 250 villages (roughly 10% of the 2,260 Mauritanian villages in the rainfed&#13;
area) that are home to about 75,000 inhabitants (10% of the population of the rainfed area).&#13;
While the Government identified the 62 communes in which the project would be implemented&#13;
during its first phase, guidelines for selecting villages which would benefit from the project, with&#13;
reasonable chances of success, were established (Annex 7). Since the participatory process upon&#13;
which the project is built takes time, the proposed project would be implemented over five years,&#13;
with this first tranche followed by others.&#13;
2.05        Village investments under the project would provide for the start-up of&#13;
community-level natural resource management plans. Investments for each participating village&#13;
(300 inhabitants in average) would amount to about US$30,000, to be financed under the Credit,&#13;
plus US$30,000 supplied by the beneficiaries themselves (mostly as labor) over the 3-4 years of&#13;
the project's intervention in the village.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Proiect's Phasing&#13;
2.06        In each village where the Project intervenes, there would be a first phase of&#13;
institutional/capacity building that would not exceed one year. This would be followed by the&#13;
design and approval of the NRM plan and its implementation. Phasing out of the Project at the&#13;
level of each village would occur after three to four years. Since not all the villages would be&#13;
affected in Year 1, it is expected that an increasing number of new villages would be "enrolled"&#13;
each year, and that, in each year starting in Year 3, project intervention with the first enrolled&#13;
villages would be phased out. It is also expected that much experience would be gained during&#13;
the five years of the proposed project, and that a rapidly growing number of communities would&#13;
be involved in the subsequent phases of the foreseen 20-year program. Therefore, project&#13;
implementation cannot be sequenced by starting with organization during the first phase, and&#13;
returning to the issue of investments during the project's second time slice, five years later. A&#13;
gradually increasing geographic coverage constitutes in itself the most appropriate phasing of&#13;
project implementation. The development process will not be linear, since the emergence of&#13;
greater numbers of skilled people (rurals and technicians), effective procedures, relevant policies,&#13;
adapted technologies and improved infrastructure will improve replicability. It is therefore&#13;
expected that an increasing number of villages would be involved annually at a lower extemal&#13;
cost, and that Mauritania's 2,260 villages in the rainfed area could be covered within the 20-year&#13;
program.&#13;
Proiect Imlementation: A Different Approach&#13;
2.07        The project's implementation principles are based on the key sector issues&#13;
identified in Chapter I, taking into account past experience in the development of the sector:&#13;
(a)  in a departure from previous strategies that treated the agricultural development&#13;
problem in a sub-sectoral manner (livestock, forestry, etc.), the project would&#13;
address rural development in an integrated manner. This means that all issues&#13;
facing a given community in managing its natural resources are addressed&#13;
simultaneously and holistically -- taking into account community goals and&#13;
priorities and the current state of the resource base -- with interventions chosen&#13;
on the basis of cost-effectiveness, sustainability, popular acceptance and sound&#13;
resource management principles (Annex 2; para. 13);&#13;
(b)  interventions under the project would be pro-active, and would address the&#13;
underlving causes of environmental degradation (i.e., mainly the overuse of&#13;
resources) instead of focusing on defensive actions. This would be done by&#13;
improving the management of all resources utilized in the targeted zones;&#13;
(c)   instead of the usual schema of action programs defined and implemented by&#13;
Government services, the project would be implemented in a bottom-up,&#13;
articiDatorv mode, meaning that, within the framework defined by the&#13;
government, organized communities would set goals and define scenarios and&#13;
activities for the zone under their control. During project identification and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
preparation, this method was tested with the aid of participatory rural appraisal&#13;
tools (e.g., social assessment) that made it possible to establish a dialogue with&#13;
some future beneficiaries and to gather the needed information;&#13;
(d)  to avoid redundancies and/or the neglect of important issues, the proposed&#13;
project would be carried out in close coordination with ongoing programs and&#13;
projects that may be able and willing to implement some of its components.&#13;
Cooperation Agreements or formal linkages would be established in the&#13;
following areas: extension (research and agricultural services projects);&#13;
household energy (technical assistance, public enterprise and energy project),&#13;
the provision of experience and skills (German-financed GIRNEM project);&#13;
and the European Union's 7th FED investment program, which provides&#13;
financing for the national program in the Tagant and Brakna regions and part of&#13;
the Trarza region.&#13;
(e)   instead of being designed in isolation from ongoing institutional developments,&#13;
the project would support the communal development policy currently pursued&#13;
by the government. Community-based NRM plans would be established with&#13;
the participation of elected community leaders and negotiated on their behalf.&#13;
These plans would later be integrated or harmonized into broader communal&#13;
development plans covering clusters of about 20 villages. In so doing, the&#13;
proposed project aims to reconcile Government-designed land-use plans&#13;
(amenagement du territoire) with the natural resource management plans of&#13;
communities.&#13;
B. SUMMARY DESCRIPTION&#13;
2.08        The project would include the following three components: (i) financial support&#13;
for investments in 250 villages chosen from representative agro-ecological zones of the country's&#13;
rainfed area; (ii) strengthenin-p of Government services in order to support community&#13;
organization, improve the legal framework for local empowerment, and finance Government's&#13;
technical support to beneficiaries; and (iii) enhancement of skills. including the development of&#13;
required technologies (research, short- and medium-term technical assistance), and the&#13;
dissemination of those technologies through extension and training.&#13;
C. DETAILED FEATURES&#13;
Village investments (US$16.9 Million)&#13;
2.09        Under the NRM approach, the final choice of technologies to be implemented in&#13;
each community is made by the community concerned, based on its own goals and ecological&#13;
constraints. Therefore, the village investments included in the project's cost tables should be&#13;
viewed as indicative, rather than quantitative project objectives, and not as indicators of project&#13;
achievement. The long-term project key perfonnance indicators would reflect the ecological and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
socio-economic impact of the community-based NRM  approach (Annex 11).  Short-term&#13;
implementation would be monitored according to the specific investment objectives included in&#13;
the project's annual work plan, and on the basis of community NRM plans that will have been&#13;
negotiated and agreed upon with technical support teams and regional authorities.&#13;
2.10        Village investments represent a large percentage of both the Credit and the total&#13;
project cost, since the equivalent of US$10 million (56% of the US$18 million Credit, including&#13;
price contingencies) would be invested at village level, while the total cost of village&#13;
investments, including beneficiaries' contributions, would amount to the equivalent of US$16.9&#13;
million, or 65% of the total project cost of US$25.9 million. By any standard, this is a high&#13;
proportion of credit proceeds allocated to end beneficiaries, in addition to the cost of their&#13;
technical support and training.&#13;
2.11        Land and water conservation. The land and water conservation techniques&#13;
envisaged require the project to supply the following inputs: (i) transportation of stones, soil,&#13;
water, building materials; (ii) plant material (seedlings and seeds); (iii) mechanized works (earth&#13;
moving, boring, firebreaks, harrowing, pitting); (iv) construction material (concrete, roofing,&#13;
beams and wire netting); (v) fencing material (posts, barbed wire); and (vi) sand dune fixation&#13;
devices (mesh, plastic, etc.). Project beneficiaries would supply the required labor, representing&#13;
up to 70% of costs. The technologies to be used for investments in land and water are outlined in&#13;
Annex 3:&#13;
(a)   water harvesting techniques, including stone and vegetation contour bunds,&#13;
surface water management dikes, and the deepening of natural and artificial&#13;
ponds;&#13;
(b)   preservation of soil fertility, erosion prevention and control of sand dune&#13;
encroachment, also including stone and vegetation contour bunds, gully&#13;
correction and sand dune fixation;&#13;
(c)   forage production on rangelands, and fuelwood production, including&#13;
protection and plantation, although most of these objectives require improved&#13;
management rather than additional investments;&#13;
(d)   rehabilitation and construction of rural roads;&#13;
2.12        Some technologies included in this component are already well developed in&#13;
Mauritania. This is especially true of dune fixation and water harvesting (cultures derriere&#13;
barrage), which are familiar to Mauritanian farmers. Others, such as plantations, have been&#13;
tested in Mauritania in the past, while certain other technologies, such as different types of bunds&#13;
(diguettes), have been developed in neighboring countries (e.g., Sahel, North Africa) from which&#13;
expertise will be sought under the project.&#13;
2.13        Infrastructure and eguipment.  These investments are needed by rural&#13;
communities, and particularly by women, who spend much time on water collection and food&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
processing. Nevertheless, in order to avoid disincentives to private initiative and to encourage&#13;
the use of credit (when available), the financing of these investments would be contingent upon a&#13;
level of cash contributions from beneficiaries not lower than 20% of the total cost. In order to&#13;
ensure proper operation and maintenance of the equipment, such investments would only be&#13;
funded under the community NRM package when (a) a community expresses strong demand and&#13;
shows serious commitment to its further operation and maintenance; (b) no other source of&#13;
financing (credit or other program) exists; and (c) a specialized entity (e.g., NGO or other&#13;
project) can provide backstopping for the sustainability of the investment. Detailed procedures&#13;
on how these investments would be financed, operated and maintained have been included in the&#13;
project's implementation manual. The following investments would be financed under the&#13;
component:&#13;
(a)   civil works related essentially to water supply (water wheels, drilling, cisterns)&#13;
and, to a lesser extent, rural roads and community buildings (e.g., storage&#13;
facilities, cooperative shops, market and livestock handling facilities, etc.);&#13;
(b)   mechanical equipment, including different types of pumps (wind mills,&#13;
motorized pumps), forest management equipment (chain saws) where&#13;
applicable, food processing devices (grain mills, oil extractors);&#13;
(c)   small agricultural equipment, also for community use (carts, wheelbarrows,&#13;
etc.), all types of agricultural tools (plows, etc.) and fencing material (where&#13;
applicable), as part of the execution of an agreed village investment.&#13;
(d)   water supply installations as part of the West African Pilot Pastoral Program,&#13;
which is aimed at assessing the relevance of a new approach to rangeland&#13;
management, and is currently implemented in six Sahelian countries under the&#13;
coordination of the Bank (Annex 2, para. 13).&#13;
2.14        Other investments (micro-enterprises). The project would provide financing for&#13;
these investments to a maximum of 60% of their costs, with the remainder financed (in cash) by&#13;
the beneficiaries, according to detailed guidelines included in the project's implementation&#13;
manual. The shortage of capital at village level, the poor or non-existent access to credit, and the&#13;
limited savings potential, make this component particularly crucial to the success of the project.&#13;
When properly managed, such operations have proven an effective means of transitioning to&#13;
effective community-based credit schemes, provided they: (i) ensure training for community staff&#13;
in financial management and accounting; (ii) foster activities targeted to external markets; and&#13;
(iii) effect a change in mentalities, after which the fund is no longer perceived as a Government&#13;
subsidy, but instead as a common good requiring community-wide commitment. The proposed&#13;
project would provide funds for income generating activities in line with project's objectives,&#13;
including, but not limited to:&#13;
(a)   cooperative and/or individual livestock fattening, for which funds are required&#13;
to purchase animals and store feed until the time of marketing;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
(b)   grain storage, for which cash is needed to free farmers of the obligation to&#13;
market their production at harvest time, when prices are lowest.  Such&#13;
operations could be of a cooperative or individual nature;&#13;
(c)   human and animal medicine supply (a successful undertaking under Livestock&#13;
II), with possible expansion to other inputs. Although they have initially been&#13;
managed on a cooperative basis, associations tend ultimately to have these&#13;
pharmacies managed by village-trained auxiliaries, thus guaranteeing that the&#13;
medicines are made available and are used efficiently;&#13;
Strengthening of Public Support ( US$4.1 million)&#13;
2.15        Institutional support provided under the project would cover three different areas:&#13;
(i) communitv organization and linkages with elected communal entities, which is being included&#13;
in the design and review of the community natural resource planning package; (ii) application of&#13;
the legal framework in order to ensure reasonably secure access to common resources; and (iii)&#13;
technical support to participating communities and to the Government in order to establish,&#13;
implement and monitor the community-based NRM plans.&#13;
(a)   At the village level, the project would be implemented by field extension&#13;
agents (AVBs) operating under the existing Agricultural Services Project&#13;
(PSA). Since this would substantially increase their current workload,&#13;
additional new agents would be recruited on a contractual basis. To ensure&#13;
adequate extension services to women, the project would encourage the&#13;
recruitment of female agents. Overall, the average ratio would be one&#13;
extension agent (agent de vulgarisation de base, A VB) for every four to six&#13;
villages, or 1/200-300 households;&#13;
(b)   Five technical support teams (EMATs), also to be recruited on a contractual&#13;
basis, would operate in the wilayas targeted under the project (para. 3.11). Each&#13;
EMAT would consist of three specialists responsible for providing&#13;
participating communities with skills not available within the existing&#13;
agricultural services, i.e.: (i) community organization, negotiation and conflict&#13;
resolution; (ii) management of communal property (especially rangeland and&#13;
forest); and (iii) financial management, access to credit and administration.&#13;
Unemployed young professionals with these profiles (not necessarily with an&#13;
agricultural background) are available in the labor market.&#13;
(c)   At the wilaya level, the Government has agreed that the project would be&#13;
implemented by existing agricultural services technical staff from regional&#13;
MDRE delegations whose salaries would be paid by the Government. This&#13;
staff would participate in project implementation and would receive daily&#13;
subsistence and required transportation from the project when working in the&#13;
field. In addition, and to complement existing staff, one regional project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18-&#13;
program assistant, as well as one financial manager and an accountant, would&#13;
be recruited on a contractual basis.&#13;
(d)   A Central Project Team (ECPG), consisting of five professionals, would be&#13;
established in Nouakchott under the cabinet of the MDRE. This Team would&#13;
include: (i) the coordinator responsible for overall project implementation,&#13;
dialogue with stakeholders, and reporting; (ii) the procurement officer; (iii) the&#13;
financial manager responsible for disbursements (Special Accounts and&#13;
Advance Accounts), village investments, accounting and auditing; (iv) a&#13;
community-based NRM specialist who would supervise the community NRM&#13;
planning process, and would be responsible for studies, WID issues and&#13;
monitoring and evaluation of project implementation and impact; and (v) the&#13;
adult training specialist who, in coordination with the national agency for&#13;
literacy, would be in charge of identifying skills gaps and recruiting&#13;
consultants. The Central Project Team will consist in principle of existing&#13;
civil servants who will be assigned to these tasks. However, because the&#13;
project is causing incremental activities and because civil service staff is&#13;
limited, contractuals could be hired if required skills are not available;&#13;
(e)   Given the pilot nature of the pastoral program (para. 2.1 1(e)), support to this&#13;
program would be geared toward providing external expertise in the areas of&#13;
rangeland management, and monitoring/evaluation of the results of the pilot.&#13;
2.16        In addition to incremental salaries for contractual staff, the proposed project&#13;
would also cover: the rehabilitation of existing offices; office equipment (photocopiers, personal&#13;
computers when required); five vehicles for the ECPG, the EMATs, and the coordinators; and&#13;
small motorcycles (125-175 cc) for the additional extension agents and field supervisors. As in&#13;
the case of the PSA, these motorcycles would be sold to agents on credit, with monthly payments&#13;
withheld from their salaries. Funding for the operation and maintenance of the vehicles and&#13;
equipment, and field allowances for the technical staff and drivers, will be borne by the project.&#13;
Skills Development (US$ 1.6 million)&#13;
2.17        Technical Assistance and Research. Adaptive research for NRM would include&#13;
diagnostic activities performed at the request of beneficiaries with support from EMATs and&#13;
researchers, followed by on-site testing. The project would finance the tests and the researchers'&#13;
services through contracts with research agencies, especially the Kaedi Research Center, but&#13;
without excluding the possibility of collaboration with other partners (public, private, NGO, etc.)&#13;
that make competitive proposals. The proposed research activities would be presented in annual&#13;
action plans to be approved by the Bank. The activities could include, for example, the&#13;
determination of the most cost-effective type of earthen dam (length, spacing, material);&#13;
measurements of the project's environmental impact (soil, vegetation, water table); the&#13;
sustainable replanting of watersheds (species, implementation, management); the choice of&#13;
species for agroforestry as a function of specific agroecological conditions, etc. The project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
would finance these activities, including 65 weeks of international specialists and 93 weeks of&#13;
national consultants.&#13;
2.18        Training and Public Awareness. The training component is crucial. Project&#13;
objectives can only be attained if support staff develops a true ability to listen, understand and&#13;
reach out to rural clients, while at the same time mastering the technical aspects of the various&#13;
rural interventions. Training, information and public awareness efforts would be directed at any&#13;
party involved in the project whenever it appears that their qualifications are not up to the&#13;
responsibilities entrusted to them. Training would be of a practical nature and generally on-site,&#13;
while the identification of skills gaps and the assessment of the program's impact would be the&#13;
responsibility of project staff. The design and implementation of training modules would mostly&#13;
be subcontracted to consultants (firms and individuals). For more details on the implementation&#13;
of this component, which will also rely on the network of rural radios (see Annex 2, paras. 3-5).&#13;
In addition to consultants' fees, the project would mainly finance beneficiaries' travel and&#13;
trainers' mission expenses. Technical support would require a total of 69 man-weeks of&#13;
expatriate consultancies, 114 man-weeks of sub-regional consultants, and 272 man-weeks of&#13;
local consultancies (Annex 12).&#13;
2.19        Improving Rural Statistical Data.   This component would also finance the&#13;
strengthening of statistical data surveys and processing in the rural sector, in order to improve the&#13;
scope and reliability of statistical data on the rural sector (crops and livestock). It will be carried&#13;
out by the National Statistical Institute (INS) under the Ministry of Planning. It will consist of&#13;
(a) a sample survey to check the relevance of data currently available on livestock (flocks, herds,&#13;
yields, production, marketing, export) and crops (areas, yields, production, marketing); and (b)&#13;
the establishment of an action plan aimed at improving the coverage and accuracy of national&#13;
statistics, to be implemented later under discrete support. The action plan would be finalized&#13;
before the mid-term review of the project.&#13;
D. PROJECT COSTS&#13;
2.20        Total base costs, net of taxes and duties, are estimated at US$25.9 million (UM&#13;
3.7 billion), based on January 1997 prices. Given the nature of investments (high dependence on&#13;
village labor, numerous small works, volumes of specific works not known before approval of&#13;
Community land management plans), physical contingencies have not been included. Price&#13;
contingencies amounting to US$2.7 million, or 12 percent of base costs, have been included and&#13;
are based on average forecasts of international inflation for foreign-supplied goods (2.5% per&#13;
annum), estimated inflation in Mauritania for local costs (3.0 percent per annum), and on an&#13;
implementation period of five years. The foreign exchange rate used was US$1.00 = UM 142&#13;
(since January 1997), and the foreign exchange portion of the total cost was estimated at 49%.&#13;
Total project costs of US$25.9 million break down as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Table 2: Project Cost Summary&#13;
(UM Million)            (US$'Million)     l_ l_l&#13;
Local Foreign  Total  Local Foreign  Total  % F E  % TBC&#13;
Project Components&#13;
1. Village Investments         1,079.2  1,326.3 2,405.5   7.6    9.3    16.9    55       73&#13;
2. Strengthening of Public Sector    400.1   184.5   584.6  2.8   1.2    4.1    32       18&#13;
3. Skills Development            141.8    91.5   233.3   1.0     0.64    1.6    39        7&#13;
4. Pastoral Pilot Program         42.9    29.6    72.5  0.3      0.2     0.5    41        2&#13;
Total Baseline Costs           1,664.0  1,631.9 3,295.9  11.7    11.5    23.2    50     100&#13;
Phyical Contingencies                -       -       -   -        -       -       -&#13;
Price Contingencies              216.0   172.4   388.3   1.5      1.2    2.7    44       12&#13;
Total Project Costs            1,880.0  1,804.3 3,684.3  13.2    12.7    25.9    49     112&#13;
% F.E. = % Foreign Exchange&#13;
% TBC = % Total Base Costs&#13;
E. FINANCING PLAN&#13;
2.21         Project costs would be financed by an IDA credit of US$18 million equivalent.&#13;
The Mauritanian contribution amounts to US$7.9 million equivalent. The financing plan is&#13;
detailed below:&#13;
Table 3: Project Financing Plan&#13;
Contributors              US$ million            UM million                  *ie&#13;
IDA                          18.0                 2,556                     69&#13;
Beneficiaries                 7.5                 1,065                     29&#13;
Government                    0.4                   57                       2&#13;
Total                        25.9                 3,678                     100&#13;
2.22         The IDA  credit would represent 69%  of project costs.  The beneficiary&#13;
contribution, (cash and labor) for village investments, is valued at US$7.5 million equivalent,&#13;
which represents 29 % of total project cost. The Government's contribution is equivalent to the&#13;
salaries of Government civil servants that would be seconded to the project. This would amount&#13;
to UM 57 million during the five project years, or 2 % of project costs. The full financing of&#13;
incremental operating costs under the project is required, since (i) the Government is funding a&#13;
portion of recurrent operating costs through the transfer of about half the project staff from other&#13;
services; and (ii) the operation is a first time slice of a long-term program, so incremental&#13;
operating costs cannot be financed on a declining basis during implementation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21 -&#13;
F. PROCUREMENT&#13;
2.23          The following table summarizes the project categories and their estimated costs&#13;
(including contingencies), as well as proposed methods of procurement. Mauritania's&#13;
procurement laws and regulations conform to IDA procurement guidelines. No special&#13;
exemptions, permits, or licenses need to be specified in Credit documents for international&#13;
competitive bidding (ICB), as Mauritania's procurement regulations allow IDA procedures to&#13;
take precedence over any contrary provisions in local regulations. All procurement for goods&#13;
and civil works would be carried out in accordance with Bank guidelines for procurement under&#13;
IBRD Loans and Credits (January 1995). All procurement for consulting services would be&#13;
carried out in accordance with the Bank's Guidelines for the Selection and Employment of&#13;
Consultants (January 1997).&#13;
Table 4: Summary of Proposed Procurement Arrangements.&#13;
(US$ million)&#13;
Categories              ICB          NCB        Other       NIF          Total&#13;
Goods                                1.2          2.0        1.1                     4.3&#13;
(1.2)        (2.0)      (1. 1)                  (4.3)&#13;
Works                                -            0.7        8.4       -             9.1&#13;
(0.7)      (8.4)                   (9.1)&#13;
Village Labor Contribution           -            -                    6.9            6.9&#13;
Beneficiary Cash Contribution        -            -                    0.6           0.6&#13;
Training &amp; Technical Support         -            -          0.9                     0.9&#13;
(0.9)                  (0.9)&#13;
Studies                              -            -           1.0      -             1.0&#13;
(1.0)                  (1.0)&#13;
Staff seconded to project            -            -                    0.4           0.4&#13;
Miscellaneous (increm. operating cost)                       2.7       -             2.7&#13;
(2.7)                  (2.7)&#13;
Total                                1.2          2.7       14.1       7.9          25.9&#13;
(1.2)        (2.7)     (14.1)     (0.0)        (18.0)&#13;
Note: Figures in parentheses are the respective amounts financed by the IDA Credit; N. 1. F.: not IDA Financed&#13;
2.24          International Competitive Bidding (ICB) would, in accordance with Bank&#13;
Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits (January 1995), be carried out&#13;
for the purchase of goods estimated to exceed US$100,000. Procurement using ICB is expected&#13;
to total US$1.2 million, mostly for the procurement of vehicles. Standard bidding documents&#13;
developed by the Bank will be used. Satellite imagery would be procured through Limited&#13;
International Bidding by inviting the existing providers, whose number is limited to two or three.&#13;
To the extent possible, contracts for goods shall be grouped in lots estimated to cost $100,000&#13;
equivalent or more each.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
2.25        National Competitive Bidding (NCB) would be carried out for goods, such as&#13;
equipment, small implements and supplies estimated to cost less than US$ 100,000 and more than&#13;
US$30,000 per contract, up to an aggregate amount not to exceed US$2.0 million equivalent; and&#13;
works estimated to cost less than US$150,000 and more than US$30,000 equivalent per contract,&#13;
up to an aggregate amount not to exceed US$0.7 million.&#13;
2.26        Small civil works contracts. Contracts for standard small works estimated to cost&#13;
less than US$30,000 per contract, up to an aggregate amount of US$8.4 million, would be&#13;
procured under lump-sum, fixed price contracts awarded on the basis of quotations obtained from&#13;
three (3) qualified domestic contractors. The invitation shall include reference unit prices&#13;
established by the ECPG, a detailed description of the works, including basic specifications, the&#13;
required completion date, a basic form of agreement acceptable to the Association, and relevant&#13;
drawings where applicable. The award would be made to the contractor who offers the lowest&#13;
price quotation for the required work, provided he demonstrates he has the experience and&#13;
resources to complete the contract successfully. These are mostly works relating to bunding, tree&#13;
planting and protection of vegetation, gully correction, watershed management and village&#13;
community projects, where most of the input (up to 70% of total costs) would come from&#13;
villagers themselves in the form of labor, and contracts would be limited to furnishing technical&#13;
assistance and the necessary materials, equipment and supplies. These works would be&#13;
supervised by five technical support teams (EMATs) based on criteria and standards applied&#13;
equally to all villages. Contributions from beneficiaries (US$7.5 million equivalent of which&#13;
US$6.9 million in labor and US$0.6 in cash) have been valued at UM 250, or about US$1.8 per&#13;
day of work. According to investment scenarios set out in Annex 8, this contribution would&#13;
amount to 21 days, 30 days and 40 days of work per active beneficiary per year in pastoral, agro-&#13;
pastoral and sylvo-agro-pastoral systems, over the three years of project implementation in the&#13;
village. In the case of water supply and productive investments, a cash contribution would be&#13;
required from the villagers (ranging from 20% to 40% of the investment cost). The project's&#13;
implementation manual describes the mechanism by which labor contributions (contracted&#13;
between the project and the ADC) would be verified and cash payments made and managed.&#13;
2.27        Local Shopping. Goods estimated to cost less than US$30,000 per contract, up to&#13;
an aggregate amount of US$ 1.1 million, would be acquired on the basis of a comparison of price&#13;
quotes from at least three reliable suppliers. These are mostly materials relating to the small civil&#13;
works mentioned above, equipment, small implements and supplies.&#13;
2.28        Consultant's Services. These services would be used for (i) studies -- land tenure,&#13;
environmental data, accounting systems, and impact analysis (estimated at 85 man weeks); (ii)&#13;
technical matters and training -- skills gap analysis, skills development (155 man weeks); and&#13;
(iii) training of project field staff and beneficiaries, estimated at 215 man weeks. Consultant&#13;
services financed by IDA, are expected to total US$1.9 million. Selection of consultants would&#13;
be done through competition among qualified short-listed firms in which the selection would be&#13;
based both on the quality of the proposal and on the cost of the services to be provided, except&#13;
for those contracts that are extimated to cost less than US$100,000. The latter would be awarded&#13;
on the basis of lowest cost. Short-lists for technical assistance contracts provided to support&#13;
ADCs, and whose value is estimated under US$100,000, may be comprised entirely of national&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23 -&#13;
consultants provided a sufficient number of qualified firms (at least three) are available at&#13;
competitive costs. However, if foreign firms have expressed interest, they would not be&#13;
excluded from consideration. Services for training sessions and small studies which can be&#13;
delivered by individual consultants would be selected through comparison of qualifications&#13;
among those approached directly or expressing interest in the assignment. The standard Letter of&#13;
Invitation and Form of Contract as developed by the Bank will be used for appointment of&#13;
consultants. Simplified forms of contract would be used for short-term assignments, i.e. those&#13;
not exceeding six months and carried out by individual consultants. The Government would be&#13;
briefed during negotiations about the special features of the new guidelines, in particular with&#13;
regard to advertisement and public bid opening. A table detailing the nature and source of&#13;
consultant services is given in Annex 12.&#13;
2.29        Adeguacy of National Bidding Procedures (NBP). National Bidding Procedures&#13;
for public sector procurement in Mauritania have proven slow and cumbersome in several past&#13;
and ongoing IDA-financed projects. It has been agreed at negotiations that, before the scheduled&#13;
mid-term review, a review of the effectiveness of national bidding procedures would be carried&#13;
out as they relate to the project's procurement experience and, if necessary, that modifications to&#13;
the current procedures would be proposed in order to accelerate project procurement while still&#13;
maintaining adequate control over contract awards and payments (para. 5.01(a)).&#13;
2.30        Procurement Reviews. IDA-financed contracts above the threshold value of&#13;
US$100,000 equivalent for goods and US$150,000 for works would be subject to IDA's prior&#13;
review procedures. The review process would cover 80 percent of the total value of the amount&#13;
contracted for goods. Selective post-review of contracts awarded below the threshold levels&#13;
would apply to about one in three contracts. Draft standard bidding documents for NCB would&#13;
be reviewed by and agreed upon with IDA. The Bank would review the selection process for&#13;
consultants proposed by the Borrower. The Borrower would be reminded that opening of the&#13;
financial envelopes cannot take place before receiving the Bank's no-objection to the technical&#13;
evaluation. Prior IDA review would not apply to contracts for the recruitment of consulting&#13;
firms and individuals estimated to cost less than US$100,000 and US$50,000 equivalent,&#13;
respectively. However, the exception to prior IDA review would not apply to Terms of&#13;
Reference of such contracts, regardless of value, to single-source hiring, to assignments of a&#13;
critical nature as determined by IDA, or to amendments of contracts raising the contract value&#13;
above the prior review threshold.&#13;
2.31        Procurement Status of Onuoiny Projects and Proposed Arrangements. During&#13;
negotiations, the Government has submitted to IDA for review: (a) a draft procurement plan; (b)&#13;
a draft Implementation Manual and (c) draft bidding documents for equipment to be procured&#13;
during the first year of project's implementation, as well as draft letters of invitation for&#13;
consultant services to be financed by IDA. The Government would submit to IDA the final&#13;
versions of these documents prior to project effectiveness. It has given assurance at negotiations&#13;
that it would apply the procurement procedures and arrangements outlined in the above&#13;
documents.  During negotiations, agreement was reached on the proper monitoring of&#13;
procurement as well as the use of the Bank's Standard Bidding Documents for ICB and that&#13;
standard procurement documents for NCB would be developed by the Borrower, reviewed by,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24 -&#13;
and agreed upon with IDA. Agreement was reached at negotiations that procurement of goods,&#13;
works and consultant services required for the project, and to be financed out of Credit proceeds,&#13;
would take place in accordance with procedures satisfactory to IDA (para.5.01(b)). During&#13;
project implementation, procurement information would be collected and recorded as follows:&#13;
(a)   prompt recording of contract award information by the Borrower; and&#13;
(b)   semi-annual reports to the Bank by the Borrower indicating (i) revised cost&#13;
estimates for individual contracts and the total project, including best estimates&#13;
of allowances for contingencies; (ii) revised timing of estimated procurement&#13;
actions, including experience with completion time and completion cost for&#13;
individual contracts; and (iii) compliance with aggregate limits on specified&#13;
methods of procurement.&#13;
G. DISBURSEMENT&#13;
2.32         The project constitutes a five-year time slice of a longer program, and the credit&#13;
would be disbursed over a period of six years (instead of the standard seven-year profile for&#13;
Mauritania). The estimated semi-annual disbursement schedule is shown in Annex 5. The IDA&#13;
credit would be disbursed on the basis of the categories shown below.&#13;
Table 5: Categories of IDA Credit Expenditures&#13;
Category                     IDA Allocation      % of expenditures&#13;
of Expenditure                  (US$ million)       to be financed&#13;
1. Works, goods and services (villages investments)  8.0               100&#13;
2. Civil works (others)                             1.0                 100&#13;
3. Goods and vehicles                               1.0                 100&#13;
4. Consultant services and training                 1.5                 100&#13;
5. Satellite imagery                                0.1                 100&#13;
6. Incremental Operating Costs                      2.5                 100&#13;
7. Refunding of PPF                                 1.0&#13;
8. Unallocated                                      2.9&#13;
Total                                              18.0&#13;
2.33         Disbursements of the IDA  credit would be fully documented, except for&#13;
expenditures valued under US$50,000 equivalent for individual consultant contracts, and under&#13;
US$100,000 for all other contracts, which would be against Statements of Expenditure (SOEs)&#13;
certified by the ECPG's Chief Financial Officer and by the Project Director. The ECPG would&#13;
be responsible for preparing withdrawal applications, and would indicate on SOEs the nature and&#13;
origin of any goods and the payment date. Documentation of withdrawals under SOEs would be&#13;
retained at the ECPG for review by IDA staff during supervision missions and for regular annual&#13;
audits.&#13;
2.34         In order to get their PICs implemented, ADCs would contract with individual&#13;
suppliers and private enterprises to get the work done. They would be supported in the process&#13;
by individual consultants when required. In order to ensure the financing, mutual conventions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
would be agreed between ADCs, providers and the project. The signature of these conventions&#13;
is a pre-requisite to the procurement and the implementation of the planned investments. With&#13;
the assistance of consultants, the ADC and the PGRNP would sign a contract with providers&#13;
selected according to the procurement procedures and the PGRNP. The investment would then&#13;
be implemented according to the convention. The signature of the Project Director or his&#13;
representative would commit the project to paying the provider according to the terms of the&#13;
contract.&#13;
2.35        To expedite disbursements, the Government would open and maintain a special&#13;
account at a commercial Bank, under terms and conditions satisfactory to IDA. The authorized&#13;
allocation would be US$800,000. IDA would make an initial deposit of US$400,000 upon&#13;
credit effectiveness, with the balance payable once cumulative disbursements under the credit&#13;
reach the equivalent of SDR 1,000,000.&#13;
2.36        In order to ensure that funds are available at the regional level, the borrower&#13;
would be allowed to withdraw from the special account, and deposit into four Advance&#13;
Accounts, an amount not exceeding the equivalent of US$50,000 each for Kiffa, Ayoun el&#13;
Atrous Nema, and Atar, and thereafter replenish said advance accounts from the special account&#13;
according to established Bank procedures. These procedures will be outlined in detail to the&#13;
borrower and the executing agencies by the Loan Department in a Disbursement Letter that will&#13;
be dispatched to the borrower and executing agencies, following Board approval. The special&#13;
account and the four Advance Accounts will be audited annually, and auditors will be required to&#13;
give a separate opinion on the operation and maintenance of these accounts as well as provide&#13;
certification of withdrawal applications that have been submitted on the basis of Statements of&#13;
Expenditures (SOEs).&#13;
2.37        The regional program assistants would obtain the necessary information justifying&#13;
incurred expenditures, which will be the basis for monthly replenishment of the Advance&#13;
Accounts from the Special Account. IDA would replenish the Special Account upon receipt of&#13;
satisfactory proof of incurred expenditures and evidence that such expenditures are eligible for&#13;
financing. Up-to-date bank statements as well as a reconciliation of the Special Account would&#13;
need to accompany each replenishment request.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
III. PROJECT ORGANIZATION AND MANAGEMENT&#13;
A. PROJECT ORGANIZATION&#13;
General Framework&#13;
3.01        The project is based upon existing structures, be they administrative services,&#13;
coordinating committees or political institutions, all acting in accordance with their usual&#13;
mandates. No new temporary ad-hoc structure is being created. All three levels of the&#13;
Mauritanian institutional set-up are affected by the project, each of them with discrete objectives:&#13;
(i) the local level, including the recently-created municipal level, with elected leaders, and the&#13;
community level, where village land-based communities make decisions regarding the&#13;
management of natural resources; (ii) the regional level, including the regions proper (wilayas)&#13;
and their district or departmental subdivisions (moughataas), where government services have a&#13;
role of review and approval; and (iii) the national level, seat of central, administrative and&#13;
political power; from which project implementation would be planned and monitored.&#13;
Detailed Set-un of the Project&#13;
3.02        Village/community level. At the local level, the project would be implemented by&#13;
the community development association (ADC) according to the guidelines stated in the&#13;
project's implementation manual. Although the choice of the Committee members is left to the&#13;
community, project staff would ensure that its members are dynamic, influential and&#13;
representative of the main socio-professional groups in the community, particularly those groups&#13;
often neglected (e.g., women and younger people), and including traditional leaders (village&#13;
chiefs) and local elected officials.  Usually, ADCs have a President (representing the&#13;
Committee), a treasurer (to collect and manage funds) and a Secretary (to keep simple books) in&#13;
addition to representatives of each of the community technical groups (GTC) dealing with the&#13;
social components of the village and the activities they carry out (agriculture, gardening, herding,&#13;
fuelwood, hunting, women's activities, etc.). For larger infrastructure works involving several&#13;
villages (large water harvesting dams, for instance), local technical committees (GTIVs) would&#13;
be established under the oversight of technical services from the MDRE Delegation.&#13;
3.03        The ADC's role is to: (i) carry out, with the project's support, the whole process&#13;
of NRM planning leading to technically feasible action plans; (ii) ensure the implementation of&#13;
planned programs and activities by mobilizing human, material and financial resources from&#13;
beneficiaries; (iii) ensure that these new facilities are being used and maintained in a sustainable&#13;
manner, and that operation and maintenance fees are being raised as agreed; (iv) help settle&#13;
litigation involving access to common resources belonging to the community; and (v) represent&#13;
the community vis-a-vis other stakeholders (project, technical services, NGOs, other&#13;
communities). From a legal standpoint, the community and its ADC need a legal status, such as&#13;
that of an association, in order to be able to enter into contractual arrangements. According to&#13;
studies carried out during project preparation, the legal framework for such recognition already&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27 -&#13;
exists. As stated in para. 1.25, the appraisal mission has agreed (and the Government has&#13;
confirmed before negotiations) that the existing legal framework accommodates project's&#13;
implementation as far as community organization and security of access to natural resources are&#13;
concerned.&#13;
3.04        Municipal level. At the municipal or communal level, the Municipal Council is&#13;
the legitimate institutional intermediary between the communities and the district and regional&#13;
administrations. Mauritanian law on territorial administration has evolved in such a way that the&#13;
municipality is involved in the design and implementation of plans for equipping the various&#13;
village lands (terroirs) that constitute it. Once community natural resource management plans&#13;
(see Para. 3.13) have been reviewed by the municipal council and approved by the regional&#13;
development committee (CRD), they will be acknowledged as compatible with national master&#13;
plans issued by DATAR, MHE, DEAR and other technical departments and become the building&#13;
blocks of any further communal and regional development planning.&#13;
3.05        District (Moughataa) Level. This level lies between the regional Government&#13;
authority (the wali in the wilaya) and the communal elected leaders (municipal council). The&#13;
Project's implementation manual describes how community's natural resource management&#13;
planning package (see Para. 3.13) is transmitted for information to the moughataa for further&#13;
communication to the wilaya. This consultation is carried out by the district development&#13;
committee (CLD) presided over by the hakem of the moughataa.  Its members include&#13;
representatives of the civil services (MDRE, health and social welfare, hydraulics, education,&#13;
energy and other decentralized government services), projects and NGOs, as well as local elected&#13;
leaders.&#13;
3.06        Regional (Wilaya) level In five capital cities of the nine wilayas where the&#13;
project intervenes, the MDRE Delegate is the Regional Project Coordinator, (CRP). He is&#13;
assisted by a regional program assistant (CPR) selected for his expertise, and recruited by the&#13;
project. Under the authority of the Director of the PGRNP and the MDRE Regional Delegate,&#13;
this contractual staff would be responsible for the project's activities in the Region: (i) with the&#13;
assistance of a financial manager, he would manage the Advance Account (where established),&#13;
expedite local procurement and payments, and maintain a general and analytical accounting; (ii)&#13;
in connection with the wilaya CRP, he would ensure that the community natural resource&#13;
management planning package submitted for approval is reviewed and processed in a timely&#13;
manner; (iii) within the MDRE Delegation, he would facilitate and monitor the participation of&#13;
civil servants from technical departments (including Ag. Services) in project activities according&#13;
to a commonly agreed work plan; and (iv) he would plan and supervise project activities at&#13;
regional level, including field visits, training, reporting and monitoring and evaluation activities.&#13;
3.07        The reg'ional dele-oation of the MDRE is the Project's operational headquarters in&#13;
the region. Three-member project support teams (EMATs) reinforce the Delegation's Rural&#13;
Organization Bureau (BOP), while civil servants from technical departments (forestry,&#13;
agriculture, livestock, genie rural) participate in project activities (SAC preparation and&#13;
implementation of project investment plans) according to an agreed-upon work program to be&#13;
monitored by the Regional Coordinator.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-28 -&#13;
3.08        The regional development committee (CRD) is presided over by the wali It&#13;
includes representatives of the administration (hakems), civil service (Ministries of Agriculture,&#13;
Interior, Health, Education, Women's Affairs, Hydraulics, Energy, etc.), private stakeholders&#13;
(NGOs and private firms), and the civil society (elected communal representatives and&#13;
professional associations). On a quarterly basis, (i) the CRD approves new community natural&#13;
resources management packages possibly in presence of community representatives, assisted by&#13;
communal elected leaders and project staff; and (ii) examines the status of project&#13;
implementation plans and apportions resources from technical services accordingly. Everv year&#13;
the CRD examines the annual NRM implementation report for the previous period and approves&#13;
the work plan and budget for the next one.&#13;
3.09        National Level.  Project financial management control is ensured, on behalf of&#13;
the Government, by the recently created Conseil de surveillance (CS) (Decree 96-026 PM of&#13;
April 1, 1996). Project technical coordination will be ensured by a Steering Committee (CP)&#13;
including representatives from relevant ministries (MDRE, Plan, Interior, Equipment, Hydraulics&#13;
and Energy) and, on a consultative basis, others such as the Association of Mauritanian Mayors&#13;
(AMM) and donors involved in the same type of activities. The CP will be presided over by the&#13;
Economic Counselor of the Prime Minister; its secretariat will be provided by the project's&#13;
central planning and implementation team (ECPG). The role of the CP will be to: (i) ensure the&#13;
coordination of project activities with those carried out by other programs and departments; (ii)&#13;
to establish broad goals to be achieved during the following year; and (iii) to review project&#13;
achievements on the same annual basis. Assurances have been obtained during negotiations that&#13;
the "Arr&amp;te" establishing composition, mandate and schedule of meetings of the Project Steering&#13;
Committee will be issued to the Bank's satisfaction by the Ministry of Planning (para. 5.01 (d)).&#13;
3.10        Project planning and implementation would be carried out by the ECPG&#13;
established within the Cabinet of the MDRE (Arrete 37 of February 11, 1996). Since the&#13;
decentralization in 1994 of MDRE's technical departments to the regional (wilaya) level, the&#13;
chain of command of technical departments (DRAP, DEAR, DREV) having staff in the regional&#13;
delegations is being channeled through the Cabinet of the MDRE. Nevertheless, since the&#13;
reorganization, the operational capacity of the Cabinet has not increased. Thus, the placement of&#13;
the project's ECPG at the Cabinet level is expected to contribute effectively to the development&#13;
of the rural sector's institutional capacity. The ECPG team (see para 2.15 (d)) is kept minimal in&#13;
order to allocate most of the project's human resources in the field, but it is granted the external&#13;
support required to make it effective. Its staff is recruited on fixed-term contracts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29 -&#13;
B. PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
Project area coverage&#13;
3.11        The rainfed area of Mauritania covers some 2,260 villages and 750,000&#13;
inhabitants (roughly 300 per village on average). There are 1,600 villages with populations in&#13;
the target range of 100-1,000 inhabitants. The objective of the four five-year time-slices of the&#13;
NRM program is to involve 85% of these villages: 250 villages during the first five-year project,&#13;
300 during the second, 350 during the third and 450 during the fourth. The 250 villages to be&#13;
covered under the proposed project would be located in nine regions or wilayas (out of 13).&#13;
Twenty-four districts or moughataas (out of 53) and 62 rural municipalities or communes (out of&#13;
163) would be involved. The project would therefore benefit roughly 75,000 inhabitants of the&#13;
750,000 in the rainfed area (10%). According to information provided by the EU, the&#13;
implementation of the national natural resource management program in the regions of Tagant,&#13;
Brakna and a part of the Trarza would be envisaged as part of its next national investment&#13;
program (PIN).&#13;
Table 6: Project's Zone of Intervention&#13;
City of operation      Wilaya of intervention     Advance Account&#13;
Nouakchott&#13;
Atar           * Tagant                  Atar&#13;
* Inchiri&#13;
* Adrar&#13;
Kiffa          * Assaba                  Kiffa&#13;
* Gorgol North&#13;
* Guidimaka North_&#13;
Ayoun El Atrous    * Hodh El Gharbi          Ayoun El Atrous&#13;
Rosso          * Trarza&#13;
Nema           * Hodh El Chargui         Nema&#13;
3.12        Selection. The choice of rural communities to benefit from the Project is sensitive&#13;
in terms of equity (with the poorest wilayas requiring more interventions) and operationality&#13;
(since interventions are more likely to be successful in areas with higher potential). The choice of&#13;
the 62 communes targeted for an intervention has been made by the Government for negotiations,&#13;
whereas the choice of village clusters within these communes would be made by the project,&#13;
using a comprehensive selection mechanism early in the process of implementation (details are&#13;
in Annex 7 and the Implementation Manual). Although the project would focus on villages&#13;
ranging from 100 to 1,000 inhabitants, smaller settlements might be eligible, provided that they&#13;
associate with other neighboring communities to reach a minimal critical mass of investment.&#13;
Larger communities might also be eligible, provided that they accept relatively lower allocations.&#13;
3.13        Community Natural Resource Planning. The community-based natural resources&#13;
management planning consists of three different stages, each producing its own discrete&#13;
document: (a) the communftv land use master plan (SAC) is established during the initial&#13;
intervention of the project, mostly using participatory rural appraisal techniques. It describes the&#13;
resource base, land use and land tenure features of the different parts of the area managed by a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30 -&#13;
given community; (b) the establishment of the communitv management plan (PAC) implies that&#13;
the community is already aware of the ecological, social and economic principles of sound rural&#13;
development. The document includes all improvements which could be envisaged in the&#13;
medium and long term, in terms of agriculture, social and infrastructure investments; (c) finally,&#13;
the communitv investment plan (PIC) selects from the PAC the activities to be co-financed by the&#13;
project. This document is detailed enough to allow the establishment of contracts needed for its&#13;
implementation, once approved. The content of the PIC would be examined by the ECPG and/or&#13;
the Regional Coordinator to ensure its conformity with the investment selection criteria&#13;
contained in the project implementation manual (economic and financial viability, and&#13;
environmental and socio-economic impact; see also para. 3.29). Depending on local conditions,&#13;
the whole process might take 3 months to one year.&#13;
3.14        Proiect activities, recruitment and coordination.  During project preparation,&#13;
guidelines were established for project implementation (Annex 2). These include (i)&#13;
implementation of community-based NRM plans; (ii) the skills development and public&#13;
awareness component; (iii) the gender issue and how to ensure participation in the process; (iv)&#13;
the test approach to the land tenure issue; (v) implementation of participatory fuelwood&#13;
management; and (vi) rangeland management. A draft of the project implementation manual has&#13;
been transmitted to the Bank for negotiation; it will be finalized and translated into Arabic as a&#13;
condition of effectiveness (para. 5.02 (a)). In addition, the project preparation team has been&#13;
asked to draw up a manual of technologies to be implemented by the project, which is the aim of&#13;
an ongoing consultancy.&#13;
C. MONITORING AND EVALUATION&#13;
3.15        Careful monitoring is needed to help decision-makers obtain quick and regular&#13;
feedback on project implementation, and to make rapid adjustments when required. Because of&#13;
the grassroots nature of the proposed project and its bottom-up approach, details on the exact&#13;
location, type and number of investments at field level cannot be known before community NRM&#13;
plans are agreed upon. The Project is inherently flexible, which makes the role of process&#13;
monitoring far more important, as well as more difficult, than a simple assessment of the&#13;
implementation of prescribed plans. A project monitoring system, including 20 indicators, has&#13;
been developed as part of the project's logical framework (Annex 10), out of which a set of six&#13;
key performance indicators has been established (Annex 11) against which the achievement of&#13;
project's development objectives will be assessed.&#13;
3.16        Collection and processing procedures of indicators selected to monitor the&#13;
project's implementation, outcome and impact are included in the project implementation&#13;
manual; they would be carried out under the coordination of the NRM specialist of the ECPG.&#13;
D. FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT, ACCOUNTING AND AUDITING&#13;
3.17        Project Management and Accounting. The project's computerized management&#13;
and accounting system has been designed. The software has been purchased and will be installed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31 -&#13;
as a condition of effectiveness. Assurances have been obtained that, for all expenditures for&#13;
which withdrawals from the Credit are made on the basis of SOEs, the Borrower shall (i)&#13;
maintain records and accounts reflecting such expenditures; (ii) retain for at least one year after&#13;
credit closing all records evidencing such expenditures; (iii) enable IDA's representatives to&#13;
examine such records; and (iv) ensure that such records and accounts are included in the annual&#13;
audit, and that the report of such audit contains a separate opinion as to whether the SOEs can be&#13;
relied upon to support the related withdrawals (para. 5.01(c)).  In order to facilitate&#13;
implementation of the component, accounting procedures satisfactory to IDA will be included in&#13;
the project's implementation manual.&#13;
3.18        The project would provide funds to establish revolving funds managed at the&#13;
community level in order to build up their financial management capacity (para. 2.14). Such&#13;
provision would be awarded according to detailed guidelines included in the project's&#13;
implementation manual: (i) each community would only be granted a single operation of this&#13;
kind, dealing either with productive or commercial activities; (ii) preconditions to be met would&#13;
cover organization (i.e., a management committee), regulation (clear rules of operation,&#13;
maintenance and accounting), finances (advance payment of beneficiary contributions) and skills&#13;
(training where required); and (iii) EMAT's financial manager would monitor these operations&#13;
specifically.&#13;
3.19        Audits. The financial manager of the ECPG would maintain all project-related&#13;
records and accounts, and would have these audited annually by independent external auditors&#13;
acceptable to IDA. All disbursements against SOEs, the Special Account and the four Advance&#13;
Accounts would be audited separately. The accounts would be maintained in accordance with&#13;
sound and internationally recognized accounting principles and practices satisfactory to IDA.&#13;
The accounting management would provide interim and annual financial statements reflecting&#13;
the financial performance and position of the Project.  An auditor's opinion and reports&#13;
satisfactory to IDA on such statements would be provided within six months of the close of the&#13;
fiscal year. The auditor's report would include a statement on the adequacy of the accounting&#13;
system and internal controls, the reliability of SOEs as a basis for Credit disbursements, and&#13;
compliance with financial covenants.&#13;
3.20        Assurances have been obtained that (i) the records and accounts for the Special&#13;
Account and Advance Accounts would be audited for each fiscal year, in accordance with&#13;
appropriate auditing principles consistently applied by independent auditors acceptable to IDA;&#13;
(ii) the Borrower would furnish to IDA as soon as available, but in any case not later than six&#13;
months after the end of each such year, a certified copy of the report of such audit by said&#13;
auditors, of such scope and in such detail as the Association shall have reasonably requested; and&#13;
(iii) the Borrower would furnish to the Association such other information concerning such&#13;
records, accounts and the audit thereof as the Association shall from time to time reasonably&#13;
request. During negotiations, the Mauritanian delegation has submitted a short list of auditing&#13;
firms to IDA for approval. The appointment of an auditing firm acceptable to IDA to audit&#13;
project accounts under a one-year automatically renewable contract, except in the case of poor&#13;
performance, will be a condition of effectiveness (para. 5.02 (c)).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32 -&#13;
E. REPORTING, SUPERVISION AND MID-TERM REVIEW&#13;
3.21        Project reporting. The project's ECPG would issue semi-annual reports on the&#13;
status of project implementation. Reports, to be issued at the end of the calendar year, would&#13;
consolidate the whole year's results according to the standard format included in the project's&#13;
implementation manual and would provide a detailed technical and financial action plan (PETF)&#13;
for the following year.&#13;
3.22        Proiect Supervision. Supervision missions would be carried out jointly or in&#13;
liaison with other operations for which coordination is considered particularly important, such as&#13;
the PSA and the PDIAIM. Supervision of the Project's financial management, accounting and&#13;
auditing follow-up would be undertaken as a separate exercise. Supervision missions would&#13;
include, in addition to the task managers, experts with the various skills and experience required&#13;
to assess project progress in financial management, popular participation, gender issues, training,&#13;
and environmental impact. In view of the high supervision input that will be required for&#13;
effective implementation of this "process-oriented" project, such input will be clearly indicated&#13;
in the Bank's task contract.&#13;
3.23        Joint Annual Review. The Borrower and the Association shall undertake, during&#13;
the first quarter of each calendar year, a joint review of the Project in which representatives of&#13;
ADCs may be invited to participate. Such review meetings would be particularly important in the&#13;
case of the proposed project, since, as noted elsewhere, village-level investments would be&#13;
chosen during project implementation. This review shall cover, inter alia (a) the progress made&#13;
in the execution of the Project, the review of the progress report of the preceding year; (b) the&#13;
ADCs adherence to the provisions of the MP, and proposed changes to said MP; (c) the&#13;
implementation of Sub-project Agreements; (d) evaluation of (i) the adequacy of the ADC's&#13;
contribution to Sub-projects; and (ii) the performance of the pilot pastoral program in accordance&#13;
to the agreed indicators; (e) a review of the recommendations of the Conseil de Surveillance and&#13;
the Comite de Pilotage ; and (f) the approval of the implementation program of the Project,&#13;
including technical, financial and procurement aspects, for the current year. Not later than one&#13;
month prior to each such review, the progress report for the preceding year shall be submitted for&#13;
review and comments. Following each joint annual review, action plans will be agreed and&#13;
aimed at addressing major problems identified during the review.&#13;
3.24        Mid-Term Review. Assurances have been obtained during negotiations that:&#13;
(a)   the borrower and IDA would conduct, not later than two and a half years after&#13;
the date of Credit effectiveness, a mid-term Project Implementation Review&#13;
which would focus on project development objectives and, in particular: (i)&#13;
implementation progress, on the basis of which preliminary decisions would be&#13;
made on the Program's continuation; (ii) the experience gained under land&#13;
tenure arrangements, with a view to setting up a time-bound Action Plan,&#13;
including steps to replace, modify or implement the existing land tenure&#13;
framework; (iii) following up the conclusions of the assessment of public&#13;
procurement procedures and making adequate recommendations; (iv)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33 -&#13;
evaluation of the training component by an external entity, with a view to a&#13;
possible merger of similar programs at the subregional level; and (v) reviewing&#13;
the Action Plan aimed at strengthening the statistical data of the rural sector&#13;
previously prepared by the ONS (para. 2.17 (g)).&#13;
(b)   not later than four weeks prior to such review, the Borrower shall furnish to&#13;
IDA for its review and comment a report in such detail as IDA shall reasonably&#13;
request, including: (i) an evaluation of progress achieved in project&#13;
implementation by the Borrower in general, and by its central, regional and&#13;
local agencies in particular, in accordance with the provisions of respective&#13;
implementation agreements; (ii) a draft action program to be carried out until&#13;
the completion of the Project, focused on the components stressed above; and&#13;
(c)   promptly after completing the mid-term review, recommendations arising from&#13;
said review would be carried out as agreed by the Borrower and IDA (para.&#13;
5.01(e)).&#13;
F. ENVIRONMENTAL AND SOCIAL IMPACTS&#13;
3.25        The objective of the Project is to halt and reverse the process of natural resource&#13;
degradation in order to secure sustainable agricultural growth, enhance biodiversity and&#13;
ecological stability, and achieve sustainable livestock and wildlife management. Nevertheless,&#13;
any program aiming simultaneously to enhance production and protect natural resources can&#13;
have potential negative impacts. These must be foreseen, and the implementation plan makes&#13;
provisions for their mitigation. Recent experience in neighboring countries has shown that,&#13;
provided they are designed in accordance with sound environmental practices, natural resource&#13;
management projects can very well precede rather than follow the finalization of the NEAP. In&#13;
Mali, the NRM project, which was implemented four years before the NEAP was issued,&#13;
provided a forum for testing some important options (e.g., local management of NRM and&#13;
institutional organization) which were later extended at the national level and subsequently&#13;
included in the NEAP.&#13;
3.26        The Environmental Assessment, carried out as part of project preparation, has&#13;
concluded that, in terms of potential negative environmental impact, actions envisaged under the&#13;
project vary greatly. Land conservation techniques (bunds, planting) have a mostly positive&#13;
impact on erosion, while agricultural tillage and livestock grazing entail greater risks and, if&#13;
mismanaged, the possibility of worsening degradation. Water supply activities (wheels, pumps)&#13;
present the risk of exhaustion of the water table.&#13;
3.27        The mitigation plan recommended by the environmental assessment recommends&#13;
(i) including, in the planning of village investments, an assessment of existing water resources;&#13;
(ii) coordination with Government services (i.e., departement de l'hydraulique), which is a&#13;
prerequisite for the approval of communities' management plans by the CRD; (iii) the inclusion,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34 -&#13;
in the training program, of an awareness of environmental risk; and (iv) implementation of an&#13;
effective monitoring system.&#13;
3.28        The Social Impact Study performed during project preparation identified areas of&#13;
potential conflict, such as village delineation, access to water, access to rangelands, and&#13;
competition over natural resources within the community itself and between the community and&#13;
outsiders. The study also identified areas in which the project is expected to have a positive&#13;
impact, such as community empowerment, protection of the most vulnerable groups (the poor,&#13;
women), development of human resources, and environmental protection. Finally, the study&#13;
recommends (i) a concerted effort to identify vulnerable groups; (ii) an effective institutional set-&#13;
up at the community level; and (iii) a well-designed training program (including conflict&#13;
resolution).&#13;
3.29        In order to ensure that investment packages (PIC) to be implemented at village&#13;
level are both socially and environmentally sound, in addition to providing optimal economic&#13;
benefits, the project's implementation manual states that, in order to be executed, the PIC will&#13;
have to be assessed by the regional coordinators supported by regional technical services&#13;
(DEAR, DRAP). This assessment will ensure that the PIC is sound (a) economically, using&#13;
standard rates of return on major microprojects included in the package; (b) environmentallv, by&#13;
assessing possible risks associated with the implementation of the PIC in terms of exhaustion of&#13;
the water table, erosion and loss of soil fertility, and overexploitation of vegetation (forest and&#13;
pastures); and (c) socially, by assessing the social equity of the proposed investments, and the&#13;
compatibility of the subsidy levels of the package with existing programs. Guidelines for the&#13;
implementation of these assessments are included in the project implementation manual.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
IV.    PROJECT BENEFITS, RISKS AND SUSTAINABILITY&#13;
A. PROJECT BENEFITS&#13;
4.01        The proposed project contains several novel features that, if successful, would&#13;
increase crop and livestock production in a difficult environment, as well as point the way&#13;
towards a solution to some of the more persistent social and enviromnental problems in the rural&#13;
sector. Project benefits can be grouped as follows: those directly increasing production at the&#13;
village level; those that are felt nationwide (i.e. that have an impact beyond the project area);&#13;
and those improving institutional and administrative capabilities.&#13;
4.02        Direct benefits can be categorized in three ways: preservation of the village&#13;
habitat (e.g. through dune fixation; protection of woodlands; well construction and repair);&#13;
improvement of subsistence production (e.g. through construction of small dams and water&#13;
retention dikes; contour bunds; anti-erosion dikes; vegetable gardening);  and increased&#13;
monetarv revenue (e.g. through establishment of orchards; woodlands exploitation for charcoal&#13;
making; promotion of cottage industries).&#13;
4.03        Since the project is the first phase of a long-termn program, and the type and&#13;
frequency of investment actions chosen by the villagers is not yet known, it would not be&#13;
meaningful to calculate an economic rate of return for the project as a whole. Nevertheless, in&#13;
order to get a realistic idea of the projects' economic viability, three model village resource&#13;
management plans have been drawn up in Annex 8: a pastoral model for the drier parts of the&#13;
project area in which livestock raising is virtually the only activity; an aWro-nastoral model for&#13;
intermediate areas where cropping is becoming more important; and an agro-svlvo-xastoral&#13;
model for the wetter parts of the project area, in which, in addition to livestock and cropping,&#13;
wood resources are significant. Taken together, these models conform to, and are representative&#13;
of, the existing production systems in the project area. The investment choices for each model&#13;
have been made, and the choices have been tested as to their conformity with eligibility and&#13;
selection criteria. An internal rate of return has been calculated for most of the investments as&#13;
well as for each model as a whole.&#13;
4.04        The calculations show that the project would yield substantial direct benefits. In&#13;
the pastoral model, execution of the pasture improvement program (improved water supply and&#13;
introduction of rotational grazing) would double livestock production in seven years due to&#13;
increased stocking rates, higher yield and better quality output. In the agro-pastoral model, the&#13;
various investments in water harvesting would place place the production of sorghum, the basic&#13;
staple, on secure footing and increase output by about 45%. In the agro-sylvo-pastoral model,&#13;
crop production and wood production would both be increased without risking resource&#13;
depletion, and economic activities by women would be diversified. The return on individual&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36 -&#13;
investments ranges from 10% to 19%; the return on each model package reaches 12%, 13% and&#13;
14% respectively (see Annex 8)&#13;
4.05        At the national level, the project entails four major benefits:&#13;
(a)  since most project investments are expected to improve water availability and&#13;
make pasture and crop production more drought resistant, the project would help&#13;
to keep people on the land, thus reducing rural outmigration.   This is an&#13;
important national policy goal: Mauritania is the only West African country with&#13;
urbanization rates so high that its rural population has declined in absolute terms&#13;
over the past 15 years (at rates between 0.5% and 1.5% per year) despite an&#13;
overall population increase of 2.5% per year, and Government bears a heavy&#13;
burden of providing adequate infrastructure and urban facilities.&#13;
(b)  disappearance of the forest and bush cover, and a decline in the regenerative&#13;
capacity of pasture land, are two of the most important environmental problems&#13;
the country faces in the rural sector. The pilot programs for improved pasture&#13;
management and woodlands protection included in the project as part of the&#13;
village resource management plans would, if successful, help to solve these&#13;
problems and arrest and reverse environmental degradation over the medium to&#13;
long term.&#13;
(c)  the establishment of village land resource management plans through the direct&#13;
involvement of stakeholders would lead to consensus solutions concerning land&#13;
and water use. Land and water use conflicts over pasture lands, wells and wood&#13;
resources are frequent, especially in times of insufficient rainfall. The project&#13;
would thus directly contribute to a reduction of social conflict.&#13;
(d)  since beneficiaries themselves will decide on, and participate in, the investments&#13;
to be made, maintenance of infrastructure would be better ensured and its useful&#13;
life longer due to a greater sense of ownership.&#13;
4.06        The institutional set-up of the project also contains features that would further the&#13;
country's ongoing process of decentralization of decision-making, to which the Government is&#13;
committed. In order to firmly anchor decision-making powers at the beneficiary level, the&#13;
project would enter into contracts with Community Associations for the implementation of&#13;
adopted and approved plans. Moreover, the plans would only have to be approved by the local&#13;
and regional authorities: by the Municipal Council of the municipality to which the village&#13;
belongs, and subsequently by the Regional Development Committee under the Regional&#13;
Governor. Thus, the Central Govermnent authorities would not intervene in the process. This&#13;
"bottom up" approach would be new to the country and, if successful, would open the way to&#13;
increased power sharing with local authorities and villagers. Finally, the project would not have&#13;
a free-standing implementation capability. It would instead rely on private contractors and&#13;
suppliers in addition to village labor for the execution of investments, on existing agricultural&#13;
services for preparation of village resource management plans, and on the regional technical&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-37 -&#13;
services of the Ministry of Rural Development for supervision of execution of works. The&#13;
technical services would be strengthened where necessary for this task. Replicability would thus&#13;
be ensured.&#13;
B. PROJECT RISKS&#13;
4.07          Project risks are largely non-quantifiable. They have been identified in the project&#13;
logical framework (Annex 10) and can be grouped together with their likely impact and associated&#13;
mitigating measures, as shown below in Table 7.&#13;
Table 7: Non-quantifiable Project Risks&#13;
Risk Level     Risk Factor          Likely Impact            Mitigation        Probability&#13;
Ability of the     Village investments not    Project's institutional    Low&#13;
administration to    implemented, public    setup is expected to&#13;
implement the      services remain ineffective  mobilize existing&#13;
From        project            and skills remain poor.    institutional resources&#13;
project                                                 and to boost its&#13;
input                                                   effectiveness.&#13;
to project   Existence/appea-  Unexpected social and    Existing legal         Medium&#13;
output      rance of conflicts    land tenure conflicts  framework seems to be&#13;
within and between   prevent rural communities  adequate, and&#13;
communities        from getting effectively    organization/conflict&#13;
organized.              resolution skills would&#13;
be developed.&#13;
Relevant           Although project is being   In addition to existing    Low&#13;
technologies to be    implemented, technologies  techniques, available in&#13;
extended not       relevant to communities'   Mauritania and abroad,&#13;
From        available          requirements are missing.   applied research would&#13;
Project                                                 be carried out under the&#13;
output                                                  project.&#13;
to project   Weak political will   Current decentralization    Recent evolution  Low&#13;
outcome     from Government to  policy would be called into  towards decentralization&#13;
provide local      question, and authoritarian  and democracy seems&#13;
communities with    approach would be       irreversible and would&#13;
decision power     implemented.             be reinforced by all&#13;
donors.&#13;
Extended period of   Although rural         Drought preparedness is  unpredic-&#13;
From        poor natural       communities enjoy        part of community NRM   table&#13;
project     conditions (drought)  conditions of genuine  planning, and easier to&#13;
outcome                        empowerment, persistent   implement in the project&#13;
to project                     drought prevents        framework.&#13;
impact                         production increase.&#13;
Persistence of     Interest groups capture  Education, adequate   Medium&#13;
From       traditional forms of   project's benefits, which   legal framework, women&#13;
project    social organization    are not distributed among   participation,&#13;
Impact to   preventing equitable  the poorest segment of the  community organization&#13;
CAS         distribution of    population.              income increase would&#13;
objectives   project's benefits                         all tend to reduce this&#13;
I risk.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38 -&#13;
C. FISCAL IMPACT OF THE PROJECT&#13;
4.08        The fiscal burden of the project on the Borrower is designed to be minimal, given&#13;
the difficult financial situation of the country and the need to reduce the budget deficit. The&#13;
Government's contribution is limited to US$0.4 million over five years, representing the salaries&#13;
(net of taxes) of existing government employees working in MDRE's field services who would&#13;
be seconded to the project. Other recurrent costs, as well as the wages of project personnel,&#13;
would be met by the donor. After credit closing/project completion, costs related to the field&#13;
level investments would be supported by the beneficiaries. Government's incremental&#13;
contribution would be nil. The continuation of extension support would be needed, but this is&#13;
presently already included under the Agricultural Services Project. The long-term incremental&#13;
cost of extension support would be limited to the salaries and field allowances of AVBs and their&#13;
supervision, approximately US$0.4 million per annum.&#13;
D. PROJECT SUSTAINABILITY&#13;
4.09        The project has been designed so as to optimize its chances of long-term&#13;
sustainability. At the village level, investments would be implemented only after beneficiaries&#13;
are effectively organized, rules of access to resources have been accepted, operation and&#13;
maintenance funds are being raised, and a system for their proper management exists. Once&#13;
villages are organized, positive results are observed and additional production is generated,&#13;
communities will be able to pursue on their own the process initiated with the project's help. At&#13;
the municipal level, village resource management plans would be consolidated into "action plans&#13;
for municipal development", preparation of which was requested by the recent Congress of&#13;
Mauritanian Mayors. At the regional and central levels, the project would be programmed and&#13;
supervised by the permanent technical services of the Ministry of Rural Development and&#13;
Environment. At the international level. Mauritania would be part of the Sahelian/West African&#13;
natural resource network currently being developed to foster an ongoing exchange of experience&#13;
between neighboring countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39 -&#13;
V. AGREEMENTS REACHED AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
5.01.       The following assurances have been obtained during negotiations:&#13;
(a)   during the scheduled Mid-Term review, the effectiveness of the national&#13;
bidding procedures would be assessed (para. 2.29);&#13;
(b)   procurement of the goods, works and consultant services required for the&#13;
project, and to be financed out of Credit proceeds, will take place in accordance&#13;
with procedures satisfactory to IDA (para. 2.31);&#13;
(c)   expenditures to be made on the basis of SOEs will be carried out according to&#13;
the Association's procedures (para. 3.17);&#13;
(d)   the project's Steering Committee has been established with terms of reference&#13;
and composition acceptable to IDA (para. 3.09) and semi-annual reports on the&#13;
status of project's implementation are being issued by project management to&#13;
the Bank's satisfaction (paras. 3.21);&#13;
(e)   the Borrower and the Association will conduct a mid-term review aimed at&#13;
assessing project's past performances and current status, while designing&#13;
actions to be taken to ensure the achievement of its development objectives&#13;
(para. 3.24);&#13;
5.02        Actions to be carried out as conditions of effectiveness:&#13;
(a)   the project implementation manual is acceptable to IDA and available in&#13;
French and Arabic (para. 3.14);&#13;
(b)   the appointment of project accountants is satisfactory to IDA and the project's&#13;
computerized accounting system is operational (para 3.17);&#13;
(c)   appointment of auditing firm of project accounts, satisfactory to IDA (para.&#13;
3.20);&#13;
5.04        Recommendation:&#13;
With the above assurances and conditions, the project would be acceptable for&#13;
IDA Credit of US$18 million, on standard IDA terms with 40 years' maturity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40 -                                 ANNEX 1&#13;
Page 1 of 2&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
LIST OF PROJECTS RELATED TO&#13;
NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT. AND LESSONS LEARNED&#13;
Projects Funded by IDA:&#13;
* Project Technical Assistance to Rural Sector: (Cr-14140-MAU). This (now completed)&#13;
IDA/UNSO project to strengthen MDRE's Environmental Protection Department has&#13;
shown that institutional development efforts whose sole aim is to strengthen public services&#13;
cannot make an effective contribution to environmental protection;&#13;
* Livestock II Proiect (Cr-16580-MAU), effective June 1987; closed June 1995, co-financed&#13;
with OPEC, AfDB and Norwegian financing, covered the entire rainfed zone. Despite some&#13;
serious difficulties, it yielded valuable insights into the promotion of socio-professional and&#13;
sylvopastoral resource management organizations that will prove useful under the PGRNP.&#13;
Livestock II demonstrated that: (i) sub-sectoral projects cannot give producers' groups the&#13;
dynamism they need; (ii) the creation of associations is not enough to ensure efficient&#13;
resource management; and (iii) the success of any rural development program will depend&#13;
on the assumption, by communities, of responsibility for its implementation;&#13;
* Aericultural Sector Adjustment and Investment Project (CR. 2093-MAU) has dealt rather&#13;
successfully with policy adjustments (land reform in the Senegal River Valley) and&#13;
investments (irrigated perimeters in the Valley);&#13;
* Technical Assistance, Energv and Public Sector SupPort Proiect (Cr. 2167-MAU) included&#13;
a household energy strategy component aimed at reducing charcoal consumption,&#13;
promoting substitute fuels, and developing the use of improved stoves. It did not address&#13;
the supply side (forest management, fuelwood marketing) to be covered by the proposed&#13;
project;&#13;
* Agriculture Service Proiect, (Cr-2575-MAU), effective since 1994, aimed at providing the&#13;
whole rural sector with extension services, including agriculturists and herders. The&#13;
proposed project would be set up, together the PSA, within one single comprehensive&#13;
Agricultural Sector development program;&#13;
* Urban Infrastructure and Pilot Decentralization Project (Cr.2835-MAU), although it deals&#13;
with a different sector, is likely to play an important role in future activities dealing with&#13;
communal organization;&#13;
* Integrated Development Program of Irrigated Agriculture (PDIAIAO, under preparation,&#13;
would aim at (i) creating an enabling institutional environment in the sub-sector; (ii)&#13;
restructuring irrigation management; (iii) upgrading farmers' skills and managerial abilities;&#13;
(iv) consolidating existing irrigation schemes; (v) improving marketing and (vi) mitigating&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-                                  ANNEX 1&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
the ecological impacts of irrigation. It would be implemented in close coordination with the&#13;
proposed project;&#13;
2.    Projects Funded by Other Donors&#13;
* Tagant and Lac d'Aleg Proiects. currently financed by the European Community, have&#13;
objectives and strategies similar to those of the proposed project, and are being implemented&#13;
under a single management staff, over three Regions where the proposed project would not&#13;
intervene;&#13;
* Gestion des RessourcesNaturelles de I'Est Mauritanian GIRNEM (1991-1997). This German-&#13;
financed project has accumulated experience that has proved useful in the preparation of the&#13;
institutional component of the proposed project;&#13;
* Pro et de Lutte contre l'Ensablement et Mise en Valeur A rosvlvo astorale (PLEMVASP)&#13;
(1993-1995). Co-financed by UNSO and UNDP. Implemented by FAO, aimed at dune&#13;
stabilization, vegetation rehabilitation, control of desertification;&#13;
- Achram-DioukProiect (1992-1995). This project, financed by Germany, carried out valuable&#13;
experiments in exploiting flood recession techniques and in organizing communities for&#13;
agrosylvopastoral land management;&#13;
- Proiet Rcpgional d'Apvui au Divelovpement Rural ( PRADER) (German financing). This area&#13;
development project in the wilaya of Hodh el Gharbi, which is part of the implementation&#13;
zone of the proposed project will, therefore, have a close relationshipwith it;&#13;
* Projet opderations villageoises POV (1992-1994), financed by the EU, involves small village&#13;
operations in Gorgol, including water management works (mainly dams);&#13;
* In addition, the following projects have dealt, or still deal, with some aspects of natural&#13;
resource management:&#13;
* Barriere Verte du Trarza (BVT), French financing; 1994-1996;&#13;
* Projet de Reboisement d'Agglomerations Situees sur la Route de l'Espoir (PRASRE),&#13;
financed by AfDB; 1994, ongoing;&#13;
* Approvisionnementen EauAftout (AEA), 1988-1995, financed by IDB;&#13;
* Hydraulique Villageoise et Pastorale du Sud-Est (HVPSE), 1988-1996, AfDB financing;&#13;
* Hydraulique et Energie (HE), 1993-1994, French financing;&#13;
* Ceinture Verte de Nouakchott (CVN), 1993-1995, French financing;&#13;
* Protection de l'Aeroport de Nema (PAN), 1994-1995, French financing;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42-                               ANNEX2&#13;
Page 1 of 7&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
IMPLEMENTATION OF PROJECT'S ACTIVITIES&#13;
Community-based NRM Planning&#13;
I     In accordance with the community-based NRM approach, the project's technical support&#13;
teams (EMATs) and extension agents (AVBs)would operate as follows:&#13;
(a)   under the leadership of the EMAT's communications/organization specialist, and&#13;
using participatory rural appraisal (PRA) techniques in which project staff would&#13;
have been previously trained, the first phase of intervention aims at building trust,&#13;
establishing Community development associations (ADC) and community technical&#13;
committees (GTC), This specialist would be responsible for the establishment of the&#13;
community land use master plan (SAC) defining the current land use and tenure&#13;
status. No further activity would be started until this step is completed. The key&#13;
element here is time.&#13;
(b)   during the second phase, the common resource manag'ement specialist from the&#13;
EMAT would extend the NRM planning methodology to the villagers, with a view to&#13;
setting up the community management plan (PAC), and to select, among the actions&#13;
included in the PAC, those which would be includes into the community investment&#13;
plan (PIC) to be co-financed by the project after being reviewed at communal and&#13;
district level, and approved by the Regional Governor. The focus of the community&#13;
investment plan could vary, depending on the situation, from a single limited action&#13;
to comprehensive programs involving entire production systems and populations.&#13;
The key element here is flexibility.&#13;
(c)   the financial and administrative specialist from the EMAT would subsequently help&#13;
the villagers to carry out the community investment plan (PIC) once it has been&#13;
approved, providing support for access to and management of funds and procurement&#13;
of inputs and services. Finally, this specialist would monitor, on behalf of the Project,&#13;
the effective delivery of goods and works (including labor provided by villagers)&#13;
contracted for as part of the implementation of community investment plans. Past&#13;
experience gained by similar projects inside and outside Mauritania, would be taken&#13;
into account.&#13;
2     The process described above is complex and time-consuming. Nevertheless, past experience&#13;
has shown that community NRM can achieve its objectives provided that (i) the community NRM&#13;
planning process is demand-driven and takes into account the community's essential requirements;&#13;
(ii) initial efforts are made to address the villagers' land tenure security; (iii) a comprehensive and&#13;
culturally aware skills development program is carried out; (iv) the role of women is acknowledged&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 2 of 7&#13;
and encouraged; and (v) arrangements for the operation and maintenance of investments are clearly&#13;
stated in the implementation manual and agreed upon by the community.&#13;
Skills Development and Public Awareness&#13;
3     The implementation of the proposed project requires new technical knowledge and skills&#13;
very different from those presently available. Thus, the success of such a project depends on&#13;
intensive human resource development. An interim training program will be in place at the time&#13;
of project start-up. The strategy for this component will aim at adapting the training program to&#13;
the Project's changing needs. The skills gap analysis and module design would be subcontracted&#13;
to private training firms. The project would establish a database of training resources available&#13;
in Mauritania and neighboring countries (facilitators, resource persons, training facilities), which&#13;
could be called upon for implementation of the modules.&#13;
4     Four different steps will be carried out by different entities working in close coordination:&#13;
(a)   the first step consists of identifying target groups to be involved in the training&#13;
program. This step will be handled by the ECPG's staff, with an eye to problems&#13;
identified in the course of project implementation. Target groups include, in addition&#13;
to project staff, the different community and village technical groups, technical and&#13;
administrative staff at the local, regional and national government levels, and the&#13;
public at large.&#13;
(b)   each group identified as requiring training is subjected to a "skills gap analysis"&#13;
which pinpoints the missing skills -- e.g., pure technical knowledge, operational&#13;
procedures, communications ability, etc. -- to be developed under the program. A&#13;
particular procedure would be followed to develop targeted public awareness&#13;
campaigns;&#13;
(c)   "modules" or training processes of various durations are then designed for each&#13;
specific target group and set of skills to be developed. These modules are based on&#13;
participatory adult training techniques, including case studies, small group exercises,&#13;
simulations and, in the case of village communities, techniques of PRA.&#13;
(d)   once tested and adjusted, the training "modules' are delivered to their intended target&#13;
groups by specialized facilitators assisted by qualified resource persons. In addition&#13;
to the training of trainers, to be provided fortnightly to extension agents and monthly&#13;
to TSTs, these modules include, for instance, full-day village sensitization sessions,&#13;
team-building workshops, short information seminars, and national public awareness&#13;
campaigns.&#13;
5     In order to have some of the target groups ready to operate at effectiveness, an interim&#13;
training and workshops program has already started This interim program would be a precursor of&#13;
the several project-launch workshops to be held at the time of effectiveness, the cost of which would&#13;
be financed under the PPF. The experience acquired under similar components of the Burkina Faso&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 3 of 7&#13;
PNGT and Mali PGRN projects would be fully exploited through the use of tested training packages&#13;
and trainers with good performance records.&#13;
Gender and Participation&#13;
6     Due to the migration of men to cities and other countries, women are increasingly&#13;
responsible for natural resource management. They supply household water and firewood and&#13;
participate actively in agricultural work, especially in the rainfed areas. Any NRM program must&#13;
therefore take women into account to the same degree as men. Although women have a lesser role&#13;
of decision-makers in many traditional communities, a dynamic women's movement is afoot in&#13;
Mauritania, and many women's associations exist for agricultural work and environmental&#13;
protection. Female extension agents are still rare, and the project will pay particular attention to&#13;
extension programs geared to women, to improving female producers' access to extension services,&#13;
and to developing tools and technologies adapted to their needs and abilities.&#13;
7     The proposed project would develop and implement a strategy that would enhance the role of&#13;
women in NRM. According to this strategy, the gender issue would not be tackled through separate&#13;
components targeting women (although this might be relevant in some circumstances). Instead, the&#13;
issue would be dealt with by the entire project staff in its day-to-day operations. Guidelines for&#13;
project staff would be established as part of the skills development program, and decisions on the&#13;
following topics would be made under community NRM plans only after being discussed and&#13;
accepted by the village women's technical committees: (i) location and operation of water points; (ii)&#13;
land-use planning (agro-forestry); (iii) movement and management of livestock; and (iv) choice,&#13;
location and operation of collective food-processing equipment (mills, oil extraction plants).&#13;
8     In addition, the Project would include measures to: (i) encourage the establishment of village&#13;
women's sub-sectoral groups; (ii) have these groups consulted on all important decisions concerning&#13;
village NRM activities; (iii) promote the participation of women in training sessions and meetings&#13;
organized under the proposed project; (iv) recruit women as technical extension staff wherever&#13;
possible, especially at village level. Issues of a broader nature, such as land tenure and gender, would&#13;
be first addressed in the Valley. The project's achievements in dealing with the gender issue would&#13;
be monitored under the proposed monitoring and evaluation system, using appropriate indicators.&#13;
Land Tenure under the Project&#13;
9     The project would not establish a land cadaster whether of privately or collectively owned&#13;
lands, since such an endeavor is not considered necessary at the present stage, in the rainfed zone.&#13;
Instead, the following approach would be applied&#13;
(a)   during project preparation, a legal consultancy has been carried out, which has&#13;
establish that the current regulatory framework of laws and regulations would allow&#13;
for the allocation of land, water and vegetation (rangeland, fuelwood) to well-&#13;
identified users' groups under certain conditions and the Government has&#13;
acknowledged the existence of this legislation, and committed itself to its&#13;
implementation under the project;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
45 -ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 4 of 7&#13;
(b)   during project implementation, according to the project's approach of "land tenure&#13;
tests", villagers willing to improve land tenure security in their area would be&#13;
assisted by knowledgeable, locally-recruited resource persons who would help them&#13;
review current local land tenure practices, paying special attention to gender. The&#13;
review would produce practical recommendations, addressed to technical and&#13;
administrative authorities, for improving the community's security of access to&#13;
natural resources. In areas of overlapping grazing rights between sedentary villagers&#13;
and seasonal transhumant herders, special attention would be paid to the&#13;
acknowledgment by villagers of all well-established seasonal grazing rights;&#13;
(c)   at mid-term review, subject to prior consultation with technical and administrative&#13;
authorities at regional and district levels, the recommendations made during the&#13;
previous phase would be reviewed and then tested for a fixed period of time; and&#13;
(d)   prior to project completion, and after close monitoring of the land tenure tests by the&#13;
ECPG and local authorities, the results of those tests would be fully assessed and a&#13;
decision would then be made either to discontinue the operation, to adjust it, or to&#13;
formalize it. In the latter case, the test could be used for the further amendment of&#13;
land tenure regulations. This is when the potential usefulness of a formal delimitation&#13;
(cadastral survey) of common and private land would be assessed, and when such a&#13;
component would possibly be included in a follow-up project.&#13;
Fuelwood Management under the Project&#13;
10    The household energy strategy (SED) designed by ESMAP in 1990, focused mainly on&#13;
demand issues (substitution, improved stoves and pricing policies) with very little emphasis on the&#13;
supply side, such as the management of the sustainable fuelwood production and distribution (para&#13;
1 .10). As a result of project preparation, the Mauritanian Government requested and was granted the&#13;
resources to participate in the Review of Policies of the Traditional Energy Sector (RPTES) carried&#13;
out under trust fund financing to establish a comprehensive sector strategy dealing with the "supply"&#13;
as well as with the "demand" side of renewable energy. A comprehensive household energy strategy&#13;
(SED) will be designed according to the recommendations of the NEAP and in agreement with the&#13;
Government. In the meanwhile, pilot participative fuelwood management operations would be&#13;
carried out as part of the village investments component of the project. The labor costs in the&#13;
following table would be borne by the beneficiaries.&#13;
Table 1: Objectives and costs of the household energy component&#13;
Activity      Nb. Sites    Area Ha.     Cost USS      labor USS    Total USS&#13;
Manasement&#13;
Gazetted forests      2          16,000      480,000        205,714       685,714&#13;
Sylvo-pastoral        4           3,200       96,000         41,143       137,143&#13;
Existing plantations  3            200         -&#13;
New Plantations&#13;
Sanddunecontrol      12            600       102,857        411,429       514,286&#13;
Agro-forestry         6            300        47,143         167,143      214,286&#13;
Total                                        726,000         825,429     1,551,429&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46 -                               ANNEX2&#13;
Page 5 of 7&#13;
11    The project's strategy would be to deal with four dimensions of the household energy sector:&#13;
(i) it would establish a close linkage between supplv and demand for household energy through&#13;
coordination with the Public Sector, Technical Assistance and Energy Project (Cr. 2167-MAU) and&#13;
the permanent structure to be established within the Ministry of Energy, which would deal with the&#13;
differential taxation of fuelwood and charcoal marketed in major cities; (ii) it would pursue&#13;
proactive coordination with related proiects and programs, and especially with the PDIAIM project&#13;
in the Valley, under which participatory management of pilot gazetted and private forests would be&#13;
implemented according to the ESMAP-RPTES approach; (iii) it would contain an enabling policy&#13;
framework including legal right of access, taxation and tax collection; and (iv) it would participate in&#13;
the implementation of the whole stratev (enforcement of regulation, monitoring, organization and&#13;
skills development of stakeholders) under a discrete institutional framework.&#13;
Rangeland Management under the Project&#13;
12    Past attempts to check the continuous degradation of collectively managed rangeland in&#13;
Mauritania have been mostly unsuccessful. Under the completed Livestock II project, the following&#13;
reasons for this failure were cited: (i) the pastoral communities has been insufficiently involved in&#13;
decision-making; (ii) the technical principles applied had often been ineffective, with an&#13;
overemphasis on "stocking rates" that had little relevance under conditions of unpredictable rainfall&#13;
and mobile production systems; (iii) an "agronomic" approach stressing the planting of exotic&#13;
species rather than improvement of the ecological succession of native species; and (iv) certain&#13;
features of plant vs animals'interraction, while well acknowledged by pastoral communities, were&#13;
ignored. Given the encouraging results of the holistic resource management approach in Chad, this&#13;
approach would be implemented in two pilot perimeters (Hodh El Gharbi and Hodh El Chargui)&#13;
under the West African Pastoral Pilot Program involving five other Sahelian countries with IDA&#13;
coordination. The amount of US$500,000 has been allocated in the project budget to implement this&#13;
pilot operation.&#13;
13    The holistic resource management model, used in rangeland management as well as in the&#13;
establishment of the community management plan, is a thought process by means of which, after&#13;
identifying the resources to be involved in management (family, village, tribe), the following steps&#13;
are taken: (i) agreeing upon goals acceptable to the whole community; (ii) assessing the health of the&#13;
environment in systemic terms of water, mineral and energy cycle, and succession; (iii) selecting the&#13;
tools and technologies most likely to achieve these goals; and (iv) carrying out the permanent&#13;
monitoring of results and the iterative adjustment of the management plan. Features of special&#13;
interest in the model are its "testing guidelines" which any investment must pass in order to be&#13;
implemented. In order to be acceptable, the proposed action must: (i) reinforce the ecological&#13;
succession; (ii) address the weakest link; (iii) deal with the causes of ecological degradation, rather&#13;
than with its symptoms; (iv) ensure the highest result for a given cost; (v) be sustainable (renewable&#13;
energy and self-generated capital); and (vi) be acceptable to the society and the culture. Project staff&#13;
has already begun to be trained in HRM.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -                               ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 6 of 7&#13;
Staff Recruitment&#13;
14    Staff recruitment would be phased according to a staffing defined by the project's Costab.&#13;
The Project Director, the financial management staff, the ECPG technical manager, six members of&#13;
the technical support teams, and 19 field extension agents have already been recruited under the&#13;
project's PPF. None of these being civil servants Additional financial management staff would be&#13;
recruited for effectiveness while Project regional coordinators, remaining EMAT staff and additional&#13;
field extension agents would start work immediately after credit effectiveness.  The further&#13;
recruitment of additional extension agents would follow the phasing of village incorporation by the&#13;
Agricultural Services project.&#13;
15    Recruitment for positions under the credit would be publicized and open to private, NGO&#13;
and government staff willing to separate from administrative service. Terms of reference have been&#13;
included in the Project Implementation Manual to be ready by negotiation. Minimal requirements&#13;
and selection criteria would be agreed upon by IDA and the Administrative and Financial&#13;
Department (DAF) of the MDRE. For purposes of implementing the Project (particularly regarding&#13;
the delkgations' civil servants involved in project implementation), the Borrower would employ and&#13;
maintain staff with qualifications, experience, terms and conditions of employment satisfactory to&#13;
IDA. In order to ensure effective staffing at the highest level, selection mechanisms, such as&#13;
"assessment centers" would be put in place with the participation of IDA staff. Remuneration of&#13;
contractual staff would be commensurate with the temporary scope of the contract, but should not&#13;
result in a disincentive to Government officers with similar qualifications and responsibilities.&#13;
Coordination with Other Projects and Programs&#13;
16    The proposed project would be closely coordinated with other similar or complementary&#13;
projects and programs. This coordination would not be limited to projects indicated below, but&#13;
would instead aim to establish effective linkages with all projects and NGOs operating within the&#13;
project area. Such coordination would strive to: (i) take advantage of the experience gained by IDA&#13;
and other donors' projects; (ii) build on the facilities and services (staff, equipment) available at field&#13;
level; and (iii) ensure that the village communities covered by the proposed project would have&#13;
access to services and inputs provided by other national programs, when available.&#13;
(a)   Aklg Lake and Tazant EU Project: This project is of particular importance to the&#13;
RNRMP since the European Union has agreed to carry out parallel financing in the&#13;
wilayas of Tagant, Brakna and part of the Trarza, under the single national level&#13;
management of the proposed IDA project, and using a similar methodology.&#13;
(b)   Apricultural Services Proiect. The objectives of both projects are complementary.&#13;
While the Agricultural Services Project extends productive technologies to individual&#13;
herders and farmers, NRM planning deals with the allocation of individual plots as&#13;
well as with the management of common land.  Both projects intervene&#13;
simultaneously at field level as the two elements of a single rural support program:&#13;
(i) RNRM's field staff would be housed in the Rural organization bureau (BOP) of&#13;
the Delegation, which is the operational base of the PSA; (ii) field activities of both&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 7 of 7&#13;
projects would be planned at regional (Delegation) level, involving similar&#13;
personnel, (iii) their training programs, including monthly and fortnight training&#13;
sessions, would be established jointly and (iv) both projects would be implemented&#13;
in the field by the same single extension agent (AVB).&#13;
(c)   Household Energy Component (Cr. 2167-MAU) This project has made considerable&#13;
progress in implementing the demand, or urban, aspects of the strategy. Close&#13;
linkages will be established when designing the comprehensive domestic energy&#13;
strategy (SED) for Mauritania.&#13;
(d)    Urban Infrastructure and Pilot Decentralization Proiect: Although this project deals&#13;
with medium and large municipalities, and not with rural ones, it might lend support&#13;
in designing the process by which village land-use master plans are consolidated&#13;
within larger communal development plans (plans communaux indicatifs), a task for&#13;
which MDRE staff is not well prepared.&#13;
(e)   Inteeorated Development Program for Irrigated Agriculture, to be implemented in the&#13;
Senegal river valley, is under preparation. It will be closely coordinated with the&#13;
proposed project. Several important issues are common to both projects (herd&#13;
movements, fuelwood energy, intensive livestock production) and will be addressed&#13;
in a coordinated manner.&#13;
(f)    GIRNEM and PRADER both financed by Germany, have objectives and strategies&#13;
similar in many ways to those of the proposed project. The close relationships&#13;
established at the outset of project preparation will be pursued to the benefit of both.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Manaeement Project&#13;
CATALOGUE OF PLANNED INVESTMENTS&#13;
ANTICIPATED COST OF ACTIVITIES&#13;
Activities                               UM'OOO          US$&#13;
SURFACE WATER CONSERVATION (Cost /ha)&#13;
Dam'&#13;
Diversion-type, with concrete sluice and a spillway, over 4 meters high,&#13;
providing for 80 hectares of irrigated crops                            300          2,140&#13;
Weir&#13;
earthen contour weir, between 2 and 4 meters high, no sluice, with or&#13;
without spillway, with upstream stone reinforcement                      70           500&#13;
Stone embankments&#13;
stone contour embankment, at least 2 meters high,                        35           250&#13;
Earthen embankments&#13;
contour embankment at least 1 meter high, earthen but with stone-filled&#13;
gabions at weak points                                                   14            100&#13;
HYDRAULIC WORKS (Unit cost)&#13;
New well2&#13;
well, average depth 4045 meters, including supervision of work, casing,&#13;
superstructure, cistern, pulley-driven lifts, materials removal costs  3,500       25,000&#13;
New well3&#13;
well, average depth 20 meters, including casing and superstructure, no&#13;
cistern or lifting device, built with local drillers and masons. UM70,000 per&#13;
linear meter                                                           1,400        10,000&#13;
Well retrofitting4&#13;
Deepening, plus repairs and new superstructure for existing wells      1,500        10,700&#13;
1   Source: such a dam would cost between UM100,000/ha (highly labor-intensive option) to UM525,000/ha&#13;
(turn-key contract). Given the size of the investment (even with the labor-intensive approach), and the low&#13;
level of revenues to be expected from agriculture above the dam (e.g., sorghum with a gross production value&#13;
of UM 18,000 per ha. per year), this type of dam is not considered suitable for the project.&#13;
2   Source: contract awarded in August 1995 for Livestock II Project. Average cost for a 22-well program.&#13;
3   Source: Ashramn-Diouck Project, updated estimate as of July 1996.&#13;
4   Source: contract awarded in June 1995. Average cost for 64-well program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-0 -                                    ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
Production well drillingl&#13;
production drilling (including three exploratory drillings), and piping,&#13;
including material moving costs                                     2,300        16.430&#13;
Well-mounted liftine device: wind-Dowered-&#13;
including installation and cistern for existing drill-holes         1,200         8,570&#13;
VEGETATION UPGRADING: (Cost/ha)&#13;
Pasture upDradin2&#13;
rangeland survey, dune stabilization, mowing, hillside retention dams,&#13;
support staff equipment (excluding irrigation), assuming rangeland of  0.4         2.90&#13;
10,000 ha.&#13;
Forestrv-Pasture upgrading&#13;
in existing forests, classified or not; signage, warden services, firebreak  6   42.90&#13;
maintenance&#13;
Anti-sandine measures&#13;
establishing a double hedgerow around the perimeter, interior windbreaks  120      860&#13;
every 30 meters, with 3-meter spacing (planted with forage species)&#13;
Forestry-pasture Dlantines&#13;
double perimeter hedge, denser internal windbreaks (spacing 2.5 meters)&#13;
Eucalvyptus plantings                                                 70           500&#13;
400 trees/ha, surrounded by a double thorn hedge&#13;
Perimeter market-gardens'                                             100          710&#13;
metal fencing (400 meters @ UM350/linear meter), seed, watering&#13;
equipment (@ UM900), hoes (@ UM950), shovels (@ UM800) and&#13;
wheelbarrows (@ UM5,800); build reservoir (UM20,000) over existing&#13;
well&#13;
200         1,430&#13;
EOUIPMENT AND CONSTRUCTION (Unit cost)&#13;
Cereals Storage&#13;
building only: UM 15,000/square meter&#13;
Manure pit                                                           600         4,290&#13;
pit only: UM2,700/square meter.&#13;
Source: Japanese assistance contract. Average cost of program of 220 production drillings, underway as of&#13;
July 1996&#13;
6   Source: estimate from local windmill builder, June 1996. Includes work supervision&#13;
The major expense here is the metal fencing, which amounts to 140,000 UM per ha (installation not included).&#13;
A live hedge would cost only 6,300 UM per ha (installation included), but offers less protection against animal&#13;
incursions and requires constant upkeep&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -                                      ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
Rural Market Construction/Rehabilitation                               27           200&#13;
facilities and installations for an area of 1,200 m2&#13;
Eguivment rental costs                                                900         6,430&#13;
trucks (for building tracks), per truck, per day;&#13;
small tools (carts, wheelbarrows, shovels, hoes, for building&#13;
weirs/embankments) per lot                                             20           140&#13;
60          430&#13;
Artisan epuiDment&#13;
sewing machines, looms, per lot&#13;
MINI-FUNDS (Unit cost)                                                 25           180&#13;
Working capital&#13;
purchase of veterinary medications, by lot&#13;
marketing fund&#13;
100          715&#13;
500         3,570&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT COST SUMMARY&#13;
MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Components Project Cost Sunmary&#13;
%     % Total&#13;
(UM Million)                     (US$ '000)            Foreign   Base&#13;
Local    Foreign    Total      Local     Foreign      Total   Exchange  Costs&#13;
1. Investissements Villageois                   1 079,2    1 326,3    2 405,5  7 599,9    9 340,3    16 940,3      55      73&#13;
2. Encadrement Technique (cout hors taxe)        400,1     184,5      584,6    2817,5      1 299,5    4117,0       32       18&#13;
3. Appui et Formation                            141,8      91,5      233,3      998,7      644,3     1 643,0      39        7&#13;
4. Programme Pilote Pastoral                      42,9      29,6      72,5       302,4      208,1      510,5       41        2                1&#13;
Total BASELINE COSTS                              1 664,0    1 631,9    3295,9    11 718,5    11 492,3    23210,8     50     100&#13;
Physical Contingencies&#13;
Price Contingencies                              216,0    1172,4     388,3     1 520,9     1 213,9    2 734,7      44       12&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                               1 880,0    1 804,3   3684,3    13239,4    12706,2    25 945,6       49     112&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Project Components by Year - Totals Including Contingencies&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
Totals Including Contingencies&#13;
1997      1998       1999      2000       2001      2002     Total&#13;
1. Investissements Villageois                     886,9    1 820,7    2 776,5    5 737,3    7 836,4      -    19 057,8&#13;
2. Encadrement Technique (cout hors taxe)        1 116,4     675,7     691,4      740,1      755,3   589,9     4568,7&#13;
3. Appui et Formation                             674,7      618,0      179,3     153,6      129,2    10,2      1 765,0&#13;
4. Programme Pilote Pastoral                      184,7      165,2       66,2      52,1       51,5    34,3       554,0&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                                2 862,7    3 279,6    3 713,4    6 683,2    8 772,4   634,4    25 945,6&#13;
Ul&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Expenditure Accounts by Components - Totals Including Contingencies&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
Encadrement&#13;
Technique            Programme&#13;
Investissements  (cout hors   Appui et    Pilote&#13;
Villageois      taxe)    Formation  Pastoral      Total&#13;
I. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Genie civil                          19 057,8        11,5         -      147,1    19216,3&#13;
B. Equipement-materiel                        -        279,8         -       91,0       370,8&#13;
C. Vehicules                                           935,0         -          -       935,0&#13;
D. Formation et appui                         -            -     761,5          -       761,5&#13;
E. Consultation-etudes                        -            -    1 003,6     244,5     1 248,0                                           &gt;&#13;
Total Investment Costs                    19 057,8     1 226,2    1 765,0     482,5    22 531,6                                            1&#13;
II. Recurrent Costs&#13;
A. Salaires-Main d'oeuvre                     -      2 409,0         -       53,5     2 462,4&#13;
B. Deplacements                               -        362,7         -       18,0       380,7&#13;
C. Fonctionnement vehicules                   -        241,9         -          -       241,9&#13;
D. Maintenance equipements                    -        328,9         -          -       328,9&#13;
Total Recurrent Costs                           -      3 342,5         -       71,4     3 413,9&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                       19 057,8      4 568,7    1 765,0     554,0    25 945,6&#13;
Taxes&#13;
Foreign Exchange                        10 396,5     1 401,5     686,0      222,1    12 706,2&#13;
C);&#13;
m 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Expenditure Accounts by Components - Totals Including Contingencies&#13;
(UM Million)&#13;
Encadrement&#13;
Technique            Programme&#13;
Investissements  (cout hors   Appul et    Pilots&#13;
Vi0lageols      taxe)    Formation  Pastoral    Total&#13;
1. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Genie civil                           2 706,2         1,6         -       20,9    2 728,7&#13;
B. Equipement-materiel                        -         39,7         -       12,9      52,6&#13;
C. Vehicules                                  -        132,8         -          -      132,8&#13;
D. Formation et appul                         -            -     108,1          -      108,1&#13;
E. Consultation-etudes                        -            -     142,5       34,7      177,2&#13;
Total Investment Costs                     2 706,2       174,1     250,6       68,5    3 199,5&#13;
11. Recurrent Costs&#13;
A. Salaires-Main d'oeuvre                     -        342,1         -        7,6      349,7&#13;
B. Deplacements                               -         51,5         -        2,6      54,1&#13;
C. Fonctionnement vehicuies                   -         34,4         -          -       34,4&#13;
D. Maintenance equipements                    -         46,7         -          -      46.7&#13;
Total Recurrent Costs                           -        474,6         -       10,1      484,8&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                        2 706,2       648,8      250,6      78,7    3 684,3&#13;
Taxes&#13;
Foreign Exchange                         1 476,3       199,0      97,4       31,5    1 804,3&#13;
e s&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Expenditure Accounts Project Cost Summary&#13;
%     % Total&#13;
(UM Million)                      (USS 000)              Foreign   Base&#13;
Local    Foreign     Total      Local      Foreign     Total   Exchange  Costs&#13;
I. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Genie civil                     1 094,1    1 332,7    2 426,7    7 704,6    9 385,2    17 089,8       55      74&#13;
B. Equipement-materiel                5,0       44,9       49,9       35,1       316,0      351,1        90       2&#13;
C. Vehicules                         12,3      110,8      123,1       86,7       780,2      866,9        90       4&#13;
D. Formation et appui                78,8       20,9      99,7       554,9       147,3      702,1        21       3&#13;
E. Consultation-etudes               81,9       83,1     165,0       576,4       585,4     1 161,8       50       5&#13;
Total Investment Costs               1 272,0    1 592,4    2 864,4    8957,7    11 214,0    20 171,7       56      87&#13;
II. Recurrent Costs&#13;
A. Salaires-Main d'oeuvre           310,6          -      310,6     2 187,4          -     2 187,4        -       9&#13;
B. Deplacements                      48,1          -      48,1       338,8           -      338,8         -       1&#13;
C. Fonctionnementvehicules           12,4       18,6      30,9        87,1       130,7      217,9       60        1&#13;
D. Maintenance equipements           21,0       21,0      41,9       147,5       147,5      295,1       50        1&#13;
Total Recurrent Costs                 392,0       39,5     431,6      2760,9       278,3     3039,1        9       13&#13;
Total BASELINE COSTS                 1 664,0    1 631,9    3 295,9    11 718,5    11 492,3    23 210,8     50      100&#13;
Physical Contingencies                  -          -         -           -           -          -         -       -&#13;
Price Contingencies                 216,0      172,4     388,3      1 520,9    1 213,9     2 734,7      44       12&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                  1 880,0    1 804,3    3 684,3    13 239,4    12 706,2    25 945,6     49      112&#13;
0 &#13;
0 W&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Expenditure Accounts by Years - Totals Including Contingencies&#13;
(USS '000)&#13;
Totals Including Contingencies&#13;
1997      1998       1999      2000       2001      2002     Total&#13;
1. Investrnent Costs&#13;
A. Genie civil                      960,6    1 893,9    2 788,1    5 737,3    7 836,4      -    19 216,3&#13;
B. Equipement-materiel              258,7       47,3      11,5       18,1       18,6    16,6       370,8&#13;
C. Vehicules                        575,3       29,9      15,4       37,8       32,3   244,3       935,0&#13;
D. Formation et appui               232,7      244,9     112,6       95,8       75,4       -       761,5&#13;
E. ConsuKation-etudes               495,2      415,2     108,6       97,2      93,3    38,5      1 248,0&#13;
Total Investment Costs               2 522,5    2 631,2    3 036,2    5 986,3    8 055,9   299,4    22 531,6&#13;
II. Recurrent Costs&#13;
A. Salaires-Main d'oeuvre           241,7      465,8     489,6      504,0      518,2   243,1     2 462,4&#13;
B. Deplacements                      42,4       73,2      74,6       76,8      79,1    34,5        380,7&#13;
C. Fonctionnement vehicules          25,3       46,2      48,1       49,4       50,7    22,3       241,9&#13;
D. Maintenance equipements           30,7       63,1      64,8       66,6       68,5    35,2       328,9&#13;
Total Recurrent Costs                 340,1      648,3     677,1      696,9      716,5   335,0     3 413,9&#13;
Total PROJECT COSTS                  2 862,7    3 279,6    3 713,4    6 683,2    8 772,4   634,4    25 945,6&#13;
Ul&#13;
OCD&#13;
e l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Expenditure Accounts by Financiers&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
Local&#13;
The Association   The Government   The Beneficiaries                                 (Excl.   Duties &amp;&#13;
Amount      %    Amount   %         Amount    %         Amount    %       For. Exch.   Taxes)    Taxes&#13;
I. Investment Costs&#13;
A. Genie civil                                     11422,1    59,4       0,0       -    7794,2    40,6    19216,3    74,1    10443,7        8 772,7&#13;
B. Equipement-materiel                                370,8   100,0      0,0       -          -       -       370,8     1,4      333,2        37,5&#13;
C. Vehicules                                          935,0   100,0      0,0       -          -       -       935,0     3,6      840,1        95,0&#13;
D. Formation et appui                                 761,5   100,0      0,0       -          -       -       761,5     2,9      159,4       602,0&#13;
E. Consultation-etudes                              1248,0   100,0       0,0       -          -       -     1 248,0     4,8      623,2       624,8&#13;
Total Investment Costs                               14 737,4    65,4      0,0       -    7 794,2    34,6   22 531,6    86,8    12 399,6    10 132,0&#13;
II. Recurrent Costs&#13;
A. Salaires-Main d'oeuvre                           2 009,8    81,6   452,7    18,4           -       -    2 462,4      9,5          -      2 462,4&#13;
B. Deplacements                                       380,7   100,0        -       -          -       -       380,7     1,5          -       380,7        -G&#13;
C. Fonctionnementvehicules                            241,9   100,0      0,0       -          -       -       241,9     0,9      143,9        98,0&#13;
D. Maintenance equipements                            250,4    76,1    78,5    23,9           -       -       328,9     1,3      162,7       166,2&#13;
Total RecurrentCosts                                  2 882,8    84,4   531,2    15,6           -       -     3 413,9    13,2      306,6     3107,4&#13;
rotal Disbursement                                    17 620,2    67,9   531,2     2,0    7 794,2    30,0   25 945,6   100,0    12 706,2    13 239,4&#13;
I ;&#13;
.0 &#13;
O Z&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAURITANIA&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PROJECT&#13;
Components by Financiers&#13;
(US$ '000)&#13;
Local&#13;
The Association   The Govemment   The Beneficiaries          Total                    (Excl.    Duties &amp;&#13;
Amount      %    Amount   %         Amount      %       Amount       %     For. Exch.   Taxes)     Taxes&#13;
1. lnvestissementsVillageois                       11 263,6    59,1      0,0       -    7794,2    40,9    19 057,8    73,5    10396,5       8 661,3&#13;
2. Encadrement Technique (cout hors taxe)           4037,6    88,4   531,2    11,6            -        -     4568,7    17,6      1401,5     3167,3&#13;
3. Appui et Formation                                1 765,0   100,0     0,0       -          -        -     1 765,0     6,8      686,0     1 079,0&#13;
4. Programme Pilote Pastoral                          554,0   100,0      0,0        -         -        -      554,0     2,1       222,1       331,8         -&#13;
Total Disbursement                                    17 620,2    67,9   531,2      2,0    7 794,2    30,0    25 945,6   100,0    12 706,2    13 239,4          -n&#13;
'V&#13;
l&#13;
0 &gt;&#13;
i &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -                                 ANNEX 5&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
ESTIMATED SCHEDULE OF DISBURSEMENTS OF IDA CREDIT-&#13;
IDA Fiscal Year       Disbursements US$   Disbursements US$   Disbursements %&#13;
&amp; Semester          Million p. Semester  Million Cumulative           Cumulative&#13;
FY98&#13;
Dec. 1997                          0.9                    0.9                      5&#13;
June 1998                          1.0                    1.9                     11&#13;
FY99&#13;
Dec. 1998                          1.1                    3.0                    17&#13;
June 1999                          1.2                    4.2                    23&#13;
FY2000&#13;
Dec. 1999                          1.2                    5.4                    30&#13;
June 2000                          1.4                    6.8                    38&#13;
FY 2001&#13;
Dec. 2000                          2.0                    8.8                    49&#13;
June 2001                         2.6                    11.4                    63&#13;
FY 2002&#13;
Dec. 2001                          2.9                   14.3                    79&#13;
June 2002                          3.2                   17.5                    97&#13;
FY 2003&#13;
Dec. 2002                          0.3                   17.8                    99&#13;
June 2003                          0.2                   18.0                   100&#13;
8   This schedule of disbursement was established assuming the project is the five years tranche of a 20-year program. Therefore standard&#13;
disbursement schedules does not apply: (i) it would be implemented over 6 years instead of the standard 7-year schedule in Mauritania;&#13;
and (ii) it maintains its annual pace of disbursement until implementation of the following tranche begins.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
PROJECT INSTITUTIONAL SET-UP&#13;
[ Project &#13;
Steering Committee|&#13;
33 '             ~~~T echnical           Ministry of             Ministry of     |&#13;
CD 3              |     Ministeries              I l  lnterior  | | Rural Development&#13;
Cabinet         (5)&#13;
Project's UCPG&#13;
Governor           MDRE Delegation&#13;
of the Region    *) Project's Coordinator&#13;
EMATs&#13;
Regional Development&#13;
SAC-PAC-PIC               Committee&#13;
e 1partment                       Preparation              Implementation&#13;
fi_ 12 '(eview                            ACPCP                          PI&#13;
|Contractors &#13;
NGOSs       _&#13;
g Q     I  C~Review  I                                       Convention 1&#13;
Extension Agent&#13;
Community&#13;
_ev. Association&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
62&#13;
ANNEX 7&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
SELECTION CRITERIA OF PARTICIPATING COMMUNITIES2&#13;
Criteria                                     Indicators                       Weighting&#13;
Village eligibility             * geographic location (within selected&#13;
communes);&#13;
* more than 100 and less than 1,000 inhabitants;&#13;
Socio-economical                * viability and sustainability of activities carried    5&#13;
sustainability                     out by community;&#13;
Community social                * degree of social cohesion (rather than its            5&#13;
cohesion                           homogeneity (not a selection criteria);&#13;
* existence of effective socio-professional&#13;
organizations;&#13;
Community past performances   * time elapsed since dwelling was established;            5&#13;
* community's ability in resolving conflicts, or&#13;
persistence of those;&#13;
* performances and sustainability of investments&#13;
established by former projects;&#13;
* spontaneous initiative from community to&#13;
protect the environment;&#13;
Community degree of             * community's understanding and acceptance of           3&#13;
commitment                         project's objectives, strategy and actions;&#13;
* community's acceptance of "project's rules of&#13;
the game" and amount of beneficiaries'&#13;
participation to village's investments;&#13;
Assessment made by              Assessment of community's ability to participate        3&#13;
other stake holders             successfully to project's implementation:&#13;
* Administrative authorities;&#13;
* technical services (extension agents)&#13;
* independent (private sector, NGOs)&#13;
Availability of human           * counterpart contribution being rather high,           2&#13;
resources                          communities with manpower will be preferred&#13;
_   to those with high level of expatriation;&#13;
Ecological replicability        * community's management plan likely to be              2&#13;
replicable else where;&#13;
9 Rating to be applied as follows: 4: maximum; 3: much; 2: average; 1: little; 0: not at all. For criteria including several indicators, an&#13;
average is calculated over these different indicators;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-63 -                              ANNEX8&#13;
Page 1 of 20&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resources Management Project&#13;
INVESTMENT CHOICES AND ECONOMIC JUSTIFICATION&#13;
A.    Introduction&#13;
1.    The project is based on a participatory approach which allows beneficiaries to select the&#13;
priority actions to be retained under the Community Investment Program (PIC), provided certain&#13;
selection criteria are adhered to. It is therefore difficult, if not impossible, to quantify beforehand&#13;
the type, size and frequency of investments of choice which makes it impractical to estimate a&#13;
rate of return for the project as a whole.&#13;
2.    However, it is possible to design rural community models of the communities that are likely&#13;
to be found under the project; to make assumptions on their priority needs; to identify certain&#13;
investments that would respond to these priorities; to ascertain that these investments would fall&#13;
within the limits of the selection criteria; and to calculate a return on these investments. Using this&#13;
approach, it is possible to estimate a rate of return on the overall investment "package" for each&#13;
model.&#13;
3.    Three models have been developed: (a) a pastoral model, in which resources are almost&#13;
exclusively limited to livestock, and which is likely to be found in the driest parts of the project&#13;
area; (b) an agro-pastoral model, in which livestock activities are still preponderant but in which&#13;
cropping activities are already more important; and (c) an agro-sylvo -pastoral model, in which&#13;
in addition to livestock and cropping, forest and bush exploitation is an important activity. This&#13;
model is likely to be found in the wettest parts of the project area where forest and bush&#13;
Savannah are present.&#13;
4.    The models are summarized below. A description of the village is given; its main&#13;
problems are noted; a hypothetical choice of actions has been made; the investment are tested&#13;
against the eligibility criteria, and a cost/benefit analysis of the investment package has been&#13;
worked out.&#13;
1.    The Pastoral Model&#13;
Description of the Area&#13;
5.    The land area, which belongs to one or more villages, is predominantly used for&#13;
livestock grazing. Recession cultivation may occur on occasion, but occupies less than 5% of the&#13;
land.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-64-                                ANNEX8&#13;
Page 2 of 20&#13;
6.    The village(s) has (have) one or more wells, which serve only as water points for&#13;
livestock and for human consumption; no irrigation is practiced.&#13;
7.    The land area is located in the most arid part of the rainfed zone. Permanently residing&#13;
inhabitants number fewer than 300 families. Nomadic herders frequently use the grazing area as&#13;
well as existing wells. The area is generally overgrazed; fodder resources are scarce and wood&#13;
resources limited or non-existent.&#13;
Main Problems emerging from the analvsis&#13;
8.    Overgrazing of the land, and the resulting decline of fodder production capacity, raises&#13;
the problem of survival of the village. Free access to the land by nomadic herders without&#13;
limitations on grazing or use of well water has so far precluded any action.&#13;
9.    The village only produces a fraction of its food needs. Contour bunding would make it&#13;
possible to increase cropland production, but due to hilly terrain, bunds need to be stone&#13;
protected.&#13;
Moving sand dunes threaten to destroy village buildings and infrastructure.&#13;
Priority Actions Decided&#13;
10.   To initiate a pasture management program, in order to reduce overgrazing, improve&#13;
fodder production and eliminate conflicts between village inhabitants and nomadic herders. An&#13;
existing well will be repaired and deepened, and equipped with a windmill and water reservoir to&#13;
reduce watering (and grazing) time for nomadic herders. Herders, in turn agree to submit to&#13;
grazing rules and water charges.&#13;
11.   A tree and bush perimeter will be established to protect village infrastructure and&#13;
cropland from moving sand dunes, and to fix the dunes (anti-erosion works).&#13;
12.   Contour bunds will be built  and partly stone protected, to increase village food&#13;
production.&#13;
Elig'ibility Criteria Test&#13;
The limits that apply to this model are the following:&#13;
(a)   project financing limit: $ 100 per inhabitant, or $30,000 for the community.&#13;
(b)   investments in water supply (wells, boreholes, etc.) cannot exceed 60% of total&#13;
investment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-65-                           ANNEX8&#13;
Page 3 of 20&#13;
(c)   water supply investments are to be shared between project and villagers in a&#13;
*800/o/20% ratio; land improvement, and erosion protection works in a 200/o/80%&#13;
ratio.&#13;
The investment tables (below) show that:&#13;
(a)   the overall investment would be about UM 6.1 million ($ 44,000), of which the&#13;
project would finance UM 3.3 million (24,000) or about 55%, which is below&#13;
the $30,000 limit for the community;&#13;
(b)   the water supply investment is estimated at UM 3.3 million, or 54% of the total&#13;
investment which is below the 60% limit;&#13;
(c)   project investment in water supply is UM 2.7 million ($19,000) or 81% of the&#13;
total water supply investment, which is at the 800/o/20% sharing limit; and&#13;
(d)   project investment in anti-erosion and land improvement works is UM  0.6&#13;
million, or 21 % of the total land works investment which is slightly above the&#13;
20%/80% sharing limit.&#13;
Economic Justification&#13;
13.   The cost/benefit tables below show that the internal rates of return for the three&#13;
investments are: 13% for water supply combined with pasture improvement; 20% for anti-&#13;
erosion works, and 11% for contour bunds. Labour costs in all these calculations have been&#13;
included. The overall return on the investment package is 12%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-66-                               ANNEX8&#13;
Page 4 of 20&#13;
PASTURE IMPROVEMENT: COST-BENEFIT ANALYSIS&#13;
EXPLANATORY NOTES&#13;
It is assumed that the Rural Community is in the arid zone of the project area, and has about&#13;
5,000 hectares of grazing lands, with a grazing population of 1,500 cattle (of which 350 milk cows)&#13;
and a goat and sheep population of 4,500.&#13;
The main initial investment is to increase the water supply and accelerate water flow, in&#13;
order to enable the establishment of rotational grazing. To achieve this, the existing well will be&#13;
repaired and deepened; and a windmill with a water reservoir will be built. Furthernore, water&#13;
charges for well use will be introduced sufficient to pay for the operation and maintenance of the&#13;
water supply system.&#13;
In the without project situation, overgrazing would continue as a result of which, pasture&#13;
production capacity is assumed to decline from the present situation (outlined below) to about 60%&#13;
of its present level, with a proportionate decrease in animal off-take and milk production.&#13;
In the with project situation, output is expected to increase in five years to levels outlined&#13;
below. It is also assumed that all infrastructure works will be completed in one year and that&#13;
rotational grazing management will begin in year 2.&#13;
Situation before Project&#13;
stock      number  productivity  sales/year  adult weight    unit        total&#13;
value(UM)   value(UM)&#13;
cattle          1,500       12%          180         220         1,540      227,200&#13;
milk cows        350       150 liter    52,500        -           3.5        183,750&#13;
goats &amp; sheep    4,500      15%          675         20           140        94,500&#13;
total                                                                   505,450&#13;
Situation with Project at Full Development&#13;
cattle            1,500      22%        330        270          1,890       623,700&#13;
milk cows          350     250 liter    87,500       -          3.5         306,250&#13;
goats &amp; sheep     4,500      25%        1,125       25          175         196,875&#13;
total                                                                1,126,825&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resources Management Project&#13;
PASTURE IMPROVEMENT: COST/ BENEFIT ANALYSIS ('000 UM)&#13;
Categories           0       1      2       3      4      5       6      7      8       9     10      11     12&#13;
Investments&#13;
Well Repair          1 500&#13;
Windmill             1 000&#13;
Water Reservoir        200&#13;
Borders                 30&#13;
Sub-total            2 730&#13;
Operating Costs&#13;
extension              200    200    100    100    100&#13;
Sub-total              200    200    100    100    100&#13;
Total Costs          2 930    200    100    100    100&#13;
Without Project&#13;
sale of cattle         227    212    197    182    167    151    136    136    136    136    136    136    136&#13;
sale of milk           184    172    160    148    136    124    111    III    II1    III    I11    III    III&#13;
sale of goats/sheep     94     88      82     76     70      63     56     56      56     56     56      56     56&#13;
Sub-total              505    472    439    406    373    338    303    303    303    303    303    303    303&#13;
With Project&#13;
sale of cattle         227    293    359    425    491    557    624    624    624    624    624    624    624&#13;
sale of milk           184    204    224    244    264    285    306    306    306    306    306    306    306&#13;
sale of goats/sheep     94    111    128    145    162    179    197    197    197    197    197    197    197&#13;
Sub-total              505    608    711    814    917   1011   11271  1127   1127   1127   1127   1127   1127&#13;
Total Net Benefits     -      136    272    408    544    673    824    824    824    824    824    824    824&#13;
Net Cost/Benefits    -2930    -64    172    308    444    673    824    824    824    824    824    824    824&#13;
Rate of Return        13%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68--                            Page 6 of 20&#13;
COST-BENEFIT ANALYSIS: ANTI-EROSION WORKS OVER 4 HECTARE&#13;
EXPLANATORY NOTES&#13;
Size of the Perimeter&#13;
It is assumed, based on actual experience, that a bush and tree perimeter of about 30 meters&#13;
bandwidth would protect an area slightly less than 100 meters behind it. Based on this, a perimeter&#13;
of 4 hectare would protect an area of 120 hectare.&#13;
Infrastructure Protected&#13;
It is assumed that within the protected area, one well (present value 100,000 UM) and 15&#13;
buildings exist (present value 40,000 UM each). If protected, they would all be amortized in 10&#13;
years. Without protection, they would have to be abandoned after three years.&#13;
Cropland protected&#13;
It is assumed that, of the 120 hectare protected, 12 hectare is cropland with a present value of&#13;
10,000 UM per hectare. Without the project, the cropland would be lost after three years. No value&#13;
has been assigned to pasture land.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resources Management Project&#13;
ANT- EROSION PROTECTION WORKS OVER 4 HECTARE: COST/ BENEFIT ANALYSIS ('000 UM)&#13;
Categories                     0      1       2      3       4      5       6       7      8       9      10&#13;
Investmenb&#13;
Fences                           90&#13;
Rastering                       222&#13;
sub-total Enclosure              312&#13;
bush seedlings                  264&#13;
tree seedlings                    54&#13;
sub-total Nursery                318&#13;
land preparation                 162&#13;
transport plants                  84&#13;
planting                         33&#13;
sub-total Plantation            279                                                                                           o&#13;
sub-total investments            909&#13;
Operating Costs&#13;
irrigation                       138     69&#13;
maintenance                             129&#13;
replanting                                      129&#13;
surveillance                     24      12      12     12      12      12     12      12     12      12     12&#13;
sub-total operating costs        162    210    141      12      12     12      12      12     12      12     12&#13;
Total Costs                    1 071    210    141      12      12     12      12     12      12      12     12&#13;
wood production (value)         -      -                                                                     21&#13;
fodder production (value)       -                                       3       3      3       3       3     12&#13;
infrastructure saved (amort.    -       105    210    315    420    350    280    210    140          70   -&#13;
value)&#13;
cropland saved (amort. value)   -        60      90    120    120    120    120    120    120    120    120&#13;
Total Benefits                          165    300    435    540    470    400    330    260    190    120&#13;
Net Cost/Benefits              -1071    -45    159    423    528    458    358    318    248    178    108&#13;
Rate of Return                 20%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-70-                              ANNEX8&#13;
Page 8 of 20&#13;
CONSTRUCTION OF STONE CONTOUR BUNDS OVER 25 HA.&#13;
EXPLANATORY NOTES&#13;
Assumptions&#13;
The contour bunds would be stone protected in view of the hilly terrain and water flow velocity&#13;
during the wet season&#13;
Per hectare, 400 meter of stone bunds would be built (20 meter spacing)&#13;
Labour cost: 120 UM per linear meter.&#13;
Equipment and supplies: (I) gabions: 15 UM per linear meter over half the distance (5,000 meters);&#13;
(2) carts and wheelbarrows for stone transport: 15,000 UM&#13;
Maintenance: 5% of construction costs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
CONSTRUCTION OF CONTOUR BUNDS ON 25 HA.: COST/BENEFIT ANALYSIS ('000 UM)&#13;
Categories                      0      1     2    3    4    5    6    7    8    9    10&#13;
Investments&#13;
stone prot. bunds (labour)     1 200&#13;
equipment and supplies           90&#13;
sub-total investments          1 290&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
stone prot.bunds (labour)          -    70   70   70   70   70   70   70   70   70    70&#13;
sub-total maintenance              -    70   70   70   70   70   70   70   70   70    70&#13;
Totalcosts                     1290     70   70   70   70   70   70   70   70   70    70&#13;
Benefits&#13;
increm. soghum production&#13;
600kg/ha at 30 UM/kg.           -      450  450  450  450  450  450  450  450  450   450&#13;
sub-total benefits              -      450  450  450  450  450  450  450  450  450   450&#13;
Prod. Costs&#13;
seeds: 60 kg/ha at 30Um/kg      -       45   45   45   45   45   45   45   45   45    45&#13;
labour:32 days at l50 UM/day    -      120  120  120  120  120  120  120  120  120   120&#13;
sub-total prod.costs            -      165  165  165  165  165  165  165  165  165   165&#13;
Total Net Benefits              -      285  285  285  285  285  285  285  285  285   285&#13;
Net Cost/Benefits             -1 290   215  215  215  215  215  215  215  215  215   215&#13;
Rate of Return                  11%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-72 -                             ANNEX &#13;
Page 10 of 20&#13;
2.    The Agro -Pastoral model&#13;
Description ofArea&#13;
The land area is still predominantly used for grazing, but the scope for cropping (either&#13;
rainfed or as recession cultivation) is greater (between 5% and 10% of the area).&#13;
The land is in an area with more rainfall than in Model A, and the village(s) contain(s) more&#13;
permanent residents than under Model A (assumption: 500 inhabitants).&#13;
The village(s) has several wells that have however insufficient flow to cover the livestock&#13;
and human needs;&#13;
Main Problems emerging from the analysis&#13;
Nomadic herders use the grazing area, and conflicts among residents as well as between&#13;
residents and nomadic herders occur over the use of well water, which often is insufficient to cover&#13;
the needs of both cattle and the human population. Also, because of overgrazing, the rangeland is&#13;
degrading.&#13;
There is insufficient crop land for the subsistance needs of the community.  A potential&#13;
exists to expand the land under crops, but it would need a more secure retention of water flows&#13;
during the wet season&#13;
Priority Actions Decided&#13;
To alleviate the water and food production problems, three interventions have been decided&#13;
upon:&#13;
(a)   repair an deepening of an existing well, together with installation of a windmill and&#13;
water reservoir, in order to start a range management program and serve the water&#13;
needs of villagers and transhumants;&#13;
(b)   construction of three retention dikes with a system of contour bunds downstream, in&#13;
order to increase the area under recession cultivation;&#13;
(c)    deepening of one of the existing village wells, in order to establish a small irrigated&#13;
perimeter to cultivate fresh vegetables and fruits.&#13;
Eli-eibilitv Criteria Test&#13;
(a)    The overall investment for the community would amount to about 6.35 million UM&#13;
(S 45,600) of which the project would finance 4.6 million UM ($ 33,000) which is&#13;
well below the project financing limit for the community ($50,000);&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
73 -                        ANNEX8&#13;
Page 11 of 20&#13;
(b)   The water supply investments are estimated at 4.2 million UM ($30,000) or 62% of&#13;
the total investment, which is slightly above the 60% limit;&#13;
(c)   In order not to exceed the 80% project financing limit on water supply investments,&#13;
the community inhabitants would have to contribute 20% or 840,000 UM ($6,000)&#13;
to cover their part of the investment financing;&#13;
(d)    The land improvement works are estimated at 2.15 million UM ($15,000) of which&#13;
the project would finance 360,000 UM ($2,600) or 16% which is well below the&#13;
sharing limit of 20%.&#13;
Economic Justification&#13;
The investment tables below show that investments in the pasture well and improvement&#13;
program, in the retention dikes and contour bunds, and in the horticulture well and perimeter, would&#13;
have intemal rates of return of 13%, 10%, and 15% respectively. The overall internal rate of return&#13;
on the package (all labour costs included) is 13 %.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
~ 74 -                      ANNEX8&#13;
Page 12 of 20&#13;
CONSTRUCTION OF RETENTION DIKE AND CONTOUR BUNDS OVER 15 HA.&#13;
EXPLANATORY NOTES&#13;
Introduction&#13;
1.    A good deal of experience exists in Mauritania with the construction of retention dikes.&#13;
They serve to retain rainwater that would otherwise run off, thus permitting the sowing of a summer&#13;
crop (if the ground is only damp or of an autumn/winter crop (on residual moisture, once the water&#13;
retained has evaporated) where cropping would otherwise be impossible. Invariably, a grain crop is&#13;
sown (sorghum or millet), typically without the use of fertilizer. Yields are low, averaging about 0.6&#13;
tons per hectare.&#13;
2.    A great variety of retention dikes exists. The simplest are earthen contour bunds erected by&#13;
the farmers themselves with hand tools, which generally need to be repaired or rebuilt frequently.&#13;
The most sophisticated are dams with stone sidings and equipped with concrete spillways and&#13;
control gates, covering an area of up to 200 hectare and built by the Government or donor-financed&#13;
projects. Construction costs vary from 14,000 UM ($100) per hectare to up to 525,000 UM&#13;
($3,700) per hectare depending on design, topography and area covered.&#13;
3.    A sizable number of the more sophisticated type of dams have been built during or after the&#13;
drought years, or are under construction. Many have revealed themselves to be uneconomic, given&#13;
the high cost of construction in relation to the value of production obtained (gross value of grain&#13;
production: about 18,000 UM to 20,000 UM per hectare), and because they are beyond the capacity&#13;
of the local population to maintain, requiring continuous Government or donor intervention for&#13;
repair or rehabilitation.&#13;
Data on the example retained&#13;
4.    The dike for which the cost/benefit analysis has been made, is at the lower end of the&#13;
investment cost range (about $280 per hectare). It has been chosen because it is at the limit of&#13;
what the local population can build and maintain with manual labour (with some project help in the&#13;
form of tools and transport of stones). The assumptions are as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-75 -                            ANNEX8&#13;
Page 13 of 20&#13;
dike length                    300 meters (depth of area behind dam: 500 meters)&#13;
earth works (labor costs)      800 UM per linear meter&#13;
stone protection (labor costs)  700 UM per linear meter including stone transport&#13;
spillway (labor costs and gabions)  6,000 UM per linear meter over 10 meters (including gabions)&#13;
20 UM per linear meter over 7500 meters (spacing every 20&#13;
contour bunds (labor costs)    meters)&#13;
annual dike maintenance        8% of construction costs&#13;
annual contour bunds repair    10% of construction costs&#13;
value of sorghum production                        600 kg valued at 30 UM per kg.&#13;
production costs:&#13;
seeds                                          60 kg. per ha. at 30 UM per kg.&#13;
labor for land preparation, sowing and   harvesting  35 days at 150 UM per day&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
CONSTRUCTION OF RETENTION DIKE AND CONTOUR BUNDS OVER 15 HECTARE&#13;
Categories             0        1        2         3        4        5         6        7        8        9        10&#13;
Investments&#13;
eath works dike            240&#13;
spillway                    60&#13;
stone protection of dike   210&#13;
contour bunds               60       90&#13;
sub-total Investments      570       90&#13;
maintenance&#13;
dike repair              -           20       40        40       40       40       40        40       40       40        40        &lt;&#13;
contourbunds             -           10        15       15       15       15        15       15       15       15        15 &#13;
sub-total maintenance    -           30       55        55       55       55       55        55       55       55        55&#13;
Total Costs                570      120       55        55       55       55       55        55       55       55        55&#13;
Benefits&#13;
Sorghum Production       -          150      235      270       270      270      270      270       270      270      270&#13;
minus:&#13;
seeds                    -           15       20       25        25       25       25       25        25       25       25&#13;
labour                   -           45       60       70        70       70       70        70       70       70       70&#13;
sub-total                -           60       80        95       95       95       95        95       95       95       95&#13;
Total Net Benefits       -           90      155       175      175      175      175       175      175      175       175&#13;
Net Cost-Benefits         -570      -30      100       120      120      120      120       120      120      120       120&#13;
Rate of Return            10%&#13;
0&#13;
0q &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_77 -                      ANNEX8&#13;
Page 15 of 20&#13;
ESTABLISHMENT OF HORTICULTURE PERIMETER OF ONE HECTARE&#13;
EXPLANATORY NOTES&#13;
I     The establishment of a horticulture perimeter of one hectare would necessitate the&#13;
following investments:&#13;
(a)   repair and deepening of an existing well valued at UM 1.5 million (see table)&#13;
(b)   construction, by manual means, of a reservoir to store well water for&#13;
irrigation: valued at UM 20,000;&#13;
(c)   purchase and installation of a metallic fence to protect the perimeter against&#13;
animal intrusion: 400 meters of fence at UM 300 per linear meter. Total cost:&#13;
UM 140,000;&#13;
(d)   purchase of tools and supplies (hoses, spraying cans, shovels, etc.): estimated&#13;
total cost: UM 40,000.&#13;
2.           Operating costs would consist of:&#13;
(a)   the purchase of vegetable seeds, estimated at 20% of the value of the finished&#13;
product (this was found to be the average on a sample of the most frequently&#13;
grown vegetables); and&#13;
(b)   maintenance of the perimeter, i.e., fence repair and replacement, purchase of&#13;
new tools, etc.: estimated at 15% of initial purchase cost annually, or UM&#13;
30,000 per annum at full development.&#13;
3.          The following assumptions have been made:&#13;
(a)   the well would provide sufficient water to irrigate one hectare. In reality,&#13;
horticultural perimeters are smaller (about one third of a hectare), but the&#13;
well -- usually located within the village-- also serves the villagers' potable&#13;
water needs and only one third of its production is used for perimeter&#13;
irrigation;&#13;
(b)   the most commonly grown vegetables are: mint, tomatoes, carrots, onions,&#13;
cabbage and eggplant. Overall production has been conservatively valued at&#13;
10 tons per hectare, with a production value of UM 80 per kilo;&#13;
(c)   vegetable gardening would almost exclusively be carried out by village&#13;
women, who would not be otherwise employed; labor costs have therefore&#13;
been excluded..&#13;
(d)   the useful life of the investment has been estimated at ten years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-78 -                           ANNEX8&#13;
Page 16 of 20&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
HORTICULTURE PERIMETER ESTABLISHMENT&#13;
Cost Benefit Analysis (Thousand UM p. Ha)&#13;
Years                    0          1          2         3          4          5 to 10&#13;
Investments&#13;
well repair               1 500&#13;
water reservoir          20&#13;
metal fence               140&#13;
tools, supplies          40&#13;
Total                    1 700&#13;
Operating Costs&#13;
seeds                    -          30         60        90         120        120&#13;
irrigation system        -          5          10         15        30         30&#13;
Total                    -          35         70        105        150        150&#13;
Total Costs              1 700      35         70        105        150        150&#13;
Production&#13;
Various vegetables       -          150        300       450        600        600&#13;
(average:&#13;
10 tons/ha at 80 UM/kg;&#13;
cropping intensity:65%)&#13;
Total Benefits           -1 700     115        230       345        450        450&#13;
Rate of Return: 15.2%    |&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
79 -                          ANNEX8&#13;
Page 17 of 20&#13;
3.    The Svlvo -Agro -Pastoral Model&#13;
Description of Area&#13;
The village land area is typically located in the more humid part of the rainfed zone. It is&#13;
still mostly used for livestock grazing, but existing or potential cropland covers more than 10% of&#13;
the area. Also, bush and woodlands are important, and a classified forest of 1,500 hectare is located&#13;
near the village.&#13;
The village(s) is (are) larger than under model B (model assumption: 800 inhabitants) and&#13;
inhabitants are generally permanent residents; few nomadic herders cross the area, but the village is&#13;
close to cattle routes.&#13;
Water is usually available in sufficient quantity for human and livestock needs. However,&#13;
the extension of cropland is limited (and even existing cropland is losing topsoil) due to rapid runoff&#13;
of rainwater,&#13;
Main Problems emergin2 from the Analysis&#13;
The impossibility of expanding crop cultivation and declining crop yields are hampering&#13;
village growth and causing emigration to the cities.&#13;
Increasingly, charcoalers are coming into the area to harvest trees for charcoal making, and a&#13;
depletion of wood resources is beginning-to be felt, leading to increased social tensions;&#13;
The village has women's associations engaged in handicrafts, which would require training&#13;
(to improve product quality) and funding (to permit better marketing).&#13;
Priority Actions Decided&#13;
In order to expand the cultivated area: construction of a dam with spillway, and a system of&#13;
contour bunds and terraces would be needed&#13;
In order to arrest and reverse the yield decline on existing cropland, anti-erosion contour&#13;
bund (digues filtrantes) would have to be constructed;&#13;
In order to halt unregulated exploitation of the woodlands: a woodland protection and&#13;
management program would be initiated for the classified forest, and a rural market for charcoal&#13;
would be established&#13;
Women's associations would be assisted in contacting and financing training facilities, and a&#13;
rollover fund of 700,000 UM for association marketing activities would be established&#13;
A women's association would be formed to operate a cooperative grain mill, which the&#13;
project would finance (cost: 1.4 million UM, or $10,000)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-80 -&#13;
Page 18 of 20&#13;
Eligibilitv Criteria Test&#13;
(a)   the total investment for the community would amount to  15.6 million UM&#13;
($111,400) of which the project would finance 4.8 million UM ($33,000) which is&#13;
well below the project financing limit of $80,000. The investment cost breaks down&#13;
as follows: (1) woodland protection and management: 7.2 million UM; (2) retention&#13;
dikes with contour bunds over 135 ha.: 5.13 million UM; (3) anti-erosion bunds over&#13;
120 ha.: 1.2 million UM; (4) grain mill: 1.4 million UM; and (5) rollover fund: 0.7&#13;
million UM.&#13;
(b)   observing the sharing limits, the project would contribute 20% of the cost of the land&#13;
improvement works, equivalent to 2.7 million UM; and 100% of the cost of the&#13;
grain mill and of the rollover fund, equivalent to 2.1 million UM.&#13;
Economic Justification&#13;
The cost/benefit calculations show that the intemal rates of return of the woodlands&#13;
protection, the retention dikes worth contour bunds, and the anti-erosion bunds would be 15%, 13%&#13;
and 13% respectively. The overall return on the package would be 14%. A return on the grain mill&#13;
has not been calculated but its main benefit would be savings in women's' working time; these&#13;
investments have been shown to be popular in similar projects throughout the Sahel.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-81 -                           ANNEX8&#13;
Page 19 of 20&#13;
ANTI-EROSION BUNDS ON EXISTING CROPLAND&#13;
EXPLANATORY NOTES&#13;
Introduction&#13;
Anti-erosion bunds of the filtrating type (digues filtrantes) serve to slow rainwater runoff during&#13;
the wet season impeding runoff of topsoil and increasing the deposit of sediments on the cropland. Usually&#13;
constructed of earth with e vegetative cover, their main beneficial effect is to increase soil fertility, thereby&#13;
increasing yields. Experience in other Sahel countries points to an average yield increase of 20% if the&#13;
bunds are well maintained. Even though the vegetative cover is done with drought resistant plants, such&#13;
bunds would only survive in the wetter parts of Mauritania (rainfall over 450 mm/year).&#13;
Investment cost&#13;
It is estimated that the establishment of bunds costs 20 UM per linear meter (virtually all in the&#13;
form of labour), and that a 20 meter spacing is required to maintain efficiency (500 linear meters per&#13;
hectare). In the model, it is assumed that they would be established over 120 hectares, over 3 years (30&#13;
hectares in year 1, 40 hectares in year 2 and the remaining 50 hectares in year 3). The resulting&#13;
investment cost totals 1.2 million um over three years.&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
It is estimated that maintenance would be 20% of investment cost each year (especially in&#13;
reestablishing vegetative cover). This would amount to 2,000 UM per hectare of finished bunds per year.&#13;
Benefits&#13;
Present average yields of sorghum are 600 kglha/year, valued at 30 UM/kg. A 20% increase would&#13;
amount to 120 kg./ha, or a total gross value of incremental production of 3,600 UM/ha. Incremental labour&#13;
costs (mostly harvesting) are valued at 20% of incremental production, or 720 UM/ha. The average life of&#13;
bunds, assuming continued maintenance, is estimated at 15 years.&#13;
Under these conditions, the internal rate of return on the investment would be 13%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-82 -                         ANNEX8&#13;
Page 20 of 20&#13;
WOODLANDS PROTECTION AND MANAGEMENT PROGRAM&#13;
EXPLANATORY NOTES&#13;
Introduction&#13;
The total area to be protected and manged would cover 1,200 hectare eventually.&#13;
Actions would consist of (a) delimiting the woodlands borders; (b) fencing and gating of&#13;
main entry points and access roads; (c) improvement of forest paths and establishing fire alleys;&#13;
(d) guarding the perimeter; and (e) managed grazing and cutting within the perimeter.&#13;
The prerequisite to this program would be that a contract will be signed and approved&#13;
between the administration, the charcoalers and the village authorities that the forest would be&#13;
for the exclusive use by the villagers, with forest management guidance by the administrative&#13;
authorities and strict cutting limits for the charcoalers.&#13;
Investment Cost&#13;
Investment costs are roughly estimated at 6,000 UM per hectare, of which 4,000 UM per&#13;
hectare would be for putting up fencing and gates. The remaining costs would be virtually all in&#13;
the form of labour; only an expense of 45,000 UM would be for the purchase of hand tools.&#13;
Benefits&#13;
A direct benefit of the operation would be the exclusive use of the perimeter by the&#13;
villagers for managed grazing and wood cutting. The gross value of production is estimated, on&#13;
an annual basis, at 1000 kg/ha of fodder (sales price: 2 UM/kg.) and 0.6 cubic meters of&#13;
wood/hectare (sales price: 3 UMlkg).&#13;
The main direct benefit, however, would be in the preservation of the woodlands;&#13;
without the protection and management program, and a continuation of unlimited cutting, it is&#13;
estimated that within 10 years, the production value would decline to 20% of its present value.&#13;
The environmental benefits would also be substantial, in the form of lower losses of&#13;
topsoil and maintenance of plant diversity in the forest as well as on forest grazing lands. In the&#13;
absence of reliable data, however, these benefits have not been quantified.&#13;
On the basis of the direct benefits alone. the internal rate of return of the protection and&#13;
management program is estimated at 15%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMFNTATION SCHEDULE&#13;
Project's activities         Responsibility       1996         1997        1998         1999        2000        2001        2002        2003&#13;
Pre-&amp;ffietiveness                                                 ...&#13;
* implementation manual           ECPG&#13;
* participative negotiations     IDA+GOM&#13;
* Board presentation              IDA                               %&#13;
* financial management system     ECPG&#13;
* contracts with auditors         ECPG&#13;
* Effectiveness                   ECPG+IDA        ...... :&#13;
Institution building: Recruitments&#13;
* Coordinator                    GOM&#13;
* ECPG Staff                     Project Coordinator                                                                                                        w&#13;
* EMAT Staff                      ECPG&#13;
* Regional coordinators/accountants   ECPG+Delegue&#13;
* Delegation Civil Servants      ECPG+Delegue&#13;
Institution Building: Eguioment&#13;
* Offices Rehab &amp; equipment       ECPG&#13;
* Vehicles                       ECPG&#13;
Technical Building: Research     ECPG, consultants&#13;
Technical building Workshops      ECPG                                       .&#13;
Technical Building: Skill Dev.                                                                             inL*iII                 .*&#13;
* Consultants' identification     ECPG&#13;
* Gap analysis, module design     ECPG, consultants&#13;
* Monthly training of EMATs       EMATS, consultant&#13;
* Fortnight training ext agents   ECPG, consultants&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Project's activities         Responsibility       1996        1997         1998        1999   |   2000         2001        2002         2003&#13;
Public awareness pregcram        ECPG+consultants                           IE&#13;
villaee invesiments&#13;
* Selection of beneficiary villages  ECPG+EMATs&#13;
* SAT preparation                EMAT+Delegation&#13;
* SAT clearance                  Reg. Coord. +CRD&#13;
* PAT and PGT preparation        EMAT+Delegation&#13;
* Contractual Arrangements       EMAT+Reg. Coor.&#13;
* Implementation of Investments  EMAT+contractor   ____.....&#13;
Review. Completion &amp; Second Phase&#13;
* SPN &amp; Reporting                IDA+ECPG&#13;
* Mid-Term review                IDA+ECPG&#13;
* Preparation 2nd phase          GOM+consultants&#13;
* Appraisal, Negotiation, Board:  IDA+GOM&#13;
* Effectiveness 2nd phase        IDA+ECPG&#13;
* Completion Ist phase           IDA                                                                                                                        o&#13;
* ICR 2nd phase                  GOM+IDA            II                       I_ 4_&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
PROJECT LOGICAL FRAMEWORK&#13;
A.   Project's Objectives&#13;
Description                        Indicators of Performances                     Assumption/ Risks&#13;
(threatening project's long term justification)&#13;
* Crop and livestock yield increases      * Rainfed cereal crop yield (sample)&#13;
* Livestock offtake (sample)              * Evolution of traditional features of social&#13;
organization which could hamper the&#13;
* Environment is rehabilitated water cycle,                                            equitable distribution of project benefits&#13;
land fertility, vegetation;             + Level of water table (sample)              between all social groups;&#13;
+ Measurement of land erosion (sample)&#13;
(Process of education, democratization,&#13;
human rights)&#13;
B.    Project's Outcome&#13;
Description                        Indicators of Performances                    Assumptions/ Risks&#13;
+ Women participation in decision making  (threatening translation of project's outcome&#13;
* Empowerment of local rural communities     (PRA)                                   into project's expected impact)&#13;
* % committed labor supplied annually&#13;
(project)                               * No occurrence of several years of&#13;
exceptionally low rainfall;&#13;
+ frequency of internal / external conflicts&#13;
* Improvement of land tenure security       (PRA)                                      (Community investment planing would&#13;
* O&amp;M fees collection from outsiders (project)   include drought preparedness scenarios);&#13;
CD&#13;
oQ&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C.   Project's Output&#13;
Description                        Indicators of Performances                     Assumptions/ Risks&#13;
* Technical services more effective and    * Adoption rate extension messages (project)  (threatening translation of project's output into&#13;
institutional support more conducive to  * % time spent by project staff in the field  project's expected outcome)&#13;
community empowerment                     (Project)&#13;
* Effectiveness community organization    * Technologies are available or well adapted;&#13;
* Relevant technologies available and social,  (PRA)                                   (effective research and use of available&#13;
technical and financial capabilities enhanced;  * % O&amp;M fees collected from direct   experience);&#13;
beneficiaries annually (project)&#13;
* Government political commitment to carry&#13;
* Village level investments implemented,   * % sustainability of equipment according to  out effective shift in decision making;&#13;
properly exploited and maintained;         amortization plan (Project)              (strengthening of on going decentralization&#13;
* % micro-enterprises funds reimbursed      process);&#13;
annually (Project)                      ____&#13;
D.   Project's Inputs/Components&#13;
Description                        Indicators of Performances                    Assumptions/ Risks&#13;
(threatening translation of project's inputs into&#13;
* Support of technical services in the rural  * % disbursement of the component (project)    project's expected outputs)&#13;
sector                                  * Number staff implementing project (id.)  * Ability of the administration to implement the&#13;
project;&#13;
* Research, extension and Skill development   * % disbursement component (project)    (relevance of the institutional setup)&#13;
of beneficiaries and other stake holders;  * man/woman-day trained (id.)           * Social conflicts (internal and external) likely&#13;
to disrupt project's implementation&#13;
* Community level investments              * % disbursement component (project)        (existence of relevant regulatory system; well&#13;
* Number communities benefiting (id.)       designed skill development)&#13;
* capacity of beneficiaries in participating in&#13;
community investments&#13;
(no risks if chosen by the community)&#13;
CD&#13;
'-*o&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
KEY PERFORMANCE INDICATORS&#13;
PYO                    PYI                    PY2&#13;
Goal  Actual   %       Goal  Actual   %       Goal  Actual   %&#13;
1. Estimated income ('000 UM p. capita)                                              l          x 1.1 |_     l&#13;
2. Land erosion (cms. p. year)                                                                  x 0.9&#13;
3. Collection of O&amp;M Fees (million UM p. year)                              6                     19 &#13;
4. Contrib. from beneficiaries (million UM p. year)                       115                    230&#13;
5. Credit Disbursement ('000 US$)                                         500                   1000&#13;
6. Beneficiaries (Number persons)                                        3700                  11000   m_&#13;
_____ PY3              PY4   _                PY5&#13;
Goal  Actual   %       Goal  Actual   %       Goal  Actual   %&#13;
1. Estimated income ('000 UM p. capita)          x 1.2                  x 1.3                   x 1.5&#13;
2. Land erosion (cms. p. year)                   x 0.8                  x 0.7                   x 0.5&#13;
3. Collection of O&amp;M Fees (million UM p. year)      38                     73                    123 i&#13;
4. Contrib. from beneficiaries (million UM p. year)  340                  680                    9001_&#13;
5. Credit Disbursement ('000 US$)                 1500                   3000                   4000&#13;
6. Beneficiaries (Number persons)               22000                  37000 n_75000n&#13;
1, 2:  Base line data not available until sampling carried out; expected goals: highly tentative;&#13;
3:    10% of consolidated infrastructures and productive investments;&#13;
4:    Village investments only.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Islamic Republic of Mauritania&#13;
Rainfed Natural Resource Management Project&#13;
NATURE AND SOURCE OF CONSULTANT SERVICES10&#13;
International      Sub-Regional           National              Total&#13;
_  SW     '000US$    SW       '000US$    SW       '000US$    SW       '000US$&#13;
Studies&#13;
* Assessment Public procurement system           3         8                              3         3         6&#13;
* Updating of groundwater master plan            66        15                             6         6         12&#13;
* Assessment of institutional matters                                9         16                             9&#13;
* Studies for Mid-term review                                        5         9          5         5        10                    X&#13;
* External audits                                                                        48        48        48                    co&#13;
Sub-total    9         23        14        25        62        62        85        110&#13;
Consultancies on technical matters&#13;
* Research sub-contracting                                           20        35        40        40        60&#13;
* computerized financial management system       10        25        10        17        10        10        30&#13;
* Institutional matters/ WID/ poverty            10        25        5         8         20        20        35&#13;
* Natural resources management matters           10        25        10        17        10        10        130&#13;
Sub-total    30        75        45        77        80        80        155       232&#13;
10 These figures are strictly tentative and do not imply any obligation on the part of project management, in terms of subject, duration, cost or origin.&#13;
o &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
International      Sub-Regional         National              Total&#13;
Consultancies on training matters&#13;
* Design &amp; implementation training program     10        25        20       35        100       100       130&#13;
* Workshops design and implementation                              15       25        10        10        25&#13;
* PRA and beneficiaries' assessments           10        25        10        17       10        10        30&#13;
* Public awareness package                     10        25        10        17       10        10        30&#13;
Sub-Total                30        75        55        93       130       130       215       298&#13;
Total                69        173       114      195       272       272       455       640&#13;
00&#13;
oo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IBRD 2S452&#13;
18.                                      140                  12r                  10'                     Forme,&#13;
MAURITANIA                                                                                     h1oomh   r       -- ALGER A&#13;
RAINFED NATURAL RESOURCE                                                                                        Shoj&#13;
MANAGEMENT PROJECT                                                                                         MAURITANIA&#13;
30'                                                                                              30 -           N-kcrrort&#13;
*      PROJECT HEADQUARTERS                                                                                                 M A L I&#13;
*      PROJECT COORDINATORS &amp; EMAT                                                                              N-ee.         *Tojbo. oj&#13;
_*     UE COORDINATION CENTERS                                                                D.kor SNA           ,_-                NIGER&#13;
I   IDA CREDIT                                                                           GAMTHEI                               N on/  y&#13;
UE PROJECT'                                                                               B,0'~' &#13;
ISOHYETS (ANNUAL RAINFALL IN MM, 1970-84)                                               GISSAU    GUINEA      r     '--°&#13;
NATIONAL PARKS                                            MO    R O  CC O                  0orrkry-/  \ DI-'i    - OT[ ,  o&#13;
-8  PRIMARY ROADS&#13;
SECONDARY ROADS&#133;8                                                                                        M1 r-t s  o   f TprWdrceidby r-k&#13;
T. Ti~~d..(  Top b.u-g-- -irolTe o- rP&#13;
------- -~  TRACKS                                                                                                     -o To -indott  Theandor a err ,ncrr'or rro" .or&#13;
-r-       RAILROADS                                                                                                 -rr map do rot opry on roe pc'rr cf&#13;
O     SELECTED TOWNS                                                                                            tr Wo'ro o-rtr ,Poryrrrer&#13;
(3     REGION CAPITALS                                                                     ,                    or, endreoenr o, orceptrrnce of&#13;
AIRPORTS                                                                                          N        r&#13;
260             PORTS                                               r                                .                        ALGERIA   26&#13;
REGION BOUNDARIES                                                           Ate Ben Tili&#13;
-  -    INTERNATIONAL                                    |±Cheqgg &#13;
BOUNDARIES                              To Lo'Youe      ir Mogrein &#13;
* UE Project includes only a                                                      -4&#13;
portion of Trarza region.        F O   R M   E  R                               T  R  S                                               '&#13;
!  \          ~TIRIS&#13;
-240                                    SPANISH    !  '    ZEMMOUR                                                    0'                         24&#13;
SAHARA   I&#13;
i   Zou4rot         ,'               r' 2                     /l&#13;
Fd6ritt       ,--        ~              f       &#13;
220                                                      |    To8ji,  T our.ne                                         /                         2&#13;
22,                                         ou I                                                                              22~~~~~~~~~~I &#13;
Nouadhibou                  -       6- oTrr  io m   ..                                                                    I.&#13;
la+IE1        i u6r                          8,° uad,na,D  R  A   Rne                                                M    A    L I&#13;
NOUAPDHMOU&#13;
200        BANC  I             INCHIRI 2   z                     anguelti                                                                        20&#13;
D'ARGUIN',                 Akj6__&#13;
Noudmghir-               - o, tx &#13;
Noue-mg  }   L                  vHODH ECH \&#13;
Tomassou,           ±       4(i e   NT                .                        \&#13;
Aqui,,--   FAg ai8a        0       *ridiikia  --_&gt;ocTi,ht            /      CHARGUI&#13;
NOUAKCHOTT            TA                             ,&#13;
Congor6fo  ., Moudje6rr           '&#13;
|. Bouti imi    t~ -Mpszta    La h'jar                                                            a   ...........................    x~&#13;
'Ale J'    &lt;~'   K (1' Tochekket                                          -&#13;
DIAWLING                                                                                            &lt;        ma              N&#13;
16'                                                                                 r                                           Bassiko 10uno 533  1 6&#13;
SENEGAL                    Gour0y20 30&#13;
t                          0       ~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~1 00  200  300&#13;
)                                               (KILOMETERS&#13;
14' 18'                  16                   14                   12                   10'                   8                    6             14&#13;
JANUARY 1997&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IMAGING&#13;
Report No.:        16384  MAU&#13;
Type:     SAR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="694784">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/05/694784/mauritania-rainfed-natural-resource-management-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1997/05/694784/mauritania-rainfed-natural-resource-management-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1997/05/694784/mauritania-rainfed-natural-resource-management-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1997/05/22/000009265_3970818102950/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1997/05/22/000009265_3970818102950/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>2965;P948</credit_no>
        <docdt>1997-05-22T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>1997-05-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Mauritania - Rainfed Natural Resource
            Management Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Rainfed Natural Resource Management
            Project will capitalize on the government's (a)
            empowering local communities and decentralizing services of
            the Ministry of Rural Development and Environment (MDRE);
            (b) implementing recommendations in the country
            environmental strategy paper (CESP) concerning more
            efficient management of natural resources; and (c)
            coordinating with existing extension services, devising a
            domestic energy strategy, and liaising with the Mauritanian
            Integrated Development Program of Irrigated Agriculture
            (PDIAIM) now in process. To break the poverty cycle, the
            project will improve the basic ecological functions (water
            and mineral cycles, ecological succession) through resource
            management, thus bringing about sustainable yield increases
            in crops and livestock and increased incomes for
            participating communities. The project's three
            components are: (1) financing investments in 250 villages
            chosen from representative agro-ecological zones in the
            country s rainfed area; (2) strengthening government
            services to support community organization, improve the
            legal framework for local empowerment, and finance
            government's technical support to beneficiaries; and
            (3) enhancing skills, including developing required
            technologies (research, short- and medium-term technical
            assistance), and disseminating those technologies through
            extension and training.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Mauritania - Rainfed Natural Resource
            Management Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Mauritania - Rainfed Natural
            Resource Management Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1997/05/694784/mauritania-rainfed-natural-resource-management-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>MR-Mauri:Rainfed Nat Res Mgt -- P001875</projn>
        <docty>Staff Appraisal Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Livestock and Animal Husbandry,Agricultural Research,Forestry,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>Mauritania</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sahel!$!80468</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>West Africa!$!80474</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3970818102950</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Water supply,General agriculture, fishing and forestry sector,General public administration sector,Roads and highways,Agricultural extension and research</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1997-1</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Natural resources development; Rain fed
            areas; Resources management; Local communities;
            Decentralization; Rural development; Extension services;
            Energy policy; Crop yields; Livestock; Income generation;
            Investment operations; Villages; Public services; Community
            participation; Community organization; Law reform; Technical
            assistance; Training
            AfDB,African Development Bank,agricultural
            development,agricultural lands,agricultural
            policies,agricultural production,agricultural
            sector,Agriculture,animal,animal fodder,animal
            husbandry,animals,aquifers,beef,biodiversity,camels,capacity
            building,cattle,cattle,cattle exports,central
            planning,cereals,climatic
            conditions,concession,cowpeas,Cropping,crops,cultivable
            land,decentralization,deforestation,desertification,development
            projects,diet,domestic demand,drought,drought
            preparedness,droughts,dry season,ecological
            conditions,economic development,economic growth,economic
            value,environmental degradation,environmental
            impact,environmental problems,environmental
            protection,equipment,exploitation,extension,extension
            services,FAO,farm,Farmers,Farming,Farming
            systems,feed,Financial Management,financial
            resources,fish,fish products,fisheries,fishing,fishing
            grounds,fodder,fodder production,food imports,Forest,forest
            exploitation,Forest lands,Forest
            protection,forestry,forests,GNP,goat
            meat,goats,grazing,grazing pressure,grazing
            rights,herders,herds,IDB,IFAD,imports,income,incomes,inflation,integration,irrigation,Land
            degradation,land rights,Land Tenure,land tenure
            legislation,land tenure security,land use,land use
            planning,Landmark,legislation,livestock,livestock
            development,livestock industry,livestock
            population,livestock production,Livestock
            raising,marketing,meat,meat production,milk,Milk
            production,millet,Natural Resource,Natural Resource
            Management,natural resources,NGOs,participatory
            approaches,pastoral land,pastoral production,pastoral
            production systems,pastoral systems,pastoralists,pasture
            improvement,pasture management,pastures,policy
            environment,pollution,pollution control,population
            growth,poverty reduction,private property,private
            sector,producers,productivity,productivity
            growth,quotas,rangeland,rangeland
            management,Rangelands,reforestation,resources
            management,rice,rural communities,Rural Development,rural
            population,salinization,savings,sheep,sheep,soil
            erosion,sorghum,sustainable development,sustainable
            use,sylvo-pastoral production,UNDP,United
            Nations,veterinary,veterinary research,Veterinary
            services,waste disposal,water resources,wheat,wood,wood
            markets,wood resources,wood supply
        </keywd>
        <owner>AFT: ESSD 2 (AFTS2)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sahel</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>West Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF023976-FAC CONSULTANT TRUST FUND (USD A/C),TF033073-MAURITANIA - RAINFED NATURAL
            RESOURCE MGMT,TF026105-SAHELIAN NATURAL RESOURCE MGT SUPPORT</trustfund>
        <repnb>16384</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resource Management and Biodiversity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources Management and Rural Issues</ml:concept><ml:concept>Degraded Lands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Desertification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dry Lands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drylands &amp; Desertification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resource Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resource Management </ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drylands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Land Tenure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Mauritania</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>