<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. T-6896-KG&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
THE KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
MAY 31, 1996&#13;
Agriculture, Industry and Finance Division&#13;
Country Department III&#13;
Europe and Central Asia Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EOUIVALENTS&#13;
(as of March 31. 1996)&#13;
Currency Unit   =  Som&#13;
I Som    =  US$ 093&#13;
US$1   =  10.8 Somn&#13;
AVERAGE EXCHANGE RATES&#13;
Som per US$1&#13;
1993      1994       1995   March 1996&#13;
Period Average      6.0        11.0      10.8       10.8&#13;
End of Period       8.3        10.6      11.2       10.8&#13;
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES&#13;
Metric System&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC - FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January I - December 31&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
CAS  - Country Assistance Strategy&#13;
CTC  - Coupon Trading Center&#13;
DEBRA  - Debt Resolution Agency&#13;
FINSAC  - Financial Sector Adjustment Credit&#13;
FSU  - Former Soviet Union&#13;
FMU  - Finsac Management Unit&#13;
GDP  - Gross Domestic Product&#13;
IDA  - International Development Association&#13;
IFC  - International Finance Corporation&#13;
IMF  - International Monetary Fund&#13;
M2 - Broad Money Supply&#13;
NBK  - National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic&#13;
NBFI - Non-Bank Financial Institutions&#13;
PESAC  - Privatization and Enterprise Sector Adjustment Credit&#13;
PPF  - Project Preparation Facility&#13;
PMU  - Project Management Unit&#13;
SAS  - State Agency for Securities&#13;
SDR  - Special Drawing Rights&#13;
TA  - Technical Assistance&#13;
TAP  - Technical Assistance Program&#13;
TOR  - Terms of Reference&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHBICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
PART I. THE FINANCIAL SECTOR ..................................... 1&#13;
PART II. THE PROJECT ............................................ 2&#13;
Project Objectives and  Description   ......................................  2&#13;
Assistance to the National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic ........................ 3&#13;
Bank Restructuring and Liquidation ..................................... 4&#13;
Debt Recovery and Resolution ........................................ 4&#13;
Central Registry  for Pledges   ..........................................  5&#13;
Training ...................................................... 5&#13;
Non-bank  Financial Institutions  (NBFIs)    ..................................  5&#13;
Public  Debt Instruments  and  Securities    ...................................  6&#13;
Rural Finance   ...................................................  6&#13;
Project Costs    ...................................................  6&#13;
Financing  Plan    ..................................................  6&#13;
PART III. PRO.JECT IMPLEMENTATION ARRANGEMENTS  .................. 6&#13;
Project Implementation    .............................................  6&#13;
Procurement             ...................................................  7&#13;
Disbursement   ...................................................  7&#13;
Project Accounting, Financial Reporting and Auditing ......................... 8&#13;
PART IV. BENEFITS AND RISKS   ...................................... 8&#13;
Benefits ...................................................... 8&#13;
Risks ........................................................ 9&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
Annex I. Detailed Cost and Financing Tables&#13;
Attachment 1:  Detailed  Project Costs:   1996-1998   ...........................   10&#13;
Attachment 2:  Detailed  Financing  Plan:   1996-1998   ..........................   11&#13;
Attachment 3: Summary of Proposed Procurement Arrangements for IDA and&#13;
Estimated  IDA   Disbursements    ......                          ........ .....................   13&#13;
Annex II. Terms of Reference&#13;
Senior Bank Adviser to Chairman, National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic  ....                                                           ........ 14&#13;
Legal Adviser to  the National Bank  of the Kyrgyz  Republic    .....................   17&#13;
Adviser on Bank Reorganization to the National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic  ...                                                          ...... 20&#13;
Adviser to  AKB  Kyrgyzstan  and  Promstroibank                               ............................   22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- ii -&#13;
Liquidation Adviser to Debt Resolution Agency (DEBRA)  ...................... 25&#13;
Financial Adviser to Debt Resolution Agency (DEBRA) ........................  28&#13;
Specialist in Non-Bank Financial Institutions Including Investment&#13;
Funds to Advise the Ministry of Finance  .................................  32&#13;
Specialist in Insurance Services to Advise the Ministry of Finance  ................. 37&#13;
Specialist in State Securities Instruments to Advise the Ministry of Finance   ....                      ....... 40&#13;
Annex III. Timetable of Key Project Processing Events  .........................  44&#13;
Annex IV. Cost Estimates from  Donors' Conference    .......................... 45&#13;
Annex V.  Implementation Plan   ........................................  48&#13;
Annex VI. Performance Monitoring Indicators   .............................. 49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
PART I. THE FINANCIAL SECTOR&#13;
1.  Before 1991, the Kyrgyz financial system was a regional component of the Soviet financial system&#13;
which mobilized and allocated resources according to the decisions of the Soviet government in Moscow.&#13;
In June 1991, the first set of financial sector reforms was introduced with the establishment of a two-tier&#13;
banking system with the National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic (NBK), the central bank, created under&#13;
the supervision of Parliament. Since then, the NBK has gradually assumed broader, more traditional&#13;
central bank powers through the enactment of a comprehensive Central Bank Law and a Commercial&#13;
Banking Law in 1992, the introduction of the national currency in 1993, and the development of a full&#13;
range of indirect monetary policy instruments. There are now weekly foreign exchange sales by the NBK&#13;
to the interbank market, regular treasury bill auctions, and credit auctions.&#13;
2.  At present, the Kyrgyz financial system consists of NBK, 17 commercial banks and a savings bank.&#13;
The "Big Four" specialized banks (Agroprombank, AKB Kyrgyzstan, Promstroibank and Elbank)&#13;
dominate the financial system, accounting for over 80% of the banking system's assets. Though money&#13;
and capital markets are underdeveloped, there are also a number of non-bank financial institutions. These&#13;
include 17 investment funds, 30 insurance companies, a stock exchange (KSE), a Coupon (privatization)&#13;
Trading Center (CTC), and three pension funds.&#13;
3. The commercial banking system is dominated by the Big Four commercial banks which are&#13;
insolvent. Other weaknesses in the banking system include a low level of capitalization, an inadequate&#13;
accounting system, deficient communication and payment systems, a lack of adequate banking skills at&#13;
all operational levels, and the ill effects of the directed credit policy followed in the past which is&#13;
reflected in the poor quality of the banks' loan portfolios. The adverse economic conditions of the past&#13;
few years have led to a further deterioration in banks' portfolios and exacerbated their problems.&#13;
4.  Because of the systemic deficiencies in the financial system, the formal financial sector in the Kyrgyz&#13;
Republic has not been an effective vehicle for mobilizing financial resources and allocating these to their&#13;
most efficient uses. The M2/GDP ratio at 12% indicates the low level of savings and financial&#13;
intermediation. Incentives for financial savings by the private sector have been undermined by lack of&#13;
confidence in the financial system and, until recently, by substantially negative real interest rates. Despite&#13;
these disincentives however, the private sector has been generating (small) positive savings while the&#13;
Government at large, including state-owned enterprises, has been the biggest dissaver (i.e., overall net&#13;
borrower).&#13;
5.  An efficient financial sector, with an effective banking system at its core, is essential to support and&#13;
foster the Kyrgyz Republic's stabilization and structural adjustment efforts. The Government's objective&#13;
is to develop and deepen the financial system, restore public confidence, and to establish, over the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
medium term, an efficient system of resource mobilization and allocation which would become&#13;
increasingly more liberal and market-oriented and offer a greater variety of instruments to both borrowers&#13;
and savers.&#13;
6. The reforms required to achieve these longer-term goals will need to be phased over a number of&#13;
years, given the emerging nature of key financial institutions in the Kyrgyz Republic and the limited&#13;
implementation capacity of the country. Immediate reforms required to facilitate the deepening and&#13;
diversification of the financial system include: refining the enabling policy and regulatory environment;&#13;
resolving the problems engendered by the insolvency of the country's four largest commercial banks, the&#13;
most pressing of which is the poor quality of these bank's portfolios; enhancing and developing skills&#13;
in the banking sector and, more specifically, strengthening the regulatory and supervisory capabilities&#13;
within the NBK; and fostering development of nascent non-bank financial institutions. The growth and&#13;
viability of the financial system also depends heavily on the growth and viability of the real sectors. The&#13;
types of financial services and products needed by the real sectors, and the availability of bankable&#13;
opportunities in the economy as a whole, will largely determine the growth of financial services in the&#13;
future.&#13;
7.  A number of multilateral and bilateral organizations have already provided technical assistance in&#13;
several areas. These include: drafting banking and securities laws; preparing a new Chart of Accounts;&#13;
assistance to NBK in bank supervision, monetary analysis, and the reorganization of its Cash and Foreign&#13;
departments; assistance to commercial banks in accounting, operational policies and procedures, credit&#13;
investigation and appraisal, trade financing and the development of a credit reporting system; automation&#13;
of the clearing house; and "specialized" audits of the four largest commercial banks by international&#13;
auditors. While this partial assistance has been useful, a more coordinated and comprehensive approach&#13;
is required.&#13;
8.  The principal objectives of the Reform Program to be supported by the proposed FINSAC are: (i)&#13;
to improve the enabling policy and regulatory environment for the development of a sound, competitive&#13;
and market-oriented banking system, by eliminating policy-induced barriers to competition, efficiency and&#13;
profitability and by strengthening prudential laws and regulations, accounting and auditing, and payments&#13;
and settlements systems; (ii) to liquidate or restructure the four dominant insolvent specialized banks, and&#13;
assist with the establishment of a competitive and efficient private banking system which is both sound&#13;
and capable of providing a broader range of financial services to borrowers and savers; (iii) to help&#13;
collect part of the non-performing loans extended by these banks, and thus accelerate enterprise&#13;
restructuring or liquidation in the process; and, (iv) to promote the development and growth of emerging&#13;
non-bank financial institutions.&#13;
PART II. THE PROJECT&#13;
Project Objectives and Description&#13;
9. The objective of the Technical Assistance Program (TAP) is to facilitate the implementation of the&#13;
policy and institutional reforms envisaged under FINSAC by strengthening the capabilities of the key&#13;
financial and regulatory institutions, assisting in the establishment of new, temporary institutions that will&#13;
effect the restructuring/liquidation of major banks, extending the new accounting infrastructure, and&#13;
training bank personnel.&#13;
10. Implementation of the reform program envisaged under FINSAC would require massive technical&#13;
assistance from abroad as the local capacity for carrying out these reforms is limited due to lack of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
exposure of the Kyrgyz authorities to a market oriented sector. Assistance available to the Kyrgyz&#13;
Republic from other donors is limited. Without IDA funding for the programs and activities not covered&#13;
by other donors, it would not be possible to transform the sector into a well-functioning and efficient&#13;
financial system capable of meeting the evolving requirements of a market-oriented economy. The main&#13;
institutions and areas which will receive technical assistance under the TAP are described below.&#13;
11. Proposed Technical Assistance. The proposed technical assistance program was designed after a&#13;
comprehensive review of the overall needs of the sector. It identifies key areas which are important for&#13;
this initial stage in the development of a healthy financial sector. The major areas requiring assistance&#13;
under the proposed TAP are described below.&#13;
Assistance to the National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic&#13;
12. The National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic has appropriately been the major beneficiary of recent&#13;
technical assistance from bilateral and international donors, but further strengthening in several areas is&#13;
needed. The following areas have been identified for additional assistance under the proposed FINSAC-&#13;
supported reform program.&#13;
(a)   Overall reform of the Financial Sector. The Chairman (Governor) of NBK needs the&#13;
services of a Senior Bank Adviser to: (i) assist with the implementation and coordination of the&#13;
FINSAC reform program, which is wide-ranging and would need expert monitoring of progress;&#13;
and (ii) advise NBK management on policy and operational issues, as they evolve during the course&#13;
of program implementation. Initially, the adviser will be funded by the Project Preparation Facility&#13;
to assist the Chairman in carrying out some preparatory work for the Financial Sector Reform&#13;
Project. When PPF funding for this assignment ends, this credit will provide the financing for its&#13;
continuation.&#13;
(b)   Bank Supervision. Although the Bank Supervision Department of NBK, given the short&#13;
period of its operation, is performing very well, its skills in both on-site examination and off-site&#13;
monitoring need to be further strengthened. While a US AID-funded adviser is presently assisting&#13;
the Department, it is important to provide the department with an adviser with extensive bank&#13;
examination experience for another 12-18 months, particularly to train on-site supervision staff on&#13;
the job, by guiding examiner teams through some actual examinations, and to monitor the problem&#13;
banks.&#13;
(c)   Implementation of the new chart of accounts. The new chart of accounts, consistent with&#13;
international practice, is about to be completed. Associated accounting rules and procedures are&#13;
being developed, along with software, to permit parallel runs between the old and new accounts.&#13;
NBK would need the services of two specialists to implement the new chart of accounts, prepare&#13;
new reporting formats and standards, manuals for practitioners, pilot tests and staff training. Similar&#13;
assistance would later be needed by all other banks. The NBK could make the services of these&#13;
specialists available to other banks, as needed.&#13;
(d)   Bank restructuring and liquidation. NBK needs the services of a bank adviser with&#13;
experience in branch systems to (i) complete the analysis of the branch network of the&#13;
Agroprombank which has been initiated by an international consulting firm and (ii) assist in the&#13;
rationalization, merger, and preparation for sale of selected branches of this bank. Later, the&#13;
consultant would advise NBK on branch rationalization issues in other banks, including Elbank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4 -&#13;
(e)   Payment and clearing systems. The current payment and clearing systems in the Kyrgyz&#13;
Republic are inefficient, cumbersome and inappropriate for a modem banking system. Both&#13;
immediate and long-term improvements are needed to reduce inter-enterprise arrears, facilitate&#13;
liquidity management, minimize the float in the system by requiring banks to maintain lesser&#13;
settlement reserves, promote cross-border flows, and instill confidence in the banking system. A&#13;
number of initiatives have been taken during the last few years, on an interim basis, to reform the&#13;
payment system. These include various studies performed by the IMF, EBRD, Bank of Japan, and&#13;
the Japanese International Cooperation Agency (JICA). Some of the refinements recommended in&#13;
these studies have been or are being introduced, while a large number still remain to be&#13;
implemented. The JICA-financed specialists have recomrmended both short-term improvements as&#13;
well as a detailed long-term feasibility and functionality study of the payment system. The total cost&#13;
estimates, including hardware and application software, however, are still the subject of discussion&#13;
between the Kyrgyz Government and the Japanese authorities, but it is understood that most of the&#13;
expertise and equipment, software etc. will be financed by the Japanese authorities.&#13;
(f)   Mortgage financing. At present, facilities for mortgage financing in the Kyrgyz Republic&#13;
are virtually non-existent. The NBK needs the services of a consultant to study the situation and&#13;
identify opportunities for creating mechanisms for mortgage financing.&#13;
(g)   Financial legislation. NBK also needs the services of a lawyer for a short period to assist&#13;
with the finalization of various financial legislation.&#13;
Bank Restructuring and Liquidation&#13;
13. Under the proposed reform program, Elbank and Agroprombank are slated for liquidation. NBK&#13;
has already applied to a court for Elbank's liquidation and is working out a scheme to pay off household&#13;
deposits. The position of Agroprombank is somewhat different. While it is also insolvent and will be&#13;
liquidated, it has a network of 52 branches, which in the past provided rural finance and otherwise acted&#13;
as Government agents for subsidy payments.  NBK and the government are keen that, before&#13;
Agroprombank's liquidation, a specialist in branch systems advise NBK on the rationalization and&#13;
disposition of its branch network with particular attention given to possibly using some of them to provide&#13;
services to rural communities.&#13;
14. Two other large banks, Promstroi Bank and AKB Kyrgyzstan Bank, which are also in financial&#13;
difficulties, are in the process of being recapitalized. They have been advised to increase capital from&#13;
"negative" to "positive", or at least to "zero" level by March 31, 1997. If they are unable to achieve&#13;
this, they will be liquidated. These banks urgently need an adviser to provide policy and operational&#13;
advice to management on credit policies, advice on financial restructuring and help to attract domestic&#13;
and/or foreign investors.&#13;
Debt Recovery and Resolution&#13;
15. As an integral part of the financial sector reform progran, the NBK has established Debt Resolution&#13;
Agency (DEBRA) as an agency under its control to act as receiver on its behalf, to take over, and to&#13;
dispose of the assets and liabilities of banks. It will also have a Debt Recovery Unit that will take title&#13;
and control of the non-performing loan portfolios of the insolvent banks with a view to seeking their&#13;
recovery and ultimate resolution. Initially, DEBRA will handle the liquidation of Agroprombank and&#13;
Elbank, but during its tenure it may be called upon to manage the liquidation of other banks which&#13;
encounter difficulties in the new market environment. DEBRA will need the services of two experts for&#13;
at least two years each for the following tasks: (i) to help organize DEBRA, establish its operating&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
procedures, and to manage the asset sales and liquidation process; and (ii) to coordinate work-out teams&#13;
and manage the recovery of outstanding balances in the non-performing loan portfolios of the intervened&#13;
banks.&#13;
Central Registry for Pledges&#13;
16. In order to implement the Law on Pledge which will be submitted to Parliament in 1996, a central&#13;
registry for pledges will be established within the Ministry of Justice. Eventually, this registry will be&#13;
extended to the district level to ensure national coverage. To aid the Ministry of Justice in this effort,&#13;
the provision of computer hardware, software and training is envisaged.&#13;
Training&#13;
17. Among the many challenges the Kyrgyz commercial banks face are the. switching over to modem&#13;
banking practices and methods and the upgrading of the skills of their staff. At present, technical skills&#13;
in most areas of modem banking either do not exist or are thinly distributed. The areas where skill&#13;
upgrading is most needed include, inter alia, strategic planning, credit analysis and risk management,&#13;
international trade finance, asset and liability management and the new legal environment which will&#13;
govern banking operations. Over the last four years, sporadic training efforts have been made by the&#13;
Kyrgyz banks by deputing their staff to foreign banks and to regional training centers in Almaty and&#13;
Tashkent. These arrangements are inadequate to meet the training needs of the nearly 4,000 commercial&#13;
bank staff in the country. There is a need for a Bankers' Training Institute in Bishkek to conduct courses&#13;
on a regular basis in various areas of interest to banks. Establishing an institute will require the&#13;
commitment of and regular funding from NBK and the commercial banks in the country. To start with,&#13;
technical assistance would be necessary to organize the Institute, develop curricula, establish a library,&#13;
provide equipment and teaching materials, and provide short-term consultants to run specialized courses&#13;
and train local trainers. The proposed institute would require the services of: (i) a commercial banker&#13;
experienced in training for about one year; (ii) short-term consultants to conduct courses over the next&#13;
two years; and (iii) two full-time teachers specialized in Business legislation of "Civil Code tradition"&#13;
countries, to provide training to lawyers in the new laws on corporation, banking, bankruptcy, pledge,&#13;
mortgages, etc.. To assist in the training of lawyers, a database containing a comprehensive collection&#13;
of all legal, official texts and major case law will be created. A principal objective of this database&#13;
system is to disseminate this information collection nationwide via a computer "station" network, with&#13;
hard copy back-ups available. Two legal publishers exist with the capability to provide this back-up.&#13;
Non-bank Financial Institutions (NBFIs)&#13;
18. While the State Agency for Securities has been given substantial responsibilities for regulating and&#13;
supervising capital markets and NBFIs, it still lacks adequate authority, technical capacity, personnel,&#13;
training facilities, equipment and budget. Under the reform program, SAS would be transformed into&#13;
the executive arm of the proposed Securities Commission, with adequate resources and authority for the&#13;
enforcement of securities law and regulations. In addition, the SAS would undertake supervisory&#13;
responsibility for investment funds, which are currently under the purview of the State Property Fund.&#13;
Under the proposed reform program, new laws on insurance companies and pension funds are envisaged.&#13;
With these developments, SAS will acquire considerable regulatory responsibilities for the execution of&#13;
which it needs to develop capability now. For these purposes, SAS will need: (a) an adviser to provide&#13;
guidance and training to enhance its implementation and enforcement capabilities; and (b) an adviser to&#13;
review existing pension fund schemes and to design new schemes for government consideration. The&#13;
Ministry of Finance, as the leading arm of the government responsible for non-bank financial institutions&#13;
(NBFIs), would need the services of: (a) two advisers, one to advise on the overall development of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6 -&#13;
NBFIs, with special emphasis on the securities market, the other to provide guidance in developing a&#13;
market for insurance services; and (b) a lawyer to assist in the drafting of new legislation on insurance&#13;
and pension funds and to improve existing legislation on leasing.&#13;
Public Debt Instruments and Securities&#13;
19. In addition to assistance in developing NBFIs and capital markets, the government needs assistance&#13;
in developing its own capabilities in the areas of public debt instruments and government securities. The&#13;
credit will finance an adviser to the MOF who will provide advice, guidance and policy strategies for the&#13;
development and deepening of government debt instruments and securities in the Kyrgyz Republic.&#13;
Rural Finance&#13;
20. Draft legislation/regulations for the development of rural credit unions and cooperatives wil be&#13;
needed very soon. This would require the services of an experienced lawyer for the MOF/Ministry of&#13;
Agriculture.&#13;
Project Costs&#13;
21. The project is estimated to cost US$7.34 million, of which US$7.26 million would be in foreign&#13;
currency and the equivalent of US$0.08 million in local currency. Total project costs include those&#13;
associated with IDA, other donor financing, and local costs. Costs include the services of advisers,&#13;
consultants, equipment, software, support and counterpart staff, books and ancillary supplies. IDA and&#13;
other donor agencies would finance 100 percent of the foreign exchange costs. Local costs would be in&#13;
the form of support services and seconded staff and would be provided by the beneficiary agencies. The&#13;
Project Preparation Facility (PPF) of US$0.07 million would be re-financed under the proposed TA&#13;
project. Detailed project costs are provided as Attachment 1 in Annex I.&#13;
Financing Plan&#13;
22. Total project costs of US$7.34 million would be financed as follows: IDA US$3.4 million; other&#13;
donors (Japan, USAID, TACIS, Finland, ADB, and TICA) US$3.86 million; and local institutions and&#13;
government US$0.08 million. A detailed financing plan is provided as Attachment 2 in Annex I.&#13;
PART III. PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
Project Implementation&#13;
23. NBK has established a FINSAC Monitoring Unit (FMU) which will have responsibility for&#13;
monitoring implementation of policy reforms under FINSAC and for managing and administering the&#13;
TAP. This will be headed by a senior NBK official; the Senior Bank Adviser (SBA) to the Chairman&#13;
of NBK will work closely with this unit and, with authorization from the Chairman, will coordinate the&#13;
work of the various experts appointed under TAP and also other technical assistance activities in the&#13;
financial sector, and submit periodic progress reports to the Chairman and, through him, to IDA on&#13;
implementation of the Reform Program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7 -&#13;
Procurement&#13;
24. All procurement, within the framework of FINSAC TA Programn, will be carried out by FMU, but&#13;
disbursement of IDA funds will be administered through the PMU, already established in the Ministry&#13;
of Finance under the PESAC and utilized by APEAC operations. Procurement of all goods and services&#13;
would follow World Bank guidelines (Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and Credits,&#13;
published by the Bank in January 1995, and revised in January 1996). Selection of consultants for&#13;
Technical Assistance would follow World Bank guidelines (Use of Consultants by Bank Borrowers and&#13;
by the Bank as Executing Agency, August 1981). Most goods are expected to cost less than $100,000&#13;
and will be procured following International Shopping. Equipment expected to cost less than US$50,000&#13;
will be procured following local shopping. Equipment purchases are expected to include computers,&#13;
software, fax machines, phones, photocopiers and other office-related equipment. Consultants will be&#13;
selected from short-listed candidates acceptable to the Bank and based on review of qualifications and past&#13;
performance. All documents relating to selection of consultants will be subject to prior review of the&#13;
Bank. Preparatory activities financed under the PPF include assistance on agreed upon steps required&#13;
before Board Presentation, including advice on the initiation of bank liquidation and restructuring&#13;
procedures, the establishment of a debt resolution agency (DEBRA), and coordination and policy advice&#13;
to the Chairman of the NBK. The Summary of Proposed Procurement Arrangements is presented as&#13;
Attachment 3 in Annex I.&#13;
Disbursement&#13;
25. The disbursement of IDA funds will be administered through the Project Management Unit (PMU)&#13;
already established in the MOF under PESAC and utilized by the APEAC operations. It will monitor&#13;
and control the proposed use of IDA funds. The estimated schedule of disbursements is given in&#13;
Attachment 3 of Annex I. Disbursements are expected to be completed within four years from the date&#13;
of effectiveness.&#13;
26. The project would finance the following categories of expenditures:&#13;
Category           |   Amount          Percentage of Expenditures To Be&#13;
(US Dollars)                Financed&#13;
100% of foreign expenditures; 100% of&#13;
local expenditures (ex-factory cost) and&#13;
1. Goods                        1,529,000    95% of local expenditures for other items&#13;
procured locally.&#13;
2.  Consultants' Services       1,170,000     100%&#13;
3.  Refunding of Project         700000&#13;
Preparation Advance&#13;
[          TOTAL                 3,399,000&#13;
27. Special Account. To facilitate timely project implementation, the Borrower would establish,&#13;
maintain and operate, under conditions acceptable to the Bank, a Special Account in US dollars in a bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8 -&#13;
During the early stage of the project, the initial allocation of the Special Account would be limited to&#13;
US$250,000. However, when the aggregate disbursement under the Credit has reached the level of SDR&#13;
1.0 million, the initial allocation may be increased up to the authorized allocation of US$500,000 by&#13;
submitting the relevant Application for Withdrawal. Replenishment applications should be submitted at&#13;
least every three months, and must include reconciled bank statements as well as other appropriate&#13;
supporting documents.&#13;
28. Statement of Expenditures (SOEs).  Disbursements would be made against Statement of&#13;
Expenditures for contracts for goods and services up to US$100,000 equivalent for which detailed&#13;
documents evidencing expenditures will be reviewed by the Project Management Unit (PMU) and made&#13;
available for the required audit as well as to Bank supervision missions. Disbursements against contracts&#13;
for goods and services exceeding US$100,000 equivalent would be made against normal documentation.&#13;
29. The project completion date would be June 30, 2001.&#13;
Project Accounting, Financial Reporting and Auditing&#13;
30. Accounting. The PMU would be responsible for the appropriate accounting of the funds provided&#13;
by IDA under the Credit, for reporting on the use of these funds and for ensuring timely submission of&#13;
audits of the financial statements or reports to IDA.&#13;
31. The PMU would establish an accounting system to provide information on the proper receipt and&#13;
use of funds furnished in accordance with the Credit Agreement. Accounting for all Special Account&#13;
transactions and all other project accounts will be maintained in accordance with practices and standards&#13;
satisfactory to the Association, with the objective of timely and accurate accounting of all transactions&#13;
under the Credit.&#13;
32. Financial Reporting. Financial reporting for the Credit would comprise a statement of receipts and&#13;
payments for the reporting period from the beginning of the program. Reporting would be in accordance&#13;
with disbursements classified and reported under the expenditure categories agreed to by the Borrower&#13;
and specified in the Credit Agreement. The PMU would submit quarterly progress reports. A Project&#13;
Completion Report would be submitted to the Association by the PMU promptly after the conclusion of&#13;
project activity, and in any event not later than 6 months after the Credit closing date.&#13;
33. Auditing. A condition of the Credit would be that the financial statements and reports on the&#13;
proceeds are audited in accordance with internationally accepted standards by independent auditors&#13;
acceptable to the Association.&#13;
PART IV. BENEFITS AND RISKS&#13;
Benefits&#13;
34. The project would provide financing for critically needed technical assistance to implement the&#13;
reforms in the financial sector as part of the Kyrgyz Republic's stabilization and structural adjustment&#13;
efforts. It would help the evolution of a healthy and efficient financial sector through refining the&#13;
enabling policy and regulatory environment, resolving the problems of the country's four financially-&#13;
troubled/insolvent commercial banks, developing and enhancing skills in the banking sector, and&#13;
strengthening the supervisory and regulatory capabilities of the central bank. While these reforms will&#13;
be phased over a number of years, their immediate impact would be the restoration of public confidence&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
in the system and a laying of the groundwork for an efficient system of resource mobilization and&#13;
allocation.&#13;
Risks&#13;
35. The major project risks relate to timely availability of well qualified and experienced technical&#13;
assistance personnel to launch the ambitious reform program, particularly within the budget allocations.&#13;
Another risk is the absorptive capacity of the concerned Kyrgyz institutions and the ability of the&#13;
counterparts to carry on the reform program after the expatriates have left. These concerns are mitigated&#13;
by the fact that the government is highly committed to carrying out structural and sectoral reforms and&#13;
IDA's experience of project implementation in the country has been very good.&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
May 31, 1996&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX I&#13;
DETAILED COST AND FINANCING TABLES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-                                              Attachment I&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Detailed Project Costs: 1996-1998&#13;
(U.S. Dol)&#13;
Foreip&#13;
Tot                   Odthr.                       Cot a   Capo-&#13;
FOREIGN FINANCING           Foreig      IDA        Donor    Local                % Of   et U&#13;
oet Cepopast                                       (1996-1991)          F_ing   F         g     F      g  Costs Total Coss  Total   of Total&#13;
1996      1997      1998&#13;
1. Overall Reforr of F-in Il Sector&#13;
a. SeniorAdvisertoNBK                                87,000               87,000     87,000              4,350     91,350     95%      1.2&#13;
b. Financial Legislation                   75,000                        75,000      75,000              3,750     78,750     95%      1.1&#13;
Bak R      euucti  and LUWdaton&#13;
a. Reorganization Adviser to NBK                     70,000              70,000      70,000              3,500     73,500     95%      1.0%&#13;
b. Adviser to AKB Kyrg and Promstroi      100,000                        100,000    100,000              5,000    105,000&#13;
. Debt Recovery and Resoudion&#13;
a. Asd sales and fiquidation specialist            185,000   180,000    365,000    365,000              18,250    383,250     95%      5.2%&#13;
b. Loan Workout Specialist                         100,000   100,000    200,000    200,000              10,000    210,000&#13;
. Bank S&#13;
a. Bank Exaniner                                    92,000               92,000                  92,000            92,000    100%      1.3%&#13;
S. Trahn&#13;
a. Bankers' Training Institute            230,000  210,000    97,000    537,000                 537,000           537,000    100%      7.3&#13;
b. Lawyer's Training                      100,000  200,000              300,000                300,000            300,000              4.1%&#13;
c. Legal Infornation Sytem                         120,000               120,000    120,000              6,000    126,000              1.7%&#13;
. Impkmtgatlo  of Chart of Accts&#13;
a. Accounting Specialists                          224,000   210,000    434,000                434,000            434,000    100%      5.9%&#13;
7. Ceal Registry for Pledges                  350,000                       350,000    350,000              17,500    367,500     95%      5.0%&#13;
. Payment ad Clearing System&#13;
a. Redesign Clearnce &amp; Payment Systen    2,965,000                     2,965,000   1,000,000   1,965,000        2,965,000    100%    40.4%&#13;
. Mortgage Fbiacing&#13;
a. Mortgage Specialist                    100,000                       100,000                 100,000           100,000    100%      1.4&#13;
110. Non-Bak Finasadal  ,iutions&#13;
a. Securities Market                                200,000  100,000    300,000                300,000            300,000    100%      4.1%&#13;
b. Investment Funds                                  60,000              60,000      60,000              3,000     63,000     95%      0.9%&#13;
c. Insrnce Services                        60,000                        60,000      60,000              3,000     63,000     95%      0.9%&#13;
d. Pension Funds                           60,000                        60,000                 60,000             60,000    100%      0.8&#13;
11. Pube  Debt Ilnstrnents &amp; Secartie         100,000                       100,000    100,000               5,000    105,000     95%      1.4&#13;
2. Rural Finance&#13;
a. Legal Framework                                   75,000              75,000                 75,000             75,000    100%      1.0&#13;
13. Sub-Total                               4,140,000  1,623,000  687,000  6,450,000   2,587,000   3,863,000 79,350  6,529,350    99%    88.9&#13;
14. Cotngsides (IDA-hmnded ony)#               66,750    31,100   14,000    111,850     111,850                       111,850    100%      1.5%&#13;
15. PFF Rdeflnang                            700,000                       700,000    700,000                        700,00    100%       9.5-&#13;
TOTAL PROJECT COSTS                        4,906,750  1,654,100  701,000  7 ,261,850   3, 398,850   3863,000  79,350 7,341,200    99%   100.0%&#13;
I   Contingencies calculated at approximately 5% of IDA-knded components.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 2&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Detailed Financing Plan: 1996-1998&#13;
(US Dollars)&#13;
IDA&#13;
Total            Total     IDA&#13;
Foreign   Local  Project    s % ef&#13;
Foreign                                    Cost    Cost    Cost       Totdl&#13;
FIN-           TACIS/          JAPAN  JAPAN   IFC/&#13;
Fancing Components                       IDA    LAND  TACIS  TICA   USAID GRANT CREDIT  TICA   ADB&#13;
Overail Reform of Fiancial Sector&#13;
a. Senior Adviser to NBK               87,000                                                                    87,000    4,350   91,350       95%&#13;
b. Financial Legislation               75,000                                                                    75,000    3,750   78,750       95%&#13;
Bank Restructuring and Liquidation&#13;
a. Reorganization Adviser to NBK       70,000                                                                    70,000    3,500   73,500       95%&#13;
b. Adviser to AKB Kyrg. and Promstroi    100,000                                                                100,000    5,000  105,000       95%        _&#13;
Debt Recovery and Resoltion&#13;
a. Asset Sales and Liquidation Specialist    365,000                                                            365,000   18,250  383,250       95%&#13;
b. Loan Workout Specialist            200,000                                                                   200,000   10.000  210,000       95%&#13;
Banlk Superison&#13;
a. Bank Examiner                               92,000                                                            92,000             92,000       0%&#13;
5. TraInig&#13;
a. Bankcrs' Training instiu                           537,000                                                   537,000            537,000       0%&#13;
b. Lawyer's Training                                           300,000                                          300,000            300,000       0%&#13;
c. Legal Information System           120,000                                                                   120,000    6,000  126,000       95%&#13;
Iinplemebtaio of New Chart of Acets&#13;
a. Ancuming Speialist                                                 434,000                                   434,000            434,000       0%&#13;
7. Cenl Registry for Fe4e                 350,000                                                                   350,000   17,500  367,500       95%&#13;
Paymnt ad Claring Syste&#13;
a. Redesign Ckarance &amp; Paymeus System  1,000,000                               465,000 1,500,000               2,965,000         2,965,000      34%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Atachment 2&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Detailed Financng Plan: 1996-1998&#13;
(US Dollars)&#13;
Total           Total     ,md&#13;
Fore|n   Loc    Projet T     % |t&#13;
Forelpn                                    Cost    Cost    cost      Total&#13;
FIN-          TACIS/          JAPAN  JAPAN   IFC/&#13;
cing Components                      IDA    LAND  TACIS  TICA  USAID GRANT CREDIT  TICA   ADB&#13;
Mortgage Financing&#13;
a. Mortgage Specialist                                                                         100,000         100,000           100,000       0%&#13;
0. Non-Bank FbIancIal Intitutions&#13;
a. Securiies Madcet                                                  300,000                                  300,000           300,000        0%&#13;
b. InvestmentFunlds                    60,000                                                                  60,000    3,000   63,000       95X&#13;
c. Inmurae Services                    60,000                                                                  60,000    3,000   63,000       95%&#13;
d. Pension Funds                                      60,000                                                   60,000            60,000        0%&#13;
1. Publc Debt Instrments and SecurWies    100,000                                                                100,000    5,000  105,000      95%&#13;
1 Rnral Finance&#13;
a. Legal Framework                                                                                     75,000   75,000           75,000        0%&#13;
1  Sub-Total                         2,587,000  92,000 597,000 300,000 734,000 465,000 1,500,000 100,000 75,000 6,450,000  79,350 6,529,350    40%&#13;
4. Contingencies (IDA-funded only)#     111,850                                                                   111,850          111,850      100%&#13;
S. PPF Refiuacin                        700,000                                                                   700,000          700,000      100%&#13;
TALPROJECT FINANCING                 3,398,850  92,000 597.000 300,000 734,000 465,000 1,500,000 100,000 75,000 7,261,850  79,350 7,341,200    46%&#13;
I Contingencies calculated at approximately 5% of IDA-funded components.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Attachment 3&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Summary of Proposed Procurement Arrangements for IDA&#13;
US$ (000)&#13;
Procurement&#13;
l_________________________________________ j ___Method                                      l&#13;
Project Element                               IS/NS            Other       |    Total&#13;
GQQ_&#13;
Computers and related Office Eqpt               1529                             1529&#13;
(1529)                           (1529)&#13;
Consultancies. Other Technical Assistance                             1170           1170&#13;
(1170)        (1170)&#13;
Miscellaneous&#13;
PPF                                                                 700            700&#13;
(700)          (700)&#13;
Government Support+                                  79                                79&#13;
TOI                                         1608              1870           3478&#13;
(1529)            (1870)         (3399)&#13;
Note: Figures in parentheses are the respective amounts Jinanced by the IDA credit.&#13;
+ Government Support includes staff support, office rental and misceclaneous expenses.&#13;
NS: National Shopping&#13;
IS: Internadonal Shopping&#13;
Estimated IDA Disbursements&#13;
on a Fiscal Year Basis&#13;
(US$ 000)&#13;
FY1997                FY1998          FY1999               FY2000&#13;
Annual                       700                  1689             910                 100&#13;
Cumulative                   700                  2389            3299                3399&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX II&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
SENIOR (CiFiEF) BANK ADVISER TO CHAIRMAN, NATIONAL BANK OF KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCE&#13;
Background&#13;
1.           The Kyrgyz Republic has embarked on a comprehensive reform program to transform&#13;
its centrally planned economy to a market economy. As a part of this program, the government is keen&#13;
to develop a modern and efficient financial sector, fashioned along the lines of financial systems in the&#13;
leading market economies, that will support the continuing transformation.&#13;
2.           The Kyrgyz financial sector consists of the National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic (NBK),&#13;
the central bank; 19 commercial banks (including four large banks which have serious portfolio&#13;
problems); the State Insurance Company and a host of small insurance companies which mushroomed in&#13;
1992-93, mostly to cater to some very specific insurance needs; the State Pension Fund; and a number&#13;
of Investment Funds, recently established to participate in the Privatization Program. The commercial&#13;
banking system dominates the financial sector.&#13;
3.           Technical assistance for the modernization of the financial sector has so far been provided&#13;
by a number of multilateral and bilateral institutions. While this assistance has been very useful, it has&#13;
been sporadic and covers only a few areas. The financial sector reform program (attached) being&#13;
supported under the proposed IDA credit (FINSAC) takes a more comprehensive view of the reforms still&#13;
needed.&#13;
4.           NBK, the central bank, which will have responsibility for implementing the reforms under&#13;
FINSAC, is interested in appointing a Senior (Chief) Bank Adviser to the Chairman (Governor) to advise&#13;
him on broad policy matters, assist him to coordinate the work of foreign experts presently assisting the&#13;
sector, and to monitor progress of reforms. The adviser will work in close cooperation with NBK's&#13;
Department for Reorganization of the Financial System of the Kyrgyz Republic and the Directorate for&#13;
Investments and Coordination of Technical Assistance.&#13;
5.           The adviser will report directly to the Chairman of NBK and will be appointed initially&#13;
for a period of one year, with possibility of extension, subject to mutual agreement.&#13;
Duties and Responsibilities&#13;
6.           The Adviser, who will be resident in Bishkek, will have the following major&#13;
responsibilities:&#13;
a.    provide overall assistance to the FINSAC Monitoring Unit (FMU) to enable it to monitor&#13;
the implementation of reforms under FINSAC and manage and administer the Technical&#13;
Assistance Program for the Financial Sector;&#13;
b.    prioritize and pay particular attention to urgent issues and problems that may arise in the&#13;
course of implementation of the program;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
c.     provide program  coordination and, where necessary, make suggestions to other&#13;
beneficiaries of the technical assistance program with regard to performance of various&#13;
tasks in order to ensure compliance with the program schedule and strategy;&#13;
d.    provide liaison between NBK and the international and bilateral organizations involved&#13;
in the reorganization of the banking and financial sectors of the Kyrgyz Republic;&#13;
e.    in cooperation with foreign consultants performing special assignments at other Kyrgyz&#13;
institutions and banks, monitor compliance with all requirements set down within the&#13;
framework of the FINSAC program;&#13;
f.     analyze recommendations made by foreign consultants and submit more concrete&#13;
proposals and recommendations for consideration of NBK management;&#13;
g.    review and analyze the technical assistance activities currently in progress in the banking&#13;
and financial sectors of the Kyrgyz Republic, evaluate their effectiveness and determine&#13;
requirements and priorities for further technical assistance;&#13;
h.    hold periodic meetings with foreign consultants working in the banking and financial&#13;
sectors with a view to avoiding duplication of effort, improving efficiency with which&#13;
tasks are carried out and developing a clearly defined strategy for the reorganization of&#13;
the sectors;&#13;
i.    meet periodically with top officials of commercial banks, ministries and involved agencies&#13;
in order to inform them about progress of consultants' work, results achieved,&#13;
effectiveness of the program and any problems encountered by consultants in the course&#13;
of their work;&#13;
j.     monitor overall adherence to work schedules and time frames, with assistance from local&#13;
personnel, and assist in drafting of work plans for newly arrived foreign consultants;&#13;
k.    provide policy advice to the Chairman, NBK, on matters pertaining to the financial&#13;
sector;&#13;
1.    to submit periodic reports to the Chairman, NBK, and IDA on the progress of reforms&#13;
under FINSAC and on the progress of the technical assistance program; the initial report&#13;
will be submitted within four weeks of his appointment and bi-monthly thereafter, by the&#13;
10th of the following month, in both English and Russian; and&#13;
M.    ensure that all procurement made under the IDA credit are in accordance with the IDA&#13;
procurement guidelines.&#13;
Qualifications&#13;
7.            The Adviser should possess a degree in Economics, Finance, or Accounting and have at&#13;
least 20 years experience in management positions in a major international bank or in a central bank in&#13;
a country having a strong and diversified financial sector. He/she could be on loan from the respective&#13;
institution or be a retired banker. He/she could also be provided by international bank management&#13;
consultancy organizations. Knowledge of Russian would be an advantage. The Adviser should be used&#13;
to working in an international environment.&#13;
Contract Arrangements&#13;
8.           The NBK is responsible for providing a personal computer, appropriate software, and&#13;
priority use of office equipment (printer, photocopier, fax, etc.) all of which are expected to be purchased&#13;
by the beneficiary out of the Project Preparation Facility. The NBK will also provide a bilingual&#13;
secretary, desk and office space, assistance in finding appropriate housing, administrative assistance in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
obtaining visas, customs clearance and any other administrative permits required by the consultant in the&#13;
performance of the assignment.&#13;
9.           The consultant contract will cover fees, including overhead, travel, accommodation and&#13;
other living expenses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
LEGAL ADVISER TO THE NATIONAL BANK OF THE KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCE&#13;
Background&#13;
1.           The transition from a command economy to a market economy requires considerable&#13;
changes in the legal framework. A number of important legal reforms have already been initiated with&#13;
a view to providing an adequate framework for ensuring sustained banking soundness and business&#13;
stability over the long term.&#13;
2.           The authorities are actively pursuing this process. A new Civil Code has just been&#13;
approved by the Parliament in spring 1996. A draft Bankruptcy Law, a draft Law on Pledge, and a new&#13;
Banking Law are now under preparation or under discussion. These laws are crucial for the building of&#13;
a new legislative framework for banking activities.&#13;
3.           The legal technical assistance program on banking legislation described in the following&#13;
paragraphs will focus on all commercial and financial regulations which might have an impact on&#13;
commercial banking activities, especially on the leasing activity. The assistance described in these Terms&#13;
of Reference is a Legal Subcomponent of the Technical Assistance Component for Non-Banking Financial&#13;
Institutions, which is part of IDA's Financial Sector Technical Assistance Project. This subcomponent&#13;
is associated with the Financial Sector Adjustment Project (FINSAC) in the Kyrgyz Republic.&#13;
Objectives&#13;
4.           The main objective of this assistance is to help the Legal Department of the National Bank&#13;
of the Republic of Kyrgyz (NBK) in its participation in finalizing and implementing the new legal banking&#13;
framework. More specifically, it aims at supporting NBK efforts to: (i) propose the key elements of and&#13;
help to draft any legal instruments which may improve the use of leasing; (ii) deal with issues related to&#13;
the finalization and implementation of the draft Law on Pledge, and especially the conception of the new&#13;
Pledge Registry (this Registry, along with modern legal instruments for credit collateral, is essential for&#13;
the development of private commercial banking activity); (iii) finalize and implement, from NBK's side,&#13;
a revised Banking Law and a revised Bankruptcy Law that are to be enacted under the support of the IDA&#13;
FINSAC project; and (iv) propose whatever other legal instruments may prove necessary to build a&#13;
transparent, sound, and efficient banking sector.&#13;
Assistance Strategy&#13;
5.           The envisaged technical assistance program will be carried out by a lawyer (hereafter&#13;
referred to as "the Consultant") having high credentials and long experience in banking issues in CIS&#13;
countries and other transition economies. The Consultant shall have extensive experience with the legal&#13;
commercial and banking framework of countries following a Civil Code tradition. It is expected that the&#13;
selected lawyer will act as a short-term resident legal adviser.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
6.           The Consultant will coordinate his/her work closely with the consultants assigned to the&#13;
other legal subcomponents of the Technical Assistance Component under the same IDA Credit. In&#13;
particular, he will fully cooperate with the Legal Adviser assigned to the Ministry of Finance. The&#13;
Consultant will further liaise, as appropriate, with other assistance teams from other donors, such as&#13;
IBRD, TACIS (EC), USAID, the Asian Development Bank, etc.&#13;
7.           The resident expert will coordinate his/her work with Government bodies in charge of&#13;
the legislative process; develop contacts with academic and professional circles specializing in commercial&#13;
and banking legislation and with banking practitioners.&#13;
8.           This project will be implemented over a six-month period and is expected to start in July&#13;
1996.&#13;
Activities and Output&#13;
9.           According to the outline of the Technical Assistance Project described supra ,this technical&#13;
assistance subcomponent will involve the following activities:&#13;
*     Assist NBK in designing, drafting and discussing whatever legal instruments may be&#13;
necessary to improve the use of leasing; for this task, he/she may participate as an expert&#13;
in drafting meetings;&#13;
*     Review and comment on the present state of the legislation related to commercial banking&#13;
activities and the ongoing preparatory work on complementary legal measures taking&#13;
place in NBK and other Government entities, with special attention to the proposed draft&#13;
Laws on Pledge, Banking, and Bankruptcy; for this task, he/she may participate as an&#13;
expert in drafting meetings;&#13;
3     Take part in any legal work related to the implementation of these laws and propose&#13;
revisions and complements that seem to be required for the existing legal framework to&#13;
be fully consistent with the development of an efficient and sound banking sector;&#13;
3     Assist the Legal Department of NBK in designing a strategy for proposing legal reforms&#13;
to ensure the move towards a transparent, stable and efficient environment, favorable to&#13;
a sound private banking sector in a market economy.&#13;
10.   On all the aforementioned issues, the Consultant is expected to provide NBK with advice during&#13;
parliamentary debates adequate to maintain the consistency of the draft laws and in keeping with the&#13;
neutrality of a foreign expert.&#13;
Reporting&#13;
11.          The Consultant will submit an Inception Report within six weeks of commencing his/her&#13;
assignment, mainly with a view to outlining the planned work program in more detail, and recommending&#13;
changes--for approval by NBK and IDA--as appropriate in view of the initial findings and discussions.&#13;
This first report will also include the suggested work program for NBK's legislative activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
12.          At the end of month four, the Consultant will submit a quarterly Progress Report, in brief&#13;
informal style, on past and planned activities and detailed inputs, oni contributions to the project&#13;
objectives, and on problems encountered and remedies introduced or proposed. This Progress Report&#13;
will also contain updates on NBK's legal reform work program.&#13;
13.          At the end of the month six, the Consultant will submit a Final Report that reviews the&#13;
last two months as well as the entire year's activities. The Final Report will also propose a bank&#13;
legislation program for the next year, and make general recommendations on the conduct of bank&#13;
legislation reform. The reports will annex all formal written materials provided by the Consultant to the&#13;
Government/NBK. Moreover, the Consultant will submit at appropriate times other reports or legal&#13;
drafts. These outputs may be submitted jointly with the Progress Report if this does not entail delays.&#13;
All reports shall be submitted to NBK (three copies in Russian, one in English), and IDA (one in&#13;
Russian, two in English). On the Consultant's suggestion and with the approval of NBK, further copies&#13;
of reports will be provided to other executive, legislative and judicial organs as appropriate.&#13;
Consultant Qualifications&#13;
14.          The Consultant will have extensive experience in banking legislation. The Consultant&#13;
shall have high credentials and long experience in banking issues in CIS countries or other transition&#13;
economies. He or she shall have a good knowledge of and extensive experience with the legal commercial&#13;
and banking framework of countries following a Civil Code tradition.&#13;
15.          He or she should have a good sense of diplomatic interaction with various official&#13;
institutions, much initiative, and a pragmatic approach. He or she should have, if possible, at least basic&#13;
Russian language skills; fluent Russian would be highly desirable.&#13;
16.          The Consultant will be selected on the basis of his/her approach, methodology, time table,&#13;
and qualifications. He/she may only be replaced with the prior written approval by NBK and IDA.&#13;
Inputs&#13;
17.          The Consultant contract will cover:&#13;
*     fees, including overhead;&#13;
*     travel, accommodation, and living expenses;&#13;
*     project-related communication, report distribution, and office supplies;&#13;
*     office equipment (one personal computer with auxiliary equipment, one printer, and&#13;
facsimile machine) for the direct project-related use by the Consultant, to be turned over&#13;
to NBK upon project completion.&#13;
18.           NBK will make available to the Consultant:&#13;
*     assistance in the arrangement of housing, hotel rooms, visas, and travel;&#13;
*     bi-lingual Russian/English language secretarial support;&#13;
*      information including draft and final legal texts as requested by the Consultant and&#13;
required for carrying out his/her assignment;&#13;
*     adequately furnished office space with telephone facilities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
ADVISER ON BANK REORGANIZATION&#13;
TO THE NATIONAL BANK OF KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCE&#13;
Background&#13;
1.    As part of the financial sector reform program, the National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic, the&#13;
central bank, has been reviewing the performance of the four largest commercial banks in the country&#13;
(all of which have serious liquidity and loan portfolio problems) with a view to determining which banks&#13;
may have to be liquidated and which need restructuring In the case of Agroprombank, it has been&#13;
decided to liquidate it.&#13;
2.    Agroprombank was- established in 1991 as a joint stock company with 600 enterprises and 1000&#13;
individuals as shareholders. It has 52 branches and a total staff of 1,300. Until 1994, it was the&#13;
dominant lender to the agriculture sector, extending loans to farmers and farm enterprises through its&#13;
branch network, as directed by government decrees. It was also used by the Kyrgyz Treasury and the&#13;
Ministry of Agriculture to distribute various pension, salary, disability and social services payments to&#13;
the populace and make remittances of taxes to Bishkek. NBK examination has revealed that virtually the&#13;
entire loan portfolio of Agroprombank is non-performing and the bank is both unprofitable and insolvent.&#13;
After considering various options it has been decided that it should be liquidated.&#13;
3 .    Since the Agroprombank has an extensive network which was the conduit for providing rural&#13;
finance, NBK is desirous of considering various options regarding the rationalization of the branch&#13;
network at the time of its liquidation. It is possible that over time a number of key branches of the bank&#13;
will re-emerge as either new independent banks, rural credit unions, branches of existing banks, or local&#13;
offices for credit cooperatives. A team of international auditors is already reviewing this matter. NBK&#13;
now needs the services of an adviser for one year to carry out the following duties:&#13;
Duties and Responsibilities&#13;
a.    Taking into account the work done by the auditors, develop an in-depth study and profile&#13;
of each branch in the network, including size of branch, location, market niche, potential&#13;
profitability, and synergy with other branches in the network;&#13;
b.    Analyze each branch under the criteria stated above (paragraph 3) and develop a profile&#13;
of those branches which could be sold independently or in a group package based on a&#13;
logical market segment;&#13;
c.    Determine which branches should be closed down and which are necessary to continue&#13;
the government payments system; and&#13;
d.    Lead a working group in NBK to carry out the above tasks and assist the working group&#13;
in implementing NBK management decisions on the above and allied matters.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Qualifications&#13;
4.           The Adviser should possess a degree in Economics, Finance, law or Accounting and have&#13;
at least 1S years experience in management positions in a major international bank, preferably in Head&#13;
Office dealing with administration of branches, or in international bank management consultancy&#13;
organizations, with exposure to bank liquidation. He/she could be on loan from the respective institution&#13;
or be a retired banker. Knowledge of Russian would be an advantage. The Adviser should be used to&#13;
working in an international environment.&#13;
Contract Arrangements&#13;
5.           The NBK is responsible for providing a personal computer, appropriate software, and&#13;
priority use of office equipment (printer, photocopier, fax, etc.) all of which are expected to be purchased&#13;
by the beneficiary out of the Project Preparation Facility. The NBK will also provide a bilingual&#13;
secretary, desk and office space, assistance in finding appropriate housing, administrative assistance in&#13;
obtaiing visas, customs clearance and any other administrative permits required by the consultant in the&#13;
perfbrmance of the assignment.&#13;
6.           The consultant contract will cover fees, including overhead, travel, accommodation and&#13;
other living expenses.&#13;
7.           Prior to submission of TOR to prospective applicants, the Ministry of Finance, in&#13;
consultation with the IDA, will review the TOR and include such other details as duration of assignment,&#13;
counterparts, required qualifications, experience and background and language proficiency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCE&#13;
ADVISER TO AKB KYRGYZSTAN AND PROMSTROIBANK&#13;
Background&#13;
1.           An adviser is required for a 6 month period to assist the management of AKB Kyrgyzstan&#13;
and Promstroibank to raise capital from institutional investors. Reporting to the Governor of the National&#13;
Bank or his delegate, and to the Chairperson of each of the 2 banks, the consultant will work with the&#13;
banks' management teams to prepare them for the sale of an interest in each bank, to identify potential&#13;
investors, to market the banks and to assist in the negotiations with investors.&#13;
2.           The banking system in the Kyrgyz Republic currently consists of the National Bank of&#13;
the Kyrgyz Republic, three former state-owned banks (Agroprombank, AKB Kyrgyzstan and&#13;
Promstroibank) and 14 small, privately owned banks. Agroprombank, the nation's largest bank, is to be&#13;
liquidated and a fourth state-owned bank, Elbank, is currently being liquidated.&#13;
3.           AKB Kyrgyzstan and Promstroibank are both joint stock institutions formed from state&#13;
banks. AKB was formerly the Soviet Housing and Social Commodity Bank while Promstroi was the state&#13;
bank for industry and construction. These two banks have significant branch networks and with the&#13;
demise of Agroprombank and Elbank have the potential to be the largest banks in the restructured banking&#13;
system.&#13;
4.           Both banks made loans to state enterprises as directed by Government and, as a result of&#13;
this practice and poor management, have negative capital according to diagnostic audits recently&#13;
performed in accordance with International Accounting Standards. These audits indicate that AKB has&#13;
gross loans of about 213 million som and required provisions against these loans of 171 million som;&#13;
capital is a negative 160 million som, and 169 million som is required to bring capital to the required 8%&#13;
level. Promstroibank has gross loans of approximately 104 million som with required provisions of 50&#13;
million som; capital is a negative 15 million som and 24 million som is required to bring capital to the&#13;
8% required level.&#13;
5.           Both banks are operating under a letter of agreement with the National Bank of the&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic (NBK) under which they are to raise additional capital and meet all prudential&#13;
guidelines. Failure to achieve recapitalization will result in the liquidation of both banks. The diagnostic&#13;
audits have provided management of both banks with recommendations for improvement but management&#13;
needs assistance in setting a new course and in raising the required capital.&#13;
Duties and Responsibilities&#13;
6.           For each bank, the adviser is to: develop investment options; counsel management on the&#13;
implications of the options and on the process for seeking investment; prepare an information package;&#13;
market the bank to potential domestic and international investors; identify a short-list of investors; prepare&#13;
management to conduct negotiations with the potential investors; and provide assistance as appropriate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
during the negotiations. The minimum required result is that by the end of the assignment management&#13;
of both banks are prepared to enter negotiations with investors who have provided written evidence of&#13;
their financial capacity and their interest in investing in the banks.&#13;
7.           The consultant will spend about I month at the beginning of the assignment working with&#13;
bank management, with the remainder of the time divided between communicating with potential investors&#13;
and preparing management for negotiations with investors. The consultant's time and efforts will be&#13;
divided equally between the 2 banks, at least until such time as potential investors have been identified.&#13;
8.           The consultant will:&#13;
a.    become familiar with each bank and the banking environment by reviewing the findings&#13;
of the diagnostic audits, interviewing management, visiting branches and customers and&#13;
conducting research into the competitive situation;&#13;
b.    work with management to identify the strengths of each bank, suggest possible strategic&#13;
directions and develop criteria for determining eligible investors;&#13;
c.    propose alternative investment options and counsel management on the implications of&#13;
each option;&#13;
d.    prepare one or more information packages for each bank directed to international and&#13;
possibly domestic investors;&#13;
e.    identify potential investors from discussions with bank management, from his or her own&#13;
contacts and from discussions with the World Bank, IFC and EBRD;&#13;
f.    communicate with potential investors and prepare a short list of eligible investors who&#13;
have provided written evidence of a serious interest in investing in the banks;&#13;
g.    prepare management to enter negotiations with investors; and&#13;
h.    assist management with negotiations as appropriate.&#13;
Qualifications&#13;
9.           The consultant will have: extensive and senior level contacts within the banking&#13;
community in Europe, Central Asia and the CIS countries; demonstrated merchant banking experience;&#13;
proven experience in facilitating investments in banks by institutional investors; and the ability to motivate&#13;
and counsel bank management to prepare them for a period of considerable change.&#13;
Contract Arrangements&#13;
10.          The NBK is responsible for providing a personal computer, appropriate software, and&#13;
priority use of office equipment (printer, photocopier, fax, etc.) all of which are expected to be purchased&#13;
by the beneficiary out of the Project Preparation Facility. The NBK will also provide a bilingual&#13;
secretary, desk and office space, assistance in finding appropriate housing, administrative assistance in&#13;
obtaining visas, customs clearance and any other administrative permits required by the consultant in the&#13;
performance of the assignment.&#13;
11.          The consultant contract will cover fees, including overhead, travel, accommodation and&#13;
other living expenses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
12.          Prior to submission of TOR to prospective applicants, the Ministry of Finance, in&#13;
consultation with the IDA, will review the TOR and include such other details as duration of assignment,&#13;
counterparts, required qualifications, experience and background and language proficiency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Liquidation Adviser to Debt Resolution Agency (DEBRA)&#13;
Terms of Reference&#13;
Background&#13;
1.           The government of the Kyrgyz Republic has established the Debt Resolution Agency&#13;
(DEBRA) as a legal entity to act in the capacity of a receiver on behalf of the National Bank of the&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic (NBK), the central bank, to take control over and dispose of the assets and liabilities&#13;
of some of the former state-controlled commercial banks in the country. The banks so identified will&#13;
have been deemed insolvent by NBK and their assets, primarily non-performing loans (classified as&#13;
doubtful or loss by NBK), will be subject to resolution and ultimate disposition, while their liabilities,&#13;
primarily deposits, will be subject to scheduled payout programs.&#13;
2.            DEBRA's operations will be carried out through two principal units (a) the Receivership&#13;
Unit and (b) the Debt Recovery Unit. The Receivership Unit will, on behalf of NBK, take possession&#13;
of assets and liabilities of intervened banks and dispose of them in accordance with the insolvency&#13;
legislation. The Debt Recovery Unit will take title of and control over the non-performing loan portfolios&#13;
of these banks and establish a recovery and resolution strategy for each of the non-performing assets&#13;
under its control.&#13;
3.           DEBRA will be headed by a managing director, who will be assisted by two full time&#13;
foreign resident advisers having responsibility respectively for receivership and debt recovery functions.&#13;
The overall management will be entrusted to a board of directors, chaired by the Governor of NBK and&#13;
having representatives of the Ministry of Finance and NBK. All recommended courses of action with&#13;
regard to liquidation of assets and liabilities of intervened banks, and the resolution and disposition of&#13;
their non-performing loan portfolios will be referred to the board for review and decision.&#13;
4.            DEBRA is presently in need of an adviser, who will be stationed in Bishkek for two years&#13;
who will provide assistance in the development of policies and procedures that wil enable the&#13;
receivership unit to co-ordinate its activities with the Bank Supervision Department of the NBK to initiate&#13;
the orderly intervention of insolvent banks. This activity will include: the establishment of guidelines&#13;
for receivership activities, including deposit payouts, conversion of liquid assets to cash, disposal of fixed&#13;
assets, etc.. The receivership adviser will also assist in the establishment of procedures for the transfer&#13;
of non-performing loans and other assets to the debt recovery unit; participate, as appropriate, in the&#13;
initiation of such legal actions as required by the receivership unit, and supervise the conduct of such&#13;
other receivership activities as called for in established liquidation procedures. The adviser will be&#13;
responsible for the establishment of an organizational structure for the receivership unit and the training&#13;
of its personnel.&#13;
Duties and Responsibilities&#13;
5.    The Receivership Adviser will be responsible for the following activities:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
a.    Assist in establishing DEBRA to carry out its functions, prepare organization structure,&#13;
rules of business and operating procedures; specifically,&#13;
i.    Drafting operating manuals for the establishment of conservatorship operations&#13;
at insolvent banks in anticipation of conversion to the receivership function;&#13;
ii.    Detailing individual roles and responsibilities of the members of the intervention&#13;
teams from the Bank Supervision Department of the National Bank, as well as&#13;
the DEBRA Receivership Unit;&#13;
b.    Issue instructions as to asset valuation, loan review, deposit analysis, liquidity review,&#13;
etc., in conjunction with established conservatorship procedures;&#13;
c.     Effect the transfer of non-performing loan assets to the Debt Recovery Unit;&#13;
d.    Initiate such legal actions as appropriate in the role of receiver;&#13;
e.     Monitor the activities of receivership unit personnel, concurring in approval of actions&#13;
taken where appropriate, assuming overall direction of the continuing training program,&#13;
evaluating the performance of the receivership unit personnel;&#13;
f.     Assume overall responsibility for the establishment of ongoing training programs for the&#13;
Kyrgyz personnel under his/her supervision. The training activities in the receivership&#13;
unit will be primarily of an on-the-job nature, as the activities of this unit will be&#13;
undertaken on the premises of the intervened banks. There will be a great deal of hands-&#13;
on assistance until the Kyrgyz staff have developed sufficient expertise to make&#13;
independent decisions;&#13;
g.     Conduct such other receivership activities as called for in established liquidation&#13;
procedures.&#13;
Liaison and Reporting Requirements&#13;
6.           The Receivership Adviser will report directly to the Chairman of the Management Board&#13;
of DEBRA. The Adviser will have continuing liaison responsibilities with Bank Supervision Department&#13;
management at the NBK. Within thirty days of the commencement of the project both advisers will&#13;
prepare a work plan for concurrence in by the supervisory management of DEBRA, the Bank Supervision&#13;
Department management, and the task manager of the World Bank. At the end of each quarter, the&#13;
adviser with prepare a progress report to the above-mentioned parties, outlining each unit's activities,&#13;
progress made to date, next quarter activities and expected achievements, and any areas of concern that&#13;
should be addressed. At the end of the project, a final report will be submitted in accordance with&#13;
established World Bank procedures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Qualifications&#13;
7.           The Adviser should possess a degree in Economics, Finance, Law or Accounting and&#13;
have at least 15 years commercial banking and/or bank regulatory and supervision experience. The&#13;
Adviser should be well-versed in bank examination procedures, loan review and audit procedures, and&#13;
have experience in the lending and debt recovery areas. He/she could be on loan from an appropriate&#13;
banking/bank management institution. Knowledge of Russian would be an advantage. The Adviser&#13;
should be used to working in an international environment.&#13;
Contract Arrangements -&#13;
8.           The NBK is responsible for providing a personal computer, appropriate software, and&#13;
priority use of office equipment (printer, photocopier, fax, etc.) all of which are expected to be purchased&#13;
by the beneficiary out of the Project Preparation Facility. The NBK will also provide a bilingual&#13;
secretary, desk and office space, assistance in finding appropriate housing, administrative assistance in&#13;
obtaining visas, customs clearance and any other administrative permits required by the consultant in the&#13;
performance of the assignment.&#13;
9.           The consultant contract will cover fees, including overhead, travel, accommodation and&#13;
other living expenses.&#13;
10.          Prior to submission of TOR to prospective applicants, the Ministry of Finance, in&#13;
consultation with the IDA, will review the TOR and include such other details as duration of assignment,&#13;
counterparts, required qualifications, experience and background and language proficiency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
FINANCIAL ADVISER TO DEBT RESOLUTION AGENCY (DEBRA)&#13;
TERMS OF REFERFNCE&#13;
Background&#13;
1.            The government of the Kyrgyz Republic has established the Debt Resolution Agency&#13;
(DEBRA) as a legal entity to act in the capacity of a receiver on behalf of the National Bank of the&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic (NBK), the central bank, to take control over and dispose of the assets and liabilities&#13;
of some of the former state-controlled commercial banks in the country. The banks so identified will&#13;
have been deemed insolvent by NBK and their assets. primarily non-performing loans (classified as&#13;
doubtful or loss by NBK). will be subject to resolution and ultimate disposition, while their liabilities,&#13;
primarily deposits, will be subject to scheduled payout programs.&#13;
2.            DEBRA's operations will be carried out through two principal units (a) the Receivership&#13;
Unit and (b) the Debt Recovery Unit. The Receivership Unit will, on behalf of NBK, take possession&#13;
of assets and liabilities of intervened banks and dispose of them in accordance with the insolvency&#13;
legislation. The Debt Recovery Unit will take title of and control over the non-performing loan portfolios&#13;
of these banks and establish a recovery and resolution strategy for each of the non-performing assets&#13;
under its contrnl&#13;
3.            In its capacity as a temporary agency operating under a governmental mandate, to recruit&#13;
and train indigenous personnel under the supervision of foreign advisers in both the receivership and debt&#13;
recovery functions so as toS create a cadre of experienced and capable supervisory and debt work-out&#13;
specialists for on-going activities within the Kyrgyz banking system after the termination of the mandate.&#13;
4.            DEBRA will be headed by a managing director, who will be assisted by two full time&#13;
foreign resident advisers having resp(onsibility respectively for receivership and debt recovery functions.&#13;
The overall management will he entrusted to a board of directors, which will be chaired by the Governor&#13;
of NBK, and will have representatives of the Ministry of Finance and NBK. All recommended courses&#13;
of action with regard to liquidation of assets and liabilities of intervened banks, and the resolution and&#13;
disposition of their non-pertorming lo:tn portfolios will he referred to the board for review and decision.&#13;
5.            DEBRA is piresently in need of a financial adviser, who will be stationed in Bishkek for&#13;
two years and head the proposed Debt Recovery Unit (DRU) DRU will act as the vehicle through which&#13;
all recoveries are made by the governmenit and all other classes of creditors, by collection, restructuring,&#13;
and resolution of outstanding balances of the intervened banks' non-performing loan portfolios. More&#13;
specifically, the adviser's dujties and responsibilities will he as follows:&#13;
Duties and Responsibilities&#13;
a.     Will develop the policies and procedures and establish the guidelines and oversight of the&#13;
activitics tit the roceivership unit as follows&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
i.     Drafting work-out loan manuals outlining the basic loan recovery principles and&#13;
techniques;&#13;
ii.    Establishing debt recovery teams from existing and/or recruited personnel, and&#13;
creating operating procedures and chains-of-command for each team member;&#13;
iii.    Creating debt recovery unit goals and objectives with regards to collection totals,&#13;
restructured loans, asset sales, write-offs, etc;&#13;
iv.    Preparing  status reports for DEBRA  supervisory  management regarding&#13;
disposition activities, personnel performance evaluations, operational reviews,&#13;
etc..&#13;
b.     Direct the work-out teams to carry out the following exercises in respect of the portfolio&#13;
assigned to them:&#13;
i.     analysis and review of the loans: to include borrower's background and its&#13;
operation; review and assessment of the borrower's financial statements, tax&#13;
returns (if applicable/available) and other relevant financial data; evaluation of&#13;
collateral, and personal and/or third party guarantees; cash flow projections to&#13;
assess realistic repayment prospects of some or all debt (principal and interest);&#13;
ii.    development of restructuring options: to include rescheduling of debt i.e.,&#13;
extension of loan maturities, balloon payments, interest rate relief etc.; requesting&#13;
additional collateral, guarantees, setting up of accounts receivable financing;&#13;
negotiating payments and compromise of principal (interest)- all these alternatives&#13;
to be discussed in direct negotiation with the borrower to devise an optimum&#13;
restructuring plan;&#13;
Hi.    recommendation as to courses of action; and&#13;
iv.    ultimate disposition of each loan in its portfolio.&#13;
c.     review  the  restructuring  plans  developed  by  the  work-out teams  and  their&#13;
recommendations and submit adviser's recommendations to the management/board, as&#13;
per rules of business;&#13;
d.     In the cases where no recovery potential exists, make recommendations to the&#13;
management/board for approval to write off uncollectible principal and interest;&#13;
e.     In cases of restructured loans, to require the work-out teams to continue to monitor debt&#13;
servicing until final payment to ensure that further attention is given to cases where&#13;
borrowers continue to experience financial difficulties;&#13;
f.     Establish and have overall responsibility for ongoing training programs for the indigenous&#13;
personnel under their supervision. It is envisioned that most of the training will be in the&#13;
form of classroom seminars where instruction will focus on:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
i.     Analysis and review of each non-performing asset;&#13;
ii.    Familiarization with the borrower and its operations;&#13;
iii.    Review and assess the borrower's financial statements, etc.;&#13;
iv.    Evaluation of collateral, and personal and/or third party guarantees;&#13;
v.     Cash flow projections for debt repayment analysis;&#13;
vi.    Debt restructuring options;&#13;
vii.   recommendations as to disposition courses of action;&#13;
viii.   Reporting and monitoring requirements and techniques&#13;
g.    Evaluate the personnel under supervision on a continuing basis and convey an assessment&#13;
and recommendation to the DEBRA supervisory management within agreed to time&#13;
frames.&#13;
h.     Carry out any other activity in respect of loans requiring resolution, as may be deemed&#13;
necessary.&#13;
Liaison and Reporting Requirements&#13;
6.            The Debt Recovery Adviser will report directly to the Chairman of the Management&#13;
Board of DEBRA. The adviser will have continuing liaison responsibilities with the Bank Supervision&#13;
Department Management at the National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic.&#13;
7.           Within thirty days of commencement of the project, both advisers will prepare a draft&#13;
work plan to be submitted and cleared by: supervisory management of DEBRA, the Bank Supervision&#13;
Department management, and the Task manager of the World Bank. At the end of each quarter, the&#13;
adviser will prepare a progress report to the above-mentioned parties, outlining the Unit's activities,&#13;
progress made to date, next quarter activities and expected achievements, and any areas of concern that&#13;
should be addressed. At the end of the project, a final report will be submitted in accordance with&#13;
established World Bank procedures.&#13;
Qualifications&#13;
8.           The Adviser should possess a degree in Finance or Accounting and have at least 15 years&#13;
experience in management positions in commercial bank lending. The Adviser should have worked with&#13;
regulatory agencies in the conservatorship-receivership areas with special emphasis on asset disposition.&#13;
A familiarity with real estate disposition will be particularly helpful. He/she could be on loan from an&#13;
appropriate banking/bank management institution. Knowledge of Russian would be an advantage. The&#13;
Adviser should be used to working in an international environment.&#13;
Contract Arrangements&#13;
9.            The NBK is responsible for providing a personal computer, appropriate software, and&#13;
priority use of office equipment (printer, photocopier, fax, etc.) all of which are expected to be purchased&#13;
by the beneficiary out of the Project Preparation Facility. The NBK will also provide a bilingual&#13;
secretary, desk and office space, assistance in finding appropriate housing, administrative assistance in&#13;
obtaining visas, customs clearance and any other administrative permits required by the consultant in the&#13;
performance of the assignment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
10.          The consultant contract will cover fees, including overhead, travel, accommodation and&#13;
other living expenses.&#13;
11.          Prior to submission of TOR to prospective applicants, the Ministry of Finance, in&#13;
consultation with the IDA, will review the TOR and include such other details as duration of assignment,&#13;
counterparts, required qualifications, experience and background and language proficiency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
SPEcIALLST IN NON-BANK FINANCIAL INsTrrITmoNs&#13;
INCLUDING INVESTMENT FUNDS&#13;
TO ADVISE THE MINSTRY OF FINANCE&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCE&#13;
Background and Issues&#13;
1.           The development of the an efficient network of non-bank financial institutions, to work&#13;
together with an operating capital market sector, is an important and fundamental part of the Kyrgyz&#13;
government's program to achieve an efficient, sustainable and market-oriented financial sector. A key to&#13;
the transformation of the Kyrgyz economy will be the role of the NBFIs in their support of the&#13;
development of the capital markets as both a facilitator of the privatization process and as an investment&#13;
source for new securities. Currently the securities market is in an early stage of development, however,&#13;
it is envisioned that the supply of securities will increase rapidly in the near future and the NBFIs must&#13;
be developed as well if they are to be available as an important source of savings to absorb these new&#13;
issues.&#13;
2.           In mature market economies, a system of NBFI operations such as insurance companies,&#13;
pensions funds, and investment funds are able to mobilize large amounts of medium and long term&#13;
savings for investment. These companies, in both the public and private sectors, are commonly considered&#13;
to be contractual savings institutions which can greatly stimulate the capital markets in which they invest.&#13;
As the fledgling Kyrgyz capital markets begin to gain in both size and strength, the NBFIs will play an&#13;
increasingly important role. The existing investment funds, insurance companies and the evolving private&#13;
sector and government pension funds all require a high level of technical assistance to strengthen their&#13;
operations and enhance their development.&#13;
3 .          In the case of the Kyrgyz Republic the current uncertain legal status and poor operational&#13;
efficiencies of the NBFIs, as well as the weak regulatory environment in which the existing NBFIs&#13;
operate, will all require adjustment. It is envisioned that technical assistance will be needed to strengthen&#13;
the performance of each of the following NBFI type operations:&#13;
Investment Funds. There are currently some 17 different investment funds operating in the&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic, of which 4 account for over 85% of the total assets managed. The funds issue&#13;
shares to the public for cash, or in exchange for privatization coupons and use these coupons to&#13;
purchase shares directly in newly privatized enterprises. By mid-1995 however, the vast majority&#13;
of the coupons issued had not been invested and many of the funds are in a very poor financial&#13;
position; to the extent that their future operations are threatened. The fund's problems are a result&#13;
of a number of diverse factors, including but not limited to:&#13;
i.    the limited scope for attracting cash in exchange for shares;&#13;
ii.   the 25% limit on any fund's investment in any enterprise;&#13;
iii.    many cases of poor fund management, and;&#13;
iv.    a lack of prudential regulations and supervision;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
v.     a shortage of investable savings in the economy.&#13;
Fund managers need training in accounting, asset/liability management, enterprise governance,&#13;
and basic management techniques. There is widespread evidence that these funds have been&#13;
paying dividends in excess of earned income, probably from the fear that investors will make a&#13;
run to sell their fund shares if their (often unrealistic) dividend expectations are not met.&#13;
Insurance Companies. The Kyrgyz republic's insurance sector has the potential for playing a&#13;
very major role in the financial markets, As the industry evolves away from its traditional, and&#13;
loss incurring, base of credit insurance and into the fields of property, accident, life and medical&#13;
policies; the potential for the accumulation of investable funds seems assured. However, it is&#13;
imperative that the industry shift its accounting systems towards internationally accepted practices.&#13;
Additional constraints to immediate financial market investment by insurance companies include&#13;
rapid changes in the nature and maturity of insurance company liabilities and the lack of&#13;
transparent market values of investments. The industry requires several fundamental adjustments&#13;
in the areas of accounting practices, prudential supervision, reserve requirements, transfer of&#13;
skills and technology from foreign insurers, and the easing of restrictive regulations regarding&#13;
limits on where companies can invest and where they must place their reserves.&#13;
Pension Funds. To date pension fund operations in the Kyrgyz Republic are marginal with only&#13;
two private funds offering services to private sector enterprises. A few of the large formerly&#13;
state-owned enterprises have formed internal pension fund schemes but they appear to be largely&#13;
underfunded, As yet the government employees funds are not managed on any coordinated or&#13;
centralized basis. There is a government managed social security system which requires&#13;
mandatory contributions from employees earning wages above a minimum level. The future&#13;
contribution of pension funds a savings contributors into the capital markets will depend on a&#13;
number of factors including:&#13;
i.     a change in public policy regarding pension funds;&#13;
ii.    the development of prudential regulations on pension funds;&#13;
iii.   new tax laws regarding investments by pension funds;&#13;
iv.    the degree to which mandatory pension funds become required;&#13;
v.    the development of a centralized public social security system, and;&#13;
vi.    new incentives to develop private pension fund operations versus individual&#13;
employer funds without regulation.&#13;
It is necessary at this stage of the development of pension funds to review the fundamental nature&#13;
and future of the pension fund system through technical assistance. The nest step would be the&#13;
development of coordinated policies, a new Law on Pension Funds, and the drafting of prudential&#13;
regulations on pension fund operations.&#13;
4.            The State Agency for Securities (SAS) is a small agency under the Ministry of Finance&#13;
with responsibilities for regulating and supervising capital markets and the NBFIs. Currently this agency&#13;
is incapable of undertaking its assigned tasks due to shortages in personnel, facilities, training, budget,&#13;
and adequate authority. It is envisioned that this agency will become a focal point for capital market and&#13;
NBFI development and that these shortcomings will be corrected. The SAS should be upgraded through&#13;
the creation of an inter-Ministry Board of Directors and eventually evolve into a permanent Securities&#13;
Commission with both regulatory and enforcement powers over the capital markets and the NBFIs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
Objectives&#13;
5.            The Ministry of Finance will be responsible for the development of the NBFIs, the design&#13;
of a comprehensive policy strategy for the sector, the evolution of the SAS, and the future role of the&#13;
NBFIs in the capital markets. Consequently, the Ministry of Finance seeks the technical assistance&#13;
services of a foreign expert to provide advise, guidance, and policy strategies for the development of the&#13;
NBFIs in the Kyrgyz Republic. This advisor, who would report directly to the Minister of Finance,&#13;
should be an experienced financial generalist with relevant international knowledge of NBFI operations,&#13;
regulatory issues, and securities market development. The assignment will be for a minimum of one year&#13;
with the possibility of further extensions at the request of the Ministry of Finance.&#13;
6.            The overall objective of this technical assistance effort will be for the advisor to provide&#13;
direct policy advice to the Minister and his designated staff in all areas of NBFI development. Emphasis&#13;
will be on addressing the problems and shortfalls outlined above and preparing the NBFI sector to become&#13;
an active and positive participant in the growth of the Kyrgyz capital markets. The advisor will act as&#13;
primary manager and coordinator for all additional short-term technical assistance which is to be provided&#13;
in such areas a insurance services, legal reform, and investment fund development.&#13;
Duties and Responsibilities&#13;
7.            The advisor to the Ministry of Finance for the development of the non-bank financial&#13;
institution sector will be responsible for providing advice and assistance in the following activities:&#13;
a.    To study and determine the existing scope, organization, and operations of existing&#13;
NBFIs as background for initiating future strategic policies for development of the sector;&#13;
bi.    To assist the Ministry of Finance in the development of new prudential regulations and&#13;
policies reforms designed to initiate further development of investment funds and their&#13;
involvement with the capital markets of the Kyrgyz Republic;&#13;
c.     Act as liaison and coordinator for efforts to upgrade to performance of investment funds&#13;
with the purpose of better integrating their investment in listed shares on the stock&#13;
exchange and improving their internal operational procedures;&#13;
d.    Advice and assist in the efforts to strengthen prudential regulations governing the&#13;
operations of investment funds and develop methodologies to enhance the enforcement&#13;
of these regulations;&#13;
e.     Assist in the efforts to enforce the provisions of the recently issued Investment Fund&#13;
Accounting Guidelines;&#13;
f.     Assist in the development and enactment of legislation for insurance companies and&#13;
pension funds, coordinating the efforts of legal experts who will be engaged specifically&#13;
for these tasks;&#13;
g.-    To provide advice and cooperation with the proposed insurance specialist who will be&#13;
engaged to provide direct technical assistance within the insurance sector;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
h.     To lead a standing working group for industry policy issues, to be formed within the&#13;
Ministry of Finance and staffed with selected personnel from the MOF, NBK, SAS, and&#13;
the national stock exchange,&#13;
i.     To provide timely, relevant, and ongoing advice to the Minister of Finance, and any&#13;
other government official as he may designate, on all matters concerning strategic issues&#13;
and the development of the NBFI sector and their relationship with the capital markets.&#13;
Implementation and Reporting Requirements&#13;
8.            The technical assistance will be implemented over a period of one year with the possibility&#13;
of further extensions at the request of the Minister of Finance. The advisor will report directly to the&#13;
Minister of Finance or his designee and will be expected to live full time in Bishkek during this&#13;
assignment. Appropriate office space, office equipment, and secretarial support will be provided the&#13;
Ministry of Finance as will assistance in locating appropriate housing, obtaining work visas, and customs&#13;
clearance.&#13;
9.            The consultant contract will cover all fees for service, including overhead, travel,&#13;
accommodation, and other living expenses.&#13;
10.          The advisor will submit to the Minister of Finance and IDA an inception report within&#13;
three weeks of the commencement of the assignment. This report should include a detailed work plan&#13;
based on initial findings and consultation with Ministry of finance and NBFI sector personnel. This report&#13;
should also include a brief summation of the consultant's understanding of the current status of the NBFI&#13;
sector and initial recommendations for addressing perceived constraints to the project goals.&#13;
11.          The advisor will submit to the Minister of Finance and IDA three quarterly reports which&#13;
will concentrate on a discussion of the technical assistance activities undertaken and the progress of the&#13;
project to date. The quarterly reports should contain a separate section which clearly lists the advisor's&#13;
recommendations and indicates the next step actions that should be implemented by each party.&#13;
12.          The advisor will submit to the Minister of Finance and IDA a final draft report at the&#13;
completion of the assignment which incorporates both a summation of the activities completed during the&#13;
project and a discussion of the NBFI sector, its current activities, and recommendations for any future&#13;
actions to be taken.&#13;
Qualiincations&#13;
Given the diverse nature of this consultancy assignment, the advisor to the Ministry of Finance for&#13;
development of the NBFI sector and its enhanced integration with the capital markets should be an&#13;
experienced financial generalist with relevant experience in the development and financial aspects of&#13;
insurance companies, pension funds and investment funds and their relationships with the capital markets.&#13;
The advisor should exhibit the following academic and professional qualifications:&#13;
*     An advanced degree in either economics, finance, business or the equivalent and at least&#13;
15 years relevant experience in the commercial banking, insurance, pension fund, or&#13;
investment fund industries. Direct experience in capital markets or investment banking&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
activities involving working relationships with investment funds or insurance fund&#13;
investment strategies would be an added strength.&#13;
*     Prior experience with developing economies and the design and implementation of&#13;
prudential regulations for NBFI operations as they relate to capital market development&#13;
policies.&#13;
*     Experience and understanding of the operational and financial aspects of NBFIs as&#13;
contractual savings institutions and their relative importance and role in the development&#13;
of the capital markets.&#13;
*     A self-starter with strong written and verbal communication skills and the ability to&#13;
prepare timely reports and action plans as may be requested by the Minister.&#13;
*     A proven ability to work well with senior government officials and provide timely and&#13;
useful advice and policy strategies in this area, as well as to provide motivation and&#13;
training to counterpart staff in the Ministry of Finance.&#13;
*     Previous international experience in a similar project, preferably within the CIS or FSU,&#13;
and the ability to communicate professionally in Russian would be an advantage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
SPECIALIST IN INSURANCE SERVICES&#13;
TO ADVISE THE MINISTRY OF FINANCE&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCE&#13;
Background&#13;
1.           The are currently 15 risk and general insurance companies operating in the Kyrgyz&#13;
Republic although over 70 operating licenses have been issued by the State Insurance Supervision&#13;
Agency. The industry profile is heavily skewed as the top five companies account for approximately 80%&#13;
of the premium income. The State Supervision Agency which was formed in 1991, has the primary&#13;
responsibility of registering and licensing insurance companies. The Agency has not been very active&#13;
in its supervision role and is currently in the process of being privatized.&#13;
2.           The industry is shifting away from its previously heavy position is credit risk insurance&#13;
where major losses have been incurred (payments exceeded premium income by 36% in 1993), and is&#13;
moving towards property, life, accident, and voluntary medical insurance. The composition of premium&#13;
income, as of mid-1995, is as follows: 52.6% in personal insurance (life and health); 37.2% in property&#13;
insurance; and 10.1% relating to goods in transit. Total premium income in 1994 top the 10 billion som&#13;
mark, approximately $1 million. Reserves of the insurance industry totaled 42% of 1994 premium&#13;
income. Premium rates and the allocation of reserves is determined by the State Insurance Supervisor.&#13;
3.           The insurance sector faces a number of development problems and challenges as related&#13;
to adjusting to western practices for risk assessment, premium rates, underwriting methodology, reserves&#13;
management, and accounting practices. The industry should expand its scope by working together with&#13;
foreign firms on a co-insurance and re-insurance basis. The current level of industry reserves appear to&#13;
be excessive with restrictions on investment alternatives for these reserves which currently must be placed&#13;
only in low yielding bank deposits. Finally there is a need restructure the accounting systems used and&#13;
relieve the burdens of the current tax regime.&#13;
4.           It is envisioned that as the insurance industry continues its improved performance and&#13;
growth it wiU evolve into a position to play a major role in the financial markets, particularly as an&#13;
investor in the capital markets. In order to achieve this goal there is a need for short-termn technical&#13;
assistance from a specialist in the insurance industry.&#13;
Objectives&#13;
5.           The Ministry of Finance is currently responsible for the development of the insurance&#13;
industry and is effecting the current privatization of the Insurance Supervisory Agency. Consequently the&#13;
Ministry of Finance seeks the technical assistance support of a foreign expert/specialist in insurance&#13;
services to provide advice and guidance for the immediate changes in the structure and supervision of the&#13;
Kyrgyz insurance sector. This assignment will be for a minimum of six months with the possibility of&#13;
a further extension at the request of the Minister of finance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
6.           The primary objective of this technical assistance effort will be for the advisor to provide&#13;
direct policy advice to Minister and his designated staff as well as work directly with insurance&#13;
professionals in the development of the industry. The advisor will act as primary liaison with the&#13;
insurance industry and the Insurance Supervision Agency for the purpose of effecting the structural&#13;
reforms necessary for transition towards western practices in the industry, the enhancement of risk&#13;
assessment and underwriting practices, premium rate determination, and reserves investment. The advisor&#13;
will coordinate his efforts with the long-term advisor for NBFI development who will also be work in&#13;
the Ministry of Finance.&#13;
Duties and Responsibilities&#13;
7.           The advisor to the Ministry of Finance for the development of the insurance industry will&#13;
be responsible for the following activities:&#13;
a.    To study and determine the existing scope, size, and operating procedures and&#13;
profitability of the insurance sector as background for developing a work plan to enhance&#13;
the industry's capability to become an active participant in the capital markets;&#13;
b.    To assist the Ministry of Finance in the privatization process for the State Supervision&#13;
Agency, formulating new prudential regulations, setting the proper level for reserves, and&#13;
standardizing new accounting practices to be implemented throughout the industry;&#13;
C.     Assist in the development and enactment of necessary industry legislation through a&#13;
universal Law for Insurance Companies, coordinating efforts with individual legal experts&#13;
who will be engaged specifically for this task;&#13;
d.     Assist industry management in the evolution and development of their companies in such&#13;
areas as: 1) risk assessment and underwriting, 2) premium pricing and marketing of&#13;
product, 3) standard accounting systems, and, 4) investment strategies and management&#13;
of reserves;&#13;
e.     Develop an industry standard for the valuation of investments and establish an initial&#13;
program for the investment of reserves in alternative financial instruments, including&#13;
shares listed on the local exchange;&#13;
f.     Assist industry management in establishing joint-venture relationships with foreign&#13;
insurance companies as co-insurers and re-insurance sources;&#13;
g.    To work closely with the long-term advisor who will be responsible for the overall&#13;
development of the NBFI sector as an advisor to the Ministry of Finance;&#13;
h.    To provide timely, relevant, and ongoing advise to the Minister of Finance, and other&#13;
government officials as may be designated, on all matters concerning the strategic&#13;
development of the insurance industry and its relationship with the capital markets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Implementation and Reporting Requirements&#13;
8.           The technical assistance will be implemented over a six months period with the possibility&#13;
of a further six month extension at the request of the Minister of Finance. The advisor will be expected&#13;
to live full time in Bishkek during this assignment. Appropriate office space and secretarial support will&#13;
be provided by the Ministry of Finance.&#13;
9.           The advisor will submit to the Minister of Finance and IDA an inception report within&#13;
three weeks of the commencement of the assignment. This report should include a detailed work plan&#13;
based on initial findings on the insurance industry and consultation with the Minister of Finance. The&#13;
inception report should also include a brief summary of the advisor's understanding of the current status&#13;
of the insurance sector and initial recommendations for the next action steps to be taken to meet the&#13;
agreed upon development goals.&#13;
10.          The advisor will submit to the Minister of Finance and IDA a final draft report at the&#13;
completion of the assignment which incorporates both a summation of the activities completed during the&#13;
assignment and a discussion of long-term strategies to be developed for the further involvement of the&#13;
insurance sector in the development of the Kyrgyz capital markets.&#13;
Qualifications&#13;
11.          The advisor to the Ministry of Finance for the strengthening of the Kyrgyz insurance&#13;
sector should exhibit the following academic and professional qualifications:&#13;
*     An advanced degree in finance or business along with a professional qualification in the&#13;
insurance field and at least 10 years relevant experience in management of an&#13;
internationally recognized insurance company.&#13;
*     A thorough understanding of the various types of general risk and life insurance, their&#13;
relative risks and policy structures, underwriting methodologies, and premium structures.&#13;
*     Prior management experience with an internationally oriented insurance company&#13;
including the design, management, and implementation of reserve investments for the&#13;
company in a developing economy.&#13;
*     Experience and understanding of the operational and accounting aspects of a general risk&#13;
insurance company in an inflationary and high risk environment.&#13;
*     A proven ability to work well with senior government officials and industry management&#13;
and to provide timely and useful advice and in-house training on specific and general&#13;
development issues concerning the industry.&#13;
*     A self-starter with strong written and verbal communication skills with the ability to&#13;
provide timely reports and action plans as may be requested.&#13;
*     Previous international experience in a similar project, preferably in the CIS or FSU, and&#13;
the ability to communicate professionally in Russian would be an advantage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
SPECIALIST IN STATE SECURITIES INSTRUMENTS&#13;
TO ADVISE THE MINISTRY OF FINANCE&#13;
TERMS OF REFERENCE&#13;
Background and Issues&#13;
1.    The development of the an efficient capital market sector, with a well developed supply of state&#13;
or government issued securities, is an important and fundamental part of the Kyrgyz government's&#13;
program to achieve an efficient, sustainable and market-oriented financial sector. A key to the&#13;
transformation of the Kyrgyz economy will be the role of the government in promotion and direct support&#13;
for the development of the capital markets as both an issuer of stable short term securities and bonds.&#13;
Also the state can perform important functions in the areas of assistance in the improvement of the legal&#13;
basis and regulation of the markets and an important facilitator of the privatization process through the&#13;
issuance of new securities. Currently the securities market is in an early stage of development, however,&#13;
it is envisioned that the supply of securities will increase rapidly in the near future and the abilities of the&#13;
state must be further developed if it is to achieve its potential in this area.&#13;
2.    In the case of the Kyrgyz Republic the current uncertain legal status and poor operational&#13;
efficiencies of the capital markets as well as the lack of marketable securities available on the exchange,&#13;
will require a concentrated effort of adjustment. It is envisioned that technical assistance will be needed&#13;
to strengthen the performance of the capital markets through the introduction of a series of government&#13;
security and debt instruments.&#13;
3.    The State Agency for Securities (SAS) is a small agency under the Ministry of Finance with&#13;
responsibilities for regulating and supervising capital markets. Currently this agency is incapable of&#13;
undertaking its assigned tasks due to shortages in personnel, facilities, training, budget, and adequate&#13;
authority. It is envisioned that this agency will become a focal point for future capital market development&#13;
and that these shortcomings will be corrected. The SAS should be upgraded through the creation of an&#13;
inter-Ministry Board of Directors and eventually evolve into a permanent Securities Commission with&#13;
both regulatory and enforcement powers over the capital markets.&#13;
Objectives&#13;
5.    The Ministry of Finance will be responsible for the design of a comprehensive policy strategy&#13;
for the capital markets sector, the development of a securities market for state financial instruments, and&#13;
the evolution of the SAS. Consequently, the Ministry of Finance seeks the technical assistance services&#13;
of a foreign expert to provide advise, guidance, and policy strategies for the development of the state&#13;
securities market in the Kyrgyz Republic. This advisor, who would report directly to the Minister of&#13;
Finance, should be an experienced capital market and securities specialist with relevant international&#13;
knowledge of official financial instruments, capital markets operations, regulatory issues, and securities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
market development. The assignment will be for a minimum period of six months with the possibility of&#13;
further extensions at the request of the Ministry of Finance.&#13;
5.     The overall objective of this technical assistance effort will be for the advisor to provide direct&#13;
policy advice to the Minister and his designated staff in all areas state security market development.&#13;
Emphasis will be on addressing the problems and shortfalls outlined above and preparing the state sector&#13;
to become an active and positive participant in the growth of the Kyrgyz capital markets.&#13;
Duties and Responsibilities&#13;
6.     The advisor to the Ministry of Finance for the development of the state securities and debt&#13;
instrument market through the local stock exchanige will he responlsible for providing advice and&#13;
assistance in the following activities:&#13;
a.     To study and determine the existing scope and extent of the government security and debt&#13;
instrument market as background for initiating future strategic policies for development&#13;
of the sector;&#13;
b.     To assist the Ministry of Finance in the development of a new short-term treasury bill&#13;
market their involvement with the capital markets of the Kyrgyz Republic:&#13;
c.     Design and promote the development of a program for state bonds and debt notes to be&#13;
issued through the capital markets;&#13;
d.     Design and promote the issuance of government-hacked long term savings instruments&#13;
for the public,&#13;
e.     Assist the government in the development of Kyrgyz securities which can be floated on&#13;
the international markets;&#13;
f.     Provide assistance in the improvement ot the legal basis for the state security markets&#13;
and the enforcement of prudential regulations for the capital markets;&#13;
g.     To provide advice and cooperation with the management of DEBRA for the purpose of&#13;
establishing a methodology for the securitization of debts transferred to DEBRA (i.e. debt&#13;
/ equity swaps);&#13;
h.     To provide timely, relevant, and ongoing advice to the Minister of Finance, and any&#13;
other government official as he may designate. on all matters concerning strategic issues&#13;
and the development of state securities sector to be traded through the capital markets.&#13;
Implementation and Reporting Requirements&#13;
7.            The technical assistance will be implemented over a period of six months with the&#13;
possibility of further extensions at the request of the Minister of Finance. The advisor will report directly&#13;
to the Minister of Finance or his designee and will be expected to live full time in Bishkek during this&#13;
assignment. Appropriate office space, office equipment, and secretarial support will be provided by the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
Ministry of Finance as will assistance in locating appropriate housing, obtaining work visas, and customs&#13;
clearance.&#13;
8.            The consultant contract will cover all fees for service, including overhead, travel,&#13;
accommodation, and other living expenses.&#13;
9.            The advisor will submit to the Minister of Finance and IDA an inception report within&#13;
three weeks of the commencement of the assigmnent. This report should include a detailed work plan&#13;
based on initial findings and consultation with Ministry of finance and capital market personnel. This&#13;
report should also include a brief summation of the consultant's understanding of the current status of the&#13;
state securities sector and initial recommendations for addressing perceived constraints to the project&#13;
goals.&#13;
10.          The advisor will submit to the Minister of Finance and IDA a final draft report at the&#13;
completion of the assignment which incorporates both a summation of the activities completed during the&#13;
project and a discussion of the state securities sector, its current activities, and recommendations for any&#13;
future actions to be taken.&#13;
Qualifications&#13;
11.          Given the diverse nature of this consultancy assignment, the advisor to the Ministry of&#13;
Finance for development of the state securities sector and its enhanced integration with the capital markets&#13;
should be an experienced capital markets specialist with direct experience in the design and trading of&#13;
government security and debt instruments. The advisor should exhibit the following academic and&#13;
professional qualifications:&#13;
a.     An advanced degree in either economics, finance, business or the equivalent and at least&#13;
10 years relevant experience in capital market operations and the theory behind the&#13;
issuance of state security and debt instruments. Direct experience in capital markets or&#13;
investment banking activities involving working relationships governments and/or the&#13;
grading of government instruments would be an added strength.&#13;
b.     Prior experience with developing economies with the design and implementation of&#13;
prudential regulations for government securities operations as they relate to capital market&#13;
development policies.&#13;
c.     Experience and understanding of the operational and financial aspects of government debt&#13;
instruments, debt/equity swaps, international government securities, and treasury bill&#13;
operations.&#13;
d.     A self-starter with strong written and verbal communication skills and the ability to&#13;
prepare timely reports and action plans as may be requested by the Minister.&#13;
e.     A proven ability to work well with senior government officials and provide timely and&#13;
useful advice and policy strategies in this area, as well as to provide motivation and&#13;
training to counterpart staff in the Ministry of Finance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
f.     Previous international experience in a similar project, preferably within the CIS or FSU,&#13;
and the ability to communicate professionally in Russian would be an advantage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX III&#13;
TIMETABLE OF KEY PROCESSING EVENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
TIMETABLE OF KEY PROJECT PROCESSING EVENTS&#13;
Time for Preparation:                3 months&#13;
Pre-Appraisal Mission:               December 4, 1995&#13;
Appraisal Mission:                   March 26, 1996&#13;
Negotiations:                       May 9, 1996&#13;
Board Presentation:                 June 25, 1996&#13;
Expected Effectiveness:              July 25, 1996&#13;
Closing Date:                        June 30, 2001&#13;
The Task Manager for this project is Ms. F. Aynur Sumer (EC3AI). The Division Chief and Department Director&#13;
are Messrs. Michael Gould (EC3AI) and Yukon Huang (EC3DR), respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX IV&#13;
COST ESTIMATES FROM DONORS' CONFERENCE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Cost Estimstes from Donors' Conference held In Bishkek ii&#13;
April 5, 1996&#13;
REQUIREMENT                            DESCRIPTION                                            YEAR                       SOURCE    STATUS&#13;
1996        1      1997       1 I998        OF                OF&#13;
VERALL REFORM OF FINANCIAL SECTOR&#13;
_ Senior Aaw'se r to NB: One adwser to: (a) coordinate the TA providers to the financial                                                 96.Funded by PPF&#13;
sctor; (b) assist in implementation of FINSA C; (c) advise NBK      105,000  87,000                        IDA      97:Uninded (wiling to&#13;
_  manafement on woicv and ooerationaM issues                                              _                        borrow from IDA)&#13;
ANK RESTRUCTURING AND LIQUEDATION&#13;
Advisreto NBK: on    One adviser to: (a) help reduce/rationalize the branch network;                                                     96:Fkuded by PPF&#13;
Rcorganztion  of   (b) assist in merger andpreparationfor sale of appropriate       105.00o  70,000                         lDA       97:Unded (NE  is&#13;
Bankiz               seected branches of Agroprom and other bans wohich are                                                             lookingfr soures)&#13;
branch systems                                                                                                     l&#13;
Adviser to AKB                                        .     .       ._Urffuided, NBK is                                                                         &#13;
Ayrgyzsean and       One adviser to provide marketing assistance in attacting          100,000                                         looking for grant based&#13;
KPromstroibana       domestic and/or foreign investors.                                                                                         TA&#13;
DT RECOVERY AND RESOLUTION&#13;
S5pecialists in Debt    I                                .        ~~ nI                                        I1                         96 Funded byPF&#13;
Sp fsu inDb           One specialnint  asset sales and lisda,uidon to oversee                                                             96-une by PP**&#13;
Collection and       I    .                .  o foBrse                                 105,000     185,000       180,000      IDA           97:UnfWnded&#13;
Resclution to DEBRA   estabshment and operat DEBRA DEB98 1-                                                              I            1     98Un fded&#13;
Spectali n Debt       One (1)financial analyst experienced in loan workouts, to                                                          96105,000d 100,00  100,0  IDA    3P97UrJcdd&#13;
Colectio and         prowde analytical support.                             *                                                 I             97*IU *    'ule-&#13;
.Resolution to DEBRA   rR                                                                      I                 _       R                  98:Unw,ded&#13;
ANK SUPERVISION&#13;
One highly experienced bank eaminr to strengthen bank                                              i            II&#13;
IStrengthening Bank   supervison skis and capabiletis in: (a) on-site bank   fiundedby USAI          92000      l        I    A IANDI         96Pwuded&#13;
Supervision          cxamination; (b) off-site surveillance; (c) problem bank  R              1                                              97: Funded&#13;
____ ____ ____ ___ m o nitoring_                                           _ _ _ _  _ __   _ _ _ _  _ _ _&#13;
Bankers Training      One commercial banker experienced in training and leasing    |                                      1                   96: humded&#13;
nBankers Traimng     operations to establish and run tbe Instiuce, develop            100,000                               TACIS          97: unfumded&#13;
|lnstatuc            |curriculum, hire outside trainers, etc.                                   __, pledged b&#13;
* ITACS DENOTE HIGHER PRIORITY TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE REQUIREMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Cost Estimates from Donors' Conference held in Bishkek i/&#13;
April 5, 1996&#13;
REQUIREMENT                           DESCRIPTION                        1                  YEAR                    |SOURCE    STATUS&#13;
1        1      1997         1998       OF                OF&#13;
J IA-U I  AN-UNIVItlTINC&#13;
Bankers Training     Short -term consultants to teach short courses and to train future  100,000  200,000     92,000     TACIS       pledged by TACIS&#13;
LInstitute           trainers&#13;
Bankers Training     Library and other equipment                                    30,000       10,000       5,000      TACIS       pledged by TACIS&#13;
Institute__              _ _  _ _ _ _  _ _ _ _  _ _ _ _  _ _ _  _ _ _ _  __                                    _ _  _  _ _  _ _ _  _  _ _ _ _   _ _ _ _&#13;
* Two (2) full-time teachers, specialized in business law of                                                  ledged by TACIS/&#13;
Training for Lawyers   Civil Code tradition countries, to give training in the new laws  100.000  200,000             TACIS/ TIC  TICA&#13;
on corporation, baneruptcy, banking, pledges, mortgages, etc.         I&#13;
* Hardware and software for a comprehensive legal infonnatio               120,000                           unfunded&#13;
L __________________    system                                                                     , _      __&#13;
BANK ACCOUNTING STANDARDS                                                                                               ..          ..&#13;
Accounting Specia.sts  Tw  (2) specialists to help inpiement the new Chart of                                        R  USAID:        96:Partly Funded&#13;
theanking specitsr  Accouns, new reporting formats and standards, manuals for                 224000       210,0000   1996 and     2/ 97: Pledged by&#13;
Lo t0fhe banking sector   practitioners, pilot tests, and training to all commercial bank_s.                          H   1997             USAID&#13;
PAYMENTS SYSTEM&#13;
inprove the Payments  Credit from the Japanese Government is $1.5 mln               1500000                              Japan   |1.5 of Japa Crty te 19l9&#13;
and Clearing Systems                                                                                                              finance_________partly________the_____1997____&#13;
Improve the Payments  Needs to be borrowedfrom IDA                                  1000000                          jj  IDA             UnfYnded&#13;
and Clearing Systems&#13;
Imrv th Pamet                                                                                                          II            46,0-Jpn grant &#13;
anprovcahenPaymenu  |Grantfrom the Japanese Government is $465,000                  465000                               Japan      465,0s alapan. grant&#13;
,and  Clearing  Systems    I _______________I_______I__                                      I_is_already_provided&#13;
MQTGAGE CREDITIN&#13;
|Consuffanf on Mortgage nalysis of opportunities for creation of mechanism on       100.000                            IPC/TICA     1996:.o Be Funded&#13;
Cerediting          Imortgage credits                                     RI&#13;
NON-BANK FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS&#13;
anon of the   One (1) advisor to the MUinistry of Finance to provide guidance      I                 1    00                 96: Funded by PPF&#13;
Sacurities      andtraining in Development of the Securiies Market    -   -    105,0001    00,000    1 00,000                   97,98: Urnded, but&#13;
* fAUCS DENOTE HIGHER PRIORIY TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE REQUIREMUET&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Cost Estimates from Donors' Conference held in Bishkek it&#13;
April 5, 1996&#13;
REQUIREMENT                            DESCRIPTION                                             YEAR                      SOURCE    STATUS&#13;
1     1996       1     1997          1998       OF                OF&#13;
l                                                     gIAN-luN nJT .npc IsN-~~~~~~~~~ ~ ~           ~~~~~lUNJlknj   F TNI}NG  Fl J1Sl)NC.&#13;
One (I) advisor to the State Agency on Securities to provide                 100,000                                Pledged by USA1I&#13;
guidance and training in Development of the Securities Market                                                       P         U&#13;
Investment fwunds    One (I) advisor to set up a new accounting system, to improve              60,000                                        Unfunded&#13;
cthe organization and management in investmentfunds        |                    J&#13;
gencies speciaizing in One (1) advisor to the Ministry of Finance to provide guidance  60,000                                              96: Unfunded&#13;
Insurance Services   and training in developing the market on insurance services&#13;
Pension Funds        One adviser to review Pension Fund Schemes, recommend             60,000                                TA CIS   |       Funded&#13;
changes, and help to design new schemes               4l                         l                              l                      lr&#13;
Legal Framework       One lanyer to NBK to draft new legislationfor speciaUzed         75,000                                                 Unfunded&#13;
banks and improve legislation on leasing._____________&#13;
One lawyerfor the Ministry of Finance to draft new&#13;
Legal FrwmeKvrk     legislation/regulations in area of non-banking financial          105,000                                           96: Funded by PPF&#13;
institutions including: (a) Law on Insurance; (b) Law on                                                            97, 98: Unfunded&#13;
= _____________  Pension Funds.                                              l                        l                               l&#13;
RURAL FINANCE&#13;
Creding             iOne advisor to the Ministry of Finance                              100,000         l          l                           Unfunded&#13;
egal       &amp; ewrk      lOne layer to draft new legislation/regulations for development            75soo  1                      ADB             97.Funded&#13;
J                      j egal Framrt  |of rural credit unions and cooperatives       I_T 1                         I ,     I            I _     _&#13;
ANNUAL TOTALS:                              0 4420000 1623000         0  687,0001&#13;
THREE YEAR TOTAL                       6730000                                    l&#13;
1/ Cost edtimates subject to revision depending on agreements with tbe Government and NBK&#13;
2/ USAID consukanii  contma ends 6/30/96.&#13;
* Cost estimates for advisory and consutany services inwlude the cost of office equipment necessary for each advisor/ consultant&#13;
* IrAICS DENOTE IHGHER PRIORITY TECICAL ASSISTANCE REQUIREMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX V&#13;
IMPLEMENTATION PLAN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
IMPLEMENTATION PLAN&#13;
(for IDA-Funded Components)&#13;
COMPONENT                             RESPONSIBLE                   TIMING&#13;
AGENCY&#13;
1. Overall Reform of the Financial Sector                                                                 l&#13;
* Senior Adviser to NBK                                  NBK            Dec. 1996 - Nov. 1997&#13;
* Financial Legislation                                  NBK            Dec. 1996 - May 1997&#13;
2. Bank Restructuring &amp; Liquidation                                                                       l&#13;
* TA to NBK                                              NBK            June 1997 - May 1998&#13;
* TA to Promstroi and AKB Kyrgyzstan Banks               NBK            Dec. 1996 - Nov. 1997&#13;
3. Debt Recovery and Resolution                                                                           l&#13;
* Asset Sales and Liquidation Specialist                 NBK            Dec. 1997 - May 2000&#13;
* Loan Workout Specialist                                NBK            Dec. 1997 - May 2000&#13;
5. Training &#13;
* Legal Information System                            NBK/MOJ           Apr. 1997 - Sep. 1998&#13;
7. Central Registry for Pledges                            NBK/MOJ           Mar. 1997 - Feb. 1998&#13;
8. Payment and Clearing System                               NBK             Apr. 1997 - Oct. 2000&#13;
9. Non-Bank Financial Institutions&#13;
* Investment Services                                   MOF             Feb. 1997 - Jan. 1998&#13;
* Insurance Funds                                       MOF             May 1997 - Oct. 1997&#13;
11. Public Debt Instruments &amp; Securities                     MOF            June 1997 - Nov. 1997&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX VI&#13;
PERFORMANCE MONITORING INDICATORS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
KYRGYZ REPUBLIC&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
Performance Monitoring Indicators&#13;
OUTPUT INDICATORS    |IPACT INDICATORS&#13;
MANAGEMENT OF OVERALL REFORM PROGRANI&#13;
Obiective:    a) Assist with     i) Assist implementing new charn of accounts and    i) Increased implementation capacity within NBK measured by&#13;
implementation and  DEBRA operations, assist improving the payments   substantial progress in achieving second tranche release conditions&#13;
coordination of    and clearing system, assist creating mechanisms for  in a timely manner;&#13;
FINSAC reform      mortgage finance;                                ii) Increased capabilities within NBK top management to handle&#13;
program;           ii) Develop training program for management and   complex technical issues in financial sector reform and&#13;
b) Strengthen the   staff of NBK:                                   development;&#13;
NBK's institutional  iii) Review, draft and finalize financial legislation;    iii) Introduction of new, and possible revision to existing.&#13;
capacity to manage  iv) Bi-monthly reports on progress of the reform  financial legislation&#13;
the FINSAC         program and coordination of the TA Program&#13;
reform program;&#13;
c) Assist with&#13;
finalization of&#13;
financial legislation&#13;
Direct&#13;
Benefiaain:  NBK&#13;
BANK RESTRUCTURING AND LIQUIDATION&#13;
Obiective:    Restnicture or     i) Complete branch analysis of Agroprombank:      i) Sale of viable former branches of Agroprombank and Elbank:&#13;
liquidate insolvent  ii) Submit timetable for completion of liquidation of  ii) Transfer of non-performing loans and other assets of insolvent&#13;
banks              Agroprombank and Elbank to IDA and FINSAC        banks to DRUt (DEBRA);&#13;
Review Commission;                               iii) Reduction of staff levels of Agroprombank and Elbank;&#13;
iii) Prepare bi-monthly reports on the financial  iv) By second tranche release, attainment of 'positive' or "zero"&#13;
performance of Promstroi and AKB Kyrgyzstan      level of capital bv Promstroi and AKB Kyrgyzstan banks. If not,&#13;
Direct                           Banks                                            commencement of liquidation proceedings&#13;
Beneficiary:  NBK, Elbank,&#13;
Agroprombank,&#13;
Promstroibank,&#13;
AKB Kyrgyzstan&#13;
DEBT RECOVERY AND RESOLUTION&#13;
Objective:    Recovery of       i) Prepare policies and procedures guides for DRU   i) Transfer of analytical skills and managerial capabilities to&#13;
outstanding        and BRU;                                         DEBRA staff measured by number of unsupervised work-out&#13;
balances of non-    ii) Develop loan work-out and conservatorship   team visits to insolvent banks, and level of independence of BRU&#13;
performing loans of manuals;                                        staff;&#13;
insolvent banks or  iii) Develop training program for DEBRA staff:  ii) Increased sophistication within the Kyrgyz financial sector&#13;
resolution via other iv) Transfer all recoverable loan assets of Elbank and evidenced by the development of markets for asset sales and other&#13;
cost-effective     Agroprombank to DRU;                             asset disposition alternatives;&#13;
means              v) Prepare report classifying the non-performing  iii) Increased financial discipline and improved portfolio&#13;
loans under its control into two categories (a) loans   management within the banking sector measured by reduction in&#13;
where the work plan for collection will be based on   value of loan loss provisions;&#13;
Direct                           automatic criteria; and (b) loans where a case-by-case iv) Govemment issuance of Som 965 million long term bond to&#13;
Beneficiary:  DEBRA, NBK         approach is practicable                          replace Agroprombank arrears to NBK&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-  0-&#13;
TRAINING&#13;
Obiective:    a) Training of    i) Develop a training program for judges, (financed  Wide disemnination of all official legal texts and major case law,&#13;
Judges;            by other donors);                               measured by the distribution, accessibility, and rates of usage of&#13;
b) Development of  ii) Procure, install and implement a computerized  the database 'stations'&#13;
a comprehensive    database system containing a comprehensive&#13;
legal information    collection of legal records&#13;
system&#13;
Direct&#13;
BeneflejarI: MOJ&#13;
CENTRAL REGISTRY FOR PLEDGES&#13;
Obiective:    Establish a Central  Procure, install and implement a database system in a Reduction of lending risk of banks, measured by reduction in the&#13;
Registry of Pledges Central Registry, to be established in the MOJ, to    rate of loan defaults&#13;
to enforce security  register pledges used as security&#13;
rights&#13;
Direct&#13;
Benefician:  MOJ, NBK&#13;
PAYMENT AND CLEARING SYSTEM&#13;
Obiective:    Improve the       Procure, install and implement new data processing   Reduction in delays of payments, currently at 2 days within a&#13;
national clearing    and communications equipment                  region and up to 14 days inter-regionally&#13;
and settlement&#13;
system&#13;
Direct&#13;
Beneficiary:  NBK, banks, bank&#13;
customers&#13;
NON-BANK FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS&#13;
Obiective:    Develop the       i) Develop methodologies to enhance enforcement  i)  Emergence of SAS into permanent securities commission&#13;
country's non-bank  of new regulations on "investment funds";      with regulatory and enforcement powers over capital markets&#13;
financial         ii) Develop work plan to enhance insurance       and NBFIs;&#13;
institutions,     industry's capability to become an active participant  ii) The consolidation of authority for all securities market&#13;
including capital   in capital markets, including, inter alia, developing   regulations and supervision in SAS;&#13;
markets, their    industry standards, skills development, and joint  iii) Development of the legal and regulatory framework for&#13;
prudential         venture relationships with foreign insurance    the sound growth of the insurance industry, pension funds and&#13;
regulation and     companies;                                      leasing institutions;&#13;
supervision       iii) Prepare new legislation on insurance industry,   iv) Development of organized secondary market for T-Bills;&#13;
pension funds and leasing;                      v) The issuance of government bonds directly to public&#13;
iv) Develop policy reforms within MOF to promote  through Kyrgyz Stock Exchange;&#13;
NBFPs;                                          vi) Increased public confidence in contractual savings&#13;
v)  Strengthen SAS as the executive arm of the  institutions, measured by increased transaction volume on&#13;
Direct                          Securities Commission                            KSE, increased number of contractual savings institutions,&#13;
Benefidary:                                                                      and increase in total value of their portfolios&#13;
MOF, SAS&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT INSTRUMENTS AND SECURITIES&#13;
Obiective:    Develop           i) Develop strategies for:                       i) Increased involvement by the government in the capital&#13;
institutional       (a) a short term treasury bill market;         markets, measured by the increased variety of govemrnent debt&#13;
capacity within     (b) a program for state bonds and debt notes to be instruments available for purchase by the public;&#13;
MOF to raise funds issued through the capital markets;             ii) Greater use of non-inflationary means to finance budget deficits&#13;
in the debt markets  (c) a program for government-backed long term&#13;
savings instruments for the public;&#13;
ii) In conjunction with DEBRA, develop a&#13;
Direct                          methodology for the aecuritization of debts&#13;
Beneficiary:  MOP, enterprises,  transferred to DEBRA (i.e., debt/equity swaps)&#13;
_  public&#13;
May 24, 1996&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
BRED 26822&#13;
KAZAKSTAN&#13;
&lt;A,  1         s                     KokD honWro, =A&#13;
/}        &lt;    = s~~~'t  \syt1   (  ~~               CHUI &#13;
DZI, 4LAL- 4B AD ~      ~         (MAN RAD&#13;
N   A    R   Y                                                                              O    K,r.    _D&#13;
/         KAZAKSTAN~~~~~"                                                K                                                                                                                        NATONAL-APIA&#13;
TO   -,     &gt;                                          r   K                                                                           ~                                                                                ORLAST  CAPITALS&#13;
| /                                                                                                                                                                                                   0     SELECTED CITES0  S H&#13;
\  6                                    9_           %&gt;,  -s                                                                                           ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~KY RGY Z R EP UB LI C|&#13;
T A J I K I S T A N                     c    t+                                        t    t,                                                                                                            RAILkOADS &#13;
e  [of ushonfs   */   loMurrpb   9                                                                                             f%~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~AIN ROADS&#13;
5 , r. 'r_, cusSlso * ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~OTHER ROADS&#13;
AZL'RL UArl  /   lI    KA ZA K STlAN        \  Erro                                                                                                                                                       s     NATIONAL CAPITAL&#13;
w.roD,;-r t m \( - \ _ \ , , / v15s a | O SEIECTED C TIES~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~SLECEDCIIE&#13;
R1LCt4ETERS                                                  OBLAST BOUNDARIES&#13;
_ _ 5:,                                                                                                                      0           L0           10           ITO              -.   s INTERNATIONAL BOUNDARIES&#13;
0  j~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~  ~~                                                                                   0&#13;
EE 1,8Llt /t- ( t ~~~~~~L @ C           H ,  N  ;A     .. vEelo h egluse0 fPfr- odBt ou &lt;E&#13;
Ar4UANSIA4,  -  414444 bto,d,'.,,~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~,'L12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IIMAGI NG&#13;
Report No:       h 6896 KG&#13;
Type: MOP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="696469">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/05/696469/kyrgyz-republic-financial-sector-technical-assistance-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/05/696469/kyrgyz-republic-financial-sector-technical-assistance-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1996/05/696469/kyrgyz-republic-financial-sector-technical-assistance-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/05/31/000009265_3961214124859/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/05/31/000009265_3961214124859/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>2891</credit_no>
        <datestored>2001-05-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1996-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Kyrgyz Republic - Financial Sector
            Technical Assistance Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objectives of the Financial Sector
            Technical Assistance Project is to facilitate the
            implementation of the policy and institutional reforms
            envisaged under the Financial Sector Adjustment Credit by:
            1) strengthening the capabilities of the key financial and
            regulatory institutions; 2) assisting in the establishment
            of new, temporary institutions that will effect the
            restructuring/liquidation of major banks; 3) extending the
            new accounting infrastructure; and 4) training bank
            personnel. The project will provide financing for a number
            of technical assistance activities designed to implement
            reforms in the financial sector to transform it into a
            well-functioning and efficient financial system capable of
            meeting the evolving requirements of a market-oriented
            economy. It consists of the following components: 1)
            assistance to the National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic; 2)
            bank restructuring and liquidation; 3) debt recovery and
            resolution; 4) payments and clearing systems; 5) central
            registry for pledges; 6) training; 7) non-bank financial
            institutions; 8) public debt instruments and securities; and
            9) rural finance.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Kyrgyz Republic - Financial Sector Technical
            Assistance Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Kyrgyz Republic - Financial
            Sector Technical Assistance Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1996/05/696469/kyrgyz-republic-financial-sector-technical-assistance-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>KG-Financial Sector Technical Assistance
            (Ta) Project -- P045631</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Settlement of Investment Disputes,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Financial Intermediation,National Governance,Financial Crisis Management &amp; Restructuring</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Kyrgyz Republic</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Central Asia!$!80456</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Commonwealth of Independent States!$!80457</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3961214124859</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Banking,Payments, settlements, and remittance systems,Law and justice,Central government administration</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1996</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Finance</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Banking systems; Central registry; Clearing
            agreements; Computer programs; Data processing equipment;
            Debt repayments; Financial institutions; Government
            securities; Liquidation; Payments systems; Public debt;
            Rural finance; Technical assistance; Training
            Accounting,ADB,asset
            sales,Auditing,auditors,audits,authority,authorization,bank
            examination,bank liquidation,bank management,Bank of
            Japan,Bank Restructuring,bank statements,bank
            supervision,Banking Law,banking operations,banking
            sector,banking system,bankruptcy,capital
            markets,capitalization,central bank,Central Bank
            Law,clearing house,clearing systems,commercial banks,credit
            policies,credit unions,Debt,deposits,economic
            conditions,Economics,enactment,enterprise
            restructuring,EXCHANGE RATES,execution,expenditure,financial
            difficulties,Financial Institutions,financial
            intermediation,Financial Reporting,financial
            resources,financial restructuring,Financial Sector,Financial
            Sector Reform,financial sectors,financial services,financial
            system,financial systems,FISCAL,FISCAL YEAR,foreign
            banks,foreign exchange,foreign investors,government
            securities,Government
            Support,guidelines,insolvency,insolvent,insolvent
            banks,institutional reforms,Insurance,interest
            rates,international environment,International
            Finance,International Monetary Fund,laws,lawyer,Legal
            Framework,legislation,liability
            management,Liquidation,liquidity,liquidity management,market
            economies,Ministry of Finance,monetary
            policy,mortgages,payment systems,portfolios,private
            banking,Privatization,problem banks,profitability,Public
            Debt,rationalization,Reorganization,resource
            mobilization,risk management,savings,Securities,settlements
            systems,Special Drawing Rights,specialized
            banks,stabilization,State Agency,State Property,state-owned
            enterprises,structural adjustment,Technical Assistance,Trading
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private/Financial Sectors Devt (ECSPF)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Central Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Commonwealth of Independent States</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF034008-KYRGYZ REPUBLIC - FINANCIAL
            SECTOR ADJUSTMENT</trustfund>
        <repnb>T6896</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>NBFI</ml:concept><ml:concept>Non Bank Financial Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Non-Banking Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nonbanking Financial Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Instruments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems &amp; Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Securities Settlement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Settlement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Resolution and Business Exit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance for Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mortgages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Settlement of Investment Disputes</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Resolution and Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Non-Bank Financial Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>State Associations</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Kyrgyzstan</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>