<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. 14702-EC&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
May 3, 1996&#13;
Natural Resources Management and Rural Poverty Division&#13;
Country Department III&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean Regional Office&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Currency Unit - Sucre (SI.)&#13;
Official Exchange Rate Effective June 1995&#13;
US$1.00 = S/. 2,533.93&#13;
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES&#13;
1 metric ton (m ton)  =       2.205 pound (lb)&#13;
I hectare (ha)        =       2.47 acres&#13;
1 kilometer (lum)            0.62 miles (mi)&#13;
1 meter (m)           =       3.28 feet (ft)&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
AgGDP         - Agricultural Gross Domestic Product&#13;
CAS           - Country Assistance Strategy&#13;
CIAT          - Research Center for Tropical Agriculture&#13;
CIP           - International Potato Center&#13;
CIRAD         - International Center for Cooperation in Agronornic Research for&#13;
Development&#13;
CONUEP        - National Council for Universities and Polytechnics&#13;
COTESU        - Swiss Fund for Technical Cooperation&#13;
EA            - Environmental Assessment&#13;
ENAC          - State Enterprise for Agricultural Marketing&#13;
FUNDAGRO    - Foundation for Agricultural Development&#13;
GOE           - Government of Ecuador&#13;
GTT           - Technology Transfer Groups&#13;
IDB           - Inter-America Development Bank&#13;
LDRC          - International Development Research Center (Canada)&#13;
INDA          - National Institute for Agricultural Development&#13;
IDEA          - Institute for Agricultuwal Strategy&#13;
IERAC         - Ecuadorian Institute for Land Reform and Settlement&#13;
INERHI        - Ecuadorian Institute for Water Resources&#13;
INIAP         - National Institute for Agriculture and Livestock Research&#13;
ISNAR         - International Service for International Agricultural Research&#13;
MAG           - Ministry of Agriculture&#13;
NARS          - National Agricultural Research System&#13;
NGO           - Non-Government Organization&#13;
OM            - Operational Manual&#13;
PIU            - Project Implementation Unit&#13;
PRONADER    - National Rural Development Program&#13;
PROFOGAN    - Livestock Development Program&#13;
PROTECA       - Agricultural and Livestock Technology Development Program&#13;
SOE           - Statement of Expenditure&#13;
USAID         - U.S. Aid for International Development&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January 1 - December 31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
LOAN AND PROJECT SUMMARY                                                          i&#13;
2. COUNTRY AND SECTOR BACKGROUND                                                        I&#13;
A. Macroeconomic Context                                                              1&#13;
B. Agriculture in the Economy                                                         2&#13;
C. Agricultural Institutions and Services                                             3&#13;
Research                                                                         3&#13;
Extension                                                                        4&#13;
Plant and Animal Health                                                          5&#13;
3. AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH                                                                5&#13;
A. Research Expenditures                                                              S&#13;
B. Government Agricultural Technology Strategy                                        6&#13;
Public Private Roles                                                             6&#13;
C. Bank Experience in Agricultural Sector Lending                                     7&#13;
4. THE PROJECT                                                                          8&#13;
A. Origin and Rationale for World Bank Involvement                                    8&#13;
B. Economic Evaluation                                                                9&#13;
C. Project Objectives  &gt;                                                             11&#13;
D. Project DescrIlption                                                              11&#13;
A Diversified, Interactive and Competitive System                               11&#13;
This report is based on the work of a World Bank mnission which visited Ecuador between May 22 and&#13;
June 2 1995. The mnission comprised of Matthew A. McMahon (Task Manager), William B. Johnson&#13;
(Financial Analyst, LA3NR), and Ms. Nohelia Mejia (Consultant). The peer reviewers were:&#13;
Ms. Gabrielle Persley (ESDAR), and Ms. Andrea Silverman (LA2NR). The Division Chief is&#13;
Mr. Nicholas Kraffl and the Director is Mr. Paul Isenrnan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Research Priorities                                                             12&#13;
Research - Extension Linkages                                                   13&#13;
E. Project Components                                                                13&#13;
Competitive Grants                                                              13&#13;
Strengthening INIAP                                                             14&#13;
Project Implementation Unit                                                     16&#13;
Status of Project Preparation: Project Year One                                 16&#13;
Project Costs and Financing                                                     17&#13;
Procurement                                                                     18&#13;
Disbursement and Special Account                                                19&#13;
Accounting and Auditing                                                         21&#13;
5. PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION                                                              21&#13;
Organization and Management                                                     21&#13;
Executive Council                                                               21&#13;
The Project Implementation Unit                                                 22&#13;
Management of the Competitive Grants                                            22&#13;
Peer Review Panel                                                               23&#13;
Operational Manual                                                              23&#13;
Processing Proposals for Competitive Research Grants, and Research and Education Exchange&#13;
Partnerships                                                                    24&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation                                                       25&#13;
Project Benefits                                                                26&#13;
Project Risks                                                                   26&#13;
Environmental Impact                                                            26&#13;
Poverty Alleviation                                                             27&#13;
6. AGREEMENTS AND RECOMMENDATION                                                       27&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
I - Loan and Project Summary Costs                                              30&#13;
2 - Organization Chart                                                          33&#13;
3 - Ecuador's Agricultural Research System                                      34&#13;
4 - Economic Evaluation                                                         44&#13;
5 - Guidelines for the Competitive Research Grants Program and Research and Education&#13;
Exchange Partnerships                                                           52&#13;
6 - Priorities for Research                                                     61&#13;
7 - Key Performance Indicators for Project Monitoring                           70&#13;
8 - Key Performance Indicators for Project Impact Evaluation                    74&#13;
9 - Audit Requirements                                                          75&#13;
10 - Project Implementation Schedule                                            78&#13;
11 - Bank Staff Inputs for Project Supervision                                  82&#13;
12 - Documents on Project File                                                  83&#13;
MAP IBRD No. 27174&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
LOAN AND PROJECT SUMMARY&#13;
Borrower:                Republic of Ecuador.&#13;
Implementing Agency:    Project Implementation Unit in the Ministry of Agriculture.&#13;
Beneficiaries:           Farmers, growers associations, universities, and the private&#13;
sector.&#13;
Poverty:                 While the project is not a direct poverty intervention it has&#13;
important implications for rural poverty as the research&#13;
priorities being financed under the project are of importance&#13;
to small farmners as illustrated in the recent Ecuador Poverty&#13;
Report (June 30, 1995).&#13;
Loan Amount:             US$21.0 million, including US$1 million to be&#13;
financed retroactively.&#13;
Terms:                   To be repaid in 21 years, including 7 years of grace, with a&#13;
LIBOR based standard interest rate for single currency&#13;
loans.&#13;
Commitment Fee:          0.75 percent on undisbursed loan balances,&#13;
beginning 60 days after signing, less any waiver.&#13;
Financing Plan:          See para. 3.25.&#13;
Net Present Value:       An economic evaluation of both research and&#13;
extension, the latter being financed by IDB, gave an&#13;
estimated NPV of US$389 million, using a discount&#13;
rate of 12 percent.&#13;
Map:                     IBRD No. 27174&#13;
Project Identification&#13;
Number:                  EC-PA-7131&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
1. COUNTRY AND SECTOR BACKGROUND&#13;
A. Macroeconomic Context&#13;
1.1         Prior to 1992, Ecuador discriminated against agriculture for most of thirty&#13;
years, as it followed an import substitution model of industrialization for economic&#13;
development. The effects of this policy, which included high tariffs, subsidized interest&#13;
rates and an expansionary fiscal policy, were accentuated by the petroleum boom of the&#13;
1970s that led to an overvalued exchange rate. The net result was that the model&#13;
subsidized industry and urban dwellers, and discriminated heavily against agriculture and&#13;
rural areas. Certain compensatory measures, such as subsidized credit, public sector&#13;
irrigation and mechanization subsidies benefited only a small group of select farmers.&#13;
1.2         The present Government has implemented a series of macroeconomic&#13;
policy reforms, building on thoseintroduced by Governments in the 1980s.1 Tariff and&#13;
non-tariff barriers to trade have been reduced substantially or removed, interest rates are&#13;
market determined, exchange rates are allowed to fluctuate, energy prices have been&#13;
increased, privatization of Government enterprises has started, and the Government has&#13;
followed a more conservative fiscal policy. In all, over 30,000 public sector jobs have&#13;
been eliminated.&#13;
1.3         The Government also has implemented some sectoral policy reforms for&#13;
agriculture, based on a program of modernization of the public sector. The state system&#13;
of agricultural price supports has been eliminated, except for a few export crops, and&#13;
storage silos sold or leased out. A new Agrarian Law has been passed which will make&#13;
land and water markets more efficient, and which eliminates the outdated land reform law.&#13;
IERAC (now INDA), the land titling agency, is in the process of being restructured.&#13;
Restrictions on agricultural exports have been removed. Irigation policy has been&#13;
reformed with; the substantial downsizing of INERHI, the regionalization of public&#13;
projects, the shifting of operation and maintenance of public systems to private water&#13;
users, and the introduction of mechanisms for greater cost recovery. In the area of&#13;
agricultural research, through a law passed by Congress in 1992, the National Institute for&#13;
Agriculture and Livestock Research (INIAP) was awarded administrative autonomy and&#13;
access to an endowment fund paid for by the National Treasury. Both the IDB and the&#13;
World Bank have strongly supported all of these reforms through the IDB Sector Loan,&#13;
and the World Bank Technical Assistance Project for Irrigation.&#13;
Whitaker, Morris D. and Duty Greene 1990. "Development Policy and Agriculture: An Historical&#13;
Perspective" in Agriculture and Economic Survival: The Role ofAgriculture in Ecuadors&#13;
Development. Edited by Morris D. Whitaker and Dale Colyer. Boulder, CO: Westview Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2&#13;
1.4         However, reforms to the sector are still not complete. Reference prices are&#13;
still being maintained for exports of coffee, cacao and bananas. ENAC still is involved in&#13;
price supports through the market for CDs. Water rights can only be transferred with&#13;
land, unless there is specific Government approval. And several Government agencies still&#13;
need to be restructured or privatized.&#13;
1.5         The net effect of the macroeconomic and sectoral reforms, referred to&#13;
above, is to increase incentives for agriculture and thereby create the conditions for it to&#13;
be a dynamic and sustainable contributor to the overall economy. This in turn, will&#13;
provide a much more positive basis upon which the modernization of the agricultural&#13;
research system can proceed. These changes will put new demands on the system and it's&#13;
on this basis that the project is designed.&#13;
B. Agriculture in the Economy&#13;
1.6         Agriculture is still the dominant sector of the Ecuadoran economy. In&#13;
1994 it accounted for 17 percent of GDP, 33 percent of foreign exchange earnings, and is&#13;
the major source of employment in the economy accounting for 35 percent of formal and&#13;
the bulk of informal employment. After a period of slow growth prior to 1980, the sector&#13;
has shown impressive growth over the past decade and a half, having risen from&#13;
13.2 percent in 1980 to 17 percent of GDP in 1994. However, physical growth came&#13;
almost exclusively from an expansion in area. Yield data for the seven principal crops&#13;
show that the average growth in production, between 1980 and 1992 was 3.58 percent per&#13;
annum, with area expansion at 4.55 percent and yields declining at a rate of -0.93 percent&#13;
per annum.2 The growth in animal production is also reflected in the increase in the area&#13;
dedicated to pastures, which has increased from 2.1 million ha in 1974 to 4.9 million ha in&#13;
1992.&#13;
1.7         Ecuadoran agriculture in general is characterized by low yields. A&#13;
comparison with Colombia, where the range of crops and growing conditions are similar,&#13;
shows yields of the main crops in Ecuador ranging from 52 percent to 27 percent lower&#13;
than those in Colombia. Even in the case of its main export crop, bananas, technology&#13;
levels fall will behind that of its main competitors. Under this scenario, with land&#13;
productivity declining and available land resources diminishing, the development strategy&#13;
must be changed to a "science-based" approach concentrating on the improvement of the&#13;
productivity of sustainable agricultural systems. This will be the challenge of this project.&#13;
2 Ecuador - Agricultural Sector Review 1992.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3&#13;
C. Agricultural Institutions and Services&#13;
Research&#13;
1.8         This activity is carried out by INIAP, universities and the private sector.&#13;
Annual expenditure is calculated at about US$7.4 million, with about 200 scientists being&#13;
engaged in conducting, supporting and managing research.&#13;
1.9         INIAP which was founded in 1959 as the research institute of the Ministry&#13;
of Agriculture has been the prime recipient of public funds for agricultural research. It has&#13;
seven research stations and a number of experimental farms and conducts research on&#13;
about thirty different crop and livestock species. Part of its land is used for seed&#13;
production and commercial farming. Over the years, from being a well-focused&#13;
organization that produced good results, it developed into a very weak organization that&#13;
maintained little of its original objectives. From the foundation of INIAP up to 1975,&#13;
public investments in agricultural research increased steadily, reaching a high of&#13;
0.85 percent of AgGDP in 1975. This level of investment compared very favorably with&#13;
that of other LAC countries. However, since then, public investments have been&#13;
drastically reduced and were only 0.25 percent of AgGDP in 1992. The result was a&#13;
serious decline in INIAPs executive and scientific capacity. Simultaneously, due to&#13;
political pressures it expanded its program beyond its budgetary capacity, reducing its&#13;
operational funds and making it very unattractive for good researchers to stay.&#13;
1.10        To overcome this downward spiral the Congress approved a law in 1992&#13;
giving INIAP administrative autonomy. Along with this autonomy it was assigned by law&#13;
an endowment fund of approximately US$10 million. This endowment fund is to be&#13;
added to yearly by the National Treasury. This autonomy - although the institute is still&#13;
almost totally dependent for its budget on the MAG - has brought many changes to the&#13;
organization. It has set its own salary scale, has reduced its personnel by about 30 percent&#13;
and is now developing a new set of research priorities. This is an ongoing process with&#13;
the objective of a smaller, better focused and more relevant institution. Following the&#13;
recent downsizing INIAP has six Ph.D., 65 M.S., and 123 other graduates (including&#13;
those in training) in a total staff of 433. Its 1995 budget is of the order of US$4.2 million&#13;
(see Annex 3).&#13;
1.11        In the case of universities, most have limited research equipment, lands&#13;
and libraries. Although there are 25 faculties of agricultural and veterinary science, many&#13;
faculty are part-time and of a total of 1,253 professional staff in 1992, only 70 had&#13;
M.S. degrees and nine had Ph.Ds. In theory, university research should be well funded by&#13;
the National Council for Universities (CONUEP) which is supposed to receive one&#13;
percent of GDP for research grants. In practice the Government has never met this&#13;
obligation and in 1992 CONUEP received only US$1.3 million or under 0.01 percent of&#13;
GDP. About 20 percent of this is allocated for projects in the agriculture sector. In&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4&#13;
addition to CONUEP funds, some universities have been able to solicit funds from&#13;
international and local sources. These are usually for small projects (see Annex 3).&#13;
1.12         The participation of the private sector in the generation of technology has&#13;
been increasing in recent years. It now funds and executes research in a variety of&#13;
commodities, such as maize, banana, coffee, palm oil, horticultural crops, flowers, milk&#13;
processing and a variety of other activities. These activities are concentrated in the&#13;
applied end of the research spectrum such as the development of hybrid seeds, field testing&#13;
of agrochemical, in vitro reproduction of plant materials, etc., and are an important source&#13;
of ready to use technology. A recent study4 of private sector agricultural research identified&#13;
nine organizations that were involved in some depth, with 22 professionals and 24 technicians,&#13;
including three Ph.Ds and M.Scs. These are much smaller numbers of researchers than at&#13;
INIAP although their estimated 1991 annual budget (US$3.1 million) was 75 percent as large.&#13;
This was attributable to better salaries and a much higher technician to researcher ratio.&#13;
Research is also being carried out in Ecuador by foreign research institutes (e.g., CIRAD, CIP,&#13;
CIAT), usually in collaboration with INIAP and is often funded by donors such as COTESU,&#13;
USAID or IDRC (CEOD).&#13;
1.13         Farmers associations have not as yet been an important source of financing&#13;
for agricultural research. They usually place more emphasis on policy activities where&#13;
they defend the interests of their associates. However in some cases they have financed&#13;
agricultural extension in a very limited way. The Government is currently processing new&#13;
legislation to promote the formation of producer associations (gremios) and this could have a&#13;
mraor influence on the direction of research in the future. Financial support from farmers will&#13;
be critical for the long-term sustainability of the research system, because it is through such&#13;
support that farmers research needs can be expressed, leading to a more demand-driven&#13;
system.&#13;
Extension&#13;
1.14         Public agricultural extension in Ecuador exists since 1945, having been&#13;
financed under a variety of programs and donors. In recent times the largest effort in this&#13;
area has been the Agricultural and Livestock Technology Development Program&#13;
(PROTECA), which had an extension component, and which was financed by the Inter-&#13;
American Development Bank (IDB) and executed by MAG. This project terminated in&#13;
September 1994. This program financed about 500 public extensionists to give technical&#13;
assistance to about 85,000 small and medium sized farmers. However, the MAG has not&#13;
institutionalized the system and when the project finished there were about 400 trained&#13;
extensionists available to be employed in other activities.&#13;
1.15         Besides PROTECA there have been other donor funded projects in&#13;
agricultural extension such as: the Research, Extension and Education Project funded by&#13;
4 Falcoi, Ccsa A. 1992, Public and Private Sector Interactions in Agricultural Research in Less-&#13;
Developed Countries: The Case ofEcuador. ISNAR.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5&#13;
USAID and executed by FUNDAGRO; the Technology Transfer Groups (GTT) funded&#13;
by Swiss Aid (COTESU) and executed by INIAP; the Livestock Development Program&#13;
(PROFOGAN) funded by the German Government and executed by MAG and some&#13;
universities; and the agricultural extension component of the PRONADER project funded&#13;
by the World Bank. For the past thirty years, many NGOs, both national and international&#13;
have been active in the area of agricultural extension. These organizations have worked&#13;
with the poorest farmers in the marginal areas.&#13;
1.16        IDB has prepared an agricultural extension project, as a part of the&#13;
Modernization of Agricultural Services Program, which also includes this project. The&#13;
extension project will focus both on competitive and small farmer agriculture. It aims to&#13;
increase the participation of the private sector by contracting implementation of the&#13;
project to private firms and in the case of competitive agriculture by introducing cost&#13;
recovery mechanisms which in the long run should lead to greater private sector&#13;
participation in the financing of the service.&#13;
Plant and Animal Health&#13;
1.17        These activities are presently executed by specific programs within MAG&#13;
under the direction of the Technical Subsecretary. Present activities of the Government&#13;
are concentrated in the areas of import and export quarantine, control of the movement of&#13;
animal and vegetable products, disease and pest control programs, register and control of&#13;
agriculture and veterinary products, diagnostic laboratories, control of packing houses and&#13;
the inspection of meat and other agricultural products. These services have been&#13;
characterized by the lack of operating budget and adequately trained personnel. Because&#13;
of this, the results have not been very good, with the entry of new pests and diseases&#13;
adding to the problems caused by the traditional endemic ones. There have been other&#13;
complications such as an increase in the residues of antibiotics, pesticides and other&#13;
contaminants found in food supplies. EDB has prepared a project for the establishment of&#13;
a new national Plant and Animal Health Service, as part of the Modernization of&#13;
Agricultural Services Program.&#13;
2. AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH&#13;
A. Research Expenditures&#13;
2.1         The greater part of agricultural research in Ecuador is funded by the public&#13;
sector. Public expenditure on agricultural research can be justified for a number of&#13;
reasons, the three principal ones being: "market failure" because firms or individuals&#13;
cannot capture sufficient benefits to justify the investment; natural resource research which&#13;
benefits all of society; and social equity. As Ecuador looks to the future and the need to&#13;
increase its investments in agricultural research, neither the public nor the private sectors&#13;
alone will be capable of responding to the research needs of the sector. One of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6&#13;
challenges will be to develop funding systems that use both public and private resources in&#13;
an efficient way.&#13;
2.2         Public investments in agricultural research (in INIAP and the universities)&#13;
have declined steadily in real terms since 1975. Public research expenditures as a share of&#13;
AgGDP also declined steadily after 1975 and were only .25 percent in 1993 compared to a&#13;
high of .85 percent in 1975. While no historical data are available on private sector&#13;
investments in agricultural research, it is clear that the sector has increased its investments&#13;
as Government support eroded. It is estimated that total (public plus private) research&#13;
investment in 1993 to be US$7.4 million or .43 percent of AgGDP, which is only slightly&#13;
above fifty percent of the level of public investment in 1975 (see Annex 3).&#13;
2.3         While there are empirical recommendations as to an appropriate level of&#13;
investment in agricultural research there is no simple formula available to determine how&#13;
much money should be invested and subjective judgment is relied on when making such&#13;
decisions. This being the case, then an important criterion for Ecuador should be the level&#13;
of investment of its competitors and short to medium term projections for investment&#13;
should be brought in line with these levels.&#13;
2.4         Even with private sector research, Ecuador has made very limited&#13;
investments in comparison to the rest of the developing world. Data for 52 developing&#13;
countries showed an average investment in agricultural research of .94 percent of AgGDP&#13;
during 1980-1985, up from .69 percent during 1970-1979. Thus, Ecuador sharply&#13;
reduced its investments in agricultural research while most of its competitors were&#13;
increasing their investments. Ecuador compares quite poorly with its regional trading&#13;
partners in terms of investments in agricultural research. According to IDB, in 1993 Peru&#13;
invested close to one percent of its AgGDP in agricultural research (not including private&#13;
sector investments) or four times more than Ecuador. Colombia also invested more than&#13;
Ecuador, at 0.5 percent of its AgGDP in 1991. These bordering countries are Ecuador&#13;
most important competitors in the Andean Pact, both for lucrative export markets in the&#13;
U.S. and Europe, and for provision of food and fiber supplies in the region. The fact that&#13;
Peru and Colombia are investing so much more in agricultural research puts significant&#13;
pressure on Ecuador to increase its investments and reform its research system (see&#13;
Annex 3).&#13;
B. Government Agricultural Technology Strategy&#13;
Public Private Roles&#13;
2.5         Research activities are spread across a continuum that ranges from basic at&#13;
one end through strategic and applied research to adaptive research at the other end.&#13;
Depending on the appropriability of the results and the level of risk involved, private and&#13;
public sectors can participate and interact along that continuum. Practice has shown that&#13;
private sector efforts are more concentrated in the applied and adaptive end of the&#13;
continuum whereas public funding focuses on basic and strategic research activities along&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7&#13;
with areas that have to do with social equity, poverty alleviation and the environment. In&#13;
an effective system public and private research complement each other, because each&#13;
sector is involved in different types of activities along the research spectrum. Historically,&#13;
public investment has been the springboard for private involvement in research in&#13;
developed countries.&#13;
2.6         It is generally accepted that in countries with the same level of&#13;
development as Ecuador that there is a large public good component in agricultural&#13;
research. However, as the economy develops further the private sector will participate to&#13;
an increasing degree. It is important to define in principle the public good component of&#13;
research and to have funding mechanisms in place that can respond to the system as it&#13;
evolves to increasing private sector participation.&#13;
2.7          The strategy of the present Government is to revitalize the agricultural&#13;
research system by; increasing overall funding and putting in place incentives, in the form&#13;
of funding mechanisms, that will increase the participation of other organizations (private&#13;
sector, universities and NGOs) both in the implementation and financing of research.&#13;
C. Bank Experience in Agricultural Sector Lending&#13;
2.8         Bank projects in Ecuador have repeatedly encountered weaknesses in&#13;
public sector management and coordination. These include excessive bureaucracy,&#13;
inadequate personnel incentive structures, and shortages of trained people at all levels.&#13;
The institutional capacity to absorb technical assistance is frequently limited. Leadership&#13;
mandates are often superficial and/or fleeting and agency management turns over&#13;
frequently. Projects require the explicit definition of issues and objectives during&#13;
identification and preparation, and a tight focus on a limited number of components.&#13;
Careful attention is needed to limiting the longer-term burden on the recurrent budget, and&#13;
human resource development should be given high priority. Regular, intensive supervision&#13;
is needed to keep components on track.&#13;
2.9         The Bank has supported and continues to support agricultural research in a&#13;
number of ways; as freestanding research projects, as components in rural development&#13;
projects, in education projects and in policy-based lending. Since the beginning of FY78&#13;
the Bank has been involved in freestanding research projects with total project costs of&#13;
US$3.8 billion and a loan amount of US$1.7 billion. Research components in other&#13;
projects have cost close to US$2.0 billion with a loan amount of US$0.5 billion.&#13;
According to the OED database, the results have been relatively favorable with 78 percent&#13;
rated as "satisfactory". Despite this positive rating common problems have been identified&#13;
across the range of projects. These problems are; inadequate counterpart funding,&#13;
overdimensioning in relation to prospective resources, lack of capacity to plan and set&#13;
research priorities, and lack of demand driven research.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
3. THE PROJECT&#13;
A. Origin and Rationale for World Bank Involvement&#13;
3.1         The 1992 Ecuador Agricultural Sector Review highlighted three broad&#13;
problems facing the agricultural sector: (i) unrealized sectoral growth; (ii) deforestation&#13;
and soil erosion from rapid expansion of the crop and livestock frontiers, raising serious&#13;
concerns about the sustainability of sectoral growth; and (iii) acute and widespread rural&#13;
poverty. This project addresses (i) and (ii) through strengthening the agricultural research&#13;
system so as to increase productivity and thereby have more efficient growth and less&#13;
exploitation of the natural resource base. While it is not a direct poverty intervention it&#13;
has important implications for rural poverty as the research priorities, i. e., rice, potatoes,&#13;
maize, etc., being financed under the project are of importance to small farmers as&#13;
illustrated in the recent Poverty Report (June 30, 1995). As the project is expected to&#13;
increase agricultural productivity it will also increase economic opportunities in rural areas&#13;
and halt the deterioration of the natural resource base which is tightly linked to rural&#13;
poverty. Through increased food production it will also maintain an adequate supply of&#13;
cheap food for poor consumers. This project is fully consistent with the CAS that is being&#13;
presented to the Board on April 4, 1996, and would support three of the broad objectives&#13;
for Ecuador: poverty alleviation, by focusing research on basic food commodities grown&#13;
by resource poor farmers; institutional strengthening, by modernizing INRAP through its&#13;
Development Plan; and private sector development, by opening research funding to a&#13;
range of institutions, including foundations, universities and NGOs.&#13;
3.2          The project is a component of the Modernization of Agricultural Services&#13;
Program by the Ministry of Agriculture. The other two components, Technology&#13;
Transfer and Plant and Animal Health are being financed separately by IDB for a total&#13;
project cost of US$41 million (paras. 1.16 and 1.17). The overall program which will be&#13;
managed by the Project Implementation Unit within MAG, is aimed at strengthening the&#13;
range of public services needed for a modern and competitive agricultural sector.&#13;
3.3         The justification for public investments in agricultural research is that some&#13;
of the results of such an activity are public goods. Private agents do not have the full&#13;
incentives to invest in such goods. Public subsidies, rather than full cost recovery from&#13;
agricultural producers benefiting from research are also justified, because benefits from&#13;
such research flow to consumers and the environment. They flow to consumers via long-&#13;
term commodity price decreases which affect the poorer classes disproportionately in a&#13;
beneficial way, and the environment benefits through more efficient use of natural&#13;
resources. This latter is very important in Ecuador as most of its agricultural growth in&#13;
the last fifteen years has come from expanding area under cultivation and pastures thereby&#13;
increasing erosion and lowering biodiversity. Under the economic framework of more&#13;
open markets and increased trade, Ecuador will be under increased pressure to modernize&#13;
its agriculture and compete internationally. Because of new developments in science, of&#13;
which the country has not taken advantage for at least fifteen years, and the present low&#13;
productivity levels (see Annex 3), the agricultural research system is presented with new&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9&#13;
demands and also opportunities to lead the sector in renewed and efficient growth. This&#13;
project will assist in orienting this public investment to more efficient uses in line with the&#13;
Governments objectives for agricultural research.&#13;
3.4          Support for the project is also warranted on the basis of past results.&#13;
Although support for agricultural research has unstable and declining over the past twenty&#13;
years in Ecuador, the system has been successful in general and in some areas has made&#13;
major contributions. Joint research on rice by INIAP, universities and international&#13;
agencies resulted in returns of 34 percent between 1970 and 1990. A series of related&#13;
studies carried out by INIAP with support from ISNAR and FUNDAGRO revealed the&#13;
following rates of return to research investments: hard corn, 70 percent; African palm,&#13;
32 percent; potatoes, 33 percent; soybeans, 17 percent; and wheat, 29 percent.5 An&#13;
economic evaluation of both research and extension, the latter being financed by IDB, was&#13;
carried out as part of the initial preparation. This study gave an internal rate of return of&#13;
44.5 percent based on certain assumptions as to changes in productivity and prices. There&#13;
are limitations on the validity of such an evaluation, since not all productivity increases can&#13;
be attributed directly to research and extension alone, and the assumptions are based on&#13;
data from past experience. The full results of the economic evaluation are available in the&#13;
project file (Annex 11).&#13;
B. Economic Evaluation&#13;
3.5          Economic analysis for the project has been carried out to test its economic&#13;
viability. A multiple criteria model has been utilized in light of the fact that agricultural&#13;
research is focused upon different objectives such as: economic growth, distribution of&#13;
income and sustainability; multiple criteria models seem to be more appropriate to&#13;
evaluate the attainment of different objectives. The model used (MODEXC, developed in&#13;
1990 by the International Center for Tropical Agriculture) is a partial equilibrium model&#13;
which evaluates the direct benefits of new technology and associated income distribution&#13;
results.&#13;
3.6          The social benefits and costs for each technological option are estimated&#13;
and benefits of each technology are distributed among specific activities (such as genetic&#13;
improvements or new fertilization systems). This process allows estimation of economic&#13;
efficiency for each activity.&#13;
3.7          The selection of commodities considered under the analysis is based on the&#13;
relative weight that each commodity holds in the gross national agricultural product&#13;
(GNAP). The GNAP used in this case represents the average for years 1991 through&#13;
1993. The result is a group of 16 products that accounts for over 90 percent of the total&#13;
aggregate value of domestic production. Based on INIAP historical data, average annual&#13;
growth rate and price projections are estimated for each commodity (see Annex 4 for&#13;
5 INIAP 1993 Retorno a las Inversiones en Investigacidn Agropecuaria Quito: Direccidn de&#13;
Planificaci6n.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10&#13;
details). These projections have been incorporated in the economic model in order to&#13;
estimate overall technology benefits.&#13;
3.8         Assumptions regarding the following have also been included in the model:&#13;
(a) exogenous growth and demand rates for commodities; (b) the consumption structure&#13;
of commodities relative to beneficiary incomes; (c) farm data representative of&#13;
beneficiaries; (d) yields of new and present technologies; (e) the time required to&#13;
implement and adopt new technologies; (f) the area to which new technologies are&#13;
applied; (g) research required to obtain new technologies and the probability of success for&#13;
such research; and (h) research and technology costs. This data allows for the estimation&#13;
of increased production because of technological change and its adoption by farmers. This&#13;
is purely technical information, taken directly at INIAP's research stations, from&#13;
interviews with different commodity research specialists.&#13;
3.9         Based on the above, the model estimates producers and consumer&#13;
surpluses, separating those that can be ascribed to technological factors. The benefits&#13;
ascribed to the project are estimated to be only thirty percent of the surpluses, multiplied&#13;
by the probability of success (about 75 to 80 percent) for each technology through the&#13;
research and transfer process. As demonstrated in Annex 4, net benefits from the project&#13;
are estimated at nearly US$176 million in year 15. Considering benefit flows for all years&#13;
and the project costs, the NPV for the project is estimated at about US$389 million, using&#13;
a discount rate of 12 percent. The ERR is estimated at 52 percent. These results are in&#13;
line with numerous ex post studies regarding the impact of agriculture research and&#13;
technology projects in Latin America and worldwide.&#13;
3.10        In addition to the overall project benefits estimation, the impact of&#13;
technology application on international trade has been measured. Trade would improve&#13;
significantly, considering that most commodities under the analysis can be exported.&#13;
Based on the consolidated results of MODEXC, it is estimated that the trade surplus for&#13;
these products could grow by 49 percent in the year 2000 and at the end of the project it&#13;
could more than triple.&#13;
3.11        Finally, sensitivity analysis has been carried out for the project to test the&#13;
impact of either overall income decreases or increases. As shown in Annex 4, by&#13;
decreasing benefits such that income resulting from the project fall by 20 percent, the&#13;
estimated internal rate of return would decline by eight percent. This represents a&#13;
reduction in the NPV of about US$95 million. Because of the relatively high NPV and&#13;
return benefits would have to fall by over 80 percent to obtain an NPV of zero. A&#13;
20 percent increase in overall costs yields similar NPV and IRR results. To obtain an&#13;
NPV of zero, costs would have to increase by nearly six times. While these results show&#13;
that project returns are sensitive to movements in overall benefits and costs, the returns&#13;
are high enough that a 20 percent unfavorable shift in either benefits or costs would not&#13;
produce negative overall results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
11&#13;
C. Project Objectives&#13;
3.12         The objective is to strengthen the national capacity to do agricultural&#13;
research, with an aim to increase agricultural productivity and output while preserving or&#13;
enhancing the natural resource base, by: (i) introducing a competitive research grant&#13;
program; (ii) developing Research and Education Exchange partnerships with intemational&#13;
science institutions; and (iii) strengthening the national agricultural research institute,&#13;
NIAP.&#13;
D. Project Description&#13;
A Diversfied, Interactive and Competitive System&#13;
3.13         To achieve the above objectives this project proposes to put in place a new&#13;
technology generation system for Ecuador. The project will create a research capacity&#13;
within the country that will result in a diversified, and interactive and sustainable research&#13;
system. Increasing or diversifying the number of suppliers of technology will by itself&#13;
bring more resources into the system and will provide a broader opportunity for private&#13;
funding sources to participate, thereby contributing to the sustainability of the system.&#13;
Through the competitive funding grants, opportunities will be provided for joint research&#13;
projects to be developed between research entities (research institutes, universities, NGOs&#13;
etc.), and the private sector. Giving the opportunity to farmers groups to cofinance such&#13;
projects will strengthen their ownership of the research system, along with their&#13;
participation on the executive council and their involvement in the discussions for priority&#13;
setting.&#13;
3.14         In the past, little has been done to encourage the integration of the three&#13;
main groups, INLAP, universities and farmers groups, that effectively make up the national&#13;
agricultural research system (NARS) in Ecuador. This all-inclusive concept of a NARS is&#13;
one of the underlying principles of this project. The project will incorporate the largest&#13;
number of research and interest groups as possible. This will help to assure that all&#13;
aspects of needed research can be covered and that the products will provide answers for&#13;
most relevant economic, social and environmental problems.&#13;
3.15         Another principle underlying this project is that of interaction. A modem&#13;
agricultural research system requires regular interaction among the various institutional&#13;
participants and scientists. Linkages between farmers and researchers need to be clearly&#13;
articulated, efficient and regular. Farmers must be able to communicate their concerns to&#13;
researchers quickly and systematically. Through participation in competitive funding&#13;
mechanisms farmers will be able to influence the research agenda. The various research&#13;
institutions must be able to affiliate with each other and work closely together in joint&#13;
research programs, when circumstances warrant. The project through special funding&#13;
mechanisms will develop these linkages and promote joint research programs between&#13;
institutions that will allow them to work together when their collective resources are&#13;
better able to resolve a problem than individual efforts (see Annex 4).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12&#13;
3.16         Another principle underlying this project is competition, which is a required&#13;
element for efficient production of new technical knowledge. The project will utilize the&#13;
concept of competition as the basis for allocating scarce research resources among&#13;
individual researchers and among research institutions. This will allow the system to be&#13;
more responsive to the needs of farmers and be more demand driven.&#13;
Research Priorities&#13;
3.17         Sectoral policy for agriculture in Ecuador encompasses the broad issues of&#13;
equity, efficiency, food security and natural resource conservation. When INIAP was&#13;
established in the mid-sixties its work program revolved around a set of priorities, which&#13;
were developed within the framework of national food self-sufficiency and thereby&#13;
concentrated on the basic food commodities. However, over the years the list of priorities&#13;
was added to indiscriminately through political pressure, and by researchers who set their&#13;
own research agenda.&#13;
3.18         In recent years, INIAP has sponsored in collaboration with ISNAR two&#13;
priority setting exercises to improve the objectivity of research resource allocation. For&#13;
the preparation of this project Fundacion IDEA used an economic surplus model&#13;
developed at CIAT (Colombia) to suggest research priorities. Although these three&#13;
studies resulted in somewhat different specific rankings of priorities there was a high level&#13;
of congruency between all studies when the top ten priorities were taken as a group. The&#13;
studies were also consistent in emphasizing that the most important commodities are those&#13;
from the coastal region. This reflects the change in agricultural production over the past&#13;
thirty years. These priorities have now been accepted by the MAG for funding under the&#13;
project (Annex 6). This exercise in priority setting should be regarded as an iterative&#13;
process of dialogue arnong all the interested parties; producers, Government, and research&#13;
organizations in order to have the flexibility to modify priorities as circumstances demand.&#13;
3.19         INIAP has used its priority setting exercises to establish a research&#13;
progran based on nine national, four regional programs and seven technical departments.&#13;
The nine national programs are: cattle and pastures, rice, corn, roots and tubers, coffee,&#13;
cacao, bananas and plantains, fruits, legumes and agroforestry. The four regional&#13;
programs are: Andean grains, soya, small grain cereals, and swine. The seven technical&#13;
departments are: soil and water, pest management, genetic resources, nutrition,&#13;
biometrics, economics and planning, and information.&#13;
3.20         Since the most important problems that have to be solved are of a practical&#13;
nature the research agenda to be financed under this project will concentrate on the&#13;
applied and adaptive end of the research spectrum. There will also be a strong orientation&#13;
towards products that make up the bulk of small farm production, such as plantains, rice,&#13;
potatoes, maize, coffee and cacao. Natural resource management research, i.e., soil and&#13;
water management, genetic resources, and pest management will also be funded.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13&#13;
Research - Ejtension Linkages&#13;
3.21        This project is part of an overall Modernization of Agricultural Services&#13;
Program being developed by the Ministry of Agriculture which also includes Agricultural&#13;
Extension and Plant and Animal Health, both of which are being financed by IDB.&#13;
Although they are being financed separately, there are operational linkages between&#13;
research and extension which will be financed by the extension component. These&#13;
linkages include the direct contracting of extension services by commercial farmers from&#13;
research entities and the technical training of extension agents by research organizations.&#13;
Since much of the research funded under this project will be applied and adaptive and will&#13;
include "on-farmn" research, the research-extension linkages will be further strengthened.&#13;
E. Project Components&#13;
3.22        The following components have been included in the project:&#13;
(a) Competitive Grants which include research grants, research and educational exchange&#13;
partnerships with international institutions; (b) Strengthening INIAP; and (c) Project&#13;
Implementation. The indicated costs are base costs.&#13;
Competitive Grants&#13;
3.23        This component (US$15,000,000) is divided into two subcomponents:&#13;
(a)   Research Grants (US$7,500,000) will finance individual research&#13;
subprojects, on an open competitive basis with variable grant support, up&#13;
to a maximum level of 75 percent of total subproject cost, a maximum&#13;
subproject cost of US$100,000 each and a maximum life of three years.&#13;
Researchers from universities, NGOs, and INIAP wili be eligible to&#13;
compete for research support in priority areas as established by MAG.&#13;
Private sector researchers will be eligible in partnership with one of these&#13;
entities, and with appropriate matching support. This competitive grant&#13;
system is proposed as a mechanism for: (a) increasing the efficiency of&#13;
allocation of funds for agricultural research; (b) assuring the participation&#13;
of scientists in agricultural research from among the several institutional&#13;
participants; and (c) strengthening interactive linkages between public and&#13;
private sector entities. In the process of judging the scientific merit of any&#13;
proposal for grant support, the following criteria, among others, will have&#13;
to be met:&#13;
* relevance of the proposal to national research priorities;&#13;
* basic capacity of the researcher to do the proposed research, i.e., level&#13;
of experience, sound technical approach, and facilities to do the work;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14&#13;
*  probability of successful outcome and intrinsic merit of the research,&#13;
i.e., will the results serve as the basis for improved technology or as a&#13;
solution for environmental problems that can be applied at the farm&#13;
level?; and&#13;
*  evidence that completing the research will strengthen capacity of the&#13;
proposer in the research area and stimulate further research, education&#13;
and development of manpower in agricultural sciences.&#13;
These subproject selection criteria, along with others, have been agreed&#13;
upon with the Bank and are included in the Operational Manual&#13;
(para. 4.11).&#13;
(b)   Research and Education Exchange Partnerships with International&#13;
Institutions (US$7,500,000) will finance on a competitive basis, the&#13;
formation of Research and Education Exchange partnerships between&#13;
research agencies, universities, key NGOs, and international science&#13;
institutions to facilitate the importation of applicable technology, to&#13;
strengthen the research capacity of Ecuadoran research institutions and to&#13;
strengthen graduate education programs in Ecuadoran universities.&#13;
Competitive grants of up to 50 percent for research and 100 percent for&#13;
scholarships will be awarded to selected participants. Each will be given in&#13;
high priority research areas. Grant funds will be used for joint research&#13;
programs, fellowships, short-term technical assistance, and personnel&#13;
exchanges. Appropriate criteria for awarding these grants will be part of&#13;
the OM (para. 4.11) and will include: the critical nature of the area of&#13;
research; potential contribution to strengthening the national research&#13;
capacity; and the sustainability of the relationship. It will also finance, on a&#13;
competitive basis, the strengthening of graduate teaching and research&#13;
programs based on partnerships with foreign universities as well as high&#13;
priority short-term training. In this way it will build on an important array&#13;
of individual faculty capacity scattered throughout the university/NGO&#13;
system.&#13;
Strengthening INALP&#13;
3.24         This component (US$6,500,000) will strengthen INIAP in the following&#13;
areas:&#13;
(a)   Development Plan (US$100,000). This plan which will be completed&#13;
within the first year of the project and will address the long term&#13;
sustainability of INIAP. The plan will include inter alia: the development&#13;
of a personnel policy; the assignment of personnel in compliance with the&#13;
research priorities to be financed; asset restructuring; role and management&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15&#13;
of the endowment fund; and a financial plan. The Development Plan will&#13;
be used as a basis to develop monitorable indicators for use in the&#13;
Implementation Agreement to be signed by MAG and INIAP for the&#13;
execution of the MNIAP component. The signing of the Implementation&#13;
Agreement will be a condition of disbursement for the other&#13;
subcomponents that follow.&#13;
(b)   Training for Advanced Degrees (US$2,000,000). Fellowship Grants for&#13;
advanced degree training and short-term training will be provided in high&#13;
priority areas. Dissertation or thesis research will be done in Ecuador, as&#13;
part of INIAPs on-going research program. The scholarships will cover&#13;
the costs of tuition, living expenses, and travel.&#13;
(c)   Ecuadoran Scientists as Long-term Consultants (US$2,900,000). The&#13;
project will finance about 22 Ecuadoran research scientists (10 Ph.Ds and&#13;
12 Masters) at local consulting salaries. This will jump-start the research&#13;
program of INIAP that is now depleted of qualified personnel and will put&#13;
in place effective research programs into which Ph.D. and Master students&#13;
can return. These consultafits will be hired for priority research areas only.&#13;
While they will be employed for the duration of the project, the successful&#13;
implementation of INLAPs Development Plan should ensure that these&#13;
consultants can be maintained as staff by INIAP once the project&#13;
terminates.&#13;
(d)   International Senior Agricultural Scientists (US$300,000). About&#13;
25 man/months of short-term support from senior agricultural scientists&#13;
and their institutions will be provided in critical research areas and for&#13;
research administration. Such scientists will be from leading research&#13;
institutions and their home research institution will provide the advisor on a&#13;
cost reimbursable basis. These advisors will be senior researchers with&#13;
experience in research funding and administration, as well as current&#13;
credentials in research. The institutional linkage will facilitate the further&#13;
integration of international researchers into Ecuador nascent agricultural&#13;
science system, and from the international science network more generally.&#13;
(e)   Equipment, Vehicles, Rehabilitation of Laboratories, and Libraries&#13;
(US$1,200,000). In terms of physical plant, INIAPs highest priority is for&#13;
rehabilitating and modernizing the research stations, including electricity&#13;
and water supply. The subcomponent will finance: the rehabilitation of the&#13;
existing facilities - civil works (US$700,000) and vehicles and equipment&#13;
(US$500,000), including laboratory equipment, vehicles and farm&#13;
machinery, library materials and equipment including software and&#13;
hardware to support an information system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16&#13;
Project Implementation Unit&#13;
3.25        The overall implementation of the project (US$3,300,000), will be the&#13;
responsibility of the Project Implementation Unit (PIU) which has been established by&#13;
MAG. It will contract the technical aspects, such as the evaluation and selection of the&#13;
Competitive Grants, to a NGO with expertise in this area.&#13;
3.26        The PIU will administer and promote the project and will be the main&#13;
contact for the Bank for project implementation. The PIU will prepare an Annual Work&#13;
Plan, including budget, for all work under its supervision, along with annual financial&#13;
statements. This subcomponent will finance technical assistance, vehicles and equipment,&#13;
contracted staff salaries, office supplies and overhead.&#13;
3.27        Technical assistance will include the implementation of a supervision,&#13;
monitoring and evaluation system for investments in Research and Education Exchange&#13;
partnership subprojects. It will also include the promotion and training of participating&#13;
entities in preparing proposals for grant funding consideration; the preparation of a project&#13;
performance report to be used as a basis for a comprehensive midterm review; the end-&#13;
evaluation of the project which will assess, inter alia, the impact of the project and&#13;
xletermine if the Government should prepare a follow-up project; and other technical&#13;
assistance, including training, to support the implementation of the project.&#13;
3.28        The management of the competitive components of the project will be&#13;
awarded under a single contract to a NGO (US$2,100,000). The NGO will be responsible&#13;
for the review, selection and administration of the Research subprojects and the Research&#13;
and Education Exchange Partnerships. The NGO will: invite proposals; review the&#13;
technical and financial aspects of the proposals; through a Peer Review Panel, select&#13;
subprojects; draft cofinancing contracts for the approved subprojects; and supervise&#13;
subproject implementation. Under this subcomponent, the project will finance a service&#13;
contract that will include technical assistance, the Peer Review Panel, consultant salaries,&#13;
office supplies and overheads, including the management fee.&#13;
Status of Project Preparation: Project Year One&#13;
3.29        INIAP is preparing the terms of reference for the preparation of its&#13;
Development Plan and will have selected the consultants by May 31, 1996. An invitation&#13;
for research proposals, will be sent out, and proposals will be reviewed by&#13;
October 1, 1996. MAG will prepare the Annual Work Plan including Budget for 1997 by&#13;
October 31, 1996. Students for graduate training will be selected by October 31, 1996.&#13;
MAG will prepare the TORs for the implementation of the monitoring and evaluation&#13;
system along with those for the promotion and training for the project by October 31,&#13;
1996 and will have selected the respective consultants by November 30, 1996. For the&#13;
NGO contract to manage the technical aspects of the program, MAG has sent to the&#13;
Bank a draft consultants contract and will select the NGO by September 30, 1996.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17&#13;
Project Costs and Financing&#13;
3.30        The estimated total project cost is US$27 million, including US$2.2 million&#13;
for contingencies (as detailed in Annex 1). Costs were calculated using January 1996&#13;
prices and include a physical contingency of five percent on institutional strengthening&#13;
components. Expected price increases over the financing period were calculated using&#13;
Bank current projections for international inflation.&#13;
3.31        The Republic of Ecuador will be the Borrower. It was agreed at&#13;
negotiations that the financial terms be modified so that the loan be a US dollar loan at the&#13;
standard interest rate for LIBOR based US dollar, single currency loans. It was also&#13;
agreed that the amortization terms for this loan benefit from the decision to finance the&#13;
Environment TA loan on fixed-rate US dollar loan terms. The shorter maturity for that&#13;
loan (13 years) enables this loan to be financed with a 21-year maturity, including seven&#13;
years grace, somewhat longer than standard country terms for Ecuador of 20 years,&#13;
including five years grace. The Government of Ecuador has requested a LIBOR-based&#13;
US dollar single currency loan in the context of its external debt management strategy.&#13;
Ecuador's net trade position is largely US dollar denominated, and Ecuador would like to&#13;
increase the share of US dollars in its overall liability portfolio to reduce its currency risk.&#13;
It has selected the LIBOR-based interest rate in order to better tailor the repayment terms&#13;
of this loan. The Government is aware of the resulting interest rate risk it is taking, since&#13;
most of its external commercial debt is also indexed to LIBOR. The Government will&#13;
make the loan available to MAG to finance project components. MAG will cofinance,&#13;
with participating entities, the Competitive Research Grant Program and the Research and&#13;
Education Exchange Partnerships. MAG will also finance the strengthening of INIAP;&#13;
and the management and administration of the project.&#13;
3.32        The project will be financed by a Bank loan of US$21 million (78 percent&#13;
of total project cost), including US$1 million in retroactive financing. This will cover&#13;
100 percent of the estimated foreign exchange costs and 68 percent of the local costs.&#13;
The balance of project costs will be financed by Government (US$3.1 million, or&#13;
11.5 percent), and by participating research groups, i.e., universities, farmer groups and&#13;
NGOs, (US$2.9 million, or 10.7 percent). MAG will finance all Competitive Grants&#13;
including Partnerships, at an average of 65 percent of total subproject costs, financing at&#13;
75 percent for the first US$4.5 million, 65 percent for the next US$4.5 million and&#13;
55 percent thereafter (para 5.1 (c) (iii)). Adequate funding will be made available to the&#13;
project, by allocating funds in the annual budget for the following year according to the&#13;
proposals to be submitted to the Bank no later than October 31 of each year following the&#13;
requirements specified in the projects Annual Work Plans (para. 5.1 (c) (i)). The&#13;
Government will provide adequate working capital to the PIU by depositing, in advance,&#13;
in the PIU account its share of the equivalent of one month's operating expenses&#13;
(para 5.1 (c) (ii)).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18&#13;
Procurement&#13;
3.33        Procurement of goods, works and contracting services financed by the&#13;
Bank under the project will follow procedures acceptable to the Bank (Guidelines&#13;
Procurement under Bank Loans and IDA Credits, January 1995). As applicable, standard&#13;
bidding documents for National Competitive Bidding (NCB) will be agreed upon and&#13;
incorporated into the Operational Manual, to be used by the implementing agencies as the&#13;
basis for procurement under the project.&#13;
3.34        Civil Works contracts costing more than US$100,000, up to an aggregate&#13;
of US$500,000, will be awarded based on NCB procedures. Minor works estimated to&#13;
cost less than US$100,000, up to an aggregate amount of US$250,000 will be procured&#13;
under lump sum, fixed price contracts awarded on the basis of quotations obtained from&#13;
three qualified contractors in response to a written invitation.&#13;
3.35        Vehicles and laboratory equipment will be packaged into contracts greater&#13;
than US$50,000 and will be procured under Limited International Bidding (LLB) from&#13;
suppliers with service and maintenance facilities in Ecuador. Other goods, and equipment&#13;
valued at less than US$50,000 equivalent per order, will be purchased on the basis of price&#13;
quotations from at least three eligible suppliers up to an aggregate of US$400,000.&#13;
3.36        The selection and appointment of consultants for studies and technical&#13;
assistance under the project will be consistent with the August 1981 Bank Guidelines for&#13;
the Use of Consultants by Bank Borrowers and by the Bank as Executing Agency, using&#13;
Bank issued standard forms of contract and standard letters of invitation acceptable to the&#13;
Bank.&#13;
3.37        Under Research Grants and Partnerships procurement of goods (fertilizers,&#13;
chemicals, etc.) and equipment (laboratoratory equipment, field implements, etc.) will be&#13;
done under shopping, due to the small size of grants. Procurement of fellowships will be&#13;
done by direct contract, because of the specific nature of each fellowship. The contract&#13;
for each grant will state that procurement will follow procedures acceptable to the Bank&#13;
and a sample contract will be included in the Operational Manual. A procurement&#13;
specialist on the staff of the PIU will review procurement under the project to ensure that&#13;
the conditions described are met. During supervision missions, the Bank will sample&#13;
contracts for review of how procurement was being implemented&#13;
3.38        Prior Review. The Bank will review all contracts for goods, equipment,&#13;
civil works and consultants over US$50,000. Approximately 15 percent of all&#13;
procurement will be subject to prior review by the Bank. This low percentage is&#13;
acceptable due to the fact that most procurement will be made by the grantees under small&#13;
grants. As a safeguard against such low levels of prior review, the staff of the PIU will&#13;
include a procurement specialist who will review all procurement not under prior review&#13;
by the Bank, in accordance with the Operational Manual. As for NCB procurement there&#13;
will be no prior registration of bidders, no requirement for local agents, and no provision&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
* a g _- - :x-:~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.                                                     . ;-- f:   . =.   . &gt;. . :.   . -. -.   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   . :. -. -  . . .   . . .   . . . . .     . -. a. . . . . . . . . .   .   . . .&#13;
O ^ # O .^.: t .. , 9. w . .-. . . ._. .,, -. .-- ,,,. ,, . E- ,, ,,,. . . c ... -. _ a-.:.. .. .C. ..&#13;
.   .   . ..   ... . .~&#13;
S .                                                                                                                                                                                                   0~~~~~~..    .    ..&#13;
|  W B                    _. . .-..   . . . '                                                                                                               .           .                         j                                         e'j j-"&#13;
w :'-- ,.|-.-.''.'|' , ,.'''' W: -;'. --I 1-1 1-.:~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.                                                                                       ..     ....              ...  ... &#13;
.......                                                                                                                                                                                       ~~~~~00            .&#13;
.. ..                ... .&#13;
2   o  t                                     ---- - -- ---  -- -~~~~.....   .   .   .- - -- .   :    :::   ::':::::::: .:                .: ':  :,'.: :.:.:.   !:1l.:l. '.:::.:':&#13;
0;   n. v                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         oc&#13;
00~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~- ...00..-...&#13;
.    . ....  .     ..... ~      ~             I &#13;
.... ..   . ..               . ..    . ....                                                                   ...       .            .. ...&#13;
FII  ~~~~~~~~~Ji;;;n~~~~~... ....  ..0                                                                                                                                                                                              A0c&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20&#13;
expenses including travel and maintenance and overhead expenses of the PIU will be&#13;
reimbursed from the loan at a rate of 85 percent of costs up to a loan disbursement of&#13;
US$225,000, 70 percent thereafter up to US$360,000, and 50 percent thereafter until&#13;
project completion. The Bank will reimburse 100 percent of the Governments share of the&#13;
Competitive Research Grants and Research and Education Exchange Partnerships up to a&#13;
maximum of 75 percent of the total investment cost of each subproject.&#13;
3.41          All disbursements from the loan, except for equipment and materials are&#13;
expected to be made against statements of expenditures (SOEs). All contracts, including&#13;
consultants, greater than US$50,000 or more equivalent, will not be eligible for SOEs. All&#13;
expenditures under research grants, fellowships, training, incremental operating costs and&#13;
contracts not requiring prior review will be disbursed under SOEs. The participating&#13;
entities responsible for the procurement of goods and contracting services will maintain&#13;
the SOE. The minimum value of each disbursement request will be US$120,000 during&#13;
the initial period of the project, and US$200,000 when cumulative disbursements from the&#13;
loan have reached US$4.4 million. Retroactive financing of up to US$1 million for&#13;
eligible expenditures made after May 31, 1995, but no more than 12 months before&#13;
signing, will be provided for under the loan. The project is expected to be completed by&#13;
June 30, 2003, with a closing date of December 31, 2003.&#13;
3.42          The Borrower will establish a Special Account in the Central Bank of&#13;
Ecuador, or a commercial bank acceptable to the Bank to cover eligible project&#13;
expenditures under the loan. The Bank will initially deposit up to US$0.6 million upon&#13;
receipt of an initial withdrawal application. This could later be increased to&#13;
US$1.0 million (representing the average expected loan disbursement for a four-month&#13;
period) once cumulative disbursements from the loan reached US$4.4 million. Subsequent&#13;
replenishment by the Bank into the Special Account will follow the procedures for which&#13;
Bank funds are disbursed against actual expenditures.&#13;
..... -Table 2: Disbursements fiom Lo:n   S$); ...          .. ..... . .. ..&#13;
Cat  o                   Amount of Loan.....% of Loanu&#13;
I Grants ~ ~ ~ ~~......              ...     to        on &#13;
a. -  Research and Education Exchan-ge -    i -t4C2ft -10,600,0002-: t::i:t:::itE050.50 - f:0 !- &#13;
t 0;::0b. ;-F-ellowshi s -   0-- j  :      il000A;:;000000 ;0  :0 AP  2,000V;; fg 00000, 000  9.5 &#13;
2. Civi 0000;000000                          0       00000000000g;tlD Works    A?07707:;0. ....... 6....00. ..00 i .0 3. . ...0.&#13;
03. Good s I NJAP0-;-ltl                             4 . . ..  .. .. .. . ..... . .. .00...  -4X,00    i .....-0...  2.00-..  i;&#13;
;-;b;.E Ohrs;--_ 22:;:0-:;-:                                     f     :--:::S:-i:0:-:i : fd .:000 :  1o:0.5&#13;
5. Incremetal 0 eat   CotsCW;0000:000000000- iCl00000:5:0S0 O-it000       2.7:;000::5:gA&#13;
i6. nallocated  t$       tt     :      04:  t-:   1- 90Q0 000;t  9.0-V&#13;
:: .               .     .   .    ....To t          1     00 0 0 0 ..  ..  . ... ..    ..  ..  ..:: :  ...0 .    ...... i: ..    .   .   .  ..  ..  ..;:'';;';.i..:   0   .0 .    .  ii  i&#13;
i:ii ~ ~ ~ ~ .   ....i::  .i::  ..:   7    7   :    :-  ::- :i    T + l    : : : ::;:  .:: .:EiE:- .....:iii .: ..:   ::i::i:: i .:.........   .......    ..: .:..&#13;
:::.::.7:   :::::  ::~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~. :::.  ..2:  :- :::: ::. .v; . .::-   ....  .. :::  ::   .. .:  .E:   ......: :::::   ..: :::   .. .. : ::.::a ^ Y 9 V .......   .. . .::.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21&#13;
Accounfing and Audifing&#13;
3.43        The PIU will establish consolidated project accounts and maintain other&#13;
records as needed, including separate accounts and records of the total cost of financed&#13;
subprojects and the cost of individual project activities. Contracts with participating&#13;
entities will include accounting and auditing requirements as provided for in the&#13;
Operational Manual.&#13;
3.44        Project accounts, the Special Account, and related financial information&#13;
(including supporting documentation for the SOEs) will be audited annually by an&#13;
independent private auditor acceptable to the Bank, in accordance with Bank auditing&#13;
guidelines. Certified copies of the audited consolidated project accounts and audited&#13;
Special Account in the Central Bank (including a separate opinion on the use of SOEs)&#13;
will be submitted annually to the Bank not later than six months after the close of the&#13;
financial year (para. 5.1 (c) (v)). As part of the Operational Manual, the contracts with&#13;
the participating entities will include a condition that, if the financial audits identify&#13;
significant irregularities in any participating entity, the PIU will take the necessary steps to&#13;
suspend the contract.&#13;
4. PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
Organization and Management&#13;
4.1         An Executive Council, chaired by the Technical Subsecretary, has been&#13;
formed within MAG, with responsibility to oversee the project. A Project Implementation&#13;
Unit (PIU) has also been established by MAG, which will be responsible for reporting to&#13;
the Bank and managing the INIAP Institutional Strengthening component. This PIU will&#13;
contract out the management of the Competitive Grants to a NGO and this contract will&#13;
be financed by this project. The NGO will be responsible for handling all technical and&#13;
pre-contractual aspects of the project and will be supported by a Peer Review Panel which&#13;
will review all proposals for the Competitive Grants component of the project (see&#13;
Organization Chart - Annex 2). The NGO will send out an invitation for proposals to be&#13;
financed, competitively, based on priorities established by the Executive Council and&#13;
approved by MAG. The annual budget for the project which will also be established by&#13;
the Executive Council and approved by MAG will determiine the size of the program for&#13;
any one year.&#13;
Executive Council&#13;
4.2         The Council will be led by the Technical Subsecretary in the Ministry of&#13;
Agriculture and will include representatives of the private sector, universities, foundations,&#13;
and NGOs. The function of the Council is: to oversee the implementation of the project;&#13;
to approve Annual Work Plans including budget; to ensure that the PIU and INIAP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22&#13;
comply with the obligations stated in their Annual Work Plans; and to ensure that&#13;
proposals conform to national research priorities as established by MAG.&#13;
The Project Implementation Unit&#13;
4.3         The PIU, which has been established by a Ministerial Resolution, will be&#13;
responsible for preparing the budget, annual work plans, making payments from the loan&#13;
account for project expenditures, and preparing financial and progress reports for the&#13;
project and will be the main contact for the Bank for project implementation. The PIU&#13;
will also contract consultants to: (a) implement a M&amp;E system; (b) prepare an evaluation&#13;
report for the Midterm Review; and (c) prepare an End Evaluation of the project. It will&#13;
contract staff to promote the project and provide training to participating entities in&#13;
preparing proposals for grant funding, and it will manage the contract for the management&#13;
of the Competitive Grants.&#13;
4.4         The PIU will have about seven staff, including support staff, led by a&#13;
Director, who will report to the Executive Council and the Technical Subsecretary in&#13;
MAG. The Director will have overall responsibility for the administration of the project.&#13;
He will be supported by a Finance and Administration Manager who will handle payments&#13;
from the loan account for project expenditures (contracted payments for research,&#13;
exchange partnerships and fellowship grants, technical assistance, equipment, vehicles,&#13;
civil works, and materials procured under the project). He will also prepare the annual&#13;
budget, consolidate project cost statements and arrange for the audit of the projects cost&#13;
statements and Special Account. There will also be a Procurement and Contracts&#13;
Specialist who will ensure that all technical assistance contracts and the procurement of&#13;
goods, equipment and vehicles, and civil works financed under the project, directly or&#13;
through the Competitive Grants, are done in accordance with procedures acceptable to the&#13;
Government and the Bank. There will also be a Monitoring and Evaluation Manager and&#13;
an assistant to monitor and evaluate project implementation.&#13;
4.5         As a condition of effectiveness the Project Director will have been hired&#13;
and the PIU will have the minimum staff in place, in numbers and with qualifications&#13;
acceptable to the Bank, to initiate the project (para. 5.1 (a) (i)). Government will, at all&#13;
times, retain in the PIU staff in numbers and composition, including the position of&#13;
director, satisfactory to the Bank for efficient implementation of the project, (para. 5.1 (c)&#13;
(vi)).&#13;
Management of the Competitive Grants&#13;
4.6         The management of the Competitive Grants will be contracted out to an&#13;
NGO. The NGO will promote these grants by organizing training workshops on the&#13;
preparation of proposals for competitive selection, send out annual invitations for&#13;
proposals; conduct a preliminary technical and financial review of proposals before passing&#13;
them onto the Peer Review Panel for final approval; draft contracts for the approved&#13;
subprojects with the selected implementing agencies; and supervise subproject&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
23&#13;
implementation. Service contracts for the execution of subprojects will be signed by the&#13;
PIU.&#13;
4.7         For fellowships that will be awarded under the project the NGO will:&#13;
screen proposals for compliance before passing them on to the Peer Review Panel; prepare&#13;
financing agreements with the selected participants; assist the awardee and those selected&#13;
from INIAP for fellowships in applying to graduate schools; monitor and supervise the&#13;
awardees progress; and arrange for students to return to Ecuador to do their thesis work&#13;
on appropriate topics in INIAP, university or private sector laboratories. It will also&#13;
advise the PIU on the payments to be made under the component. A draft contract,&#13;
between MAG and the NGO, for the management of the Competitive Grants has been&#13;
prepared. It will be a condition of effectiveness that the NGO has been selected and a&#13;
Letter of Intent signed (para. 5.1 (a) (ii)).&#13;
4.8         Under the project there is a Strengthening component for INIAP. This will&#13;
be in the form of technical assistance to prepare a Development Plan, fellowships, research&#13;
consultants, civil works to rehabilitate existing facilities, vehicles, equipment and materials.&#13;
INIAP will prepare all of the necessary pre-contractual documentation and pass this on to&#13;
the PIU and the NGO, where appropriate, for processing. All payments will be made by&#13;
the PIU. INIAP would agree through an Implementation Agreement with MAG to meet&#13;
certain requirements which would include the preparation of a Development Plan that&#13;
would deal with the assignment of personnel; the separation of production and research&#13;
activities; asset restructuring; and the role and management of the Endowment Fund. It&#13;
will be a condition of disbursement of the INIAP component that the Implementation&#13;
Agreement with INIAP would be signed (para. 5.1 (b) (i)).&#13;
Peer Review Panel&#13;
4.9         A Peer Review Panel (five members) will be contracted through the NGO,&#13;
to review, and select: the Research Grants and the Research and Education Exchange&#13;
partnership subprojects to be financed under the project. The Panel will present the&#13;
selected proposals to the contracted NGO for financing. Panel members will be&#13;
contracted at a standard daily rate for about thirty days per year. Contracts will be for&#13;
two years. The Peer Review Panel will consist of scientists with a proven record in&#13;
research and will come from the various research entities, including the private sector.&#13;
International participation will be needed in certain instances. There will be an&#13;
environmental specialist on the Peer Review Panel who will review proposals for their&#13;
environmental impact. The qualifications and terms of service for all panel members will&#13;
be included in the OM, and MAG will ensure that the Peer Review Panel will be&#13;
maintained with members satisfactory to the Bank.&#13;
Operational Manual&#13;
4.10        An Operational Manual (OM), will be a working document for the project,&#13;
describing how to plan, identify, prepare, select, contract, finance, supervise, evaluate, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24&#13;
account for the proposals to be financed with participating entities under the project. It&#13;
will be a condition of loan effectiveness that the OM has been adopted by MAG, through a&#13;
Ministerial Resolution (para. 5.1 (a) (iii)), and MAG will implement the project as per the&#13;
agreed OM and that the Government will send to the Bank for approval, any proposed&#13;
changes to the OM (para. 5.1 (c) (vii)).&#13;
Processing Proposals for Competitive Research Grants, and Research and&#13;
Education Exchange Partnerships&#13;
4.11        The system for the identification, processing and approval of proposals for&#13;
financing is based on open competition for funds, based on research priorities set by MAG&#13;
and selection criteria developed in the Operational Manual. Entities eligible to compete&#13;
will be INIAP, universities, growers associations and other private sector entities.&#13;
4.12        The PIU will send letters each year to participating and prospective entities&#13;
inviting proposals for the various competitive subcomponents of the project. This&#13;
invitation letter will state basic criteria for proposals, in accordance with the OM, as well&#13;
as the projects investment priorities for that year. The contracted NGO will enter&#13;
proposals received into a database and eliminate duplicates, technically unacceptable&#13;
proposals, those that do not meet environmental standards, and those that did not address&#13;
the main objectives of the project. The final list will be sent on for final review to the Peer&#13;
Review Panel.&#13;
4.13        The Peer Review Panel will review and select the proposals on a technical&#13;
basis and criteria established in the Operational Manual and within the annual budget&#13;
allocations. They will then inform the PIU as to their final selections along with the&#13;
reasons for such a selection. For the proposals that are accepted, the PIU will notify the&#13;
implementing agencies as to the acceptance of the proposal and the amount of financing.&#13;
For each approved subproject, the contracted NGO will prepare draft financing contracts&#13;
between the PIU and the participating entity. Once Government budgetary contributions&#13;
were secured, the PIU will sign contracts with participating entities and make payments&#13;
according to the schedule set forth in the contract. Letters will also be sent out indicating&#13;
which proposals were not selected and the reasons for such action.&#13;
4.14        The PIU will prepare an Annual Work Plan, including budget, for the&#13;
project in accordance with normal Government timing and procedures. The PIU will send&#13;
to the Bank for review, by June 30 of each year, the proposed Annual Work Plan,&#13;
including budget, to be undertaken by the PIU under the project for the coming year&#13;
(para. 5.1 (c) (viii)).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
4.15        In order to ensure adequate monitoring and supervision, the PIU will&#13;
appoint consultants not later than three months from the date of effectiveness, under terms&#13;
of reference (included in the OM), satisfactory to the Bank, to implement a monitoring&#13;
and evaluation system for the project and send a report to the Bank for comment within&#13;
six months from the effectiveness date (para. 5.1 (c) (ix)).&#13;
4.16        The PIU will submit an annual progress report to the Bank (due&#13;
February 28 of each year) and a short progress report, (due August 31 of each year),&#13;
identifying the major issues, problems and actions taken in the planning and&#13;
implementation of the project (para. 5.1 (c) (x)). These reports will include the status of&#13;
each component and discuss any problems that might arise which could affect&#13;
implementation. This information will also help the Bank and the PIU to plan the timing&#13;
and composition of supervision missions.&#13;
4.17        Midterm Review. To evaluate the project, the PIU will hire consultants,&#13;
no later than 24 months from the date of effectiveness, under terms of reference&#13;
satisfactory to the Bank, to prepare a midterm performance report. No later than 30&#13;
months after the effectiveness date, and using the above report as a basis, the Borrower&#13;
will undertake jointly with the Bank, a Midterm review and evaluation of the activities&#13;
carried out under the project and the results achieved. This review will include but not be&#13;
limited to: (a) the Executive Council, the PIU, the management contract for the&#13;
Competitive Grants, and the Peer Review Panel; (b) all aspects of the implementation of&#13;
approved proposals, particularly the selection process and the response of the private&#13;
sector and universities; and (c) the effectiveness of the provisions of the Operational&#13;
Manual and its application. Consultants satisfactory to the Bank will be hired, no later than&#13;
24 months after effectiveness, to prepare a midterm project performance report and the&#13;
midterm review will take place no later than 30 months after the date of effectiveness.&#13;
Once the review has been completed all required adjustments, including changes to the&#13;
Operational Manual agreeable to the Bank, would be introduced (para. 5.1 (c) (xi)).&#13;
4.18        End Evaluation. Consultants will be hired by June 30, 2000, to assess the&#13;
overall success of the project and to determine whether and when a follow-up project will&#13;
be needed. The consultants will assess the projects success in developing and integrating&#13;
links across the research spectrum from basic to adaptive research, and in promoting an&#13;
integrated, interactive and competitive research system that involves the public sector,&#13;
farmers groups, universities and other private sector entities (para. 5.1 (c) (xii)).&#13;
4.19        The Borrower, through MAG, will prepare and furnish to the Bank, no&#13;
later than six months after the close of the project, a plan for the future operation of the&#13;
project. The Borrower has also agreed to give the Bank a reasonable opportunity to&#13;
exchange views with the Borrower on such a plan and thereafter carry out the plan, taking&#13;
into account the Banks comments (para. 5.1 (c) (xiii)).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26&#13;
Project Benefits&#13;
4.20        Benefits will accrue to the agricultural research system, by making it more&#13;
competitive; by involving a broader range of institutions; by attracting more funding from&#13;
the private sector and therefore leading to greater sustainability; by developing exchange&#13;
partnerships and therefore facilitating the importation of technology, and strengthening of&#13;
graduate teaching in universities. The project will also develop a critical mass of scientists&#13;
capable of doing research.&#13;
4.21        Beneficiaries will be farmers, the majority of whom are poor, and who&#13;
produce the basic food commodities, such as rice, maize, potatoes and plantains along&#13;
with those that produce export crops such as bananas and plantains. Technologies&#13;
developed under this project will improve management of soil and water, increase disease&#13;
and pest resistance of crops which will result in reduced pesticide use, develop integrated&#13;
pest management methods and soil conservation methods, and produce higher yielding&#13;
crop varieties.&#13;
Project Risks&#13;
4.22         General risks to this type of project are lack of Government commitment,&#13;
inability to set priorities and maintain them, lack of counterpart funding, uncertainty of&#13;
private sector participation and the lack of good working conditions for returning M.S.&#13;
and Ph.D. fellows. The project will address the commitment risk by eliciting a statement&#13;
of the Governments agricultural technology strategy in which it provides assurances of the&#13;
priority it gives to public funding of agricultural research. The project will set as a&#13;
condition of effectiveness the setting of priorities by the MAG in conjunction with&#13;
producers and research organizations. In terms of sustainability of funding, an analysis of&#13;
future needs has been made during project preparation, the results of which have been&#13;
presented to MAG for discussion and will be used as the basis for eliciting sustained&#13;
support in the future. The preparation of a Development Plan by iNLAP which will&#13;
address such issues as asset restructuring and the management of its endowment fund will&#13;
improve the sustainability of that institution. This analysis also includes investments from&#13;
the private sector. To support the MAG in managing the Competitive Grants component&#13;
of the project a NGO will be contracted. INIAP's autonomy along with access to&#13;
competitive funds should better employment conditions for higher level staff.&#13;
Environmental Impact&#13;
4.23        The direct and immediate environmental impacts of agriculture can be&#13;
grouped into four categories: (a) loss of habitat; (b) loss of soil productivity; (c) modified&#13;
hydrology; and (d) soil and water contamination. On the whole this project should have&#13;
beneficial environmental impacts. Encroachment by farmers and ranchers on frontier&#13;
tropical forests and other natural habitats should diminish as: (i) yields increase on&#13;
productive lands; and (ii) generation of technology enhances Ecuador's ability to deal with&#13;
environmental issues such as land degradation and agricultural chemical pollution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27&#13;
4.24        Research programs financed by the project will; improve management of&#13;
sods and water, increase disease and pest resistance of crops and thereby reduce chemical&#13;
use, develop integrated pest management methods that will include more rational use of&#13;
pesticides, and develop soil conservation methods. As one of the main objectives of the&#13;
project is to increase the productivity of agriculture this should result in less pressure&#13;
being put on land and water resources. Research on animals and pasture should also&#13;
produce environmental benefits. Since much of the recent expansion on the coast has&#13;
been for pastures for animal production, more efficient use of pasture will decrease the&#13;
pressure on fragile tropical lands.&#13;
4.25        Specifically the project would have an environmental assessment (EA)&#13;
specialist on the Peer Review Panel of the project to screen research proposals. The&#13;
Operational Manual would include environmental criteria for the selection of research&#13;
projects under the competitive grants component.&#13;
Poverty Alleviation&#13;
4.26        While it is not a direct poverty intervention it has important implications for&#13;
rural poverty as the research priorities, i.e., rice, potatoes, maize, etc., being financed&#13;
under the project are of importance to small farmers as illustrated in the recent Poverty&#13;
Report (June 30, 1995). Rural poverty is tightly linked to the productivity of agriculture&#13;
and environmental degradation. This project will strengthen the knowledge base of&#13;
Ecuadoran agriculture and thereby increase productivity. Such productivity increases will&#13;
lead to more efficient growth, increase economic opportunities in rural areas, and halt the&#13;
deterioration of the natural resource base. The project will benefit farmers, most of whom&#13;
are poor. Through research on basic commodities such as rice, barley, plantains, and&#13;
potatoes, which make up the bulk of the calories consumed by the poor, poor consumers&#13;
will also benefit.&#13;
5. AGREEMENTS AND RECOMMENDATION&#13;
5.1         During negotiations of the loan, agreement from the Government of&#13;
Ecuador has been reached on the following actions:&#13;
(a)   Conditions of Effectiveness:&#13;
(i)   the director of the PIU will have been hired and a minimum staff in&#13;
place, in numbers and composition acceptable to the Bank&#13;
(para. 4.5);&#13;
(ii)   the NGO for the management of the Competitive Grants&#13;
component has been selected and a Letter of Intent signed&#13;
(para. 4.7); and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28&#13;
(iii)   the OM acceptable to the Bank, has been adopted by MAG,&#13;
through a Ministerial Resolution (para. 4.10).&#13;
(b)   Condition of Disbursements:&#13;
(i)   disbursement for expenses in the "Strengthening INIAP"&#13;
component, other than those for consultants to prepare the&#13;
Development Plan, would be conditional on the signing of the&#13;
Implementation Agreement with INLAP which would include the&#13;
Development Plan which would deal with, inter alia, the&#13;
assignment of personnel; the separation of production and research&#13;
activities; asset restructuring; and the role and management of its&#13;
endowment fund (para 4.8).&#13;
(c)   during negotiations the following agreements were reached with the&#13;
Borrower;&#13;
(i)   adequate funding will be made available to the project, by allocating&#13;
funds in the annual budget for the following year according to the&#13;
proposals to be submitted to the Bank no later than October 31 of&#13;
each year following the requirements specified in the projects&#13;
Annual Work Plans (para. 3.32);&#13;
(ii)   the Borrower will provide adequate working capital to the PIU by&#13;
depositing, in advance, in the PIU account its share of the&#13;
equivalent of one months operating expenses (para 3.32);&#13;
(iii)    MAG will finance all Competitive Grants, including Partnerships at&#13;
an average 65 percent of total subproject costs, financing at&#13;
75 percent for the first US$4.5 million, 65 percent for the next&#13;
US$4.5 million and 55 percent thereafter (para 3.32);&#13;
(iv)   the Borrower will ensure that all parties participating in the project&#13;
follow procurement procedures satisfactory to the Bank&#13;
(para. 3.39);&#13;
(v)    accounting and audit requirements described in paras. 3.43 and 3.44&#13;
will be followed;&#13;
(vi)    Government will, at all times, retain in the PIU, staff in numbers&#13;
and with qualifications, including the position of director,&#13;
satisfactory to the Bank (para. 4.5);&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
29&#13;
(vii)    MAG will implement the project as per the OM and Government&#13;
will approve the OM and submit it to the Bank for approval any&#13;
proposed changes to the OM (para. 4.10);&#13;
(viii)   the PIU will send to the Bank for review, by June 30 of each year,&#13;
the proposed Annual Operating and Work Plans to be undertaken&#13;
by the PIU under the project for the coming year (para. 4.14);&#13;
(ix)    consultants will be contracted, not later than three months from the&#13;
date of effectiveness, under terms of reference satisfactory to the&#13;
Bank, to implement a monitoring and evaluation system for the&#13;
project, and send a report to the Bank for comment within six&#13;
months from the date of effectiveness (para. 4.15);&#13;
(x)   the PIU will submit an annual progress report to the Bank, due&#13;
February 28 each year, and a short progress report (due August 31&#13;
of each year) identifying the major issues, problems and actions&#13;
taken in the planning and implementation of the project&#13;
(para. 4.16);&#13;
(xi)   the PIU will hire consultants, no later than 24 months from the&#13;
effectiveness date and under terms of reference satisfactory to the&#13;
Bank, to prepare a midterm performance report, and that no later&#13;
than 30 months after the effectiveness date, and using the above&#13;
report as a basis, the Borrower would undertake jointly with the&#13;
Bank, a midterm review and once the review has been completed,&#13;
all required adjustments, as well as changes to the Operational&#13;
Manual agreeable to the Bank would be introduced (para. 4.17);&#13;
(xii)   consultants will be hired, by June 30, 2000, to assess the projects&#13;
success to date and determine if there should be a follow-up project&#13;
(para. 4.18); and&#13;
(xiii)    MAG will prepare a plan, within six months after project closing,&#13;
for the future operation of the project and discuss this plan with the&#13;
Bank (para. 4.19).&#13;
5.2   Recommendation. Subject to the above agreements and conditions, the proposed&#13;
project would be suitable for a Bank loan of US$21 million with a term of 21 years,&#13;
including a 7 year grace period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Loan and Project Summary Costs&#13;
ECUADOR                                         Annex 1&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT                                 Page 1&#13;
LOAN AND PROJECT SUMMARY COSTS&#13;
CATEGORY                                                           US$1000_                               World     Local&#13;
Local   Foreign   TOTAL      %                 Bank    Support&#13;
COMPElITIVE GRANT&amp; &#13;
1. Raleech Grnts                                            6,376    1,125    7,500      30.2               4876      2625&#13;
2. Exchange Pwtirrships - Research                          4,080    1,020    5,100      20.6               3315       1785&#13;
3.                  - Edkucation                              240    2,160    2,400       9.7               2400          0&#13;
4. Tota                                                     4,320    3,180    7,00      30.2               5715       1785&#13;
5. Total Comeponent                                        10,895    4,306   15,000      60.5              10590      4410&#13;
STRENOGTHNING INAP&#13;
1. Development Plan                                             0      100       100      0.4                100          0&#13;
2. Training&#13;
. PhDs                                                         0      900       900      3.6                900          0&#13;
b. MSe and Other Training                                      0    1,100    1,100       4.4               1100          0&#13;
3. Netional Re_sarchere &#13;
a. PhDc                                                    1,800         0    1,800      7.3               1 530       270&#13;
b. MS'                                                     1,080         0    1,080      4.4                918        162&#13;
4. rnternational RePearchts                                     0      300       300       1 .2               300         0&#13;
5. Civil Works                                                595      105       700       2.8                595       105&#13;
S. Equipnent, VehNic, Materials etc.                           78      442       520       2.1               442         78&#13;
7. Total Component                                          3.863    2,847    6,500      26.2               5885        616&#13;
PROJECT IMPLJMdTATION UNT&#13;
1. Tectlcal Aa_ietanca inc.Midterm  nd End Evaluations        180      180       380       1.                306         54&#13;
2. Vehclee and Eqaipment                                       10       66        65      0.3                  65        10&#13;
3. Project Staff                                              716        0       715       2.9               488        227&#13;
4. Operating, Maintenance and Overhead Coats                   48        12       60      0.2                  41        19&#13;
6. R_e erch Management Contract                             1,60      420    2,100       8.5               1785        315&#13;
S. Total                                                    2,833      667    3,300      13.3               2675        625&#13;
TOTAL  OJECT *ASE CO8TS                                    16,981    7,819   24,800    100.0               19150      56so&#13;
Total Contingencies - Physical                                336       154      490       1.8                428        62&#13;
- Price                                    1,171      539    1,710        6.3               1423       288&#13;
TOTAL tJECT COSTS                                          18,487    8,513   27,000    100.0               21000      6000&#13;
PINANCINO PLAN&#13;
1. Private Sector and Universities                          1666    1,236    2,900       10.7&#13;
2. IMAP                                                     2,060         0    2.060      7.6 &#13;
3. Mrtvty ot Agrtculbwo                                     1,040         0    1,040       3.9&#13;
4. Bank Loan                                               13,500    7.500   21,000      77.8&#13;
Total                                                      18,265    8,735   27,000    100.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
31&#13;
| ECUADOR                                                             Annex 1&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT                                                  Page 2&#13;
_C OFINANCING MATRIX&#13;
Part.       MAG's         Bank Loan&#13;
Entities      Share    as a % of MAG&#13;
COMPEhTINE GRANTS                                                     %             X              %&#13;
1. Rerwch Grants                                                      36          66 /1           100&#13;
2. Exchange Pwtnershipe - Reeearch                                    36          65/1            100&#13;
3.                  - Education                                                    100            100&#13;
STRENGTHENINC INAP /2&#13;
1. Development Ple,n                                                               100            100&#13;
2. Training&#13;
a. PhDs                                                                           100            100&#13;
b. MS and Other Training                                                          100            100&#13;
3. National Reeswrcherh&#13;
a. PhDs                                                                           100           100/85&#13;
b. MSe                                                                            100           100/86&#13;
4. International Researchers                                                       100           100/86&#13;
S. Civil Works                                                                     100           100/85&#13;
6. Equiprent, Vehicles, Materials etc                                              100           100/85&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEBIENTATION UNIT /2&#13;
1. Technical Assistance inc.Midterm and End Evaluations                            100           100/85&#13;
2. Vehicles and Equipment                                                          100           10018S&#13;
3. Project Staff                                                                   100         85/70/50 13&#13;
4. Operating. Maintensnce nd Overhead Coats                                        100         85/70/50 13&#13;
5. R"earch Management Contract                                                     100           100/85&#13;
Note 1: Subgrents from MAG would average 86b  of total subproject costs with MAG financing 75% up to the first US$4.6 million,&#13;
86% for th next US$4.5, and 65% thereafter. IDB would finance research subprojects on the eame baeis ae the Bank.&#13;
Note 2: Trairnig, Technical Assistance. Civil Works, Vehicles and Equipment would be reimbursed at a rate of 100%&#13;
for foreign coats and 86% for local coots.  1           1                          I&#13;
Note 3: Salariei and Operating costs would be reimbursed at 86% until withdrawals in this Category, have reached&#13;
an aggregate amount eqavelent to $225,000; 70% until withdrowal have reached $ 360,000 and 50% therefter.&#13;
_ _ _ _       _ _         _ _             _ _        __            __               __                 _                _       _&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
32&#13;
-           -     Annex 1&#13;
ECUADOR                                        P                   _ __&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
LOAN AND PROJECT SUMMARY COSTS&#13;
I&#13;
aee.   Centlngeuck&#13;
CATEGORY                                                 Coas  Physalc    Price    Toal         %&#13;
COMPEnTIVE GRANTS&#13;
1. Resrch Grants                                           7,500               502   8,002       29.6&#13;
2. Exchag Partnernhips - Rerch                             6,100    =          383   5,483       20.3&#13;
3.                 - Education                             2,400         _     146    2,546       9.4&#13;
4. Total                                                   7,600               529   8.029       29.7&#13;
5. Total Component                                        165000         _    1,032  16,031      59.3&#13;
STRINTHIdING IHAP&#13;
1. Deveopment Plan                                          100         6        1      108       0.4&#13;
2. Trainingg&#13;
a. PhDt                                                    900        46       60    1,005       3.7&#13;
b. MSc ndw Oh Traring                                     1,100       56       89    1,244       4.6&#13;
3. NatIonal Reoerchwe&#13;
a. PhDe                                                   1,800       90      161   2,041        7.6&#13;
b. MSa                                                    1,080       64 W     94    1,228       4.6&#13;
4. International FReearchers                                 300       15        28     343       1.3&#13;
S. Civil Works                                              700        36       27      762       2.8 &#13;
. EqLipmrent, VNhicl_, Materiale aet.                       520        26       20      666       2.1&#13;
7. Total Component                                         6,500      325      470   7,296       27.0               =         -&#13;
PROJECT IMPLE.EITATION UNIT&#13;
1. Teclwicsl Aaaitance inc.Midterm and End Evaluationr      380        18       36      413       1.5&#13;
2. Vehiclee and Equipment                                     86        3         1      89       0.3&#13;
3. Pr*ct Staff                                              715        36       65      806       3.0 &#13;
4. Operating, Maintenance and Overhead Costs                  80        3         4      87       0.2&#13;
S. Raerch Management Contract                              2,100      106      161    2,368       8.7&#13;
6. Total                                                   3.300       165      246    3.711     13.7  ___&#13;
TOTAL PROJECT BASE COSTS                                  24,800       490     1,747   27,037    100.0&#13;
Total Contingencts Physical                                 490&#13;
-Prica                                    1,710 _&#13;
TOTAL POJECT COSTS                                        27,000 &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
33&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Organization Chart&#13;
MINISTRY OF&#13;
AGRICULTURE&#13;
EXECUTIVE        TECHNCAL&#13;
COUNCIL          SUBSECRETARY&#13;
PROJECT&#13;
IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
UNIT&#13;
COMPETITIVE&#13;
PEER REVIEW      GRANTS&#13;
PANEL            MANAGEMENT UNIT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
34&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL SERVICES PROJECT&#13;
Ecuador's Agricultural Research System&#13;
Investments in Agricultural Research&#13;
1.           Rates of Retum Around the World. Expenditures on agricultural research&#13;
consistently have been an excellent investment for a wide variety of governments and countries&#13;
around the world. Evenson, Waggoner and Ruttan6 reviewed 34 studies of returns to such&#13;
investments in various developed and developing countries and reported that returns ranged&#13;
from 20 to 110 percent per year. A similar review of 10 studies in South America found&#13;
returs ranging from 11 to 119 percent (Scobie)7. These high rates of return have helped these&#13;
countries to experience more rapid economic growth and development relative to countries&#13;
which discriminated against agriculture.&#13;
2.            These returns, which cover many years of investment, are comparable to the&#13;
rates of return received by a private investor on a certificate of deposit, savings account or&#13;
other investment instrument. They are extraordinarily high by any standard and suggest that&#13;
even developed countries still are substantially underinvested in agricultural research.&#13;
3.           Returns in Ecuador. Ecuador also has experienced success in its efforts to&#13;
generate, access and diffuse improved technologies, even though average yields still are&#13;
relatively low. Posada Torrese found a benefit-cost ratio of 2.46 for expenditures on&#13;
agricultural research in Ecuador between 1971 and 1981. Joint research on rice by INAP,&#13;
universities and international agencies resulted in returns of 34 percent between 1970 and 1990&#13;
(Palomino and Echeverria)9. A series of related studies carried out by INHZP with support&#13;
from ISNAR and FUNDAGRO revealed the following rates of return to research investments:&#13;
hard corn, 70 percent; african palm, 32 percent; potatoes, 33 percent; soybeans, 17 percent;&#13;
and wheat, 29 percent (INLAP)10.&#13;
6Evenson, Robert E., P.E. Waggoner and V.W. Ruttan 1979. "Economic Benefits to Research: An&#13;
Example from Agriculture." Science 205: September 14: 1101-1107.&#13;
7 Scobie, Grant M. 1986. "Partners in Research: The CGIAR in Latin America. Washington, D.C.:&#13;
paper presented to the Executive Directors of 1DB, February 18.&#13;
s Posada Torres, Rafael. 1986 "Ecuador and the CGIAR Centers: A Study of their Collaboration in&#13;
Agricultural Research" Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, September, CGIAR Study Paper&#13;
No. 11.&#13;
9 Palomino, Julio and George Norton. 1992. "Determinaci6n de Prioridades de Investigaci6n&#13;
Agropecuaria en Ecuador" Quito: MNIAP.&#13;
10 INIAP 1993a. "Retorno a las Inversiones en Investigaci6nAgropecuaria" Quito: Direcci6n de&#13;
Planificaci6n.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
35&#13;
4.            Thus, Ecuador science base has made a modest contribution to agricultural&#13;
development. It is interesting to speculate how much larger the contribution might have been&#13;
with a more neutral macroeconomic policy matrix and if the funding constraints discussed&#13;
below had been addressed on a sustained basis.&#13;
5.           Standards for Funding Levels. ISNAR and the World Bank recommend as&#13;
a standard that between one and two percent of the gross domestic product of agriculture&#13;
(AGDP) be expended on agricultural research (ISNAR and IICA p.45)11. A separate source&#13;
indicates that two percent has become the accepted target (ISNAR)"2. Expending one to two&#13;
percent of AGDP on agricultural research is the necessary investment range for building a&#13;
viable science base for agriculture on the basis of experience in developed and developing&#13;
countries.&#13;
6.           Perspective on Ecuador's Investment History. Investments in agricultural&#13;
research in NIAP and the universities declined steadily in real terms at three percent per year&#13;
between 1974-76 and 1991-93 ". Research expenditures as a share of AGDP also declined&#13;
steadily after 1975 and were only .25 percent in 1993 compared to a high of .85 percent in&#13;
1975. The rapid erosion of investments during the last two decades is in sharp contrast to the&#13;
period 1965-1975 when funding increased at 14.5 percent per year.&#13;
7.           The situation is not quite so dismal when one considers that the private sector&#13;
also engages in agricultural research and it is evident that its investment has increased as&#13;
Government support has eroded. It is now estimated that private sector investments are about&#13;
US$3.1 million'4. Based on these estimations the total research investment (public and private)&#13;
in 1993 would be US$7.4 million or .43 percent of AGDP. Nevertheless, the trend in&#13;
agricultural research investments as a share of AGDP still would have declined from the high in&#13;
1975.&#13;
8.           Even with private sector research, Ecuador has made very limited investments&#13;
in comparison to the rest of the developing world. Data for 52 developing countries showed&#13;
an average investment in agricultural research of .94 percent of AGDP during 1980-1985, up&#13;
from .69 percent during 1970-1979 (ISNAR and ilCA p. 47). Thus, Ecuador sharply reduced&#13;
its investments in agricultural research while most of its competitors were increasing their&#13;
investments.&#13;
ISNAR and IICA (International Service for National Agricultural Research and Interamerican Insfitute&#13;
for Agricultural Cooperation). 1989. "Reforzamiento del Instituto Nacional de Investigaciones&#13;
Agropecuarias: Base para un Sistema Nacional de Investigaci6n Agropecuaria". The Hague:&#13;
ISNAR, June.&#13;
12 ISNAR (International Service for National Agricultural Research) 1990. "Why are Expenditures on&#13;
Agricultural Research so Small?" ISNAR Newsletter 12: January:2.&#13;
13 Univrsity viestments in research were only reported globally. It was assumed, for this analysis, that&#13;
10 percent of the total was dedicated to agriculture.&#13;
14 Falconi, Cesar A. 1992, Public and Private Sector Interactions in Agricultural Resrch in Less-&#13;
Developed Countries: The Case of Ecuador. ISNAR.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
36&#13;
Ecuador in Comparison with Regional Trading Partners&#13;
9.           Share of AGDP Invested in Sectoral Research. Ecuador compares quite&#13;
poorly with its regional trading partners in terms of investments in agricultural research.&#13;
According to internal IDB project documents, in 1993 Peru invested close to one percent of its&#13;
AGDP in agricultural research (not including private sector investments) or 4.0 times more&#13;
than Ecuador. Colombia also invested more than Ecuador at .5 percent of its AGDP in 1991,&#13;
and historically has invested much more. These bordering countries are Ecuador most&#13;
important competitors in the Andean Pact, both for lucrative export markets in the U.S. and&#13;
Europe, and for provision of food and fiber supplies in the region. The fact that Peru and&#13;
Colombia are investing so much more in agricultural research puts significant pressure on&#13;
Ecuador to increase its investments and reform its research system.&#13;
10.          The case of Spains response to its integration into the European Common&#13;
market in 1986 is instructive. Spain invested only about .5 percent of AGDP in agricultural&#13;
research in 1978. By 1988 it had increased this to nearly 1.5 percent and had substantially&#13;
reformed its agricultural research system (Herruzo and Echeverria)'5 as it was forced to&#13;
become more productive in order to compete in the Common Market.&#13;
11.          Yields of Principal Crops. The failure to invest more in agricultural research&#13;
is reflected in relatively low yields in Ecuador compared to its neighbors (Annex Table 3). The&#13;
strong correlation between the levels of investment in research cited above, and yields suggests&#13;
a clear lesson for Ecuador. If it is to compete with its neighbors it must increase investments in&#13;
research and agricultural productivity.&#13;
12.          The Emerging World Economy and the Need to Compete. Ecuador faces&#13;
a looming productivity crisis of major proportions. The low levels of yields relative to its&#13;
regional and hemispheric trading partners places the country at a major disadvantage. When&#13;
one considers the extent of the disparity in the context of the emerging global economy and&#13;
significant new market opportunities, it underscores the urgency with which Ecuador must deal&#13;
with its productivity crisis.&#13;
13.          Ecuador clung to its inward-oriented macroeconomic policy matrix for a&#13;
decade or more after most of its neighbors began to open their economies. Now the&#13;
accelerating pace of regional, hemispheric and global economic integration is forcing the&#13;
country to play catch-up in an increasingly competitive environment. NAFTA, the Andean&#13;
Pact, and MercoSur are harbingers of ever more rapid, comprehensive and expanding free&#13;
trade and economic integration during the next few years. This presages a complete&#13;
realignment in production and trading patterns as private investors focus on those goods and&#13;
services which they can produce most efficiently for a global economy.&#13;
5Hemrzo, A. Casimiro and Ruben Echeverria. 1993. "Agricultural Research in Spain: Experiences&#13;
Relevant to Latin America." The Hague: ISNAR, Discussion Paper No. 93-04, February.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
37&#13;
14.          Ecuador moribund research system for agriculture and its relatively low levels&#13;
of productivity can only be described as one of the most serious problems facing the nation.&#13;
The country is in an extremely precarious situation which is getting worse, as research&#13;
investments lag far behind its competitors. The Government must act decisively and soon with&#13;
substantial infusions of resources, especially human capital, if the country is to take advantage&#13;
of emerging new markets for products it produces. Even with such actions, the long gestation&#13;
period for agricultural research means that some opportunities are lost forever. But failure to&#13;
act will relegate the economy to even lower growth rates and eventual stagnation when&#13;
petroleum reserves are exhausted.&#13;
ILL Ecuador's Agricultural Research System:&#13;
Challenges and Opportunities&#13;
15.          Fundamental Problems. The research system suffers from several basic&#13;
problems which all tend to derive from inadequate funding for agricultural research. Because&#13;
INIAP has dominated the system for the last three decades most of the problems relate to&#13;
INIAP. Some of the constraints, however, relate to weaknesses in universities, and lack of&#13;
cohesiveness in the system.&#13;
16.          Too Few Research Scientists. Ecuador has significantly underinvested in&#13;
research scientists (ISNAR and IICA pp. 3943); (Venezian and Moncada pp. 29-30)16. The&#13;
number of researchers with post-graduate degrees in INIAP and the universities is inadequate&#13;
to produce the level of new technical knowledge needed for rapid, sustained increases in&#13;
agricultural productivity. For examnple, INIAP had only 6 Ph.Ds and 65 Masters in 1994,&#13;
down substantially from the mid-1980s. Universities had an additional 9 Ph.Ds and 70 Masters&#13;
in agricultural disciplines. This compares with 126 Ph.Ds and 353 Masters in Colombias&#13;
Govenmuent and semi-public research agencies, and universities (ISNAR unpublished data).&#13;
Several areas especially lack research scientists in Ecuador, including animal sciences, natural&#13;
resources, agricultural economics, rural sociology, biotechnology, and irrigation sciences.&#13;
17.          Inadequate Salaries. The principal constraint to attracting and retaining&#13;
agricultural scientists during the 1980s has been the relatively low salaries offered. As budget&#13;
support declined, INIAP lost four out of five Ph.Ds and 18 of 67 Masters between 1986 and&#13;
1989, or nearly one-third of its senior scientists in a three-year period. While the situation has&#13;
improved somewhat, LIAP continues to be plagued by turnover of research scientists. The&#13;
underlying problem is limited funding for INIAP, universities and other research institutes and&#13;
NGOs which are part of the system. Unless funding is increased, it will be very difficult to&#13;
increase salaries to market levels, even if the problem of an inadequate salary scale were&#13;
resolved. Thus, the research system has a difficult time competing for scarce human capital&#13;
and developing the critical mass of scientists necessary for a sustained research program.&#13;
16 Venezian Leigh, Eduardo and Jesus Moncada de la Fuente. 1989. "Ecuador. Propuesta de un Sistema&#13;
de Investigac6n y Transferencia de Tecnologia Agropecuaria ". Quito: MAG/USAID, September.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
38&#13;
18.          Little Interaction with the Private Sector. The current research system has&#13;
limited interaction with or support from the private sector. Research by INIAP has become&#13;
increasingly confined to research stations. In the 1980s, research programs were coordinated&#13;
closely with production research programs (Programas de Investigaci6n en Producci6n-&#13;
PIPs) which were carried out on cooperating farms. The PIP program provided a feedback&#13;
System from farmers to researchers as weil as involving researchers more directly in outreach&#13;
activities. However, the PIP program was reduced substantially because of budget constraints.&#13;
Results tend to remain "bottled up" on the stations and to be less relevant to farmers and&#13;
especially to other entrepreneurs in the food system. As public budget support has declined and&#13;
the private sector has had to become more involved in research, farners appear to have&#13;
become less and less supportive of INIAP. Universities, which also have increased their&#13;
involvement in agricultural research, have developed reasonably good linkages to the farmers&#13;
they serve. However, their research base is very small and tends to be oriented primarily&#13;
toward marginal farmers. Ecuador's research system needs to increase on-farm trials and&#13;
feedback from farmers and more fully integrate and include natural resource, economic and&#13;
social concerns into research design and recommendations.&#13;
19.          Limited Participation of Universities. Ecuador's universities are mainly&#13;
teaching institutions which historically have had little involvement in agricultural research or&#13;
exension activities. The number of university research scientists in agriculture (nine Ph.Ds and&#13;
70 Masters) is quite limited relative to the total agricultural faculty of 1,253. But it is&#13;
approximately twice the number of research scientists in INIAP and represents a resource that&#13;
can expand the amount of research being done for the sector.&#13;
20.           The limited agricultural research that is carried out is done almost exclusively&#13;
through thesis work, with some guidance from the major professor. The quality of thesis&#13;
research varies widely depending on source of funding and the quality of related guidance.&#13;
Library and other research facilities are deficient and linkages to the international network of&#13;
agricultural science are extremely limited. Resource constraints and poorly-trained faculty&#13;
result in little laboratory or field work. Classroom lectures dominate the educational process,&#13;
and most of the largely urban-raised students graduate with little or no practical experience in&#13;
agriculture.&#13;
21.          Resources for higher education are spread too thin. What is needed is a more&#13;
foased effort with substantial upgrading of a few key faculties of agriculture. The higher&#13;
education system needs to be linked into the international science network for agriculture and&#13;
more completely integrated into the national research and extension system, especially in the&#13;
area of research.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
39&#13;
22.           Weak International Linkages. Ecuador's research system does not have&#13;
strong, sustained working relationships with sister institutions in the international science&#13;
network. Ecuador science base for agriculture tends to work in isolation compared to many&#13;
other national systems (Posada Torres); (Joint Subcommittee)17. There is ample evidence that&#13;
national research systems substantially increase their productivity as they become fully&#13;
articulated into other national systems, international and regional research centers and foreign&#13;
agricultural universities (Hayami and Ruttan);1 (Arndt, Dalrymple and Ruttan)'9. Such&#13;
linkages eliminate duplication of effort and save scarce resources as the national science base&#13;
exploits research results from the international agricultural science network. Such results from&#13;
one country may have the potential of conferring large benefits in other countries but must be&#13;
accessed and then adapted by the national research system to fit different agro-climactic and&#13;
ecologic conditions in the new location.&#13;
23.           Inadequate Infrastructure. The physical infrastructure supporting Ecuador&#13;
science base for agriculture is beginning to deteriorate. Several experiment stations need to&#13;
have basic infrastructure such as plumbing and electricity modernized. Laboratory equipment&#13;
is outmoded and must be upgraded if the system is to be fully productive. Library holdings are&#13;
out of date and not adequate to provide researchers with access to peer research. Computer&#13;
facilities are limited both in terms of hardware and software. Finally, the research system has&#13;
very limited communication linkages to the international system, such as InterNet.&#13;
24.           Lack of Focus. Due to political pressure and lack of strong leadership INIAP&#13;
lost its focus throughout the 1980s. This led to a proliferation of programs that was not&#13;
matched by the financial resources put at its disposal. For example, by the late 1980s INTAP&#13;
research had expanded into nine research support programs (e.g., plant pathology), eighteen&#13;
crop and livestock commodity programs and four production systems programs (e.g., multiple-&#13;
crops). As a result, INMAP was attempting to cover over 80 separate research programs. The&#13;
problem has become even more difficult with the rapid loss of senior scientists since 1986, as&#13;
inexperienced junior scientists have had to fill positions for which they are not prepared. A&#13;
similar problem exists in universities which basically respond to the priorities present in the&#13;
limited amount of funding they receive.&#13;
25.           Research programs have concentrated almost exclusively on production&#13;
agriculture. Post-harvest handling and storage, processing, marketing and consumption are&#13;
largely ignored in the design of research programs. The important set of natural resources&#13;
issues affecting agriculture are not addressed by IMAP at all. They are dealt with on a&#13;
sporadic and ad hoc basis by private NGOs and foundations such as Funwdci6n Natura and in&#13;
17 Joint Subcommittee (Joint Ecuadorian/North Carolina State University Subcommittee). 1987.&#13;
"Reorientaci6n del Sector Agricola: Una estrategia para acelerar la aplicaci6n de las ciencias con&#13;
el fin de aumentar la productividad en la agricultura ecuatoriana" Quito: USAID, February.&#13;
18 Hayami, Yujiro, and Vernon W. Ruttan. 1985. "Agricultural Development: An International&#13;
Perspective" 2nd. Edition. Baltimore and London: The Johns Hopkins University Press.&#13;
9 Arndt, Thomnas M., Dana G. Dalrymple and Vernon M. Ruttan. 1977. "Resource Allocation and&#13;
Productivity in National and International Agricultural Research" Minneapolis: University of&#13;
Minnesota Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
40&#13;
a few university faculties of biology. Other important areas such as agricultural economics,&#13;
rural sociology and irmgated agriculture also are severely understaffed.&#13;
26.          No Systematic Approach. There is no systematic approach or congruent&#13;
policy structure to condition and focus agricultural research in Ecuador. The four principal&#13;
players in the system-INLAP, universities, the private sector, and NGOs, have little interaction&#13;
with each other. There is no clearly stated set of national priorities to guide resource&#13;
allocations, the institutional structure is disjointed and does not have a policy construct which&#13;
defines objectives and roles, there is little or no incentive for individual researchers to take&#13;
initiative, and the system is isolated from the international science network. More critically, the&#13;
private sector and consumers, which generally reap large benefits from the public goods nature&#13;
of much of the systens research, do not appreciate the role of public sector research in&#13;
agriculture.&#13;
27.          Agricultural research suffers from discontinuity of policies, personnel and&#13;
leadership. For example, there have been six Directors General of INIAP since 1981. Each&#13;
new administration has resulted in changes in the emphasis, organization, key personnel and&#13;
allocation of funds (Posada Torres). Even though INLAP now is an autonomous agency, the&#13;
Director must meet political as well as technical criteia and the agency thus is subject to short-&#13;
term political pressures. The result is a tendency toward centralized planning and management.&#13;
28.          Because research results tend to have a long gestation period, and also to be&#13;
location specific even within a countuy, a decentralized system is more efficient (Hayami and&#13;
Ruttan, Chapter 12). In South American countries the trend is toward autonomous,&#13;
decentralized systems, such as Brazils public corporation, the Brazilian Agency for Agricultural&#13;
Research (EMBRAPA). Ecuador needs to strongly consider the efficiencies inherent in a more&#13;
decentralized structure of it research systeni, including regionalization of INIAP, and stronger&#13;
role for universities.&#13;
Recent Improvements&#13;
29.          There have been several significant developments, especially during the last&#13;
two years, in the Ecuadoran agricultural research system. These developments and policy&#13;
changes provide a solid basis upon which a project intervention can be designed and&#13;
implemented. Collectively, they are a foundation upon which a new, modernized national&#13;
research system can be built.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
41&#13;
30.          An Autonomous INIAP. INLAP was given financial and administaive&#13;
autonomy on July 22, 1992 which has alleviated its salary constaint to some degree. This&#13;
autonomy has allowed the Institute to increase its salary levels to a base of US$750 for Ph.Ds&#13;
and US$450 for Masters. In practice the Ph.Ds currently employed earn as much as US$1,500&#13;
to US$2,000 through joint appointments with or through other entities. INLAP now has the&#13;
authority to increase salaries to market levels, but still will be subject to political pressures&#13;
about salary levels, since it still is a state agency, Also, it is subject to state rules about&#13;
personnel managernent. It can eliminate unwanted positions by buying early retrments, but it&#13;
loses the budget associated with the position. And it can only increase its staff through a&#13;
complicated approval process.&#13;
31.          Nevertheless, INIAP now enjoys substantially greater flexibility which should&#13;
facilitate the modernization of the research system. But even with modest increases in salary&#13;
levels, the Institute and universities face growing salary pressure from the increasing&#13;
internationalization of Ecuador's economy and the resulting integration of the professional&#13;
labor market.&#13;
32.          An Endowment Fund. INIAP also was given an endowment fimd of&#13;
S/. 20,000 million as part of the process of receiving its autonomy. The Government agreed to&#13;
pay this in three installments, with the first of S/. 7,000 million (about USS3.25 million at the&#13;
current exchange rate of 2,170) already paid, and the second intallment of S/. 7,000 million&#13;
now due. This is an important step in increasing budget support for INLAP. However, archaic&#13;
regulations force INIAP to invest the fund in state bonds which yield less than the rate of&#13;
inflation, so the principal balance is being eroded. If this problem can be addressed, the fimd&#13;
will grow to nearly US$10.0 million by 1997. If INLAP sells assets not needed for research,&#13;
the find could grow to as much as US$30.0 million by 1999. Interest eamnings on a fund of&#13;
this size will make a major contribution to INLAPs budget, as the project comes to an end.&#13;
Even with an endowment of this size, however, the Government will need to increase its aual&#13;
budget support to INIAP if the country is to meet minimum international standards of one&#13;
percent of AgGDP invested in agricultural research.&#13;
33.          A Downsizing Plan. lNIAPs current staffing, is 433 consisting of 194&#13;
professionals, 47 technicians, 87 administrative stag 50 service staff and 61 vacancies. In&#13;
addition six INIAP staff are away on higher degree training and 33 professional staff are&#13;
provided through contracts (many of which are in the technology transfer area). The recent&#13;
downsizing reduced total staff from 667 to 433 by major cut-backs in non-professional staff&#13;
INIAP appears to have done an excellent job in absorbing this reduction, although the number&#13;
of technicians per researcher is now below what is normal at research institutes and far below&#13;
the ratio in private sector agricultural research in Ecuador. Of the 188 professionals on hand&#13;
now 12 (six percent) are involved in senior management at headquarters and the seven research&#13;
stations, 11 (six percent) are in finance and administration, 10 (five percent) in the planning and&#13;
evaluation unit, five (three percent) in information/communications, 21 (11 percent) in&#13;
technology transfer, 13 (seven percent) in production and 116 (62 percent) in conducting&#13;
research. This suggests a rational and balanced distribution, particularly as many of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
42&#13;
contracted staff not included in this total have a function that relates closely to technology&#13;
transfer and validation so that the real figure for this task may be closer to 20 percent.&#13;
34.          The manpower plan for training in the project will need to be carefully designed&#13;
in terms of disciplines in order to ensure that it is tailored to develop persons who are potential&#13;
leaders, while at the same time ensuring that INIAP trains a core of expertise in all key&#13;
disciplines. An effort should be made to ensure that all trainees take some courses in&#13;
management as this is likely to be an important part of the task of a number of them when they&#13;
return. In addition to training biological researchers the training programn should be used to&#13;
strengthen the planning/economics expertise in INIAP and also skills in information, so that&#13;
INLAP can capitalize on the "information revolution" that is now taking place throughout the&#13;
world.&#13;
35.          Priority Setting. INIAP has been aware of the need to focus and concentrate&#13;
its research program for several years. It has sponsored a careful analysis of research priorities&#13;
(Palomino and Norton)20 and has developed and implemented a more focused and&#13;
concentrated research program (RIAP 1993b)21. This program includes 12 national programs&#13;
covering 20 crops, and another seven interdisciplinary research programs. This new, focused&#13;
set of priorities is an improvement over the ad hoc collection of research programs that had&#13;
evolved in response to political pressures in the 1980s. The Ministry of Agriculture has&#13;
adopted these priorities as the basis for funding subprojects in the Agricultural Research&#13;
Project.&#13;
36.          Increased University Involvement. Universities have become increasingly&#13;
involved in agricultural research throughout the 1980s, with funding support from CONUEP.&#13;
They have developed small pockets of capability with substantial local support from farmers&#13;
and their associations. They have become increasingly aggressive in pursuing relationships and&#13;
funding support from other sources, including international agencies. They also have&#13;
developed extension and outreach programs to serve local clientele. The universities represent&#13;
a fledgling base of regional support for agricultural research from the private sector. Their&#13;
faculty resources need to be further integrated into the research system on a more regular and&#13;
sustained basis, for they are an important resource for strengthening and modernizing it.&#13;
37.          Expanding Linkages within the System. Linkages among the four major&#13;
players in the agricultural research system are increasing. Universities have signed research&#13;
contracts with INAP, the Foundation for Agricultural Development (FUNDAGRO) and&#13;
others (Venezian and Moncada pp. 44145). NGOs are becoming a more integral part of the of&#13;
the agricultural science network in Ecuador through contracts for research with INIAP and&#13;
universities. And the private sector has increased its ties to the system, especially to&#13;
universities. INIAP has long had important ties to university faculties. It selects students in&#13;
20 Palomino, Julio and George Norton. 192. "Determinaci6n de Prioridades de Investigaci6n&#13;
Agropecuaria en Ecuador. " Quito INL4P.&#13;
21 INIAP. 1993b. "Politicasy Estrategias del Instituto NacionalAutonomo de Investigaciones&#13;
Agropecuarias (INIAP). Quito.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
43&#13;
their last year from various university faculties and provides them with scholarships as part of&#13;
the APo Tcnico Rural program (one year of required public service as part of a undegraduae&#13;
degree program). In return, the students work at INIAP experiment stations where they learn&#13;
basic research skills and do their thesis as part of an INIAP research project, under close&#13;
supervision and guidance of INIAP scientists. The numbers of students trained under this&#13;
program have ranged from 15-40 per year, depending on the number of positions assigned by&#13;
MAG (ISNAR and IICA p. 37). INIAP hires the most capable of these graduates into its&#13;
research staff Thus, INIAP identifies a select corps of advanced university students and trains&#13;
them in research methodology and applied agricultural sciences. In essence, it provides the&#13;
closest thing there is to post-graduate training in agriculture science in Ecuador. It also has had&#13;
a fairly good program of advanced training for its staff in various degree and nondegree&#13;
programs abroad.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
44&#13;
ANNEX 4&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECI&#13;
Economic Evaluation&#13;
1.            Economic analysis for the project has been carried out to test its economic&#13;
viability. A multiple criteria model has been utilized in light of the fact that agricultural&#13;
research is focused upon different objectives such as: economic growth, distribution of&#13;
income and sustainability; multiple criteria models seem to be more appropriate to&#13;
evaluate the attainment of different objectives.&#13;
2.            The model used is one which was developed in 1990 by the International&#13;
Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT). It is a partial equilibrium model called "Analysis&#13;
of Economic Surpluses" (MODEXC) and is designed to evaluate the direct benefits of&#13;
new technology and associated income distribution results. The evaluation for the&#13;
proposed project, which measures the potential impact of technology generation and&#13;
transfer projects, uses MODEXC for several reasons:&#13;
* The model has a solid theoretical basis. It explicitly includes exogenous changes in&#13;
supply and demand, that are not linked to technological change under analysis;&#13;
3  The model has been successfully used in a number of studies: Pachico, Lynam and&#13;
Jones (1987)22, Alston, Edwards and Freebairn (1988)2, Rivas et al (1992)24,&#13;
Jarvis and Sere (1988)25.&#13;
*  The resulting indicators permit prioritization among commodities. They show&#13;
which commodities produce larger social benefits and which should have a higher&#13;
priority when research budgets are being assigned.&#13;
22 Pacheco, D. J.K. Lyiman and P. Jones (1987). The distribution of benefits from technical change&#13;
among classes of consumers and producers: an ex-ante analysis of beans in Brazil. Research Policy.&#13;
Volume 16, No. 5, pp. 279-285.&#13;
23 Alston, J.M., G.W. Edwards and J.W. Freebairn (1988) Market distortions and benefits from research.&#13;
American Journal of Agnicultural Economics 70(2) pp. 281-288.&#13;
24 L. Rivas, James Garcia, Carlos Sere, Lowell S. Jarvis and Luis R Sanint. Modelo de Andis de&#13;
Excedentes Econnmicos (MODEXC) abril de 1992 CAT, Documento de Trabajo 107.&#13;
25 Sere, C. and L.S. Jarvis (1988): The betting line of beef: ex ante estimates of improved pastures:&#13;
research benefits for the Latin American Tropics; Presented in ISNAR\RUTGERS "Agricultural&#13;
Technology Management Workshop", Rutgers University, New Bnmswick, New Jersey, July 6-8,&#13;
1988.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
45&#13;
3.          The social benefits and costs for each technological option are estimated&#13;
and benefits of each technology are distributed among specific activities (such as genetic&#13;
improvements or new fertilization systems). This process allows estimation of economic&#13;
efficiency for each activity.&#13;
4.          In order to evaluate the impact of technology transfer activities, it is&#13;
necessary to emphasize that their objective is to get new technologies accepted by the&#13;
market. Given this fact, it is necessary to consider these activities in the technology&#13;
generation process, and quantify the benefits according to their relative weight in the&#13;
process. This should be taken into account when the case of the National Autonomous&#13;
Institute for Agricultural Research (INIAP) is analyzed. It should be remembered that&#13;
INIAP does not transfer technology to producers. Its mission is to generate and validate&#13;
technology for the use of private and public organizations that are in charge of transfer&#13;
and extension activities.&#13;
5.          The selection of commodities considered under the analysis is based on the&#13;
relative weight each commodity holds in the gross national agricultural product (GNAP).&#13;
The GNAP used in this case represents the average for years 1991 through 1993.&#13;
6.          The result is a group of 19 products that accounts for 97 percent of the&#13;
total aggregate value of domestic production. However, the model has been run for just&#13;
16 products --excluding sugar cane, tomatoes and cotton, that only account for four&#13;
percent of total aggregate production. The following table shows the assumed average&#13;
annual growth rate for each of the 16 products. The output projections are based on&#13;
NIAP historical data which measures the impact of a package of technology (similar to&#13;
the one applied under the proposed project) on commodity production. The price&#13;
projections are based on historical commodity price trends.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
46&#13;
Average Annual Rate of Growth of Prices and Production&#13;
Thousands of US$&#13;
Rice                  0.9/O        3.1%&#13;
Bananas               0.2%          1.5%&#13;
Cocoa                 -1.7%         3.2%&#13;
Coffee                 1.3%         0.4%&#13;
Beef                  0.2%          2.5%&#13;
Barley                -1.3%         1.4%&#13;
Dry Beans             -3.5%         2.5%&#13;
Milk                  -0.8%         3.90/o&#13;
Maize                 -0.9%         3.5%&#13;
Sweet Corn            3.3%         -1.4%&#13;
Maize Soft Dry        -0.2%         1.90/a&#13;
Oil Palm              0.2%          1.5%&#13;
Potatoes              -2.5%         2.70/a&#13;
Plantains             -1.7%         2.90/o&#13;
Soybeans              0.1%          1.70/o&#13;
Wheat                 -2.90/o      -1.0%Vo&#13;
Average               -0.6%         1.9%/6&#13;
7.           These growth assumptions for specific commodities, along with the&#13;
following additional assumptions have been incorporated in the economic model in order&#13;
to estimate benefits for the overall project. These additional assumptions include:&#13;
3 An estimation of the exogenous production growth rates and demand for the&#13;
commodities considered under the analysis;&#13;
*  Identification of supply and demand price elasticity, and demand income elasticity&#13;
values for the selected commodities;&#13;
*  The consumption structure for selected commodities in relation to income levels&#13;
consistent with those of beneficiaries under the project; and&#13;
*  Identification of farm models representative of farms impacted by the project.&#13;
8.          In addition, to measure the impact of specific technologies under the&#13;
project, technical coefficients and research costs associated with new technologies, and the&#13;
way in which these technologies influence the supply of the selected commodities, have&#13;
been estimated. These estimates include the:&#13;
* Yields of the new and present technologies;&#13;
* Time frame in which the new technologies are inplemented;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
47&#13;
* Time frame for adoption of the new technologies;&#13;
* Potential land area where new technologies could be used;&#13;
* Percentage of potential area required by the new technologies;&#13;
* Research activities that are undertaken to obtain a given technology;&#13;
* Estimate of the probability of success of the research process; and&#13;
* Cash flow of research costs for each activity and technology.&#13;
9.           This data allows for the estimation of increased production because of&#13;
technological change and its adoption by farmers. The yield growth rates used in the&#13;
assumptions are averaged over the period used in the evaluation, while real growth rates&#13;
may be more uneven. It is also assumed that the technologies are scale neutral and all&#13;
farmers will participate in their use to varying extents. This is purely technical infonnation,&#13;
taken directly at INIAP's research stations, from interviews with different commodity&#13;
research specialists.&#13;
10.          The model calculates points of market equilibrium for each of the fifteen&#13;
years in which the project is evaluated. Based on this, the model estimates producers and&#13;
consumer surpluses, separating those that can be ascribed to technological factors. It&#13;
should be kept in mind that the benefits ascribed to the project are only a part of the total&#13;
benefits. Only thirty per cent of the surpluses, multiplied by the probability of success for&#13;
each technology through the research and transfer process has been considered the benefit&#13;
that can be ascribed to the project. This probability of success ranges between 75 and 80&#13;
percent depending on the specific technology.&#13;
11.          The results of calculating the market equilibrium for all commodities&#13;
considered under the analysis, and separating out only benefits which accrue from&#13;
technology use, are shown in the following table. Total net benefits are estimated at&#13;
nearly US$750 million in year 15. Using the methodology described in paragraph 10 to&#13;
estimate the portion of these total benefits which can be ascribed to the proposed project,&#13;
net benefits from the project are estimated at nearly US$176 million in year 15.&#13;
12.          Using the benefit flows attributable to the project, as shown in the&#13;
following table, and the project costs for both Agricultural Research and Extension, the&#13;
Net Present Value (NPV) and Internal Rate of Return (IRR) are calculated. The NPV is&#13;
estimated at about US$389 million, using a discount rate of 12 percent. The IRR is&#13;
estimated at 52 percent. These results are in line with numerous ex post studies regarding&#13;
the impact of agriculture research and technology projects in Latin America and&#13;
worldwide.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
48&#13;
Research and Technology Transfer Benefits&#13;
Thousands of US$&#13;
1995               9,763              2,174&#13;
1996               13,112             3,028&#13;
1997              101,310            23,912&#13;
1998              167,849            39,450&#13;
1999              223,262            52,693&#13;
2000              354,771             83,736&#13;
2001              431,059            100,938&#13;
2002              485,149            112,557&#13;
2003              521,897            120,916&#13;
2004              553,068            128,337&#13;
2005              586,303            136,283&#13;
2006              622,374            144,914&#13;
2007              661,486            154,277&#13;
2008              704,012            164,461&#13;
2009              749,910            175,459&#13;
13.         Finally, the analysis also shows that there are significant benefits to&#13;
international trade; that is, for the commodities which were analyzed using an open&#13;
economy assumption. For most of these, there is a high probability that exports would&#13;
increase, assuming appropriate economic policies, infrastructure, and sanitary conditions.&#13;
14.         The following table shows that the commercial benefits, which would&#13;
accrue from increased exports of these commodities, would significantly improve&#13;
Ecuador's trade balance. When the results of the model application are consolidated, the&#13;
trade surplus for these products could grow by 49 percent in the year 2,000, from&#13;
US$415 millions to US$619 millions, and at the end of the project it could more than&#13;
triple to US$1,303 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
49&#13;
Imports and Exports 1992 and Projections for 2000 and 2009&#13;
Thousands of US$&#13;
Rice                          20,168 T101478 T351,993 &#13;
Bananas                      472,629          546,022 |579,202|&#13;
Cocoa               1          6,236            1,288           11,260&#13;
Coffee                        10,889           15,038           13,507&#13;
Beef                               0            14,124          75,677&#13;
Barley                        (3,171)          (6,032)          (9,586)&#13;
DryBeans*l                         0                0                0&#13;
Milk                           (325)           26,743          300,056&#13;
Maize                             (4)           14,450          80,779&#13;
SweetCorn*                         0                0                0&#13;
Maize Soft Dry                     0                7               11&#13;
OilPalm**                     (1,012)            1,106            1,025&#13;
Potatoes**                         0                0                0&#13;
Plantain**                         0                0                0&#13;
Soybeans**                   (43,774)         (43,770)         (43,779)&#13;
Wheat                        (46,558)1        (51,362)|        (57,279)&#13;
Total                        415,078 l        619,094         1,302,866&#13;
* Not a tradable product.       ** Palm Oil.&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis&#13;
15.         The sensitivity analysis canied out for the project tests the impact of either&#13;
overall income decreases or cost increases. As the following tables show, by decreasing&#13;
benefits such that income resulting from the project falls by 20 percent, the estimated internal&#13;
rate of return would decline by eight percent. This represents a reduction in the NPV of about&#13;
US$95 million. Because of the relatively high NPV and return, as the switching value&#13;
demonstrates, benefits would have to fall by over 80 percent to obtain an NPV of zero. A&#13;
20 percent increase in overall costs yields similar NPV and IRR results. To obtain an NPV of&#13;
zero, costs would have to increase by nearly six times.&#13;
16.         These results suggest that project returns are quite sensitive to movements in&#13;
overall benefits and costs. Such sensitivity can be explained somewhat by the significant&#13;
variation of commodities incorporated in the model and the associated range of estimates for&#13;
movements in prices and output. Furthermore, the estimated benefits are based exclusively on&#13;
improved product yields, directly linked to commodity prices and output. There is no&#13;
consideration of off-farm income which could result from the project and would be mnore stable&#13;
than income from the production and sale of commodities. In any case, as the switching values&#13;
indicate, the estimated project returns and net present value are significantly high enough that a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
50&#13;
20 percent unfavorable shift in either benefits or costs would not produce negative overall&#13;
reslts.&#13;
Benefits Reduced by 20 Percent&#13;
Thousands of US$&#13;
1995               1,739             51,250            49,511&#13;
1996               2,423             15,864           -13,442&#13;
1997               19,130            15,954            3,176&#13;
1998              31,560             13,281            18,279&#13;
1999              42,155              8,273            33,882&#13;
2000               66,989                              66,989&#13;
2001               80,750                              80,750&#13;
2002               90,045                              90,045&#13;
2003               96,733                              96,733&#13;
2004              102,669                             102,669&#13;
2005              109,027                             109,027&#13;
2006              115,931                             115,931&#13;
2007              123,421                             123,421&#13;
2008              131,568                             131,568&#13;
2009              140,367       _    _     _          140,367&#13;
NPV: US$294,905         IRR: 44%           Switching Value: -82%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
51&#13;
Costs Increased by 20 Percent&#13;
Thousands of US$&#13;
\(W1 var       Projec(t lBeiletfis   (Costs          Net I (4i'Iit0&#13;
ltetI(lc e(i   h)N 20"i.0&#13;
1995               2,174             61,500           -59,326&#13;
1996               3,028             19,037           -16,009&#13;
1997              23,912             19,145            4,768&#13;
1998              39,450             15,937           23,513&#13;
1999              52,693             9,927            42,766&#13;
2000               83,736                              83,736&#13;
2001              100,938                             100,938&#13;
2002              112,557                             112,557&#13;
2003              120,916                             120,916&#13;
2004              128,337                             128,337&#13;
2005              136,283                             136,283&#13;
2006              144,914                             144,914&#13;
2007              154,277                             154,277&#13;
2008              164,461                             164,461&#13;
2009              175,459      1                1    175,459&#13;
NPV: US$372,776         IRR: 46%           Switching Value: +570%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
52&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL SERVICES PROJECT&#13;
Guidelines for the Competitve Research Grants Program and Research and&#13;
Education Exchange Partnerships&#13;
1.          A Competitive Research Grants Program (CRG Program) is a new venture&#13;
in Ecuador. Fortunately, as suggested above, it is not a totally foreign concept to&#13;
professionals there, many of whom have been educated in the United States or in Europe.&#13;
Several agricultural researchers and engineers in both university and private nonprofit&#13;
industry sectors that have competed successfully for research awards from foreign&#13;
institutions, such as the Smithsonian Institute in Washington, D.C., U. S.A. Moreover, the&#13;
Ecuadoran university community already has an identifiable competitive grants program in&#13;
place, which is administered by CONUEP (Manual de Evaluaci6n de Proyectos de&#13;
Investigaci6n). It should be noted, however, that although a competitive grants program&#13;
is in place in the universities, the program has never been funded at the recommended level&#13;
of 1.0 percent of GNP. In 1992, for example CONUEPs available research funds were&#13;
under 0.01 percent GNP. Thus, while the program may not be well known, or appreciated&#13;
in all sectors, its existence shows that there is a small number of agricultural scientists and&#13;
engineers at work in the universities. They should be able to prepare research proposals&#13;
and compete in a CRG Program, even though their number might be small.&#13;
2.           A CRG Program operates on the principle that the system selects for&#13;
scientific excellence by providing the Principle Investigator (PI), or the Project Director&#13;
(PD) with adequate funding to enable research on a particular topic. Research enablement&#13;
typically includes support for personnel, research materials, research instrumentation,&#13;
opportunities for attending and participating at scientific meetings, and paying costs for&#13;
publishing scientific results in edited professional journals. The PI is the designated&#13;
individual researcher responsible for preparing and submitting the research grant, and for&#13;
carrying out the research plan. A PD is an individual researcher responsible for&#13;
administering a group, or team, of researchers working on a specific research theme. For&#13;
example, a PD would be the professional scientist in charge of a multidisciplinary, multi-&#13;
institutional association of university, INLAP, NGO, and/or private sector laboratories.&#13;
3.           The CRG Program encourages, and sometimes requires, multidisciplinary,&#13;
multi-institutional associations or partnerships. For example, an individual research grant&#13;
has one PI, but may have additional Co-PIs, or Contractors, from different disciplines&#13;
and/or institutions. This arrangement is always encouraged, where appropriate, and&#13;
allows for the performance of joint research projects between different university, INIAP,&#13;
NGOs, and private sector laboratories. (Private sector research laboratories will be&#13;
eligible to enter into partnerships with these entities and will be expected to provide&#13;
appropriate matching support for the project.).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
53&#13;
4.          The success of the CRG Program in identifying and supporting excellent&#13;
research requires a simple, direct system for Award selection. The steps in the process are&#13;
few and are summarized below (a detailed description follows in Figure 1):&#13;
* the PI/PD submits the proposal for scientific peer review to the Research&#13;
Implementation Unit (MU) via his/her institutional base;&#13;
*  the proposal is checked for completeness and entered into the competition;&#13;
*  the proposal is reviewed by the MU Director in charge of its review and sent to&#13;
five panel members with a request for written reviews;&#13;
*  the Peer Review Panel convenes, as scheduled, to discuss each proposal and&#13;
make funding recommendations (after discussion of each proposal, the five&#13;
panelists responsible for earlier written reviews prepare an additional statement&#13;
to convey the "sense" of the panel discussion to the PI, i.e., was the proposal&#13;
received enthusiastically, was the research topic well presented, interesting,&#13;
was it competitive, or, if not, what might the PI do to make it competitive,&#13;
etc.); and&#13;
- the MU makes a final funding decision and notifies the PI and the grantee (the&#13;
PIs institutional base) if an Award is to be made and the amount.&#13;
Applicant&#13;
Principal&#13;
Investigator&#13;
MU &#13;
Office                                   T&#13;
Recipient&#13;
Institution&#13;
MU&#13;
Officer&#13;
, i \       '             ~MU&#13;
Site Visit    0                                    Officer&#13;
Recommendation&#13;
Mail (ad hoc)            Proposal&#13;
Review  .                as is/if&#13;
Revised &#13;
Panel       t   ,\&#13;
Review                                             Overall&#13;
Discussions with Applicant            Evaluation&#13;
Figure 1: Flow Chart for Competitive Review of Research Grant Proposals&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
54&#13;
5.          As illustrated in Figure 1, once the applicant proposal arrives at the MU&#13;
office, the process of review begins. The proposal is checked by office staff for&#13;
completeness and compliance with format guidelines as defined in the Operational Manual.&#13;
In the event that the proposal is incomplete, or is not compliant, the proposer will be&#13;
notified and given ten working days to send the required number of corrected copies of&#13;
the proposal. Each proposal is assigned an identification number by office staff, and the&#13;
proposal is given to an MU Officer.&#13;
6.           The MU Officer will review the proposal further for compliance with&#13;
format guidelines and for appropriateness in the research program. Inappropriate&#13;
proposals are those determined to lie outside MU funding areas and will be withdrawn&#13;
from competition. The proposer will be notified of this decision. The proposal will not&#13;
normally be returned.&#13;
7.           Careful review of each research grant proposal is a time-consuming,&#13;
laborious task. As illustrated in Figure 1, the MU Officer must judge each proposal&#13;
separately based upon the reviews of experts in the field. All the proposals will be&#13;
reviewed by the Peer Review Panel. Review panel discussions of research grant proposals&#13;
occur behind closed doors. Only MU personnel and other individuals authorized by the&#13;
MU office may be present during these discussions.&#13;
8.          Under circumstances when the MU Officer performs a site-visit and/or&#13;
sends the proposal to additional experts for ad hoc (outside) review (in addition to Peer&#13;
Review Panelists), panel members requested to review the proposal must always be&#13;
informed of the results of these actions. The MU may decide to pursue these additional&#13;
modes of review either before or after the Peer Review Panel meeting. Proposals of&#13;
"sitting" members on the Peer Review Panel only may be reviewed without direct&#13;
consultation with the Peer Review Panel. In these cases, the MU Officer must obtain the&#13;
professional evaluation (in writing and signed) of three experts in the field in order to&#13;
arrive at a funding decision. This decision must also be agreed to by at least one&#13;
additional, appropriate MU grant review officer.&#13;
9.           At the end of the review, PI/PD notification begins. The PI/PDs of Awards&#13;
are notified first by telephone and officially once all conditions are met, through his/her&#13;
grantee business office. To initiate the Award, the MU explains the conditions and&#13;
requests the PI/PD to prepare and send an Abstract (about 200 words) of the project in&#13;
laymans terms for public information, and a revised budget section and research grant&#13;
cover sheet, signed by both the PI/PD(s) and the grantee responsible officer if the amount&#13;
of the Award is different from that originally requested. After all the requisite budgetary&#13;
documents have been signed and submitted to the MU office, the Award can be made and&#13;
money transferred to the appropriate grantee business office. Finally, a congratulatory&#13;
letter with copies of proposal reviews (names of reviewers are confidential and do not&#13;
show on these copies) and the panel statement are sent to the PI/PD.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
55&#13;
10.         In the CRG Program when an Award is made, the PI/PD institutional base&#13;
(e.g., university, INIAP, or NGO) is the grantee and is responsible for the institutional&#13;
accountability of the MU research moneys. This is generally handled by specialists in&#13;
business/accounting offices. The accounting office must establish an account in the name&#13;
of the PI/PD by which he/she can authorize spending award money in the support of the&#13;
research project. In the event that the PI/PD official changes institutions, any residual,&#13;
available funds from the Award will be transferable to the new PM/PD support institution.&#13;
11.         In a similar manner, letters of decline are prepared for each one of the&#13;
proposals not to be funded. These letters express regrets and are accompanied by copies&#13;
of each review (names of reviewers are confidential and do not show on these copies) plus&#13;
a Peer Review Panel statement, which should reflect the tone and note important points&#13;
raised during panel discussion that could be of use in reshaping and/or focusing the&#13;
research program for resubmission.&#13;
12.         Award Selection Criteria. The Award selection is the most important&#13;
activity of the Competitive Grant System and the final decision to recommend an Award&#13;
rests with the MU Officer responsible for the grant review. However, in every review&#13;
process the scientific merit of grant proposals that lie outside the MU Officers area of&#13;
expertise must be decided. In this, and all other cases as well, the MU officer must obtain&#13;
evidence to support a decision from experts in the research area of the grant proposal. As&#13;
outlined in the previous section. three resources for proposal review are available: site-&#13;
visits on the part of the MU officer, or other qualified professional designated by the MU&#13;
officer; ad hoc (reviewers not on the Peer Review Panel) mail reviews; and&#13;
recommendations made by panelists in their reviews and after discussions at the formal&#13;
panel meeting. All proposals will be reviewed by the Peer Review Panel (except those&#13;
submitted by panelists themselves; see earlier discussion). The proposal will be judged by&#13;
at least three panelists independently (before the panel meeting, panelists will have written&#13;
and signed their independent proposal reviews and distributed them to the other&#13;
appropriate panel members beforehand), and finally after panel discussion. The MU&#13;
officer may rely only on panelists, or can choose independently or at the request of the&#13;
panel, to seek additional expert advice by ad hoc review and/or by conducting a site visit.&#13;
No pending proposal(s) from a panelist present at the panel session will be mentioned on&#13;
the list of proposals given to the panel to review. These proposals will be reviewed solely&#13;
by ad hoc review.&#13;
13.         In the process of judging the scientific merit of any research grant proposal&#13;
addressing INIAP initiatives and other national priorities in agricultural research&#13;
established by MAG, the responsible MU officer should consider the following criteria&#13;
stated briefly below in arriving at a funding decision.&#13;
* Research Performance Competence. Is the PI/PD capable/experienced in&#13;
performing proposed experiments, is the proposed technical approach sound,&#13;
and are facilities available to perform the work?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
56&#13;
* Intrinsic Merit of the Research. What will be the end result of the project and&#13;
will it contribute to, or lead to, important advances in the field?&#13;
* Utility or Relevance of the Research. Will the results of the project make&#13;
important contributions to general knowledge outside the immediate area of&#13;
interest, and serve as a basis for improved technology or as a solution to&#13;
environmental problems?&#13;
* Will the project contribute to a better understanding or improvement of&#13;
agricultural production, implementation of better measures for protection of&#13;
the environment, as well as stimulate further research, education; and&#13;
*  development of manpower in agriculture sciences?&#13;
14.         In addition, the "Manual de Evaluacion de Proyectos de Investigaci6n"&#13;
(CONUEP, 1991) cites additional important criteria that include but are not limited to:&#13;
clarity of presentation, organization of ideas in a convincing manner, identification of&#13;
research objectives and goals, significance of the research program, and proper grammar.&#13;
Research and Education Exchange Partnerships with International Institutions&#13;
15.         Research and Education and Exchange Partnerships would be based on&#13;
themes that are designated as areas of national priorities by the Ministry of Agriculture and&#13;
would be based in Ecuadoran research institutes, foundations and universities.&#13;
Partnerships based in institutes and foundations would emphasize research while those&#13;
based in universities would emphasize education and training in agricultural research. The&#13;
Partnership grant would be awarded to the Ecuadoran institution.&#13;
16.         The role of the Partnerships with International Institutions is to:&#13;
*  foster joint research program development;&#13;
*  develop academic units with the intellectual recognition for functioning&#13;
as the units for awarding graduates in agricultural sciences at the M.S.&#13;
level;&#13;
*  organize special 6 to 8 month introductory course on the agricultural&#13;
theme of the Partnership to be taken by all appropriate Ph.D. and M.S.&#13;
fellowship candidates before their departure for foreign study. These&#13;
special courses should be organized to form the center of a fully&#13;
developed, recognized M.S. degree program;&#13;
* establish specialized technological centers equipped with research&#13;
equipment items in support of research and technology transfer;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
57&#13;
* recruit and help to identify candidates for Ph.D. and M.S. fellowships;&#13;
* attract highly qualified Ph.D.-level professionals to participate in the&#13;
program as adjunct faculty members; and&#13;
* purchase laboratory materials to help support Ecuadoran student&#13;
graduate degree thesis research.&#13;
17.          Partnership facilities and personnel will play a major role in the&#13;
development of the Ecuadoran agricultural community in technical development and&#13;
educational training. However, the number of advanced degree personnel both within&#13;
INIAP and in the universities is too small to accomplish the task alone. To help make up&#13;
for this "short fall" appointments must be made of adjunct faculty bearing the degree of&#13;
Ph.D. and actively working the field.&#13;
18    .     Adjunct faculty appointments are quite common among developed country&#13;
universities and are used to bring individuals with highly specialized skills, who hold Ph.D.&#13;
degrees, into a specific program, or into an academic unit,. These adjunct faculty&#13;
members are nonpaid salary appointments who receive voting/decision-making privileges&#13;
within the "appointing" unit, where they also benefit from the prestige of the appointment&#13;
and their association with the research program itself. Faculty members from U.S.&#13;
institutions often participate in programs such as these by obtaining paid leaves of absence&#13;
from their home institutions. Room and board living expenses are usually provided by the&#13;
host institution. For this, adjunct faculty members will bring their own expertise to bear&#13;
on the project in Ecuador. They will also be required to aid in the host institutions&#13;
teaching responsibilities either in the classroom or in the research laboratory. All adjunct&#13;
professors and adjunct faculty appointments from the private sector (qualified personnel&#13;
who hold the degree of Ph.D. in an appropriate area), need to participate in the 6 to 8&#13;
month introductory course on the agricultural theme of the Partnership. It is believed that&#13;
this classroom/laboratory experience can serve to initiate graduate student training in&#13;
Ecuador. Thus, adjunct faculty appointments will be made to qualified academicians and&#13;
private sector professionals in Ecuador and outside the country.&#13;
19.         The development of graduate degree programs inside Ecuador should be a&#13;
primary objective of the Partnership program, especially in university-based projects. The&#13;
Central University of Quito, the largest public university in Ecuador, is already organizing&#13;
and presenting course offerings in agricultural sciences using faculty recruited from both&#13;
within and outside of Ecuador. At present the postgraduate program (Programa de&#13;
Postgrado en Ciencias Agricolas) has three 10 week course offerings with meetings&#13;
occurring approximately once each month over an entire year. A Diploma of&#13;
Specialization (Diploma de Especialista) is granted upon completion of all 10 modules.&#13;
Initiatives such as this one, suggest that the organization of a 6 to 8 month introductory&#13;
course by individual universities using both university regular and adjunct faculty should&#13;
be readily possible.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
58&#13;
20.         In accord with this discussion, a Partnership with its adjunct faculty (and&#13;
appropriate adjunct technical researchers) can become the site for the formation of a M.S.&#13;
degree program in a specific area. These M.S. degree programs should begin to be&#13;
developed one year after the first Partnership awards have been made. It will not be&#13;
possible to begin to organize a recognized Ph.D. degree program for at least ten years,&#13;
after Ph.Ds trained in this program return and have had the opportunity to develop their&#13;
own research careers in Ecuador. Even then, the research community will need to&#13;
continue to rely upon adjunct faculty interest and cooperation, and these programs will&#13;
most likely be inter-institutional.&#13;
21.          A Partnership Grant should not be looked upon as a permanent mechanism&#13;
for the funding of a group of investigators, but as a mechanism that serves a particular&#13;
purpose at a particular time in the scientific development of the Ecuadoran agricultural&#13;
research community. It would be expected that some projects initiated under Partnership&#13;
funding might evolve or expand in such a way as to warrant separate lines of support,&#13;
while new Partnership projects would emerge to take their place. When a Partnership no&#13;
longer fulfills the intended puipose, it would be expected to come to a natural end. As&#13;
such time, support of ongoing research may, of course, be sought under the Competitive&#13;
Research Grants Program.&#13;
22.          "Sister" Institution Partnerships. There are a large number of models&#13;
available for both informal and formal "sister" institutional alignments. The formation of&#13;
an analogous networks can be organized in joint INIAP, university, private sector research&#13;
partnerships with international institutions in Ecuador. Institutional Partnerships must be&#13;
organized with great care and the "sister" institute must be fully aware of what is&#13;
expected. In the case of universities, the Ecuadoran institution will cooperate with its&#13;
"sister" institute in both student education and in laying the groundwork for a degree-&#13;
granting Ecuadoran "institution" in agricultural services.&#13;
23.          The task of training foreign graduate students is the traditional role of most&#13;
"sister" institute partnerships. Graduate student training will begin in Ecuador in special&#13;
introductory courses (in which appropriate "sister" institute adjunct faculty members will&#13;
participate) followed by additional course work at the foreign "sister" institute or other&#13;
appropriate institution. Once this course work is completed, students will return to their&#13;
Ecuadoran institution. In the case of the Ph.D. candidate, to perform his/her research&#13;
thesis work. Once the Ph.D. thesis research is completed to the satisfaction of both&#13;
institutions, the degree candidate will return to the "sister" institute, or other appropriate&#13;
institution, to defend the thesis in accord with the requirements for the degree of Ph.D.&#13;
24.          The task of building a recognized award granting entity in Ecuador in&#13;
agricultural research will be long-term as discussed earlier. At present, the Ecuadoran&#13;
agricultural research community is small and does not have a critical number of Ph.D.-&#13;
level personnel to grant a recognized graduate degree. This could begin to change,&#13;
however, under favorable conditions that will allow for the Competitive Research Grants&#13;
program to take affect, and which in turn should give employment for returning young&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
59&#13;
Ph.D. researchers to Ecuador and provide them with the means to organize their own&#13;
research programs. As a beginning, the Partnership with useful "Sister" Institution&#13;
Partnerships can operate to form a foundation. In keeping with this objective, the&#13;
Ecuadoran university in its negotiations with a sister institute, must make the need clear&#13;
for sharing in the responsibility of laying the groundwork for a graduate degree granting&#13;
program in Ecuador through active faculty teaching/research commitments.&#13;
25.         Applicants for advanced degree fellowships will be evaluated on their&#13;
ability, accomplishments, and potential as evidenced by letters of recommendation; results&#13;
on standardized graduate school entry examinations (as required by the admissions&#13;
committee at a "sister" institution); the quality and significance of their proposed research&#13;
topic; the cross-disciplinary potential of the research topic; and the likely impact of the&#13;
proposed training and research on the applicant's future scientific development and long-&#13;
range career goals. Applications will be reviewed by an advisory committee comprised of&#13;
faculty members which includes adjunct faculty members. This advisory committee will&#13;
make its recommendations to the NGO administering the competitive aspects of the&#13;
project where final selection of graduate fellows will be made. The NGO will notify&#13;
awardees within one month after the advisory committee recommendation, and&#13;
immediately begin to lay plans, in consultation with the sponsoring Ecuadoran institution,&#13;
for the student's advanced graduate training outside the country. This could include&#13;
language training, as appropriate.&#13;
26.         Administration of the Partnerships. The Director of the MU will have&#13;
primary responsibility for organizing the Partnership grant review and award processes&#13;
which will also be adjudicated by the Peer Review Panel. To respond effectively to the&#13;
research and educational needs of a growing Ecuadoran Agricultural Research&#13;
Community, the duties of the MU officers must be far-reaching and their decisions should&#13;
be viewed as being informed and just. They should include, but are not limited to:&#13;
*  helping to identify and interpret national priorities in agriculture established by&#13;
the MAG in terms appropriate to education/training topic areas in the&#13;
agricultural sciences;&#13;
*  working closely with Partnership grantees to establish excellent "sister"&#13;
institution partnerships in strong support for advanced degree education of&#13;
Ecuadoran students and in aiding to lay the groundwork for a recognized&#13;
degree-granting entity in agricultural sciences in Ecuador;&#13;
*  aiding universities, institutes and foundations receiving agricultural research&#13;
grant support in identifying and recruiting students qualified for advanced&#13;
training at the M.S. and Ph.D. levels in agricultural sciences;&#13;
*  working with universities in organizing an appropriate graduate fellowship&#13;
advisory committee comprised of both regular faculty and adjunct faculty&#13;
members;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
60&#13;
*  assisting advanced degree fellows, in consultation with the sponsoring&#13;
researcher(s) and the appropriate SATC unit in preparing the student for&#13;
graduate studies outside Ecuador. (The Educational Director should already&#13;
be in direct contact with appropriate "sister" universities and/or placement&#13;
services);&#13;
*  seeing to the personal needs graduate fellowship awardees while outside the&#13;
country; and&#13;
*  helping arrange for students to return to Ecuador to do thesis work on&#13;
appropriate topics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
61&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Priorities for Research&#13;
Memorandum No. 0156 SPIS/DPIPS&#13;
TO             Technical and Administrative Undersecretary&#13;
FROM           Director of Sector Planning, Investment and Budget&#13;
SUBJECT       Selection and Prioritization of Crops and Livestock&#13;
DATE           February 8, 1995&#13;
Since the matter is considered of great importance for proper management by the&#13;
agnculture sector authorities, it has been thought advisable to select and rank the crops and&#13;
livestock on which the State should focus its attention, in view of the limited resources available. I&#13;
am accordingly detailing in the following the background data, criteria and procedures used in&#13;
selecting and ranking the crops and livestock discussed and their identification.&#13;
L     Background Data and Justification&#13;
Agricultural policy management in the closing years of the twentieth century does&#13;
not have the same roots and purposes as in the early 1900s. The circumstances have changed&#13;
drastically, especially if the situation as it was then is compared with the 1950s and 1960s when&#13;
the so-called "Green revolution " was at its height. The flow of events has caused successive&#13;
governments to take steps aimed primarily at meeting domestic supply needs and including&#13;
adoption of measures designed to ensure responsible use and control of renewable natural&#13;
resources.&#13;
For a while, the public sectors concern did not go beyond obtaining higher&#13;
productivity and profitability, so that emphasis was placed on the research and extension services&#13;
as a means for harnessing the potentials offered by technological development. However, this&#13;
policy proved inadequate as the years passed. The social changes and pressures, the deterioration&#13;
of the environment as a result of overuse and poor management of natural and technological&#13;
resources, the variable behavior of the market in the vast field formed by a supply and demand&#13;
extending beyond the national borders and the demands for larger incomes expressed by the&#13;
various actors in the agriculture sector gave rise to a more complex and less linear approach to the&#13;
problems noted.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
62&#13;
Accordingly, generation and transfer of technology and the establishment of a&#13;
price policy with a view to increasing productivity and improving profitability are no longer the&#13;
only goals, but steps are envisaged for upgrading product quality, ensuring appropriate use of&#13;
agricultural chemnicals and biological agents to reduce toxicity and pollution levels in persons and&#13;
the environment, locating and delirmiting crops in light of their agroecological and commercial&#13;
possibilities, conserving natural resources by means of appropriate use and providing the&#13;
infrastructure and services necessary for the production, conservation and transportation of&#13;
agrolivestock and forestry products.&#13;
In this context, the strategies to be employed and the application of new know&#13;
how, such as the organization and training of groups for self-nanagement purposes, design,&#13;
dissemination and implementation of agrosylvopastoral systems and their derivatives, and the&#13;
application of biotechnology, are also irnportant.&#13;
In light of the foregoing, it will be readily apparent that the conceptual framework,&#13;
for development purposes, of the agriculture sector has changed. Today production and&#13;
productivity are not the only concems, but consideration is also given to return and sustainable&#13;
managernent of the resources used in the production process, especially those connected with&#13;
preservation of the environment.&#13;
However, the promotion and implementation of all these activities are subject to&#13;
the funds available, which is why all the needs cannot be met simultaneously in a given time&#13;
period. Selection and prioritization are therefore called for, so that the results obtained will be real&#13;
and highly beneficial, both from the economic standpoint and in the social and ecological spheres.&#13;
IL    Criteria and Procedures for Selection and Prioritization&#13;
In accordance with the above, the Directorate of Planning formulated seven&#13;
criteria that facilitated the selection and ranking of the crops and livestock on which the&#13;
agricultural public sector will have to concentrate in the short and medium term. These criteria are&#13;
the following:&#13;
Area cultivated or total number of animals per species.&#13;
Potential percentage increase in productivity.&#13;
-     Number of technologies available per crop or species of animal.&#13;
-     lInportance of the product in the family shopping basket.&#13;
-     Possibilities of exporting the product.&#13;
-     The products commercial perfonnance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
63&#13;
The weighting factors are described in Attachment 1 and the information required&#13;
for the ratings is extracted from documents produced by the Directorates of Policy Analysis,&#13;
Agricultural Infonnation and Renewable Natural Resources; and of Research, Technology&#13;
Transfer and Extension.&#13;
In addition, the National Agricultural Research Institute (anstituto Naciona de&#13;
Investigaciones Agropecuarias - ILMP) has also produced for its own account a selection and&#13;
prioritization of crops and livestock, based on the following criteria assigned appropriate&#13;
weightings:&#13;
-     Effective demand for technology on the farmers' part.&#13;
-     Need for research.&#13;
-     Social importance of the item in terms of food supply.&#13;
-     Availability of technology for transfer.&#13;
-     Commercial potential.&#13;
As is apparent, three of these five criteria coincide with those applied by the&#13;
Ministry of Agriculture and Stockraising (MAG).&#13;
Finally, the Directorate of Research, Technology Transfer and Extension has&#13;
drawn up its own list using criteria similar to those detailed above.&#13;
At a meeting organized by the Directorate of Planning to agree on priorities as&#13;
regards crops and livestock, a committee was appointed to harnonize the various criteria used by&#13;
the agencies referred to aad to draw up a definitive and official list for the Ministry of Agriculture&#13;
and Stockraising. The committee was made up of representatives of the Directorates of Planning,&#13;
Agricultural Information and Renewable Natural Resources, and of Research, Technology&#13;
Transfer and Extension.&#13;
The procedure foliowed by the committee in establishing the priorities was to&#13;
compare the three lists available and to rank the crops and livestock in accordance with those&#13;
placing highest in the three lists, while those shown as least priority are those which only featured&#13;
in one of them, plus some others that the committee considered on account of certain factors&#13;
analyzed in the relevant session.&#13;
Attachment 2 sets out the comparative lists.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
64&#13;
Im    Priority Crops and Livestock&#13;
On the basis of the criteria and procedures agreed upon and the exchange of views&#13;
among the committee members, three priority echelons were established, each of which consists of&#13;
ten products:&#13;
Echelon 1 is mnade up of the following products, in the order shown: rice, coffee,&#13;
potatoes, cocoa, flint maize, soft maize, bovine cattle, bananas and plantains, soybeans and kidney&#13;
beans.&#13;
Echelon 2 is made up of: cassava, wheat, broad beans, peas, barley, cotton,&#13;
regular tomatoes, tree tomatoes, quinoa and swine.&#13;
Echelon 3 comprises: oil palm, sugarcane, naranjilla, apples, guineapigs, mangoes,&#13;
babaco, peaches and lemons.&#13;
Attachment 3 summarizes the factors that determined the selection and&#13;
prioritization of the crops and livestock listed.&#13;
It should be noted that the above list is not exclusive, exhaustive or final, since&#13;
future circumstances may change the order of priorities, or cause some products to be dropped&#13;
and others to be added.&#13;
(sgd.) Arturo Chavez C.&#13;
Attachmnents: as stated&#13;
cc:   Ing. Jaime Durango&#13;
Directors of Agricultural Informnation, Renewable Natural Resources, Research,&#13;
Technology Transfer and Extension&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
65&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Attachment 1&#13;
Valuation Criteria for Assigning Priority to Crops and Livestock&#13;
ITEM                 REFERENCE UNIT   VALUATION&#13;
1. Area cultivated                Ha                    1 point per 20,000 ha&#13;
2. Percentage potential increase in    %                1 point for each 10% increase&#13;
productivity&#13;
3. Importance in family shopping  Very important        10 points&#13;
basket                            Important             5 points&#13;
Of minor importance   2 points&#13;
4. Technologies available         No. of technologies    0.5 point for each technology&#13;
5. Possibility of industrial processing  Excellent      10 points&#13;
Very good            8 points&#13;
Good                 5 points&#13;
Regular              3 points&#13;
Slight               1 point&#13;
6. Possibility of exports&#13;
Excellent            10 points&#13;
Very good            8 points&#13;
Good                 5 points&#13;
Regular              3 points&#13;
Slight               1 point&#13;
7. Commercial performance26&#13;
Excellent            10 points&#13;
Very good            8 points&#13;
Good                 5 points&#13;
Regular              3 points&#13;
Poor                 1 point&#13;
26 The commercial performance weightings were based on the percentage increase in prices between 1980 and 1993.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
66&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Attachment 2&#13;
Prioritization of Crops and Livestock&#13;
PRIORITY        INIAP      DITTE            MAG DIR. OF             MAG&#13;
PLANNING    COMM[TTEE&#13;
1ST          Rice         Rice              Bovine cattle    Rice&#13;
ECHELON   Cocoa            Flint corn       Oilpalm          Coffee&#13;
Coffee       Coffee            Flint maize      Potatoes&#13;
Potatoes     Cocoa             Coffee           Cocoa&#13;
Flint maize    Potatoes        Potatoes         Flint maize&#13;
Plantains     Soft maize       Rice             Soft maize&#13;
Bananas      Cassava           Cocoa            Beef &amp; dairy cattle&#13;
Soft maize    Plantains        Wheat            Bananas &amp; plantains&#13;
Beef cattle    Beef cattle     Soft maize       Soybeans&#13;
Dairy cattle   Dairy cattle    Broad beans      Kidney beans&#13;
2ND          Kidney beans  Cotton           Soybeans         Cassava&#13;
ECHELON   Soybeans         Regular          Bananas          Wheat&#13;
Quinoa       tomatoes          Kidney beans     Broad beans&#13;
Cassava      Wheat             Cassava          Peas&#13;
Broad beans  Barley            Peas             Barley&#13;
Naranjilla    Tree tomatoes    Cotton           Cotton&#13;
Tree         Melons            Barley           Regular tomatoes&#13;
tomatoes     Mangoes           Peanuts          Tree tomatoes&#13;
Peas         Quinoa            Regular          Quinoa&#13;
Apples       Kidney beans      tomatoes         Swine&#13;
Barley       Peas              Plantains&#13;
3RD                                                          Oilpalm&#13;
ECHELON                                                      Sugarcane&#13;
Naranjilla&#13;
Apples&#13;
Guineapigs&#13;
Mangoes&#13;
Peanuts&#13;
Babaco&#13;
Peaches&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
67&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Attachment 3&#13;
Reasons for the Selection and Prioritization of Crops and Livestock&#13;
First Echelon of Priority&#13;
1TEM                                    REASONS&#13;
RICE                  Crop of primary importance for the family shopping baske, with export possibilities but requiring&#13;
technological improvements to increase productivity and reduce costs.&#13;
COFFEE                Export crop, with low unit yields, poor bean quality and oversupply. Rerewal and rehabilitation of&#13;
plantations are warranted m the best areas for the crop, while diversification is called for where it is&#13;
marinal, and also improvemet m the processing of the beans and developmeat of upland coffee.&#13;
COCOA                 Export crop, with good commercial performance, which requires renewal and rehabiiato of the&#13;
plantations and upgrading of bean quality.&#13;
FLINT MAIZE           Basic crop for livestock feed, the main indirect input for obtaining pouty and pig meat, with&#13;
productivity indexes that are still low and good industrial possibilities.&#13;
POTATOES              A widely grown product characterized by oversupply and a family shopping basket staple, with&#13;
productivity indexes that are still low and very susceptible to attack by numerous pests and disases.&#13;
The present type and level of pesticide application are causing toxicity and pollution problems in&#13;
persons and soils, a siuation that requires immediate attention.&#13;
SOFT MAIZE            A crop cultivated in large areas of the upland regions, with low productivity and some industrial&#13;
opporunities. It is an important food staple in the uplands.&#13;
BANANAS AND           Crops that are both exported and consumed domestically in large quantities, susceptible to attack by&#13;
PLANTAINS             senous pests and diseases and which need better management in order to obtain higher pnces in the&#13;
intenmational markets.&#13;
BOVINE CATTLE         Veiy important in tenns of the family shopping basket, as the main source of meat and milk, with&#13;
low yields, good industial and export possibilities and excellent commnercial performance.&#13;
SOYBEANS              Crop of primary importance (as oil) in the family basket, low productivity indexes, good industrial&#13;
and domestic market possibilities and good conmercial performance.&#13;
KIDNEY BEANS          Widely grown crop, a family basket staple, with low productivity indexes and good export&#13;
possibilities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
68&#13;
Second Echelon of Pnority&#13;
ITEM                                    REASONS&#13;
CASSAVA               A very important food staple in the coastal and eastern regions, with excellent industrial possibilities&#13;
and good export prospects.&#13;
WHEAT                 A very important food staple, mostly imported, and requiring better technological experbise to&#13;
improve its productivity and return.&#13;
BROAD BEANS           Legumes, of good nutritional content, an important foodstuff especially for rural dwellers, with&#13;
excellet possibilities for increasing their productivity and return and very good conmnercial&#13;
performance.&#13;
PEAS                  Legumes, very important in the family shopping basket, with excellent potential for increasing their&#13;
productivity and very good commercial performance.&#13;
BARLEY                An important food staple for the rual upland population, with considerable possibilities for&#13;
industrial processing and export as a processed product (beer) and good commercial perfonnance.&#13;
COTTON                A basic input for the country's textile ixustry, very susceptible to pests, good commercial&#13;
performance.&#13;
REGULAR               An important product in the family shopping basket, with well developed industial processing; their&#13;
TOMATOES              cultivation suffers from excessive pesticide use and urgent adjustments are needed to preserve the&#13;
populations health.&#13;
TREE TOMATOES         A fnait with excellent vitamin content and medicinal properties; very good export possibilities but&#13;
presently involving serious health problems. Excellent commercial performance.&#13;
QUINOA                Product with h_i protei content and good prospects for domestic and nternatio  consum_ption,&#13;
and also for idusti processing.&#13;
SWINE                 Animals which convert agricultural surpluses into meat and serve as a good income source for&#13;
low-income farmers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
69&#13;
Third Echelon of Priority&#13;
1TEM                                    REASONS&#13;
OILPALM               An industrial crop, of prinary importance for the family basket (oil) and with good export&#13;
possibilities. The producers are well organized and marketing is running smooily, so this crop&#13;
should require little public attention.&#13;
SUGARCANE             The private sector being well organized and efficient, than occasional political support is needed&#13;
from the public sector.&#13;
NARANJILLA            A fnut that is very important for the economy of the regions, the naranjilla needs research and&#13;
etension to combat pests and diseases.&#13;
APPLES                A frnit crop whose quality can be upgraded, leading to fewer imports.&#13;
GUINEAPIGS            Small domestic animals widely raised by the low-income rural population in the upland regions, of&#13;
great nutritional value and offering considerable commercial prospects.&#13;
MANGOES               A tropical fruit with good export possibilities.&#13;
PEANUTS               An oil seed with good commercial performance and highly esteened by the imabitants of the coastal&#13;
regions.&#13;
BABACO                A subtropical fruit with good export potential.&#13;
PEACHES               Quality improvement could have the effect of reducing imports of this fruit and appreciably&#13;
increasing the returns obtainable from it in certain upland provinces.&#13;
LEMONS                This crops susceptibility to pests and diseases warrants continued assistance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
70&#13;
ANNEX 7&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Project Supervision&#13;
Key Performance Indicators for Project Monitoring&#13;
Table la:          Indicators for the Competitive Research Grants sub-component showing&#13;
linkages to strategy objectives, targets, the method of collection and how often it&#13;
will be collected&#13;
Projed         Strategy           Process Indicators         Tgt       Method   How Oftle&#13;
Components   Objectives&#13;
Competitive    lmaa               Nos. of promotions         8         Progres   Every 6&#13;
research       Competition        No. of workshops                     Report    nths&#13;
grant                             Tot nos applicants         40                   Biannual&#13;
Total no. approved        25&#13;
No. grant applicatzons by           Progrea    Biaimul&#13;
INLAP                     10        Report&#13;
Universities              20&#13;
Joint projeds             6&#13;
Private sector (greniios)  4&#13;
linked to priorities  No. of projects financed&#13;
by:&#13;
subject&#13;
(see Table 2)&#13;
Private and public   Nos. of grants awarded to:        Site       Biannual&#13;
Inteation          univermities              12        visis&#13;
INLAP                     7         Progrss&#13;
joint projects            4         Report&#13;
private sector            2&#13;
Amount of resources (%/*)           Progres    Bianul&#13;
captured from:                      Report&#13;
univerities               24&#13;
INIAP                     14&#13;
private sector            12&#13;
GOE                      50&#13;
Client oriented    Nos. of projects involving          Progress   Biannual&#13;
fanmer participation      10        Report&#13;
on farm research          10&#13;
nos. of project fnanced in&#13;
area of small fanner agric.   15&#13;
*        Not pre-specified&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
71&#13;
Table lb:          Indicators for Research and Education Exchange Partnerships sub-component&#13;
Project        Strtegy            Process Indicators        Tgt       Method   HOw ofen&#13;
Components   ObJectives                                                     _&#13;
Research and   Increased          Nos. promotions           2         Progre    every 6&#13;
education      Competition        Nos. workshops                      Report    muths&#13;
exchange&#13;
parterhlps                        Nos. MSc prog application   5       Prog       Twice&#13;
Nos. MSc prog approved    2         Repo"t&#13;
Nos. PhD application      10        Progres    Aml (for&#13;
Nos. PhD approved         4        Report    3 yr.)&#13;
Priority linked    MSc prop by discipline             Progre    Twice&#13;
genetics                  1        Report&#13;
inigation                 1&#13;
Nos. of PhDs                       Progres    Amnual (for&#13;
by discipline             TA4       Report    3 years)&#13;
Strengthen         Nos. local staff hired             Progres    Anuual&#13;
Intitutional       by discipline                      Report&#13;
Capacity           genetics                  12mm&#13;
irrigation                12mnm&#13;
Nos. support staff                  Progres    Amiusl&#13;
by discipline                      Report&#13;
genetics                 36nmm&#13;
irrigation               36mm&#13;
Nos. foreign  aff                  Prog       Twice (firt&#13;
by discipline                      Report    2 yn)&#13;
genetics                 2&#13;
irrigation               2&#13;
Strengthen        Not. Partnrship           2         Progres    Twce (first&#13;
Institutional                                         Rqet    2 yecs)&#13;
Capacity&#13;
Resouroes in (%/.)                 Progress   Annual&#13;
contributed by:                    Repot&#13;
national outrpat          85&#13;
inteational counterpart    15&#13;
Nos. graduate courses     2         Progres    Twice (first&#13;
established                         Report    2 yr.)&#13;
Nos. graduate degrees              Progres    Ams&#13;
awarded by***:                     Rewrt&#13;
intemnaional Institution  4&#13;
National Institution      30&#13;
PhD disciplines have not yet been selected.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
72&#13;
Table lc:           Indicators for Strenatbeninp INLAP sub-cor Donent&#13;
Project            Strategy            Process Indicators         Tgt    Method        How Often&#13;
Comnonenta         Objectives&#13;
Strengthening      Strengthen          Developnment Plan          1       Progress     I t year&#13;
INLAP              Intitutional                                           Report&#13;
a. Training for    Capacity            Nos. of MSc                6&#13;
sdvanced degrees                       Nos of PhDs                4       Progres&#13;
Nos. Short tenm course    5       Report        Annual&#13;
Nos. fellowships awarded    11&#13;
Priority Linked    Nos MSc by disciplines:&#13;
Cocoa                      I      Progres       Anmal&#13;
Agric Econ                 1      Report&#13;
Maize, Leg, Ent.           I&#13;
TOT, Prod systems          1&#13;
Barnan/Plantain/Ag         I&#13;
Agro forestayI&#13;
Nos. PhDs by discipline:&#13;
Rice                      I       Progress      Annual&#13;
Potato                    I       Report&#13;
Coffee/cocoa/ent           I&#13;
Coffee/coa/phyto          1&#13;
Nos. thesis completed in          Progress      Annual5&#13;
Ecuador                           Report&#13;
MSc                       2&#13;
PhD                       4&#13;
Nos. shot term by                 Progres       Anmul&#13;
discipline                        Report&#13;
Tech Prod Ban-Plntain      1&#13;
lnatitufional Developmnct    1&#13;
Rice&#13;
IPM                        I&#13;
Farm level irrigation      I&#13;
K Regin  and       inreae              Not. of MSc applications   24&#13;
local long term    Competition         Noc MSc approved           12&#13;
consultants&#13;
Noc of PhD applications    20     Progress      Once&#13;
Not of PhD approved       10      Report        Once&#13;
Priority linked    Nos MSc by discipline:             Progress     Once&#13;
Agroforestry               I      Report&#13;
Agric Econ/Planning       2&#13;
Water management          1&#13;
Aniral Production         1&#13;
Biotechnology             1&#13;
Legums &#13;
Nutrition and quality      I&#13;
Oil SeedsI&#13;
hIfonnation system         1&#13;
Biometrics&#13;
Pastures                  I&#13;
Not PhD by  eas.                  Progrea       Once&#13;
Banana/Plantain           I       Report&#13;
Aninma Production          I&#13;
Agroforestry              1&#13;
cocoa                      I&#13;
Agric Econ/Planning       I&#13;
1PM                       1&#13;
VirologyI&#13;
Potato                    1&#13;
Hard maize                I&#13;
Rice&#13;
Strengthen         Nos. of applications       15      Progress     Annual&#13;
c. Internadtonal    Institutional      Nots approved              5       Report&#13;
short term         Capacity            Nos. by discipline:&#13;
sentists                               Animal Production          I&#13;
Banana/Plantain           1&#13;
Research Admin            1&#13;
Natural resources          1&#13;
Production systems         1&#13;
* The numbers of thesis completed will only start from the second year for the MScs and from the third year for&#13;
the PhDs; after these years information will be collected on an annual basis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
73&#13;
Table 2:      Number of research proposals by commodity and&#13;
discipline expected to be approved in the first year.&#13;
DISCIPLINES&#13;
COMMODITY    IPM          Soil,    Nutrition   Biotech   Agro-  Total&#13;
Water,     and               forestry&#13;
Irrigation   quality&#13;
Meat                                  1                          1&#13;
Soft maize         1                                             1&#13;
Milk                                  1                  1       2&#13;
Potatoes           1            _               1                2&#13;
Rice               1        1                                    2&#13;
Cocoa              1              .                     1       2&#13;
Coffee             1        1                            1       3&#13;
Banana/Plantain    1        1 1                 1                3&#13;
HardMaize          2        1     _                              3&#13;
Fruit              1        1                   1   j            3&#13;
Pastures                    1                            2       3&#13;
Total   9        6          2        3         5      25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
74&#13;
ANNEX 8&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Project Supervision&#13;
Key Performance Indicators.for Project Impact Evaluation&#13;
Strategy Objectives    Impact Indicators         Method of data collection  Frequency of collection&#13;
Strengthen Institutional   Priority setting      Survey (INIAP)           At start&#13;
Capacity                mechanisms established                            Mid term&#13;
and functioning                                   End&#13;
Numbers of               Literature Review        Every 3 years&#13;
Technical/scientific&#13;
publications                _&#13;
Strengthen Participation   Ratio of public/private  Secondary Data        At start&#13;
of Private Sector       expenditure on research                           Mid term&#13;
End&#13;
Increase Competition    Active flow of research  From process indicators    Mid term&#13;
applications                                      End&#13;
Every 3 vears&#13;
Conduct Client Oriented   Resource allocation vis-a-  Case studies, participatory   At start&#13;
Research                vis established priorities    methods             Mid term&#13;
End&#13;
Research transferred to  Case studies, participatory   At start&#13;
farmers fields           methods                  Mid term&#13;
End&#13;
Rate of adoption by      Case studies, participatory   At start&#13;
farmers                  methods                  Mid term&#13;
I__ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _   _E nd&#13;
Improved Interaction    Mechanism established    Survey, case studies,    At start&#13;
for ongoing interaction  participatory methods    Mid term&#13;
End&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
75&#13;
ANNEX 9&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Audit Requirements&#13;
Draft Summary Terms of Reference&#13;
A. Project Expenditures&#13;
1.          Annually, MAG would hire an independent auditor satisfactory to the Bank&#13;
to undertake an audit of the Project Accounts, Statements of Expenditures, the Special&#13;
Account and Internal Control&#13;
2.          MAG-PIU would submit to the auditor the following information by&#13;
April 30, of each year starting in 1997.&#13;
(a)   consolidated project accounts for the previous year showing total project&#13;
costs by component and the source and application of funds along with&#13;
supporting documentation as required by the auditors;&#13;
(b)   a report on its internal control (both financial and physical) for the project;&#13;
(c)   a report on corrective actions taken in response to the opinions and&#13;
recommendations made by the auditor in the audit report from the previous&#13;
year;&#13;
(d)   Bank statements for the Special Account showing source and application&#13;
of funds; and&#13;
(e)   copies of Statements of Expenditures (SOEs) for the previous year and all&#13;
documentation supporting these SOEs.&#13;
3.          Project Accounts. The auditor will prepare audited financial statements of&#13;
total project costs which cover all investment costs of the project which would include&#13;
costs incurred by MAG and the Participating Entities. These statements would also show&#13;
source of funds. The auditor will audit to a level necessary to do the following:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
76&#13;
(a)   state an opinion as to whether the consolidated financial statements fairly&#13;
reflect the total financial expenditures of the project;&#13;
(b)   comment on the adequacy of the accounting system used for consolidating&#13;
project accounts; and&#13;
(c)   state that civil works and equipment financed by the project exists and were&#13;
used for project purposes.&#13;
4.          Statements of Expenditures. The auditor will audit all of the Statements&#13;
of Expenditure used through the year for withdrawals from the Special Account to ensure&#13;
that:&#13;
(a)   all expenditures were made by MAG on legitimate project components,&#13;
through approved and signed contracts or direct procurement; and&#13;
(b)   payments were actually made an canceled checks are available.&#13;
5.          Special Account. The auditor will audit the Bank accounts for the Special&#13;
Account to ensure that:&#13;
(a)   all funds withdrawn from the World Bank loan were dully deposited in the&#13;
Special Account;&#13;
(b)   all funds withdrawn from the Special Account have supporting SOEs; and&#13;
(c)   the Special Account Balance agrees with the reconciliation of the Special&#13;
Account shown on the World Bank loan statements.&#13;
6.          Internal Control. The auditor will review the system of internal control,&#13;
both financial and physical and review the following:&#13;
(a)   adequate internal controls are being employed on financial and physical&#13;
activities of the project; and&#13;
(b)   corrective measures have been taken by MAG in response to observations&#13;
made in previous years.&#13;
7.          General. The auditor should also report on compliance by MAG on its&#13;
obligations under the loan agreement relating to the total costs of the project and the&#13;
World Bank loan account.&#13;
8.          MAG should forward to the Bank the audit report(s) for the consolidated&#13;
project accounts, SOEs and the Special Account, for the previous fiscal year, no later than&#13;
six months after the end of that fiscal year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
77&#13;
9.           The auditor should also review the annual budget at MAG for project&#13;
activities vis-a-vis the actual funds available and the actual funds utilized.&#13;
10.         The auditor should report on the adequacy of the budget allocation vis-a-&#13;
vis project requirements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
{n~   ~f- -iS.         w ..''E'''E'='                           -        -       -,tst&#13;
I&gt; ~       I- &#13;
i~~~~I                        El1&#13;
0  i       C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
c       ...  .. ...  ...  ................&#13;
m   ~              -e&#13;
C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
9'"p"IlS uowum uamajdwj $O3O4J&#13;
IOJrOUa HJUY3S3M 2UIIrnfLIUIOV&#13;
xoavnos&#13;
01 XINNV&#13;
8L&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Ecuador - Agricultural Research Project&#13;
1996             1997              1998              1999             2000              2001&#13;
ID   Task Name                                       Duration Qtr 1|tr Qtr 10tr 4QtrlQtr2lQtr3Qtr 4Qtr Qtr2Qtr3tr4Qtr Qtr Qtr3[Qtr 4Qtr  tr 2Qtr3tr  tr  tr  tr&#13;
32               Year 3                                   44d&#13;
33           Undertake Training                         1304d .                                                            /&#13;
34       National Researchers - Contracted              1370d&#13;
36           Prepare TOR                                  22d&#13;
36           Select Consuttants                           44d&#13;
37           Implement Component                        1304d                                /          ,                                                     /&#13;
38       Interrantional Researchers - Contracted        1370d&#13;
39           Prepare TOR                                  22d&#13;
40           Select Consultants            .        .d&#13;
41           lmplementComponent                          1304d                             /             /    /                 /                                 /&#13;
42   Implementation Unit                                1457d&#13;
43       Project knplementation                         1392d&#13;
44           Prepare Annual Budget and Work Plan         849d&#13;
4S               Year I                                   22d&#13;
46                Year 2                                  22d&#13;
47               Year 3                                   22d&#13;
48               Year 4                                   22d&#13;
49               Year 5                                   22d&#13;
SO           Technical Assistance                       1392d&#13;
61               Developmert Plan for INWAP              306d&#13;
52                    Prepare TOR                         22d&#13;
U3                    Select Consubnts                    22d&#13;
Task                                  Summary                               Rolled Up Progress&#13;
Project. AgncultLurd Research Proect  Progress                             Rolled Up Task&#13;
Date: 2/29/96&#13;
Miestone                              Rolled Up Milestone 3&#13;
Page 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I                                      U~~~~~~~~~~~~~C &#13;
E.                                  C&#13;
I  ................................... .........  .. ................... ...... =.. ..................  ......  E=... .... ...................................................... ....................  3 =7  &#13;
a~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0 10] -ES           *C                  g          &#13;
0)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
l~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ _E                                                         -u Nw&#13;
l~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ........          .   .....  ..   .   . .....  &#13;
08&#13;
CDco~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~E&#13;
to~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~t&#13;
2.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
*0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
08&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Ecuador - Agricultural Research Project&#13;
1996              1997              1998              1999              2000              2001&#13;
ID   Task Name                                        Duration  tr 1 tr 2Otr 3Otr 4|Qtr 1 O0tr 2Qtr 3OQtr 4|Qtr 1 ptr 210tr 3|Qtr 4[Qtr 1 |Qtr 21Qtr 3 Qtr 4|Qtr 1 lQtr 2Qtr 3tr 4Qtr 1 tr  tr&#13;
76               Implement Component                     1 304d&#13;
77       Management Contract                             1218d&#13;
78           Prepare TOR                                   22d&#13;
79           Invite Proposals                              22d&#13;
s0           Select Consultants                            44d&#13;
S1           Implement Component                         1 130d            .y~~&gt;    ~7   /4/$ W t%                      &amp;t%Q')//ty/&#13;
Task                                   Summary                               Rolled Up Progress&#13;
Project: Agricultural Research Project &#13;
Date: 2/29/96                        Progress                               Rolled Up Task&#13;
Milestone                              Rolled Up Milestone  &gt;&#13;
Page 4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
82&#13;
ANNEX 11&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Project Supervision&#13;
Bank Staff Inputs for Project Supervision&#13;
Approximate                  Activity                Anticipated               Input in Staff&#13;
Date                                                Skills                 Field Time&#13;
Requirements                  (Weeks)&#13;
September 1996            Project Launch Workshop   Task Manager                          1&#13;
focusing on project concept  Research Funding&#13;
and implementation,       Specialist                            I&#13;
procurement and&#13;
disbursement procedures&#13;
(retro-active financing,&#13;
special account&#13;
arrangements). Review&#13;
workplan and budget for&#13;
1997&#13;
February 1997             Mission after effectiveness  Task Manager&#13;
to review staffing, training,  Financial Analyst                1&#13;
promotion programi&#13;
September 1997            Supervision Mission to    Task Manager                          2&#13;
review the results of first    Research Specialist              I&#13;
year subprojects, M&amp;E     M&amp;E Specialist                        1&#13;
systemn, and work plan for&#13;
1998&#13;
February 1998             Supervision Mission to    Task Manager                          2&#13;
review institutional issues,  Institutional Specialist&#13;
including Peer Review     Financial Analyst&#13;
Panel, flow of funds,&#13;
project and financial&#13;
reporting and OM.&#13;
September 1998            Supervision Mission to    Task Manager                          I&#13;
review all aspects of     Research Specialist                   1&#13;
project implementation&#13;
and the work plan for 1999&#13;
February 1999             Supervision Mission to    Task Manager                          3&#13;
start the mid-term review    Institutional Specialist           2&#13;
covering The Executive    Financial Analyst                     2&#13;
Council, the PIU and      Research Specialist                   2&#13;
Management of&#13;
Competitive Grants&#13;
including the response of&#13;
Universities and private&#13;
sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
83&#13;
ANNEX 12&#13;
ECUADOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH PROJECT&#13;
Documents on Project File&#13;
Preparation and Appraisal Documents&#13;
1.          The INLAP Component - Preparation Report - Barry Nestel.&#13;
2.          Programa de Investigaci6n de la Universidadesy del Sector Privado -&#13;
Fundaci6n IDEA.&#13;
3.          Componente Investigaci6n - Fundaci6n IDEA.&#13;
4.          Generaci6n de Tecnologia - INIAP - Fundaci6n IDEA.&#13;
5.          Cambio Institucional del INIAP - INIAP.&#13;
6.          Proyecto de Modernizaci6n de los Servicios Agropecuarios Documento&#13;
Principal - Fundaci6n IDEA.&#13;
7.          Componente de Evaluaci6n Economica del Proyecto - Fundaci6n IDEA.&#13;
8.          Environmental Appraisal - Fundacion IDEA.&#13;
9.          Componente de Economia - Fundacion IDEA.&#13;
10.         Competitive Research Grants Component - R. Uffen.&#13;
11.         Research Component Annex - M. Whitaker.&#13;
12.         Componente de Evaluaci6n Econ6mica del Proyecto - Fundaci6n IDEA&#13;
13.         Monitoring and Evaluation for the Ecuador Agricultural Research Project&#13;
Prepared by Fiona Samuels, ITAD Ltd.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
84&#13;
Other Documents&#13;
14.         Public and Private Sector Interactions in Agricultural Research in Less-&#13;
Developed Countries: the Case of Ecuador. Cesar Falconi ISNAR&#13;
15.         El Rol de la Agricultura en el Desarrollo Economico del Ecuador: Ed.&#13;
Morris D. Whitaker.&#13;
16.         Politicas y Estrategias del Instituto Nacional A ut6nomo de&#13;
Investigaciones Agropecuarias - IMAP 1993.&#13;
17.         Una Metodologia para la Determinaci6n de Prioridades de Investigaci6n&#13;
Agropecuaria por Rubros y Areas de Trabajo (El Caso Ecuatoriano) Patricio Espinosa,&#13;
George Norton and H. Douglas Gross.&#13;
18.         Determinaci6n de Prioridades de Investigaci6n Agropecuaria en Ecuador.&#13;
Julio Palomino C. and George W. Norton.&#13;
19.         La Calidad de la Investigaci6n en el INIAP Informe de Consultoria&#13;
Presentado a la Agencia Alemana GTZ. Francisco Muinoz.&#13;
20.         Resumen del Proceso de Modernizaci6n del INIAP - 1993.&#13;
21.         Grant Proposal Guide (NSF 94-2) National Science Foundation.&#13;
January 1994.&#13;
22.         Application Kit. United States Development of Agriculture (USDA)&#13;
September 1992.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
81                      ao^                      79^   ,                    78                       77~                       76&#13;
Son tlor.r,o Q\&#13;
ESMERALDAS -                      ,    )                                        C      LOM           A&#13;
t           a    -- &lt;                   q  1'! .      '&gt;                           ~~~~~~~~~C  O  L O  M  B I A&#13;
P,\  C C     - I                         ESMERALDAS   -ARCH&#13;
. ) (  I  dX  N   . r p Rblo Z6rak  &gt;-  ^&lt;A -  z, j~TASIJP l*.-BABI_/' Aon   ._ ,  r&#13;
~.R8~oT6.oI.                             ISd.RI., C.4 ,&#13;
NGO             A        oo TAk     o ~n~&#13;
I,'-..                                                              .---.CAA LI_&#13;
|  /p  .e  I...... ,'l\ rnrnTAIJIA              I          .         .............. 2   r oF d,ondo                ' 5&#13;
Bohlo d. Co.,q.,                                                               1                //*o&#13;
Mon;ll&lt;t    G A RIIA  ; t  F  r     {;NAPO-PAYAMINOC&#13;
PRORT,oJOg  J           ~     ~      SCFJE ICm    /UA BT -                             -._  -       ..&#13;
KTOVIE~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
'~' fV  (iE  F  /,NUACO                            OXo-T4         ,                                                  Y&#13;
PO.K&#13;
=                b~~~~~ABAf1Sef     ) s  &#13;
EL ROSARIO                                                PA&#13;
s~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~S no     CUI            ....................    MACAS&#13;
',0P  j            N,BOI. l                                   C .  \  . ,  -  '&#13;
' (t   , '.-+,Gyi S-    )  r               j                   _                     I~~~~~~~~~~~ i &#13;
P-q.                                                                           ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~76&#13;
TTEN&#13;
- 3        ( 1/ 1 1 ;. I        I       Tg         s ;_ 1 l j; U_2   ?  q U I plozq     /    /                                       ECUADOR&#13;
'l' V ''/ ''    MACHA8;.f) %  -J fJ         ,2         /                                    AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH&#13;
(oI       o       78'                      77'                   PROJECT&#13;
A    EXPERIMENTAL STATIONS (INIAP)&#13;
X.GALAPAGOS ISLANDS&#13;
,ZAMO                        ARCHIPIELAGO DE COLON|                    EXPERIMENTAL FARMS (INIAPF&#13;
CHiNtCHTh                                                    - O---- - PAVED ROADS&#13;
-Clfl.   r_,    J  '/55crOTHER ALL WEATHER ROADS&#13;
*                                                                                        -c  t so--- iA)MORAO // eslA C--rsoxrss | RAILROADS&#13;
/                                                                         4   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~AIRPORTS&#13;
)   I t l I A  ;    )             1 .\, ' I I S    ';   ; I i      o 0-        +      POR.TS&#13;
P E R U                                                                    ISLA SAN SAiVAPDO                              RIVERS&#13;
PROVINCE BOUNDARIES&#13;
.SMA SANTA CRUZ                    INTERNATIONAL BOUNDARIES&#13;
0    25   50   75   GG5FER INA5&#13;
IS~A SAN&#13;
KILOMETERS                                               ISIA                         CR SSTO,A L&#13;
5                      5                                               ISABELA&#13;
., ,, / ,,, ,,,o,r ,,A  ......U1   'R. SAS4 0"            .......'.1 n.',L    Al_&#13;
.  *..  .... ....  ..15&#13;
_I _X -                                                        I _&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IMAGING&#13;
Report No:      14702- EC&#13;
Type: SAP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="696530">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/05/696530/ecuador-agricultural-research-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/05/696530/ecuador-agricultural-research-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1996/05/696530/ecuador-agricultural-research-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/05/03/000009265_3961029223827/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/05/03/000009265_3961029223827/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>4075</loan_no>
        <docdt>1996-05-03T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2001-04-17T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Ecuador - Agricultural Research Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The principal objective of this
            Agricultural Research Project for Ecuador is to strengthen
            the national capacity to conduct agricultural research, with
            the aim of increasing agricultural productivity and output
            while preserving or enhancing the natural resource base, by:
            (i) introducing a competitive research grant program; (ii)
            developing research and education exchange partnerships with
            international science institutions; and (iii) strengthening
            the national agricultural research institute, INIAP. The
            project components include: (i) competitive grants which
            include research grants, research and educational exchange
            partnerships with international institutions; (ii)
            strengthening INIAP; and (iii) project implementation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Ecuador - Agricultural Research Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Ecuador - Agricultural Research Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1996/05/696530/ecuador-agricultural-research-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>EC-Agricultural Research Project -- P007131</projn>
        <docty>Staff Appraisal Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems,Agricultural Research,Science Education,Scientific Research &amp; Science Parks,ICT Policy and Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <count>Ecuador</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3961029223827</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Tertiary education,Other social services,Agricultural extension and research,Central government administration</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1996</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural research; Educational
            exchanges; Nongovernmental organizations; Project
            implementation; Research grants; Research partnerships
            adaptive research,Agricultural
            Development,agricultural extension,agricultural
            growth,Agricultural Marketing,agricultural
            production,agricultural products,Agricultural
            Research,Agricultural
            Technology,Agriculture,agroforestry,Animal Health,animal
            production,biodiversity,cattle,cereals,CIAT,CIP,collaboration,commodities,Competitive
            Grants,Competitive Research,crops,deforestation,development
            projects,Development Research,diagnostic
            laboratories,diseases,economics,Environmental
            Impact,equipment,Exchange Rate,exchange
            rates,Extension,extension
            services,extensionists,Farmers,farming,farms,Financial
            support,food production,food security,food
            supplies,fruits,funding mechanisms,genetic
            resources,horticultural
            crops,IDB,IDRC,incomes,integration,International
            Agricultural Research,International Center for Tropical
            Agriculture,International Development Research
            Center,International Potato Center,interviews,investment in
            agricultural research,irrigation,ISNAR,laboratories,Land
            Reform,land
            resources,lands,legumes,libraries,Livestock,Livestock
            Development,Livestock Research,maize,management
            research,NARS,Natural resource management,Natural
            Resources,Natural Resources Management,new
            technologies,NGOs,nutrition,pastures,pest control,pest
            management,pesticides,pests,Potato,potatoes,Poverty
            Alleviation,priority setting,private sector,private sector
            agricultural research,programs,Public research
            expenditures,public services,quarantine,research
            capacity,research equipment,research funding,Research
            Grants,research institutes,research institutions,research
            needs,research organizations,Research Priorities,research
            programs,research projects,research
            stations,researchers,rice,roots,Rural Development,Rural
            Poverty,scenario,sciences,scientists,soil
            erosion,soybeans,strategic research,sustainable
            research,swine,Technical Assistance,technicians,Technology
            Transfer,Tropical
            Agriculture,tubers,Universities,USAID,validity,Water Resources,wheat
        </keywd>
        <owner>Agriculture &amp; Rural Dev (LCSAR)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF023029-PHRD-AGRICULTURAL SERVICES</trustfund>
        <repnb>14702</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Integrated Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pesticides</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Downsizing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right-sizing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rightsizing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Size and Structure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Knowledge &amp; Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Scholarships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Downsizing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Ecuador</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>