<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. 15267-EGT&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
ARAB REPUBLIC OF EGYPT&#13;
SECOND SOCIAL FUND PROJECT&#13;
April 25, 1996&#13;
Human Resources Division&#13;
Middle East Department&#13;
Middle East and North Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY&#13;
(as of April 1996)&#13;
Currency Unit  =  Egyptian Pound (LE)&#13;
US$ I  =  LE3.4&#13;
LE I  =  US$0.29&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
July I - June 30&#13;
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES&#13;
Metric System&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
ADB           African Development Bank&#13;
BOD           Board of Directors of the Social Fund&#13;
CAPMAS        Central Agency for Public Mobilization and Statistics&#13;
CDP           Community Development Program of the Social Fund&#13;
EC            Executive Committee of the Board of Directors of the Social&#13;
Fund&#13;
EDP           Enterprise Development Program of the Social Fund&#13;
ERR           Economic Rate of Return&#13;
ERSAP         Economic Reform and Structural Adjustment Program&#13;
GDP           Gross Domestic Product&#13;
GOE           Government of Egypt&#13;
HRDP          Human Resources Development Program of the Social&#13;
Fund&#13;
ICB           International Competitive Bidding&#13;
IDP           Institutional Development Program of the Social Fund&#13;
IDA           International Development Association&#13;
IMF           International Monetary Fund&#13;
LMP           Labor Mobility Program&#13;
NCB           National Competitive Bidding&#13;
NGO           Non-Governmental Organization&#13;
O&amp;M           Operations and Maintenance&#13;
PPP           Purchasing Power Parity&#13;
PVO           Private Voluntary Organization&#13;
PWP           Public Works Program of the Social Fund&#13;
SA            Sponsoring Agencies&#13;
SLWP          Small Scale Labor Intensive Works Program&#13;
SFD           Social Fund for Development&#13;
SFDC          Small Business Finance and Development Corporation&#13;
SOE           Statement of Expenses&#13;
UNDP          United Nations Development Program&#13;
WTO           World Trade Organization&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Credit and Project Summary                                                                                                                     Page&#13;
1. BACKGROUND  AND  ASSESSMENT OF THE  FIRST  PHASE .....................................................................1I&#13;
A. INTRODUCTION AND BACKGROUND .................................................................I&#13;
B. SOCIAL FUND: EVALUATION  1993-95 AND PROPOSALS FOR FUTURE SUSTAINABILITY ............................................I&#13;
C. SPECIAL FEATURES OF THE  SOCIAL FUND .................................................................4&#13;
D. RATIONALE FOR IDA  INVOLVEMENT .................................................................4&#13;
2. THE PROPOSED PROJECT .....................................................................S5&#13;
A. PROJECT OBJECTIVES .................................................................5&#13;
B. PROJECT DESCRIPTION .................................................................5&#13;
C. COST AND FINANCING .................................................................6&#13;
D. IMPLEMENTATION ARRANGEMENTS .................................................................7&#13;
Operating Procedures of SFD ....................7,.........,,.......7&#13;
Project Monitoring ........................................................................................................,,....8&#13;
Planned Reviews....................9&#13;
SupervisionPlalan..................................,.,.,.,.,.......,,,,,,,,,,,,,,........,,,,,,,,,,,.,,Plan,.,.,.......,,.,,,.......,.,,.,......,,9,,.,...&#13;
E. SUSTAINABILITY .9&#13;
F. PROCUREMENT.10&#13;
G. DISBURSEMENT.I1&#13;
H. ACCOUNTS AND AUDITS .12&#13;
3. THE PROJECT EXECUTION AGENCY .12&#13;
4. SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC ASSESSMENT .13&#13;
A. BENEFITS AND ECONOMIC ANALYSIS .                                                                                                                13&#13;
B. RISKS.1. 4&#13;
C. ENVIRONMENTAL ASPECTS AND PARTICIPATIONR..                                                                                                       14&#13;
5. AGREEMENTS AND RECOMMENDATION .14&#13;
This staff appraisal report and the accompanying memorandum were prepared based on the findings of an appraisal mission&#13;
during December 6 to 21, 1995. Mission members included: Mr. Qaiser Khan (MN2HR, Task Manager and Mission Leader),&#13;
Ms. Judith Brandsma (PSD, Small and Microenterprise Specialist), Ms. Randa El-Rashidi (MN2HR, Human Resources&#13;
Specialist), Mr. Takatoshi Kamezawa (MN2HR, Education Specialist) and Mr. Mario Zelaya (MN21E, Environmental Engineer).&#13;
The mission was joined in Egypt by a parallel European Union mission. The report was produced by Ms. Mira Hong. The&#13;
managing Division Chief is Mr. Jacques Baudouy and the managing Department Director is Mr. Inder Sud.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLES&#13;
TABLE 1.1: COST OF JOB CREATION FOR DIFFERENT SOCIAL FUNDS IN US$/JOB .........................................................2&#13;
TABLE 2.1: PROJECT COSTS SUMMARY IN US$ MILLION ..............................................................6&#13;
TABLE 2.2: FINANCING PLAN BY DISBURSEMENT CATEGORY IN US$ MILLION ............................................................7&#13;
TABLE 2.3: MONITORING INDICATORS FOR PHASE II ..............................................................8&#13;
TABLE 2.4: SUMMARY OF PROPOSED PROCUREMENT ARRANGEMENTS IN US$ MILLION ........................................... 10&#13;
TABLE 2.5: ESTIMATED DISBURSEMENT SCHEDULE (IDA CREDIT) .............................................................  11&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
ANNEx 1:  PUBLIC WORKS PROGRAM&#13;
ANNEx 2:  COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM&#13;
ANNEx 3:  ENTERPRISE DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM&#13;
ANNEx 4:  HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM&#13;
ANNEX 5:  SFD ACHIEVEMENTS TO DATE AND ECONOMIC ANALYSIS FOR PHASE 11&#13;
ANNEx 6:  PROJECT MANAGEMENT AND CRITERIA FOR SUB-PROJECTS&#13;
ANNEx 7:  MONITORING DURING PHASE 11&#13;
ANNEx 8:  PARTICIPATION AND TARGETING&#13;
ANNEx 9:  DETAILED PROJECT COST TABLES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EGYPT&#13;
SECOND SOCIAL FUND PROJECT&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
Credit and Project Summary&#13;
Borrower:                     Arab Republic of Egypt&#13;
Implementing Agency:         Social Fund for Development&#13;
Poverty Category:             Program of Targeted Interventions&#13;
Credit Amount:                SDR 82.3 million (US$120.0 million equivalent)&#13;
Terms:                        Standard IDA terms with 35 year maturity&#13;
Commitment Fee:               0.50% on undisbursed loan balances, beginning 60 days after signing,&#13;
less any waiver&#13;
Project Objectives and        The objective of the project is to help: (a) create jobs through support&#13;
Description:                  of small enterprises and labor-intensive works; and (b) support&#13;
community infrastructure and services in partnership with NGOs and&#13;
local groups. This will be achieved through building on the strengths&#13;
of the 1993-96 phase of the SFD by supporting various programs&#13;
during 1997-2000, including labor-intensive works; community&#13;
development projects; small and micro-enterprise development; and&#13;
support to workers made redundant by public sector reform or&#13;
increased competition due to trade liberalization.&#13;
Financing Plan:                                       US$ million&#13;
IDA                                 120                 15%&#13;
European Union                      200                 26%&#13;
Arab Funds                          170                 22%&#13;
UNDP/ADB                             14                  2%&#13;
Bilateral Donors                     97                 13%&#13;
Government and&#13;
Beneficiaries                       174                 22%&#13;
TOTAL                               775                100%&#13;
Economic Rate of Return:      It is difficult to estimate an ERR given the difficulty of quantifying&#13;
benefits of upgrading public health, environment, literacy and other&#13;
services. Based on a sample of projects financed during 1993-96 under&#13;
the first project, the ERR for the project activities for which benefits&#13;
are quantifiable, accounting for some 75 percent of project cost, is&#13;
estimated to be 21 percent (see Annex 5 for details). These estimates&#13;
should be treated with caution given the subjective nature of many&#13;
assumptions.&#13;
Map:                          IBRD 27482&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Arab Republic of Egypt&#13;
Second Social Fund Project&#13;
Staff Appraisal Report&#13;
1. BACKGROUND AND ASSESSMENT OF THE FIRST PHASE&#13;
A. INTRODUCTION AND BACKGROUND&#13;
1.1    In response to a difficult economic situation caused by falling oil prices and the Gulf War, Egypt embarked&#13;
on a broad economic adjustment program with support from the World Bank and the IMF. The main stabilization&#13;
goals have been met and provide a basis for sustainable economic growth. The principal problems which still&#13;
persist are high levels of poverty and unemployment. Between 20-30 percent of Egyptians are estimated to live in&#13;
poverty, and a recent survey found the unemployment rate, when adjusted for underemployment, to be close to 21&#13;
percent. Eighty-five percent of the unemployed are between 19 and 29 years of age, and most are recent graduates.&#13;
1.2    The high level of poverty is not just a social and equity issue: those factors which cause widespread&#13;
poverty also contribute substantially to the lack of broad-based growth.  Egypt has the potential to develop a&#13;
dynamic and forward-looking small enterprise sector which could lead to both broad-based employment generation&#13;
and poverty reduction. Egypt also has age-old social structures and community groups which are close to the&#13;
people (particularly the poor) and can play a strong role in the country's economic development. Broad based&#13;
economic growth that harnesses the energies of Egypt's small entrepreneurs and community organizations can also&#13;
help reduce the attraction of extremist political movements, thus contributing to political and social stability.&#13;
B. SOCIAL FUND: EVALUATION 1993-95 AND PROPOSALS FOR FUTURE StISTAINABILITY&#13;
1.3    Social Fund for Development (SFD): The SFD was set up in 1991 at the height of the Gulf crisis. Its&#13;
activities between 1993-96 (referred to as Phase I while Phase 11 refers to 1997-2000) was supported by many&#13;
donors including IDA through Credit No. C2276-EGT approved by the Board on June 21, 1991. This credit is&#13;
expected to be fully disbursed by December 31, 1996. The SFD was conceived with three objectives: (a) to help&#13;
reduce poverty through supporting employment generation and community development efforts; (b) to help mitigate&#13;
the possible negative impact of the Economic Reform and Structural Adjustment Program (ERSAP); and (c) to&#13;
provide help to the Gulf returnees. These objectives were to be achieved through five programs: Public Works&#13;
Program (PWP) to support labor intensive construction projects; Community Development Program (CDP)&#13;
including support for microenterprise and community based social services; Enterprise Development Program&#13;
(EDP) to help new and on-going small enterprises; Labor Mobility Program (LMP) to help labor adjust to economic&#13;
reform; and Institutional Development Program (IDP) to support the SFD secretariat as well as poverty monitoring&#13;
through surveys and studies. A review of SFD performance by the Government (SFD-Mission Beyond 1996,&#13;
October 1994) concluded that the SFD has been very successful. A more recent evaluation was done by the World&#13;
Bank based on information collected using the following methods: (a) extensive in-depth field visits; (b) impact&#13;
survey in five govemorates; and (c) review of administrative data from the SFD and its partners. The World Bank&#13;
evaluation confirmed the previous positive assessment of 1994, though it found that some areas needed&#13;
improvement. The evaluation findings are summarized below.&#13;
1.4    The SFD met its first objective. It was able to create 50,000-70,000 jobs per year, i.e. almost 25 percent of&#13;
annual non-agriculture jobs created. The SFD did this without crowding out the private sector, primarily by&#13;
supporting small enterprises which previously had no access to banks. The second objective was to be met by&#13;
helping workers made redundant through public enterprise restructuring or privatization. This objective was only&#13;
partially met as the pace of privatization/restructuring was slower than expected. The SFD also partly met the third&#13;
objective by creating employment opportunities for Gulf returnees. The SFD met its employment creation objectives&#13;
with annual expenditures equivalent to only 0.2 percent of GDP, or about 6 percent of annual donor flows to Egypt.&#13;
This job-creation cost compares favorably with other countries, based on data from various units within the World&#13;
Bank (see Table 1.1). SFD's achievements are given in Annex 5, and an assessment of its various programs&#13;
follows.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 2                                                                 Egypt: Second Social Fund Project&#13;
Table 1.1: Cost of Job Creation for Different Social Funds in US$/Job&#13;
Egypt Honduras iNicaragua Madagascar Bolivia Senegal Ghana&#13;
Cost per Job at Market Exchange Rates    1,401  2,1201    2,5801    786   2.700   5,445  2,122&#13;
Cost per Job at PPP Exchange Rates  7,212     9,759    14,302     3,260   9,388  12,100  10,610&#13;
Source: Bank Staff Estimates&#13;
Box 1: How the SFD has an Inmpact on the Poor&#13;
The small dusty village in Fayoum lies close to the edge of the cultivated area, where green gives way to desert. At&#13;
the tail-end of a water distribution system running from a canal bringing Nile water, the village receives a lot of&#13;
contaminated water which has already passed through other places. SFD helped residents to build a waste water&#13;
treatment plant constructed with :local materials. Labor accounted; for over 50 percent of the cost. The villagers&#13;
contributed almost 25 percent in:cash. In the same village, the SFD helped develop a community center and runs a&#13;
women's adult literacy program.  The literacy program has been helping young girls who have dropped out of&#13;
school due to family financial pressures to learn reading, writing and arithmetic. In another part of Fayoum, a&#13;
young businessman with support from SFD has created ernployment opportunities for 10 women by setting up a&#13;
smaIll business to clean and repackage agriculture products. The businessman himself is not from the poorest group&#13;
of residents but his employees are.&#13;
1.5    Public Works Program (PWP): The objective of this program was to transfer income while developing&#13;
local infrastructure by creating employment through the use of labor intensive but efficient public works. The&#13;
program has met the objective of generating employment while constructing quality works in collaboration with&#13;
local Governments and communities. The principal problem encountered during Phase I has been operations and&#13;
maintenance (O&amp;M) of SFD financed infrastructure. Though local Governments have provided assurances of&#13;
supporting operations and maintenance and Governors have included this in budget requests, resources have not&#13;
been forthcoming due to fiscal constraints. The SFD is developing an approach to involve local communities in&#13;
operations and maintenance. The proposed approach calls for setting up users associations, which would collect&#13;
voluntary contributions in cash or kind from beneficiaries. To encourage these associations, the SFD would provide&#13;
matching funds for maintenance activities on a downward sliding scale. (Annex I, para.14 provides details).&#13;
Box 2: Restoring Pride in a Forgotten Community&#13;
Toad village lies close tolEgypt's great tourist attractions around Luxor, but a visit there reveals living conditions&#13;
hard to imagine outside the:worst refugee camp. A survey indicated that 73 percent of children under 12 in the&#13;
village suffer from: intestinal infections and diseases. lTe main causes for this were identified as a lack of sanitary&#13;
habits, poor sanitation andT waste disposal and an. excess: of flies surprising even in this poor corner of Egypt. The&#13;
local Community Development Association had very limited resources and appealed to the SFD for help. The&#13;
SFD's community. development program designed :a program including: health and environmental awareness&#13;
campaigns, spraying of flies, construction of septic pits, and establishment of a mechanism for solid waste collection&#13;
and disposal.  .The. village remains poor but conditions: have improved, and the villagers are proud of the&#13;
improvements they have brought about in their lives.&#13;
1.6    Community Development Program  (CDP): The objective of this program  was to help the poorest&#13;
communities, giving priority to their most vulnerable members. The range of activities supported by the CDP&#13;
includes: (a) social services such as literacy classes, health care, family planning, etc.; (b) micro-enterprises to&#13;
increase the income of the poorest households; and (c) community centers which provide a base for social services&#13;
and recreational activities. In the course of its operations, the CDP has adopted a very participatory approach and is&#13;
also supporting the development of NGOs. About 73 percent of direct beneficiaries were rural, and 66 percent were&#13;
female. Two issues persist and need to be addressed during Phase II (refers to SFD between 1997-2000). The first&#13;
issue is providing sufficient resources to support O&amp;M of SFD financed activities. This issue is being addressed by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Egypt: Second Social Fund Project                                                               Page 3&#13;
establishing users' groups, as in the case of PWP, for each of the financed activities. The second issue is the lack of&#13;
market orientation for the CDP microenterprise and training activities: the CDP has sometimes provided training for&#13;
skills which are saturated or have no market. This problem will be addressed by closely monitoring local market&#13;
conditions before approving support for enterprises (Annex 2, para.32).&#13;
1.7    Enterprise Development Program (EDP): The objective of the EDP is to help create employment through&#13;
support for new and existing small enterprises by providing a package of technical assistance, training and credit.&#13;
The difference between the CDP and the EDP lending activities is that the average CDP loan is US$500 and credit&#13;
is extended through NGOs, while the EDP's average loan is US$4,000 and credit is extended through banks. Bank&#13;
lending is complemented by technical assistance and is provided through NGOs. Banks take the full commercial&#13;
risk of their lending and hence have sole loan decision authority. The program has disbursed over LE 700 million to&#13;
intermediaries for on-lending and has spent substantial additional resources to develop and deliver technical&#13;
assistance packages. Over 60,000 sub-loans are outstanding, and 25 percent of the borrowers are female.&#13;
1.8    Given current interest rates to final borrowers, as well as the spreads that the banks can charge, the interest&#13;
rate on a loan to an existing small business is slightly above inflation (spread of 3 percent) while the interest rate on&#13;
a loan to a new business is slightly below inflation (spread of 4 percent). Interest rates to final borrowers are&#13;
reviewed on a yearly basis. Repayment rates appear good, although this conclusion is based on limited data as&#13;
many sub-loans are still in the grace period. The banks started their first repayments to the EDP last summer and&#13;
these funds will be re-lent. About 40 percent of loans were for start-up enterprises and thus, the EDP program&#13;
provided access to the banking system for borrowers who otherwise would not have received a loan. In total,&#13;
120,000 permanent jobs were created (measured as a job still in existence one year after its creation). Forty-three&#13;
percent of loans are for small industry, 21 percent for services, 23 percent for agriculture and animal production,&#13;
and 11 percent for trade. Unemployed graduates are a priority target group of the EDP.&#13;
Box 3: Harnessing Egypt's Talentfor Entrepreneurship&#13;
Galal (name changed) leaves the shop area and, despite the fact that he has lost a leg, goes rapidly up a set of steep&#13;
stairs to his workshop. His small business in the market area of Aswan is thriving: he employs ten people making&#13;
clothing. This would have seemed an impossible dream when he joined the handicapped training programn jointly&#13;
offered by the SFD and the Ministry of Social Affairs. He completed his training and qualified for a small loan&#13;
under the productive families sub-project supported by SFD's community development program. His business&#13;
continued to grow and he has expanded with a loan from a bank through SFD's enterprise development program.&#13;
SFD support has helped this determined individual, and through him helped also his ten employees.&#13;
1.9    The EDP was designed primarily as a "job-creation" mechanism to assist entrepreneurs and to disburse&#13;
loans quickly and efficiently without much regard for issues affecting sustainability of the SFD itself. It has&#13;
successfully helped thousand of borrowers while operating under a set of (often conflicting) donor demands and&#13;
constraints. The EDP in effect acts as a successful wholesale small business support and finance agency, delivering&#13;
loans to small businesses through banks and delivering business services through NGOs. During the assessment of&#13;
Phase I of the program, it was agreed that the issue of sustainability needs to be addressed in Phase 11. This would&#13;
require that: (a) SFD on-lending to banks carries an interest rate sufficient to maintain the value of SFD funds in real&#13;
terms; (b) the cost of the services provided by SFD staff is recovered in the long-term, directly or indirectly, from&#13;
the banks/beneficiaries; (c) the banks have a sufficient spread to cover their costs, including an allowance for&#13;
default; and (d) the EDP, while maintaining its social objectives, is managed as a self-standing commercial program.&#13;
A Task Force including SFD staff, banks and donor representatives has been established to identify means of&#13;
achieving these goals, and it has issued a preliminary report which has been made available to the World Bank and&#13;
other donors. Thefindings of the Task Force has been developed into a business plan which was discussed during&#13;
negotiations; its execution has been included as a covenant in the Credit and Project Agreement (para. 5.2).&#13;
1.10    Labor Mobility Program (LMP): The objectives of this program were to provide workers in restructured&#13;
or privatized public sector enterprises with financial assistance, training and placement services. The original&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 4                                                             Egypt: Second Social Fund Project&#13;
program was intended to help 50,000 workers at a cost of US$90 million. Since the Government's privatization&#13;
program moved considerably more slowly than was expected, the demand for LMP activities was limited and&#13;
donors agreed to reduce the program to US$40 million (with the funds being reallocated to other programs),&#13;
implicitly reducing the target to 20,000 workers. So far the program has assisted 3,000 workers in three enterprises&#13;
and is currently working on assisting an additional 10,000 workers in seven enterprises.&#13;
1.11   Institutional Development Program  (IDP):  The IDP's objectives included support for (a) SFD&#13;
management; and (b) poverty monitoring in collaboration with researchers and CAPMAS (Central Agency for&#13;
Public Mobilization and Statistics). The management of the SFD has been efficient (overhead costs are 6 percent of&#13;
disbursements). CAPMAS/SFD completed a survey (living standards measurement) in 1993 which provides data&#13;
for poverty analysis. The survey includes data to update price indices and the GDP deflator.&#13;
1.12    Gender Targeting: The SFD targets women as a special group for assistance: 25 percent of EDP loan&#13;
beneficiaries were women, which is higher than would be expected given Egypt's entrepreneurship patterns, and&#13;
compares favorably to other enterprise development activities which achieve a 10 percent target of support to&#13;
women. Over 60 percent of CDP beneficiaries were women, including a third of the micro-entrepreneurs.&#13;
C. SPECIAL FEATURES OF THE SOCIAL FUND&#13;
1.13    Managerial Autonomy: The SFD's managerial autonomy in terms of decision making, procurement and&#13;
disbursements is a major factor behind its success. The Board of Directors (BOD) and its Executive Committee&#13;
(EC) set policy and leave day to day management to the Managing Director.&#13;
1.14   Role of NGOs: NGOs play a prominent role in SFD programs, particularly in the areas of community&#13;
development (CDP) and enterprise development (EDP). Up to July 1995, NGOs managed LE 100 million out of LE&#13;
192 million approved for CDP sub-projects (52 percent), and LE 609 million out of LE 1,406 million approved for&#13;
EDP sub-projects (43 percent). Thus, the SFD has also been able to attain its objective of working in partnership&#13;
with NGOs. NGOs provide an essential link to communities and are able to articulate community concerns well.&#13;
Their role will become even more prominent in Phase II. Initially the SFD had to rely primarily on government&#13;
sponsored NGOs, but it has been able to broaden the range of NGOs it deals with and thus to broaden its appeal to&#13;
communities. Close collaboration with the main religious NGOs as well as with the Egyptian Red Crescent and the&#13;
Family Planning Association has helped the SFD to work with smaller NGOs and community groups through the&#13;
use of a mentor system. Many of these smaller NGOs are now working independently, mostly in poor rural areas&#13;
(NGO-SFD relations are discussed in Annexes 1, 2 and 3 in the context of various programs).&#13;
1.15   Role of Donors: Donors have played a major role in supporting the SFD in the past. This strong support&#13;
can be attributed to donor interest in supporting Egypt's poor and unemployed and also to the SFD's demonstrated&#13;
efficiency. SFD effectiveness has been recognized by many donors who provided funding, including the European&#13;
Union, Denmark, France, Germany, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, the Arab Fund, the Kuwait Fund,&#13;
the Abu Dhabi Fund, China and India. Many donors have pooled their funds with the World Bank Group during&#13;
Phase 1. Others have worked in parallel. Without this vigorous and sustained donor support, SFD's initial progress&#13;
would not have been possible.&#13;
D. R4TIONALE FOR IDA INVOLVEMENT&#13;
1.16   The Bank's Country Assistance Strategy for Egypt discussed by the Board on March 24, 1994&#13;
recommended a strong emphasis on poverty reduction through development of human resources (see paragraphs 37-&#13;
42 of Report No. P-6263-EGT) and using the contribution of Egypt's small entrepreneurs. The World Bank has&#13;
taken a broad based approach in the social sectors and has supported projects in basic health and education. The&#13;
support to SFD is providing a vehicle to help reduce poverty and improve living conditions by creating employment&#13;
and supporting community development.  The proposed project will support activities designed to reduce&#13;
unemployment and increase growth by harnessing the productive capacity of Egypt's small entrepreneurs and&#13;
community groups. It also provides an important vehicle to support World Bank/NGO partnership.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Egypt: Second Social Fund Project                                                             Page 5&#13;
1.17    The Government of Egypt requested the World Bank to take the lead in developing the project and in&#13;
convening the donors meeting because of the World Bank's : (i) global experience with social funds, (ii) technical&#13;
and financial support for Phase 1; and (iii) experience in mobilizing donor resources. The donors meeting was&#13;
chaired by the World Bank and was held on April 16th through 17th, 1996. The meeting was hosted by the&#13;
European Union at their headquarters in Brussels. The meeting was able to raise US$775 million for Phase II&#13;
including US$174 million from Egyptian sources. The IDA Credit has been a catalyst for raising US$481 million&#13;
from other donors.&#13;
2.  THE PROPOSED PROJECT&#13;
A. PROJECT OBJECrIVES&#13;
2.1    The project objectives are to help: (a) create jobs through support of small enterprises and labor intensive&#13;
works, and (b) support community infrastructure and services in partnership with NGOs and local groups. These&#13;
objectives would be accomplished through building on the strengths of the first phase of the SFD. The issues raised&#13;
in paragraphs 1.5 to 1.9 will be addressed to assure that the SFD is more sustainable, more highly targeted and more&#13;
efficient during Phase II.&#13;
B. PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
2.2    The proposed second phase of the SFD will include the following programs:&#13;
(a)    Small-scale Labor Intensive Works Program: The SLWP will build on the public works program,&#13;
with an increased focus on community partnership and targeting. Sub-projects will continue to be&#13;
executed in close cooperation with Governorates. the local branches of the relevant technical&#13;
Ministries and the concerned community.&#13;
(b)    Community Development Program: The CDP would build on the current program and continue&#13;
to focus on (i) community and NGO participation, (ii) capacity building and (iii) targeting of&#13;
women, the poor, and the unemployed. CDP sub-projects will continue to be executed in&#13;
partnership with NGOs and the beneficiary communities, with involvement of local authorities at&#13;
the planning stage.&#13;
(c)    Enterprise Development Program: The EDP has evolved into a credit program providing loans&#13;
to banks for on-lending to entrepreneurs and a technical assistance program for entrepreneurs&#13;
through NGOs. During implementation of Phase II, the EDP would be restructured according to a&#13;
business plan (agreed with the World Bank) designed to assure long-term sustainability.&#13;
(d)    Human Resource Development Program: The HRDP would build on the public enterprise labor&#13;
mobility program but extend its mandate to support labor mobility in private sector companies&#13;
affected by trade liberalization. The program would also provide support on a matching grant&#13;
basis to small enterprises that wish to train their workers. Grants would be transparent and would&#13;
be larger for skills with higher mobility. The labor mobility program would be executed in&#13;
partnership with the enterprise concerned, while training services would be provided under&#13;
contract by the private sector.&#13;
(e)    Institutional Development Program: The IDP would support SFD management as well as poverty&#13;
monitoring and other studies linked to poverty and social safety nets.  During Phase 11,&#13;
decentralization of functions would increase through transfer of responsibility for programs to&#13;
SFD's regional offices when feasible. This would allow even closer association with local&#13;
Governments than is now the case.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 6                                                               Egypt: Second Social Fund Project&#13;
C. COST AND FINANCING&#13;
2.3    Costs: The project will be implemented over a four-year period. The total cost of the project is estimated&#13;
at US$775 million net of taxes and duties, with a foreign exchange cost of US$27 million. As summarized in Table&#13;
2.1, it is expected that US$92 million (12 percent) would be allocated to Small Scale Labor Intensive Works,&#13;
US$208 million (27 percent) to Community Development, US$354 million (46 percent) to Enterprise Development,&#13;
US$80 million (10 percent) to Human Resources Development, and US$40 million (5 percent) to Institutional&#13;
Development. No contingencies have been applied as the project supports envelopes for programs rather than&#13;
specific activities. Detailed project costs are shown in Annex 9.&#13;
Table 2.1: Project Costs Summary (in US$ million)&#13;
Local      Foreign     Total      % Foreign      % Total&#13;
Exchange.   Project Costs&#13;
Small-scale Labor Intensive     92.0                    92.0                        12&#13;
Works&#13;
Community Development           208.0                  208.0                        27&#13;
Enterprise Development          354.0         -        354.0          -             46&#13;
Human Resources Development     60.2         19.8       80.0          25            10&#13;
Institutional Development       34.0         7.0        41.0          17            5&#13;
Total Project Cost              748.3        26.7       775.0         3             100&#13;
Note: Figures may not add up due to rounding.&#13;
2.4    Financing: The financing plan for Phase 11 was finalized during a donors meeting held in Brussels on&#13;
April 16-17, 1996. During the meeting, contributions of US$526 million dollars were confirmed by donors in&#13;
addition to the Government contribution. The following donors formalized contributions during the meeting: the&#13;
Arab Fund, Denmark, the European Union, France, Germany, the Kuwait Fund, the Netherlands, the United&#13;
Kingdom, IDA, and the UNDP. In addition, other donors such as the Abu Dhabi Fund, the African Development&#13;
Bank, Korea and Switzerland have confirmed their interest and are expected to add at least US$75 million. The&#13;
Egyptian Government pledged the equivalent of US$120 million, double their Phase I contribution. Egyptian&#13;
NGOs and beneficiaries are expected to contribute at least $54 million, so that the financing of Phase II would&#13;
include $174 million (22%) from domestic sources, and $601 (78%) million from external sources. Ninety percent&#13;
of total financing is confirmed. The proposed IDA credit of US$120 million would cover 15 percent of total Phase&#13;
11 costs. Other donors are expected to provide parallel financing for Phase II with the exception of the Netherlands&#13;
contribution of US$20 million which will be in the form of joint-cofinancing with IDA and will be disbursed&#13;
through IDA. The financing plan is summarized in Table 2.2 (the Arab Funds category in Table 2.2 includes the&#13;
Abu Dhabi Fund, the Arab Fund and the Kuwait Fund).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Egypt: Second Social Fund Project                                                                       Page 7&#13;
Table 2.2: Financing Plan by Disbursement Category (in US$ million)&#13;
IDA    European    Arab      U`NDP/    Bilateral    Govemment,    Total&#13;
Union     Funds     African                Beneficiaries &amp;&#13;
Dev. Bank                   NGOs&#13;
Small-scale Labor Intensive Works  25        20         -          5           42            -           92&#13;
Community' Development             50        40        15          5           28            70          208&#13;
Enterprise Development             30       120        150         -           20           34           354&#13;
Hluman Resources Development       iS        10         -          -           5             50          80&#13;
Institutionial Development          -        10        5           4           2             20          41&#13;
Total                              120      200        170        14           97           174          775&#13;
D. IMPLEMENTATION ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
Operating Procedures of SFD&#13;
2.5     The project will be implemented by SFD in accordance with its established procedures.  These are stated&#13;
in its Operational Manual, which was developed in consultation with the Government and donors. The mission&#13;
found the manual to be acceptable though occasional revisions will be required to take into account changing&#13;
conditions on the ground. During negotiations the borrower and SFD gave assurances that the statutes, by-laws&#13;
and operating procedures of SFD will remain acceptable to the World Bank Group at all times (para. 5.2).&#13;
2.6     The SFD executes projects in partnership with development partners - Govemorates, NGOs, commercial&#13;
banks and Ministries. Proposals for a wide range of activities are submitted to one of the SFD programs by partner&#13;
agencies. For example, a proposal could involve several rural roads and water supply systems for a particular&#13;
region. The activities, each of which is referred to as a sub-project, would be executed by SFD in cooperation with&#13;
the proposing agency. The package of proposals (called a sub-programn) could include activities such as a waste&#13;
water plant in one village, a road providing access to a second and a community center in a third. Individual&#13;
proposals are screened to assure that they do not replicate activities undertaken by other agencies or include&#13;
activities with harmful social or environmental side-effects. Sub-program proposals as a whole are then subjected to&#13;
economic and environmental analysis. Full economic and environmental analysis is required when sub-program&#13;
size exceeds US$500,000. Due to their small size, it is not possible to carry out this level of economic and&#13;
environmental analysis for most sub-project proposals. In these cases, a screening process is used to determine cost-&#13;
effectiveness.&#13;
2.7     Sub-project Cycle. The SFD initiates and accepts sub-project proposals submitted by sponsoring agencies&#13;
(SA) to any ten of the regional or six satellite offices. Selection of proposals is based on two sets of criteria. The&#13;
first is contained in guidelines focusing on regional allocations which are established in the Operational Manual.&#13;
These regional allocations are based on the distribution of poverty and are made for public works and community&#13;
development sub-projects only. For public works, the regional authorities set priorities on the basis of both poverty&#13;
within the region and demand from communities, while for community development, NGOs play a much greater&#13;
FThis report uses the following terms: project refers to the overall Second Social Fund Project, program refers to specific SFD programns&#13;
such as Public Works, Community Development etc., sub-program denotes the group of activities within a defined area carried out in&#13;
partnership with one implementing agency and the term sub-project is applied to specific activities such as a road or a community center.&#13;
SFD itself uses the word project for what is called a sub-program here and the word activity for what is called a sub-project here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 8                                                                    Egypt: Second Social Fund Project&#13;
role in identification (see Annexes I and 2 for process and Annex 6 for criteria). After preliminary screening by the&#13;
regional and satellite offices, acceptable sub-projects are forwarded to the national office for a detailed desk and&#13;
field appraisal.  Sub-project appraisal at the national office emphasizes technical feasibility and social and&#13;
institutional analysis as well as simplified economic and environmental analysis. Two types of criteria apply. In&#13;
addition to meeting the criteria contained in the Operational Manual for regional allocations, proposals are evaluated&#13;
for cost-efficiency, level of community commitment as expressed by contributions in cash or kind, and geographical&#13;
balance (with a bias towards poorer areas). During Phase If the Operational Manual will be updated and revised&#13;
following periodic consultations with the World Bank Group and other donors. The objective of these revisions is&#13;
to refine SFD procedures in light of experience gained in Phase I so that the effectiveness of its operations may be&#13;
increased. Criteria which have been tested and proven to be effective will be added, while care is taken to avoid&#13;
adding so many of these criteria that rapid execution might be hampered. During negotiations assurances were&#13;
received that the SED Operctional MUanual will be periodically reviewed and updated in consultation with the&#13;
World Bank Group (para. 5.2).&#13;
2.8     The average time for sub-project processing, from reception of a sub-project proposal to approval, has&#13;
averaged about 4.5 months while the average implementation period for sub-projects has been 12 to 18 months.&#13;
Upon formal approval of a sub-project, a framework agreement is drawn up between SFD and each Sponsoring&#13;
Agency (SA) specifying the responsibilities of each party; procurement methods; implementation schedules;&#13;
financial terms and conditions, the SA contribution; supervision; and handover mechanisms.&#13;
Project Monitoring&#13;
2.9     Project monitoring indicators are provided in Table 2.3. Because the SFD is a demand driven institution,&#13;
actual outputs are subject to change: the estimates in Table 2.3 were derived from Phase I experiences. In addition&#13;
to the indicators in Table 2.3, the SFD's monitoring system (described in Annex 7) will generate a wide range of&#13;
information to provide SFD management and donors with the information necessary to measure progress, targeting&#13;
and efficiency. In addition to process monitoring, impact monitoring would be done through surveys, beneficiary&#13;
assessments, and complementary studies. This will provide continuous feedback on SFD impact on beneficiaries.&#13;
These surveys are done under contract by research institutes and not by SFD staff. The first impact surveys have&#13;
been completed.&#13;
Table 2.3: Monitoring Indicators for Phase II&#13;
Item                                               1997          1998          1999        2000&#13;
Kilometers of Potable Water Networks                125           125           125          125&#13;
Kilometers of Rural Roads improved                  100           100           100          100&#13;
# of Health Awareness campaigns                      33            33            33           33&#13;
# of people in adult literacy classes             4,000         4,000         4,000        4,000&#13;
# of Microenterprise Loan Recipients             10,000        10,000        10,000       10,000&#13;
# of small entrepreneurs helped                  10,000        10,000        10,000       10,000&#13;
% Female among Community Development&#13;
Direct Beneficiaries                                 50            50            50           50&#13;
% Female among small entrepreneurs helped           25             27            28           30&#13;
Temporary Jobs in person years                   20,000        20,000        20,000       20,000&#13;
Number of Permanent Jobs                         50,000        50,000        50,000       50,000&#13;
2.10    The SFD currently prepares monthly progress reports which include the following information by region&#13;
and sector: (a) sub-projects presented, appraised, in execution, completed, and evaluated, including the number of&#13;
projects and beneficiaries, amounts committed and disbursed, and average cost per beneficiary per project; (b)&#13;
sources of funds for each sub-project; (c) SFD staffing, indicating any changes that may have taken place; and (d)&#13;
operating costs. Annual financial and technical audits will provide independent information.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Egypt: Second Social Fund Project                                                          Page 9&#13;
Planned Reviews&#13;
2.11   Impact assessments and related studies will be complemented by a mid-term review aimed at assessing the&#13;
administrative, financial and technical aspects of sub-projects as well as the institutional efficiency of SFD.&#13;
Specifically, the review will: (a) evaluate project performance during implementation; (b) provide management with&#13;
feedback on project achievements and shortcomings; and (c) document the status of project execution for the benefit&#13;
of the Borrower and the financing agencies.  Following the mid-term review, agreed corrective actions will be&#13;
implemented expeditiously. In addition to the mid-term review, Annual Implementation Reviews (AIR) would be&#13;
conducted by the SFD, donors and the World Bank Group. These reviews would analyze: (a) financial performance&#13;
and budget execution against projected targets; (b) workplan and budget proposals for the following year; (c)&#13;
recurrent budget implications of SFD investments; (d) adjustments required in project design and implementation&#13;
schedule; and (e) results of evaluation studies and indicators on sub-project quality and impact.&#13;
2.12    During negotiations the Government gave assurances that it and the World Bank Group will carry out an&#13;
annual review of project implementation not later than November 30 each year on the basis of appropriate&#13;
documentation prepared by SFD that would include the budget and work-plan proposals for the following year.&#13;
During negotiations assurances were also received that the World Bank Group and the Government would carry out&#13;
a mid-term review no later than November 30, 1998 to: (a) evaluate the impact of sub-projects on beneficiaries and&#13;
the sustainability of sub-projects; and (b) make recommendations on thefuture orientation of the SFD. Assurances&#13;
were given that the Government would implement all actions agreed with the World Bank Group as a result of the&#13;
mid-term review. It is understood that the mid-term review will replace the annual review in 1998 (para.5.2).&#13;
Assurances were also given that SFD would submit semi-annual progress reports to the World Bank Group, not&#13;
later than three months after the end of each semester (para. 5.2).&#13;
Supervision Plan&#13;
2.13   The SFD is now one of the most effective implementation agencies for World Bank/IDA projects in Egypt,&#13;
reducing the need for close supervision.  Supervision will focus on continuing program  assessment and&#13;
sustainability. Several key conditionalities would be monitored through World Bank Group supervision, including&#13;
implementation of the EDP business plan and periodic revisions of the SFD manual. The proposed project would&#13;
be supervised jointly by the Headquarters staff and resident mission staff with the latter being responsible for&#13;
routine procurement and disbursement matters. The Task Manager will provide support on policy matters and carry&#13;
out supervision missions. Due to the importance of EDP transformation, a World Bank specialist in enterprise&#13;
development will be used regularly. Supervision for Phase II is expected to be combined with that for Phase I until&#13;
the closing date. For the two projects combined, it is expected that during FY97 about forty staff weeks will be&#13;
needed to assist in the transfornation of the EDP, resolution of the O&amp;M issue and the revision of procedures for&#13;
CDP microenterprise development and training. The need for supervision resources is expected to drop to 20 staff&#13;
weeks in FY98. The European Union plans to place two international experts in Egypt to supervise Phase I.&#13;
E. SUSTAINABILITY&#13;
2.14   Three aspects of the project need to be considered with regard to sustainability: the SFD as an institution,&#13;
its sub-programs, and individual sub-projects. Sustainability of the SFD as an institution in the intermediate horizon&#13;
is assured, as donor interest and support remain high. The SFD is proving to be an important vehicle to help the&#13;
central authorities work with regional authorities: it has shown very good results on the ground and in helping to&#13;
build capacity at the regional and local government level and has developed into one of the most efficient and&#13;
effective agencies in the country. Several Ministries, including Education, Health and Population and Public Works&#13;
have requested that it help execute their own programs. While many SFD activities can be transferred to local&#13;
authorities over time and parts of the SFD such as EDP can become financially sustainable, the World Bank's global&#13;
experience indicates that this will happen very slowly and the need for SFD will continue over a fairly long time.&#13;
The Government's long-term commitment to SFD is evident through the increase of its financing share for Phase I.&#13;
Strong donor support was confirmed by the successful donor meeting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 10                                                                   Egypt: Second Social Fund Project&#13;
2.15    During Phase 11, the SFD's enterprise development program is expected to gradually become financially&#13;
sustainable. The labor mobility support to be provided by the human resources program is designed to meet a&#13;
transitory need and would eventually be phased out. Activities included in the labor intensive works and&#13;
community development programs should eventually be moved to local and regional Governments, once Egypt&#13;
completes its decentralization process. The SFD supports the decentralization process by helping to build local&#13;
capacity to develop and execute projects of interest to communities. The sustainability of individual CDP/SLWP&#13;
sub-projects would be assured by selecting proposals which are both carefilly screened and have strong beneficiary&#13;
support manifested by contributions in cash or kind. During negotiations, the SFD gave assurances that it would&#13;
develop a program for improving O&amp;M of CDP/SLWP projects by December 31, 1997 (para.5.2). The&#13;
sustainability of the investments financed by EDP would be assured by the application of commercial financial and&#13;
business principles in their selection and approval.&#13;
F. PROCUREMENT&#13;
2.16    Procurement under the project will be carried out in accordance with World Bank Procurement Guidelines&#13;
using standardized local bidding procedures and contract forms developed by SFD and agreed with the Bank.&#13;
Procurement during Phase I has proven to be economic and efficient, and procurement during Phase 11 will build on&#13;
Phase I experience. The SFD and the Sponsoring Agency (local government and NGO) would jointly procure&#13;
goods and civil works for sub-projects. This approach, shown to be transparent and fair during Phase 1, results in&#13;
the selection of the lowest bidder. The SFD's procurement arrangements under the existing framework agreement&#13;
require packaging of sub-projects only when significant implementation efficiencies would result. Table 2.4&#13;
summarizes the project components, their estimated costs and the proposed method of procurement. Most activities&#13;
to be financed during Phase 11 are currently on-going and using Phase I resources. Phase 11 activities can start&#13;
immediately.&#13;
Table 2.4: Summary of Proposed Procurement Arrangements (in US$ million)&#13;
NCB              Other          Not IDA          Total&#13;
financed&#13;
Civil Works                  7.1             35.1 a           66.0           94.4&#13;
(7.1)            (35.1)           (0)           (28.4)&#13;
Equipment                                     8.3 b           58.2           80.3&#13;
(8.3)            (0)          (22.1)&#13;
Credit Funds                                 31.4 c           300.9          332.3&#13;
(31.4)           (0)           (31.4)&#13;
Technical Assistance                          8.5 d           73.0           81.5&#13;
(8.5)            (0)           (8.5)&#13;
Training                                     29.6 e           129.2          158.8&#13;
(29.6)           (0)           (29.6)&#13;
Salaries                                                      22.6           22.6&#13;
(0)            (0)&#13;
Operations and                                                 5.1            5.1&#13;
Maintenance                                                    (0)            (0)&#13;
Total                        7.1             112.9            655.0          775.0&#13;
(Total IDA)                 (7.1)            (112.9)           (0)          (120.0)&#13;
Note: Figures in parenthesis are the respective amounts to befinanced by IDA.&#13;
a Contracted to communities.&#13;
b Procured through international or local shopping.&#13;
cPrudent shopping to commercialpractices.&#13;
dAwarded in accordance with Bank Guidelines on consultants.&#13;
'A warded in accordance with Bank Guidelines on consultants&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Egypt: Second Social Fund Project                                                         Page 11&#13;
2.17    Procurement for SFD Sub-Projects: Procurement under EDP loans will follow commercial practices.&#13;
These are relatively small loans (averaging under $4,000) and it is expected that the recipients would shop prudently&#13;
and according to their needs. Civil Works undertaken by the SFD will include: expansion of potable water&#13;
networks, construction of rural roads and cleaning public irrigation canals. Civil works contracts will include small&#13;
works usually not exceeding US$150,000 in dispersed communities. Due to the nature of the works and the&#13;
difficulty of large packaging, it is not expected that any work contract exceeding this amount will reach a size large&#13;
enough to justify ICB. Civil works between US$150,000 to US$3 million would be awarded through National&#13;
Competitive Bidding (NCB), but foreign contractors will not be precluded. Contracts between US$50,000 and&#13;
US$150,000 will be procured through NCB with bid advertisement within the Governorate only. Civil works under&#13;
US$50,000 would be procured through community contracting and such contracts will not exceed an aggregate of&#13;
US$3 million. Goods and equipment to be financed by the IDA Credit include primarily materials for social&#13;
services, e.g. medicines, educational materials, etc. No contracts for goods and equipment are expected to exceed&#13;
US$300,000. Goods and equipment contracts with an estimated value not to exceed US$5,000,000 would be&#13;
purchased through International Shopping or UN Procurement agencies (as permitted under para. 3.9 of the&#13;
Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits of January, 1995). Due to the efficiencies&#13;
achieved through using local shopping contracts under the SFD Phase I, continued use of local shopping during&#13;
Phase 11 will apply to contracts under US$50,000 up to an aggregate amount not to exceed $3,300,000.&#13;
2.18   Technical Assistance and Training: Technical assistance and training will cover services to help small&#13;
entrepreneurs, support for community social services and feasibility studies for sub-projects. Consultants will be&#13;
appointed following the World Bank's Consultant Guidelines and will be recruited locally through competitive&#13;
selection. Consultant assignments will include monitoring, evaluation and administrative support to the SFD. Egypt&#13;
has qualified local consulting firms with the expertise required to carry out these functions, including knowledge of&#13;
local dialects and traditions.&#13;
2.19    Procurement Review Thresholds: Bidding packages for IDA financed contracts above the threshold of&#13;
US$500,000 for civil works and US$250,000 for goods and equipment would be subject to prior review procedures.&#13;
The threshold for prior review of consultant services would be US$100,000 for contracts with consulting firms,&#13;
US$50,000 for individuals and all sole source contracts and terms of reference regardless of the contract value. All&#13;
other contracts will be subject to selective post award review. The SFD will be responsible for following&#13;
monitoring procedures and for maintaining proper records for easy review by IDA. It is expected that two thirds of&#13;
NCB contracts for civil works and one third of NCB contracts for goods and equipment will be subject to post&#13;
award review.&#13;
G. DISBURSEMENT&#13;
2.20   The proposed credit would be disbursed over a period of about four years and would be completed by&#13;
December 31, 2000, the project completion date. This disbursement pace is faster than other projects in Egypt but&#13;
consistent with Phase I experience. The last date for presentation of sub-projects by SFD to the World Bank Group&#13;
would be June 30, 2000. The closing date of the IDA Credit would be June 30, 2001.&#13;
Table 2.5: Estimated Disbursement Schedule&#13;
Fiscal Year   1997      1998      1999      2000&#13;
Annual           25        35        35        25   1&#13;
Cumulative       25        60        95        120&#13;
Percentage      20%/0     50%       80%       100%_  j&#13;
2.21    Estimated disbursements by IDA fiscal year are shown in Table 2.5.  There would be only one&#13;
disbursement category: SFD sub-projects and disbursements would be 100 percent of amounts disbursed to&#13;
implementing agencies against statements of expenditures for all contracts up to the limits for prior review (para.&#13;
2.18). Contributions by the implementing agency and by entrepreneurs are expected to cover taxes and other costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 12                                                              Egypt: Second Social Fund Project&#13;
2.22    To ensure that funds are readily available, SFD would open a Special Account in a commercial bank on&#13;
terms and conditions satisfactory to the World Bank. An initial deposit of US$12 million, corresponding to about&#13;
four months of expenditures under the project, would be advanced to the account from the IDA credit. The Special&#13;
Account would be replenished monthly, or after one third of the initial deposit amount has been disbursed,&#13;
whichever is sooner. During negotiations the Government agreed that the Special Account and the SOEs would be&#13;
audited in conjunction with the annual audit of SFD's accounts (para 5.2).&#13;
H. ACCOUNTS AND AUDITS&#13;
2.23   Independent external auditors, acceptable to the World Bank, would conduct annual financial and&#13;
functional audits of SFD. Functional audits would examine a sample of sub-programs and sub-projects, review&#13;
individual contracts and compliance with contract terms, inspect the progress of civil works, reconcile the physical&#13;
progress with the financial expenses incurred, and state whether procurement guidelines were being followed. The&#13;
reports would be submitted to the SFD Board not later than three months after the end of the fiscal year. Annual&#13;
audit reports would cover SFD's balance sheets and income statements and include the auditor's assessment of the&#13;
financial statements, as well as separate opinions on: (a) project accounts; (b) SOEs; (c) the Special Account; (d)&#13;
whether procurement of all contracts was carried out in accordance with agreed guidelines; (e) the adequacy of the&#13;
intemal controls system; and (f) the sample of sub-projects examined to see whether SFD guidelines are followed.&#13;
At negotiations, the Government gave assurances that: independent auditors, acceptable to the World Bank Group,&#13;
would conduct annual audits of SFD's accounts, and annual technical and managerial audits of SFD's operations;&#13;
and that SFD would submit certified copies of the annual audit reports, which would include any adverse material&#13;
findings and an annual summary of the quarterly functional audits no later than six months following the end of the&#13;
Government's fiscal year (para. 5.2).&#13;
2.24    The SFD would maintain consolidated accounts for the entire project, and detailed accounts for individual&#13;
sub-project grants. Sponsoring agencies would be required by the sub-project agreement to establish appropriate&#13;
accounting systems. The SFD would assist sponsoring agencies in developing appropriate accounting procedures.&#13;
3.  THE PROJECT EXECUTION AGENCY&#13;
3.1    The SFD was established by presidential decree in 1991. It is an autonomous agency with legal personality&#13;
as well as technical, financial and administrative flexibility. It reports directly to the President of the Republic. The&#13;
organization did not become fully operational until early 1993. The SFD Board of Directors (BOD) acts as a&#13;
technical steering committee. It is chaired by the Prime Minister, and is comprised of fifteen members, including&#13;
eight ministers and seven representatives from the private sector. Ministerial representation on the BOD eliminates&#13;
duplication of efforts and ensures adherence to sector priorities. The BOD sets SFD's operational guidelines,&#13;
prioritizes its annual budgets and financial contributions and authorizes disbursements.&#13;
3.2    The Executive Committee (EC), chaired by the chairman of the BOD, consists of eight members from the&#13;
private sector. The EC evaluates projects submitted to the SFD prior to presentation to the BOD, and is authorized&#13;
to approve projects from US$500,000 to US$3 million. Acting on behalf of the BOD, the EC also approves&#13;
guidelines for manuals and sub-projects, establishes guidelines for implementation of projects approved by the&#13;
BOD, delineates resource availability, and maintains regular contact with donors. Day to day operations of the SFD&#13;
are the responsibility of the Managing Director (MD), who is appointed by the Board. He approves sub-projects of&#13;
less than US$500,000, authorizes all disbursements and prepares progress reports and presents these to the BOD.&#13;
The MD heads a staff of 133 people, distributed into departments by sub-project themes, as well as administrative&#13;
and support services (see Annex 6 for details).&#13;
3.3    The SFD's well-defined administrative structure contributes to its efficient management. The current&#13;
structure will largely be retained, but will place a stronger emphasis on the demand driven approach and on&#13;
decentralization of authority and functions. The main office in Cairo sets overall strategy, prepares technical plans&#13;
and budgets for sub-projects, handles financial transactions, and provides operational support and guidance to ten&#13;
regional and six satellite offices outside of Cairo. These offices are the main point of contact between requesting&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Egypt: Second Social Fund Project                                                                   Page 13&#13;
agencies and the SFD. They provide advice to communities, NGOs and regional governments on SFD procedures,&#13;
process applications, conduct appraisals, and support implementation.&#13;
3.4     SFD financed sub-projects have been implemented rapidly and efficiently, with operating costs averaging 6&#13;
percent of total disbursements. This figure compares favorably with other Social Funds (Senegal and Nicaragua are&#13;
at 5 percent, Bolivia at 5.5, and Honduras at 10 percent). Fifty percent of operating costs are allocated to the&#13;
enterprise development component, 22 percent to the community development component, 20 percent to the public&#13;
works, 6 percent to human resources development, and 2 percent to institutional development. Over a period of&#13;
three years, the SFD contracted 200 sub-projects for a total value of US$370.52 million, with an average of US$1.86&#13;
million per project.3 Of the US$204 4 million received from donors, US$191 has been disbursed, representing 94&#13;
percent of available funds.&#13;
3.5     The SFD's efficiency is explained by its: (a) effective management style; (b) status outside the civil&#13;
service; (c) administrative structure, which has clearly delineated lines of responsibility and accountability; (d)&#13;
partnership with local communities, close association with NGOs and local governments; and (e) use of&#13;
standardized project types, which simplifies project preparation and processing. The acceptance rate is 65-70&#13;
percent of proposals submitted, which is comparable with other social funds.&#13;
4. SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC ASSESSMENT&#13;
A. BENEFITS AND ECONOMIC ANALYSIS&#13;
4.1     The project is expected to have significant benefits in terms of employment creation and in helping lower-&#13;
income families through enhanced income generation. Based on Phase I experience, it is estimated that the project&#13;
would create 200,000 permanent and 80,000 temporary jobs. The results of a beneficiary profile survey carried out&#13;
in five Governorates show that SFD beneficiaries are poorer than the population at large, thus confirming the&#13;
validity of the SFD's approach. Overall, it is estimated that the project would help raise the incomes of I to 1.5&#13;
million people.&#13;
4.2     In addition to its direct impact on poverty, the project would have two other significant benefits. First, it&#13;
would create significant social and economic infrastructure in the poorer communities. Second, the active&#13;
involvement of NGOs and local communities in all aspects of sub-projects through Phase I has given a strong sense&#13;
of empowerment to people who may otherwise have felt disfranchised. By continuing this in Phase II, the project&#13;
would contribute to social stability. In this respect, SFD has been a model for other programs in Egypt.&#13;
4.3     Economic Evaluation: It is difficult to calculate an ERR for the overall project given the difficulty of&#13;
quantifying the benefits of some of its activities, such as upgrading public health and the environment and providing&#13;
job-training. Nevertheless, the SFD attempts to quantify benefits wherever possible, using measures of willingness&#13;
to pay for community services; estimates of travel cost savings (roads); rental values (community buildings); and&#13;
enhanced prospects for earnings (technical training and enterprise development). A minimum threshold rate of&#13;
return of 12 percent is required for sub-project approval. Based on a sample of projects financed during Phase I,&#13;
and extrapolating across the entire program, the rate of return for activities with quantifiable benefits (which&#13;
account for 75 percent of project cost), is estimated to be 21 percent (see annex 5 for details). This estimate should&#13;
be treated with caution given that is based on subjective assumptions. Sensitivity analysis indicates a rate of return&#13;
of 15 percent would prevail even if the benefit estimates were reduced by 20%.&#13;
2&#13;
US$191 million have been disbursed through sponsoring agencies.&#13;
3&#13;
There is an active pipeline of sub-project requests totaling US$241 million.&#13;
4&#13;
Committed resources from the 17 donors is in the amount of USS613.1 million. However, the actual flow of funds to SFD started in March&#13;
1993 and reached USS204 million by September 30, 1994.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 14                                                                 Egypt: Second Social Fund Project&#13;
4.4     Besides ERR, the SFD also uses measures of cost-effectiveness to review sub-projects. It ensures that sub-&#13;
project costs and cost per beneficiary are within sub-sector norms. As indicated previously, the cost per job created&#13;
of UJS$1,401 compares favorably with other social funds.&#13;
B. RisKs&#13;
4.5     The main risks are that the SFD would: (a) become less efficient; and (b) lose its beneficiary orientation.&#13;
The first risk will be reduced by (i) increasing decentralization, (ii) continuing to rely on staff with performance&#13;
linked contracts; and (iii) continuing to increase transparency. The second risk will be reduced by (i) continuous&#13;
beneficiary assessments; (ii) establishing an independent client relations unit; and (iii) using frequent encounter&#13;
sessions with key partners including regional governments, NGOs and community groups.&#13;
4.6    The risks in the public works program include: (a) not targeting the poor; and (b) negative environmental&#13;
sidc-effects. The first risk will be mitigated by focusing on poor areas and requiring a labor intensive approach.&#13;
I'he second risk is mitigated by requiring environmental screening for sub-projects.&#13;
-I 2    I'he main risk in the communit, developnment program  is that the SFD could determine priorities for&#13;
communities and the program's key partners such as NGOs, rather than allow them to take the lead in identification&#13;
(f sub-programs and specific activities. This risk will be minimized by continuous application of participatory&#13;
processes as described in section "'C" below.&#13;
4i.8    The principal risk for the enterprise development program is one of sustainability at both the program&#13;
level and the individual enterprise level. Program sustainability will be assured by the structural revisions in the&#13;
.DP discussed in Sections 1 and 2. Individual enterprise sustainability will be assured through careful screening of&#13;
proposals and through appropriate provision of technical support and training to the entrepreneurs.&#13;
4.9     The main risk for the human resources development program is that training may not focus on labor&#13;
market needs. This risk is reduced by supporting only training requested by enterprises.&#13;
C. ENVIRONMENTAL ASPECTS AND PARTICIPATION&#13;
.4.10    Environment: The project has been rated category "B." The public works program and the community&#13;
development program will support community infrastructure through financing sub-projects requested by&#13;
conimunities.  These sub-projects range from  waste water treatment and rural roads to community centers.&#13;
Sub-projects in waste management may also be supported.  All sub-project proposals will be subjected to&#13;
environmental screening criteria and larger sub-projects will be subject to detailed environmental analysis.&#13;
Community participation and leadership is essential in approval of sub-projects. The project will work in close&#13;
consultation with NGOs and community groups.&#13;
4. 1I    Participatory Approach: Although the SFD has employed a participatory approach throughout Phase 1,&#13;
this approach has not been implemented systematically. This issue has been addressed through project preparation,&#13;
and systematic beneficiary assessments and focus group meetings are expected to be employed during Phase 11.&#13;
Extensive consultations with regional and local authorities now take place regularly. Sessions in which the SFD's&#13;
partners (such as NGOs and communities) can express their opinions freely will also be used on a regular basis.&#13;
5. AGREEMENTS AND RECOMMENDATION&#13;
Before negotiations, the Government and SFD  provided a draft business plan for the long-term&#13;
,,itainability of SFD's enterprise development program. The plan was discussed and agreed upon during technical&#13;
discussions preceding negotiations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Egypt: Second Social Fund Project                                                         Page 15&#13;
5.2    During negotiations the following agreements were received:&#13;
(a)    The business plan for EDP transformation will be executed during Phase TI and will not be&#13;
modified without prior approval of the World Bank Group (para 1.9);&#13;
(b)    The SFD Operational Manual will be reviewed periodically with the World Bank Group and will&#13;
remain acceptable to the World Bank Group at all times (para 2.7);&#13;
(c)    The SFD will develop a strategy for improving operations and maintenance of public works and&#13;
community development projects by December 31, 1997 (para. 2.15);&#13;
(d)    The statutes and by-laws of SFD will remain acceptable to World Bank Group throughout project&#13;
implementation (para 2.5);&#13;
(e)    The borrower will carryout, not later than November 30 each year and jointly with the World&#13;
Bank Group, an annual review of project implementation on the basis of appropriate&#13;
documentation prepared by SFD that would include the budget and work-plan for the following&#13;
year (para. 2.12);&#13;
(f)    The borrower will: (i) carry out, jointly with the World Bank Group, a mid-term review not later&#13;
than November 30, 1998; (ii) submit to the World Bank Group a report by consultants not later&#13;
than four weeks prior to the review; and (iii) implement the recommendations of the mid-term&#13;
review (para 2.12); and&#13;
(g)    The borrower will submit to the World Bank Group, the following audit reports: (i) financial&#13;
audits annually, with the report to be submitted within six months of the close of the fiscal year;&#13;
and (ii) technical and managerial audits to be submitted within six months of the close of the fiscal&#13;
year (para. 2.19).&#13;
5.3    Recommendation: Subject to the above terms and conditions, the proposed project would be suitable for&#13;
a credit of SDR82.3 million (US$120.0 equivalent) to the Arab Republic of Egypt on standard IDA terms with a 35&#13;
year maturity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 1: PUBLIC WORKS PROGRAM&#13;
I.     Background. The Public Works Program component (PWP) of the Egypt Social Fund was designed to: (i)&#13;
initiate and stimulate a program of actions aimed at softening both the initial adverse effects of the reform process&#13;
and the negative impacts of the Gulf crisis on Egypt; and (ii) establish mechanisms to protect selected target&#13;
population groups (e.g., displaced public enterprise workers, households headed by females, and unskilled and&#13;
semi-skilled unemployed workers) in Egypt from the possible longer-term adverse effects of adjustment.&#13;
2.     In order to meet its mandate the PWP undertook construction, rehabilitation and maintenance of essential&#13;
municipal services in areas facing budgetary contraction, high incidence of poverty and unemployment. PWP sub-&#13;
projects were carried out by local private contractors using local labor, and included construction and rehabilitation&#13;
of water supply and sewerage systems, streets and rural roads, irrigation and drainage canals etc; and maintenance&#13;
such as cleaning canals, public buildings, solid waste collection and disposal. PWP sub-projects were able to&#13;
generate substantial temporary and permanent employment opportunities, provide essential basic infrastructure,&#13;
generate commitment and generate contributions, foster a collaborative working relationship between various&#13;
stakeholders.&#13;
3.     PWP Targeting and Allocation of Resources. The PWP targeting was based on a social and economic&#13;
study carried out in 1991. The allocation of funds was based on population size and ranking of rural areas by means&#13;
of a combined index for poverty and unemployment. Based on total funds for PWP of LE 465.6 million, the&#13;
allocation to governorates ranged from LE 51.1 million for Sohag (the highest) to LE 1. I million for the Red Sea&#13;
(the lowest). Upper Egypt, which is the region of highest priority received LE 294.9 million (about 60 percent);&#13;
Lower Egypt, received LE 158.1 million (about 37 percent), and the Border Governorates, which due to their low&#13;
population base, received LE 12.6 million (about 3 percent).'&#13;
4.     The Main Results of the PWP Program. PWP activities were successful in meeting one of it's primary&#13;
objectives: employment generation in poor rural communities. By the end 1995, about 4 1 0,000 M/m temporary&#13;
jobs and about 2, 1 00 permanent positions were created in Upper Egypt (which correspond to contracted works&#13;
amounting to an estimated LE 337.48 million). 280,000 m/m temporary jobs and about 1,500 permanent positions&#13;
were created in Lower Egypt (which correspond to contracted works amounting about LE 206.84 million), and&#13;
16,000 m/m temporary jobs and about 80 permanent positions were created in the Border Governorates (which&#13;
correspond to contracted works amounting about LE 12.6 million). The average cost of creating temporary&#13;
employment opportunities, expressed in man-months, is estimated at about LE 820 in Upper Egypt, about LE 738 in&#13;
Lower Egypt and about LE 787 in the Border govemorates. The average cost of labor in public works is estimated&#13;
at about 30 percent of the total cost, which compares well with the average salary for unskilled or semi-skilled labor&#13;
(about LE 200-250/month).&#13;
5.     The principal conclusions of the program are as follows:&#13;
(a)   (i) Projects were demand driven; (ii) targeting of poor community groups within the govemorate was&#13;
undertaken; (iii) focus on the provision of essential infrastructure rehabilitation of public buildings was&#13;
accomplished (schools, clinics, youth centers and community development centers); (iv) operations and&#13;
maintenance costs were clearly spelt out in the framework agreement; (v) PWP activities have been labor&#13;
intensive; and (vi) community contributions (10 percent in cash/kind) have been an integral aspect of sub-&#13;
project selection;&#13;
(b)    Local employment opportunities have been invited as have local small size construction industries.&#13;
The labor component ranged from 30 percent (for rural roads) to 50 percent (for canal covering) of total&#13;
construction cost depending upon the nature of the works; the work was widely distributed among local small&#13;
contractors; and the average administrative cost ranged from 2 to 4 percent of the construction cost, which is&#13;
below the generally accepted figure of 5 percent. A comparison of average unit cost of construction of SFD&#13;
Since Alexandria does not include rural areas, funds for public works activities were not allocated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Page 2 of 4&#13;
funded versus Government funded projects of similar size and type of works, indicated that such costs are&#13;
about the same and minor difference may be due to quality control and extent of supervision;&#13;
(c)   It is difficult to measure the quantitative social, economic and environmental impact of SFD projects&#13;
in rural communities for two reasons. First, there is no base line data to determine the conditions prior to&#13;
project implementation. Second, it is costly and time consuming to survey the social, economic and&#13;
environmental conditions for each sub-project. Furthermore, the impact generated from the diverse types of&#13;
projects would produce varying and inconsistent results. Some data would depend on information obtained&#13;
from the beneficiaries and such data may not be reliable; therefore, the only objective assessment would&#13;
entail a qualitative evaluation to determine whether positive improvements would be enjoyed by&#13;
beneficiaries. To date, the SFD has conducted studies in ten governorates prior to project implementation,&#13;
and two studies following project completion (in Menoufiya and Gharbiya). The Gharbiya study, indicated&#13;
that beneficiary willingness to contribute to projects increased from 17 percent prior to project&#13;
implementation and 30 percent following project completion. The study farther indicated a change in&#13;
priorities as a result in a perceived changed in the economic benefits (beneficiary's satisfaction change to 87&#13;
percent for roads and 50 percent for water supply);&#13;
(d)    NGOs including local development associations (LDAs), are active participants in the PWP complete&#13;
sub-project cycle. The bulk of participating NGOs consist of social care (child and elderly) and social&#13;
development (women activities, literacy, and vocational training). The participation of NGOs and LDAs&#13;
ensure timely implementation of sub-projects, foster capacity building, and supervision of works; and&#13;
(e)    Theoretically, operations and maintenance are ensured within the budget of line ministries during&#13;
sub-project preparation and implementation. A similar commitment is obtained from the sponsoring&#13;
agencies and beneficiaries and spelt out in the framework agreement. In practice, the issue of sustainability&#13;
has not been tested. Nevertheless, given the current economic austerity being faced by the Government, the&#13;
availability of funds for O&amp;M has become questionable. Involving LDAs in O&amp;M should be encouraged&#13;
and incorporated into the framework agreements, in order to ensure community participation and stakeholder&#13;
commitment, especially given of the budgetary contractions.&#13;
PWP Procedures for Sub-Project Management&#13;
6.     The submission of the PWP sub-project proposal by a sponsoring agency marks the first stage of the sub-&#13;
project cycle. Govenorates develop a list of projects based on requests received from communities through district&#13;
offices. The SFD screens the list of projects and identifies eligible sub-projects based upon the established selection&#13;
criteria. The screening process involves an evaluation by a PWP Committee in the PWP department. Following&#13;
clearance, the proposal is presented to the SFD Executive Committee (SFD/EC) for final approval. The SFD/EC&#13;
approval is followed by a framework agreement signed by both parties, the SFD and the Sponsoring Agency. Prior&#13;
to sub-project implementation, the SFD appoints a project manager who assumes full responsibility for project&#13;
supervision (monitoring progress and making payments to Intermediary Agencies). Generally more than one&#13;
Intermediary Agency is involved at the governorate level (e.g., water supply department, roads department,&#13;
irrigation department, etc.) and agreements are established between each Intermediary Agency and the project&#13;
manager. The Intermediary Agency becomes the party responsible for contracting out the works to Executing&#13;
Agencies (local private contractors, NGOs, beneficiaries).&#13;
7.     The SFD tranches are forwarded directly to an account controlled by the project manager, who in turn&#13;
authorizes payments to Intermediary Agencies' accounts for payments to Executing Agencies (contractors).&#13;
Contractors are paid by Intermediary Agencies based on disbursement applications for works completed according&#13;
to the contractual agreements. Fund transfers are not made through the Sponsoring Agency (Govenorate).&#13;
8.     The SFD Regional Offices also monitor implementation and key sub-project implementation parameters&#13;
are recorded at SFD Headquarters by the Planning and Statistics Department. The PWP Department has developed&#13;
monitoring and evaluation indicators which recently have become operational. Substantial implementation of such&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Page 3 of 4&#13;
monitoring and assessment systems would take more time and would be better tested with the new projects.&#13;
Sponsoring and Intermediary Agencies will play a key role in self-generating such data at sub-project design and&#13;
during implementation.&#13;
Recommendations for PWP Component during Phase 11&#13;
9.     PWP would continue to give priority to low-income rural communities (80-90 percent) and some urban&#13;
slums with an emphasis on communities in Upper Egypt (60 percent of reserves). Subprojects will be designed to&#13;
integrate infrastructure with community development activities.  Targeting of beneficiaries follow the same&#13;
approach already adopted in the first phase of SFD. Needs assessment studies will be carried out to screen and&#13;
improve the design of subprojects. Sponsoring and Intermediary Agencies will play an active role in the design of&#13;
infrastructure, identification and design of monitoring parameters, and identification and evaluation of impact&#13;
assessment indicators.  Such monitoring and impact assessment data will be given to SFD for review and&#13;
processing. The findings of monitoring and impact assessment indicators will be used to evaluate project objectives&#13;
and introduce design changes.&#13;
10.    Efforts will be made to ensure more participation of LDAs, Private Voluntary Organizations (PVOs) and&#13;
Non-Governmental Organizations (NGOs), to ensure sustainability of sub-projects.&#13;
11.    The information provided below provides an estimate of fund allocation by sector for Phase 11 (SFD funds&#13;
would cover half of the requirements listed below, in which case allocation of funds would be pro-rated&#13;
accordingly):&#13;
(a)    environmental infrastructure LE 306 million (US$90 million) or about 43 percent;&#13;
(b)    potable water systems LE 170 million (US$50 million) or about 24 percent;&#13;
(c)    rural roads LE 119 million (US$35 million) or about 17 percent;&#13;
(d)    building rehabilitation LE 51 million (US$15 million) or about 7 percent;&#13;
(e)    O&amp;M fund of LE 34 million (US$10 million) or about 5 percent; and&#13;
(f)    project management &amp; supervision LE 27 million (US$8 million) or about 4 percent.&#13;
12.    Sewerage and sewage treatment systems, would focus on the provision of environmentally sound on-site&#13;
disposal of waste waters and domestic refuse. PWP staff will draw on the pilot biomass sub-project under design by&#13;
the Community Development Program which would be used in rural areas. This system consists of on-site&#13;
treatment of on-farm sewage, manure and organic food waste for biogas and sludge compost production for on-farm&#13;
use as fuel and fertilizer, respectively. The use of piped sewerage systems would be reserved for the exceptional&#13;
cases where ground water is shallow that precludes the use of on-site systems.&#13;
13.    Evaluation reports would be undertaken to assess the social and economic benefits, cost-effectiveness,&#13;
quality of supervision, technical aspects of design and quality of works, and adequate provisions for operation and&#13;
maintenance for sustainability. Future reports would review the technical aspects to a greater extent in order to&#13;
ensure conformity and suitability (i.e. verify materials quality and construction quality of roads, the design of&#13;
pavement and base for the traffic load, and drainage channels to protect the road embankment from erosion.&#13;
Furthermore, they would review the geometric design such as compatibility of slopes and curves with speed design,&#13;
and whether roads signs are adequate and strategically located to warn and inform the travelers).&#13;
14.    The SFD will explore the legal framework which would enable establishing O&amp;M units at the village level&#13;
to assume responsibility for the operation and maintenance of public services provided by the SFD. Legally, only&#13;
voluntary contributions could be raised by an NGO but no taxes or tariff as cost-recovery mechanism could be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Page 4 of 4&#13;
raised as such charges can only be made by an Authority (under the authority law) or the Ministry of Finance (under&#13;
the tax law). The SFD will explore practical alternatives such as amending the law or just simply working under the&#13;
law for NGOs. The SFD has agreed to include three essential components within the framework agreement,&#13;
namely: (i) establishing an O&amp;M unit at the village level, such as the LDAs or an NGO, and providing training on&#13;
management of O&amp;M and fund raising and management; (ii) developing a service contribution or charge to&#13;
generate revenues for operation and maintenance to be collected and managed by LDAs or NGOs; and (iii)&#13;
providing seed funds under the SFD funded project (about 5 percent of project cost) to establish a fund for operation&#13;
and maintenance of the works. The actual maintenance may be contracted out and paid by responsible LDAs or&#13;
NGOs with funds from the O&amp;M fund. The SFD would supervise compliance with the agreement periodically&#13;
(such as every six months or annually) to ensure that such arrangements are sustainable. The fundamental principle&#13;
of this approach would be to make beneficiaries aware of their responsibility to ensure sustainability of&#13;
infrastructure through contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 2: COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM&#13;
Background&#13;
1.     The Community Development Program  (CDP), an integral part of SFD was designed to finance&#13;
improvements in: (i) productive activities focusing on income and employment generation; and (ii) social&#13;
development activities to improve the delivery of essential services to poor communities. These objectives have&#13;
been achieved to a large extent, with CDP evolving to respond to community needs, in some instances by utilizing&#13;
innovative approaches. Through its integrated project activities, CDP has infused communities with an enhanced&#13;
level of social awareness and self-esteem, especially women. CDP represents an important vehicle for mobilizing&#13;
the energies and resources of community groups, local governments, NGOs, and the private sector by using a&#13;
participatory approach, thus leading to more sustainable projects. Stimulating community involvement and active&#13;
NGO participation in Egypt can be regarded as a dramatic transformation and departure from the reliance of&#13;
communities on the public sector for the provision of services. The promotion of self-help activities can be seen as&#13;
the cornerstone of CDP projects and an effective mechanism for addressing poverty alleviation.&#13;
2.     CDP's flexibility and decentralized approach allows it to exploit the diverse strengths of different actors, to&#13;
benefit from the geographical coverage that multiple organizations might be able to provide, and to finance projects&#13;
simultaneously in multiple sectors.&#13;
3.     This report draws upon field visits, interviews, data, and various documents collected in the field.&#13;
A. Outputs of CDP Operations&#13;
4.     Community Participation. The active involvement of community groups is evident in CDP projects,&#13;
where they are involved in project selection and design. Once communities have developed a sense of ownership of&#13;
a project, they have proven to be more willing to share in its financing and to ensure that it is well maintained and&#13;
properly operated. This statement has been clearly represented in a myriad of CDP projects in the governorate of&#13;
Qena, especially in the Toad project where the community was willing to mobilize resources to implement projects&#13;
as well as provide contributions aimed at assisting marginalized families attain basic services.&#13;
5.     Provision of Basic Social Services. CDP projects have been able to distribute resources to communities&#13;
previously underserved by government agencies or private-sector organizations. CDP activities focus on the&#13;
provision of health, education and training services to poor population groups. Health activities represent 21&#13;
percent of CDP's overall project portfolio. Activities eligible for funding by CDP are: (i) provision of supplies,&#13;
equipment and personnel for primary health care centers; (ii) immunization campaigns; (iii) mother and child&#13;
nutrition programs; and (iv) provision of supplies and equipment for child care centers. Funds were allocated to&#13;
rehabilitate and equip 46 clinics, conduct 569 health awareness campaigns and train 820 health personnel.&#13;
Beneficiaries interviewed in upper Egypt and Alexandria, confirmed the need for the provision of such services and&#13;
the unavailability of alternatives.&#13;
6.     Education and training comprised 42 percent of CDP activities. Activities eligible for funding include: (i)&#13;
short-term literacy programs; (ii) practical training programs; and (iii) community organization and leadership&#13;
training. Due to its success in responding to unmet demand, 35 percent of the education budget has gone towards&#13;
financing adult illiteracy projects. The Education and Training component has helped rehabilitate 187 classrooms,&#13;
establish 9,123 illiteracy classes, and train 9,241 individuals to teach illiteracy classes. In the area of vocational&#13;
training and related training, 28 training workshops have been equipped, and 8,369 individuals have benefited from&#13;
such activities. Communities expressed satisfaction with the education and training services provided through CDP&#13;
projects, and requested a continuation of such services.&#13;
7.     The pilot survey undertaken in Beni Suef and Minya indicate that access to education has improved&#13;
through the provision of the adult education programs. These courses are attended by various members of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 2 of 6&#13;
family, from all age groups. Discussions with beneficiaries highlighted their desire to enhance their income levels&#13;
and overall standard of living, a goal not deemed attainable prior to the introduction of the projects. The education&#13;
classes have afforded women the opportunity to learn basic skills such as mathematics, which in turn enabled them&#13;
to start small micro-enterprise businesses and supplement family income. Discussions with communities in upper&#13;
Egypt have indicated that vocational training has also played an important role in developing skills of young people&#13;
and afforded them employment opportunities.&#13;
8.      Employment Generation. Creating employment rapidly has been a primary objective of CDP projects.&#13;
The bulk of employment opportunities for low-income and unskilled labor have emerged as a result of labor-&#13;
intensive infrastructure projects. Infornation on the extent and cost of employment creation indicates that the 109&#13;
projects undertaken by CDP have generated 70,620 permanent jobs, and 18,152 temporary jobs both directly and&#13;
indirectly, at a cost of LE 147.5 million.' These figures reflect a close match between the expected outputs&#13;
(76,053 permanent and 35,000 temporary).&#13;
9.      The extension of credit, construction of schools, latrines or health centers stimulated demand for local&#13;
industry and absorbed a portion of the labor force in the selected communities. CDP encourages the use of labor-&#13;
intensive techniques in their projects, as well as the utilization of local resources. Communities visited in upper&#13;
Egypt emphasized the importance of employment generation activities that have materialized as a result of CDP&#13;
funded projects.&#13;
10.    Productive family activities have financed new and existing income generating schemes, involving the&#13;
establishment of small revolving funds for self-help productive activities and related training in management and&#13;
productive skills. To date, 29 percent of CDP funds have been allocated to the provision of credit programs given&#13;
to 27,657 direct beneficiaries- who would normally not have had access to funds or appropriate training required for&#13;
managing a business. Preliminary data from a pilot survey conducted in Beni Suef and Minya indicate that these&#13;
loans resulted in job creation and provided families with enhanced supplemental incomes.&#13;
11.    Credits have been used for working capital and equipment purchases, and range from LE 500 to LE 5,000.&#13;
With the average loan size averaging LE 1,000. At the inception of the project, interest on credits for productive&#13;
activities were 10 percent. Following discussions between the World Bank and SFD staff, a consensus was reached&#13;
on lowering the interest rate to 7 percent for the beneficiary. Repayment schedules vary depending on the size and&#13;
use of the credit, with two years being the typical repayment period. Collateral requirements require personal or&#13;
groups guarantees. Beneficiaries surveyed in the pilot projects in Beni Suef and Minya have expressed satisfaction&#13;
with the level of assistance established through this mechanism. Beneficiaries in Alexandria and upper Egypt and&#13;
have indicated a willingness to apply for future loans.&#13;
12.    Sharing of Information and Experiences. CDP projects have created avenues for cooperation between&#13;
various stakeholders.&#13;
(a)     Line Ministries. Projects proposed by line ministries are designed and prepared in conjunction with CDP&#13;
staff. This allows for a collaborative process and sharing of experiences. Furthermore, staff from the&#13;
public sector can learn and internalize CDP's partnership role with NGOs and local community groups,&#13;
thus leading to the adoption of a more participatory approach in project design and implementation. In&#13;
other instances, staff hired to work on CDP projects have been recruited to work in Ministries upon&#13;
completion of their assignments. It is envisaged that data collected by CDP can be utilized by the public&#13;
sector to allow for improved coordination, design and implementation of future projects.&#13;
(b)    NGOs. In order to respond to increasing demands, CDP has encouraged the formation of voluntary&#13;
clusterings. This approach aims at forging partnerships among large and small NGOs while expanding&#13;
These figures are provided by the CDP office in Cairo.&#13;
Loan applicants in many cases are members of large households. In many instances, the majority of family&#13;
members participate in productive activities, and thus the project has a positive multiplier effect.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 3 of 6&#13;
project reach and facilitating greater awareness of diverse views of stakeholders. The Red Crescent, Coptic&#13;
Evangelical Organization for Social Services, and CARITAS are some of the larger NGOs successfully&#13;
participating in this approach.&#13;
(c)    Communities. Meetings and visits among various community members aimed at sharing experiences and&#13;
establishing temporary twinning arrangements have resulted following the successful completion of CDP&#13;
activities in selected areas. This was evident in upper Egypt.&#13;
13.    Packaging of Projects. The design and implementation of standardized projects have facilitated quick and&#13;
efficient project implementation and has proven to be extremely effective in reaching the maximum number of&#13;
beneficiaries. This is particularly relevant in the adult literacy eradication projects which have been received&#13;
enthusiastically by 80 percent of the 26 govemorates. In fact, upon completion of Phase I of the program, requests&#13;
for additional programs have flooded the CDP office. These programs are well designed, and respond to community&#13;
needs in a manner that currently is not provided by the public sector. This is an instance where the Ministry of&#13;
Education can attempt to draw lessons in designing small and technically simple projects. Other packages to be&#13;
implemented by CDP include, upgrading PHC through the use of extension officers, development of health&#13;
emergency services, dental hygiene, and family programs.&#13;
14.    Stemming Rural-Urban Migration. The introduction of integrated projects within a community has a&#13;
positive impact in stemming rural-urban migration. Young people interviewed during the mission, expressed a&#13;
desire to remain in their respective communities given the availability of social services and employment&#13;
opportunities.&#13;
15.    Positive Externalities through Linkages of Projects (Integrated Projects). Combining a number of&#13;
components within a CDP project such adult illiteracy eradication projects with micro-enterprise activities has&#13;
resulted in increasing the level of awareness and understanding of communities, and afforded beneficiaries,&#13;
especially women, the opportunity to utilize basic reading and writing skills in managing their own business. An&#13;
improvement in the status of women also reveals their desire to have fewer children.&#13;
16.    NGOs. NGOs play a significant role in the operations of CDP activities (75 percent of the projects are&#13;
implemented by NGOs), the active participation of both national and international NGOs, as well as religious&#13;
organizations, in programs and projects sponsored and financed by the Govemment and external assistance agencies&#13;
is unprecedented. The CDP has developed a positive working relationship with several NGOs by overcoming their&#13;
initial lack of trust and skepticism, which was based in part on many NGOs' ideological opposition to the&#13;
Government's economic adjustment program. This was achieved by establishing transparent and efficient operating&#13;
methods, engaging in active, and continuous dialogue with the NGOs.&#13;
17.    Given the NGOs close association with community groups, involving them in the planning, preparation,&#13;
implementation and operation of projects has been essential to the success in implementation of CDP projects.&#13;
NGOs have also participated actively in project supervision, particularly in areas where the latter have been&#13;
involved for extensive periods.&#13;
18.    Due to the limited capacity of smaller NGOs, the CDP program has provided technical assistance. In&#13;
selected governorates in the Saiid, training NGOs in proposal preparation ranges from 3-5 months. The use of&#13;
"clustering NGOs" has been recently applied in order to meet the increasing demand being generated by&#13;
communities This method entails involving a primary NGO, with a cluster of satellite or smaller NGOs. The&#13;
philosophy behind this approach reflects CDPs emphasis on capacity building. Training is provided to the primary&#13;
NGO, as well as the smaller NGOs. Following completion of training, the primary NGO assumes responsibility of&#13;
monitoring and supervising the activities of the satellite NGOs. In this manner, accountability is maintained within&#13;
the context of NGOs, and dispersed projects are addressed through the outreach of satellite NGOs.&#13;
19.    Local Government Involvement.  CDP projects have laid the groundwork for decentralizing the&#13;
responsibility for small-scale infrastructure investment to local governments. This has been achieved by involving&#13;
local governments in prioritizing, preparing and supervising the execution of projects with inputs from their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 4 of 6&#13;
respective communities. As sponsors of projects, they have participated in contract management and assumed&#13;
responsibility for maintenance and operating costs of CDP projects. Some of the following factors have contributed&#13;
to the success in financing a relatively large program implemented primarily by the local government. First, most&#13;
projects financed have been small and technically simple. They were relatively easy to prepare and could be rapidly&#13;
appraised, contracted and executed. Second, CDP provided blueprints to the sponsoring local governments to&#13;
facilitate construction and ensure that projects met appropriate quality standards.  This is evident in health&#13;
awareness campaigns and adult illiteracy eradication projects. Third, CDP staff supervised project execution jointly&#13;
with representatives of the sponsoring local governments. Fourth, CDP through it's regional offices kept its lines of&#13;
communication with local government representatives open and provided them with information on the status of&#13;
CDP financed projects on a regular basis. Finally, while willing to provide technical assistance and advice,&#13;
especially to the poorest governorates, CDP has discouraged elaborate development planning exercises.&#13;
20.    By involving community groups in project selection and implementation, CDP has built local capacity for&#13;
municipal self-help efforts. Neighborhood funds groups for local improvement have been created to finance small&#13;
projects, such as drainage, health awareness campaigns, and the provision of some social services. Through its&#13;
innovative and flexible mechanisms, CDP stimulated the formation of partnerships between local authorities and&#13;
beneficiaries in the selection, implementation, and maintenance of these projects. This could lay the groundwork for&#13;
generating cost sharing and partial or full recovery on the part of the beneficiaries.&#13;
21.    The CDP could create the basis for local governments to assume more difficult functions, such as&#13;
stimulating local economic development and creating a broader local tax base. Given the high concentration of&#13;
poor communities in urban areas, the importance of strengthening local governments' capacities and increasing the&#13;
involvement of community groups in efforts to improve the infrastructure and delivery of social services and&#13;
encourage self-help efforts is critical.&#13;
22.    Sustainability and Cost Recovery. Soliciting agencies are requested to incorporate mechanisms to be&#13;
used for cost recovery, operations and maintenance in project proposals. The CDP evaluates the institutional&#13;
capacity of the soliciting agency and feasibility of the proposed mechanism to ensure proper operation and&#13;
maintenance. Operations and maintenance costs are allocated within each line ministries budget, therefore, projects&#13;
implemented by the public sector would be ensured a budget for such activities.  Projects involving direct&#13;
community implementation institute mechanisms to recover sufficient funds through modest fees and contribution&#13;
in kind to cover costs of operations and maintenance. CDP projects also include technical assistance for operations&#13;
and maintenance. This approach is successfully being implemented in certain villages in upper Egypt. Certain&#13;
projects such as adult illiteracy eradication do not require financial assistance beyond the life of the project. In most&#13;
other cases, it is imperative for CDP to monitor project sustainability beyond project implementation stage.&#13;
23.    Women's Participation. CDP activities have targeted and responded to needs which reflect the integral&#13;
role of women in poverty alleviation efforts in Egypt. As productive agents, women's participation in income&#13;
generating activities represent a crucial part of the survival strategy of poor households. Women have increasingly&#13;
shifted away from traditional agricultural into commercial activities, either in the selling of agricultural products or&#13;
in trading of urban goods and services. The status of women and their empowerment in their communities has been&#13;
dramatically enhanced through the use of a participatory approach and the provision of social and productive&#13;
services. CDP activities involve women representatives on the board of local committees. To raise the productivity&#13;
of women's activities, CDP has expanded access to basic education and training, credit and improved infrastructure&#13;
such as markets and roads. To date 50 percent of CDP projects have financed projects of these types to low-income&#13;
women.&#13;
24.    Apart from their increasingly important role in the economic well-being of poor families, women have&#13;
traditionally played the central role in the development of Egypt's human resource base. CDP's investments in&#13;
health and nutrition have addressed the precarious health conditions of Egyptian women and children, aimed at&#13;
complementing the Ministry of Health's efforts in reducing maternal and infant mortality. In addition, the provision&#13;
of safe drinking water and sanitation facilities has also improved the health status of women.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 5 of 6&#13;
25.    Private Sector Involvement. Private contractors have carried out a large number of projects financed by&#13;
CDP. The significant involvement of NGOs in CDP operations is one way of involving the private sector. Staff&#13;
involved in CDP operations have been recruited from the private sector, a key element in the success of CDP&#13;
activities. In addition, private sector consultants have also been recruited to supervise project execution, secure&#13;
pertinent information in a cost effective manner, and audit CDP/SFD operations.&#13;
26.    Expeditious Project Processing and Flexibility. Given the flexibility inherent in SFD activities, project&#13;
processing and implementation time span have been very reasonable, especially in comparison to the delivery of&#13;
services through the public sector. The CDP interventions have helped promote incremental decentralization by&#13;
strengthening the role of regional representatives as project sponsors and has been instrumental in forging&#13;
partnerships with various members of society who traditionally have undertaken activities in isolation.&#13;
27.    Administrative Efficiency and Operating Costs of the CDP. Overall administrative costs of SFD&#13;
activities are 10 percent, comparable to most social investment funds which average 8 to 13 percent of their annual&#13;
commitments, upon achieving full output. CDP consumes I percent of administrative costs. At its peak, CDP has&#13;
approved 109 projects since its inception, worth about LE 226 million (LE 147.5 million have been disbursed).&#13;
This scale of operation has been achieved using a staff of 12 (CDP Cairo office). The speed, flexibility and&#13;
effectiveness with which CDP promoted and approved a large number of projects has helped it in rapidly&#13;
establishing its credibility.&#13;
B.     Next Steps - Challenges Facing CDP&#13;
28.    CDP should continue implementing its mandate and focusing on community and NGO participation with a&#13;
continued emphasis on capacity building and targeting of women, the poor, and unemployed. Increased donor&#13;
coordination during a second phase could serve to facilitate project implementation. The following points should be&#13;
addressed during Phase II of the Social Fund for Development Project in order to enhance its operations.&#13;
29.    Project Packaging. The adoption of project packaging and/or blueprint approach should be encouraged in&#13;
relevant projects (i.e. education and health), as should the integrated project approach. Information on successful&#13;
packaging approaches should be disseminated to the relevant ministries.&#13;
30.    Sharing of Experiences. Success stories should be documented and circulated among regional, satellite&#13;
offices, government agencies, NGOs and community groups in order to allow for replication of these activities&#13;
when relevant. This would allow for the development and transfer of effective methods for planning and project&#13;
implementation.&#13;
31.    Project Sustainability and Operations. The issue of project sustainability should be closely monitored&#13;
following the completion of project implementation. Mechanisms should be developed to respond to projects that&#13;
are meeting sustainability challenges. The CDP will start, initially on an experimental basis, a system of assuring&#13;
long-term sustainability of projects through setting up users groups to raise contributions towards long-term&#13;
operations. The SFD would start by providing matching grants to these users groups on a downward sliding basis,&#13;
eventually phasing the grants out. The success of this approach, which seems to be only one feasible, is not assured&#13;
because the CDP works in the poorest areas and the beneficiaries have little cash to offer - though they may be able&#13;
to make contributions in labor.&#13;
32.    Market Orientation for CDP Microenterprise Programs:  There have been cases where CDP&#13;
microenterprise programs have supported sub-projects which make little business sense, e.g. loans for handicrafts&#13;
for which the market is already saturated or training in skills for which there is little demand. This has led to default&#13;
in some microenterprise loan repayments and the situation needs to be corrected. It is recommended that during&#13;
Phase II, attention be given to marketability as is already done in the case of the EDP. This is already happening in&#13;
the case of the more experienced NGOs and should be generalized broadly.&#13;
33.    Supervision and Monitoring. The CDP has paid limited attention to supervision and monitoring. This&#13;
shortcoming can be attributed to the emphasis being placed on quick disbursements and the allocation of staff for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Page 6 of 6&#13;
this purpose. This issue is currently being addressed, and monitoring indicators are being included in the appraisal&#13;
and evaluation forms. With the existence of 10 regional and 6 satellite offices monitoring and supervision will&#13;
become a primary focus during Phase 11 of the SFD. Other aspects that require strengthening are impact evaluation&#13;
and beneficiary assessments. In addition, market studies as well as an evaluation of the fund's operations should be&#13;
undertaken to identify strengths and weaknesses of CDP and the conditions that facilitate or hinder performance.&#13;
34.    Targeting. Funding of community development activities has been targeted based on the original poverty&#13;
map developed by SFD in 1992. Efforts are underway for SFD to update its poverty map and targeting mechanism&#13;
in order to reflect the evolving nature of SFD, and the current patterns of poverty in Egypt. The poverty map should&#13;
be made available during the early stages of Phase 11.&#13;
35.    Decentralization. The SFD is reviewing its decentralization efforts and a delineation of responsibilities&#13;
between the main office and the field offices is currently being finalized. A more decentralized approach in the area&#13;
of project approval will allow for further flexibility in CDP operations given the increasing demand being generated&#13;
from communities.&#13;
36.    Resistance from Ministries to Work with NGOs. This has lead to temporary delays. In response,&#13;
innovative approaches are being developed to create modalities for collaboration between the public sector and&#13;
NGOs. These approaches should be documented and success cases should be circulated to stakeholders.&#13;
38.    Lack of Capacity in NGOs. Innovative training mechanisms are being developed to provide quicker&#13;
capacity building (i.e., creating apprentice programs, instituting a junior manager within an NGO with requisite&#13;
skills for capacity building), as are information-sharing and networking activities between larger and smaller NGOs.&#13;
These efforts should be evaluated in light of their sustainability and effectiveness.&#13;
39.    Limited Participation in Urban Areas. An emphasis on promoting a participatory approach in urban&#13;
areas needs to be encouraged. A review of success cases using participatory approaches in rural areas could provide&#13;
relevant examples.&#13;
40.    Coordinating Projects between different Departments in SFD. Coordinated efforts to synchronize&#13;
activities between various departments undertaking multi-sectoral projects needs to be streamlined.&#13;
41.    Limit Off-Budget Financing to Public Sector Agencies. CDP activities should provide temporary relief&#13;
to public agencies by financing priority projects while public agencies undergo structural reform. Off-budget&#13;
financing for ministries or public agencies should be gradually reduced, by placing a cap on the amount of funds&#13;
available to public agencies. This approach should be implemented in order to reduce public reliance on the social&#13;
fund for off-budget financing.&#13;
42.    Operating Manual. A revision of the Operating Manual should be undertaken to reflect lessons learned&#13;
and allow for future streamlining of activities between the CDP main office, regional and satellite offices.&#13;
43.    Conflicting Donor Interests.  Lack of synergy between donor objectives has resulted in sending&#13;
conflicting signals. There is a need for donors to streamline their objectives and their disbursement schedules in&#13;
order to allow for smoother operations .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3: ENTERPRISE DEVELOPMENT PROGRPM&#13;
Introduction&#13;
I.     The following Annex provides an overview of issues pertaining to the sustainability of the Enterprise&#13;
Development Program (EDP) of SFD. First, the current status and performance of the EDP is described followed&#13;
by a discussion of how sustainability and cost coverage could be achieved over time. This discussion includes an&#13;
overview of the basic premises underlying sustainability which were adopted by SFD during appraisal and which&#13;
need also be adopted by the Government of Egypt and donors. Finally, the steps to taken towards long term&#13;
sustainability of EDP are discussed. These include the establishment of a task force to work on a feasibility study&#13;
and business plan for EDP sustainability to be presented at the Donor Meeting in April 1996, and a redesign of&#13;
current features of the program that worked in the past but that will inhibit sustainability in the future.&#13;
Enterprise Development Program: Current Status&#13;
2.      The Enterprise Development Program is one of the core programs of the Social Fund for Development.&#13;
The objective of EDP is to create jobs for unemployed people and other disadvantaged groups through the&#13;
development and support of new and existing businesses. The EDP provides entrepreneurs with credit (mainly&#13;
through banks) and business services such as training, business counseling, support with business plan preparation&#13;
and marketing support. In addition, it is engaged in the development of new innovative sectoral programs such as&#13;
silk-production and fish-farms. Under EDP 120,000 permanent and 40,000 temporary jobs were created.&#13;
3.      Up to December 1995, the EDP credit department has lent over LE 500 million to 5 public sector banks&#13;
that on-lend to new and existing businesses. All loans were for low-income beneficiaries. Sub-loan repaymenit is&#13;
satisfactory and the banks started repaying the SFD (see table I for an overview of the performance of EDP's main&#13;
financial intermediaries). The banks recently signed on for another LE 250 million. In effect, the EDP credit&#13;
department has acted as a wholesale bank (APEX) that delivers credit to small businesses through retail banks.&#13;
4.      The success of EDP's credit program could not have been possible without the department for business&#13;
services that provided thousands of new and existing businesses with support. These services are delivered eith.r&#13;
directly by EDP or through selected NGOs receiving grants to deliver service packages. The staff of the EDP works&#13;
intensively with these NGOs to help them develop their institutional capacity to work with small businesses.&#13;
Entrepreneurs who use EDP services increase their chances of obtaining a bank loan and learn to better manage&#13;
their businesses. In effect, the EDP business services department has acted as a wholesale organization that delivers&#13;
valuable services to entrepreneurs through retail NGOs/PVOs.&#13;
The Opportunity&#13;
5.      The EDP is in an unique position to become sustainable and to achieve operational and possibly financial&#13;
costs coverage over the next few years by gradually charging fees for its services. The dynamics of this process are&#13;
described in the graph below. Currently the banks and the entrepreneurs do not pay any fee though they receive a&#13;
valuable service. Banks receive "bankable business plans" and the banks' clients are actively supported by EDP&#13;
(monitoring, problem solving) also after they receive a bank loan. This service delivery is implicit and the value is&#13;
not recognized. Like any other APEX type operation, the EDP could charge banks a percentage fee on costs of&#13;
loan funds to cover its costs of delivering these implicit services. On an outstanding portfolio of LE 750 million, a I&#13;
to 2 percent fee would generate LE 7.5 to 15 million on an annual basis. Also, the EDP could charge the&#13;
entrepreneurs a low flat fee for training and other assistance and a success fee if the entrepreneur receives a loan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 2 of 7&#13;
THE PATH TOWARDS SUSTAINABIIrrY&#13;
Grants from Donors&#13;
Performance Contracts&#13;
r EDP Credit                                       EDP Non-Financial Services&#13;
Operational Costs                                    Opera toal0 costs&#13;
,,,                                  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Grants:&#13;
c;   '" I  @           AZ I                                        .D    |  !  Performance Contracts&#13;
a0Promotion&#13;
o Inst. BLD&#13;
osBeneficiary services&#13;
o Monitoring&#13;
BANK                     BANK                  Fee               NGOs / PVOs&#13;
|  Operational Costs _  0   L _  Operatinal Costs                   Operational Costs&#13;
c                   ~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
L-3 -j 1       -       LB                             _L                    B&#13;
LB1 BX          I B            B I0!C  C B1C &#13;
6       The unique opportunity exists to transform  EDP into a specialized small business support and finance&#13;
organization comprised of two complementary functions: the first focusing on project identification and definition,&#13;
offering technical support and marketing services; and the second specialized in offering financially engineered&#13;
credit packages. This organization would act like a wholesale agency providing loans for on-lending to banks and&#13;
technical service packages through NGOs/PVOs. The organization could have its own Steering Committee under a&#13;
common Board of Directors. It would be managed as a private sector organization but any surpluses would be re-&#13;
invested in the small business development programs.  During Phase 11, the organization would operate&#13;
independently but within the SFD structure. This would entail the operation of a separate cost and revenue&#13;
accounting system for EDP. The current MIS system appears capable to accommodate this change.&#13;
7.      Capitalization for this institution could come from the following sources of funds: (i) EU counterpart funds&#13;
currently allocated to SFD; (ii) untied donor funds currently allocated to SFD; (iii) re-flows i.e., the banks'&#13;
repayments of interest and principal; and (iv) new donor funds under Phase 11. Over time, this small business&#13;
support and finance organization could mobilize resources on local, regional, and international capital markets.&#13;
8.      The organization would keep its development mandate and could use surpluses from one project to finance&#13;
another core project to achieve certain development objectives. It could also negotiate donor funds -- based on&#13;
performance contracts -- to continue delivering services that are needed from a development perspective but cannot&#13;
generate (sufficient) surpluses to cover their costs.&#13;
9.      The corporate and organizational structure would be linked to the other programs of SFD; the Community&#13;
Development Program, the Public Works Program, and the Human Resource Development Program. Common&#13;
operational functions (i.e., office administration, personnel, accounting, MIS, treasury, legal and audit, and GM-&#13;
secretariat services) could be provided as contracted services by sections or secretariats within the EDP-&#13;
Organization for CDP and other units, which handle project-type business rather than uniform daily transactions.&#13;
Thus, the cost and quality advantages of specialized skills within the EDP-unit could be shared economically by the&#13;
other program units. As all units would probably operate under a joint Board of Directors and under partly&#13;
identically staffed Steering Committees, the normal policy and strategic and controlling instruments could ensure&#13;
the close cooperation of the management of all the Program units.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 3 of 7&#13;
10.     The transformation of EDP towards sustainability could be achieved by an evolutionary restructuring&#13;
process of the current legal and organizational structure. Any restructuring and streamlining process would be&#13;
based on a thorough feasibility study demonstrating the viable options to prepare for the following decision steps of&#13;
SFD management, for proposals to the Government of Egypt, and for negotiations with the Donors. In the following&#13;
section, some of the basic premises of sustainability that would be incorporated in the feasibility study are&#13;
discussed.&#13;
The Basic Premises of Sustainability&#13;
11.    In order to achieve sustainability of the EDP and also enhance the prospects of a sustainable SFD&#13;
operation, the following basic premises were adopted by the SFD:&#13;
*    The EDP will use its current achievements (outstanding portfolio and beneficiaries reached) as an important&#13;
basis to develop sustainability now and in the future, which will go beyond the lifetime of Phase 11.&#13;
*    Sustainability cannot be achieved overnight; a medium term time frame of two to four years is needed to&#13;
enable the organization to cover its costs.&#13;
*    To achieve its development objectives, continued donor funding is required in the following areas: (i) funding&#13;
(on a decreasing basis) for the EDP overhead during the process of transition; this funding could be based on&#13;
EDP meeting certain performance standards that are raised over time; (ii) funding to enable the organization to&#13;
fulfill its socio-economic development mandate through transparent subsidies based on performance contracts;&#13;
and (iii) funding (on a decreasing matching grant basis) to enhance the viability, efficiency and outreach of&#13;
EDP's intermediaries (banks and NGOs) because the EDP's viability depends upon that of its intermediaries.&#13;
*   The organization will have a capital basis that is sufficient to serve its projected tasks now and in the future; an&#13;
initial capitalization of no less than LE 250 million is required. Preliminary calculations indicate that the&#13;
organization could leverage this capital and could possibly channel loans to small businesses up to LE 1.0&#13;
billion in two to three years.&#13;
*    The EDP needs to ensure (legally) that it has sufficient funds for initial capitalization to make sustainability&#13;
and independence feasible and realistic within the agreed time frame. The EDP would legally own these funds&#13;
irrespective of any developments which may influence the nature of SFD and/or its constituent core programs.&#13;
-   Since the viability of EDP is dependent on that of its intermediaries (banks and NGOs), the selection of (and&#13;
investment in) intermediaries would be based on their meeting performance standards of outreach,&#13;
creditworthiness, and financial soundness.&#13;
*    The EDP will over time charge fees for its services from banks, NGOs, and beneficiaries. Since EDP clients&#13;
will only pay for these services as long as they value them, this will constitute the basic test of market demand&#13;
and will ensure that EDP will deliver those services that are needed and tailored to demand.&#13;
*   The banks will only continue "purchasing" the EDP services if small business lending is financially attractive&#13;
for them. In this context, they should be free to negotiate the price of on-lending taking into account risk,&#13;
costs of small business lending, and a reasonable margin, without passing on costs of inefficiency to the final&#13;
borrower.&#13;
*   The EDP will need more flexibility in targeting and developing terms and conditions for its services (credit&#13;
and technical) to intermediaries and to new and existing businesses.&#13;
*    The EDP financial operations should preserve the real money value of its funds and it should hence charge at&#13;
least real positive interest rates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 4 of 7&#13;
*   United donor support for and incentives to EDP and SFD are needed to help it become sustainable.&#13;
Steps towards Sustainability&#13;
12.    The following next steps are recommended: (i) establish a task force to develop a strategy and business&#13;
plan on how to reach sustainability and how to manage the restructuring process; (ii) legally ensure that EDP can&#13;
maintain already allocated donor funds; (iii) redesign certain current features of EDP that worked in the past to&#13;
"open up" the small business lending market but that may inhibit future sustainability; and (iv) set up an&#13;
independent cost and revenue accounting system for EDP within SFD's MIS.&#13;
I.     Task Force&#13;
13.    The SFD has established a task force, comprising of key decision makers in the Fund and external&#13;
consultants, to develop a strategy and business plan to achieve EDP sustainability within the context of a SFD&#13;
operation. This document will constitute the basis for Phase II and donor negotiations. A first draft is expected to be&#13;
ready by mid-February 1996 and the final version by the end of March 1996. Representatives of the EU and IDA&#13;
are advising this task force. See Attachment I for draft terms of reference for the task force.&#13;
14.    This feasibility study will include projections on the achievable targets within the main Programs or&#13;
activities of SFD:&#13;
(a)    Development of EDP loan business (credit volume targets for sectors and areas, budgets for&#13;
technical assistance and institution building, overhead costs, real value capital maintenance requirements&#13;
and risk analysis, volume of funds to be mobilized from donors, Governments, savings institutions, and&#13;
domestic or foreign banks, surplus to be generated to contribute to non-income generating social activities&#13;
of SFD, etc.)&#13;
(b)    Realistic funding volume generated or contracted with donors (grants, etc.) for subsidized social&#13;
functions and activities such as CDP, etc.&#13;
(c)    According to the current mission and functions and the achieved business volume in the EDP&#13;
field, the feasibility study should evaluate realistic options for a corporate and organizational structure that&#13;
incorporates future legal and bank technology requirements.&#13;
II.    Legally ensure that EDP can maintain already allocated donor funds.&#13;
15.    As mentioned earlier, EDP funding for capitalization could come from counterpart EU funds, untied donor&#13;
funds, and fund re-flows. Currently, over LE 750 million is on-lent to banks that are just starting to repay the fund.&#13;
Formally, the SFD has a repayment obligation for these funds to the Government of Egypt which could (partially)&#13;
free SFD from its repayment obligation and permit it to use the funds for capitalization of an EDP finance&#13;
organization.&#13;
III.    Redesign current features of the EDP&#13;
16.    At the time of design and implementation of EDP, the main (donor and government) emphasis was on&#13;
disbursement in order to create jobs without regard to sustainability. Hence, EDP is not at fault for some&#13;
weaknesses that were a result of the initial design; rather the staff of the EDP should be commended for its&#13;
achievements within such a short time frame and within a complex set of (often) conflicting (donor) demands. In&#13;
the future, the following characteristics of the EDP as it is currently operating may inhibit sustainability and hence&#13;
should be addressed:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 5 of 7&#13;
17.    Selection of Intermediaries. Currently, public sector banks are the main intermediaries for on-lending.&#13;
Their performance varies widely and they did not intrinsically change the way they do business. This is especially&#13;
apparent in the fact that they still require high collateral and that repayments schedules do not incorporate cash flow&#13;
dynamics. Banks will be the main income generator for the independent and sustainable EDP program, and they&#13;
will only continue "buying the EDP services and funds" if small business lending represents an attractive&#13;
opportunity for them. In this context, banks should be free to determine the price of on-lending without getting a&#13;
license to pass on costs of inefficiency to the final borrower (see below). Banks may also require institutional&#13;
support to help them become better and more efficient small business lenders.&#13;
18.    For Phase 11, the following changes are recommended: (i) widening the range of intermediaries to include&#13;
private banks, leasing companies and Islamic banks; (ii) selection of banks based on performance standards (or in&#13;
case of new intermediaries based on proven top management commitment to this field and a credible business plan&#13;
to serve this target group); (iii) provision of institutional support (on a decreasing matching grant basis) to enable&#13;
banks to become more efficient, reach volume and reduce risks.&#13;
19.    More flexibility in Targeting. It is strongly recommended that EDP reviews its targeting mechanisms.&#13;
Entrepreneurs that start or manage new and existing businesses do not necessarily have to be very poor or come&#13;
from certain disadvantaged groups such as graduates or unemployed public sector employees. The main objective&#13;
is that new businesses are created or that existing small businesses grow. Also, international experience indicates&#13;
that the unemployed do not necessarily make good entrepreneurs. More flexible target requirements will lead to&#13;
more potential entrepreneurs whose businesses will create jobs possibly employing number of disadvantaged&#13;
groups.&#13;
20.    More flexible Sub-loan design. Sub-loan terms and conditions should focus on enhancing flexibility to&#13;
better meet the entrepreneurs' needs and to ensure viability of intermediaries. Attention should be given to: (i) the&#13;
definition of micro and small businesses, taking into account sectoral differences; (ii) broadening the permitted&#13;
purposes (uses) of the sub-loans; (iii) increasing the loan ceiling (for instance up to 10 percent of the banks' SFD&#13;
portfolio) to accommodate growth of existing EDP clients and to allow for increased demand for larger loans of new&#13;
clients; loan ceilings could be changed yearly according to inflation; (iv) varying grace periods and maturities&#13;
according to the project cash flow and purpose of the loan; (v) pricing of the sub-loans according to project risks&#13;
and costs of making the sub-loan; (vi) providing incentives to banks to accept more flexible collateral; and (vii)&#13;
recognizing subsidies whenever to ensure they are transparent to banks, entrepreneurs, and donors.&#13;
IV. Set up an independent cost and revenue accounting system for EDP&#13;
21.    The current SFD MIS appears to be capable to account for EDP cost and revenues separately within the&#13;
SFD structure. Establishing an independent system will enable EDP to better understand its cost and revenue&#13;
dynamics. It will be linked to an annual (or bi-annual) budgeting process that will be used as a management tool for&#13;
strategic and operational decision making.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 6 of 7&#13;
Attachment 1: Terms of Reference Task Force&#13;
Develop a model to determine financial dynamics and minimum capitalization needed as well as non-financial&#13;
interventions and entrepreneurial needs and their costs. The following steps are considered essential to&#13;
determine the model:&#13;
*   Current costs and revenue flows. Analyze the current direct and indirect (overhead) costs of EDP. Make a&#13;
distinction between costs incurred for investment in intermediaries, development of services packages and&#13;
service delivery (credit and non-financial services). Identify those services that could generate revenues,&#13;
making a distinction between services that could (i) fully recover their costs of delivery, (ii) partially recover&#13;
their costs of delivery and services, and (iii) services that should be considered as non-recoverable investment&#13;
in development for which the costs incurred should be considered overhead.&#13;
*   Assessment of future development needs. Analyze the future social economic development objectives that&#13;
EDP wishes to achieve within the next five years; identify specific programs to be undertaken (or continued)&#13;
and the expected costs of doing so.&#13;
*   Assessment of banks' demand for sources of on-lending. This analysis should include the demand from&#13;
current and potential new intermediaries. It should also include a cash flow analysis of funds re-flowing that&#13;
can be re-lent and new funds needed for on-lending. The absorption capacity of the intermediaries should also&#13;
be taken into account. Determine the costs of EDP's delivery of these financial services and fees that can be&#13;
charged for the delivery.&#13;
*   Assessment of entrepreneurs demand for non-financial services. Analyze the entrepreneurs' demand for&#13;
non-financial services, assess costs of the delivery of these services and determine a possible fee structure.&#13;
*   Assessment of institutional development needs of NGOs and banks. Assess the needs for institutional&#13;
development of EDP's intermediaries to enable them to increase efficiency and outreach. Assess cost of these&#13;
needs.&#13;
Development of the model based on scenarios. Use the information obtained above as input for a financial model&#13;
to determine optimal capitalization needed and financial dynamics for a period of five years. The model should&#13;
incorporate varying assumptions on: (i) fees that can be charged over time; (ii) risks of non-repayment by financial&#13;
intermediaries of funds for on-lending; (iii) demand for financial and non-financial services; and (iv) inflation. The&#13;
model should also show increased cost coverage and sustainability over time and should identify the financing gaps&#13;
for each year. The financing gap should make a distinction in financing needed for overhead coverage, investment&#13;
in intermediaries, investment in service development and delivery of services that cannot be fully recovered.&#13;
Assess the needs for continued donor funding for next five years. Based on the outcomes of the financial model&#13;
under different scenarios, make an assessment of donor funding needed for the next five years identifying in detail&#13;
for what categories donor funding is needed (overhead, investment in intermediaries, services that cannot fully&#13;
recover their costs, certain programs to achieve social and economic development objectives). For each category&#13;
determine monitoring indicators that could be used as a basis for performance contracts with donors.&#13;
Organizational and legal structures. Determine the optimal organizational and legal structures of EDP. This&#13;
would include: (i) the optimal legal form required for the small business development and finance institution; (ii)&#13;
description of management instruments such as Board of Directors, Steering Committees, executive management,&#13;
their respective tasks and responsibilities; (iii) staffing requirements; (iv) reward and incentive systems; (v)&#13;
operational procedures; and (vi) budgeting process (as control tool).&#13;
The transition process. Prepare a phased-in transition plan. For each phase, describe in detail objectives to be&#13;
achieved, how these will be achieved and how progress will be measured and monitored.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Page 7 of 7&#13;
Table 1.: Performance of EDP's main financial Intermediaries&#13;
PBDAC&#13;
- total onlending (rounded)                        LE 50 million&#13;
- total number of sub-borrowers (rounded)          5,000&#13;
- female borrowers (rounded)                        1,100 (22,0 percent)&#13;
- average loan size                                LE 10,000&#13;
- liquidated debt (on first batch of LE 32 million)  20.7 percent&#13;
- portfolio at Risk (at least one missed payment)   2.5 percent&#13;
NBE (National Bank of Egypt)&#13;
- total onlending (rounded)                       LE 205 million&#13;
- total number of sub-borrowers (rounded)         12,400&#13;
- female borrowers (rounded)                       3,200 (25,8 percent)&#13;
- average loan size                               LE 16,000&#13;
- liquidated debt (on first batch of 53 million)   8.6 percent&#13;
- portfolio at Risk (at least one missed payment)  8.0 percent&#13;
Bank of Alexandria&#13;
- total onlending (rounded)                       LE 85 million&#13;
- total number of sub-borrowers                    3,800&#13;
- female borrowers (rounded)                        680 (17.8 percent)&#13;
- average loan size                               LE 12,500&#13;
- liquidated debt (on first batch of 40 million)   3.5 percent&#13;
- portfolio at Risk (at least one missed payment)  1.5 percent&#13;
Banque du Caire&#13;
- total onlending (rounded)                       LE 82 million&#13;
- total number of sub-borrowers (rounded)          3,700&#13;
- female borrowers (rounded)                        830 (22.4 percent)&#13;
- average loan size                               LE 22,100&#13;
- liquidated debt (on first batch of 30 million    5.4 percent&#13;
- portfolio at Risk (at least one missed payment))  14.5 percent&#13;
Misr Bank&#13;
- total onlending (rounded)                        LE 102 million&#13;
- total number of sub-borrowers (rounded)          3,450&#13;
- female borrowers (rounded)                         680 (19.7 percent)&#13;
- average loan size                                LE 30,000&#13;
- liquidated debt (on first batch of 50 million)    3.4 percent&#13;
- portfolio at Risk (at least one missed payment)  11.0 percent&#13;
Notes:&#13;
1. Data exclude lending programs for cattle raising&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 4: HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM&#13;
A. Background and Phase I - Labor Mobility Program&#13;
Background&#13;
I.     In recent years, the growth rate of employment in Egypt has not kept pace with labor force growth leading&#13;
to increased unemployment. A recent survey indicates that the unemployment rate was about 20.5 percent in 1993,&#13;
and more than 80 percent of those unemployed were graduates from university and technical secondary schools,&#13;
whose levels of skills were not relevant to the market needs. This skill mismatch was largely due to the poor quality&#13;
of both training and education.&#13;
2.     Egypt has a large number of public sector enterprises, and many of which continue to make losses, partially&#13;
due to over-staffing. Research shows that the level of redundant workers in public sector enterprises ranges from 30&#13;
to 40 percent. Based on the results, it has been projected that these redundant workers would be laid off as many&#13;
more public sector enterprises are expected to be privatized in coming years.&#13;
3.     In order to absorb these redundant workers and to provide job opportunities to unemployed graduates, the&#13;
expansion of the private sector is indispensable. Domestic enterprises will soon face strong competitive pressures&#13;
from the trade liberalization resulting from Egypt's accession to the World Trade Organization and its Free Trade&#13;
Treaty with the European Union.&#13;
Phase I - Labor Mobility Program&#13;
4.     The main objective of Phase I of Labor Mobility Program (LMP) was to focus on redeployment of workers&#13;
in public sector enterprises through technical assistance. The technical assistance included: (i) upgrading workers'&#13;
skills through retraining; and (ii) preparing workers for alternative jobs. In addition, the program also aimed to&#13;
provide retraining and placement of unemployed graduates.&#13;
5.     In order to facilitate labor mobility of public enterprises, LMP worked with three public sector enterprises,&#13;
and SFD provided assistance to 3,000 workers of these companies. For example, in Alexandria Shipyard, LMP&#13;
helped in retraining redundant workers. Those workers were retrained as certified welders, and their productivity&#13;
increased as much as 300 percent. The cost for retraining was LE 3,500 per worker.&#13;
6.     Currently, SFD has been authorized to work on the labor mobility programs of additional seven public&#13;
sector enterprises (total of 10 enterprises) from January 1996. The SFD will assist public sector enterprises through&#13;
programs such as retraining, early retirement, spin-offs of its business, and self-employment. The total number of&#13;
workers receiving SFD assistance by the end of 1996 is about to be 10,000 at an estimated cost of LE 110 million.&#13;
7.     To match workers to employment opportunities, LMP implemented 15 demand-led training projects&#13;
through private sector/union owned training facilities. Primarily, the training institutions identified jobs and then&#13;
requested SFD help to train workers for these jobs thus, all graduates are employed. In these activities, SFD&#13;
finances the fees for trainees and the cost of up-grading the training modules and equipment in both public and&#13;
private training centers.  These projects helped place about 2,000 unemployed graduates in permanent job&#13;
opportunities at an average cost of LE 1,500 per trainee.&#13;
B. Phase 11 - Labor Mobility Program&#13;
Phase 11 Objectives&#13;
8.     During Phase 11, LMP would be revamped into a broader Human Resources Development Program which&#13;
would assist: (a) labor mobility in public enterprise being restructured or privatized; (b) redeployment of workers in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 4&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
private enterprises which would facing new competitive pressures due to the trade liberalization; and (c) help small&#13;
and medium size (under 50 employees) private sector enterprises to improve their workers' skills. To achieve these&#13;
objectives, the program would expand the mandate of LMP to support labor mobility of private sector enterprises.&#13;
Phase 11 - Description&#13;
9.     In order to achieve the above objectives, Phase 11 of the program will have two components:&#13;
(a" Labor Mobility Component&#13;
10.    This component will assist labor mobility activities in public sector enterprises and in private enterprises&#13;
facing competitive pressures due to trade liberalization. Labor mobility would include an early retirement program&#13;
(not IDA funded), financial assistance to start new businesses, and retraining of redundant workers. A major&#13;
activity of this component would be retraining of redundant workers in public sector enterprises, so that it can help&#13;
these workers to find new jobs in private sectors. Private enterprises wishing to benefit from this program would&#13;
need to demonstrate that their competitive situation was altered by trade liberalization. This support to private sector&#13;
enterprises would start on a pilot basis and expand based on the results.&#13;
(b) Small and Medium Enterprise Skills Development Component:&#13;
11.    This component will provide financial assistance to train workers in small and medium size enterprises on&#13;
a matching subsidy basis. The main areas of training would be marketing, maintenance, quality control, and&#13;
technical skills, which are essential to expand their businesses. The matching subsidies would be transparent and&#13;
the proportion of subsidy would vary with the mobility of that particular skill. This component will not finance&#13;
stipends of trainees and salaries of trainers. In order to prioritize the area of training, the component would support&#13;
the periodical informal labor market survey (twice a year to be undertaken under contract by a private research&#13;
institutes) to assess the recent skill requirements in the regional market.&#13;
12.    The entrepreneurship skills training offered by this component are different from similar training provided&#13;
by other programs of SFD activities; i.e., Enterprise Development Program and Community Development Program.&#13;
The major difference is that the component limits finance to only skills training with high inter-firm mobility. It&#13;
would be mainly targeted to small and medium sized enterprises with 50 employees or less.&#13;
13.    A follow-up survey will be carried out for those who receive training in order to determine the cost-&#13;
effectiveness of the proposed program in terms of job creation.&#13;
C. Labor Mobility Phase II Costs&#13;
(a) Labor Mobility Component&#13;
14.    Compensation costs of early retirement program (not funded by IDA) are estimated to range from LE&#13;
2,000 to LE 7,000 per person. Financial assistance to start to new businesses would cost around LE 2,000 per&#13;
worker. The average cost for retraining redundant workers in public sector enterprises is estimated to be US$1,000&#13;
per trainee, while the cost for training workers in private sector enterprises would range from US$1,000 to&#13;
US$5,000. Target number of workers trained in this component would be 15,000 and 5,000 workers for public and&#13;
private sector employees respectively. For both public and private enterprises, the maximum training period per&#13;
worker would be six months. Estimated total program cost for this component would be US$30 million.&#13;
(b) Small and Medium Enterprise Skills Development Component&#13;
15.    The enterprise skills development training is estimated to cost US$1,000 per person. It is expected that&#13;
cost would vary according to the type of skill training. Duration of training would not exceed six months for any&#13;
type of skills training. The target number of participants for this training component would be 7,000 workers over 4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 4&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
years. The program would also include a labor market survey which would cost around US$3,000 per governorate.&#13;
Thus, the estimated total program cost for this component would be US$10 million. Overall, the total cost for&#13;
Human Resources Development Program is estimated to be US$40 million.&#13;
D. Monitoring Indicators&#13;
16.    The monitoring indicators of the program would be the number of workers who received training or the&#13;
number of workers received assistance under this program. Proposed monitoring indicators for Phase 11 Human&#13;
Resources Development Program are shown in the table below:&#13;
Proposed Monitoring Targets Indicators for Human Resources Development&#13;
Item                                    1997-2000 [1997   1998 ] 1999   2000&#13;
(I). Labor Mobility Component         l&#13;
A. Public Enterprises&#13;
No. of workers received compensation for     3,000    750    750    750    750&#13;
early retirement&#13;
No. of redundant workers received            6,000   1,500   1,500   1,500   1,500&#13;
retraining                                                I&#13;
No. of workers received assistance for       6,000   1,500   1,500   1,500   1,500&#13;
starting new business&#13;
B. Private Enterprises&#13;
No. of workers received training             5,000   1,250   1,250   1,250   1,250&#13;
(II). Enterprise Skills Development                           _&#13;
No. of workers in small and medium size      7,000   1,750   1,750   1,750   1,750&#13;
enterprises received training                                     I _&#13;
17.    In addition to above target indicators, the impact of the proposed program would be measured by other&#13;
indicators such as the number of new jobs created by this program, number of workers acquired the required level&#13;
of skills after training, and the number of new businesses created by this prograrn.&#13;
E. Stage of Preparation&#13;
18.    This LMP part of this program is already on-going and needs to supported as an accompaniment to Egypt's&#13;
industrial restructuring process. The same approach will be applied in supporting the private sector affected by&#13;
trade liberalization with one major difference. The program will fund only training costs and not stipends. The&#13;
same rule will apply to small and medium enterprise training.&#13;
19.    The Government of France is currently providing technical assistance to SFD to help assess the quality of&#13;
Egypt's public and private training institutes. The consultants will also be looking at the proposed human resource&#13;
development program and provide guidance to SFD.&#13;
20.    The next step is to carry out informal surveys on labor mobility by skill in Egypt and use the results to&#13;
calibrate the proportion of subsidy to be given to the private sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 5: SFD ACHIEVEMENTS TO DATE AND ECONOMIC ANALySIS FOR PHASE 11&#13;
A.      Achievements to Date&#13;
I1.     Despite a slow start due to the need to find proper staff and put in place proper procedures, SFD has made&#13;
considerable progress and has achieved significant results. Tables I and 2 show disbursements and employment&#13;
generation achieved by SFD. Note that there is a slow-down in the productive families program after 1993. This&#13;
was due to the need to assimilate properly the large number of families brought in during year 1993. More modest&#13;
and steady annual targets have been established for Phase 11.&#13;
Table 1: Egypt Social Fund for Development Targets Achieved Through June 30, 1995&#13;
Total Funding        Employment Opportunities&#13;
Program                  |L.E. Million   US$  Million   Temporary  Permanent    Beneficiaries&#13;
Public Works                     488.7         143.8       23,051          3,101      5,000,000&#13;
Community Development             192.2         56.6       30,392         76,526      2,581,019&#13;
Enterprise Development            798.1        234.9       32,388        147,178       736,297&#13;
Emp. &amp; Re-training                 29.5          8.7        1,103          3,164        21,335&#13;
Total                           1,508.6        444.0       86,934        229,969      8,338,651&#13;
Table 2: Targets Achieved During SFD Phase I&#13;
Item                         Average Unit  1993    1994    1995 T  Total&#13;
_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ I  C ost   L E&#13;
A. Public Works Program&#13;
1. Environmental Infrastructure&#13;
a. Wastewater networks in km.                             145,000       _        6      12         18&#13;
b. Wastewater treatment plants (# of subproj.)            561,705       _                2         2&#13;
c. Wastewater pump stations (# of subproj.)                80,635                1       1         2&#13;
d. Canal covering in km.                                  455,000       4       14      16        34&#13;
e. Canal protection in km.                                378,000      27       55      92       175&#13;
f Channel maintenance in km.                               25,000           _          600       600&#13;
g. Other project (# of subproj.) 1/                        14,500      38       98      11       147&#13;
2. Potable Water&#13;
a. Networks in km                                          37,924      84      557     833      1,474&#13;
b. Elevated and ground tanks (units)                      204,354       _        8      44        52&#13;
c. Artisian wells (units)                                  18,978       2       48      64       114&#13;
d. Other projects (# of subproj.) 2/                       19,635       2       21      95       118&#13;
3. Rural Roads&#13;
a. Road construction in km                                142,853      15      136     266       417&#13;
b. Road improvement in km                                  35,900       5       20                25&#13;
4. Building Refurbishment&#13;
a. Clinics (units)                                         46,016      12       38      74       124&#13;
b. Youth centers (units)                                   50,215       1       76      91       168&#13;
c. Schools (units)                                         41,246      27     200      146       373&#13;
d. Social centers (units)                                  76,851                6      14        31&#13;
e. Other projects (# of subprojects) 3/                    48,643               26      32        59&#13;
Notes:&#13;
1/ Filling ponds, irrigation structure maintenance.&#13;
2/  Pump room, water station fence, water intake upgrading and tank renovation.&#13;
3/  Veterinary units, nursery and public service buildings.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
Page 2 of 5&#13;
Table 2 (Continued)&#13;
B. Community Development Program&#13;
1. Health Services&#13;
a. Number of health clinics equipped 4/                   8,214      17       11      18        46&#13;
b. Number of awareness campaigns 5/                       2,282     127     209      233      569&#13;
c. Number of health personnel trained 6/                    930      28      28      764      820&#13;
2. Education &amp; Training&#13;
Number of classrooms established 7/                    28,675               7      180       187&#13;
b. Number of illiteracy classes established                 501   1,450   4,924   2,758      9,132&#13;
c. Number of individuals trained to teach literacy classes  2,347   1,619   4,180   3,442    9,241&#13;
d. Number of beneficiaries receiving vocational training    245     329   2,013   6,027      8,369&#13;
e. Number of training workshops equipped                 48,965      12       9        7        28&#13;
3. Productive Families Loan Program&#13;
a. Number of fainilies                             Not applicable  21,626   5,944    239    27,809&#13;
b. Number of loans                            _    Not applicable  21,626   5,944    239    27,809&#13;
c. Percentage loans under L.E. 15,000 8/           Not applicable   100%    100%    100%&#13;
d. Average loan size                               Not applicable   1,200   1,200   1,200 _&#13;
4. NGOs Capacity Building&#13;
a. Upgrading technical &amp; admin. capacity                  2,285      57                8        65&#13;
5. Support to Youth and Community Centers 9/&#13;
a. Community centers equipped                            Not yet      _                -         -&#13;
b. Youth centers equipped                                Not yet       _         _      _&#13;
6. Environment&#13;
a. Number of environmental projects 10/                 800,000       2        1       4         7&#13;
C. Enterprise Development Program 11/&#13;
1. Contracted amount (L.E. Million)                 Not applicable 488,228 257,183 390,077 1,135,488&#13;
2. Disbursement to beneficiaries (L.E. Million)     Not applicable  92,496 437,094 161,475   691,065&#13;
3. Number of enterprises                            Not applicable   8,694  11,823  18,572    39,089&#13;
4. Number of entrepreneurs                          Not applicable   8,694  13,755  21,087    43,536&#13;
5. Average cost of enterprise                              17,037  10,639  31,777   8,694          -&#13;
6. Employment opportunities&#13;
a. Number of permanent empl. opp. 12/              Not applicable  22,604  35,763  45,774   104,141&#13;
b. Number of temporary empl. opp.                  Not applicable   8,799  13,921  17,818    40,538&#13;
7. Total permanent equivalent 13/                   Not applicable  25,637  40,403  51,713   117,753&#13;
8. Average cost per job                                     5,854   3,622  10,818   3,122&#13;
Notes:&#13;
4/  Number of health clinics includes clinics totally or partially equipped.&#13;
5/  Number of awareness campaigns includes health, social and environmental awareness.&#13;
6/ Number of health personnel trained includes physicians, nurses, and extension workers in health.&#13;
7/ Number of classrooms established: for some classes CDP provides furniture and refurbishment and for other classes.&#13;
CDP only fumishes.&#13;
8/  100% of loans are below 15,000 L.E. because the maximum loan size allowed to CDP loans is 7,000 L.E.&#13;
9/  These represent now activities for which projects are still under contracting.&#13;
10/ Environmental projects include potable water, latrines, garbage collection, drainage, backfilling, pest spraying and tree&#13;
planting.&#13;
11/ Figures for the EDP are up to November 8, 1995.&#13;
12/ Permanent jobs at 2.6xnumber of entrepreneurs.&#13;
13/ 3 temporary jobs are equivalent to I permanent job.&#13;
2.      The data in Table 2 shows that SFD has made considerable progress. The data for 1995 is annualized&#13;
based on the results accomplished up to September, 1995. The unit costs data shows that the SFD is quite efficient.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
Page 3 of 5&#13;
B. Economic Rate of Return Analysis for Phase 11&#13;
3.      While the formal targeting indicators developed for Phase 11 are given in Table 3.1 in the main report, the&#13;
data in Annex 1, Table 3 show a wider range of indicators which will be used to guide operations during phase II.&#13;
These have been developed based on experience of the on-going phase. However, as SFD is a demand driven&#13;
operation these figures are subject to change. They are primarily meant to give SFD guidance. The sub-project&#13;
distribution underlying the indicators in Annex 5, Table 3 were also used as the basis for economic analysis of&#13;
Phase 11.&#13;
Table 3: SFD Phase H1 Monitoring Targets&#13;
Item                                                         1 1997-20001   19971   19981   19991    2000&#13;
A. Public Works Program&#13;
1. Environmental Infrastructure&#13;
a.Wastewater Upgrading (# of Subprojects)                             25        6        6        6         6&#13;
b. Wastewater Networks in Kilometers                                 125       31       31       31        31&#13;
c. Wastewater Treatment Plants (# of sub-projects)                    20        5        5        5         5&#13;
d. Wastewater Pump Stations (# of sub-projects)                       20        5        5        5         5&#13;
e. Canal Covering in Kilometers                                       50       13       13       13        13&#13;
f Canal Protection in Kilometers                                     125       31       31       31        31&#13;
2. Potable Water&#13;
a. Networks in Kilometers                                            500      125      125      125       125&#13;
|b. Elevated and Ground Tanks                                         40       10       10       10        10&#13;
c. Artesian Wells                                                     40       10       10       10        10&#13;
3. Rural Roads&#13;
a. Road Construction in Kilometers                                   125       31       31       31        31&#13;
b. Road Improvement in Kilometers                                   400       100      100      100       100&#13;
4. Building Refurbishment                                                I&#13;
a. Clinics (units)                                                    60       15       15       15        15&#13;
b. Youth Centers (units)                                              60       15       15       15        15&#13;
c. Schools (units)                                                    60       15       15       15        15&#13;
d. Social Centers (units)                                             60       15       15       15        15&#13;
B. Community Development Program&#13;
1. Health Services&#13;
a. No. of Health Clinics rehab./estab/ equipped                      130       33       33       33        33&#13;
b. No. of Health Awareness Campaigns                                600       150      150      150       150&#13;
c. No. of Health Personnel Trained                                  500       125      125      125       125&#13;
2. Education and Training                                               I_I&#13;
a. No. of Classrooms established                                     130       33       33       33        33&#13;
b. No. of People in Illiteracy Classes                            15,000    3,750    3,750    3,750     3,750&#13;
c. No. of Individuals Trained to Teach Illiteracy Classes           700       175      175      175       175&#13;
d. No. of Beneficiaries Receiving Vocational Training             14,000    3,500    3,500    3,500     3,500&#13;
e. No. of Training Workshops Equipped                                150       38       38       38        38&#13;
3. Productive Families (Micro-enterprises) Loan Program&#13;
a. Number of Loan Recipients                                      40,000   10,000   10,000   10,000    10,000&#13;
b. Average Loan Size                                               3,000     750       750      750       750&#13;
4. Support to Youth and Community Centers_&#13;
a. Community Centers Equipped&#13;
b. Youth Centers Equipped                                              3        1        1        1         1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
Page 4 of 5&#13;
Table 3 (Continued)&#13;
C Enterprise Development Program&#13;
1. Number of Enterprises                                1   40,0001  10,OC        10,000        10,000&#13;
2. Number of Entrepreneurs                              |   45,0001 11,250  11,250   11,250    11,250&#13;
D. Human Resources Development Program&#13;
Expected Number of Trainees                                  24,000   6,0001  6,000   6,00       6,000&#13;
E. Overall Job Creation Targets&#13;
1. Public Works Program                                 |_|_T_T_T&#13;
a. Temporary Jobs in Person Years                           27,200   6,800   6,800   6,800      6,800&#13;
b. Permanent Employment Opportunities                        4,000   1,000   1,000   1,000       1,000&#13;
2. Community Development Program&#13;
a. Number of Temporary Jobs in Person Years                  4,000   1,000   1,000   1,000      1,000&#13;
b. Number of Permanent Jobs Created                         41,000   10,250  10,250  10,250    10,250&#13;
3. Enterprise Development Program&#13;
a. Number of Permanent Employment Opportunities            160,000  40,000  40,000  40,000    40,000&#13;
b. Number of Temporary Employment Opportunities             50,000  12,500  12,500  12,500    12,500&#13;
TOTAL NUMBER OF JOBS                                        286,200  71,5501 71,5501 71,550    71,550&#13;
TOTAL POPULA TION GETTING ADDITIONAL INCOME               1,431,000 357,750 357,750 357,750   357,750&#13;
4.      Economic Evaluation: It is difficult to calculate an ERR for the overall project given the difficulty of&#13;
quantifying benefits of some of its activities such as upgrading public health, environment, job-training, etc.&#13;
Nevertheless, SFD attempts to quantify benefits wherever possible using willingness to pay (for community&#13;
services); estimates of travel costs savings (roads); rental values (community buildings); and enhanced prospects for&#13;
earnings (technical training and enterprise development). A minimum threshold rate of return of 12 percent is&#13;
required. These estimates should be treated with caution given that they are based on subjective assumptions.&#13;
5.      Table 4 shows the phasing of the different costs and benefits for every thousand Egyptian Pounds of&#13;
investment. The Economic Rate of Return (ERR) analysis excludes health and literacy projects as well as&#13;
institutional development projects. It also excludes microenterprises even though they are subjected to financial&#13;
sustainability tests. The ERR analysis therefore covers almost 75 percent of project funds and can be considered&#13;
good representation of the project.&#13;
6.      Based on a sample of projects financed during Phase I and extrapolating rates of return across the entire&#13;
program, the rate of return for the activities with quantifiable benefits which account for some 75 percent of project&#13;
cost, is estimated to be 21 percent. A sensitivity test was carried out by reducing benefits by 20 percent while&#13;
constant cost showed the ERR to be about 15 percent. These estimates should be treated with caution given that they&#13;
are based on subjective assumptions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
Page 5 of 5&#13;
Table 4: Costs and Benefits per 1000 LE of Investment and its Phasing&#13;
INVESTMENT COSTS             RECURRENT COSTS&#13;
Item                 Year I Year 2 Year 3 Year 4+ Year I Year 2 Year 3 Year 4+&#13;
A. Public Works Program&#13;
1. Environmental Infrastructure         500   500                      0      0     15      30&#13;
2. Potable Water                        500   500                                    15     30&#13;
3. Rural Roads                          500   500                      0      0    50      100&#13;
4. Building Refurbishment               500   500                      0      0     15      30&#13;
B. Community Development Program&#13;
1. Health Services                    1,000                                 100   200      300&#13;
2. Education &amp; Training                1,000                                100   200      300&#13;
3. Productive Families Loan Program    1,000                                100  1,200   1,500&#13;
C. Enterprise Development Program      1,000                                300   400      400&#13;
D. Human Resources Program            1,000                                 100   200      100&#13;
E. Institutional Development           1,000                                100   200      300&#13;
BENEFITS                  NET BENEFITS&#13;
Year I Year 2 Year 3 Year 4+ Year 1 Year 2 Year 3 Year 4+&#13;
A. Public Works Program&#13;
I. Environmental Infrastructure                      N/A      N/A   N/A   N/A   N/A        N/A&#13;
2. Potable Water                                      110    220  -500   -500    95         190&#13;
3. Rural Roads                                        150     300  -500   -500    100      200&#13;
4. Building Refurbishment                             100     200  -500  -500    85         170&#13;
B. Community Development Program&#13;
1. Health Services                    N/A   N/A   N/A    N/A    N/A   N/A   N/A    N/A&#13;
2. Education &amp; Training               N/A   N/A   N/A    N/A    N/A   N/A   N/A    N/A&#13;
3. Productive Families Loan Program           N/A  N/A    N/A    N/A   N/A   N/A    N/A&#13;
C. Enterprise Development Program              250    500     800 -1,000   -150            400&#13;
D. Human Resources Program                     200   300      300 -1,000    100   100      200&#13;
E. Institutional Development          N/A   N/A   N/A    N/A    N/A   N/A   N/A    N/A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 6: PROJECT MANAGEMENT AND CRITERIA FOR SUB-PROJECTS&#13;
A.     Project Management&#13;
1.     The SFD was established by a presidential decree issued in 1991, as an autonomous agency with legal&#13;
personality and technical, financial and administrative flexibility which reports directly to the President. The&#13;
autonomous nature of SFD is govemed in accordance with the provision of its Articles of Agreement, By-laws, and&#13;
the Framework Agreement between SFD and the government. The SFD's autonomous nature, which includes&#13;
authority to enter into contracts, establish its own operating procedures, including those for procurement and&#13;
disbursement, facilitates its ability to work with regional governments, private sector contractors, community&#13;
organizations and NGOs in an efficient and effective manner.&#13;
2.     The SFD Board of Directors (BOD) acts as a technical steering committee. It is chaired by the Prime&#13;
Minister, and is comprised of fifteen members, including eight ministers and seven representatives from the private&#13;
sector. Ministerial representation on the BOD eliminates duplication of efforts and ensures adherence to sector&#13;
priorities. The BOD is responsible for establishing SFD's guidelines for project approval and follow-up, operational&#13;
guidelines and prioritization of projects. In addition, to having policy making functions and approving SFD's&#13;
Operating Manual and annual budgets, the BOD accepts financial contributions and authorizes disbursement of&#13;
funds.&#13;
3.     To allow for efficiency and flexibility in implementation, an Executive Committee (EC) chaired by the&#13;
chairman of the BOD was created with eight members from the private sector. This is consistent with the&#13;
institutional set-up and autonomy of other successful social funds. The EC evaluates projects submitted to the SFD&#13;
prior to presentation to the BOD, and is authorized to approve projects in the amount of US$500,000 up to US$3&#13;
million. The EC has also been designated to act on behalf of the BOD and approve guidelines for manuals and sub-&#13;
projects, establish guidelines for implementation of projects approved by the BOD; delineate resource availability;&#13;
and maintain regular contact with donors.&#13;
4.     Daily operations of SFD including the hiring and management of national and regional staff (a total of 133)&#13;
are the responsibility of the Managing Director (MD), who is appointed by the Board. The MD prepares the work&#13;
programs; approves sub-projects under US$500,000; authorizes all disbursements; prepares progress reports and&#13;
presents them to the BOD.&#13;
5.     The SFD's well-defined administrative structure contributes to its efficient management of operations, as&#13;
well as its ability to absorb an increased volume of projects. It is envisaged that the current structure will be&#13;
retained for the most part, with a stronger emphasis being placed on a demand driven approach, as well as more&#13;
decentralization of authority and functions to the field and satellite offices.&#13;
6.     The national office is comprised of five departments headed by individual Director Generals reporting&#13;
directly to the MD. (Refer to Annex -- for an organizational chart , and Annex -- for a detailed description of the&#13;
roles of respective departments)  They are: (i) Finance, Administration and Personnel, (ii) Public Works; (iii)&#13;
Community Development; (iv) Enterprise Development; and (v) Human Resources.  These departments are&#13;
supported by five units which in turn report directly to the MD and serve to facilitate the overall objectives of SFD.&#13;
7.     The supporting units are: (a) Management Information Systems (MIS) responsible for maintaining the MIS;&#13;
(b) Credit responsible for determining the credit worthiness of projects involving intermediary agencies and/or&#13;
beneficiaries for both the Community Development and Enterprise Development Programs; (c) Projects and&#13;
Planning office, (includes a monitoring targeting evaluation and studies unit), with requisite skills to plan and&#13;
review SFD activities, as well as appraise and evaluate projects; (d) Legal mandated to prepare framework&#13;
agreements and handle related legal matters: (e) International Cooperation Affairs and Information for Public&#13;
Relations Department charged with managing and organizing marketing campaigns involving information&#13;
dissemination on the role of SFD as well as handling problems arising from poor communication; and (f) Internal&#13;
Auditing which reports directly to the MD and BOD.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Page 2 of 7&#13;
8.      The Cairo office provides support to the regions, prepares technical plans and budgets for sub-projects,&#13;
deals with financial transactions of the sub-projects, assists with procurement, plans and coordinates training. The&#13;
SFD is represented outside of Cairo through ten regional and six satellite offices.' The regional and satellite offices&#13;
are the main point of contact between requesting agencies and SFD, they provide advice to communities, NGOs,&#13;
and regional government on SFD procedures; receiving completed application forms; coordinating sub-project&#13;
appraisal committees; and conducting field appraisals and launch workshops. The regional and satellite offices are&#13;
linked to the national offices through telephones and facsimiles. An emphasis on a more decentralized role for the&#13;
regional and satellite offices during Phase 11 will be encouraged. This will allow for improved synergy between&#13;
different programs, speed up the approval process, and help improve the impact of SFD activities on the intended&#13;
beneficiaries.&#13;
9.      Sub-project Cycle. The SFD initiates and accepts sub-project proposals submitted by a sponsoring agency&#13;
(SA) to any ten of the regional or six satellite offices,2. The selection of SA proposals for loans or grants3 are based&#13;
on specific guidelines established in the Operational Manual. SFD accepts sub-project proposals submitted by SAs&#13;
to the national, regional and satellite offices, based on clearly articulated guidelines established in the Operational&#13;
Manual. With assistance from trained university students (technical training is provided to the students for this&#13;
specific task) regional and satellite offices provide SAs with assistance in proposal preparation when needed.&#13;
10.     A preliminary screening is conducted by the regional and satellite offices which is then forwarded to the&#13;
national office for a detailed desk and field appraisal. As reflected in the Operational Manual, the basic elements of&#13;
sub-project appraisal are guided by: technical feasibility; social and institutional analysis; as well as simplified&#13;
economic and environmental analysis. Contributions in kind or cash will also be determinants of sub-project&#13;
eligibility, especially during Phase II.&#13;
Il.     Depending on the amount of financing requested from SFD, sub-projects can be approved either by the EC&#13;
or the MD based on precise selection criteria detailed in the Operational Manual. Upon the formal approval of a&#13;
sub-project, a framework agreement is drawn up between SFD  and each SA.  These agreements specify&#13;
responsibilities of each party: procurement methods; implementation schedules; financial terms and conditions;&#13;
and SA contribution; supervision, completion and handover mechanisms.&#13;
12.     The SFD financed sub-projects have been implemented rapidly and efficiently. Several factors explain&#13;
SFD's ability to process and approve projects rapidly. Paramount among these is the effective management style&#13;
displayed by the MD and his staff. Furthermore, SFD's status as a statutory organization outside the civil services&#13;
has helped contain political pressure. A sound administrative structure, and the clear delineation of responsibility&#13;
and accountability to staff in charge of promotion and appraisal of sub-projects is another factor contributing to&#13;
SFD's success in implementation. As does the partnership with local communities, close association with NGOs&#13;
and local Government and the use of standardized project types, which considerably simplifies project preparation&#13;
and streamlines project processing. This, combined with extensive screening, has led to an acceptance rate of 65-70&#13;
percent of the proposals submitted, a figure comparable with other social funds.&#13;
B.      Operational Manual/Sub-project Selection Criteria&#13;
13.     As is the tradition of all social funds, SFD is governed by a set of clear guidelines and operating procedures&#13;
approved by the Government and IDA.  It details SFD's organization, staffing, administration, financial&#13;
Satellite offices were established in order to provide better coordination with activities carried out in govemorates, and to&#13;
allow for closer monitoring and follow-up.&#13;
2    SAs include ministries, the public or private sector, non-governmental organizations (NGOs) and communities.&#13;
Grants are targeted towards infrastructure projects in rural communities as well as poor urban neighborhoods, and loans&#13;
towards income generating activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Page 3 of 7&#13;
arrangements and operating procedures and sub-project selection criteria (discussed in length in the following&#13;
paragraphs). The fundamental rules governing the operational manual will be retained and strengthened, and other&#13;
elements will be revised to assure that the organization retains its dynamic nature.&#13;
Sub-project Eligibility Criteria&#13;
14.    Proposals funded under the Egypt Social Fund (SFD) project fall within a typology of subprojects (SPs)&#13;
encompassing public works, enterprise development, community development programs and more recently, human&#13;
resources development (this component is new and the SP selection criteria are currently being developed). These&#13;
components were designed with a view to: (i) a reduction in the levels of poverty through supporting employment&#13;
generation and community development efforts; (ii) mitigating the negative impact o the Economic Reform and&#13;
Structural Adjustment Program; and (iii) creating employment opportunities for the Gulf returnees as well as&#13;
unemployed youth.&#13;
15.    Selection and evaluation of SPs as well as Sponsoring Agencies (SAs) are guided by transparent evaluation&#13;
and selection criteria delineated in the Operating Manual of the SFD. The principal elements of SP selection&#13;
procedures emphasize: (i) general criteria; (ii) social criteria; (iii) technical feasibility; and (iv) sustainability,&#13;
including financial and institutional analysis. These selection criteria apply to all components within the SFD&#13;
program. It should be noted that for the Public Works program, Enterprise Development and Microenterprise&#13;
programs, additional criteria have been developed to reflect the specific needs of those sectors.&#13;
General Selection Criteria&#13;
* The objectives of the sub-project should comply and attempt to achieve the overall goals of the Egypt Social&#13;
Fund, and the programs should encourage the participation of the private sector, NGOs and voluntary&#13;
institutions&#13;
* The sub-project should be identified on the basis of direct contacts with the target groups in the target&#13;
geographical areas, so that project components represent community priorities&#13;
* The participation of women should be an integral component, especially in the CDP and EDP SPs, either as&#13;
targeted beneficiaries or in project management and execution&#13;
* The proposed SPs must not be included in any government action program in order to avoid duplication of&#13;
activities&#13;
* An acceptable level of community participation should be demonstrated either directly or through a sponsoring&#13;
agency (SA) (i.e. local government, NGO, local development communities)&#13;
* The SP should generate employment opportunities at a suitable cost and finance labor intensive technology&#13;
when deemed appropriate&#13;
* A plan for sustainability and maintenance should be prepared as part of the proposal and mechanisms to ensure&#13;
it's continued operations into the future should be demonstrated&#13;
*  The SP should conform with national norms and standards&#13;
* Written authorization of permits from local and regional governments should be obtained, and coordination of&#13;
public and private institutions in SP implementation should be ensured&#13;
Selection criteria for the CDP are guided by the general, social, institutional, and financial guidelines of the&#13;
SFD. Specific selection criteria for CDP have not been developed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Page 4 of 7&#13;
*  The project should demonstrate an acceptable cost per beneficiary&#13;
*  Technical feasibility of SPs should be demonstrated&#13;
*  Administrative costs of an SP should not exceed 10 percent of total costs. SA's are allowed to charge a&#13;
sponsorship fee not to exceed 5 percent of the total project cost.&#13;
*  Target Groups:      a/ Lower income communities, particularly in rural govemorates&#13;
b/ Communities lacking complete or partial access to the basic and essential public&#13;
services&#13;
c/ Redundant workers in the public sector enterprises&#13;
d/ Gulf returnees, who are unemployed&#13;
e/ Unemployed youth&#13;
f/ Women&#13;
*  The SP design should be environmentally sound&#13;
DETAILED CRITERIA&#13;
Social Criteria&#13;
* The proposed SP should cover a target theme&#13;
* The population in the area to be covered&#13;
* Available social indicators for the area&#13;
* The request must originate with the community&#13;
* The SP responds to the priorities of the majority of beneficiary households&#13;
* The Community will play an active role in implementation and monitoring or implementation&#13;
Technical Criteria&#13;
*  Conformity with and complementary to national planning&#13;
* Norms and standards, if any, established by a concerned Ministry are adhered to&#13;
Description of the general state of the infrastructure, access to water and sanitation&#13;
* Works to be undertaken, equipment and materials to be procured, schedule of works&#13;
* Total area of infrastructure&#13;
* For expansion, suitability of area for expansion&#13;
* Local availability of essential materials needed for a SP&#13;
Economic and Financial Criteria&#13;
* The financing plan, should include contributions from SAs/beneficiaries either in cash or kind for public work&#13;
SPs. For projects over US$0.5 million, the economic rate of return should exceed 12 percent&#13;
* Cost benefit analysis, and or/cost per beneficiary&#13;
* Sustainability, i.e., the capacity to provide for successful operations and maintenance beyond the investment&#13;
period, including cost recovery in cash or kind, when appropriate&#13;
=: the central or local Government and/or beneficiaries (including SAs) should offer some form of&#13;
operations and maintenance assurances&#13;
=&gt; adequate training for operations and maintenance should be included in SFD's training budget&#13;
Institutional and Management Criteria&#13;
*  Sufficient institutional arrangements to ensure rigor in SP implementation and subsequent operations and&#13;
management, while at the same time taking into account ease and speed of implementation&#13;
*  Communities should have guidance and receive technical assistance from SAs (i.e. the existence of a supporting&#13;
agency when the implementing agency is weak in SP execution)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Page 5 of 7&#13;
*  Current personnel availability of the beneficiary representatives (communities, SAs etc..), skill levels,&#13;
attendance frequency&#13;
*  For SPs requiring expansion, the availability of additional personnel, skill level and attendance frequency&#13;
*  Necessary equipment, and materials to adequately deliver services at the estimated levels&#13;
Selection Criteria for the Community Development Program&#13;
Objective: CDP activities are designed to: (i) finance improvements in productive activities (discussed under the&#13;
selection criteria of the EDP/CDP section) ; (ii) social development activities (health, education, and training) to&#13;
improve the essential services to the poor communities&#13;
As indicated in the early part of the document the selection criteria for the CDP are guided by the general, social,&#13;
financial and economic, and institutional and management guidelines of the SFD. Specific selection criteria for&#13;
CDP have not been developed&#13;
Selection Criteria for the Public Works Program&#13;
Objective: To transfer incomes, while strengthening local infrastructure development and creating employment&#13;
opportunities through the use of labor intensive works&#13;
*  Types of SPs financed: Irrigation and Drainage Project; Maintenance and improvement of Rural roads and&#13;
Village Entrances; Improvement of the Village Market Place; Landscaping; Solid Waste Management; potable&#13;
water projects; and Sanitary Drainage System and Lowering the Subsoil Water Level&#13;
&#149;  Target groups are unemployed workers in the lower income bracket and poor rural communities, in addition to&#13;
redundant workers and returning gulf returnees&#13;
*  The SPs undertaken should aim to create permanent jobs, through operation and maintenance activities for&#13;
financed projects&#13;
. SPs should employ simple technology, suitable for labor intensive public works programs&#13;
*  Employment of local contractors within the targeted community should be fostered&#13;
*  Labor wages to the project fund should exceed 25 percent&#13;
*  Utilization of mechanical equipment is not encouraged, unless strongly justified, and approved by the project&#13;
engineer and the SFD representatives&#13;
*  Certain categories/components are excluded, such as: financing the wages of permanent labor following project&#13;
completion; and the purchase of mechanical equipment&#13;
*  Ensuring operations and maintenance beyond the life of the project is a pre-requisite&#13;
Selection Criteria for the Enterprise Development Program and Microenterprise Program within the CDP5&#13;
Objective: Creating employment through the support for new and existing small enterprises by providing a&#13;
package of technical assistance, training and credit.&#13;
Banks&#13;
*  Bank profitability, leverage and liquidity&#13;
*  Risk associated with the asset and liability management of the bank. Ability to repay back loans&#13;
*  Identification of the geographical location of the bank and its network (ability to extend credit to diverse&#13;
geographic areas)&#13;
*  Asset/portfolio quality&#13;
*  The bank's ability to market it's products to the end beneficiaries&#13;
*  Ability to ensure rapid delivery of credit lines, this requires the adoption of quick methods for evaluating and&#13;
extending funds to beneficiaries.&#13;
The difference between CDP and EDP is the average loans size. CDP loans average US$500 and are&#13;
channeled through NGOs, EDP loans average US$4,000 and are channeled through Banks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Page 6 of 7&#13;
* Banks must be willing to establish special units for the utilization of SFD funds. These units would evaluate&#13;
and monitor loans, and generate reports requested by SFD and allow for external auditing of SFD transactions&#13;
* Assessment of the bank's absorptive capacity of loan officers&#13;
* SFD credit terms with respect to the average loan size, simple collateral, interest rates should be adopted&#13;
SA 's Inmlementing Credit Programs&#13;
*  The implementing SA must be a non-profit organization or development foundation with experience in credit&#13;
delivery&#13;
*  Organizational structure should be decentralized to ensure rapid delivery of credit and management support to&#13;
the target groups&#13;
*  The implementing agency should demonstrate tan effective loan monitoring system that relies on close contact&#13;
and follow-up with loan beneficiaries through an established extension system&#13;
Selection Criteria of a Sponsoring Agency&#13;
* It should have an independent legal status and be certified to receive grants or loans and to implement activities&#13;
* Technical capacity is required for SP project preparation, supervision and monitoring. If capacity is lacking,&#13;
SFD can provide the relevant training to build up local capacity&#13;
* Past experience in implementing similar SP(s) is preferred&#13;
- Financial accounts are reviewed&#13;
SFD funds allocations should be carefully recorded&#13;
- Permission should be obtained from the respective ministry and related agencies to operate in a particular sector&#13;
- Technical personnel assigned to carry out activities in the specified sector (health, education, PW) should be&#13;
qualified and officially certified in their area of responsibility, and have at least two years of experience&#13;
C Community representation and direct links with the communities is required&#13;
- Provide assurances of operations and maintenance of SPs.&#13;
16.    Revisions of SFD's operational manual will reflect the evolving nature of the organization as well as&#13;
recommendations emerging from studies and evaluations conducted on all aspects of management and organization.&#13;
It is envisaged that revisions would highlight: (i) the fund's more decentralized role; (ii) participatory and demand-&#13;
driven approach; (iii) the merging of income generating activities as well as re-designing its current methodology;&#13;
(iv) improving synergy between different interventions; and (v) providing transparency through "two-way-&#13;
communication". These revisions were discussed during the appraisal mission and it was agreed that any revisions&#13;
to the operating manual affecting project implementation would require prior approval from IDA.&#13;
C.     Project Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
Structure&#13;
17.    The SFD enjoys a sophisticated computer based management information system (MIS) designed to&#13;
monitor the physical and financial progress of sub-project implementation and evaluate SFD's overall performance.&#13;
As a monitoring device, it provides transparency and accountability of SFD activities, maintains data on targeting,&#13;
and facilitates contracting and payment. The MIS tracks SFD activities through the sub-project cycle, including&#13;
sub-project data, supervision, and identifies cost overruns and potential bottlenecks. MIS generated performance&#13;
reports are an integral part of the monthly report submitted by SFD management to the BOD for their review, and&#13;
the quarterly reports and annual reports submitted to donors. For the most part, SFD Phase 11 will build and extend&#13;
the monitoring system currently in place. Modifications will be aimed at enhancing monitoring and allowing for a&#13;
widespread desegregation of information. Specifically, improvements are aimed at: (a) enhancing information&#13;
dissemination on approval and disbursements at the SFD secretariat level; and (b) introducing a more participatory&#13;
approach in sub-project monitoring, by actively involving sponsoring agencies (SAs) in the process and thus&#13;
minimizing gaps in data reporting and recording requirements, which may lead to delays and discrepancies, which&#13;
undermine the usefulness of the system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
Page 7 of 7&#13;
18.    In order to address the first issue, the Planning and Programs Department will be responsible for collecting&#13;
information from the various operational departments (i.e., Finance, Community Development, Public Works,&#13;
Enterprise Development) and generating detailed information on approval and disbursement rates This will&#13;
facilitate and enhance SFD's tracking system and thus allow for a more transparent and accountable assessment of&#13;
financial flows required for day-to-day management decision-making.&#13;
19.    The second revision is crucial as it provides the baseline information for beneficiary and impact&#13;
assessments, and provides the bulk of the input for MIS project portfolio tracking. Currently, gaps exists in data&#13;
reporting and recording requirements, which have led to an ineffective and inaccurate application of the monitoring&#13;
system.&#13;
20.    In order to resolve this shortcoming, and to be consistent with SFD's participatory nature, SA's will receive&#13;
proper training which will enable them to become actively involved in monitoring progress on sub-projects output&#13;
delivered indicators. Information pertaining to outcome indicators and beneficiary assessments will be contracted-&#13;
out to specialized agencies possessing the necessary statistical capability, except in the cases where SFD regional&#13;
staff have the capacity to undertake beneficiary assessment. Information generated from the various indicators will&#13;
be forwarded to the Planning and Programs Department at SFD on a quarterly basis, which will allow for the&#13;
generation of a quarterly report following SFD spot checks. This approach ensures consistency with the intended&#13;
use of resource allocation and will safeguard SFD's role of poverty and unemployment reduction.&#13;
21.    In the case where SA's lack the technical or financial skills required for monitoring output delivered&#13;
indicators, SFD regional staff will provide training and/or assistance to fill the managerial and financial gaps, and&#13;
work in collaboration with SA's to fulfill their mandate.  This approach will serve as a springboard for&#13;
systematizing the delivery of training to address common constraints encountered in monitoring, and enhance&#13;
information dissemination, as well as prioritization and identification of community needs. More importantly, this&#13;
approach will assist in developing local capacity.&#13;
22.    A strengthening of ex-post evaluation, to be carried out by private firms and NGOS including beneficiary&#13;
assessment is being proposed and will provide critical information relating to inputs required to improve&#13;
intervention with the target population and determine the relationship between currently utilized methods in sub-&#13;
project cycle as well as beneficiary satisfaction. Improving client relations and enhancing communications between&#13;
SFD and its partners is actively being pursued by a separate unit "the International Cooperation Affairs and&#13;
Information for Public Relations unit". Staff from this unit will be assigned to all regional and satellite offices and&#13;
would report directly to the MD. The unit would address problems arising from poor communications and&#13;
recommend corrective actions, as well as organize information dissemination carnpaigns.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEx 7: MONITORING DURING PHASE 11&#13;
1.     Egypt's Social Fund for Development (SFD) 11 builds on and extends the monitoring system already in&#13;
place under SFD 1. The enhanced monitoring system under SFD 11 will help to answer two key questions about&#13;
SFD's impact: first, what benefits is SFD providing; and second, to whom are these benefits provided.&#13;
A.     Some Concepts&#13;
2.     Impact monitoring is defined here to include three types of monitoring: (i) implementation progress&#13;
monitoring; (ii) outcome monitoring; and (iii) targeting effectiveness monitoring. These concepts are discussed&#13;
below.&#13;
* Implementation Progress Monitoring. Implementation progress monitoring tracks the extent to which the&#13;
intended goods and services (inputs and outputs) are being delivered.&#13;
* Outcome Monitoring. Outcome monitoring tracks the extent to which the development objectives which&#13;
underlie the delivery of the specific goods and services are being achieved.&#13;
* Targeting Effectiveness Monitoring. Targeting effectiveness monitoring tracks the extent to which the groups&#13;
and individuals intended to benefit are actually benefiting.&#13;
B.     Significance of Systematic Monitoring and Targeting&#13;
3.     Importance of Monitoring. The main purpose of monitoring the implementation progress and outcomes&#13;
of SFD interventions is to be able to make adjustments in design and implementation as warranted. Effective&#13;
monitoring is a useful management tool and can provide early warning signals about impending problems.&#13;
4.     There are two levels at which it is important to monitor SFD operations: (a) at the level of the SFD&#13;
headquarters; and (b) at the level of the subprojects undertaken by SFD's sponsoring agencies. Monitoring the&#13;
overall functioning of the SFD secretariat can highlight opportunities for improving its efficiency (e.g., increasing&#13;
operational speed), and informing SFD policy (e.g., the need to focus resources on Governorates with high&#13;
poverty/unemployment indices that may have received lower resources than their allocation). The importance of&#13;
monitoring the progress of subprojects undertaken by sponsoring agencies emerges from the fact that SFD differs&#13;
from traditional projects in that it does not design or implement subprojects itself, but relies, instead, on a large&#13;
number of small and widely dispersed organizations to do so; monitoring the extent to which the various activities&#13;
of these organizations are consistent with the intended use of the resources allocated to them is critical.&#13;
5.     Importance of Targeting.  Given scarce resources and the unlimited needs of the poor and the&#13;
unemployed, the chances of SFD achieving its goal of providing an effective safety net for the poor and the&#13;
unemployed would be enhanced by improving the targeting of its resources to these groups.&#13;
6.     Cost of Monitoring. Monitoring has definite costs in terms of staff time and the budget. But, these costs&#13;
should be weighed against its longer term benefits. While no precise calculations have been made here of the cost&#13;
of the proposed monitoring system, three factors indicate that these costs are not likely to place an undue burden on&#13;
the SFD headquarters. First, SFD's existing monitoring system already systematically records and regularly updates&#13;
information on SFD approvals and disbursements, the total number of beneficiaries, and the number of temporary&#13;
and permanent jobs created by each SFD component. Hence, the marginal cost of compiling the additional&#13;
information that the proposed monitoring system entails should be relatively low. Second, the responsibility for&#13;
collecting the required information on Implementation Progress will vest with the sponsoring agencies -- not SFD.&#13;
The sponsoring agencies will report this information regularly to SFD which will record the information in its&#13;
database after spot checks on its accuracy. Third, with regard to data on Outcomes and Targeting Effectiveness, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 7&#13;
Page 2 of 4&#13;
sponsoring agencies will again be responsible for their collection, but in those cases where the sponsoring agencies&#13;
lack the capacity to collect this information and for whose collection SFD has to assume responsibility, this&#13;
information will be collected only on a sample basis -- not for all SFD subprojects or beneficiaries. Nevertheless,&#13;
the new monitoring system will entail some costs and these should be factored into SFD's costing process. It is&#13;
recommended that the cost of the new monitoring system be closely monitored as soon as it begins operation and&#13;
adjustments made in its scope as necessary.&#13;
C.      Indicative List of Performance Indicators for SFD&#13;
7.      Based on the three types of impact monitoring discussed above, indicators are divided into three categories:&#13;
* Outputs Delivered Indicators. These indicators provide an overview of the goods and services actually&#13;
delivered by the various SFD components -- they reflect implementation progress;&#13;
* Outcome Indicators. These indicators provide an indication of whether the purposes for which the various&#13;
goods and services are being delivered are being achieved -- they reflect outcomes; and&#13;
* Beneficiary Profile Indicators. These indicators help to determine whether the actual beneficiaries of SFD are&#13;
indeed the ones that it intended to benefit -- they reflect targeting effectiveness. '&#13;
D.      Data Collection and Reporting Methodology for the Identified Indicators&#13;
8.      Pyramidical Data Collection and Reporting Structure. The Projects and Planning Department of SFD&#13;
will be responsible for managing the new monitoring system. It will maintain a central database and update the&#13;
information on each of the identified performance indicators every quarter. The data collection and reporting&#13;
structure is outlined below.&#13;
9.      The Approval and Disbursement indicators as well as the Operational Speed indicators will be directly&#13;
under the charge of the Projects and Planning Department with this department calling upon information from SFD's&#13;
Finance Department and the SFD operational departments (i.e., CDP, EDP, and PWP Departments, and the Credit&#13;
Department for information on SFD loans) as needed. Many of these indicators are already systematically collected&#13;
and updated by the Projects and Planning Department.&#13;
10.     For the Outputs Delivered indicators, the Projects and Planning Department will receive systematic inputs&#13;
relating to the identified indicators every quarter from the operational departments. The operational departments&#13;
will, in turn, receive information on these indicators from the sponsoring agencies, also every quarter. The&#13;
sponsoring agencies will maintain records of the outputs they deliver to their beneficiaries and report these data to&#13;
the operational departments. Staff from the operational departments will confirm the accuracy of the Outputs&#13;
Delivered data provided by sponsoring agencies by regularly conducting checks during supervision visits to the sub-&#13;
project sites.&#13;
11.     The responsibility for collecting data on Outcome indicators and Beneficiary Profile indicators will also lie&#13;
with the sponsoring agencies who will provide this information to the relevant SFD operational department, who&#13;
will in turn, provide it to the Projects and Planning Department every quarter after spot checking its accuracy. The&#13;
sponsoring agencies should design the performance monitoring system for their subprojects from the earliest stages&#13;
of sub-project conception and regularly collect data on the selected indicators for all subprojects as soon as their&#13;
I/ Beneficiary Profile indicators can provide an indication of the Type 11 error in targeting (i.e., the extent to which unintended groups, for&#13;
example, the non-poor are benefiting from the program), but they cannot capture the Type I targeting error (i.e., the extent to which some poor&#13;
people are being missed).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 7&#13;
Page 3 of 4&#13;
2&#13;
implementation begins. However, it is possible, that for presently ongoing subprojects, the sponsoring agencies&#13;
might find it difficult to collect the required Outcome and Beneficiary Profile data since no system was put in place&#13;
for their collection when the subprojects began implementing. There might also be some sponsoring agencies who&#13;
simply lack the necessary technical capacity to routinely collect this information and to maintain systematic records.&#13;
In either case, the Projects and Planning Department will assume responsibility for the collection of this information&#13;
-- on a sample basis -- through SFD's Regional Offices with the assistance of the concerned sponsoring agency. For&#13;
Beneficiary Profile indicators, data will be collected by administering simple questionnaires to beneficiaries, and&#13;
staff from the SFD Regional Office will record the responses of the beneficiaries. Collecting data on Outcome&#13;
indicators will be more complex and in most cases it will be cost-effective to contract-out its collection to&#13;
specialized agencies possessing the necessary statistical capability. These agencies would be able to conduct control&#13;
group analysis in selected cases to separate the effect on outcomes of factors un-related to SFD. Where appropriate,&#13;
these agencies would also be able to undertake systematic Beneficiary Assessments and qualitative studies for&#13;
specific SFD subprojects.&#13;
12.     Four-tiered Sampling Methodology.   Data on the Approval and Disbursement indicators, and the&#13;
Operational Speed indicators will be collected for all SFD subprojects. The Outputs Delivered indicators will also&#13;
be collected for all SFD subprojects. With regard to Outcome and the Beneficiary Profile indicators, these&#13;
indicators will be collected by the sponsoring agencies for all subprojects, but, in cases where the sponsoring&#13;
agencies lack the capacity to do so, the Projects and Planning Department (or specialized agencies contracted by it)&#13;
will take on this responsibility and collect these data for a saanpl of SFD subprojects. The sample will be chosen&#13;
using a four-tiered sampling methodology as below.3&#13;
? Tier I The Projects and Planning Department will select a random sample4 of 30-50 percent5 of the sponsoring&#13;
agencies (stratified by type of sponsoring agency) for each of the three components to which at least 25 percent&#13;
of the allocated resources have been disbursed.&#13;
*   Tier 2  The Projects and Planning Department will then request each of the chosen sponsoring agencies to&#13;
provide a list of the Govemorates in which they are operating. From this list of Governorates, the Projects and&#13;
Planning Department will select randomly 20-30 percent' of the Governorates.&#13;
*   Tier 3  The Projects and Planning Department will request the sponsoring agency to provide a list of&#13;
subprojects supported in each of the selected Govemorates. From this list of subprojects, the Projects and&#13;
2&#13;
I For example, in the illiteracy prograw, the sponsoring agency could request the Beneficiary Characteristics data at the time of enrolling&#13;
the students.&#13;
3&#13;
/ It may be noted that monitoring Beneficiary Profile indicators may be less relevant in cases where SFD supervision missions to sub-&#13;
project sites confirm that the sponsoring agencies are delivering services in impoverished geographic locations, or that they are providing&#13;
services which are "basic" (e.g., adult literacy training) and which are, therefore, likely to be self-targeted to the poor. In the absence of&#13;
systematic recording and analysis of these factors during SFD supervision missions, monitoring Beneficiary Profile indicators will be useflul&#13;
even in these instances.&#13;
4&#13;
/ A standard statistical technique for choosing random samples will be used.&#13;
5&#13;
/ These percentages are indicative; an appropriate absolute number of observations should be chosen for the sample.&#13;
/ This tier of sampling is relevant in the case of the EDP component where SFD operations are listed by the sponsoring agencies, e.g.,&#13;
Banque du Caire instead of a listing of each of the subprojects financed by Banque du Caire. For components for which a list of each of the&#13;
subprojects is available, this tier would be omitted.&#13;
7&#13;
/ See footnote 5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 7&#13;
Page 4 of 4&#13;
Planning Department will select randomly 20-30 percent' of the subprojects. The SFD Regional Office with&#13;
the assistance of the sponsoring agency will collect the Outcome indicators for this sample of subprojects and&#13;
report them to the concerned SFD operational department.&#13;
* Tier 4 For the Beneficiary Profile indicators one more stage of sampling will be required; for the identified&#13;
sample of subprojects, the Projects and Planning Department will request a list of beneficiaries from the&#13;
sponsoring agency. From this list of beneficiaries, the Projects and Planning Department will select randomly&#13;
20-30 percent of the beneficiaries9. Again, the SFD Regional Office with the assistance of the sponsoring&#13;
agency will collect Beneficiary Profile data on the selected beneficiaries and report it to the concerned SFD&#13;
operational department.&#13;
13.    Format for the Projects and Planning Department's Database. Data on Outputs Delivered, Outcomes, and&#13;
Beneficiary Profile will be compiled by the Projects and Planning Department in a format that includes: name of&#13;
sub-project; acronym of the SFD component that the sub-project falls under; the type of beneficiaries to whom the&#13;
data pertains (e.g., in a public works program whether the beneficiary data relates to those who are employed on the&#13;
public works, or to those benefiting from the use of the infrastructure); month and year during which the data was&#13;
collected; month and year when this data is being reported; name of sponsoring agency; name of Governorate in&#13;
which the sub-project is operational; rural or urban coverage of the sub-project; sub-project start date; planned&#13;
sub-project completion date; and percentage of total sub-project allocation disbursed to date. The database should&#13;
allow producing separate print-outs by Component, by Governorate, by RuralUrban, or by Sponsoring Agency.&#13;
The database should also permit the production of print-outs for SFD-wide informnation, e.g., it should allow us to&#13;
answer questions such as what percentage of SFD beneficiaries are women, or, what percentage of SFD&#13;
beneficiaries are rural.&#13;
14.    Interpretation of the Data. The data collected in the above manner for the specified indicators will not be&#13;
combined into a single index, but rather the information will be used as a matrix that provides an overview of the&#13;
different aspects of SFD's performance. Data on the different indicators in the matrix will not, by itself, enable us to&#13;
arrive at firm conclusions about project performance; such data can only point to areas that need further&#13;
examination and it should be examined in the light of the goals of the intervention and the location-specific&#13;
conditions.&#13;
15.    An evaluation of the monitoring system will be undertaken to ensure effective implementation and allow&#13;
the system to evolve and reflect the changing environment.&#13;
S&#13;
/ See footnote 5.&#13;
9&#13;
/ See footnote 5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 8: PARTICIPATION AND TARGETING&#13;
Participation&#13;
1.     In addition to creating employment and delivering social services through a demand driven approach, the&#13;
Egypt Social Fund for Development (SFD) has been successful in fostering a participatory approach to sub-project&#13;
design, implementation and evaluation. SFD has also created complementary relationships between the objectives&#13;
of the fund and those of line agencies and the final beneficiaries. This in turn has catalyzed beneficiary participation&#13;
in decision making and unleashed the latent energy of people, leading to a more sustainable development approach&#13;
in comparison with the more traditional project approach.  Specifically, the involvement of beneficiaries in&#13;
consultation, cost sharing and decision making has improved the outcomes of sub-projects by: (a) ensuring that sub-&#13;
projects are relevant to beneficiary needs; and (b) generating commitment to sustaining project activities.&#13;
2.      Beneficiary participation strategies are imperative to ensure the sustainability of the a large number of&#13;
dispersed sub-projects. These include: (i) transferring participatory approaches to government agencies and&#13;
intermediaries; (ii) decentralizing management; (iii) sharing information with stakeholders; (vi) training staff in&#13;
participatory approaches; and (v) training beneficiaries. Each approach is discussed in detail below.&#13;
(a)     Transferring Participatory Approaches to Government Agencies and Intermediaries. Incorporating&#13;
mechanisms to transfer the participatory elements to regular government ministries, as well as other sponsoring&#13;
agencies (i.e., NGOs) is being pursued by the fund. During Phase 11, SFD is planning a training program for&#13;
ministry staff in management information during sub-project appraisal and execution. Given the important role&#13;
delegated to NGOs/intermediaries, SFD has allocated resources for assessing and strengthening their capacities, in&#13;
terms of beneficiary representation and development effectiveness. NGOs are evaluated during appraisal of a sub-&#13;
project, on the basis of criteria which indicate where training might be required. In response to the training needs&#13;
required by NGOs, a one year pilot program is being initiated in six governorates to benefit twenty NGOs with the&#13;
goal of building their institutional capacity.&#13;
(b)     Decentralizing Management.  The existence of ten regional and six satellite' offices facilitates the&#13;
implementation of a participatory approach throughout the sub-project cycle by allowing for close community&#13;
consultation. This has fostered a collaborative decision making process and forged links between community&#13;
organizations engaged in joint development activities.&#13;
(c)     Sharing Information with Stakeholders. The SFD employs a variety of mechanisms and strategies aimed at&#13;
fostering a participatory dialogue, which include information sharing and consultative sessions and workshops with&#13;
stakeholders (governorates, NGOs, and communities) during the promotion, and appraisal stages. In addition, these&#13;
efforts are complemented by beneficiary assessment, sub-project ex-post evaluations, and participatory rural&#13;
appraisal methods designed to evaluate and constantly improve project design in order to target the intended&#13;
beneficiaries more precisely, involve them in the sub-project cycle, and define the characteristics of the least&#13;
advantaged groups.&#13;
(d)     Training Staff in Participatory Approaches.  Involving staff (NGOs, and religious leaders) who have&#13;
worked with beneficiaries, has demonstrated success in designing and implementing sub-projects. Familiarity with&#13;
the cultural milieu, ability to communicate with the poor are assets which allow the fund to operate more&#13;
effectively. Fund staff receive training in participatory intervention methods in order to enable them to become&#13;
more responsive to the needs of the beneficiaries. During Phase 11 of the SFD, efforts should be made to introduce&#13;
an incentive structure that rewards staff for adhering to participatory procedures.&#13;
(e)     Training Beneficiaries In the case where beneficiaries do not have the requisite skills to prioritize, and/or&#13;
prepare proposals and/or technical designs, SFD provides technical assistance to help beneficiary groups prepare&#13;
The number of regional and satellite offices is not expected to increase over the life of the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 8&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
proposals and carry out technical design. In such instances extensive training and institutional strengthening&#13;
programs are provided to the stakeholders, with an emphasis on local planning, prioritization of needs, management,&#13;
monitoring, as well as operations and maintenance. This empowers beneficiaries to identify and prioritize their&#13;
needs to develop strategies to meet them.&#13;
Targeting&#13;
3.      Given it's mandate to mitigate the impact of economic adjustment on the poor and marginalized groups,&#13;
the SFD has fulfilled its aim at extensive coverage across the country. Priority target areas were selected based on a&#13;
targeting map prepared by SFD in 1992. The amounts of financing extended were weighed according to the relative&#13;
poverty rankings of each governorate. Data generated from the Central Agency for Public Mobilization and&#13;
Statistics (CAPMAS) has been used to occasionally supplement the original poverty map. Efforts are underway for&#13;
SFD to update it's poverty map and targeting mechanism in order to reflect the evolving nature of SFD, and the&#13;
current patterns of poverty in Egypt.&#13;
4.      Currently, SFD's geographic and sectoral resource allocations reflects both a demand and supply driven&#13;
nature.  It does not identify potential sub-projects but responds to proposals generated by beneficiaries or&#13;
intermediaries. Thus, those groups with the greatest ability to generate proposals are better positioned to benefit&#13;
from SFD funds, though typically they are not the neediest. SFD is attempting to reconcile the discrepancies&#13;
between demand and supply by streamlining targeting and promotion efforts in order to better respond to the poor.&#13;
During Phase I, SFD's activities focused on the disbursement of funds, and targeting was relegated to a secondary&#13;
role. Therefore, except for a recent pilot survey, limited data exists on SFD's targeting effectiveness. This situation&#13;
is quickly being revised, and staff at the fund are in the process of remedying this short-coming. Data on targeting&#13;
will be collected during promotional campaigns as well as desk and field appraisals using participatory approaches.&#13;
5.     Pilot Survey-Targeting. A recent pilot survey conducted in two Governorates (Minya and Beni Suef) to&#13;
assess the effectiveness of SFD's targeting mechanism was undertaken by the Project and Planning Department.&#13;
This was done to test some of the recommended Beneficiary Profile indicators in collaboration with the Community&#13;
Development Program and the Enterprise Development Program. Seven sub-projects (three in Beni-Suef and four&#13;
in Minya) out of 19 sub-projects were chosen based on the accessibility of sub-project sites. Varying numbers of&#13;
districts in which these sub-projects were operating were chosen for each sub-project. A sample of 5 percent of the&#13;
beneficiaries (100 percent of the beneficiaries, where the total number of beneficiaries was small) was chosen in&#13;
each selected district for each sub-project (amounting to a total sample of 903 beneficiaries). Beneficiary Profile&#13;
data were also collected for a sample of beneficiaries for two additional sub-projects (sample of 583 beneficiaries).&#13;
6.      The results of the CDP pilot highlighted that a large segment of beneficiaries in the literacy program in&#13;
Beni-Suef were women (54 percent); 68 percent of the beneficiaries of the Giza literacy program were illiterate and&#13;
the rest were drop-outs as opposed to 63 percent illiterate and 37 drop-outs. 42 percent of beneficiaries participating&#13;
in the Productive Families Project had assets of less than L.E.500 (US$150); and six of the 9 projects had&#13;
beneficiaries roughly of whom came from households with 7 or more members; and 20 percent of the beneficiaries&#13;
in the seven sub-project did not have access to sanitation facilities, indicating they were very poor.&#13;
7.      The methodology used for determining the beneficiaries from the Enterprise Development Program (EDP),&#13;
was taken from a total of 18 EDP sponsoring agencies that had been contracted and had received disbursements&#13;
from SFD. A sample of 8 agencies were chosen, A random sample of 10 percent of the loan recipients were&#13;
selected which amounted to 347 out of a total of 3480 loan recipients. The results indicated that in several&#13;
governorates, more than half the beneficiaries were women, and in other govemorates, most of the beneficiaries&#13;
were located in rural areas. In select cases, 33 percent of the beneficiaries had been unemployed prior to receiving&#13;
the EDP loan.&#13;
8.     The above information would require complementary data collected through BA, or a Needs and Capacity&#13;
Study. Nevertheless, in broad terms the results from the pilot indicated that specific SFD sub-projects are reaching&#13;
individuals who could be classified as "needy", suggesting that SFD's current targeting mechanism could be&#13;
achieving its intended beneficiaries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 8&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
9.      Given the evolving nature of SFD, target groups will have to be redefined to guide the design of each of&#13;
SFD's components. The existing socio-economic data which focuses on the governorate level needs to be narrowed&#13;
to the district, village, or community level, thereby enabling SFD to concentrate resources on those specific&#13;
locations that have the highest poverty/unemployment rates.&#13;
10.    Priority Ranking. Assigning a three-layered targeting and ranking methodology for the selection of sub-&#13;
projects for financing by SFD is being explored. This methodology used in other social funds, assigns priority ranks&#13;
of 1, 2 etc.. to: (a) intended target groups; (b) different types of sub-projects; and (c) the Governorates. The target&#13;
group rank would be regarded as the overriding rank; if two sub-projects had the same target group rank, the rank&#13;
for the sub-project type would determine which sub-project is chosen for financing. It two sub-projects had the&#13;
same target group rank and the same sub-project type rank, the rank for the governorate would determine the choice&#13;
of the sub-project for financing. The objective of the ranking exercise is to learn how the fund is doing in meeting&#13;
community needs. In addition to the above recommendation, it is imperative for SFD to apply targeting criteria&#13;
throughout the sub-project cycle, starting with promotion through implementation and supervision. During each&#13;
stage, using participatory methods for collecting data will also allow for a diagnostic self-assessment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 9: DETAILED PROJECT COST TABLES&#13;
Components Project Cost Summary&#13;
%       % Total&#13;
(L.E. Million)                 (US$ Million)    Foreign     Base&#13;
Local    Foreign      Total      Local   Foreign    Total   Exchange   Costs&#13;
Small-scale Labor Intensive Works    312.8         -        312.8      92.0         -     92.0           -       12&#13;
Community Development                707.2         -       707.2    208.0          -    208.0            -       27&#13;
Enterprise Development              1,203.6        -      1,203.6    354.0         -    354.0            -       46&#13;
Human Resources Development          204.8      67.2        272.0     60.2       19.8     80.0         25        10&#13;
Institutional Development            115.7      23.7        139.4     34.0       7.0      41.0         17         5&#13;
2,544.1     90.9      2,635.0    748.3      26.7    775.0           3       100&#13;
Physical Contingencies                   -         -            -         -        -         -          -&#13;
Price Contingencies                                           -                     -                   -&#13;
2,544.1     90.9      2,635.0    748.3      26 7     775.0          3       100&#13;
Expenditure Accounts Project Cost Summary&#13;
%         %%Total&#13;
(L.E. Million)                 (US$ Million)        Foreign       Base&#13;
Local    Foreign      Total      Local   Foreign    Total       Exchange        Costs&#13;
I. Investment Costs&#13;
Civil Works                   321.0         -       321.0      94.4         -       94.4               -        12&#13;
Equipment                     270.7       2.4       273.0      79.6       0.7       80.3               1        10&#13;
Credit Funds                 1,129.9        -      1,129.9    332.3         -      332.3                -       43&#13;
Technical Assistance          239.4      37.6       276.9      70.4      11.1       81.5              14        11&#13;
Training                      489.0      50.9       540.0    143.8       15.0      158.8               9        20&#13;
Total Investment Costs         2,449.9     90.9      2,540.8    720.6      26.7      747.3               4        96&#13;
II. Recurrent Costs&#13;
Salaries                       77.0         -        77.0      22.6         -       22.6               -         3&#13;
Operations &amp; Maintenance        17.3        -         17.3      5.1         -        5.1                -         1&#13;
Total Recurrent Costs             94.2        -         94.2     27.7         -       27.7                -        4&#13;
2,544.1     90.9      2,635 0    748.3      26.7     775.0                3       100&#13;
Expenditure Accounts by Components (US$ million)&#13;
Small-scale Labor  Community    Enterprise    Human Resources   Institutional&#13;
Intensive Works   Development  Development    Development    Development   Total&#13;
I. Investment Costs&#13;
Civil Works                           73.6         20.8              -                  -              -      94.4&#13;
Equipment                             13.8         62.4              -                  -            4.1      80.3&#13;
Credit Funds                             -         20.8          311.5                  -              -    332.3&#13;
Technical Assistance                   0.9          6.2           21.2               26.4           26.7      81.5&#13;
Training                               0.9         72.8           21.2               53.6           10.3    158.8&#13;
Total Investment Costs                 89.2        183.0          354.0               80.0           41.0    747.3&#13;
II. Recurrent Costs&#13;
Salaries                               1.8         20.8              -                  -              -      22.6&#13;
Operations &amp; Maintenance               0.9          4.2              -                  -              -       5.1&#13;
Total Recurrent Costs                   2.8         25.0              -                  -              -      27.7&#13;
92.0        208.0          354.0               80.0           41.0    775.0&#13;
Taxes&#13;
Foreign Exchange                         -            -              -               19.8            7.0      26.7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ARAB REPUBLIC OF EGYPT&#13;
POPULATION PROJECT&#13;
IBRD 27482&#13;
280                                320                                360,&#13;
Mediterraneon  Sea a                                                                       320&#13;
Marsa Matruh 0                Aiexondria:    Phe,tsaid                           KAtL    JORDAN&#13;
sh.ih I                                             ORDA&#13;
)                                             Damanhur anta rEI zxrt  &#13;
Shibin el Koni  V  -' lsmo,liya!&#13;
-.           QS~~~osez                I&#13;
CAIRd&#13;
|                                   ,~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~El Fayoumu     .j &#13;
ffj       A  R A    B    R  E  P U  B  L I C                1;CiSuef                                       SAUD&#13;
OF  EGYPT                      EIMinyao(                                                 SAUDI&#13;
- 280 j      _  _-- _  _- _  _  _  _  _  _   .    _  _  _  _ _  _ARABIA  28&#13;
I                                        ,~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~N'&#13;
0&#13;
,Asiut               Hurghoda&#13;
Sohog&#13;
0      SELECTED CITIES                                 oQena&#13;
|  *   NATIONAL CAPITAL                                  Luxor&#13;
RIVERS                                  Mataan0 /&#13;
CULTIVATED AREAS&#13;
-  -  -   GOVERNORATE BOUNDARIES&#13;
OCCUPIED TERRITORIES                                 Kom Ombo&#13;
240a                                                                             Asw-an                               240&#13;
Dom&#13;
0      50     100    150 MILES&#13;
II I , t&#13;
0   50  100 150 KILOMETERS&#13;
-f             - - ---  -  --    - --_  -   -   -    -  -    -   -    -   -   -- _   -  -    -   -    -   -   -   -   -   -   -   -_     - -    -  -    - - -&#13;
| rh boundaries. colors. d.rnssminotons nnd coy of her ,o!rsnooon&#13;
1 's,o,,fson du m-p do not-py, oo te prt of The World Baor             SUDAN&#13;
*  Group. any oudgrrert or, the legol trtotJ of any serotory, or any32&#13;
eodorseset or Ooceptn-e of such bo-nd,es                         32                                      36&#13;
MARCH 1996&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IMAGING&#13;
Report No:      15267 EGT&#13;
Type: SAR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="696598">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/04/696598/egypt-second-social-fund-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/04/696598/egypt-second-social-fund-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1996/04/696598/egypt-second-social-fund-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/04/25/000009265_3961022111536/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/04/25/000009265_3961022111536/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>2865</credit_no>
        <docdt>1996-04-25T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2001-04-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Egypt - Second Social Fund Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objectives of the Second Social Fund
            Project are to help: 1) create jobs through support of small
            enterprises and labor intensive works; and 2) support
            community infrastructure and services in partnership with
            nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) and local groups. The
            project will include the following programs: 1) small-scale
            labor intensive works program; 2) community development
            program; 3) enterprise development program; 4) human
            resource development program; and 5) institutional
            development program.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Egypt - Second Social Fund Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Egypt - Second Social Fund Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1996/04/696598/egypt-second-social-fund-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>EG-Social Fund II -- P043102</projn>
        <docty>Staff Appraisal Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Development Economics &amp; Aid Effectiveness,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Egypt, Arab Republic of</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe, Middle East and North Africa!$!107234</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>North Africa!$!80464</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3961022111536</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other social services,Micro- and SME finance</subsc>
        <admreg>Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1996</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Social Protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Community development; Human resources
            development; Labor intensity; Nongovernmental organizations;
            Small enterprises
            accounting,ADB,AIR,AUDITS,Autonomy,banking
            system,beneficiary assessments,commercial banks,Community
            Development,crowding,crowding
            out,decentralization,decentralization process,decision
            making,development activities,development
            partners,development programs,development projects,ECONOMIC
            ANALYSIS,economic development,economic growth,Economic
            Reform,economic situation,employment,Enterprise
            Development,Entrepreneurship,expenditures,families,family
            planning,financial performance,FISCAL YEAR,foreign
            exchange,girls,health care,income,inflation,Institutional
            Development,interest rates,intermediaries,International
            Development,laws,living conditions,living standards,local
            authorities,local government,local Governments,oil,oil
            prices,operating costs,overhead costs,partnership,political
            movements,priorities,private sector,privatization,public
            health,public sector,Purchasing Power,regional
            Governments,Resource Development,Resources
            Development,safety,screening,social safety nets,social
            services,solid waste collection,Structural
            Adjustment,SUSTAINABILITY,Targeted
            Interventions,TARGETING,technical
            assistance,unemployment,United Nations Development
            Program,waste,waste disposal,water supply,workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Human Development Group (MNSHD)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe, Middle East and North Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>North Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF035698-MENA REGION - SECTOR STRATEGY
            FOR EDUCATION,TF035116-YEMEN - SOCIAL FUND,TF034878-LEBANON - POVERTY ASSESSMENT,TF034581-EGYPT - PVO SECTOR STUDY -
            STUDY EXTENSION,TF032903-EUROPE AND MIDDLE EAST -
            EDUCATION (EGYPT, YEMEN, JORDAN),TF021678-SOCIAL FUND FOR DEVELOPMENT
            PROJECT II</trustfund>
        <repnb>15267</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Microenterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Funds and Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Zero Pillar</ml:concept><ml:concept>PIM Diagnostic Tool</ml:concept><ml:concept>Project Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Micro-enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Project Cycle Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Roads</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Egypt</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>