<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. 15364-IN&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
MARCH 7, 1996&#13;
Energy and Infrastructure Operations Division&#13;
Country Department II&#13;
South Asia Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
(As of February 1996)&#13;
Currency Unit = India Rupees (Rs)&#13;
Rs 1.00 = US$0.03&#13;
US$1.00 = Rs 35.0&#13;
Guarantor's and Borrower's Financial Year&#13;
April I - March 31&#13;
MEASURES AND EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Metric                               British/US System&#13;
I meter (m)                  =       3.281 feet&#13;
I square meter (m2)          =       10.764 square feet&#13;
I cubic meter (m2)           =       35.3 15 cubit feet&#13;
I kilometer (km)             =       0.621 mile&#13;
I metric ton                 =       2,205 pounds&#13;
I tkm                        =       ton-kilometer (0.621 ton-mile)&#13;
I pkm                        =       passenger-kilometer(0.621 passenger-mile)&#13;
ACRONYMS AND ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
ADB    =   Asian Development Bank            IFP            Infrastructure financing project&#13;
BOT    =    Build, operate and transfer      IL&amp;FS   =    Infrastructure Leasing and Financial Services&#13;
Limited&#13;
CARE  =   Credit Analysis and Research Ltd.  IPO       =    Initial public offering&#13;
CAS    =   Country assistance strategy       LIBOR   =    London interbank offered rate&#13;
CBI    =   Central Bank of India             MOST   =    Ministry of Surface Transport&#13;
CEM          Country economic memorandum    NBFC            Non-banking financial company&#13;
COD    =    Committee of directors           OD       =    Operational directive&#13;
CP      =   Commercial paper                 PRP       =    Performance-related pay&#13;
DEA    =    Department of Economic Affairs    PWD     =    Public works department&#13;
(Ministry of Finance)           R&amp;R      =    Resettlement and rehabilitation&#13;
ED      =    Executive Director              RBI       =    Reserve Bank of India&#13;
ERR    =    Economic rate of return          RMG       =    Risk management group&#13;
FYB    =    First-year benefits              SEBI    =    Security Exchange Board of India&#13;
GDP    =   Gross domestic product            SEC       =    Securities and Exchange Commission&#13;
GOI    =   Government of India               SPV       =    Special purpose vehicle&#13;
HDFC  =    Housing Development Finance       USAID   =   US Agency for International Development&#13;
Corporation&#13;
IFC     =    International Finance Corporation   UTI  =    Unit Trust of India&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
LOAN AND PROJECT SUMMARY&#13;
I - ECONOMIC  AND  SECTORAL  BACKGROUND   ........................                                              .......................     2&#13;
*    India's economic policies and  performance ...............................................................                            2&#13;
* Evolving a policy and an institutional framework for private investment in&#13;
infrastructure   ................................................................                                               3&#13;
*    The Bank's assistance strategy  in the infrastructure sector .......................................                                  4&#13;
11- INFRASTRUCTURE LEASING AND FINANCIAL SERVICES LIMITED&#13;
(IL&amp;FS) ................................................................6&#13;
- The company ...............................................................                                                              6&#13;
*    Regulations and  operating  policies ................................................................9&#13;
*    IL&amp;FS's current operations ...............................................................                                           10&#13;
*    Future strategy  and  financial perfonnance ...............................................................                          12&#13;
III - THE  PROJECT  ...............................................................                                                       16&#13;
*  Project objectives.                     ...................             ............................................    16&#13;
*    Project description ...............................................................                                                  16&#13;
*    Indicative pipeline of subprojects ....................................                         ...........................          17&#13;
*    Project cost and financing  plan ...............................................................                                     17&#13;
*    Project implementation  and monitoring    ...............................................................                            19&#13;
*    Procurement ...............................................................                                                         20&#13;
*    Security  arrangements ...............................................................                                              21&#13;
*    Onlending  and  disbursement ......................                            .........................................            22&#13;
*    Environmental and  social considerations ...............................................................                            24&#13;
The project was prepared bv a team composed of Mmes. Joelle Chassard (Task manager, SA2EI),&#13;
Susan Morse (Financial Consultant), Jelena Pantelic (SA2El), and E. Schaengold (ASTHR), and&#13;
Messrs. Syed Ahmed (LEGSA), Raul Auzmendi (Transport Consultant), Chandra Godavitarne&#13;
(SA2RS), Harald Hansen (SA2EI), P. Illangovan (ASTEN), and I. U.B. Reddy (SA2RS). Mmes. A.&#13;
Armstrong, V. Scott and 0. Valladolid assisted in the production of the report. The peer reviewers&#13;
were Messrs. Hoon Mok Chung (ASTDR), John Flora (TWUTD), and Michael Klein (PSD). The&#13;
report was endorsed by Messrs. Heinz Vergin, Director (SA2) and Jean-Fran,ois Bauer, Chief&#13;
(SA2EI).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IV  - PROJECT  JUSTIFICATION   .......................................                     .........................     26&#13;
*   Project sustainability ...............................................................                               26&#13;
*   Economic analysis ...............................................................                                    26&#13;
*   Benefits ...............................................................                                             27&#13;
*   Risks ...............................................................                                                27&#13;
V  - AGREEMENTS AND  RECOMMENDATION ..................................................                                   30&#13;
*   Agreements ...............................................................                                           30&#13;
*   Recommendation  ...............................................................                                      31&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
2.1  IL&amp;FS: composition of the Board of Directors .32&#13;
2.2 IL&amp;FS: organization chart .33&#13;
2.3  Implementation of a cost accounting system .34&#13;
2.4       IL&amp;FS: exposure limits for commercial infrastructure projects and limits to&#13;
investments in affiliates .35&#13;
2.5       IL&amp;FS: income statements, cash flow  statements, balance sheets, and&#13;
selected financial ratios (1991/92 - 2000-01 .36-42&#13;
2.6  IL&amp;FS's financial forecast: sensitivity analysis .43-44&#13;
3.1  Subproject eligibility criteria .45-47&#13;
3.2  Subproject pipeline and implementation schedule .48-55&#13;
3.3    IL&amp;FS's proposed training and technical assistance activities (summary)                                            56-58&#13;
3.4 IL,&amp;FS's project ccle .59-61&#13;
3.5  Subproject evaluation report .62-64&#13;
3.6  Performance monitoring indicators .65&#13;
3.7 Supervision plan .66-67&#13;
3.8  Selection of BOT operators .68-70&#13;
3.9  IL&amp;FS's pari passu security structure .71-73&#13;
3.10   IL&amp;FS: foreign exchange risk management and treasury operations                                                   74-75&#13;
3.11  Environmiient and social report (ESR) .76-90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
LOAN AND PROJECT SUMMARY&#13;
Borrowers:               - India, acting by its President (for the IDA credit)&#13;
- Infrastructure Leasing and Financial Services Limited&#13;
(IL&amp;FS) (for the IBRD loan)&#13;
Guarantor:               India, acting by its President (for the loan to IL&amp;FS)&#13;
Beneficiaries:           Public sector agencies; special purpose entities established for&#13;
the construction and operation of commercial infrastructure&#13;
projects&#13;
Poverty:                 Not applicable&#13;
Amounts:                 - SDR3.4 million (US$5 million equivalent) (for the credit to&#13;
India)&#13;
- US$200 million (for the loan to IL&amp;FS)&#13;
Terms:                   - For the credit to India: repayment over 35 years.&#13;
- For the loan to IL&amp;FS: repayment over a 20-year period,&#13;
including 5 years of grace. Standard interest rate for LIBOR-&#13;
based single currency loans.&#13;
Commitment fee:          - For the credit to India: 0.50% on undisbursed balances,&#13;
beginning 60 days after signing, less any waiver.&#13;
- For the loan to IL&amp;FS: 0.75% on undisbursed loan balances,&#13;
beginning 60 days after signing, less any waiver.&#13;
Onlending terms:         Proceeds of the Bank loan will be onlent either (i) in rupees at a&#13;
market-determined rate. In this case, IL&amp;FS will bear the&#13;
foreign exchange risk; or (ii) in US dollars at a variable market-&#13;
determined rate. The tenor of the subloans will vary between&#13;
17 and 20 years.&#13;
Proceeds of the IDA credit will be onlent on the standard terms&#13;
and conditions for central assistance to the states applicable at&#13;
the time.&#13;
Financing plan:          See para. 3.06.&#13;
Net Present Value:       Not applicable&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
STAFF APPRAISAL REPORT&#13;
I - ECONOMIC AND SECTORAL BACKGROUND&#13;
India's economic policies and performance&#13;
1.01  In mid-1991 India's development strategy took a radical turn when, in response to a&#13;
severe macroeconomic crisis, the new government launched an ambitious program of&#13;
economic reforms. The program did not limit itself to restoring macroeconomic stability. It&#13;
also reoriented structural policies governing the investment regime, foreign trade, the&#13;
financial sector, taxation, and public enterprises. As a result, almost all areas of the economy&#13;
have been opened to domestic and foreign private investment. Import licensing restrictions&#13;
on intermediate and capital goods have been virtually eliminated. Tariffs have been&#13;
significantly reduced and full convertibility has been established for current account&#13;
transactions. In the financial sector, prudential regulations that meet international standards&#13;
have been introduced; banks now have significantly more discretion in their lending&#13;
decisions; financial markets have been liberalized; and entry restrictions have been&#13;
eliminated. The external accounts have strengthened considerably and, although still a major&#13;
obstacle to higher growth, central fiscal imbalances have been lowered. The result has been a&#13;
rebouncing of the economy, helped by an unprecedented sequence of good monsoons and a&#13;
strong industrial recovery. GDP growth has been steadily increasing, from 1% p.a. in 1991-&#13;
92 to an estimated 5.8% in the current financial year. The robust performance of the Indian&#13;
economy is thus a testimony to the continuing favorable impacts of the liberalization and&#13;
reform efforts.&#13;
1.02  There are daunting challenges ahead. Paramount among them is that of meeting the&#13;
needs of a rapidly-growing population while reducing the incidence of poverty, in a country&#13;
with limited land and water resources, limited capital, and enormous social needs. In the next&#13;
30 years, even taking into account ongoing family planning efforts, India's population is&#13;
expected to increase by another 450 million. This "third India" will put enormous additional&#13;
pressure on the country's natural resources, social programs, and already strained&#13;
infrastructure. With the pace of urbanization accelerating, the consequences of population&#13;
growth will be particularly serious in urban areas where the provision of sanitation and public&#13;
health services as well as infrastructure is already below standard, and the absolute number of&#13;
poor is increasing.&#13;
1.03  The structural reforms introduced over the last four years have gone a long way in&#13;
reorienting India's development strategy to meet these challenges. For example, the private&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
sector now plays a much more important role in India's development process, and an&#13;
incentive regime more conducive to a pattern of labor-intensive growth is being established.&#13;
However, there still remains a large "unfinished" reform agenda which will take several more&#13;
years to implement. Improving the fiscal situation, particularly with regard to states'&#13;
finances, is of critical importance. Equally important is the need to conclude the process of&#13;
structural reforms started in 1991 (e.g., in international trade, the financial system, the tax&#13;
regime, and public enterprises). Finally, reforms need to be extended to key sectors of the&#13;
economy, an issue where the participation of the states is critical because of their important&#13;
role in formulating and implementing sector policies. This is the case in agriculture, the&#13;
social sectors, and particularly infrastructure.&#13;
Evolving a policy and an institutionalframework/for private investment in infrastructure&#13;
1.04  The expansion and efficient use of infrastructure is fast becoming one of India's key&#13;
development issues. Of grave concern today is the risk that poor infrastructure will&#13;
undermine severely India's ability to achieve its medium- and long-term objectives of higher&#13;
and sustainable economic growth. At the root of the problem is a severe absorptive capacity&#13;
and implementation constraint which, combined with a financial constraint, has led to&#13;
chronic underinvestment in the sector and a less than optimal use of the funds available.&#13;
Implementation of public sector infrastructure projects has generally been slow, with frequent&#13;
cost overruns and inadequate construction quality. Addressing the situation requires, above&#13;
all, a redefinition of the role of the public sector in the provision of infrastructure and the&#13;
establishment of an appropriate legal, regulatory and administrative framework for private&#13;
investment so that the latter can assume a dynamic role in areas from which it has been&#13;
mostly excluded so far (telecommunications, power, ports, roads, urban infrastructure, water&#13;
supply). The impetus for change has to come primarily from the central and state&#13;
governments. A number of legislative steps and policy announcements have already been&#13;
made in that direction. In September 1991, the Electricity (Supply) Act of 1948 was&#13;
amended to permit private domestic and foreign investment in power. GOI's Telecom Policy&#13;
statement of May 1994 launched the liberalization of the telecommunications sector. Finally,&#13;
the May 1995 amendment to the National Highway Act, 1956 permits private sector&#13;
participation in the development and maintenance of national highways and expressways.&#13;
The removal offormal barriers to private investment must now be followed by the&#13;
establishment of policy and institutional frameworks fully supportive of such investment.&#13;
1.05  The existing regulatory framework was formulated with the public sector in mind and&#13;
is not appropriate to encourage the massive private investments India needs in these areas.&#13;
Regulations governing entry, pricing in monopolistic conditions, the conduct of regulatory&#13;
authorities, dispute resolution and arbitration are either aimed at preventing private&#13;
investment or, in cases where the private sector is allowed, lead to inefficient investment.&#13;
The lack of finance on terms commensurate with the typical long gestation and revenue-&#13;
earning capacity of infrastructure projects is also slowing down the pace of private&#13;
investment in the sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Bank's assistance strategy in the infrastructure sector&#13;
1.06  Assistance on these policy issues has therefore received growing importance in the&#13;
Bank's work. The Bank group has pursued it through a variety of means. A substantial&#13;
amount of technical assistance has been provided in the context of loans or through the&#13;
administration of bilateral grants. In power for example, through the combination of project&#13;
preparation (e.g., proposed Orissa state power restructuring project, and similar operations in&#13;
Haryana, Uttar Pradesh, Bihar and Rajasthan), bilaterally-funded technical assistance&#13;
programs, the ongoing technical assistance project for private power development, and the&#13;
preparation of a guarantee framework for private investments in power, considerable progress&#13;
has been achieved towards fundamental power sector reforms and the removal of essential&#13;
barriers to private investment. Similarly, in the telecoms sector, bilaterally-funded technical&#13;
assistance has enabled the Bank to assist in laying the ground for a regulatory framework&#13;
conducive to private sector entry. A port sector report provided the basis for our policy&#13;
dialogue in this area. In its sequel, the Bank has extended technical advice on the preparation&#13;
of international standard tender documents to induce private investment in new facilities and&#13;
in the management of existing facilities.&#13;
1.07   By contrast, our involvement in assisting in the establishment of an enabling&#13;
environment for private investment has been comparatively less intensive in the roads, water&#13;
supply and urban infrastructure sectors, partly because of the diversity of counterparts with&#13;
whom one needs to work (GOI, state governments, local governments, municipal&#13;
authorities). This is where the Bank's technical assistance is turning to now. A transport&#13;
sector report as well as the specific review, in the 1995 Country Economic Memorandum&#13;
(CEM), of bottlenecks to private investment in the roads sector have provided a valuable&#13;
opening for a dialogue on these issues. An urban infrastructure review is now under&#13;
preparation. Discussions are also underway for putting in place a program of assistance to&#13;
the Ministry of Surface Transport (MOST) to help develop a comprehensive regulatory and&#13;
administrative framework for private investment in the national highway sector and&#13;
providing technical advice to GOI for facilitating such private investment. In this sector,&#13;
however, as well as in water supply and urban infrastructure, much more needs to be done at&#13;
the state and local levels to enable efficient planning and implementation of private&#13;
investments.&#13;
1.08  In response to a request by Indian authorities, the Bank's latest country assistance&#13;
strategy (CAS) for FY96-98 proposes to increase the Bank's assistance in establishing an&#13;
environment conducive to efficient private investment in infrastructure. Direct lending&#13;
continues to be envisaged to power, roads and urban infrastructure but all loans in these areas&#13;
would be policy-based investment operations. At the Government's request, in those sectors&#13;
as well as in telecommunications and ports where there is already considerable private sector&#13;
willingness to invest, the Bank is considering providing private investors in infrastructure&#13;
with term financing through financial intermediaries. Such operations are designed to&#13;
support the establishment of policies and regulations conducive to efficient private&#13;
investment in infrastructure, using the intermediaries' interest in getting the framework right&#13;
(as tested in the telecoms sector). They are expected to play a catalytical role in mobilizing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
finance for private investment in infrastructure with more appropriate maturities than those&#13;
currently available. They will also assist financial intermediaries in developing appraisal and&#13;
risk evaluation procedures for large private infrastructure projects -- an area in which India's&#13;
financial sector has limited experience.&#13;
1.09  In this context, the first step was taken in September 1995 by restructuring the&#13;
ongoing Tamil Nadu Urban Development Project (Cr. 1923-IN) and promoting the entry of a&#13;
private fund manager to commercially manage the mix of public and private sources of&#13;
finance provided to the Municipal Development Fund. This is the first attempt made in one&#13;
state to establish a joint public-private partnership in the municipal infrastructure area. This&#13;
project is expected to provide a replicable regulatory and administrative environment for&#13;
investment -- public, private or mixed -- in municipal infrastructure.&#13;
1.10   The proposed Project is the second initiative. It seizes upon a unique opportunity&#13;
provided by Infrastructure Leasing and Financial Services Ltd (IL&amp;FS), a 51% privately-&#13;
owned finance company with strong ties to the public sector. By supporting IL&amp;FS's&#13;
expansion in this area, the focus of the Bank is to assist first hand in the development of&#13;
prototype contractual arrangements for private investment in IL&amp;FS's areas of involvement&#13;
(urban bypasses and bridges, water supply and sewerage, effluent treatment, and other&#13;
municipal infrastructure), thereby facilitating entry of the private sector on a much larger&#13;
scale in areas heretofore dominated by the public sector. It is a "process" operation whereby&#13;
the Bank uses IL&amp;FS as a vehicle to build up India's capacity to attract private investment in&#13;
infrastructure, pilot-test institutional and contractual arrangements in a variety of subprojects&#13;
under various administrative and political conditions, and help establish a track record as a&#13;
pre-requisite for large-scale private investment in the sector. GOI has selected IL&amp;FS as the&#13;
first financial intermediary to receive the Bank's support given the pioneering role it is&#13;
already playing in promoting private investment in infrastructure, its exceptional&#13;
understanding of the synergy required between public and private interests for successful&#13;
infrastructure development, its highly competent and innovative staff, and its high-quality&#13;
Board.&#13;
1.11   The third and much larger operation is the proposed Infrastructure Financing Project&#13;
(IFP) (FY98). With the removal of major policy and administrative barriers to private&#13;
investment in infrastructure through previous lending operations, sector work and TA&#13;
programs, financing on a much larger scale will then be possible. It is envisaged therefore to&#13;
expand the scope of the Bank's assistance significantly by involving several public financial&#13;
institutions and use the IFP as a vehicle to promote financial policy reforms aimed at&#13;
developing a domestic long-term debt market. The proposed agenda of reforms contains the&#13;
following key elements: (i) changing the investment guidelines applicable to, and increasing&#13;
competition among, contractual savings institutions; (ii) fostering the development of&#13;
benchmark interest rates; (iii) encouraging active management by institutions of their&#13;
securities portfolios; (iv) reducing transaction taxes; (v) rationalizing debt market regulations;&#13;
and (vi) establishing a secure clearing and settlement system for corporate debt services.&#13;
The sequencing and pace of the reforms will influence the speed at which the proposed&#13;
operation can be processed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
11- INFRASTRUCTRE LEASING AND FINANCIAL SERVICES LIMITED (IL&amp;FS)&#13;
The company&#13;
2.01  Ownership. In 1983, the Banking Regulation Act of 1949 was amended to allow&#13;
Indian commercial banks to enter the leasing business through separate subsidiaries. Central&#13;
Bank of India (CBI), a major nationalized commercial bank, decided to promote its leasing&#13;
activities through a joint venture with Unit Trust of India (UTI), a public sector mutual fund&#13;
management, and Housing Development Finance Corporation Ltd. (HDFC), the country's&#13;
leading private housing finance institution. The result was the establishment of Infrastructure&#13;
Leasing and Financial Services Limited (IL&amp;FS) in 1987. Actual operations began in 1988&#13;
with the owners contributing Rs.60 million (about US$2 million) in the following&#13;
proportions: CBI (50.5%), UTI (30.5%), and HDFC (19%).&#13;
2.02  IL&amp;FS has since broadened its shareholder base not only to increase capital, but also&#13;
to strengthen business relationships and develop strategic alliances. For example, the&#13;
Intemational Finance Corporation (IFC) and, subsequently, ORIX Corporation, a Japanese&#13;
financial services company, were inducted as new shareholders in 1993 when the original&#13;
promoters diluted their equity stake in the company. More recently, in order to: (a) raise&#13;
capital, (b) broaden its name recognition in the public eye for further business development,&#13;
and (c) establish a "market" price for its shares, IL&amp;FS decided to proceed with an initial&#13;
public offering (IPO) equivalent to 25% of its enlarged capital. Due to the poor performance&#13;
of the capital markets, this issue has been temporarily warehoused with UTI; its launching is&#13;
now expected to take place in mid-1996. Once the IPO is completed, the ownership structure&#13;
of IL&amp;FS will be as shown in Figure 2. 1.&#13;
Figure 2.1 - IL&amp;FS's ownership structure&#13;
(Shareholding of common stock)&#13;
HDFC       IFC    IL&amp;FS&#13;
Orix      9%         9%    employees&#13;
IS%     _                    4%&#13;
Retail Investors&#13;
25%&#13;
UTI&#13;
18%              CBI&#13;
20%&#13;
2.03  Board of Directors. The Board of Directors was initially constituted solely by&#13;
representatives of the three promoting institutions. In 1990, it was broadened to include a&#13;
number of prominent individuals from both the private and public sectors. It was again&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
restructured in 1995 to create 4 executive directorships that were filled by senior management&#13;
of the company. Annex 2.1 provides the current composition of IL&amp;FS's Board. The Board&#13;
meets every two months; it takes all policy decisions for the company and considers&#13;
approvals of business transactions of a significant value. It is well structured, with&#13;
representatives of all shareholders, government, private sector and employees. As IL&amp;FS's&#13;
business expands into commercial infrastructure projects, and to enhance the Board's&#13;
oversight function in this area, it might soon be desirable to appoint to the Board one or two&#13;
individuals with a strong private sector background in infrastructure development, finance or&#13;
construction. As a complement, IL&amp;FS may expand the practice of setting up panels of local&#13;
and international experts to assist Board members and senior management in decision-&#13;
making and implementation'. Given the significant role the Board plays in the conduct of&#13;
IL&amp;FS's operations, it would be beneficial to the Bank to be kept informed of the Board's&#13;
agenda of deliberations. Agreement was reached at negotiations that IL&amp;FS will provide to&#13;
the Bank, within 30 days after any meeting of its Board, the agenda of such meeting,&#13;
including all documents that were forwarded and considered at such meeting.&#13;
2.04   Management. Day-to-day management of the company, including major credit&#13;
investment and underwriting proposals subject to Board-established guidelines, is entrusted&#13;
to the Managing Director, who is assisted by four Executive Directors (EDs), who together&#13;
form the Committee of Directors (COD). Annex 2.2 provides a summary of the&#13;
organizational structure of the company. IL&amp;FS is managed in a flexible manner such that&#13;
assignments are often handled by ad hoc, interdisciplinary task groups. Considerable effort&#13;
has gone into corporate planning and management philosophy resulting in a well thought-out&#13;
corporate business plan and well-executed strategic plans (para. 2.14). The management&#13;
team (which has virtually been intact since the founding of the company) is aware of the&#13;
strengths and weaknesses of the corporation and has formulated strategies to compete with&#13;
much larger organizations both for new business and for human resources. One pillar of&#13;
IL&amp;FS's development strategy has been to forge relationships with a wide array of&#13;
international partners, either through joint ventures or cooperation agreements, so that the&#13;
company can position itself as a quality player in its mandated areas of operations and ensure&#13;
it has access to international technology and training2.&#13;
2.05    Staff and training. IL&amp;FS is a relatively lean organization; it employs a total of 189&#13;
staff, of which 126 are professional. The company has tended to bring in professionals with&#13;
substantial experience and has refrained from campus-based recruitment. Professional&#13;
careers are managed to give individuals varied exposure to the company's activities; to&#13;
facilitate this, IL&amp;FS has developed a modular organization structure with a high degree of&#13;
autonomy, and a work ethos which fosters independence and entrepreneurial behavior. To&#13;
Expert panels are already being established in the area of urban infrastructure and telecoms. Similar panels should be&#13;
considered for roads and water supply projects for example.&#13;
2   One example of such relationship has been the appointment of IL&amp;FS as country advisor to Oppenheimer &amp;&#13;
Company Inc. (USA) for their offshore country fund, the "India Fund Inc.". In that process, IL&amp;FS has registered&#13;
with the US Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) as an "Investment Advisor", an impressive achievement&#13;
given the rigorous SEC filing criteria.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
motivate and retain competent professionals in a highly-competitive job market, the company&#13;
has evolved a variety of forward-looking remuneration strategies such as stock options, a&#13;
performance-related pay (PRP) program involving an appropriation of 5% of yearly net&#13;
profits -- the first such program to be offered in India by a financial institution -- and career&#13;
growth through joint ventures. As the company recruits only experienced staff, it does not&#13;
have a systematic training program for new entrants. However, it does provide training on&#13;
an ad hoc basis. Until now, training expenditures have remained relatively low. As IL&amp;FS&#13;
is embarking on a major move into the infrastructure business where little experience has yet&#13;
been gathered in India, it is building up its institutional capacity and plans to provide its&#13;
Projects staff with structured training programs to help them in the delivery of their&#13;
responsibilities, particularly in identification, evaluation, implementation monitoring, and&#13;
quality assurance functions (para. 3.07).&#13;
2.06   Systems and controls. financial reporting and audit. IL&amp;FS has in place well-&#13;
developed, high-quality accounting systems and internal auditing arrangements. The&#13;
principal instrument for management control is a budget which is approved by the Board.&#13;
IL&amp;FS uses a reputable firm of chartered accountants as external auditor. A formal system&#13;
has been in place since January 1993 to ensure compliance with: (i) the covenants and&#13;
investment agreements entered into with creditors and shareholders; (ii) the company's credit&#13;
policies and procedures, including those stipulated in its Operating Framework (para. 2.10);&#13;
and (iii) statutory and regulatory requirements. Following the establishment of regional&#13;
offices in Delhi and Bangalore, the company has further strengthened its accounting system&#13;
to better monitor the operations of its various profit centers from a geographical perspective.&#13;
It now needs to build up its capacity to carefully monitor the profitability of individual&#13;
products marketed by the company. This has clearly not been a problem until now: the&#13;
company has remained of a manageable size, thus enabling its senior management to keep&#13;
good track of the various business activities and their relative profitability. As the company&#13;
grows rapidly and the number of product lines multiplies -- as is currently anticipated -- such&#13;
monitoring will become increasingly difficult and therefore needs to be cast within a more&#13;
systematic framework. A comprehensive cost accounting system by product line thus needs&#13;
to be put in place (Annex 2.3 provides details on the general purpose of such a system).&#13;
During negotiations, agreement was reached that IL&amp;FS will establish and implement a&#13;
comprehensive cost accounting system by product line no later than March 31, 1997.&#13;
2.07  IL&amp;FS follows internationally accepted commercial accounting standards in&#13;
preparing its financial statements. The latter are presented in a format that meets the&#13;
requirements of the Indian Companies Act, 1956. These requirements, however, are better&#13;
suited for manufacturing companies than for financial institutions such as IL&amp;FS and make it&#13;
more difficult to interpret the company's financial situation. The reports submitted to the&#13;
Board for the annual budget provide a more comprehensible picture of IL&amp;FS's financial&#13;
performance. Agreement was reached at negotiations that IL&amp;FS will submit to the Bank by&#13;
June 30 of each year its annual audited accounts in the format required by the Companies Act&#13;
as well as its financial statements presented in the budget format and duly certified by the&#13;
auditor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9-&#13;
Regulations and operating policies&#13;
2.08   IL&amp;FS is a non-banking financial company (NBFC) regulated by the Reserve Bank&#13;
of India (RBI) under its NBFC (Reserve Bank) Directions, 1977, as amended (the&#13;
Directions). In addition, it is a company incorporated under the Indian Companies Act, 1956.&#13;
IL&amp;FS is recognized as a Category I Merchant Banker under the Security Exchange Board of&#13;
India (SEBI) Act. Its activities are monitored by the Department of Financial Companies of&#13;
the RBI, which performs inspections and reviews the portfolio and quarterly reports&#13;
submitted by IL&amp;FS for capital adequacy, asset quality, etc. IL&amp;FS is in general compliance&#13;
with all the applicable regulations.&#13;
2.09   Under the Directions, IL&amp;FS has been historically classified as an equipment leasing&#13;
company. In November 1994 it applied to RBI seeking a new NBFC classification given its&#13;
unique positioning in the infrastructure sector. This initiative was taken by IL&amp;FS as the&#13;
company is not currently meeting the RBI standards applicable to equipment leasing&#13;
companies3. In January 1996, RBI informed IL&amp;FS of its decision to retain the existing&#13;
classification of the company as an equipment leasing company until March 31, 1997 while&#13;
acknowledging IL&amp;FS's intention to make leasing and infrastructure finance its principal&#13;
business4. During negotiations, agreement was reached that any material modification to the&#13;
existing regulatory framework applicable to IL&amp;FS, that adversely affects the operations of&#13;
the company, will be an event of default under the loan.&#13;
2.10   In addition to the guidelines contained in the above-mentioned regulations, IL&amp;FS&#13;
has developed a comprehensive Operating Framework that spells out (i) the company's&#13;
operating policy, (ii) its risk management framework and policies, and (iii) guidelines and&#13;
framework of operations. The Framework was updated in July 1995 to reflect the company's&#13;
planned expanded involvement in commercial infrastructure projects. In particular, its risk&#13;
management framework and policies now set out in an extensive manner IL&amp;FS's risk&#13;
management philosophy and process, provides a detailed analysis of the types of risks&#13;
associated with its various activities, and proposes an array of risk mitigation measures to be&#13;
carefully monitored internally through a well-defined allocation of responsibilities5. In&#13;
general, the Operating Framework sets sound management principles. However, in some&#13;
instances, investment exposure limits are presented more as guidelines than strict ceilings&#13;
beyond which no further exposure should be taken. In these cases, the language of the&#13;
3   Such companies are required to have at least 50% of their assets in equipment leasing and hire-purchase business&#13;
taken together and earn at least 50% of their income from such business activities. IL&amp;FS does not wish to undertake&#13;
hire-purchase activities to meet the 50% requirement as the corporate sector (its main client base) is not amenable to&#13;
such activity. Given applicable fiscal and accounting norms, it is also not feasible ordinarily for an NBFC to have&#13;
leased assets equivalent to 50% of its portfolio.&#13;
4   As a result. leasing and infrastructure assets will be considered together in the calculation of the applicable standards.&#13;
5   Because of the increasing complexity of risk management. IL&amp;FS is planning to institute a "Risk Management&#13;
System" that would be entrusted to a Risk Management Group (RMG). The responsibility of the RMG, inter alia,&#13;
would include assisting IL&amp;FS's business managers in evaluating various risks in their business areas, initiate risk&#13;
mitigation steps. reporting risks to the various management levels for corrective actions, and ensuring compliance of&#13;
directives laid by the Board or the COD.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10-&#13;
Framework needs to be tightened accordingly. Furthermore, three specific aspects related to&#13;
the company's investment in commercial infrastructure projects need to be revised: (i)&#13;
because of the inherent risks associated with this type of projects, particularly with India's&#13;
and IL&amp;FS's limited track record in this area, it is considered more prudent that IL&amp;FS limit&#13;
its credit exposure to infrastructure projects to one third of the company's total credit&#13;
exposure (instead of the 40% of total assets currently provided for in the Framework). This&#13;
would ensure a careful balance between leaving enough room for IL&amp;FS to develop its&#13;
infrastructure business and ensuring that, as a result, it does not take excessive risks that&#13;
could threaten its fundamentally sound financial position; (ii) it is important to preserve the&#13;
integrity of lending decisions in those cases where IL&amp;FS may be both a significant equity&#13;
investor in and a lender to the same commercial infrastructure project entities; thus the sum&#13;
total of investments (including equity, loans and guarantees) in affiliates of the company&#13;
should not exceed 30% of IL&amp;FS's net worth; and (iii) when considering IL&amp;FS's total&#13;
equity investments -- which should not exceed its net worth -- all expenditures incurred by&#13;
IL&amp;FS on commercial infrastructure projects prior to financial closure should be treated as&#13;
equity. In close consultation with IFC, the Bank discussed with IL&amp;FS a proposal for&#13;
revising the related sections of the risk management framework that reflects the specific&#13;
conditions under which these projects will be implemented and the risks they will entail. The&#13;
agreed version is presented in Annex 2.4. During negotiations, agreement was reached that,&#13;
as a condition of loan effectiveness, IL&amp;FS will revise its Operating Framework to (i) set&#13;
definite investment exposure limits instead of guidelines, (ii) limit to one third of its total&#13;
credit exposure, IL&amp;FS's credit exposure to infrastructure projects, as calculated in&#13;
accordance with a methodology satisfactory to the Bank, (iii) limit to 30% of the company's&#13;
net worth its aggregate investments in entities in which its share in the paid-in capital is more&#13;
than 33 1/3%, and (iv) treat as equity all expenditures incurred by IL&amp;FS on infrastructure&#13;
projects prior to financial closure. In addition, agreement was reached that (i) IL&amp;FS will&#13;
continue to conduct its operations in accordance with the principles and procedures&#13;
enunciated in its revised Operating Framework, and (ii) any material modification to the&#13;
Operating Framework, without prior approval of the Bank, will be an event of default under&#13;
the loan.&#13;
IL&amp;FS's current operations&#13;
2.11   Assets. IL&amp;FS is engaged in lease and loan financing -- which constitutes its core&#13;
business -- as well as merchant banking and other financial activities. It is today one of the 5&#13;
largest and best regarded non-bank finance companies (NBFCs) in India; it is currently rated&#13;
"AAA" by Credit Analysis and Research Ltd. (CARE), one of the 3 Indian credit rating&#13;
agencies. Since the company was founded, revenues and net profit after tax have increased at&#13;
an average annual rate of 56% and 57%, respectively. Its assets have grown from Rs.734&#13;
million (US$44 million) in its first year of operation (FY88/89) to Rs. 13.2 billion (US$418&#13;
million) in FY94/95 -- an impressive growth rate of over 50% per year in local currency and&#13;
over 40% in US$ dollar terms. It has successfully built up its balance sheet with a safe, but&#13;
not overly profitable, lending and leasing business. As of March 31, 1995, loans and leases&#13;
accounted for 77% of the company's total assets and 76% of its income. The leasing&#13;
business is attractive to IL&amp;FS as the company benefits from accelerated tax depreciation on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- Il -&#13;
its leased assets6. The core lending and leasing business is restricted to the country's top 60&#13;
corporate groups as well as creditworthy public sector agencies, which has meant that,&#13;
although risks are low, competition in this segment has limited profitability. IL&amp;FS tries to&#13;
differentiate itself from its competitors by providing products which are customized to client&#13;
needs. The quality of the lease and loan portfolio is good and has seen a marked&#13;
improvement over the last three years; it reflects not only the large, high-quality client base,&#13;
but also the company's tight credit control and portfolio management.7 In parallel with the&#13;
core business of lending and leasing, an investment banking business has evolved since&#13;
IL&amp;FS's inception. Asset-based investment banking activities are mainly securities&#13;
investment and trading, and property development. A growing area of business for IL&amp;FS is&#13;
now its fee-based investment banking activities: asset management, corporate and project&#13;
advisory work, and underwriting and issue management. To date, the contribution of the&#13;
bottom line of these activities has been modest, but its growth is a key component of&#13;
IL&amp;FS's business strategy (para. 2.15). IL&amp;FS is also engaged in the development of&#13;
various new businesses -- through the establishment of joint ventures -- most of which are a&#13;
logical extension of current activities that will give rise to new financial products or will&#13;
increase investment banking services that IL&amp;FS can offer. The breakdown of IL&amp;FS's&#13;
assets as of March 31, 1995 is presented in Figure 2.2 below.&#13;
Figure 2.2 - Breakdown of IL&amp;FS's assets&#13;
(as of March 31, 1995)&#13;
Investment    Infrast. devt   Joint&#13;
banking     &amp; financing  ventures&#13;
assets         1%         4%     Others&#13;
16l                               7%&#13;
Leasing                              Loans &amp;&#13;
25%                                debentures&#13;
47%&#13;
2.12   Funding. Historically, IL&amp;FS has sourced its resource requirements through the&#13;
induction of new shareholders, and through its credit lines from commercial banks, Indian&#13;
financial institutions and multilateral agencies. Over the past few years, it has dramatically&#13;
changed its resource base. IL&amp;FS began as a subsidiary of a bank (CBI), which, along with&#13;
6   The volume of leasing in each year is set in order to bring IL&amp;FS's taxable income to zero.&#13;
7   As of March 3 I. 1995, arrears on leases over 90 days represented 0.3% of total lease receivables; arrears on loans&#13;
over 90 days accounted for 0. 1% of total loan receivables. Loans and leases affected by arrears over 90 days&#13;
represented 2.2% and 1.5% of total loan and leasing assets respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12-&#13;
the company's other major shareholders, served as the main source of funds. The opening of&#13;
its capital to new strategic shareholders (IFC and ORIX) not only broadened its equity base&#13;
but also facilitated the company's access to a wider range of debt funds. At present, IL&amp;FS&#13;
borrows from multilaterals8 (IFC and the Asian Development Bank), local banks (it has&#13;
obtained renewable credit lines from a consortium of 19 banks), domestic financial and&#13;
investmnent institutions and insurance companies (an important source of medium- to long-&#13;
term fimds9). IL&amp;FS has also been successful in mobilizing funds through the placement of&#13;
commercial paper (CP) and issue of debentures to select corporate groups in an attempt to&#13;
diversify its resource base. Figure 2.3 presents IL&amp;FS's liability profile as of March 31,&#13;
1995.&#13;
Figure 2.3 -- IL&amp;FS's liability profile&#13;
(as of March 31, 1995)&#13;
Short-term              Others&#13;
Borrowings                5%&#13;
33%                           Equity Capital&#13;
5%&#13;
Reservs &amp;&#13;
Surplus&#13;
16%&#13;
Long-term&#13;
Borrowings&#13;
41%&#13;
Future strategy andfinancial performance&#13;
2.13 One of IL&amp;FS 's primary mandates was to establish itself as a premier institution to&#13;
structure and finance, both directly and through syndication, private infrastructure projects.&#13;
The fulfilment of this objective was deferred to allow the company to build up its balance&#13;
sheet to a size sufficient to enable it to take on the requisite risks associated with lumpy&#13;
infrastructure investments. With total assets estimated to reach Rs. 16,307 million (US$470&#13;
million) at the end of the current financial year and a net worth of Rs.3,732 million (US$110&#13;
million), it is now in a position to start financing infrastructure projects. To reinforce this&#13;
state of readiness is the strength derived from a unique combination of public and private&#13;
sector influences that have defined the company's development until now. IL&amp;FS has&#13;
consistently built upon the special position it has enjoyed from having been promoted by&#13;
public-sector institutions and being overseen by an influential Board of Directors. At the&#13;
same time, its management and professional staff, having been recruited largely from the&#13;
8   The average tenor of these borrowings, which are mainly for lending towards import of capital assets, is 10 years.&#13;
9   The tenor of these facilities is typically between 5 and 8 years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
private sector rather than the promoting institutions, have left the company with a distinctly&#13;
private sector culture. This unique characteristic is seen as a key strength to enable IL&amp;FS to&#13;
enter the commercial infrastructure business in a major way. It has started to position itself&#13;
as the leader in developing the concept for commercializing infrastructure projects, the&#13;
associated legal framework as well as financing alternatives. Over the last few years, IL&amp;FS&#13;
has been actively engaged in creating and developing frameworks to enable such&#13;
commercialization, and has been in continuous dialogue with the relevant authorities in order&#13;
to develop policy as well as the recommended legislative changes that promote such intent.&#13;
The sectors chosen by IL&amp;FS for initial development were power and telecommunications,&#13;
surface transport and transportation systems. As explained earlier (para. 1.06), power and&#13;
telecommunications are somewhat better positioned for commercial implementation;&#13;
IL&amp;FS's initial focus in these sectors has therefore been towards providing investment&#13;
banking services. The surface transport sector has been far different in that IL&amp;FS has had to&#13;
develop models which are sought to be replicable across the sector and structured to facilitate&#13;
market borrowings. Thus, in these areas, IL&amp;FS has been required to undertake a&#13;
multiplicity of roles in a project, including initial conceptualization, development, financing,&#13;
implementation and management. Its record to date in this area is limited to the successful&#13;
implementation of a small toll road in Madhya Pradesh (the 11.5-km Rau-Pithampur bypass);&#13;
it has also advanced significantly the preparation of three additional projects, two of which&#13;
(Delhi-NOIDA bridge and Panvel bypass) are in the final stages of development.&#13;
2.14  Corporate business plan. IL&amp;FS has developed a comprehensive corporate business&#13;
plan for the next five years to manage a successful move into infrastructure. The plan has&#13;
been conceived in the light of the prevailing economic environment in India, and IL&amp;FS's&#13;
perception that the changes over the last few years would continue into the foreseeable future.&#13;
It reflects IL&amp;FS's keen interest in preserving its position in the market as a prudently&#13;
managed, commercially oriented and profitable institution, and maintaining its track record&#13;
of innovation and delivery. A summary of IL&amp;FS's projected financial performance is&#13;
presented in Table 2.1 below. Past and projected income statements, cash flow statements&#13;
and balance sheets are provided in Annex 2.5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14-&#13;
Table 2.1 - Summary of IL&amp;FS's projectedfinancial performance 1995/96-2000/01&#13;
(Rs. million, unless otherwise indicated)&#13;
1995-96    1996-97    1997-98    1998-99   1999-000   2000-01&#13;
Total Assets                            16,307     19,619     26,640     33,860     39,599      44,866&#13;
Infr. Project Assets                      275       1,331      3,108      6,239       8,313      9,863&#13;
of which: - debt                           51        980      2,383      5,135      6,935       8,207&#13;
- equity                        224        351        724       1,104      1,378      1,656&#13;
Long-tenn debt                           8,807     10,062     15,005     18,775     22,210      24,573&#13;
Net worth                                3,742      4,283      4,944      6,944       8,420     10,178&#13;
of which: - share capital                894         894        863        949        949        949&#13;
- reserves and surplus        2,848      3,389      4,081       5,995      7,471      9,229&#13;
Total Income                             2,439      3,191      4,063      5,417       6,668      7,593&#13;
of which: - interest income             1,344      1,474      2,028      2,965      3,746       4,333&#13;
- lease income                  946       1,315      1,528      1,805      2,144      2,378&#13;
- fee income                    125        230        278        333        400         488&#13;
Interest and finance charges             1,472      1,740      2,319      3,056       3,606      4,048&#13;
Ratios:&#13;
Project Assets as a % of total assets     1.69       6.78      11.67       18.43      20.99      21.98&#13;
Debt: equity ratio                        3.06       3.09       3.72       3.16        3.01       2.74&#13;
Debt service coverage ratio               1.47       2.14       2.00       2.10        2.24       2.45&#13;
Retumnonnetworth(%)                      12.71      18.18      19.08       19.55     21.91       21.12&#13;
Return on total assets (%)                3.09       3.99       3.74       4.10        4.54       4.61&#13;
2.15   The main thrust of IL&amp;FS's growth over the next 5 years will be the dramatic&#13;
expansion of its commercial infrastructure project portfolio, which, for the moment, is&#13;
limited to the Rau-Pithampur toll road'". Commercial infrastructure assets are projected to&#13;
amount to about Rs.9.863 million (US$280 million) by the end of 2000/01 as compared to&#13;
Rs.275 million (US$8 million) as of March 31, 1995. To sustain this growth, IL&amp;FS has&#13;
forecasted a robust expansion of its core loan and leasing business that would increase by&#13;
about 24% p.a. over the period, a pace considered achievable in light of the projected overall&#13;
economic and industrial growth in India. Another important feature of IL&amp;FS's corporate&#13;
plan is the significant growth in non-fund based business derived from a conscious effort at&#13;
developing a wide range of advisory services". The impact of such development would be&#13;
0   The Rau-Pithampur toll road, being the first commercial infrastructure project arranged by IL&amp;FS, was actually&#13;
implemented by the company acting as project developer; the total cost of the project appears therefore as an asset on&#13;
IL&amp;FS's balance sheet. IL&amp;FS has just received approval to domicile the asset into a special purpose vehicle in&#13;
which the Government of Madhya Pradesh will take a 20% stake. The SPV will then issue toll revenue bonds, a first&#13;
for India.&#13;
l  IL&amp;FS plans to offer a range of advisory services encompassing: (i) corporate advisory services (structured finance,&#13;
capital markets, project financing), (ii) securities management, and (iii) infrastructure advisory services. For example,&#13;
with the experience gained as country advisor to the Oppenheimer "India Fund", is now spearheading the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
reflected in a relatively rapid growth in fee income (28% p.a.). Finally, the plan assumes&#13;
that the existing fiscal regime applicable to leasing activities would be maintained. In the&#13;
event the prevailing incentives are either reduced or eliminated, IL&amp;FS could, to a certain&#13;
extent, pass on the associated additional costs through an increase in its spread. However, it&#13;
would also likely face stiffer competition and see a slower growth in its leasing assets. To&#13;
evaluate the impact of possible events on IL&amp;FS's financial performance, a sensitivity&#13;
analysis was carried out using different scenarios (Annex2..6). If IL&amp;FS's growth in assets&#13;
were significantly curtailed as compared to the base case scenario presented above, and and if&#13;
there were no income from capital gains and no growth in fee income -- a worst case scenario&#13;
-- the company's return on net worth would basically remain at its present level (about 14-&#13;
15%), while its debt service capability, as measured by its debt service coverage ratio, would&#13;
actually improve as a result of lower funding requirements.&#13;
2.16   The company's move into the infrastructure sector means that the average maturity&#13;
of its assets will grow. In order to manage its liquidity risk, the average maturity of its&#13;
borrowings must also be increased. IL&amp;FS is therefore looking to take up more medium-&#13;
and long-term debt. Although it is already raising medium-term funding from domestic&#13;
commercial banks, their capacity to provide longer maturity debt is limited. In the absence of&#13;
a well-functioning long-term debt market in India, IL&amp;FS has no other option but tap foreign&#13;
sources for long-term funds. IFC is not in a position to provide additional funds with&#13;
maturities and on the substantially-increased scale that is now being sought by the company -&#13;
- IL&amp;FS is already the largest exposure of IFC's Asia Capital Markets Department. The&#13;
Bank is thus considered to be the main source of funds to meet the pressing needs for long-&#13;
term financing. In addition to the Bank loan, USAID has approved a US$25 million line of&#13;
credit to IL&amp;FS in support of one of the projects in the pipeline (Tirupur integrated area&#13;
development program). The company is discussing further non-rupee lines with other&#13;
foreign agencies (DEG of Germany, USEximbank, FMO of Holland) as well as a number of&#13;
international commercial banks interested in the Indian market (ING Bank, Bank of America,&#13;
Chase Manhattan, Societe Generale, Fuji Bank and Deutsche Bank). While the potential&#13;
sources of foreign funding are wide and numerous, a significant constraint may be the ability&#13;
to swap these funds into rupees.&#13;
2.17 The development of IL&amp;FS's infrastructure business will modify the risk profile of&#13;
what is currently a very prudently managed enterprise. The prudential guidelines embedded&#13;
in RBI's Directions are certainly appropriate for IL&amp;FS's current set of activities, essentially&#13;
low-risk lending and leasing to top Indian corporates, but they are insufficient for higher-risk&#13;
and lumpier infrastructure development and financing. IL&amp;FS's risk management&#13;
framework addresses by and large this concern (para. 2. 10). As a complement, agreement&#13;
was reached during negotiations on the following two financial performance targets for&#13;
IL&amp;FS: (i) maintain at all times a debt service coverage ratio of not less than 1.25; and (ii)&#13;
maintain at all times a debt to equity ratio of not more than 6:1.&#13;
development of specialty funds for the infrastructure sector, the first of which is being established with American&#13;
Insurance Group (AIG) (USA). The first tranche of US$70 million was closed on January 10, 1996 and included&#13;
anchor investors such as ADB, Orix and Tata Industries; the second, of US$80 million, is expected to close in April&#13;
1996.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16-&#13;
III - THE PROJECT&#13;
Project objectives&#13;
3.01   The Project aims to develop prototype contractual arrangements for private&#13;
investment in IL&amp;FS's areas of involvement, thereby facilitating entry of the private sector&#13;
on a much larger scale in areas heretore dominated by the public sector. In the process, it&#13;
would build up India's capacity to attract private investment in infrastructure, pilot-test&#13;
institutional and contractual arrangements in a variety of subprojects under various&#13;
administrative and political conditions, and help establish a track record as a prerequisite for&#13;
large scale private investment in the sector. The Project would also meet the pressing needs&#13;
of commercial infrastructure project entities for long-term rupee financing. pending the&#13;
implementation of financial sector reforms for the development of a domestic long-term debt&#13;
market, currently under preparation. Equally important, it would foster efficiency in the&#13;
delivery and use of selected infrastructure services, encourage the establishment of more&#13;
efficient practices in the construction and operation of infrastructure project, and assist in&#13;
alleviating the severe financial and institutional constraints to the expansion of infrastructure&#13;
in India.&#13;
Project description&#13;
3.02   The Project will assist IL&amp;FS in financing infrastructure subprojects such as major&#13;
bridges, urban bypasses, port facilities, water supply and effluent treatment schemes, and&#13;
integrated area development projects, to be implemented on a build-operate-and-transfer&#13;
(BOT) basis (or a variation thereof) and expected to be started within the next three years. It&#13;
consists of three interrelated components:&#13;
+  an investment component in the forn of a line of credit to IL&amp;FS, the proceeds of which&#13;
will be used to provide long-term finance to special purpose entities established for the&#13;
construction and operation of commercial infrastructure projects in IL&amp;FS's pipeline&#13;
(para. 3.04);&#13;
*  a subproject preparation component to cover specialized consultancy services to advise&#13;
the public authorities granting the subproject concessions or to assist project developers&#13;
in preparing their subprojects (para. 3.05); and&#13;
*  a training and technical assistance component to cover (i) IL&amp;FS's staff development for&#13;
its staff, (ii) specific studies that IL&amp;FS is undertaking to facilitate the evaluation and&#13;
implementation of commercial infrastructure projects (e.g., legal and regulatory&#13;
framework applicable to BOT projects in sectors of IL&amp;FS's interest, innovative&#13;
financing for environmental infrastructure in medium-sized cities and townships, traffic&#13;
forecasting, willingness to pay and fixation of user charges for water supply and road&#13;
projects) (para. 3.07).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17-&#13;
Indicative pipeline of subprojects&#13;
3.03  IL&amp;FS has identified a long list of subprojects which it may eventually consider for&#13;
financing and which provides valuable information on the potential size of the market.&#13;
However, it is clear that some of the projects in that list may either slip or not be executed at&#13;
all, while new subprojects may be incorporated at a later date. In the course of preparing the&#13;
Project, the Bank and IL&amp;FS agreed that, to achieve the maximum results, it would be best to&#13;
focus on certain priority sectors and establish a track record in India, that would then&#13;
facilitate replicability in future. A set of eligibility criteria for the line of credit has thus been&#13;
developed and is presented in Annex 3.1. Agreement was reached at negotiations that these&#13;
eligibility criteria will be applicable to all subprojects to be funded under the line of credit&#13;
unless otherwise agreed by the Bank on a case-by-case basis.&#13;
3.04  Given the above criteria and after reviewing the state of preparedness of each&#13;
subproject, IL&amp;FS has drawn up an indicative pipeline of subprojects (Annex 3.2)&#13;
tentatively considered for financing under the Project. It is a scaled-down version of the&#13;
above-mentioned list, bearing in mind that (i) commercial infrastructure projects take a&#13;
considerable time to develop, and (ii) IL&amp;FS can only gradually build up its capacity to&#13;
handle the correspondingly large volume of appraisal work. The pipeline includes 18&#13;
geographically dispersed subprojects, distributed as follows: (i) 10 are in transport (urban&#13;
bypasses and bridges, roads and highways, railways), (ii) 6 are area development projects&#13;
(including a combination of water supply, effluent treatment, power supply and road&#13;
development schemes). (iii) one is a port facility, and (iv) the last one is a large area&#13;
development project to be developed in stages (Bay of Cambay). Some of the subprojects are&#13;
at a relatively advanced stage of preparation and have a high probability of being&#13;
implemented under the Project, they are expected to start construction within the next 18&#13;
months. By contrast, others are only at the preliminary development stage and the&#13;
probability that they will be ready for implementation within the next three years is, at the&#13;
moment, somewhat lower. Any slippage on these projects is expected to be made up by other&#13;
projects currently under development and not included in the pipeline.&#13;
Project cost and financing plan&#13;
3.05  The aggregate cost of the subprojects in the pipeline (including development costs) is&#13;
estimated at about Rs.58,000 million (US$1.6 billion). The figures indicated above provide&#13;
an order of magnitude of the investments envisaged. Out of this aggregate cost, development&#13;
expenses for projects still at their initial stage of development and envisaged to be financed&#13;
under the Project are estimated at about US$19 million, US$5 million of which would&#13;
correspond to the cost of advisory services (including computer hardware and software)&#13;
which public sector authorities (e.g., GOI, state governments, municipalities) could avail of&#13;
to select BOT operators and negotiate concession agreements. It is proposed to finance this&#13;
latter subcomponent through an IDA credit to GOI, the proceeds of which would be utilized&#13;
by the concerned GOI or state government agencies. Agreement was reached at negotiations&#13;
that the IDA credit will become effective only once the loan to IL&amp;FS has been made&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18-&#13;
effective. It is still too early to provide a reasonable estimate of the breakdown of costs&#13;
between local and direct or indirect foreign currrency expenditures; this will likely vary&#13;
considerably from subproject to subproject, depending on the nature of the subproject, the&#13;
BOT operator, and the extent to which the contractor imports construction equipment. Given&#13;
the experience gathered so far on the first two subprojects in the pipeline, the foreign cost&#13;
component is likely to be higher than for public sector projects as great emphasis is placed in&#13;
introducing best international practices through a careful selection of consortium members&#13;
for the special purpose entities. It has thus been assumed that about 40% of the subproject&#13;
costs would be in foreign currency.&#13;
3.06   The subprojects would be developed with a mix of financing comprising: equity from&#13;
project sponsors and other partners such as institutional investors (through specialty equity&#13;
funds), debt financing from contractors or suppliers, term financing from other domestic&#13;
financial institutions, banks and the domestic markets (e.g., through the offering of "toll&#13;
revenue bonds"), and long-term financing from multilateral agencies such as the proposed&#13;
Bank loan and bilateral funds such as the US$25 million line of credit from USAID. As part&#13;
of its review of each individual subproject (paras. 3.08 and 3.13), the Bank will also assess&#13;
whether a World Bank guarantee might be an appropriate vehicle for Bank support to the&#13;
subproject, either as a complement to or a substitute for a subloan from IL&amp;FS. The amnount&#13;
of the Bank loan has been deliberately set at a relatively conservative level to reflect&#13;
uncertainties as to the pace of implementation of the subprojects and hence of disbursement&#13;
from the loan. However, should the subprojects materialize more rapidly than anticipated,&#13;
additional commitments could be envisaged through guarantees and/or a second line of credit&#13;
to IL&amp;FS. Bringing the subprojects to financial closure will require a mix of project&#13;
development expertise and relatively novel and complex financial engineering. IL&amp;FS is&#13;
expected to play a key catalytic role in the process. It will build on its proven record of&#13;
success in investment banking and financial services, and the strategic alliances it has&#13;
established with foreign institutional investors'2. For all subprojects in its pipeline, IL&amp;FS is&#13;
also laying great emphasis on aligning the interests of the major stakeholders and the local&#13;
governments in the success of the projects. Table 3.1 below provides an indicative project&#13;
cost and financing plan.&#13;
12  For example, IL&amp;FS will offer to the AIG equity fund all the infrastructure projects it is aware of. It has also been in&#13;
discussion with General Electric Capital Corporation (GECC) for a relationship for infrastructure deal referrals for&#13;
which IL&amp;FS would receive a fee.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 3.1 - Indicative project cost andfinancing plan&#13;
(millions of US dollars)&#13;
Cost                     Foreign      Local        Total&#13;
Investment                 675         905         1,555&#13;
Subproject preparation      1 0          9           19&#13;
Training and tech. assist.    I         -             1&#13;
Total                686         914        1,600&#13;
Financing&#13;
IBRD                        200         -           200&#13;
IDA                          5          -             5&#13;
IL&amp;FS                        -          44           44&#13;
Indian fin. institutions/banks  -      430          430&#13;
Capital markets                         150         150&#13;
State governments &amp; agencies   -        100         100&#13;
Export credit agencies     200          -           200&#13;
Bilateral funds             75          -            75&#13;
Project sponsors &amp; others  206          190         396&#13;
Total                686         914        1,600&#13;
Project implementation and monitoring&#13;
3.07  The Project will be implemented by IL&amp;FS, acting as equity investor and lender to&#13;
the special purpose entities. During project preparation, the Bank reviewed in detail IL&amp;FS's&#13;
project appraisal procedures and capabilities and suggested a number of adjustments to be&#13;
made in the company's organizational structure, staffing and processes so that it would be&#13;
better equipped to handle the anticipated large volume of infrastructure business. Key&#13;
reassignment and recruitment decisions were subsequently made by IL&amp;FS's management,&#13;
internal processes and procedures have since been clearly formulated, and greater recourse is&#13;
being made to outside expertise to assist in project appraisal. In addition, a comprehensive&#13;
planning exercise has been carried out by IL&amp;FS to assess the manpower requirements --&#13;
both internal and external -- of its infrastructure business, evaluate training needs and&#13;
estimate the cost of consultancy services. A summary of the training program and technical&#13;
assistance activities envisaged by IL&amp;FS is provided in Annex 3.3.&#13;
3.08  IL&amp;FS has designed a comprehensive system of steps and procedures to be followed&#13;
by its staff for appraising subprojects and evaluating subloan applications. The resulting&#13;
project cycle is an elaborate and well-thought out project evaluation system (Annx3.4).&#13;
However, for IL&amp;FS, some of the subproject appraisal activities will be undertaken for the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
first time in a structured format. Systems must therefore be in place that are of a standard&#13;
and quality that can withstand the scrutiny of all potential financiers. Because of the size,&#13;
relative complexity and novelty of the subprojects which the proposed loan will finance, it is&#13;
highly desirable that all subproject appraisal activities be carried out in close consultation&#13;
with the Bank. It has been agreed with IL&amp;FS that, for the first two subprojects in each&#13;
sector category (e.g., roads, water supply, integrated area development)'3, there would be&#13;
close interaction with the Bank as appraisal of infrastructure projects is still an area where the&#13;
company has least experience and where the Bank can contribute most. In particular, the full&#13;
documentation on the contractual framework for the subprojects (e.g., concession agreement,&#13;
construction contract, O&amp;M contract, lenders' agreement, shareholders' agreement) will be&#13;
reviewed in detail by the Bank for their risk mitigation aspects. This is critical as IL&amp;FS is&#13;
breaking new grounds in India and is thereby setting precedents that may potentially become&#13;
government policies. For all subprojects, IL&amp;FS will prepare a detailed subproject&#13;
evaluation report, an outline of which is provided in Annex 3.5. These arrangements were&#13;
confirmed during loan negotiations.&#13;
3.09   Performance monitoring indicators have been established that will provide tools for&#13;
monitoring progress of the Project and the extent to which it is meeting its development&#13;
objectives (Annex 3.6). A comprehensive management review of all aspects of the Project,&#13;
including IL&amp;FS's operations, financial performance and annual budget, will be carried out&#13;
before April 30 of each year. In addition, a mid-term review of the Project will be held&#13;
before April 30, 1998 to take stock of the progress to date and identify any appropriate&#13;
measures to improve implementation of the Project, as the need may arise. These&#13;
arrangements were confirmed during loan negotiations. Given the Bank's expected intensive&#13;
involvement throughout the life of the Project, and especially in the first two years where&#13;
considerable efforts will be deployed to put in place an appropriate contractual framework&#13;
that would be replicated for subsequent projects, unusually large supervision resources will&#13;
be required to monitor project implementation. An indicative supervision plan is provided in&#13;
Annex 3.7; it may be reviewed and updated as appropriate during project implementation.&#13;
Procurement&#13;
3.10   In line with the Bank's revised procurement guidelines, two courses of action are&#13;
envisaged for the procurement of goods and services under the Project. Whenever possible,&#13;
and particularly for those subprojects in which IL&amp;FS's involvement is identified at an early&#13;
stage, it is envisaged that BOT operators will be selected through international competitive&#13;
bidding, following which the selected operator will be free to procure goods, works and&#13;
services required for the facility using its own procedures. As part of the advisory services&#13;
IL&amp;FS is providing to state and local governments for the preparation of subprojects, IL&amp;FS&#13;
has sought consultants' advice to develop the basic documentation for selecting a BOT&#13;
operator. It is also looking to the Bank for assistance in developing acceptable procedures for&#13;
13 Namely, the Panvel bypass, the Delhi-NOIDA bridge, the Tirupur area development program and the Dewas water&#13;
supply scheme.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
inviting and evaluating proposals. During project preparation, the Bank already provided&#13;
some inputs. General guidelines were discussed with IL&amp;FS which, in some instances, is&#13;
acting as advisor to state governments or other public agencies that will eventually manage&#13;
the competitive bidding process (Annex 3.8). Given the diversity of subprojects, the lack of&#13;
experience with competitive selection of private infrastructure operators in India and the&#13;
limited availability of reference documents in the Bank to guide IL&amp;FS in carrying out such&#13;
procurement, it is anticipated that extensive work will be required in this area in the early&#13;
stage of project implementation. In those cases where the BOT operator will not be selected&#13;
on a competitive basis, construction contracts or supply of construction materials and&#13;
equipment will be procured following normal World Bank ICB procedures, unless otherwise&#13;
agreed with the Bank on a case-by-case basis. During project preparation, the Bank reviewed&#13;
the procurement and contracting activities for two of such cases and suggested a number of&#13;
improvements to be made in the area of procurement procedures and bid documentation to&#13;
ensure that IL&amp;FS adopts international best practices. Technical assistance and consultancy&#13;
services would be procured in accordance with the provisions of the Bank's guidelines for the&#13;
use of consultants. Table 3.2 below provides a summary of the procurement arrangements&#13;
envisaged under the project.&#13;
Table 3.2 - Summary of Procurement Arrangements'4&#13;
(indicative) (in millions of US dollars)&#13;
ICB          Others        Total&#13;
Subprojects                110            75          185&#13;
Technical assistance&#13;
- Implementation support    -             19           19&#13;
- Policy support            -              0.5          0.5&#13;
- Capacity building         -              0.5          0.5&#13;
Total               110             95         205&#13;
Security arrangements&#13;
3.11   The Bank loan will be a US$ LIBOR-based loan. It will be extended directly to&#13;
IL&amp;FS and guaranteed by GOI. The provision of GOI guarantees in support of&#13;
infrastructure development in general is under active consideration by a high-powered&#13;
working group within the Ministry of Finance. Its recommendations are expected to be&#13;
submitted before the end of March 1996. At that time only will the detailed terms and&#13;
conditions of GOI's guarantee of the Bank loan to IL&amp;FS be finalized. However, agreement&#13;
was reached at negotiations that GOI will levy a guarantee fee of not less than 1.2% on the&#13;
4  The amounts shown correspond to IBRD/IDA financing; as of the appraisal date the respective total cost of the&#13;
individual subprojects is not known and therefore not shown in the procurement table.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
amounts outstanding and disbursed, a level considered appropriate considering the pioneering&#13;
role IL&amp;FS is expected to play in establishing a track record for India in the area of private&#13;
investment in infrastructure. Agreement was also reached that, as a condition of loan&#13;
effectiveness, GOI and IL&amp;FS will enter into an indemnity agreement on terms and&#13;
conditions satisfactory to the Bank. In addition to the GOI guarantee, the Bank will take a&#13;
pari passu interest in the security structure currently in force in respect of the present lenders&#13;
to IL&amp;FS (Annex 3.9). To complete the security package, an inter-creditor agreement needs&#13;
to be in place. IL&amp;FS has finalized the agreement to the satisfaction of the Bank and will&#13;
circulate it shortly to all the other lenders for their comments. Agreement was reached at&#13;
negotiations that, as a condition of loan effectiveness, the security arrangements for the&#13;
World Bank loan will be completed, including the placement of the loan under the mortgage&#13;
shared equally with other lenders and the execution of the inter-creditor agreement.&#13;
Onlending and disbursement&#13;
3.12   The proposed loan to IL&amp;FS is meant to meet the pressing needs of commercial&#13;
infrastructure project entities for long-term rupee financing, pending the implementation of&#13;
financial sector reforms for the development of a domestic long-term debt market (para.&#13;
1. 11). Furthermore, given the intrinsic risks of infrastructure projects and the fact that cost&#13;
recovery will, in most if not all cases, be in local currency, it is considered more prudent not&#13;
to pass on the foreign exchange risk to the final beneficiaries of the loan so as to preserve the&#13;
financial viability of the subprojects. Proceeds of the loan to IL&amp;FS will therefore be onlent&#13;
to the subproject entities, mainly in the form of rupee term loans with maturities matching&#13;
that of the original loan to IL&amp;FS as closely as possible (17-20 years) and a market-&#13;
determined rate'5. Only in exceptional cases will IL&amp;FS onlend in US dollars in which case&#13;
it will charge a market-determined variable rate'6. These onlending arrangements were&#13;
confirmed at negotiations. For subloans made in rupees, IL&amp;FS will bear the foreign&#13;
exchange risk. The company plans to hedge the currency risk by swapping the proceeds of&#13;
the Bank loan into back-to-back rupee-denominated loans with the same repayment&#13;
structures as the Bank loan. For this to be cost-effective in the absence of a swap market in&#13;
India, IL&amp;FS will need to do it in amounts of at least US$25 million at the minimum. To&#13;
enable IL&amp;FS to arrange these swap transactions, a Special Account, with an authorized&#13;
allocation of US$25 million, will be established in a commercial bank, on terms and&#13;
conditions satisfactory to the Bank. The amounts deposited in the Special Account will be&#13;
used exclusively for executing the swap transactions, and the rupees obtained therefrom will&#13;
be deposited into a Swap Account, to be used for eligible expenditures. Annex 3.1 0 provides&#13;
further details on such arrangements. They were confirmed at negotiations. Depending on&#13;
the terms of the swap agreement, IL&amp;FS may onlend the proceeds of the loan at a fixed or&#13;
variable rate. In either event IL&amp;FS will not bear the interest rate risk. The IDA credit will&#13;
5  IL&amp;FS estimates that, under prevailing conditions, it would onlend at a spread of 400 basis points over the lending&#13;
rate obtained from the swap counterparty.&#13;
16  Under present conditions and given the cost of the funds to IL&amp;FS, the company reckons that it would onlend at a&#13;
spread of 400 basis points over LIBOR.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
be onlent on the standard terms and conditions applicable to central assistance to the states at&#13;
the time.&#13;
3.13  As indicated earlier, subprojects financed by the line of credit will need to meet&#13;
specific eligibility criteria (para. 3.03). In particular, subprojects will need to comply with&#13;
the following financial performance benchmarks:&#13;
* a capital structure for the SPV of no more than 75% debt, with the promoter's&#13;
contribution representing at least 25% of the paid-in capital;&#13;
* a project debt service coverage ratio of no less than 1.25 on an annual cash-flow basis;&#13;
and&#13;
* the entire financing package to have been finalized (committed or raised) or promoter&#13;
guarantees of high quality to have been provided prior to the finalization of the financial&#13;
package.&#13;
These will need to be fully documented in the subproject evaluation report prepared by&#13;
IL&amp;FS, which will form the basis for the Bank's review of individual subprojects.&#13;
Agreement was reached at negotiations that, as conditions of disbursement for the investment&#13;
component, (i) IL&amp;FS will submit to the Bank, for its review and approval, the final project&#13;
evaluation report, including the environmental and social (EA/SA) assessment reports, and&#13;
(ii) the contracts for the financing of the subproject will have been executed together with all&#13;
the other contracts associated with the implementation of the subproject.&#13;
3.14  Drawdowns from each subloan will be contingent on the SPV meeting conditions&#13;
precedent relative to progress of construction. Such conditions would be specified in the&#13;
lender's agreement between IL&amp;FS and the SPV and would be spelled out in the evaluation&#13;
report submitted by IL&amp;FS to the Bank. Disbursements under the loan will be made for&#13;
100% of the amounts paid by IL&amp;FS for expenditures incurred under eligible subloans;&#13;
disbursements for consultancy services and training will be for 100% of expenditures.&#13;
Disbursements under the credit will be for: (i) 100% of expenditures for consultancy services,&#13;
and (ii) for equipment and software, 100% of foreign expenditures, 100% of local&#13;
expenditures (ex-factory cost) and 80% of local expenditures for other items procured locally.&#13;
As indicated in the eligibility criteria, proceeds of the Bank loan would not cover more than&#13;
25% of the total cost of individual subprojects. The loan is expected to disburse over a five-&#13;
year period. An indicative schedule of disbursements has been assumed in the financial&#13;
projections for IL&amp;FS (Annex 2.5). The cut-off date for new loan commitments to be&#13;
financed under the Project would be December 31, 1998. The Project would be completed&#13;
by March 31, 2001 and the closing date for the loan would be September 30, 2001.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Environmental and social considerations&#13;
3.15  IL&amp;FS, with assistance from an NGO, has prepared an Environmental and Social&#13;
Report (ESR), the objective of which was to put in place an environmental and social&#13;
assessment process which adequately responds to GOI requirements and, for subprojects&#13;
involving Bank financing, the Bank's operational directives (ODs). Organized in 3&#13;
volumes'7, the ESR: (a) states the company's environmental and social goals; (b) provides&#13;
the contextual setting for the environmental and social assessment process; (c) identifies the&#13;
major issues in the priority sectors; (d) details the environmental assessment and social&#13;
assessment (EA/SA) process that IL&amp;FS will follow when appraising suprojects; (e) outlines&#13;
methods to moderate risks and liabilities due to environmental and social factors; (f) specifies&#13;
the organizational arrangements in IL&amp;FS to manage the environmental and social&#13;
assessment process; and (g) spells out the staff development plan. Relevant regulations,&#13;
guidelines (including the Bank's relevant operational directives), checklists and protocols are&#13;
provided as an attachment to the report. Land acquisition and resettlement procedures&#13;
described in the ESR will apply only to land acquired, whether by public or private sector&#13;
agencies, on or after June 15, 1995 (the date of commencement of preparation of the ESR).&#13;
During project preparation, the Bank "field-tested" the ESR approach in the context of one&#13;
subproject (para. 3.17) and met with various government officials and NGOs to assess their&#13;
concurrence with the approach proposed in the ESR. The Executive Summary of the ESR is&#13;
presented in Annex 3.1 1.&#13;
3.16  In the process of preparing the document, IL&amp;FS's management has demonstrated a&#13;
strong commitment to implement the ESR and taken a proactive stand for tackling&#13;
environmental and social issues. IL&amp;FS clearly sees the EA/SA process as an integral part of&#13;
its risk management framework: specific environmental and social risks are identified upfront&#13;
and mitigation measures fully integrated into the project design, thereby reducing the risks of&#13;
delays during contruction and operation that could threaten the project's financial viability.&#13;
It also enables IL&amp;FS to screen projects and avoid financing investments for which, for&#13;
example, land acquisition may result in costly resettlement and rehabilitation (R&amp;R). IL&amp;FS&#13;
has brought a few innovative features into the environmental and social assessment process,&#13;
such as the establishment of neighbourhood committees or the preparation of annual&#13;
environmental and social audits for the company. It has set an example of best practice that&#13;
might well be considered for other operations supported by the Bank in India and elsewhere.&#13;
3.17  IL&amp;FS, with the assistance of local consultants, prepared an environmental and social&#13;
assessment for the proposed Delhi-NOIDA link bridge subproject. The draft report was&#13;
reviewed by the Bank and the final version incorporates all the comments. The Delhi&#13;
Administration, NOIDA and the project SPV have all committed to implement the mitigation&#13;
actions. Air pollution and noise have emerged as the major environmental issues in certain&#13;
localities adjacent to the project location. A greenbelt, noise barriers and air quality&#13;
7  Volunie I is the Executive Summary; Volume 11 is the main report; and Volume 111 is a compilation of reference&#13;
documents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
monitoring are included in the project design. Five per cent of the total landfall area is under&#13;
dispute, the remaining is unencumbered land. A negotiated settlement with the affected&#13;
people is being pursued by the Delhi Administration. The compensation will be based on the&#13;
entitlement framework contained in the ESR.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
IV - PROJECT JUSTIFICATION&#13;
Project sustainability&#13;
4.01  In this particular case, project sustainability must be looked at from three inter-related&#13;
angles: (i) from the point of the individual subprojects; (ii) from the institutional IL&amp;FS&#13;
viewpoint; and (iii) from a broad sectoral perspective. The proposed project will support the&#13;
implementation of commercial infrastructure projects which IL&amp;FS is and will continue to be&#13;
carefully screening for their financial, economic, technical, environmental and social merits.&#13;
Among the eligibility criteria agreed with the Bank, IL&amp;FS has set a minimum real financial&#13;
rate of return of 14% which it considers to be the minimum for attracting private finance.&#13;
The subprojects are structured to generate sufficient revenues to recover capital as well as&#13;
operating and maintenance costs through the duration of the concessions. Particular attention&#13;
is also given by IL&amp;FS for establishing an appropriate institutional framework for the&#13;
implementation of the individual projects, through a pro-active dialogue with GOI on&#13;
regulatory and legal issues and by encouraging public/private partnerships with state&#13;
governments and their agencies. Since the financial viability of the proposed investments&#13;
depends on the cost-effective design, implementation and operation of individual projects,&#13;
the incentives for sustainability are greater than in the case of similar investments&#13;
implemented by the public sector. The agreed procedures for Bank review of subprojects&#13;
(paras. 3.08, 3.09 and 3.13) should also enhance the likelihood of sustainability of the&#13;
subprojects.&#13;
4.02   With regard to IL&amp;FS's sustainability, the company has developed an Operating&#13;
Framework which inter alia sets out a risk management framework and related policies as&#13;
well as the company's guidelines and framework of operations (para. 2. 10). To ensure that&#13;
IL&amp;FS's expanded involvement in infrastructure is sustainable in the long run, the Project&#13;
includes the following safeguards: (i) IL&amp;FS's risk management framework, as revised, will&#13;
set prudent limits to the company's exposure to infrastructure projects; (ii) financial&#13;
covenants will provide additional prudential guidelines for IL&amp;FS's overall operations; and&#13;
(iii) the agreed financial eligibility criteria for onlending to individual subprojects are&#13;
expected to contain the credit risks of individual subprojects.&#13;
4.03   By supporting IL&amp;FS' efforts in the development of private infrastructure&#13;
investments, in collaboration with the concerned agencies of GOI and individual states, the&#13;
project will assist in defining an improved regulatory and institutional framework for the&#13;
sector and hence establishing the sustainability of private infrastructure investments in India.&#13;
Economic analysis&#13;
4.04   The economic analysis of the Project will be carried out at the subproject level, on an&#13;
investment-by-investment basis. As indicated earlier, each subproject will be subject to both&#13;
a detailed financial analysis and a conventional economic evaluation by IL&amp;FS, assisted, as&#13;
necessary, by specialized consultants. During project preparation, the Bank reviewed the&#13;
preliminary economic evaluations carried out by IL&amp;FS for a sample of subprojects in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
transport and water supply sectors. While IL&amp;FS's staff demonstrated extensive knowledge&#13;
of the principles of economic analysis of projects, some improvements were suggested to&#13;
enhance the coverage, thoroughness and rigor of the evaluations. The Bank agreed with&#13;
IL&amp;FS a methodology to be followed for investments in each sector, including: (i) a clear&#13;
articulation of the underlying rationale for the choice of each subproject, (ii) the consistency&#13;
of the subproject within future sectoral development plans, (iii) the identification of the&#13;
expected beneficiary groups, (iv) the valuation of economic benefits and costs using&#13;
appropriate shadow prices, (vi) the identification of the risks of the subproject and the&#13;
associated mitigation measures, (vii) the establishment of a minimum economic rate of return&#13;
(ERR), (viii) the test of first-year benefits (FYB) to check appropriate timing of the&#13;
investment, and (ix) the use of incremental analysis in the context of a phased project.&#13;
During loan negotiations IL&amp;FS confirmed that it will follow an acceptable methodology&#13;
when carrying out the economic evaluation of subprojects and that it will fully document&#13;
such analysis in the evaluation report to be submitted to the Bank for each subproject.&#13;
Benefits&#13;
4.05   At the subproject level, the project will achieve the benefits normally attributed to&#13;
specific infrastructure projects; these will be clearly identified and measured on a case-by-&#13;
case basis in the economic evaluation of individual subprojects. At the macroeconomic level,&#13;
the Project should be seen as a precursor for greater involvement of domestic financial&#13;
institutions and the capital markets in the infrastructure sector. It will help overcome one of&#13;
the major obstacles to a satisfactory market response to GOI's economic reform efforts and&#13;
promote increased capital availability for infrastructure, improved efficiency in the use of&#13;
these resources and overall faster economic growth. The Project will enable IL&amp;FS to&#13;
promote commercially-viable infrastructure projects on a much wider scale than heretofore.&#13;
By giving such investments a clear commercial orientation, the concept adopted by IL&amp;FS&#13;
for their implementation is expected to induce better cost recovery, faster construction, the&#13;
application of improved maintenance policies, the introduction of technological&#13;
improvements, better utilization of the infrastructure capacity, and better interaction between&#13;
users and providers of services. The project will also provide the company with the&#13;
appropriate institution-building and technical assistance support required to develop it into a&#13;
successful infrastructure company. IL&amp;FS will thus have become a rare institution in the&#13;
developing world, achieving what it does as a purely indigenous enterprise.&#13;
Risks&#13;
4.06   The Project -- innovative in its concept and design -- entails certain risks which are&#13;
proposed to be mitigated in the following manner:&#13;
* first, the Project is breaking new grounds. The pioneering of commercial infrastructure&#13;
projects in India in itself constitutes a key risk, particularly in the absence of a well-&#13;
established administrative, legal and regulatory regime. To mitigate this risk, IL&amp;FS is&#13;
using great care in selecting ("cherry-picking") only those projects which it considers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
commercially viable, in establishing close partnerships with local authorities and other&#13;
stakeholders, and spending significant resources in developing appropriate contractual&#13;
frameworks (e.g., concession agreements) for these projects. The Project will also&#13;
ensure that the public contracting parties will have access, whenever required, to expert&#13;
advisory services to ensure that the subprojects supported under the operation are the&#13;
result of a fair and responsible contracting and negotiating process;&#13;
secondly, BOT-type infrastructure projects are still relatively new to IL&amp;FS and raise&#13;
credit risk issues quite different from the more traditional corporate finance and&#13;
investment banking business in which IL&amp;FS has so far excelled. IL&amp;FS is building up a&#13;
core team of professional staff and has agreed to build into its appraisal process a greater&#13;
degree of reliance on outside consultants to complement its own resources. Systems are&#13;
being put in place to ensure careful and comprehensive appraisal of projects which will&#13;
be reinforced by a close interaction with the Bank and specific financial eligibility&#13;
criteria;&#13;
thirdly, there is a risk that IL&amp;FS may have set excessively optimistic targets for&#13;
implementation of the subprojects in its pipeline. Thus, embedded in the project is also a&#13;
risk of delays in disbursing the proposed loan. This could in turn induce IL&amp;FS to either&#13;
shift towards simpler and less productive projects or rush the procedures and deviate from&#13;
a proper contractual framework. A reasonable degree of conservatism has been built into&#13;
the financial projections discussed in Chapter 11. The close working relationship&#13;
between the Bank and IL&amp;FS, the proposed covenants and onlending arrangements,&#13;
including milestone provisions for disbursements, and Bank reviews and approvals of&#13;
individual subprojects should also minimize the risk of IL&amp;FS deviating from the priority&#13;
sector and project types as well as the agreed procedures. In addition, to secure an&#13;
effective role for the Bank in monitoring progress of implementation of the project, the&#13;
supervision plan provides for a significantly enhanced supervision effort by the Bank,&#13;
particularly during the first two years of project implementation. (para. 3.09);&#13;
fourthly, IL&amp;FS's involvement in a number of large and relatively complex projects,&#13;
raises the risk of too rapid an expansion of its infrastructure operations. While it has&#13;
followed until now prudent management practices, it must continue to maintain a proper&#13;
balance between growth and sound investments. The financial covenants proposed for&#13;
this project should provide appropriate checks on IL&amp;FS's growth in infrastructure assets&#13;
and future exposure to infrastructure projects;&#13;
finally, the loan to IL&amp;FS includes a new feature whereby the company will be allowed&#13;
to use proceeds from the loan account and immediately swap them into Rupees in order&#13;
to protect itself from the foreign exchange risk on repayment of the loan. Appropriate&#13;
safeguards have been built into the terms and conditions of such Special Account and the&#13;
associated Swap Account so that the funds disbursed from the loan account are used&#13;
exclusively for the Project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
4.07  It is also worth noting that IL&amp;FS itself, as a commercial entity, is well aware of the&#13;
issues related to risks and risk management; this has been extensively reflected in its&#13;
Operating Framework (para. 2.09). The risk management framework and policies set out in&#13;
detail (i) IL&amp;FS' risk management philosophy; (ii) the objectives of risk management; (iii)&#13;
the company's risk management process; (iv) the internal allocation of responsibilities; and&#13;
(v) definition and types of risks incurred in IL&amp;FS's various business activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
V - AGREEMENTS AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
Agreements&#13;
5.01   Agreement has been reached with IL&amp;FS that:&#13;
(i)  it will provide to the Bank, on a timely basis, all important documents and&#13;
information submitted to the Board for its consideration (para. 2.03);&#13;
(ii)  it will implement a comprehensive cost accounting system by product line to be&#13;
fully operational by March 31, 1997 (para. 2.06);&#13;
(iii)  it will submit its annual audited accounts to the Bank by June 30 of each year (para.&#13;
2.07);&#13;
(iv)  any material modification to the existing regulatory framework applicable to&#13;
IL&amp;FS, that adversely affects the operations of the company, will be an event of&#13;
default under the loan (para. 2.09);&#13;
(v)  it will continue to conduct its operations in accordance with the principles and&#13;
procedures enunciated in its Operating Framework, as suitably revised, and that any&#13;
material modification to the Operating Framework, without prior approval of the&#13;
Bank, will be an event of default under the loan (para. 2.10);&#13;
(vi)  it will maintain at all times a debt service coverage ratio of not less than 1.25 (para.&#13;
2.17);&#13;
(vii) it will maintain at all times a debt to equity ratio of not more than 6:1 (para. 2.17);&#13;
(viii) it will apply eligibility criteria, acceptable to the Bank, to all subprojects to be&#13;
financed under the loan (para. 3.03);&#13;
(ix)  it will onlend the proceeds of the loan on terms and conditions acceptable to the&#13;
Bank (para. 3.12);&#13;
(x)  it will use the amounts deposited in the Special Account exclusively for executing&#13;
swap transactions, on terms and conditions acceptable to the Bank, and it will&#13;
deposit the rupees obtained thereby in a Swap Account, payments out of which will&#13;
be used exclusively for eligible expenditures under the Project (para. 3.12); and&#13;
(xi)  it will follow a methodology acceptable to the Bank for the economic analysis of&#13;
subprojects (para. 4.04).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31-&#13;
5.02  Agreement has been reached with GOI that it will guarantee the proposed loan to&#13;
IL&amp;FS under terms and conditions satisfactory to the Bank, including the levy of a guarantee&#13;
fee of not less than 1.2% on amounts outstanding and disbursed (para. 3.11).&#13;
5.03  Agreement has been reached with GOI and IL&amp;FS that annual management reviews&#13;
of the Project will be carried out by April 30 of each year and that a mid-term review of the&#13;
Project will be carried out no later than April 30, 1998 (para. 3.09).&#13;
5.04  Conditions of effectiveness of the loan to IL&amp;FS will be that:&#13;
(i)  IL&amp;FS's Operating Framework has been revised to (a) set definite investment&#13;
exposure limits instead of guidelines, (b) limit to one third of its total credit&#13;
exposure, IL&amp;FS's credit exposure to infrastructure projects, as suitably defined, (c)&#13;
limit to 30% of the company's net worth its aggregate investments in affiliates, as&#13;
suitably defined, and (d) treat as equity all expenditures incurred by IL&amp;FS on&#13;
infrastructure projects prior to their financial closure (para. 2.10);&#13;
(ii)  GOI and IL&amp;FS have entered into an indemnity agreement on terms and conditions&#13;
satisfactory to the Bank (para. 3.1 1); and&#13;
(iii) the security arrangements for the loan have been completed by IL&amp;FS, including&#13;
the placement of the loan under the mortgage shared equally with other lenders and&#13;
the execution of the intercreditor agreement (para. 3.1 1).&#13;
5.05  A condition of effectiveness of the development credit will be that the loan to IL&amp;FS&#13;
has been made effective (para. 3.05).&#13;
5.06  Conditions of disbursement for the investment component of the loan to IL&amp;FS will&#13;
be, with respect to all subprojects, that the Bank will have reviewed and approved each&#13;
subproject and that all contracts associated with the implementation of the subproject will&#13;
have been executed (para. 3.13).&#13;
Recommendation&#13;
5.06  With the above assurances, agreements and conditions, the proposed Project would be&#13;
suitable for a Bank loan of US$200 million to IL&amp;FS, to be repaid over a period of 20 years&#13;
(including 5 years of grace) at the Bank's standard interest rate for LIBOR-based single&#13;
currency loans, and an IDA credit of SDR3.4 million (US$5 million equivalent) to India, to&#13;
be repaid over 35 years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
ANNEX 2.1&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS: Composition of the Board of Directors&#13;
The Board of Directors has 18 members comprising the Chairman, the Vice&#13;
Chairman and Managing Director, I I non-executive directors and 4 executive directors.&#13;
The present Chairman is also Chairman of HDFC. Other than the Chairman, 6 of the&#13;
non-executive directors are shareholder representatives including 2 from CBI, I from&#13;
UTI, 2 from ORIX Corporation, and I from IFC. Two other non-executive directors are&#13;
prominent Indian industrialists, including the chairman of the Mahindra group. The&#13;
remaining three are current or former GOI secretaries.&#13;
Current members of the board are:&#13;
Messrs. - Deepak Parekh        Chairman&#13;
Chairman, HDFC&#13;
- Yoshihiko Miyauchi    President, ORIX Corporation&#13;
- Yoshiaki Ishida      Managing Director, ORIX Corporation&#13;
- Irving Kuczynski     Director, IFC&#13;
- Keshub Mahindra      Chairman, Mahindra Group&#13;
- K.M. Birla           Chairman, Birla Group&#13;
- RK Bhargava          Secretary (Ret'd), GOI&#13;
- RC Bhargava          Chairman &amp; Managing Director, Maruti&#13;
Udyog Ltd.&#13;
- K Padmanabhiah       Secretary, Ministry of Home Affairs&#13;
- C Ramachandran       Secretary, Ministry of Urban Affairs and&#13;
Employment&#13;
- DK Contractor        Executive Director (Ret'd) CBI&#13;
- KC Chowdhary         Executive Director, CBI&#13;
- BG Daga              Chief General Manager, UTI&#13;
- Ravi Parthasarathy   Vice Chairman &amp; Managing Director,&#13;
IL&amp;FS&#13;
- Vimal Bhandari       Executive Director&#13;
- Ashok Totlani        Executive Director - Infrastructure&#13;
- Arun K Saha          Executive Director &amp; Company Secretary&#13;
- Gopal Rajagopalan    Executive Director - New Initiatives&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS organization chart&#13;
C.d l- W.&#13;
M.,m''                                ,  m  .&#13;
I an |~~~~~~~~&#13;
;~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~02                        $BMM MM  9" W3   X       ff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
ANNEX 2.3&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PROPOSED PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Implementation of a cost accounting system&#13;
1.   IL&amp;FS has in place well-developed high-quality accounting systems and internal&#13;
auditing arrangements. Following the establishment of regional offices in Delhi and&#13;
Bangalore, the company has further strengthened its accounting system to better monitor&#13;
the operations of its various profit centers from a geographical perspective. What is&#13;
needed however is the capacity to carefully monitor the profitability of individual&#13;
products marketed by the company. This has clearly not been a problem until now as the&#13;
company has remained of a manageable size, thus enabling its senior management to&#13;
keep good track of the various business activities and their relative profitability, but not&#13;
yet in a systematic manner. As the company grows rapidly and the number of product&#13;
lines multiplies -- as is currently anticipated -- such monitoring will become increasingly&#13;
difficult. It is therefore necessary that, in anticipation of future growth, IL&amp;FS start&#13;
implementing a comprehensive cost accounting system by product line so that it is fully&#13;
operational by 3/31/97.&#13;
2.    On an annual basis, the company's statutory auditor should certify to the Bank&#13;
that an adequate system of accounting for costs per product line is in place (to be certified&#13;
as of 3/31/97). Such system shall be throughout the company for all major product lines&#13;
and shall make available to senior management, division managers and the Board (as well&#13;
as the Bank) sufficient information to determine "gross" and "net" spreads per major&#13;
product line. Such a system shall take into account overhead costs, including marketing,&#13;
product and project development, finanncing costs and other administrative burdens and&#13;
shall require the development of a transfer pricing model or other formula for appropriate&#13;
allocations. The "gross" spreads shall be before the allocation of overhead expenditures.&#13;
If appropriate, IL&amp;FS shall work with its statutory auditor or others to develop an&#13;
appropriate transfer pricing model to determine such spreads.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
ANNEX 2.4&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS: exposure limits for commercial infrastructure projects&#13;
and&#13;
limits to investments in affiliates&#13;
* With regard to infrastructure investments, credits extended to infrastructure projects&#13;
will not exceed one third (33 1/3%) of the Company's total credit exposure.&#13;
Infrastructure investments are those projects of a utility nature (e.g., power&#13;
generation, power distribution; water supply, water distribution, transport facilities&#13;
including roads, bridges, tunnels; airports, port facilities, water and air transport&#13;
operators or systems, passenger and freight handling facilities, rail systems and&#13;
railway operators; telecommunication operators, equipment and systems) which bear&#13;
a greenfield startup/major expansion risk or where the pricing of output or services is&#13;
subject to Government approval. Excluded from this list will be infrastructure&#13;
investments extended to creditworthy industrial houses where the infrastructure&#13;
investment constitutes no more than 25% of the assets of the industrial house, or for&#13;
which full and unconditional guarantees have been given by such industrial houses.&#13;
Total credit exposure will include all forms of investment which are made by means&#13;
of instruments (including loans', lease contracts, guarantees, debt underwritings and&#13;
other similar financial obligations) which are not counted as equity (as defined&#13;
elsewhere in the risk management framework). Appropriate adjustments to a credit&#13;
exposure will be made to reflect the proportion of debt service coverage met by a firm&#13;
offtake contract of a creditworthy industrial house. Compliance with this covenant&#13;
will be reviewed in its entirety annually.&#13;
* Aggregate investments (including total credit exposure and equity as referred to&#13;
above) in affiliates of IL&amp;FS will not exceed 30% of IL&amp;FS's paid-in share capital&#13;
and unimpaired reserves. For purposes of this section, an IL&amp;FS affiliate is to be&#13;
defined as an entity where IL&amp;FS's share of the paid in equity capital is more than 33&#13;
1/3%. Excluded from this limit are long-term strategic investments made by IL&amp;FS&#13;
in developing its business activities2.&#13;
including subordinated loans.&#13;
2   These include investments in the share capital of its stock-broking venture, asset management venture, auto&#13;
finance venture, Kampsax India, Transroute.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36-&#13;
ANNEX 2.5&#13;
Page 1 of 7&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTRE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS: income statements, cash-flow statements,&#13;
balance sheets, and selected financial ratios&#13;
(1991/92-2000/01)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS: Income Statement&#13;
(Rs. Million)&#13;
1991-92    1992-94     1994-95     1995-96    1996-97     1997-98    1998-99    199910    200-01&#13;
L Income&#13;
Interest Income&#13;
Liquid Investments                         99          28          80         126         89          97         104         112         119&#13;
Current Maturities                        200         314         260         372        396         444         607         717        853&#13;
Corporate Bonds                           208         448         181        222         244         241         216         212        210&#13;
Loans &amp; Advances&#13;
Infrastructure                            15         78          55         153         290        425         560         670         760&#13;
Others                                    53         81         371         414         344        413         574         741         888&#13;
Investment in Venture Capital               0           0           7          38         38          38          38          38          38&#13;
Dividend on Corp Investments                0           0           0          18         27          27          27          27          27&#13;
ifrastructureIncomeProject                  0           9           6           0         46         306         725       1,153       1,361&#13;
Bandra Kurla Complex                        0         138           0           0          0          39         113          76          76&#13;
Total Interest Income                     575       1,094         961       1,344       1,474      2,028       2,965       3,746       4,333&#13;
Lease Income&#13;
Lease Advance - Infrastructure&#13;
Interest                                  18         15          32         141         144         160        179         207         222&#13;
Lease Management Fee                       5          4           3           9          12          15         17          20          21&#13;
Lease Advance - Others&#13;
Interest                                  33         32           7          23          23          26         29          34          36&#13;
Lease Management Fee                      10          6           6           2           2           2          3           3           3&#13;
Lease Rentals                             411       1,120         721         730       1,055       1,226       1,396      1,618       1,793&#13;
Lease Rentals - Panvel                      0           0           0           0           0          0          61         122         122&#13;
Toll Income                                 0           2           3           2           3          3           4           4           4&#13;
OperatingAssets                             0           0           0          38          76         96         116         136         176&#13;
Total Lease Income                        477       1,179         771         946       1,315       1,528       1,805      2,144       2,378&#13;
Fee Income                                                                                                                                                 to&#13;
Advisory Fees                              84          90         113         125        230         278         333         400         488&#13;
Project Management Fees                     0           0           4           0           7          17         26          12           2           t &#13;
Project Merchant Banking Fees               0           0           0           0           0          0          22          39           0&#13;
Total                                      84          90         118         125        237         295         380         450         490&#13;
Profit on Sale of Investments&#13;
Quoted Investments                        139         137         158           0         166        213         266         328         393&#13;
Liquid Investments                          0           0           0          24           0          0           0           0           0&#13;
Total Profit on Sale of Investments       139         137         158          24         166        213         266         328         393&#13;
Total Income                               1,275       2,499       2,008       2,439      3,191       4,063       5,417       6,668       7,593&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IL&amp;FS: Income Statement&#13;
1991-92    1992-94    1994-95    1995-96    1996-97    1997-98    1998-99    1999-00    2000-01&#13;
IL Expenses&#13;
Interest and Finance Charges&#13;
Existing Borrowings                      997       1,623      1,161      1,290       1,054        929        901        768         610&#13;
New Borrowings                             0           0          0        291        854       1,498       2,188      2,838       3,438&#13;
Less: Interest Capitalized               -96        -101        -73        -109       -168        -109        -32          0           0&#13;
Net Interest Expenses                    901       1,523      1,088       1,472      1,740       2,319      3,056       3,606      4,048&#13;
Administrative &amp; General Expenses            54         119        154         167        195        234         281        337         404&#13;
Depreciation&#13;
Leased Assets                            234         577        345         303        469         566        669        798         922&#13;
Toll Road                                  0           0          1           1          1           1         62         123        123&#13;
Fixed Assets (Own)                        13         29          23          32         42         46          72         97          96&#13;
Operating Assets                           0           0          0          14         27         32          36         41          51&#13;
Total Depreciation                       247        606         369        350         539        646         840       1,059      1,193&#13;
Total Expenses                            1,202      2,247       1,611      1,988       2,474      3,199       4,177      5,002       5,645&#13;
Profit                                       73        251         397        451         717        865       1,240      1,666       1,948&#13;
H0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TINIAL&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
HAFS: Cash Flow Statement                                                                       (Rs. Million)&#13;
1991-92     1992-94      1994-95      1995-96      199697. s:1.997-9"        1998-9q9    199IM00O &#13;
Sources of Funds&#13;
Profit for the year-                            7 3        251           397         451          717          865        1,240        1,666         198      ~     3&#13;
Depreciation                                   247          606          369         350          539          6.46         840        1,059         1,193        4f&#13;
Lease Termunal A/C                               0           2 3          4 1          90         286          491          517          727           913&#13;
Lease Rent Suspense                           -152         -240           2 1          3 3        112           90          103          113            5 947&#13;
Increase in Share Capital                      102          217           98          176           0            0           86            0             0&#13;
Share Premiuum                                   0          600          980         510            0            0          863            0             0&#13;
New Borrowings                               4,069        2,867        3,257       4,998        4,179        7,198        6,276        6,800         6,092         $4&#13;
Repayment of Bridge Finance                    431        1,335        1,879        1,098       2,270        1,710        3,032        3,530         4,220       14762:&#13;
Repayment ofbLoanis &amp;Advances                  350          774        2,056        1,894        1,054         965        1,371        2,1482,6&#13;
Sale of Corporate Bonds                          0          906         228          196          275          594          568          512           562:       Z$&#13;
Sale of hinvestmnents                            0           22        1,053         362            0            0            0            00&#13;
Panvel SPC Deposit                               0            0            0            0         388          500        1,184         -104          -104:::...165&#13;
Working Capital                                210          -82          169          168          139          -51        -367         -139           -23         -.44..&#13;
5,331       7,278       10,548       10,324        9,960       13,007       15,714       16,311        17,528&#13;
Application of Funds&#13;
Bridge Finance Disbursement                    141        1,706        2,369        2,050        1,500       2,960        3,530        4,220         5,000::::.'"&#13;
Loans &amp; Advances Disbursement                  840        1,569        3,401        2,000        1,700       2,650        3,050        3,600         3,900       1,0&#13;
Marketable Securities                          HI1          136          242         236          210          235          260          285           285        1,7&#13;
Corporate Bonds                                913           93          870         300          350          400          450          500           500:.:,:,::&#13;
Lease Disbursemecnt                            859        1,178        1,078        1,200        1,400        1,600       1,800        2,100         2,200::.&#13;
Own Assets                                     171          154           45          336         264          296          133           92            75:.&#13;
Rau Piaiampur                                    0           68            0           1 7           0            0           0            0             0            (&#13;
Operating Assets                                 0            0           59          550            0         250            0          250           250:,&#13;
Repayment of Borrowings (Old)                1,828        1,681          586        3,003        1,849         393          694        1,027          1,016       47&#13;
Repayment of Borrowings (New)                    0            0            0            0         575         1,613       2,063        2,338         2,563&#13;
Redeinption of Preference Shares                 0           21            0            0            0          31            0            0             0_&#13;
hivestment in Projects                           0            0           6 1           0        1,056        1,777       3,131        2,074          1,550:'...&#13;
Investments                                    371          496        1,552          363            0            0           0            0             0.  0......&#13;
Institutional Complex                            0          191            0         261          260          129         -522         -359             0.42&#13;
Panvel Bypass                                    0            0            0            0         620          500          952            00&#13;
Dividend                                        26           27          132          132          176          176         173          19019&#13;
Cash                                            71          -41          152         -124            0           -3            0           -5             1 &#13;
5,331       7,278       10,548       10,324        9,960       13,007       15,714       16,311        17,528         4R&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
HL&amp;FS: Balance Sheet&#13;
(Rs. Million)&#13;
1991-92    1992-94     1994-95     1995-96     19967                          . 1.99-98 1998-99    1l999-00 2000-1:&#13;
ASSETS&#13;
Fixed Assets&#13;
Fixed Assets (Own)                       311         465         603        939        1,203       1,499       1,632       1,724       1,799&#13;
LeasedAssets                           1,663       2,641       3,217       4,585       5,977       7,525       9,262      11,271      13,424&#13;
Leased WIP                               216         321         624        456        1,084       1,636        579         670         717&#13;
Operating Assets                           0           0           0         550         550        800         800        1,050       1,300&#13;
Project Assets                             0         259         299         577        837         966        2,517      2,157        2,157&#13;
Less: Accumulated Depreciation         -478         -989      -1,211      -1,561      -2,100      -2,746      -3,586     -4,644       -5,838&#13;
Total Fixed Assets                   1,713      2,697       3,532       5,546       7,551       9,681      11,204      12,228      13,560&#13;
Long Term Investments&#13;
Premises Deposits                         31          56         109         130         155         180        210         250         250&#13;
Deb/Bonds/Govt Securities              1,627         806       1,751       1,896       2,001       1,837       1,748       1,767       1,735&#13;
Unquoted Sbares                           41          16          16          16          16          16         16          16           161&#13;
.. ..... .. . ..~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
NewProjects-Debt                           0           0          51         51          980       2,383       5,135       6,935       8,207p&#13;
NewProjects-Equity                         3          11         224         224        351         724        1,104       1,378       1,656&#13;
Loans&amp;LAdvances                        1,013       2,962       4,730       6,237       6,144       9,112      11,315      13,649      15,660&#13;
Venture Capital                            0         127         150         150         150         150        150         150          150&#13;
Total Long Term Investments         2,715       3,978       7,031       8,704       9,798      14,402      19,679      24,144      27,674&#13;
Short Tern Investments&#13;
Bills of Exchange                        786         425         354         281         250        218         191           0            0&#13;
Quoted Trade Investments                 152         298         337         500        650         825        1,025       1,250       1,475&#13;
Units of Mutual Fund                     303         344         509         179        209         239         269         299         329&#13;
Total Short Term Investments        1,241       1,067       1,199         961       1,109       1,282       1,486       1,549       1,804&#13;
Current Assets&#13;
Cash &amp;      Bank Balances                 67          26         220          96          96          93         93          88           881,79&#13;
Trade Debtors                            192         230         216         206         358        440         574         691          781342&#13;
Interest Accrued                          86          24          63         254         279         398        580         761          880&#13;
AccruedRentalsnot due                    316         557         536         503         390         301         198         85           26&#13;
Advance Tax                              206         153          40          25          25          30          35         40           40&#13;
PrepaidExpenses                            2           2          133         13          13          13          13          13          13&#13;
Total Current Assets                  869         992       1,086       1,096       1,161       1,275       1,492       1,678       1,828&#13;
TOTAL ASSETS                        6,538       8,733      12,849      16,307      19,619      26,640      33,860      39,599      44,866&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IL&amp;FS: Balance Sheet&#13;
(Rs. Million)&#13;
1991-92    1992-94    1994-95    1995-96    1996-97    197-98    1998-9          19990    200041&#13;
LIABILITIES&#13;
Net Worth&#13;
Equity Shares                            222         588        686         863        863         863        949         949        949&#13;
Preference Shares                         52          31         31          31         31           0          0           0           0&#13;
P&amp;L Surplus                              109         119        106         380        921       1,613       2,663      4,140       5,898&#13;
DebentureRedemptionReserve                 0           8          12         12          12         12          12         12          12&#13;
General Reserve                           51          41        200         200        200         200        200         200        200&#13;
Investment Allowance Reserve              36          36         36          36         36          36         36          36          36&#13;
Share Premium                             14         614       1,594      2,104       2,104      2,104       2,967      2,967       2,967&#13;
Contingency Reserve                        0          67        117         117         117        117         117        117         117&#13;
Total Net Worth                       484       1,503       2,781      3,742       4,283      4,944       6,944       8,420     10,178&#13;
Long Term Borrowings&#13;
Bank Term Loan                             0         250        900           0           0          0           0          0           0&#13;
Fl Term Loan                            1,942      2,098       2,432      1,633       1,282      1,868       2,253      2,405       2,547             I&#13;
Multilateral Agencies                    272         272       1,056      2,042       2,740      3,519       4,047      4,876       5,804             4&#13;
IBRD Borrowing                             0           0          0           0        929       2,332       4,208      6,008       7,000&#13;
OtherTermLoans                           138         260         135          0           0          0           0          0           0&#13;
Deferred Credit                          358         225         128         79          20          0           0          0           0&#13;
Fixed Deposits                            10           4          3         253        625        1,125      1,375       1,750      1,875&#13;
Bank Overdraft                           380         714       1,652      3,800       2,666      3,361       2,991       2,270      1,447&#13;
Floating Rate Bonds                        0           0          0         500         900        900       1,000       1,000      1,250&#13;
Deposit from SPC                           0           0          0           0         388        888       2,072       1,968      1,865&#13;
Total Long Term Borrowings           3,099      3,823       6,306      8,307       9,550      13,993     17,947      20,278     21,788&#13;
Current Liabilities&#13;
Short Term Loans                       2,511       1,868       1,506      1,000       1,500       1,750      1,500       1,500      1,650&#13;
Debentures                                 0       1,105       1,656      2,156       2,556      3,556       4,556       5,556      6,306&#13;
Provision for Interest                   111         129          88        395        477         607         772        902       1,012         IV&#13;
Sundry Creditors                         277          45         63         103         385        435         253        328         403&#13;
Misc. Liabilities                         18         107         193        304         568       1,059      1,576       2,302      3,216         H&#13;
Proposed Dividend                         27         123         132        176         176        173         190        190         190&#13;
Customer Advance                          10          24          56         56          56         56          56         56          56&#13;
Provision for Non Performing Assets        0           6          24         24          24         24          24         24          24&#13;
Provision for Investment Valuation         0           0          43         43          43         43          43         43          43&#13;
Total Current Liabilities            2,955      3,407       3,762       4,258      5,786       7,703      8,970      10,901      12,900&#13;
TOTAL LIABILITIES                    6,538       8,733     12,849      16,307      19,619     26,640     33,860      39,599      44,866&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IL&amp;FS selected financial ratios&#13;
_- - -- --&#13;
Debt:equity ratio&#13;
11.83     4.61      3.40      3.06      3.09      3.72      3.16       3.01       2.74&#13;
Debt service coverage&#13;
ratio           n.a.      n.a.      2.21      1.47      2.14      2.00      2.10       2.24       2.45&#13;
Return on net worth (%)&#13;
24.16     14.96     19.60     12.71     18.18     19.08     19.55     21.91       21.12&#13;
Return on total assets&#13;
1.40     3.29      3.68       3.9      3.99      3.74      4.10       4.54       4.61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43-&#13;
ANNEX 2.6&#13;
Pikc   of 2&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS's financial forecast: sensitivity analysis&#13;
A sensitivity analysis was carried out on IL&amp;FS's financial forecast to assess the&#13;
impact of certain events on its future financial performance, as compared to the base case&#13;
scenario discussed in Chapter II and Annex 2.5. The following scenarios are presented&#13;
below. Their respective outcomes are summarized in Attachment 1.&#13;
Scenario A: (a)  commercial infrastructure assets grow at a slower pace to reach Rs.&#13;
7,923 million (US$226 million) by March 31, 2001; US$150 million,&#13;
instead of the projected US$200 million, is disbursed from the Bank&#13;
loan;&#13;
(b)  fee income increases by Rs. 150 million only over the 1995/96 figures;&#13;
(c)  no income provision is made for capital gains on the proprietary&#13;
portfolio, the size of which remains the same over the entire period;&#13;
(d)  leasing and investment banking assets are 20% lower than in the base&#13;
case through the entire period.&#13;
Scenario B: (a)  same as above;&#13;
(b)  fee income increases by Rs.65 million over 1995/96 (the establishment&#13;
of the AIG fund has already secured the receipt of such additional&#13;
income);&#13;
(c)  same as above;&#13;
(d)  leasing and investment banking assets are one third lower than in the&#13;
base case.&#13;
Scenario C: (a)  same as above;&#13;
(b)  no increase in fee income as compared to 1995/96 results;&#13;
(c)  same as above;&#13;
(d)  leasing and investment banking assets are 50% lower than in the base&#13;
case.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-44-&#13;
ANNEX 2.6&#13;
Attachment 1&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis Summary Results&#13;
1995/96    1996/97    1997/98    1998/99   1999/2000   2000/01&#13;
Scenario A&#13;
Debt: equity ratio           3.06        2.86       3.33       2.80       2.77        2.66&#13;
Debtservicecoverageratio      1.47       2.01       2.19       2.18       2.44       2.66&#13;
Retumonnetworth(%/o)         12.71      15.94      15.87       15.52      17.00      16.10&#13;
Retumontotalassets(%/6)      3.09        3.60       3.32       3.51       3.71        3.58&#13;
Scenario B&#13;
Debt: equity ratio           3.06        2.76       3.22       2.72       2.71        2.64&#13;
Debt service coverage ratio   1.47       1.96       2.25       2.20       2.52        2.92&#13;
Retum onnetworth(%/o)        12.71      14.40       13.12      13.25      15.49      14.78&#13;
Retum on total assets (%/6)  3.09        3.29       2.80       3.05       3.41        3.28&#13;
Scenario C&#13;
Debt: equity ratio           3.06        2.64       3.00       2.45       2.40       2.33&#13;
Debt service coverage ratio   1.47       1.89       2.26       2.27       2.70        3.01&#13;
Retum on net worth (%/6)     12.71      12.02      11.40       12.57      15.07      14.17&#13;
Retum on total assets (%/o)  3.09        2.78       2.52       3.06       3.53        3.38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.1&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Subproject eligibility criteria&#13;
1.    IL&amp;FS, through a specialized group called Infrastructure Project Advisory Services, is&#13;
constantly developing a pipeline of projects, which constitutes the source of future business for&#13;
its investment banking activities. The identification of potential investments is made through&#13;
permanent contacts held by the company with major actors in the infrastructure field. Their&#13;
action could be characterized as follows: (i) the continuous infrastructure needs search&#13;
conducted, on a regular basis, by relevant agencies in GOI and State governments; (ii) the&#13;
identification work being carried out by regional and local organizations, private as well as&#13;
public, which also detect deficiencies and/or identify infrastructure requirements; and (iii)&#13;
proposals raised by private groups interested in developing a certain undertaking which already&#13;
has a tentative official approval. Upon receipt of the different ideas, IL&amp;FS will screen the&#13;
identified projects, and start with the project appraisal cycle.&#13;
2.    For the proposed Bank loan, eligibility criteria (Attachment 1) have been developed to&#13;
sort out priorities for Bank lending and ensure replicability of subprojects. The latter will&#13;
simplify the processing of onlending requests, through obvious economies of scales that would&#13;
undoubtedly occur. The eligibility criteria will be applicable to all subprojects to be funded with&#13;
the assistance of the proposed line of credit to IL&amp;FS, unless otherwise agreed by the Bank on a&#13;
case-by-case basis. These subprojects would involve private investments for capacity&#13;
augmentation and/or new facilities. The criteria specify, as an illustration, the priority sectors&#13;
and give examples of the types of subprojects in each sector. They also include essential&#13;
financial eligibility criteria for onlending.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46-&#13;
ANNEX 3.1&#13;
Attachment 1&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA FOR BANK-FINANCED SUBPROJECTS&#13;
Priority Sectors     integrated urban infrastructure: (i) provision of urban&#13;
infrastructure facilities and services for municipalities&#13;
and similar authorities in an integrated manner; (ii)&#13;
provision of infrastructure services for industrial estates&#13;
and/or economic zones.&#13;
t transport sector: (i) toll bridges; (ii) toll urban bypases;&#13;
(iii) other toll roads where there is an alternative non-&#13;
tolled road.&#13;
*  water supply and sanitation sector: (i) water source&#13;
augmentation and distribution; (ii) sewerage works and&#13;
domestic sewage and industrial waste treatment and&#13;
disposal; (iii) utility management with augmentation and&#13;
rehabilitation; (iv) solid waste management.&#13;
* DSubprject Size     Maximum of US$200 million and minimum of US$1 0&#13;
million.&#13;
O  Capital Struture   No more than 75% debt (senior and subordinated).&#13;
eof he SPV         Promoter's contribution to represent at least 25% of the.&#13;
equity. Subproject debt service coverage ratio of no less&#13;
than 1.25 on an annual cash-flow basis.&#13;
* Development         Subprojects should have been developed within prudent&#13;
gidelines&amp;         project development guidelines, including experienced&#13;
participants (e.g., construction consortium, O&amp;M operator),&#13;
turnkey fixed price contract with specific performance and&#13;
adequate liquidated damage provisions, prudent contracts for&#13;
offtake sales or concession agreements, operating&#13;
agreements, linkage among the contracts to reduce risk,&#13;
adequate insurance, and adequate protection for minority&#13;
equity owners (such as IL&amp;FS).&#13;
*  IBRD Financial     Maximum 25% of individual subproject cost. Proceeds of&#13;
Participation      the Bank loan would be onlent only to those projects in&#13;
which the entire financing package has been finalized&#13;
(committed or raised) or in which promoter guarantees of&#13;
high quality have been provided prior to the finalization of&#13;
C________________ ;the completion of the financial package.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47-                 ~~~~ANNEX 3.1&#13;
Attachment 1&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
*  Financial IRR      Minimum real FRR of 14% required for each subproject.&#13;
*  Econonic IRR       Minimum ERR of 12% required for each subproject, and&#13;
test of optimum investment time through first year&#13;
benefit/cost &gt; 12%, or its equivalent maximum net present&#13;
value at i=12%.&#13;
*  Environmental and   Subprojects shall conforn to environmental and social&#13;
Social Requirements  (R&amp;R) requirements of GOI and IBRD. Subproject&#13;
appraisal, approval, construction and operation consistent&#13;
with IL&amp;FS environmental and social policy and&#13;
operational procedures.&#13;
*  Institutional &amp;    The contractual agreements, in form and substance&#13;
Contractual        satisfactory to the Bank, should clearly lay down the mutual&#13;
Arrangements       rights and obligations of the various participants to the&#13;
subproject, and reflect a fair and reasonable allocation of&#13;
risks among them. In addition, there should be no explicit&#13;
or implicit government guarantee in support of the&#13;
subproject.&#13;
*  Implementation     For subprojects &lt; US$60 million, a maximum&#13;
Period             implementation period of three years; else, a maximum of&#13;
five years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-48-&#13;
ANNEX3.2&#13;
Page 1 of 8&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Subproject pipeline and implementation schedule&#13;
1.    IL&amp;FS has identified a long list of projects in transport, mass transit systems, power,&#13;
telecommunications, water supply, sewage and effluent treatment and integrated area&#13;
development1. Some of these projects are large, like the multi-purpose road bridge across the&#13;
Gulf of Cambay connecting the eastern and western regions of the State of Gujarat (total&#13;
estimated cost when all phases are completed: US$1.6 billion), or the Bangalore Mass Rapid&#13;
Transit System involving the construction of 90 km of light rail at a total estimated cost of&#13;
US$1.4 billion. However, the more typical IL&amp;FS project ranges from about US$60 million&#13;
(Delhi-Noida bridge, Panvel bypass) to around US$200 million (Tirupur, Mangalore area&#13;
development projects). The projects vary also with respect to project preparation, with some&#13;
already reaching the final stages prior to start of construction (Panvel bypass and, to a lesser&#13;
extent, Delhi-Noida bridge), while others are still at a preliminary stage (Adityapur intra-city&#13;
link, Gujarat roads and Mangalore area development). Most of the projects are being&#13;
promoted by state governmnents. Some, for example, are promoted by a group of industries to&#13;
enhance the infrastructure facilities within and around their location; this is the case, for&#13;
example, of the Tirupur area development progran, which is promoted by the Tirupur&#13;
Exporters' Association (combined annual turnover: US$1 billion), or the Dewas water supply&#13;
project, promoted by a large pharmaceutical company.&#13;
2.    The company is aware that some of these projects may either slip or not be executed&#13;
at all, while new subprojects may be incorporated in the course of implementing the proposed&#13;
Project. The atttached indicative pipeline of subprojects form the core group of investments&#13;
identified for possible financing under the Project. It is a scaled down version of the above-&#13;
mentioned list, bearing in mind that (a) commercial infrastructure projects take a considerable&#13;
time to develop, and (b) IL&amp;FS can only gradually build up its capacity to handle the&#13;
correspondingly large volume of appraisal work. This pipeline should be considered as&#13;
indicative as further changes may occur during the implementation of the Project.&#13;
3.    The attached tables show the individual projects with a brief description, the estimated&#13;
cost, the current status and the planned construction period. Each table includes projects to&#13;
be started in three successive IL&amp;FS fiscal years, the first one covering the period April 1,&#13;
1996 to March 31, 1997. Subprojects in the 1996/97 group, for example, are quite advanced&#13;
in general and have a high probability of being implemented soon: this is the case, for&#13;
example, of the Panvel bypass and the Delhi-NOIDA bridge where IL&amp;FS is acting as project&#13;
sponsor and setting up joint ventures with other parties (contractors, toll operators) for the&#13;
Normally, it means the development of an area to facilitate industrial growth. Typically, an integrated area&#13;
development program envisages the provision of several infrastructure services such as: surface transport,&#13;
power, telecom, water supply, drainage and effluent treatment, and commercial and/or housing&#13;
development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49-&#13;
A1NNEX 3.2&#13;
Page 2 of 8&#13;
implementation of the projects. Subprojects in the latter two groups vary in their degree of&#13;
complexity of preparation; hence the probability of their being started within the&#13;
implementation period of the Project varies significantly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
INDIATIY PROJECT PIPELINE&#13;
1996-97&#13;
No          Name                   Description             Cost                     Status                             Implementation&#13;
(Rs Mn)&#13;
Start        Commissioning&#13;
Panvel Bypass        - National Highway project       2072    - Feasibility studies completed            Q3 1996-97         Q4 1998-99&#13;
Maharash             - 10.135-km, four-lane bypass            - Executed final MoU&#13;
to Panvel town on National             - Detailed engineering studies completed&#13;
Highway 4 (NH4); includes              - Update traffic study to be completed by&#13;
one flyover, three river                February 1996&#13;
bridges, one ROB and seven             - Concession agreement to be executed&#13;
underpasses.                            between MoST, GoM and IL&amp;FS by&#13;
March 1996                                                                    o&#13;
2    Delhi-Noida Bridge    - State project                 2309    - Feasibility studies completed             Q4 1996-97        Q4 1998-1999&#13;
UP/Delhi             - 550-m eight-lane bridge                - Detailed engineering completed&#13;
across river Yamuna; with              - PQ for turnkey contract issued&#13;
approx. 3.50 km. approach              - Shortlisting completed in November 1995&#13;
roads and grade-separated              - Bid document finalisation and issue by&#13;
interchanges                            February 1996&#13;
- Concession agreement between GoD,&#13;
GoUP and IL&amp;FS to be executed by&#13;
April 1996&#13;
at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
INDICATIVE PROJECT PIPELINE&#13;
1996-97&#13;
No         Name                   Description             Cost                    Status                            Implementation&#13;
(Rs Mn)&#13;
Start        Commissioning&#13;
3    Tirupur Area         - State project                 7782    - Initial feasibility studies completed  Q4 1996-97        QI 2000-2001&#13;
Develop. Programme   - An integrated area develop-           - SPV incorporated (NTADCL)&#13;
Tamil Nadu            ment scheme including water            - GoTN order issued authorising NTADCL&#13;
supply, drainage, effluent             to draw water to implement scheme on a&#13;
treatment, roads and telecom            commercial basis&#13;
- Detailed project studies, including&#13;
engineering, financial, economic, contrac-&#13;
tual agreements, bidding documents, etc.,&#13;
to be completed by July 1996&#13;
- Roads works to be awarded for cons-&#13;
truction by December 1996&#13;
- Water supply and related infrastructure&#13;
to be awarded by February 1997&#13;
4    Dewas Water Supply   - State project                 1579    - Feasibility studies completed          Q4 1996-97        QI 2000-2001&#13;
Scheme               - The project seeks to                  - Agreement on recommended com-&#13;
Madhya Pradesh        substantially augment the                mercial framework for implementation&#13;
water supply to Dewas                   reached in December 1995&#13;
industrial estate                     - Contractual agreements to be drafted by&#13;
March 1996&#13;
- PQ notice to be issued by April 1996&#13;
5    Borivali-Virar       - Indian Railway project        2800    - Engineering studies completed          Q4 1996-97        Q4 1999-2000&#13;
Quadrupling Project   - Project being implemented            - Commercial space development plan to&#13;
Maharashtra            on a commercial format                  be completed by April 1996&#13;
- 60 km of additional track             - Agreement with IR by April 1996&#13;
- 6 new stations                        - PPM to be completed by June 1996&#13;
- Commercial development                - Financial and technical close by&#13;
of space                                September 1996&#13;
xII&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
INDICATIVE PROJECT PIPELINE&#13;
1997-98&#13;
No            Name                       Description             Cost                       Status                             Implementation&#13;
(Rs Mn)&#13;
Start      Commissioning&#13;
Adityapur Bridge          - State project                    570    - Initial screening report completed            Q3 1997-98     Q3 1999-2000&#13;
Bihar                     - 500-m, 2-lane high level bridge         - TORs finalised&#13;
- 5-km approach roads                     - Appointment of consultants to be completed&#13;
by March 1996&#13;
- Project documentation to be completed by&#13;
September 1996&#13;
- Financial and technical close by June 1997&#13;
2    Elevated Highway          - National Highway project         1000    - Initial engineering studies completed        Q3 1997-98      Q3 1999-2000&#13;
Panipat                   - 5-km elevated highway on                - TORs for additional studies to be finalised&#13;
Haryana                    National Highway I (NH I)                  by March 1996&#13;
- Project documentation to be completed by&#13;
September 1996&#13;
- Financial and technical close by June 1997&#13;
3    Bubaneshwar-Cuttack       - State project                    1472    - Feasibility study completed in December 1995  Q4 1997-98     Q4 1999-2000&#13;
Bypass                    - Bypass to National Highway 5            - Additional project documentation to be&#13;
Orissa                      (NH5)                                     completed by June 1996&#13;
- Includes roads &amp; bridges                - Financial and technical close targeted for&#13;
Q4 1997-98&#13;
4    Gujarat Roads Project     - State project                    1500    - Initial screening report completed           Q4 1997-98      Q4 2000-2001&#13;
Gujarat                   - Widening and strengthening of            - Preliminary Report to be completed by&#13;
existing two-lane state high-             February 1996&#13;
ways                                    - Detailed project documentation to be&#13;
completed by November 1996&#13;
- Financial and technical close by Q3 1997-98&#13;
0I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
INDICATIVE PROJECT PIPELINE&#13;
1997-98&#13;
No  Name                       Description                      Cost      Status                                    Implementation&#13;
(Rs Mn)&#13;
Start          Commissioning&#13;
5    Moradabad Area            - National Highway &amp; Ministry              - Projects promoted by local exporters'    Q4 1997-98        Q4 2000-2001&#13;
Development Programme       of Commerce project                       association&#13;
Uttar Pradesh             - The programe envisages two              - Land has been acquired&#13;
distinct schemes:                       - TORs completed in Nov. '95&#13;
(a) Implementation of a 2-lane    600    - Project documentation to be completed by&#13;
bypass of 20 km on                       Q3 1996-97&#13;
National Highway 24 (NH24)             - Financial &amp; technical close by Q3 1997&#13;
(b) Provision of captive power    1000                                                                                    w&#13;
facility for Moradabad export&#13;
units&#13;
6    Mangalore Area            - State project                    7225    - Scheme has been approved by Govt. of     Q4 1997-98        Q4 2000-2001&#13;
Development Programme    - Water supply scheme for                    Karnataka&#13;
Karnataka                   Mangalore industry and town             - Cabinet approval for commercial&#13;
implementation of project expected by&#13;
December 1995&#13;
- Project documentation to be completed&#13;
byQ3 1996&#13;
- Financial and technical close by Q4&#13;
1997-98                                 ___&#13;
Standby Project for FY 1997-98:&#13;
No            Name                      Description             Cost                      Status                              Implementation&#13;
(Rs Mn)&#13;
Start        Commissioning&#13;
Worli-Bandra Link Bridge   - State project                 6331    - Feasibility studies completed              Q4 1997-98        Q4 2000-2001&#13;
Maharashtra               - 1 2-km, 6-lane, partially cable-       - Approval of MoEF for EIA awaited&#13;
stayed bridge                          - Financial and technical close targeted for Q4&#13;
- 5.8-km approach roads                    1997-98&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
INDICATIVE PROJECT PIPELINE&#13;
1998-99&#13;
No            Name                      Description             Cost                      Status                             Implementation&#13;
(Rs Mn)&#13;
Start        Commissioning&#13;
I    Vasai-Virar Area          - State project                  12000   -Initial concept has been proposed for Govt.  Q4 1998-99       Q4 2003-04&#13;
Development Programme    - Provision of water, transport            of Maharashtra (GoM) approval&#13;
Maharashtra                and related infrastructure to           -GoM approval expected Q1 1996-97&#13;
rapidly developing region              -Preparation of project documentation to&#13;
north of Bombay                         commence in Q2 1996-97&#13;
2    lndore-Bhopal Highway     - State project                  2000    -GoMP to tender for BOT operators            Q1 1998-99         Q1 2003-04&#13;
Madhya Pradesh            - 200-km state highway linking           -Selection of BOT operators targeted for Q3&#13;
Indore, commercial capital of           1996-97                                                                         n&#13;
Madhya Pradesh to Bhopal               -IL&amp;FS review to appraisal targeted for Q4&#13;
administrative capital of MP            1996-97&#13;
3    Tuticorin Port            - National Port project          7000    -MOST tender selection to be completed       Q1 1998-99         Q3 2001-02&#13;
Tamil Nadu                - Upgrading, modernisation and            by Q2 1996-97&#13;
expansion of existing port on&#13;
a commercial format&#13;
4    Vizag Area Development    - State project                  5000    -Vizag municipality and industry would       Q2 1998-99         Q3 2001-02&#13;
Andhra Pradesh            - 50 MGD water supply scheme              be the sponsors&#13;
to industry to household               -Preparation of project documentation to&#13;
- Effluent treatment scheme              commence in Q2 1996-97&#13;
5    Outer Ring Road           - State project                  3000    -Proposal for implementation of outer        Ql 1998-99         Q3 2001-02&#13;
Tamil Nadu                - 60-km 2-lane highway                    ring road on a commercial format has&#13;
been accepted by GoTN&#13;
-Initial screening report to be completed&#13;
by December 1995&#13;
-TORs to be finalised by February 1996&#13;
-Preparation of project documentation to&#13;
commence from April 1996&#13;
-3Z&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
INDICATIVE PROJECT PIPELINE&#13;
Standby Project for FY 1998-99:&#13;
No             Name                       Description              Cost                       Status                               Implementation&#13;
(Rs Mn)&#13;
Start         Commissioning&#13;
Gulf of Cambay             - State project                   50000   - Initial screening report completed           Q4 1997-98          Q3 2002-03&#13;
Gujarat                    - Multi-facility bridge, includ-           - MoU entered into between GIIC and IL&amp;FS&#13;
ing road, rail, water, gas and           - Project documentation to be completed by&#13;
oil pipelines                              Q2 1997-98&#13;
- Approach roads&#13;
- Area development&#13;
Qn&#13;
0J&#13;
ac&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-56-&#13;
-56-                  ~~~~ANNEX 3.3&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS proposed training and technical assistance activities&#13;
(summary)&#13;
Training&#13;
The development of infrastructure projects typically involves three distinct phases: (i)&#13;
project identification and platning, (ii) detailed design and execution, and (iii) operation and&#13;
maintenance. Given the range of activities, IL&amp;FS needs to deliver from within its ranks a&#13;
diverse range of skills across infrastructure development and project management, including inter&#13;
alia, financial engineering, economic, legal and support functions. IL&amp;FS has formulated a&#13;
comprehensive staff development program, the details of which are contained in the project files.&#13;
In order to provide the appropriate skills to its personnel, the company proposes to have a&#13;
three-tier staff development program aimed at providing specialized training based on the&#13;
functional responsibilities of the staff. The method of achieving skill upgradation at various&#13;
levels are as elaborated below:&#13;
* Junior level: IL&amp;FS personnel would attend structured training courses, generally for a&#13;
duration of 2-3 weeks, to familiarize themselves with techniques of project development and&#13;
commercialization of infrastructure projects, mainly as a public/private partnership. Courses&#13;
would consist of classroom training and case study presentations;&#13;
* Middle level: IL&amp;FS personnel need to attend advanced courses on the formulation of&#13;
infrastructure projects as well as develop expertise in designing innovative debt instruments&#13;
and securitisation. The training program for such personnel would mainly be through&#13;
providing avenues for interaction with experienced practitioners at workshops/seminars.&#13;
Additionally, specially designed advanced courses would be delivered;&#13;
*  Senior level: IL&amp;FS personnel would be provided with an opportunity to visit projects&#13;
implemented on a commercial format and interact with major bankers, suppliers, contractors,&#13;
consultants, operators and concessionaires. Such interactions would expose them to the latest&#13;
thinking on the nature and form of agreements reached, for implementation and operation of&#13;
such projects.&#13;
Additionally, it is proposed that international experts be invited to work along with&#13;
IL&amp;FS personnel on a focused basis in areas like risk assessment and allocation, bid evaluation,&#13;
contracts and performance monitoring.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX3.&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
Technical assistance&#13;
IL&amp;FS has identified a number of areas where detailed studies or focussed advisory&#13;
services would be required to facilitate the evaluation and implementation of commercial&#13;
infrastructure projects. These are, for example, legal and regulatory framework applicable to&#13;
BOT projects in sectors of IL&amp;FS's interest, innovative financing for environmental&#13;
infrastructure in medium-sized cities and townships, traffic forecasting, willingness to pay and&#13;
fixation of user charges for water supply and road projects. A brief description of the proposed&#13;
studies is provided below. The results of these studies would be used by IL&amp;FS and would be&#13;
available to others on a selective basis.&#13;
Specific Studies:&#13;
* Contractual and legal documents: The main objective would be to examine the legal and&#13;
regulatory framework applicable to sectors of IL&amp;FS interest. Additionally the assignment&#13;
would include preparation of an outline bid document to invite BOT operators. As a part of&#13;
this document, evaluation criteria for selection of BOT operator in the sectors where IL&amp;FS&#13;
is actively involved would also be included.&#13;
* Financing environmental infrastructure in industrial townships: The main objective would be&#13;
to examine innovative approaches to financing water supply, wastewater treatment and&#13;
garbage disposal as an integrated package. IL&amp;FS has initiated some work as part of the&#13;
preparatory activities of the Tirupur integrated area development project, but this needs to be&#13;
significantly enhanced. The resulting model could be replicated in other industrial&#13;
townships. IL&amp;FS will draw extensively from international experience, as there is none&#13;
comparable locally. The scope of the assignment would include: (a) literature review and&#13;
study of international experiences; (b) researching financial and regulatory instruments such&#13;
as municipal bonds, water tariffs, effluent charges, tradable pollution permits and self-&#13;
enforcement; (c) applying these in two suprojects -- Tirupur and Mangalore; (d) negotiateing&#13;
with the Government to mainstream these instruments as an integral part of municipal&#13;
financing; and (e) preparing the commercial documents for the two suprojects.&#13;
* Traffic forecasting: The principal objective of this study is to establish an appropriate&#13;
method for forecasting traffic on the road network by relating it to population and socio-&#13;
economic characteristics in its catchment area. It should be based either on a travel demand&#13;
model, or other suitable method, that allows the analysis of the relationship between traffic&#13;
volume for each type of vehicles and specific economic variables. The study would include&#13;
analysis of traffic and other information on two typical road stretches, where MOST has&#13;
already undertaken traffic counts. The study should evolve a methodology using data bases&#13;
as are generally available in the country, collection of specific primary information, and&#13;
verify its consistency on the sample stretches.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-58-                         ANNEX 3.3&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
* User charge estimation - Willingness to Pay: The main objective is to determine viable user&#13;
charges based on a willingness-to-pay assessment of users. The study would cover two&#13;
sectors - water supply and roads. The consultant would be required to undertake user surveys&#13;
and relate willingness to pay with service levels and income in the case of water supply and&#13;
with respect to perceived congestion and trip purpose in the case of road users. The study&#13;
would take into account the past literature and studies conducted abroad, and suggest an&#13;
appropriate methodology for the conduct of such studies in India. It would be desirable if the&#13;
study results in the construction of willingness-to-pay curves similar to indifference curves.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS PROJECT CYCLE&#13;
MILESTONES             J                 GOAL                             PROCESS STEPS                 RESPONSIBILITY               DECISION/PRODUCT&#13;
Screening                         - Assessment of initial feasibility       a. Desk review                    IL&amp;FS                     - Initial screening report&#13;
- Identification of critical issues       b. Field investigations           IL&amp;FS/SPV/Sponsor           Decision to proceed or otherwise&#13;
- Examination of project eligibility with  c. Interactions:                IL&amp;FS/SPV/Sponsor/           with the project&#13;
respect to IL&amp;FS project selection criteria  - Project sponsor/SPV       Government&#13;
- Delineation of IL&amp;FS Role                 - Government&#13;
- Initial risk assessment                   - Users&#13;
Scoping                           Consensus on:                             a. Interactions between IL&amp;FS,    IL&amp;FS/SPV/ Sponsor/        - Memorandum of Understanding&#13;
- Extent, scope and nature of project      sponsors, SPV, government,       Government                  (MOU)&#13;
preparation                              public, users, etc.                                          Finalisation of Channels of&#13;
- Allocation of responsibility                                                                          Consultation&#13;
- Methodology of study&#13;
- Time frame                                                                                                                                   '.&#13;
- Sharing of costs&#13;
- Channels of Consultation&#13;
Finalisation of terms of reference  - TOR to be finalised with respect to all  a. Preparation of TOR          SPV/Sponsor/Consultant    - Terms of reference (TOR) for&#13;
(TOR) for project preparation       tasks to be undertaken during project     - findings from screening and                               appointment of consultants&#13;
studies                             preparation phase                           scoping&#13;
- technical components&#13;
- execution arrangements&#13;
b. Verification of TOR and       IL&amp;FS&#13;
consistency check with IL&amp;FS&#13;
business practices&#13;
Appointment of consultants        - Selection of suitable consultants       a. Selection of suitable consultants   SPV/Sponsor           - Consultants appointed&#13;
b. Consistency checks with IL&amp;FS&#13;
business practices              IL&amp;FS&#13;
iir&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MILESTONES                               GOAL                            PROCESS STEPS                RESPONSIBILITY               DECISION/PRODUCT&#13;
Project preparation              - Establish technical, economic, financial,    a. Field                    SPV/Sponsor/Consultant    - Detailed feasibility and&#13;
environment and social viability         - investigation                                             investment banking report&#13;
- Evolve a suitable procedure for the      - surveys                                                   (DFIBR)&#13;
commercial implementation of the project  - interactions                                           - Environmental and social&#13;
- Establish the contractual framework for  - sector studies                                            assessment report (ESAR)&#13;
the project including preparation of draft   b. Technical and engineering  SPV/Sponsor/Consultant    - Contractual framework&#13;
contractual agreements                  studies                                                      documentation (CFD)&#13;
- Identify, assess and allocate risks    c. Environmental and social studies  SPV/Sponsor/Consultant    - Detailed process of&#13;
associated with the project during     d. Market demand studies                                      implementation, including&#13;
construction, operation and maintenance    e. Economic analysis          SPV/Sponsor/Consultant      request for proposal/bidding&#13;
phases                                 f. Financial analysis             SPV/Sponsor/Consultant      documents and evaluation&#13;
g. Resource mobilisation plan    Sl'V/Sponsor/Consultant     criteria for selection of operator&#13;
h. Institutional and legal       SPV/Sponsor/Consultant      (DPI)&#13;
framework                      SPV/Sponsor/Consultant    - Risk identification. assessment&#13;
i. Development of contractual                                and management plan (RMP)&#13;
framework                      Sl'V/Sponsor/Consultant&#13;
j. Documentation for BOT operator&#13;
selection                      SPV/Sponsor/Consultant                                            T&#13;
- Performance standards&#13;
- Execution arrangements&#13;
- Evaluation framework&#13;
k. Risk analysis and allocation  SPV/Sponsor/Consultant&#13;
Initial project evaluation       - Review of draft project documentation by    a. IL&amp;FS verification        IL&amp;FS/Consultants         - Initial project evaluation report&#13;
IL&amp;FS                                   b. Clearance/concurrence                                    - Agreement on:&#13;
- Clearances/approvals by government       - State govemment clearance     SPV/Sponsor                - DFIBR&#13;
- GO[ clearance                SPV/Sponsor                 - EAR/SAMP&#13;
- MA concurrence               IL&amp;FS                       - CFD&#13;
-DPI&#13;
- RMP&#13;
Selection of Operator             Selection of a suitable Operator         a. Issue of PQ Notice            SPV/Consultant            - Award recommendation&#13;
b. Shortlisting of Operators     SPV/Consultant&#13;
c. Bid document release          SPV/Consultant&#13;
d. Evaluation and selection of   SPV/Consultant&#13;
operator&#13;
e. Consistency check with IL&amp;FS    IL&amp;FS&#13;
business practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MILESTONES             |                 GOAL                   |        PROCESS STEPS                RESPONSIBILITY               DECISIONIPRODUCT&#13;
Project financial close          -Translation of agreement into legally   a. Negotiation of contractual     IL&amp;FS, SPV/Sponsor,       - Final Project Evaluation Report&#13;
binding instruments                       documentation between SPV,      Govemment. Operator,      - Signed:&#13;
- Finalisation of financial consortia for the  government and Operator       SPV/Merchant Banker       a. Concession agreement&#13;
project                                 b. Preparation of private                                     b. Shareholders agreement&#13;
placement memorandum. and                                  c. Construction agreement&#13;
negotiation with lenders and                               d. O&amp;M contract agreement&#13;
other shareholders                                         Finalisation of project I&#13;
consortium&#13;
- I.enders' agreement&#13;
Project Monitoring and Audit     - Ensuring conformity to standards and    a. Periodic progress report      SPV/IL&amp;FS                 - Compliance report&#13;
agreements during construction.        b. Field visits                  IL&amp;FS/Lenders              - Annual audit&#13;
operation, and maintenance             c. Interactions with             IL&amp;FS/SPV&#13;
- Ensuring compliance with respect to      Govemment, SPV. Operator,&#13;
disbursement procedures                  lender. MA. local&#13;
user groups, etc.&#13;
H&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-62-&#13;
ANNEX 3.5&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Subproject evaluation report&#13;
1.    The development and financing of commercial infrastructure projects are highly complex&#13;
operations. IL&amp;FS is expanding not only onto new grounds, but also into a demanding line of&#13;
activities, where no experience is available in India. Because of its early involvement in the&#13;
design of some projects, its extensive role in bringing them to financial close and their inherent&#13;
complexity, IL&amp;FS is compelled to set for itself high standards of project appraisal.&#13;
2.    A project report will be the document that includes all necessary supporting data, analysis&#13;
and recommendations for a proposed onlending operation to become a subproject of the&#13;
proposed Bank loan. It will be the basic document that IL&amp;FS submits to the Bank for review&#13;
and. if applicable. for issuance of the Bank's no objection for the operation to become a&#13;
subproject. To avoid duplications and possible misunderstandings, the project reports will&#13;
resemble to a large extent what IL&amp;FS will submit to its Board for project approval.&#13;
3.    Attachment I shows, schematically, the agreed content of a typical project report. With&#13;
respect to the section on "Sectoral Framework", IL&amp;FS may have a problem in covering this&#13;
area, in a comprehensive manner, in those cases where there is no official sectoral plan or&#13;
strategy, as its staff is not mandated, nor has the capacity to undertake this type of background&#13;
study. In such cases, IL&amp;FS would strive to collect as much sectoral information as possible&#13;
through meetings with government officials and lending agencies, and review of relevant&#13;
documents, and would take the results as a framework to check the overall economic viability of&#13;
the sub-projects.&#13;
4.    IL&amp;FS is adequately getting organized to prepare project reports for each case. Most of&#13;
the contents of such reports are already being covered by the company, although not in a&#13;
systematic way. As indicated elsewhere in this SAR, IL&amp;FS currently has an advanced input in&#13;
individual projects by providing advisory services to public agencies extending the concessions.&#13;
These public agencies do not yet have the capabilities, nor the financial means to develop&#13;
projects on their own in India. Thus, IL&amp;FS is temporarily filling a vacuum, but at the same&#13;
time is getting valuable experience in project appraisal. The project report, in most cases, will be&#13;
the culmination of a lot of works that IL&amp;FS will have been involved in through those advisory&#13;
services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-63-&#13;
ANNEX 3.5&#13;
Attachment 1&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
CONTENT OF A PROJECT EVALUATION REPORT&#13;
* ...IL&amp;FS'9s Role inTProject  Brief history of IL&amp;FS's involvement in project&#13;
Preparation            preparation, other groups involved, coordination, details&#13;
on who prepared the report.&#13;
* Sectoral Framework      Available plans in relevant and related sectors,&#13;
consistency of proposed subproject with future sectoral&#13;
plans, risk evaluation, proposal by promoter to improve&#13;
some sectoral issues.&#13;
* S*uproWect Technical    Location, size, capacity, general configuration and layout,&#13;
Description  . .       alternative designs, basis for selecting the design,&#13;
technical data, construction procedure, timetable,&#13;
proposed management.&#13;
*  Subproject Cost| Break-down of cost estimate, base data, physical and price&#13;
Estimate               contingencies, interest during construction, fees.&#13;
.   Resource Availability    Availability and estimated cost of construction materials,&#13;
water, power, human resources, social infrastructure, as&#13;
needed.&#13;
* Procurement             Detailed description of procurement process, compliance&#13;
with Bank guidelines, expected subcontracts, sample&#13;
bidding documents.&#13;
*  Sponsor                Members of consortium, previous experience,&#13;
organization, management, staffing, legal constitution,&#13;
technical/financial capabilities, assets/liabilities.&#13;
' Institutional &amp;          Details of all contractual agreements required for the&#13;
Contractual Framework  commnercial implementation of subprojects.&#13;
* Implementation          Timeframe.&#13;
Framework&#13;
* Market Assessment       Willingness to pay surveys for relevant income groups,&#13;
representative samples, rejection criteria for inconsistency,&#13;
forecasted users' behavior; existing, diverted and&#13;
generated demand, its mix, forecasted demand, scenarios&#13;
on variations of relevant economic variables, including&#13;
different toll rates and structure; optimum tariff/price to&#13;
maximize revenues, recommended value, comparison with&#13;
users' perceived benefits and willingness to pay.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-64-&#13;
ANNEX3.&#13;
Attachment 1 (cont'd)&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
*  Economic Analysis    Underlying rationale for the choice of each subproject,&#13;
expected beneficiary groups, economic benefits and costs,&#13;
each increment of investment to be feasible (marginal&#13;
analysis), staged construction, shadow prices, optimum&#13;
timing, economic indexes (ERR, NPV, B/C) if relevant.&#13;
+  Environment &amp;        In accordance with IL&amp;FS policy.&#13;
Social Assessment&#13;
f  Financing Plan       Identification of sources of funding, the nature of the&#13;
financing instruments, their terms and conditions, the status&#13;
of financing commitments already received or to be received,&#13;
the proposed security package and associated interereditor&#13;
arrangements. Details of IL&amp;FS financial involvement:&#13;
amount and description of securities to be acquired&#13;
(senior/subordinated/deep discount), including coupon&#13;
ondebt, any equity kickers, repayment schedule, security&#13;
package, major lending terms or conditions for funding.&#13;
*  Financial Analysis   Detailed cash flow analysis, calculation of FRR. Base case&#13;
proformas of revenues and costs by major categories; major&#13;
assumptions, including taxes, interest and operating costs&#13;
(fuel and O&amp;M, escalation rates, currency rates). Indication&#13;
of the next actions involved for reaching financial closure,&#13;
clearances/approvals to be received from DEAIRBI, etc.&#13;
Audit arrangements for the project presentation of the&#13;
financing plan for the project, with distinction between&#13;
"during construction" and "after commissioning", if required.&#13;
*  Risk Analysis;       Risk due to uncertainties on cost, financing shortage,&#13;
Sensitivity          demand, Government policies, tariff/price levels, users'&#13;
behavior, actions to be taken by other parties, competing&#13;
projects, and currency fluctuations. Sensitivities.&#13;
*  Required Clearances   detailed list of official authorizations/clearances obtained and&#13;
to be obtained, estimated required timing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-65-                             ANNEX 3.6&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Performance monitoring indicators&#13;
INPUT INDICATORS                      4   Overall loan disbursement (cumulative, computed&#13;
annually)&#13;
4 Technical assistance to IL&amp;FS (consultants' inputs&#13;
in staff-weeks/ training of IL&amp;FS staff in staff-&#13;
days)&#13;
4   Technical assistance to public. authorities&#13;
(consultants' inputs in staff-weeks)&#13;
PROCESS INDICATORS                      4   Financial closure of subprojects (# of projects&#13;
closed per year)&#13;
* Magnitude of private sector funds leveraged&#13;
4 Start of construction of subprojects (# of projects&#13;
started per year)&#13;
*   Subproject commissioning   of projects&#13;
commissioned per year)&#13;
OUTPUT INDICATORS                     4*   Kilometers of roads constructed/improved&#13;
4   Liters/day of water delivered&#13;
*   Cubic meters of waste water/effluentrteated&#13;
* Kilometers of sewers built&#13;
*:  Number of houses built&#13;
OUTCOME INDICATORS                       4:  Vehicle usage (traffic eounts on roads/bridgeail&#13;
link built)&#13;
D Daily water consumption (domestic, Industial)&#13;
4   Ratio of final cost vs. closure estimate by :&#13;
subproject&#13;
4 Ratio of actual vs. projected construction period&#13;
IMPACT INDICATORS                      4   Growth in industrial output in subproject area&#13;
4   Reduced transportation costs&#13;
*   Improved water quality&#13;
4* User satisfaction (% of surveyed)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Supervision Plan&#13;
Total Estimated number of subprojects in the pipeline           18&#13;
of which:   transport                                           10&#13;
integrated area development (IAD)                    6&#13;
others                                               2&#13;
P = Preparation                C = Construction                  0 = Operations&#13;
Y                 Subproject Development Lifeline                             Supervision Requirements (in staff weeks)&#13;
Task Manager/ Environmental   Social   BOT Expert Economist  Technical    Annual&#13;
_  Transport      I TAD      Others   Financial Analyst   Specialist    Specialist                          Experts       Total&#13;
95/96       P         5           3                         7 7             6            6           4           4           10&#13;
C        --          --           --            --              --           --          --          --           --         3&#13;
96/97       P        7            4           2             12              6            6           8            8          10&#13;
C        3           2            --2                           2            2           -                       6&#13;
O         -    --          --            --             --             --          --                 --          --         62&#13;
97/98       p        3           2            2             8               4            4                        6           4&#13;
C        7           4            --            2               2            2                       --          10&#13;
mid term review&#13;
5              5             5                       3           6           66&#13;
98/99       P         I           --         -.             3               1             1                       4           2&#13;
C        7           6           2              4               3            3                        -10&#13;
O        2           --          --             3               1             1                                  2           38&#13;
9/2000     P         1          --          --             --              I            I           --          --&#13;
C        4           6           2              3               3            3           -                        8&#13;
O        5           --          --             5               2            2                       4            4          36&#13;
000/01    P         I           --          --             --                           1                                    --&#13;
C        4           2            2             3               2            2                                    4&#13;
O        6           4            0             5               2            2                        4           4          30&#13;
_ II]                                                                     X "          7 4 1 .  12    I    33   80         269&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-67-&#13;
ANNEX 3.7&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
Notes:&#13;
The plan is prepared on a rolling basis with subprojects moving from one phase to&#13;
another -- preparation, construction and operation -- over the successive years. A&#13;
further 9 projects are expected to enter the preparation phase in FY96/97.&#13;
Tasks in subproject preparation will include the review of initial screening report,&#13;
terms of reference for studies, study outputs (e.g., detailed feasibility reports, EA/SA,&#13;
EMP, RAP, IPDP), project agreements and other legal instruments. During&#13;
subproject construction and operation, execution of construction contracts,&#13;
implementation of EMP, RAP and IPDP will be monitored.&#13;
The Bank review function will progressively reduce as IL&amp;FS develops in-house&#13;
expertise. As regards environmental and social considerations, an in-depth review of&#13;
the ESR and IL&amp;FS organizational arrangements will be reexamined during the mid-&#13;
term review of the Project. Following the review, the supervision plan may need to&#13;
be modified.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-68-&#13;
ANNEX 3.8&#13;
Page I of 3&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Selection of BOT operators&#13;
1.    In several cases, it is proposed that the BOT operator for the subprojects to be financed&#13;
under the loan will be selected competitively, following which the selected entrepreneur will be&#13;
free to procure the goods. works and services required for the facility, from eligible sources,&#13;
using its own procedures. It is essential then that, to enable IL&amp;FS to use the proceeds of the&#13;
Bank loan to onlend to the subprojects, transparent and explicit procedures be followed in the&#13;
selection of the BOT operator. Below is an outline of the general guidelines applicable to what&#13;
should be an open and competitive process for selecting BOT operators. Naturally, the specifics&#13;
of individual subproject specifics would bear heavily on the actual application of these&#13;
guidelines.&#13;
2.     Selection of operators would normally be on the basis of price'. As such selection&#13;
involves operational and financial issues not usually faced in the procurement of goods and&#13;
therefore requires considerable effort from the operators as well as the entity in charge of&#13;
managing the competitive bidding process, it is recommended that a two-stage process be&#13;
followed that involves prequalification and selection from the prequalified bidders.&#13;
3.     Stage I -- Prequalification. This involves the solicitation of interested private operators to&#13;
construct, own and operate the subproject. Solicitation should be made through an&#13;
announcement published in the international and Indian press and also distributed to the&#13;
embassies of member countries of the Bank. Interested firms would submit prequalification&#13;
statements based on a prequalification document (Request for qualification -- RFQ) which sets&#13;
out the information required from the developers and the evaluation criteria which are based on&#13;
the operators': (a) ability to raise equity and implement the subproject; (b) the operator's&#13;
financial condition, capacity to borrow and experience in raising equity; (c) technical&#13;
qualifications, including key personnel and experience with similar technology; and (d) project&#13;
development experience, which includes development of projects of a similar nature and&#13;
experience with private sector projects in developing countries. In their response, firms would&#13;
outline their experience and qualifications as they relate to implementing the proposed&#13;
subproject. The prequalification statements would then be evaluated using a "pass-fail criteria"&#13;
approach based on the criteria set out, enabling the establishment of a short list of prequalified&#13;
bidders.&#13;
This would typically be the case for water distribution systems, waste disposal, effluent treatment plants, power plants. etc.&#13;
Variations thereon could also he used for tolls charged on road or bridge projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-69-&#13;
ANNEX 3.8&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
4.    Stage II -- Selection. The prequalified operators would be required to respond to a&#13;
Request for Proposals (RFP) (bidding documents). The list of prequalified applicants could also&#13;
be published in the international press to ensure that qualified manufacturers are aware of the&#13;
subproject. The RFP would be broadly structured under the following headings:&#13;
* Invitation to prequalified applicants&#13;
* Information for applicants&#13;
*  Instructions to applicants&#13;
*  Security package and financing structure&#13;
*  Proposal evaluation and criteria for evaluation&#13;
*  Applicants' proposal and supporting data&#13;
*  Mandatory performance requirements and drawings&#13;
5.    The RFP should also contain drafts of the contractual framework (e.g., concession&#13;
agreement and other relevant documents), feasibility and investment banking report, risk&#13;
identification, environmental and social assessment reports, and management plans. The RFP&#13;
should clearly define operating requirements, evaluation methodology, technical requirements,&#13;
capital structure conditions for obtaining resources from IL&amp;FS under the proposed World Bank&#13;
loan, etc. The operators would submit their bid to develop the subproject based on the RFP. A&#13;
pre-bid meeting of the prequalified applicants could be held to elicit their comments on the RFP.&#13;
Clarifications based on the issues raised during the pre-bid meeting would then be issued to all&#13;
prequalified applicants. Bids for the subproject would be evaluated and ranked based on the&#13;
price quoted for the service to be rendered. The responsive proposal with the lowest evaluated&#13;
tariff would be selected and given an exclusive right -- for a limited time -- to develop the&#13;
project. The selected operator would be required to finalize the subproject agreements with&#13;
concerned parties (Government. lenders, etc). The second and third ranked candidates would,&#13;
however, be requested to keep their bids valid in the event the selected candidate does not fulfill&#13;
an agreement satisfactorily. The RFP would stipulate a project implementation schedule which&#13;
the selected operator would be required to adhere to and would be enforced through liquidated&#13;
damages contained in the subproject agreements. A minimum level of equity financing from the&#13;
operators could be required.&#13;
6.    Evaluation Methodology. The evaluation methodology would of course vary with the&#13;
type of subproject and service to be provided. In general, the price of the service required (e.g.,&#13;
price of water delivered) is a function of the operating efficiency and cost of the infrastructure&#13;
facility, as well as financing terms and operating regime. The concession agreement and&#13;
accompanying documents define the operating regime. The operators, in response to the RFP,&#13;
are required to quote for each year of the concession, the price for the service to be rendered,&#13;
based on prices for equipment, goods and services, as of 30 days prior to bid opening for&#13;
example. and other prices that might have already been furnished in the RFP. Based on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-70-&#13;
ANNEX 3.8&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
quantity of service that will have been specified in the bidding documents (e.g., quantity of water&#13;
to be supplied to the distribution system, traffic volume, plant capacity and annual energy to be&#13;
generated) and the bidder's quoted prices, the revenue stream is computed for each year over the&#13;
life of the concession. The revenue streams are then discounted using a discounting rate&#13;
specified in the bidding documents to arrive at the "averaged discounted price or levelized tariff'&#13;
which forms the basis of selection. The investors are also required, in their proposal, to furnish:&#13;
(a) details of the cost of the investment; (b); construction schedule; (c) financing plan; (d) terms&#13;
of financing; and (e) details of the calculation of the price of the service to be rendered. The loan&#13;
proceeds will be disbursed against construction costs. The developer is therefore required to&#13;
provide details of the construction cost, i.e., cost of supply, civil works and installation, and the&#13;
calculation for arriving at the quoted price. Moreover, as a condition for obtaining finance from&#13;
IL&amp;FS, the operator should be required to submit a construction contract satisfactory to IL&amp;FS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-71-&#13;
ANNEX 3.9&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PROPOSED PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS pari passu security structure&#13;
1.    Security offered to the initial lenders to IL&amp;FS was in the nature of a negative lien on the&#13;
company's assets. With effect from November 30, 1993, security in the nature of a negative lien&#13;
was substituted by way of a pari passu security structure. The structure envisages that all the&#13;
present and future assets (except those specifically exempted) of the company stand&#13;
hypothecated/mortgaged to Central Bank of India (CBI) acting as trustee to the present and&#13;
future senior lenders. It is illustrated in the figure below.&#13;
Security structure&#13;
IL&amp;FS               Hypothecation/Mortgage     Central Bank of India&#13;
3(8rrower)             &amp; Power Attorney             (trustee)&#13;
Responsibility to&#13;
ABC&#13;
(Lenders)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-72-&#13;
ANNEX 3.9&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
2.    The responsibilities of the trustee are as follows:&#13;
*     Effective and valid creation of the security on the movable assets by IL&amp;FS&#13;
by way of registration of the charge with the Registrar of Companies (ROC) (other than the&#13;
assets specifically excluded).&#13;
+     To ensure that the security coverage of 1.33 times the outstanding mortgage debt&#13;
thereby secured is maintained throughout the currency of trust security.&#13;
*     Effective and valid insurance cover for normal risk and for assignment of&#13;
assurance policies or registration of bank clause thereon in favour of the trustee/ existing and&#13;
future lenders.&#13;
*     Safe custody of all original documents of title, lease agreements, invoices,&#13;
registration books and other documents of title, to ensure the due recognition of the interest of&#13;
the Agent and Trustee and the existing and future senior lenders in respect of the leased assets by&#13;
the lessees and hirers and the due noting of the creation and registration of security created in&#13;
favour of the trustee and various other matters as may be provided.&#13;
*     Issue of periodical statements and certificates by the Agent and Trustee after&#13;
due verification and various other matters as may be provided therein.&#13;
3.    Under the security structure the company is required to maintain an asset cover of 1.33&#13;
times the borrowings. IL&amp;FS has to submit to the trustee each quarter an auditors' certificate&#13;
confirming that the asset cover is being maintained.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.9&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
Documents that covers the pari passu security structure&#13;
Document                                  Features&#13;
Memorandum of hypothecation of movable    This document provides for creation of first&#13;
assets by IL&amp;FS in favour of CBI (Trustees)  charge on all the movable assets of IL&amp;FS&#13;
in favour of Central Bank of India (CBI).&#13;
Power of attorney in favour of CBI as Agent   This document authorizes CBI to receive all&#13;
and Trustee for collection of lease rentals  the amounts due to I1&amp;FS by way of lease&#13;
and/or hire charges in respect of movable  rentals and initiate legal proceedings, if&#13;
leased assets                             necessary, in respect of lease agreements&#13;
between IL&amp;FS and its lessees.&#13;
Power of attorney in favour of CBI as Agent   This document authorizes to execute&#13;
and Trustee for senior lenders for creation of  mortgages in a form acceptable to senior&#13;
first mortgage and charge on immovable    lenders over all the immovable properties&#13;
assets                                    and assets of IL&amp;FS.&#13;
Power of attorney regarding assignment and   This power of attorney authorizes CBI to&#13;
charge of book debts and lease receivables    recover all book debts of IL&amp;FS, including&#13;
lease receivables.&#13;
Deed of covenant and undertaking from     This is an undertaking from IL&amp;FS to CBI&#13;
IL&amp;FS in favour of CBI as Agent and       to furnish periodic statements containing&#13;
Trustee for senior lenders to furnish     description of the new leased assets along&#13;
periodical statement of new assets/excluded    with relevant documents.&#13;
assets&#13;
Trusteeship letter by senior lenders to CBI to   Authorization by senior lenders to CBI to&#13;
act as agent &amp; Trustee for and on behalf of    act as Agent &amp; Trustee on behalf of the&#13;
the senior lenders                        senior lenders and to accept and hold the&#13;
mortgages, charges and securities created by&#13;
IL&amp;FS in trust and for the benefit of the&#13;
senior lenders.&#13;
Acceptance letter by CBI consenting to act as  Acceptance by CBI to act as Agent &amp;&#13;
Agent and Trustee for and on behalf of the  Trustee on behalf of the senior lenders and&#13;
senior lenders                            to accept and hold the mortgages, charges&#13;
and securities created by IL&amp;FS in trust and&#13;
for the benefit of the senior lenders.&#13;
New common loan agreement with new        The new loan agreement between IL&amp;FS&#13;
senior lenders                            and the proposed/new senior lenders&#13;
provides for creation of security on a pari&#13;
passu basis with the existing senior lenders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-74-&#13;
ANNEX 3.10&#13;
Page 1 of 2&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
IL&amp;FS: foreign exchange risk management and treasury operations&#13;
Until now, IL&amp;FS has hedged against foreign exchange (F/X) risk incurred in&#13;
borrowing long term in foreign exchange (from IFC and ADB) by arranging with local&#13;
counterparties back-to-back loan swaps. In these transactions, the company exchanges a&#13;
F/X liability for a rupee-denominated liability with repayment structures identical to the&#13;
original foreign exchange loan. In this fashion, the swap counterparty agrees, in a&#13;
commercial sense, to take over the F/X obligations of IL&amp;FS and directly services the&#13;
lender. However, IL&amp;FS remains the borrower on record and is liable for the loan and all&#13;
other obligations and covenants.&#13;
So far, IL&amp;FS has successfully executed three such swaps: one with IFCI and two&#13;
with the Export-Import Bank of India for F/X loans bearing maturities of 10 or 15 years.&#13;
It is currently finalizing a fourth one with Bank of India for a USAID-guaranteed 30-year&#13;
US$-denominated borrowing. Because there is no market in India for such hedging&#13;
mechanisms, loan swaps are strictly negotiated transactions subject to exchange rules and&#13;
regulations imposed by both the Ministry of Finance (MOF) and the Reserve Bank of&#13;
India (RBI). Arranging a swap is a relatively time-consuming process as a creditworthy&#13;
swap counterparty needs to be identified, the terns of the swap negotiated on a&#13;
transaction-by-transaction basis, and approval of the proposed swap obtained from MOF&#13;
and RBI,. Therefore, two basic conditions need to be met for these swaps to be cost-&#13;
effective: (i) there must be a minimum size to the transaction, in the order of US$20-25&#13;
million; and (ii) there must be predictability in the timing of the F/X liability so that&#13;
IL&amp;FS can manage the transaction as efficiently as possible and avoid finding itself in a&#13;
supplier's market.&#13;
IL&amp;FS will use the same mechanism for managing its foreign exchange risk under&#13;
the Project. To facilitate the execution of swap transactions, a Special Account, with an&#13;
authorized allocation of US$25 million, will be established by IL&amp;FS in a commercial&#13;
bank, on terms and conditions satisfactory to the Bank. Amounts deposited into the&#13;
Special Account will be withdrawn exclusively for the purpose of executing swap&#13;
transactions; the rupees obtained thereby will be deposited in a Swap Account, payments&#13;
out of which will be used exclusively for eligible expenditures under the Project.&#13;
For the first deposit into the Special Account, IL&amp;FS will submit to the Bank&#13;
copy of the draft negotiated swap agreement as documentation for the withdrawal of the&#13;
authorized allocation from the loan account. Within seven working days of disbursement&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-75-                        ANNEX31D&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
by the Bank, the swap transaction will have to be executed and the rupees thus obtained&#13;
by IL&amp;FS deposited in the Swap Account. If the swap is not executed within seven&#13;
working days, IL&amp;FS will have to refund the deposit.&#13;
For replenishment of the Special Account, IL&amp;FS will submit, not only copy of&#13;
the associated negotiated swap agreement, but also evidence of payments for eligible&#13;
expenditures made out of the proceeds of the previous deposit in the Swap Account.&#13;
Any unutilized portion of a deposit in the Swap Account, or such portion required&#13;
to be refunded under certain circumstances, will have to be refunded to the Special&#13;
Account for immediate refunding to the Bank in US dollars, using the exchange rate in&#13;
force at the time of the executed swap transaction.&#13;
It can be noted that ADB recently negotiated a loan with the Housing&#13;
Development Finance Corporation (HDFC) whereby arrangements similar to the ones&#13;
described above have been agreed and the use of the Special Account for swaps has been&#13;
permitted.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-76-                             Page 1 of15&#13;
INDIA&#13;
PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE (IL&amp;FS) PROJECT&#13;
Environmental and social report (ESR)&#13;
The objective of the environmental and social report (ESR) is to put in place an&#13;
environmental and social assessment process in IL&amp;FS which adequately responds to GOI&#13;
requirements and, for subprojects involving Bank financing, the Bank's operational directives&#13;
(ODs), namely OD 4.01 on Environmental Assessment, OD 4.30 on Involuntary&#13;
Resettlement, and OD 4.20 on Indigenous People, as well as Bank Procedures (BP) 17.50 on&#13;
Public Disclosure.&#13;
The process followed by IL&amp;FS for preparing the ESR is summarized below:&#13;
(a)   drafting of the ESR began in July 1995, as a recommendation of the Bank&#13;
preparation mission. The effort was led by IL&amp;FS with the assistance of the&#13;
NGO/Consultant -- Development Alternatives -- and guided by terms of&#13;
reference agreed with the Bank;&#13;
(b)   preparation followed a consultative process involving independent experts,&#13;
senior managers and Projects staff of IL&amp;FS;&#13;
(c)   IL&amp;FS shared interim outputs with the Bank for its comments. The Bank's&#13;
environment, social and legal divisions (ASTEN, ASTHR, LEGSA) and the&#13;
Departmental staff (SA2EI, SA2RS) reviewed these outputs. Additionally,&#13;
IL&amp;FS managers visited Washington in September and October 1995 for&#13;
consultation on the ESR;&#13;
(d)   the final draft version of the ESR was discussed with the Secretary and&#13;
officials of the Ministry of Environment and Forests (MOEF) to obtain GOI&#13;
concurrence. IL&amp;FS also consulted with NGOs;&#13;
(e)   the ESR was formally approved by IL&amp;FS's Board of Directors on November&#13;
27, 1995; and&#13;
(f)   responding to the advice given by Bank management to field-test the&#13;
application of the ESR approach, IL&amp;FS also prepared the detailed&#13;
environment and social assessment report for the proposed Delhi-NOIDA&#13;
Link Bridge subproject. The report built on the previous initial environmental&#13;
examination of the project and was prepared by National Environmental&#13;
Engineering Research Institute (NEERI) and AIMS Research.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-77-                               Page2 of 15&#13;
The ESR, as a document, is in 3 volumes: Volume I -- Executive Summary, Volume&#13;
II -- ESR, and Volume III -- Attachments. It: (a) states the company's environment and&#13;
social goals; (b) provides the contextual setting for the environmental and social assessment&#13;
process. (c) identifies the major issues in the priority sectors; (d) details the environmental&#13;
assessment and social assessment (EA/SA) process (operational procedures) that IL&amp;FS will&#13;
follow when appraising subprojects; (e) outlines methods to moderate risks and liabilities due&#13;
to environmental and social factors; (f) specifies the organizational arrangements in IL&amp;FS to&#13;
manage the environmental and social assessment process; and (g) spells out the staff&#13;
development plan. Relevant regulations, guidelines, checklists and protocols are provided as&#13;
an attachment to the report.&#13;
The EA/SA process framework is intrinsically linked to the company's project cycle&#13;
and involves the following iterative stages: (a) screening; (b) scoping, including public&#13;
consultation; (c) drafting terms of reference for the preparation of the EA/SA report; (d)&#13;
preparation of EA/SA study by subproject proponents; (e) EA/SA review, institutional&#13;
interface and public consultation; (f) translation into legal instruments of agreements on the&#13;
Environrnental Management Plan (EMP), the Resettlement Action Plan (RAP) and the&#13;
Indigenous Peoples Development Plan (IPDP); (g) implementation monitoring; and (h)&#13;
annual environmental and social audit. The latter is a novel feature, and for the first time, it&#13;
is being employed by a financial institution in India.&#13;
The executive summary of the ESR is provided below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-78-               Page 3 of 15&#13;
INFRASTRUCTURE LEASING &amp; FINANCIAL SERVICES LIMITED&#13;
ENVIRONMENTAL AND SOCIAL REPORT&#13;
VOLUME I:  EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
November 1995&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-79-                              Page 4 of 15&#13;
LIST OF ACRONYMS&#13;
ADR    -       Alternative Dispute Resolution&#13;
BOO    -       Build Own Operate&#13;
BOOT   -       Build Own Operate Transfer&#13;
BOT    -       Build Operate Transfer&#13;
CBO    -       Community Based Organisation&#13;
CC      -      Corporate Consultant&#13;
CFD    -       Contractual Framework Documentation&#13;
COD    -       Committee of Directors&#13;
CPCB   -       Central Pollution Control Board&#13;
CRZ    -       Coastal Regulation Zone&#13;
DFIBR  -       Detailed Feasibility and Investment Banking Report&#13;
DPI    -       Detailed Process of Implementation&#13;
EA      -      Environmental Assessment&#13;
EAP    -       Environmental Assessment Process&#13;
EAR    -       Environmental Assessment Report&#13;
ED      -      Executive Director&#13;
EIA     -      Environmental Impact Assessment&#13;
EMP    -       Environmental Mitigation Plan&#13;
ESMG   -       Environmental and Social Management Group&#13;
ESR    -       Environmental and Social Report&#13;
FRI    -       Forest Research Institute&#13;
GOI    -       Government of India&#13;
IL&amp;FS  -       Infrastructure Leasing and Financial Services Limited&#13;
IPDP    -      Indigenous People Development Plan&#13;
ISR     -      Initial Screening Report&#13;
ITRC    -      Indian Toxicology Research Centre&#13;
LA      -      Local Authority&#13;
LAA    -       Land Acquisition Assessment&#13;
MA      -      Multilateral Agencies&#13;
MoEF   -       Ministry of Environment and Forests&#13;
MOU    -       Memorandum of Understanding&#13;
NEERI -        National Environment Engineering Research Institute&#13;
NGO    -       Non Governmental Organisation&#13;
O&amp;M    -       Operation &amp; Maintenance&#13;
OD      -      Operational Directive&#13;
PAP    -       Project Affected Person&#13;
PRA    -       Participatory Rural Appraisal&#13;
R&amp;R    -       Resettlement and Rehabilitation&#13;
RAP    -       Rehabilitation Action Plan&#13;
REP    -       Risk Evaluation Process&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-80-                                  Page 5 of 15&#13;
RMG    -       Risk Management Group&#13;
RMP    -       Risk Mitigation Plan&#13;
SA      -      Social Assessment&#13;
SAMP   -       Social Assessment and Management Plan&#13;
SAP     -      Social Assessment Process&#13;
SAR     -      Social Assessment Report&#13;
SDP     -      Staff Development Plan&#13;
SIA     -      Social Impact Assessment&#13;
SPCB    -      State Pollution Control Board&#13;
SPV     -      Special Purpose Vehicle&#13;
TOR    -       Terms of Reference&#13;
UMTS  -        Urban Mass Transit System&#13;
WB      -      World Bank&#13;
Wll     -      Wildlife Institute of India&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-81-                              Page 6 of 15&#13;
EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
PURPOSE&#13;
(1)   Infrastructure Leasing and Financial Services Limited (IL&amp;FS) is pioneering and&#13;
promoting innovative approaches to infrastructure development in India. It is developing&#13;
a pipeline of commercially viable projects which includes urban by-passes, mass transit&#13;
systems, water and sanitation infrastructure and integrated area development.  The&#13;
projects are to be developed as Build-Own-Operate-Transfer (BOOT) or Build-Operate-&#13;
Transfer (BOT) schemes&#13;
(2)    The environmental and social framework for IL&amp;FS has been designed to be consistent,&#13;
inter alia, with the BOOT/BOT framework. The ESR outlines the various policies,&#13;
procedures and assessments that will enable IL&amp;FS as a financial intermediary to ensure&#13;
that a project is developed in consonance with the ESR and is adequately protected from&#13;
attendant risks&#13;
(3)    Thus, the purpose and aim of the ESR is to provide the Institution an overall framework&#13;
to guide it in the identification, assessment and management of environmental and social&#13;
concerns at the organisational and at the project level&#13;
(4)    The ESR has been prepared by IL&amp;FS with the assistance of Consultants - Development&#13;
Alternatives - specialised in the field of environment and social issues. The process of&#13;
preparing this report has included desk research on the legal and institutional framework,&#13;
analysis of priority issues in the infrastructure sector, consistency checks with&#13;
operational directives of the World Bank and other multilateral agencies. There have&#13;
also been a series of discussions within and outside IL&amp;FS for the preparation of the&#13;
Report&#13;
(5)   The ESR has been formally approved by the Board of Directors of IL&amp;FS&#13;
ENVIRONMENTAL AND SOCIAL STATEMENT OF IL&amp;FS&#13;
(6)   The Environmental and Social Statement of the Institution commits each project to three&#13;
cardinal principles:&#13;
(a)    Enhance the quality of life and environment in and around the project location&#13;
(b)    Prevent adverse environmental and social situations&#13;
(c)    Mitigate possible adverse environmental and social impacts&#13;
While enhancement is the first priority, incorporation of prevention and mitigation&#13;
measures will ensure minimal adverse impacts&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.1&#13;
-82-                            Page 7 of 15&#13;
(7)   IL&amp;FS is internalising this Environmental and Social statement into its business&#13;
operations through detailed operational procedures including systems for continuous&#13;
performance evaluation and self regulation. The highlights of an Annual Environmental&#13;
and Social Audit will be made public alongwith the Annual Balance Sheet&#13;
LEGAL AND INSTITUTIONAL SETTING&#13;
(8)   The legal and constitutional setting provides the context in which the environment and&#13;
social statement and operational procedures of IL&amp;FS is framed. Fundamental national&#13;
commitments are enshrined in the Constitution of India, while the Acts, Notifications,&#13;
policies, rules and other documents issued by Central and State Governments provide&#13;
operational details. India also has obligations on environmental and social issues&#13;
through its participation in international conventions and treaties&#13;
(9)   A number of specific regulatory instruments for environmental protection have been&#13;
developed by both Central and State Governments. Many of these have a bearing on&#13;
IL&amp;FS infrastructure projects. (India's contributions to and learnings from negotiations&#13;
for international treaties have also helped immensely in sharpening the focus of the&#13;
regulatory instruments currently in place). Most States and Central Government have&#13;
either Ministries or departments of environment and forests as agencies dealing with&#13;
environmental issues&#13;
(10)  With its basic commitment to address environmental concerns in infrastructure projects,&#13;
IL&amp;FS has attempted to capture the essence of the regulatory framework in India and the&#13;
experience of the World Bank as embodied in its Operational Directives. It has&#13;
incorporated the strengths of both the World Bank operational directives and the Indian&#13;
legislation and policies in the ESR&#13;
(I1)  Compared to the more specific legal instruments on environmental issues, the&#13;
legislations, notifications, rules and policies on social issues are relatively less definitive.&#13;
While Constitutional provisions provide several guarantees to project-affected persons,&#13;
international agreements on social and cultural issues have only limited application&#13;
(12)  Given its concern for social issues associated with infrastructure projects, IL&amp;FS has&#13;
developed its policy and operational procedures based on the legal and policy framework&#13;
in India and the operational directives of the World Bank&#13;
(13)  In order to provide a benchmark for the discussion of possible entitlements in the R&amp;R&#13;
process, the ESR provides a menu of typical impacts that project affected households and&#13;
individuals may experience. Against these impacts, the corresponding beneficiary&#13;
designation and the possible entitlement options have been developed based on the&#13;
operational directives of the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-83-                                Page 8 of 15&#13;
(14)   The actual combination of types of impact, beneficiaries and entitlement options will&#13;
depend on the specificities of a sub-project itself. It would, thus, be up to the Special&#13;
Purpose Vehicle (SPV) and its sub-project consultants team to develop a coherent&#13;
rehabilitation action plan. IL&amp;FS will remain responsible for appraising it within the&#13;
proposed operational framework&#13;
MAJOR ISSUES IN PRIORITY SECTORS&#13;
(15)   While infrastructure projects deliver major benefits, the construction and operation of&#13;
each type of project involves certain activities that could have adverse environmental and&#13;
social impacts&#13;
(16)   Presently, IL&amp;FS focus in the infrastructure sector includes the following:&#13;
(a)    Integrated Area Development&#13;
(b)    Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
(c)    Transportation&#13;
(d)    Power&#13;
(17)   Specific environmental impacts during the construction and operation phase of the&#13;
project will be identified, assessed and a suitable mitigation plan evolved. The exercise&#13;
begins with the identification of issues in the alternative project sites. The degree and&#13;
magnitude of these issues are captured in the subsequent investigations (EA and SA&#13;
process). Resolution of these issues are incorporated in the project design&#13;
(18)  Infrastructure projects are also often confronted with a range of socio-economic issues.&#13;
The socio-economic impacts will vary considerably depending on the specifics of the&#13;
project location and the resettlement area. IL&amp;FS is committed to:&#13;
(a)    Fulfilling the legitimate needs of the project affected groups, and&#13;
(b)    Adopting a transparent process acceptable to the concerned stakeholders.&#13;
(19)   The salient social issues related to infrastructure projects include:&#13;
(a)   Involuntary Resettlement&#13;
(b)    Protection of Marginalised and Vulnerable Groups&#13;
(c)    Public Consultation and Consensus Building&#13;
(20)   While IL&amp;FS will aim to avoid involuntary resettlement, it may become inevitable in&#13;
some of the projects. In such cases, the attempt will be to atleast restore, if not improve,&#13;
the standard of living of the affected persons. IL&amp;FS will ensure proper valuation of&#13;
land and assets, on entitlement policy for each category of impact, minimisation of&#13;
cumbersome procedures and a well developed compensation package&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-84-                                       Page 9 of 15&#13;
(21)   In  some  of the  infrastructure  projects, there  may  be  specific  issues  relating  to&#13;
marginalised and vulnerable groups like the economically and socially disadvantaged;&#13;
the elderly; women and children; the physically handicapped; and indigenous people. As&#13;
a general principle Il,&amp;FS will aim at enhancing their opportunities&#13;
(22)    In each project, IL&amp;FS will attempt to establish an effective local mechanism  sensitive&#13;
to socio-economic issues and capable of co-ordinating implementation of. various project&#13;
components including RAP and IPDP.  Non-Government Organisations (NGOs) and&#13;
Community Based Organisations (CBOs) will play a critical role in this process which&#13;
will also redress the grievances of the affected groups&#13;
OPERATIONAL PROCEDURES&#13;
(23)   The environmental and social assessment process will dovetail with the IL&amp;FS project&#13;
cycle. It is envisaged that at each stage of the project cycle, environmental and social&#13;
assessment issues would be addressed concurrently. Based on the foregoing principles, a&#13;
summary of the IL&amp;FS project cycle is provided in the table below&#13;
IL&amp;FS PROJECT CYCLE SUMMARY&#13;
MILESTONE                   I RESPONSIBILITY             ::PRODUCT&#13;
Screening                    IL&amp;FS/SPV/Sponsor/            Initial Screening Report&#13;
Government&#13;
Scoping                      IL&amp;FS/SPV/Sponsor/               Memorandum of Understanding&#13;
Government                       (MoU)&#13;
Finalisation  of Channels of&#13;
Consultation&#13;
Finalisation   of  Terms  of    L&amp;FS,SPVSponsor/           Terms of Reference (ToR) for &#13;
Reference    for     project  Consultant                   appointment of consultants&#13;
preparation studies&#13;
AppointIent of consultants   IL&amp;FS SPV/Sponsor             Cons-utants Ap oi ned&#13;
Project Preparation          SPV/Sponsor/Consultant        Draft final documentation prepared&#13;
.acording to agreed formats&#13;
.................................................................................................. ........................................................................&#13;
Initial Project Evaluation   IL&amp;FS/ Consultants,           -   Initial   Project  Evaluation&#13;
' SPV/Sponsor                      Report&#13;
Agreements   on    project&#13;
documentation&#13;
Selection of Operator        IL&amp;FS;SPV/Consultant              Award of Recommendation&#13;
Project Financial Close      IL&amp;FS;SPV/Sponsor,                Final   Project   Evaiuation&#13;
Government, Operator,            Report&#13;
Merchant Banker                  Signing of Agreements&#13;
Finalisation of project finance&#13;
consortium&#13;
Project Monitoring and Audit   IL&amp;FS/SPV/Lenders               Compliance Report&#13;
Annual Audit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-85-                                                      Page 10 of 15&#13;
(24) Based on the IL&amp;FS project cycle, IL&amp;FS has developed an Environmental &amp; Social&#13;
Assessment process. IL&amp;FS is committed to ensure that each project will rigorously&#13;
follow a detailed Environment and Social Assessment Process as summarised in the table&#13;
below:&#13;
EA/SA PROCESS SUMMARY&#13;
MILESTONE                                RESPONSIBILITY    PRODUCT&#13;
Environmental/Social Screening  IIL&amp;FS,  SPV/Sponsor.  IL&amp;FS    -    Environmental  screening  and&#13;
with SPV/Sponsor                              social  screening  as  part  of&#13;
Project    Initial       Screening&#13;
Report&#13;
Decision    to    proceed    or&#13;
otherwise&#13;
i ..................................... ............. ................................................................... ..........................................................................&#13;
Environmental/Social Scoping    I SPV/Sponsor/LA                                ' Scope and coverage of EAR/SAR&#13;
li .............................................................. ....................................I.............................. .............................I...........................................&#13;
Finalisation    of   Terms    of   IL&amp;FS,SPV/LA/Consultant                        Terms  of  Reference   (ToR)  for&#13;
Reference   for  EA    and   SA                                                   appointment of consultant&#13;
studies&#13;
A ppointment of consultants              IL&amp;FS /SPV/Sponsor                       Consultants Appointed&#13;
l EA/.SAStudy                            SPV/Sponsor                 through    Draft EAR/SAR including:&#13;
Consultant                               -    EMP&#13;
-  RAP&#13;
IPDP&#13;
-    Implementing Monitoring Plan&#13;
-    Institutional       Responsibility&#13;
Framework&#13;
Risk Allocation Framework&#13;
Review of EAR/SAR               .        IL&amp;FS/SPV/Sponsor                             Clearance    by    Government&#13;
agencies&#13;
Concurrence by MA&#13;
Agreement  on   EAR/SAR&#13;
actions&#13;
.....................         .......... ..............................................................   ........................................................................ &#13;
Translation of Agreements into   IL&amp;FS/SPV/Operator/                                    Concession Agreement&#13;
Legal Instruments                        Contractor, SPV &amp; Government                   Shareholders Agreement&#13;
Construction Agreement&#13;
O&amp;M Agreement&#13;
Lenders Agreement&#13;
..... .......................................................................................................................;... .........................................................................&#13;
Project Monitoring                       IL&amp;FS/SPV/Lenders                      I Periodic Monitoring Reports&#13;
Annual    Environmental    and I Corporate Consultant                             Environment and social audit report&#13;
Social Audit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-86-                            Page 11 of 15&#13;
(25)  The Environmental Assessment Process (EAP) will identify likely environmental&#13;
impacts and evolve relevant mitigation measures. While the project will attempt to&#13;
enhance environmental quality, it will at a minimum prevent or set in place appropriate&#13;
mitigation measures. The EAP will be undertaken by a multi-disciplinary team of&#13;
consultants with support from NGOs, CBOs, Government Agencies and due processes of&#13;
consultation&#13;
(26)  IL&amp;FS is committed to ensure that the legitimate needs of the project affected groups are&#13;
fulfilled through a transparent process acceptable to the concerned stakeholders. The&#13;
Social Assessment Process (SAP) adopted will restore the quality of life, if not improve&#13;
it, when compared to the situation before the infrastructure project. The SAP will be&#13;
undertaken by a composite team drawn from among specialists like anthropologists,&#13;
sociologists, community development experts; and others from non-governmental&#13;
organizations (NGOs), community based organizations (CBOs), project affected persons&#13;
and appropriate public institutions&#13;
ENVIRONMENTAL AND SOCIAL RISK MANAGEMENT&#13;
(27)  IL&amp;FS shall establish structures that will serve to minimise many of the normal&#13;
infrastructure project risks. Nevertheless, IL&amp;FS will remain exposed to several other&#13;
risks, especially relating to environmental and social concerns&#13;
(28)  Major environment and social problems could adversely affect project operations,&#13;
earnings  and hence loan servicing obligations.  Consequently IL&amp;FS will place&#13;
significant emphasis on a rigorous Environment and Social Risk Assessment, Analysis&#13;
and Management at the project level&#13;
(29)  In order to effectively manage the environmental and social risks attendant to&#13;
infrastructure projects, IL&amp;FS will incorporate a risk evaluation process at each stage of&#13;
the EA/SA process&#13;
(30)  In essence, the risk evaluation process shall enable the Institution to develop appropriate&#13;
mechanisms to manage and monitor risks on an on-going basis. Within IL&amp;FS the risk&#13;
evaluation process shall be implemented by the project team and the Risk Management&#13;
Group&#13;
(31)  The risk evaluation process shall thus comprise of the following sequence of steps&#13;
* Risk Identification&#13;
* Risk Assessment&#13;
* Allocation of Risks&#13;
* Risk Management including mitigation measures&#13;
(32)  After the appropriate risk management systems are set in place, IL&amp;FS will ensure the&#13;
appropriate allocation of risk and the associated liabilities, through a contractual&#13;
framework and, if feasible, insurance coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-87-                               Page 12 of 15&#13;
(33)   Each project will have a responsibility framework outlining the extent of risk and&#13;
associated liability to be shared between each of the project stakeholders.  The&#13;
instruments through which this will be implemented, include:&#13;
(a)    Risks/responsibilities of Government      Concession Agreement&#13;
(b)    Risks/responsibilities of SPV             Concession Agreement,&#13;
Lenders' Agreement, O&amp;M&#13;
Agreement, Construction&#13;
Agreement&#13;
(c)    Risks/responsibilities to be borne by     Shareholders' agreement&#13;
Shareholders&#13;
(d)    Risks/responsibilities to be borne        O&amp;M Contract&#13;
by Operator&#13;
(e)    Risks/responsibilities to be borne        Construction Agreement&#13;
by Contractor&#13;
ORGANISATIONAL SUPPORT&#13;
(34)  IL&amp;FS shall establish an organisational structure with the requisite expertise to facilitate&#13;
compliance with the ESR. It will inculcate and develop the requisite skills within the&#13;
Institution, and access complementary and specialised skills through the appointment of&#13;
External Consultants on an assignment basis&#13;
(35)   The table below  summarises the responsibility for each task within IL&amp;FS. This&#13;
allocation framework assigns departmental responsibilities with a view to integrating the&#13;
environment and social assessment process with the overall project cycle. The process&#13;
flow in terms of preparation, review and authorisation is geared towards ensuring that&#13;
sufficient independent cross-checks exist within the system to ensure effective process&#13;
and management control&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-88-                                      Page 13 of 15&#13;
SUMMARY OF IL&amp;FS DEPARTMENTAL RESPONSIBILITY ALLOCATION&#13;
MILESTONE               | PREPARATION             |_REVIEW              APPROVAL&#13;
Screening                Project team               Executive Director    Committec   Of&#13;
ESMG *                     (Infrastructure)   Directors&#13;
Corporate Consultant **&#13;
Finalisation    of   TOR  Consultants               ESMG                Executive&#13;
consistency check                                                       Director&#13;
(Infrastructure)&#13;
Appointment of consultant                           Project team        ESMG&#13;
Review of EAISA          Project team               Credit               Committee    of&#13;
ESMG                      Legal               Directors&#13;
Corporate Consultant      RMG&#13;
ED (Infrastructure)&#13;
Translation ol agreements  Legal                    ESMG                ED&#13;
into Legal Instruments                              Project Team        (Infrastructure)&#13;
RMG&#13;
Credit&#13;
Monitoring               Project team               ESMG                Committee    of&#13;
Corporate Consultants                         Directors&#13;
Environmental and Social  Independent Consultants   Committee       of  Board         of&#13;
Audit                                               Directors           Directors&#13;
*       ESMG                             Environmental and Social Management Group&#13;
**      Corporate Consultant             IL&amp;FS Corporate Consultant for&#13;
Environmental and Social Issues&#13;
(36)   At the Corporate level, IL&amp;FS will&#13;
(a)     Create an Environmental and Social Management Group (ESMG) as a part of the&#13;
Projects Department&#13;
(b)     Appoint a Corporate Consultant for Environmental and Social issues&#13;
(c)     Clearly  delineate  functions/across concerned  Departments and  provide  the&#13;
necessary training required to ensure that the requisite levels of skills and&#13;
awareness are developed within each of the concerned Departments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-89-                                     Page 14 of 15&#13;
\ (37)  At the project level, IL&amp;FS will ensure that the SPV/Project Sponsor appoints Project&#13;
Consultants to undertake assignments on environmental and social issues in conformity&#13;
with its business practices. Project Consultants for social issues will be selected from&#13;
among non-governmental organisations (NGOs), community based organisations (CBOs)&#13;
or public agencies&#13;
STAFF DEVELOPMENT PLAN&#13;
(38)   In order to position the organisation to achieve the objectives as set in the ESR, IL&amp;FS&#13;
will implement a staff development plan. The Staff Development Plan (SDP) is oriented&#13;
to facilitate the implementation of the environmental and social assessment process as an&#13;
intrinsic part of the project cycle&#13;
(39)   A  number of Departments in IL&amp;FS would be routinely involved in the preparation,&#13;
review and approval of the various outputs emanating from the environmental and social&#13;
assessment process. At the present juncture, IL&amp;FS staff have not been formally trained&#13;
with respect to environmental and social issues. Thus, all concerned staff will initially&#13;
undergo an orientation  programme on the ESR and its application to project specific&#13;
environmental and social issues. Subsequently, each Department will undergo training&#13;
specific to their responsibilities in the EA/SA process&#13;
(40)   Training modules will include a combination of workshops, seminars, site visits and&#13;
interactions with project authorities. The responsibility for implementing the SDP in&#13;
IL&amp;FS will vest withi the Personnel Department&#13;
IL&amp;FS - MULTILATERAL AGENCY INTERFACE&#13;
(41)   As a financial intermediary, IL&amp;FS will access funding from  a variety of lenders&#13;
including multilateral agencies such as the World Bank&#13;
(42)   In  order to  ensure  that the projects are  in  conformity  with  World  Bank's OD&#13;
requirements and business practices, IL&amp;FS shall submit the following documents for&#13;
the review of the Bank. The table below provides the institutional interface matrix&#13;
INTERFACE MATRIX&#13;
EA/SA MILESTONE                   OUTPUT TO BE SUBMITTED TO THE&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Screening                                  Initial screening report&#13;
Finalisation of terms ofl reference tor EA and SA  Terms of reference&#13;
studies&#13;
.4 ....... .... .... .... ... ........ ..... . ............. .......... .... ............ ....... ....   ........................................................... ................................................&#13;
Reviexw of EA and SA studies and mitigation  Draft EAR and SAR according to agreed formats&#13;
plans&#13;
Translation of agreements into instruments  e nders Agreement alongwith other Agreements&#13;
onitoring                                   Compliance report&#13;
Environmental and Social Audit           . Audit compliance report&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 3.11&#13;
-90-                            Page 15 of 15&#13;
43)   It is envisaged that World Bank concurrence to the output generated at each milestone&#13;
will be obtained prior to progressing to the next stage. However, when the capacity of&#13;
IL&amp;FS is in place, it is expected that World Bank and other multilateral agency&#13;
concurrence will be required only for the EAR and SAP Summary Reports and the&#13;
agreements, prior to approving finances for sub-projects. This capacity building is&#13;
expected to take two years&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IMAGING&#13;
Report No:       15364 IN&#13;
Type: SAR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="696689">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/03/696689/india-private-infrastructure-finance-ilfs-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/03/696689/india-private-infrastructure-finance-ilfs-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1996/03/696689/india-private-infrastructure-finance-ilfs-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/03/07/000009265_3961019182132/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/03/07/000009265_3961019182132/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>3992</loan_no>
        <credit_no>2838</credit_no>
        <datestored>2001-04-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1996-03-07T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            India - Private Infrastructure Finance
            (IL&amp;FS) Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objectives of the Private
            Infrastructure Finance Project are to: 1) develop prototype
            contractual arrangements for private investment in the
            Infrastructure Leasing and Financial Services Limited's
            (IL&amp;FS) areas of involvement, thereby facilitating entry
            of the private sector on a much larger scale in areas
            heretore dominated by the public sector; 2) build up
            India's capacity to attract private investment in
            infrastructure, pilot-test institutional and contractual
            arrangements in a variety of subprojects under various
            administrative and political conditions, and help establish
            a track record as a prerequisite for large scale private
            investment in the sector; 3) meet the pressing needs of
            commercial infrastructure project entities for long-term
            rupee financing; 4) foster efficiency in the delivery and
            use of selected infrastructure services; 5) encourage the
            establishment of more efficient practices in the
            construction and operation of infrastructure project; and 6)
            assist in alleviating the severe financial and institutional
            constraints to the expansion of infrastructure in India. The
            project consists of three interrelated components: 1) an
            investment component in the form of a line of credit to
            IL&amp;FS; 2) a subproject preparation component, which will
            cover specialized consultancy services; and 3) a training
            and technical assistance component, which will include: (a)
            IL&amp;FS's staff development for its staff; and (b)
            specific studies that IL&amp;FS is undertaking to facilitate
            the evaluation and implementation of commercial
            infrastructure projects.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            India - Private Infrastructure Finance
            (IL&amp;FS) Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>India - Private Infrastructure
            Finance (IL&amp;FS) Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1996/03/696689/india-private-infrastructure-finance-ilfs-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>IN-Ilfs-Private Infrastructure Finance -- P039935</projn>
        <docty>Staff Appraisal Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Municipal Financial Management,Housing Finance,Public Sector Economics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3961019182132</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>General water, sanitation and flood
            protection sector,Central government administration,Power,Roads and highways,Ports, waterways and shipping</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>World Development Sources, WDS 1996</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Finance</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Consulting services; Evaluation studies;
            Investment; Line of credit; Project preparation; Staff
            training; Technical assistance
            accounting,accounting standards,accounting
            systems,ADB,affiliates,asset
            management,auditing,autonomy,balance sheet,balance
            sheets,Banking Regulation,banking services,capital
            adequacy,capital assets,capital goods,capital markets,cash
            flow,cash flow statements,commercial banks,contractual
            savings institutions,Credit Analysis,credit control,credit
            policies,credit
            rating,debentures,debt,depreciation,disbursement,Economic
            analysis,economic growth,economic
            policies,Electricity,Equity Capital,equity
            investments,expenditures,financial institutions,financial
            intermediaries,financial markets,financial
            performance,financial ratios,financial reporting,Financial
            Services,financial statements,foreign exchange,foreign
            exchange risk management,Gross domestic product,health
            services,Housing,housing finance,income
            statements,insurance,interest income,interest
            rates,investment banking,leased assets,Leasing,legal
            framework,loan financing,local governments,macroeconomic
            stability,mandates,maturities,merchant banking,Municipal
            Development,municipal infrastructure,natural resources,net
            profit,net worth,new entrants,policy decisions,population
            growth,ports,Present Value,private housing,private
            sector,private sector participation,profitability,provision
            of infrastructure,prudential regulations,public
            enterprises,public offering,Public sector,Public
            works,rating agencies,regulatory framework,Reserve Bank of
            India,Risk management,risk
            mitigation,roads,savings,Securities,subsidiaries,subsidiary,syndication,tax,taxation,technical
            assistance,telecommunications,Transport,treasury,treasury
            operations,Urban Development,urban
            infrastructure,urbanization,water supply
        </keywd>
        <owner>Energy (SASDE)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>15364</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental and Social Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Environmental and Social Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highway Tolls</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Pricing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road User Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Toll Roads</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental and Social Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Tolls</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>