<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>/ G   5L0&#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank                                                                         January 1996&#13;
Note No.66   Finding Real Owners-Lessons from&#13;
Estonia's Privatization Program&#13;
Jobn Nellis      The Estonian government has quickly privatized   Progress&#13;
more than 90 percent of its industrial and manu-&#13;
facturing enterprises. The Estonian privatiza-   By November 1995, the Estonian privatization&#13;
tion agency, following the approach devised   agency had concluded more than 400 sales con-&#13;
by the German Treuhandanstalt (former staff  tracts for medium-size and large industrial firms&#13;
of which advise the agency), batches thirty to   or parts of firms.2 These sales generated about&#13;
forty firms and advertises them for sale. The   US$200 million in direct receipts-though much&#13;
prime goal is to find 'real owners" capable of   of this is being paid in installments. Purchas-&#13;
running a durable, productive firm. Purchase   ers contracted to invest an additional US$160&#13;
offers are thus judged not only on price, but   million in the divested firms and assumed at&#13;
also on the quality of business plans submit-  least US$130 million in liabilities. The privati-&#13;
ted, particularly with regard to expected invest-  zation agency estimates that the sales created&#13;
ment and employment creation. Winning   or maintained some 49,400 jobs-a significant&#13;
bidders negotiate contracts formalizing their  number in a country of 1.5 million people.&#13;
commitment. No special concessions are made   Besides infrastructure firms and a couple of&#13;
to workers and managers in the affected firms,  particularly difficult industrial cases (oil shale&#13;
but they can and often do submit a bid and a   and alcohol firms), there is not much left to&#13;
business plan-and they have won the com-   privatize.&#13;
petition in some thirty cases.&#13;
Small-scale privatizations and "leftovers"&#13;
In seventeen sales (with more in progress), the&#13;
Estonians have combined strategic investment   More than 90 percent (over 1,100) of the small&#13;
with voucher exchanges, a mix beyond the   business units and assets in Estonia have been&#13;
reach of most other transition economies. And   divested through auctions, raising some US$23&#13;
now Estonia is addressing, earlier and more   million. This process is regarded as substantially&#13;
comprehensively than most other formerly com-   complete, since the remaining items appear to&#13;
munist countries, the complicated issue of in-   be of little interest to investors. "Leftovers"-&#13;
volving the private sector in the provision of   unsold assets or parts of businesses resulting&#13;
infrastructure services.                  from the tender method of sale-are constantly&#13;
being created. Many have been divested, but&#13;
So far, allegations of corruption and insider deal-  several with severe financial or environmental&#13;
ing-though not absent-have been fewer than   problems are not moving and may never be sold.&#13;
in most other transition economies. And al-  Experience has not yet yielded a hard and fast&#13;
though a fair number of sales have been to  rule on how long to try to sell businesses be-&#13;
foreign buyers, there has been little political  fore giving up and liquidating them. Some have&#13;
protest.' Many observers thought that a transi-  been sold even after a long stay in the leftover&#13;
tion economy could not handle a privatization   category. A good solution would be for the&#13;
strategy as politically risky and as administra-   privatization agency to set a "normal" period of&#13;
tively intense. But the Estonians have proved   sale-say, one year from tendering-after which&#13;
them wrong.                                liquidation would start.&#13;
Private Sector Development Department Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Finding Real Owners-Lessons from Estonia's Privatization Program&#13;
Contract control                              stake to a strategic investor and offered varying&#13;
minority stakes for vouchers-using a "Russian&#13;
With 400 concluded contracts, the privatization   auction" pricing mechanism  that roughly&#13;
agency's postsale supervision process is being   matches supply to demand. Fifteen similar ex-&#13;
formalized. The agency reports no problems with   changes are under way. This combined method&#13;
investment and employment promises but does   has several benefits. First and foremost, the&#13;
have problems with installment payments of the   scheme mixes the economic and financial gains&#13;
purchase price.3 In December 1995, the agency   of obtaining a core investor with the political&#13;
said that seventy buyers were having difficulty in   advantages of giving the public a chance to ac-&#13;
meeting their payment schedule. Only once has   quire shares and use its voucher accounts. A&#13;
the agency repossessed a firm when the buyer   scheme that allows people to trade vouchers&#13;
failed to make payments. In effect, the govern-   for shares (even if they quickly sell them) gen-&#13;
ment is unwilling to renationalize on a large scale   erates political support for the privatization pro-&#13;
or declare the new private firms bankrupt. While   gram by counteracting the claim that divestiture&#13;
still insisting on the need for payment of the ob-   benefits only the foreigner, the local elite, or&#13;
ligation, controllers often give the new owners   the politically well connected. This is important&#13;
more time. Given these generous enforcement   in Estonia, where claims that the privatization&#13;
and supervision practices, would it have been   process was nontransparent won votes in the&#13;
preferable to maximize the purchase price and    1995 electoral campaign. Second, the trading of&#13;
omit nonprice criteria? Agency officials say no;   vouchers and shares and the activities of the&#13;
they view investment and employment commit-  investment funds promote the development of&#13;
ments as legitimate, given the short time horizon   capital markets.&#13;
of so many investors in the region.&#13;
But the method also has costs. Some critics say&#13;
Public offerings and use of vouchers          that since August 1994, when it was first decided&#13;
to hold back a minority of shares in divested&#13;
Two large and fifteen small "'combination" sales   firms for later exchange for vouchers, the pace&#13;
have been concluded. These sales combine par-   of contract conclusion has slowed. This could&#13;
tial purchase by a strategic core investor with   have occurred naturally, as sales reduced the sup-&#13;
divestiture of a minority of equity through a pub-   ply of better opportunities. But critics claim that&#13;
lic offering limited to Estonians, who exchange   investors were anxious about who the future mi-&#13;
vouchers for shares. In the two large sales, in-   nority owners would be, what their rights would&#13;
vestment funds reportedly contracted with indi-   be, how the public offerings would be conducted,&#13;
viduals to use their personal vouchers to buy   and how the government would vote its residual&#13;
shares and then to sell their shares to the funds.   shares in the interim. They say that prices paid&#13;
Share prices were fLxed, and both offerings were   by core investors have fallen by a greater per-&#13;
oversubscribed. Concerns have been expressed    centage than prices for shares reserved for the&#13;
that the investment funds, acting in concert,   public offerings, that the uncertainty has caused&#13;
gained a significant ownership stake cheaply,   promised investment to decline, and that the core&#13;
and concentrated ownership excessively, defeat-  investors are striking deals with investment funds&#13;
ing the goal of promoting diffused shareholding.   to buy up shares for transfer, at a discounted&#13;
But nobody was forced to sell his or her shares.   price, to the core investors. The solution, say the&#13;
And from the viewpoint of corporate gover-   critics, would be to limit voucher use to buying&#13;
nance, concentrated ownership by investment   housing and land-the use originally intended&#13;
funds is superior to widely diffused ownership   for the vouchers-and allow the privatization&#13;
by small shareholders.                        agency to focus on its proven strategy of selling&#13;
whole companies to investors. But these views&#13;
In the fifteen small combination sales now con-   underestimate the political importance of the&#13;
cluded, the privatization agency sold a majority   voucher program. Privatization is everywhere and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
always intensely political. Estonia is but one of   raise the vouchers' depressed trading value, but&#13;
many transition economies whose electorate has   cost the government considerably in forgone&#13;
replaced radical reformers with governments ad-   revenue: as much as US$10 million to US$20&#13;
vocating more caution and prudence in reform,   million in voucher value could be absorbed.)&#13;
particularly in privatization. For all their complex-&#13;
ity, schemes in which vouchers are exchanged   Infrastructure and land&#13;
for shares can provide the level of public sup-&#13;
port needed to carry out privatization.     Large infrastructure firms remain to be pri-&#13;
vatized, including the port, the airline, the elec-&#13;
Voucher value                               tricity company, and a majority share of the&#13;
telecommunications company. If the combina-&#13;
An unresolved problem in the Estonian privati-  tion method were used in these sales, a large&#13;
zation program is that the face value of the   amount of voucher value could be absorbed&#13;
vouchers outstanding far exceeds the likely value   through even minority offerings. From a more&#13;
of assets being sold. And even more vouchers  technical perspective, some Estonians feel that&#13;
are being created as restitution proceeds slowly.  the need for investment capital in infrastructure&#13;
According to estimates by the Ministry of Fi-  firms is so great that few or no shares should&#13;
nance, about 10.5 billion crowns worth of vouch-   be reserved for free distribution against vouch-&#13;
ers have been issued: 8 billion crowns in   ers, but the politically constituted policymaking&#13;
"national capital" vouchers, allotted to all citi-  board of the privatization agency has not yet&#13;
zens, and 2.5 billion crowns in "compensation"   pronounced on this matter. In addition, ex-&#13;
vouchers, given out for injustices suffered in the   changing vouchers for land might use up a good&#13;
Soviet period. The ministry calculates that the   share of voucher value, but the mechanics of&#13;
public has exchanged about 1.2 billion crowns   land sale and exchange are only now being&#13;
of vouchers for housing (70 percent of which   elaborated, and the intention is to limit voucher&#13;
has been privatized) and another 1.8 billion   use to 50 percent of the price of a parcel of&#13;
crowns of vouchers in privatization transac-  land. Much time will probably pass before land&#13;
tions-of which only about 100 million crowns   sales start to absorb many vouchers.&#13;
of vouchers were used in the two large combi-&#13;
nation public offerings. A rough calculation   Compensation bonds&#13;
yields a face value for the remaining vouchers&#13;
of about 7.1 billion crowns, or US$630 million.   Yet another possible use of vouchers is purchas-&#13;
The minority percentages held back from all the   ing compensation bonds from the Compensa-&#13;
firms remaining to be sold are unlikely to be   tion Fund. This fund also receives half the&#13;
large enough to absorb this outstanding stock   after-expenses proceeds from privatization sales.&#13;
of vouchers (though the problem is eased if the   Ministry of Finance officials said that byjune 1995,&#13;
trading of vouchers allows their price to fall to   270 million crowns (about US$24 million) of&#13;
clear the market).                          vouchers had been invested in these bonds,&#13;
which are paying an attractive rate of interest.&#13;
Citizens may use their vouchers in a variety of   One worry is that the fund has to invest in long-&#13;
ways (including simply selling them to any bid-  term, high-risk restructuring of enterprises, rais-&#13;
der). They may exchange them for shares in  ing questions about the income stream that will&#13;
companies or in investment funds, or they may   be generated to pay interest on the bonds. And,&#13;
use them to buy the housing in which they live,   obviously, the more assets sold for vouchers and&#13;
to purchase land, or to buy bonds from a Com-   the more vouchers accepted for payment of in-&#13;
pensation Fund. And in November 1995, it was   stallments, the less income will be generated for&#13;
announced that vouchers may be used at face   the Compensation Fund to service the bonds.&#13;
value for up to 50 percent of installment pay-   Estonian governments have so far resisted the&#13;
ments for privatized companies. (This should   notion that vouchers might be redeemed at face&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Finding Real Owners-Lessons from Estonia's Privatization Program&#13;
value, so the inflationary potential of vouchers is    eration needed will be privately supplied. But&#13;
slight. But unless the government can speed up         two changes of government have taken place&#13;
the exchange of vouchers for land and shares,    since this program  was announced. Although&#13;
exchanging vouchers for compensation bonds    privatization will clearly continue-a majority&#13;
may be the only recourse for many citizens. It    stake of Estonian Airlines was recently put up&#13;
would be politically embarrassing if the bonds'    for bid (with a closing date in January 1996)-&#13;
market value fell sharply.                             there has been neither a formal acceptance nor&#13;
a modification of the previous policy statement.&#13;
What to do?                                            It would be reassuring if the government re-&#13;
confirmed its principles of infrastructure priva-&#13;
To avoid a discounting of the vouchers from face    tization: creating a market structure to promote&#13;
value, the simple solution is to put more good          competition where possible, imposing credible&#13;
assets up for sale-and inform voucher holders    and efficient regulation where necessary, and&#13;
that they have until a certain date to arrange an    locating core investors to provide governance.&#13;
exchange. But this solution is hard to implement&#13;
while questions persist about which assets are    Conclusion&#13;
up for exchange and under what conditions.&#13;
Moreover, the government is unlikely to set a    In scope and pace, Estonian privatization has&#13;
deadline while vouchers are still being created    been a success. No privatized firm has yet failed,&#13;
by a slow-moving court process. But while the    and the privatization agency reports that most&#13;
voucher issue is complex and has the potential    divested firms are expanding their employment.&#13;
to cause some political problems, it should be    The partially privatized telephone company has&#13;
The Note series is    economically containable, given the range of    improved the quantity and quality of service&#13;
open forum intended to    possibilities for voucher exchange and the "safety    markedly since the involvement of private part-&#13;
encourage dissemina-  valve" of the compensation bonds.                       ners. But these promising results are tempered&#13;
tion of and debate on                                                         by the fact that the seventy privatized firms ex-&#13;
ideas, innovations, and&#13;
best practices for    Infrastructural complexity                              periencing problems with installment purchase&#13;
expanding the private                                                         payments are only being admonished. Although&#13;
sector. The views     Before the 1995 elections, the Estonian govern-    four of five privatized firms are current on their&#13;
published are those of&#13;
the authors and should  ment had endorsed a privatization program  to         obligations, how  long they will stay current if&#13;
not be attributed to the  divest most remaining infrastructure or prob-    there is no penalty for nonpayment or partial&#13;
World Bank or any of its   lem  industrial enterprises by selling the major-    payment is another question. But this problem-&#13;
affiliated organizations.&#13;
Nor do any of the con-    ity of shares to the purchaser able to guarantee    though significant-is not overwhelming.&#13;
clusions represent    investments and effective management. The gov-&#13;
official policy of the  ernment argued, however, that these large com-&#13;
World Bank or of its                                                          I The electorate's dissatisfaction with some aspects of prvatization&#13;
Executive Directors   panies first required reorganization to turn them         contributed to the 1995 defeat of the incumbent coalition. But it&#13;
or the countries they  into joint stock companies, division into mar-           could be argued that it was the few instances of insider trading,&#13;
represent.            ketable                                                   rather than the scope and pace of the program or the involvement&#13;
parts, and the introduction of competi-     of foreigners, that caused the dissatisfaction.&#13;
Comments are welcome.   tive forces or regulation. In almost all areas of    z This section updates an earher Note by the author ("Privatization in&#13;
Please call the FPD   infrastructure, the program recommended found-            Estonia: Major Accomplishments and Remaining Problems," Note&#13;
Note line to leave a  ing "holding-type stock companies" to oversee             19, July 1994).&#13;
message (202-458-11)13 Estonian purchasers can pay 20 percent down and the balance&#13;
or contact Suzanne    reorganization and privatization. Some of what            over a period of three to ten years. Foreign buyers supposedly&#13;
Smith, editor, Room   was proposed was accomplished. (At least one              must pay all at once, but most create a local company to take&#13;
G8105, The World Bank,    action along those lines had predated the pro-        advantage of the installment plan.&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,    gram: a 49 percent share of the telephone com-&#13;
or Internet address   pany was turned over to a private consortium            John Nellis, SeniorlManager, Private Sector&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.   in 1992.) Many business activities in the port of    Development Department (member of the World&#13;
@Printed on recycled  Tallinn are already in private hands. And it is    Development Report team, 1995-96) (email:&#13;
paper.                broadly accepted that any new  electricity gen-    jnellis@worldbank.org)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="696805">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/01/696805/finding-real-owners-lessons-estonias-privatization-program
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1996/01/696805/finding-real-owners-lessons-estonias-privatization-program</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1996/01/696805/finding-real-owners-lessons-estonias-privatization-program</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/01/01/000009265_3980420172834/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1996/01/01/000009265_3980420172834/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1996-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2001-04-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Finding real owners - lessons from
            Estonia's privatization program
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Estonian government has quickly
            privatized more than 90 percent of its industrial and
            manufacturing enterprises. The Estonian privatization agency
            batches 30-40 firms and advertises them for sale. The prime
            goal is to find "real owners" capable of running a
            durable, productive firm. Purchase offers are judged not
            only on price, but also on the quality of business plans
            submitted. In 17 sales, the Estonians have combined
            strategic investment with voucher exchanges. An unresolved
            problem is that the face value of the vouchers outstanding
            far exceeds the likely value of assets being sold. This Note
            concludes that Estonian privatization has been a success in
            scope and pace. No private firm has yet failed, and the
            privatization agency reports that most divested firms are
            expanding their employment. However, these promising results
            are tempered by the fact that the 70 privatized firms
            experiencing problems with installment purchase payments are
            only being admonished. But this problem, though significant,
            is not overwhelming.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Finding real owners - lessons from
            Estonia's privatization program
        </docna>
        <display_title>Finding real owners - lessons
            from Estonia's privatization program</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1996/01/696805/finding-real-owners-lessons-estonias-privatization-program</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Health Service Management and Delivery,Municipal Financial Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Health, Nutrition and Population,Urban Development,Conflict and Development</teratopic>
        <count>Estonia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Nellis, John</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Commonwealth of Independent States!$!80457</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980420172834</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Privatization-DV</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 66</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Health, Nutrition and Population,Urban Development,Conflict and Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Private Sector Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Denationalization; Industrial enterprises;
            Public enterprises; Infrastructure; Small enterprises;
            Capital assets; Compensation bonds; Installment payment;
            Transition economies; Voucher exchange; Public offering
            affiliated
            organizations,assets,auction,auctions,bid,bidders,bonds,capital
            markets,employment,face value,housing,insider
            trading,liquidation,market
            value,offerings,privatization,purchase
            price,reorganization,telecommunications,tendering,transition economies,vouchers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off of VP, FPD - WB (FPDVP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Commonwealth of Independent States</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>16925</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Supply and Markets</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Estonia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>