<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank                                                                            October 1995&#13;
Note No.58   Restructuring Regulation of the Railroad&#13;
Industry&#13;
loannis N.       Throughout the world, the rail industry has been   cost conditions. Because rail infrastructure is of&#13;
Kessides and     one of the most heavily regulated sectors. The   minimal value for other purposes, the fixed costs&#13;
Robert D. Willig    public utility paradigm of government regula-   are largely sunk. These sunk costs of infrastruc-&#13;
tion has failed to handle the central regulatory   ture create significant entry barriers, especially&#13;
problem-the mixture of competitive and mo-   where there are natural monopoly conditions.&#13;
nopoly elements in supply-and is now being&#13;
blamed for the poor financial condition of the   The cost conditions relating to the operation of&#13;
railroads, for the deterioration of rail plant, for   services on this physical network, on the other&#13;
the lack of innovation, and for the mediocre   hand, may be more consistent with active and&#13;
quality of rail services. This Note outlines a set   potential competition. To operate a service, it is&#13;
of principles, called constrained market pric-   necessary to have trains, staff, support, and rights&#13;
ing, for regulatory reform in the public interest   of way. Although hiring staff and buying or leas-&#13;
and considers their implications for railroad   ing rolling stock inevitably involve some sunk&#13;
restructuring.                              costs, they are small relative to the massive sunk&#13;
costs of establishing network infrastructure. And&#13;
Catalyst for new thinking                   most of the cost of locomotives and freight cars&#13;
might be easily and quickly recovered by roll-&#13;
Contestability theory offers a new, improved   ing them to other markets.&#13;
set of guidelines for appropriate government&#13;
intervention in the structure and conduct of   Thus, contestability suggests a modulated ap-&#13;
firms and industries-including sound criteria   proach to regulation. In activities subject to ef-&#13;
for distinguishing between cases in which in-   fective competitive pressure from the actual (or&#13;
tervention is warranted and those in which it is  potential) supply of substitute services, and in&#13;
not. It focuses increased attention on entry bar-   markets in which efficient technology does not&#13;
riers and their defining characteristics. Contesta-   require significant sunk costs, traditional regu-&#13;
bility analysis shows, for example, that high   latory constraints should be avoided and open&#13;
fixed costs and the consequent economies of   entry and more flexible pricing permitted. And&#13;
scale, traditionally considered impediments to  in markets in which the railroad has signifi-&#13;
entry, need not permit excessive prices or prof-   cant market power, regulation should constrain&#13;
its or any of the other symptoms usually asso-   the prices and terms of services no more (and&#13;
ciated with market power. It is the presence of   no less) than the forces of active or potential&#13;
sunk costs, rather than economies of scale   competition would in competitive or contest-&#13;
alone, that matters for market performance.  able markets. This theory of contestability, to-&#13;
gether with other advances in regulatory theory&#13;
In the rail industry, fixed costs are large because   and practice, is the basis for the following three&#13;
of the infrastructure-track, stations, and the   principles for railroad regulation:&#13;
like-that must be provided before any trains can   * Permit a private sector railroad freedom in&#13;
run on a route. Duplicating this infrastructure is    pricing and operations in services facing ef-&#13;
generally inefficient, so provision of the physical    fective competition in the relevant market,&#13;
network is characterized by natural monopoly  whether from other railroads, other transport&#13;
LIU              Private Sector Development Department ' Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Restructuring Regulation of the Railroad Industry&#13;
modes, other origins, other destinations, or   to all its traffic, it would lose the traffic for&#13;
other commodities.                             which demand could not support the price&#13;
Permit a railroad to set prices that are re-   assigned. The remaining shippers would then&#13;
sponsive to differences in demand and in    be saddled with a larger portion of the carrier's&#13;
marginal costs and to enter into voluntary    unattributable costs since they would no longer&#13;
contracts with shippers that have individual-   share those costs with the lost traffic.&#13;
ized terms, conditions, commitments, and&#13;
compensation mechanisms.                       Ramsey pricing overcomes this problem by ap-&#13;
Permit a railroad to charge "captive shippers,"   portioning all unattributable fixed and common&#13;
those over which the railroad has monopoly   costs of the railroad among its services on the&#13;
power, prices that are no higher than the    basis of their demand characteristics. Each ser-&#13;
stand-alone costs of the shipper's service and    vice is priced at a markup over marginal cost&#13;
that do not generate earnings that consistently   that is inversely related to the elasticity of de-&#13;
exceed the railroad's replacement costs, in-   mand for that service. Under Ramsey pricing, it&#13;
cluding a competitive return on capital.      is the shortfall between total costs and the rev-&#13;
enues that would accrue from pricing each ser-&#13;
The regulatory challenges                        vice at its marginal cost that is apportioned on&#13;
the basis of demand. Ramsey prices therefore&#13;
The substantial economies of scale and scope    deviate from marginal costs only to the extent&#13;
in the railroad industry create several challenges    necessary to provide adequate revenues-they&#13;
for this regulatory framework. Perhaps the most   permit the railroad to achieve revenue adequacy&#13;
troubling is the cost allocation problem-the im-   with the least sacrifice of economic welfare com-&#13;
possibility of allocating, in a nonarbitrary way,   pared with marginal cost pricing.&#13;
a share of fixed and common costs to any one&#13;
of a railroad's many activities. There is no way    Price ceilings-stand-alone cost&#13;
to subdivide those costs in a mechanical fash-&#13;
ion that is unique and is founded in economic    A critical issue for efficiency is the criterion used&#13;
logic. Historically, regulatory authorities have de-   to set the ceiling on rates where there is market&#13;
termined tariffs on the basis of so-called fully   dominance. While rate ceilings derived from fully&#13;
distributed costs. Under this method, regulators    distributed costs are inimical to the public inter-&#13;
allocate shared production costs to individual   est, economically rational ceilings can be ob-&#13;
services in terms of some common basis of uti-   tained from the stand-alone costs. This is the&#13;
lization, such as gross ton-miles.               cost of serving any captive shipper or group of&#13;
shippers that benefit from sharing joint and com-&#13;
Fully distributed cost (FDC) pricing suffers from    mon costs as if the shipper or group were iso-&#13;
several defects. The most serious one is that it  lated from the railroad's other customers. The&#13;
does not necessarily use a causal approach in   stand-alone cost method finds the theoretically&#13;
measuring marginal cost responsibility-taking    maximum rate that a railroad could levy on ship-&#13;
into account how much costs would increase    pers without losing its traffic to a hypothetical&#13;
if more of a particular service were used, or   competing service offered by a hypothetical&#13;
how much they would fall if less of that ser-   entrant facing no entry barriers or by a shipper&#13;
vice were used. Instead, costs are averaged ar-   providing service for itself. Thus, the stand-alone&#13;
bitrarily. A further defect of FDC pricing is its   cost criterion serves as a surrogate for competi-&#13;
neglect of demand data.                         tion and leads to a simulated competitive price.&#13;
Ramsey pricing                                   The stand-alone cost test does not apply-and&#13;
cannot be made to apply without disastrous&#13;
FDC pricing frequently "overassigns" or 'under-   consequences-if railroads are not allowed to&#13;
assigns" a carrier's unattributable costs to par-   abandon unremunerative facilities or services.&#13;
ticular services. If a carrier applied FDC pricing    Where that freedom is denied, a railroad can-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
not earn adequate revenues if its rates on po-   out, however, it is unclear how effective an equal&#13;
tentially remunerative activities are constrained    access mandate is likely to be.&#13;
by stand-alone cost ceilings. For this reason, it&#13;
is unwise for public policy to limit the free-   If the integrated carrier is regulated in a way&#13;
dom of railroads to curtail unremunerative ser-   that permits it to charge higher prices to cap-&#13;
vices without providing public funds to help   tive shippers the more of their business it has,&#13;
defray the costs of those services.              it would have an incentive to exclude other&#13;
participants. Similarly, if regulation limits the&#13;
Options for railway restructuring                amount the integrated carrier can earn from&#13;
the share of service it provides when it does&#13;
The historical model of railway operations is   cooperate with other entities, the carrier would&#13;
the monolithic organization, where a single en-   have an incentive to undermine or avoid effi-&#13;
tity controls all facilities and operating and ad-   cient cooperation in order to enlarge its share&#13;
ministrative functions and determines what   of the service. The integrated carrier would also&#13;
services to provide to generally captive markets.   have an incentive to exclude an efficient par-&#13;
The conditions that gave rise to this model no    ticipant if by doing so, the carrier, acting in a&#13;
longer exist in most countries, and governments    predatory manner, could weaken the potential&#13;
have had to consider a fundamental restructur-   entrant's ability to compete in another market.&#13;
ing of the railway entity and of its relationship    Under classic rate-of-return regulation or un-&#13;
with the state. The two main options are verti-   der a system of regulated "divisions" that speci-&#13;
cal separation and competitive access.           fies what an integrated carrier can earn from&#13;
an activity in which there is cooperation, an&#13;
Vertical separation                              integrated carrier does have incentives to un-&#13;
dermine efficient cooperation.&#13;
Vertical restructuring options that separate the&#13;
ownership of facilities from other rail functions,   In sharp contrast, under constrained market pric-&#13;
such as train operations and marketing, have re-   ing, an integrated carrier would generally have&#13;
cently attracted much favorable attention because    a real profit motive to cooperate with an effi-&#13;
they seem to segregate the difficult regulatory    cient participant in its business. Under this sys-&#13;
problems associated with the largely sunk road-   tem, "divisions" are not specified by regulation&#13;
bed costs. If ownership of track and trains is   -even on service provided to a captive ship-&#13;
separate-with the track assets held by the gov-   per. Instead, the stand-alone cost ceiling applies&#13;
emnment, by a consortium of operators, or by a    to the price charged to the shipper, and coop-&#13;
regulated private entity-there can be vigorous    eration with an efficient entity enlarges the pot&#13;
active and potential competition over railway    of returns available from the service, allowing&#13;
services provided by operators with equal ac-   the integrated carrier to earn more money rather&#13;
cess to the roadbed. This competition would   than less. Consequently, except for the rare pos-&#13;
eliminate the need to regulate the operators and    sibility of predation, an integrated carrier would&#13;
give them powerful incentives to provide effi-   have ordinary business incentives to find and&#13;
cient services that are responsive to the needs of   to cooperate with efficient participants in its busi-&#13;
shippers and a growing entrepreneurial economy.   ness and to negotiate mutually beneficial terms&#13;
with them. This is just a railroad version of&#13;
Competitive access                               "make-or-buy" decisions in other industries.&#13;
Unlike vertical separation, competitive access    Despite the incentives for efficient behavior by&#13;
permits integrated operations by the rail entity.   integrated carriers provided by constrained mar-&#13;
It implies a requirement that the integrated car-   ket pricing, it is useful and wise to augment the&#13;
rier make its facilities available to other entities    system of regulation with a fallback set of stan-&#13;
on a "fair and equal basis." If the integrated car-   dards to apply if disputes about predation&#13;
rier has strong incentives to keep other entities   through competitive access should arise. These&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Restructuring Regulation of the Railroad Industry&#13;
standards would be based on the principle that    Separating track assets from operations is likely&#13;
an integrated carrier that possesses a "bottle-    to be a particularly attractive option where a&#13;
neck"-a facility without which the competitor    dense and extensive rail network permits many&#13;
cannot offer its services-should not refuse an    operators to function, ensuring both active and&#13;
agreement that provides for full compensation    potential competition. It is also likely to work&#13;
of all its costs, including opportunity costs.       well where fixed facilities are mature and well&#13;
developed, limiting the domain of new infra-&#13;
Efficient component pricing and parity pricing    structure investments, where incentive problems&#13;
are both names that have been given to the    are more likely to arise. Where fixed facilities&#13;
principle that an integrated carrier should of-    are not well developed, regulation of the infra-&#13;
fer the services of its bottleneck at a price that    structure entity should permit it to enter into&#13;
yields it the same return as if it had performed    medium- or long-term  contracts with shippers&#13;
the end user's service itself. Behavior consis-    or with operators that themselves have contracts&#13;
tent with this principle leads to efficient verti-    with shippers, so that the risks and rewards from&#13;
cal relationships and is thus consistent with    investments can be efficiently shared by ship-&#13;
nonpredatory incentives under the constrained    pers, operators, and the infrastructure entity. If&#13;
market pricing rules. Such pricing of bottle-    the infrastructure entity is expected to seek re-&#13;
neck facilities does not place additional com-    covery of its replacement costs, it should be&#13;
petitive pressure on pricing to shippers, since    permitted and even encouraged to use price dis-&#13;
it is based on the return that could be earned    crimination to help bring shippers' prices into&#13;
from the shipper's service at the extant price.    line with principles of Ramsey efficiency.&#13;
But it does generate incentives for supplying&#13;
an efficient combination of transport services,    The competitive access option could also be&#13;
it does provide quality and cost competition    fraught with problems if the incentives of bottle-&#13;
among potential and actual participants for sup-    neck holders are adverse to efficiency and com-&#13;
This series is published    plying part of that efficient combination, and it   petition. But under rail regulation that focuses&#13;
to share ideas and invite   does help to ensure that those with efficient    on the rates charged to shippers rather than on&#13;
discussion. It covers&#13;
financial and private  innovations in logistics or in marketing trans-    other prices, such as those charged for access to&#13;
sector development as  port services will be able to work with carriers    bottleneck services, incentives generally promote&#13;
well as industry and  to implement their ideas.                            efficient vertical relationships. As a result, if inte-&#13;
energy. The views&#13;
expressed are those of                                                     gration is permitted under this system of price&#13;
the authors and are not    Separation versus competitive access            regulation, the outcomes are predictably consis-&#13;
intended to represent                                                     tent with efficient participation by the integrated&#13;
an official statement of T&#13;
Bank policy or strategy.   The primary virtue of separation as a policy op-    carrier and by other, nonintegrated carriers, on&#13;
tion is that it may ensure active or potential com-    terms that permit compensatory support for the&#13;
Comments are welcome.   petition among rail operators or retailers-and     efficient participants. Further, prices to shippers&#13;
Please call the FPD&#13;
Note line to leave a  efficient selection among them for provision of    can be selected in accordance with Ramsey effi-&#13;
message (202-458-1111)   their services. However, prices are unlikely to    ciency, even as they are constrained by regula-&#13;
or contact Suzanne   be fully Ramsey-efficient for the coverage of re-    tion where the carrier has monopoly power.&#13;
Smith, editor, Room&#13;
G8105, The World Bank,    placement costs, because of the difficulties of&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,   reflecting the differences in shippers' demands    This Note is based on a chapter by the authors in Claudio Frischtak,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,   in the prices charged for infrastructure services.   ed., 'Regulatory Policies and Reform: A Comparative Perspective"&#13;
or Internet address                                                       (World Bank, Private Sector Development Department. Washington,&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.   At the same time, separation may create serious    D.C., forthcoming). To order, contact Cindy Wong at (202) 473-3606&#13;
coordination problems, loss of economies of    or by email (cwong@worldbank.org).&#13;
SPrinted on recycled  scope, and otherwise unnecessary transactions&#13;
paper.               costs. In addition, in thin markets rail operators    loannis N Kessides, Principal Economist, Private&#13;
may not face effective active and potential com-    SectorDevelopmentDepartment (email: ikessides@&#13;
petition, undermining the potential for realiz-    worldbank.org), andRobertD. Willig, Professorof&#13;
ing the primary benefit of this option.              Economics and Public Affairs, Princeton University&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="697016">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/10/697016/restructuring-regulation-railroad-industry
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/10/697016/restructuring-regulation-railroad-industry</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/10/697016/restructuring-regulation-railroad-industry</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1995/10/01/000009265_3980420172808/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1995/10/01/000009265_3980420172808/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>1995-10-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1995-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Restructuring regulation of the railroad industry
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Throughout the world, the rail industry
            has been one of the most heavily regulated sectors.  The
            public utility paradigm of government regulation has failed
            to handle the central regulatory problem--the mixture of
            competive and monopoly elements in supply-- and is now being
            blamed for the poor financial condition of the railroads,
            for the deterioration of rail plant, for the lack of
            innovation, and for the mediocre quality of rail services.
            This Note outlines a set of principles, called constrained
            market pricing, for regulatory reform in the public interest
            and considers their implications for railroad restructuring.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Restructuring regulation of the railroad industry
        </docna>
        <display_title>Restructuring regulation of the
            railroad industry</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1995/10/697016/restructuring-regulation-railroad-industry</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Education for the Knowledge Economy,Knowledge Economy</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Education,Environment</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Kessides, Ioannis N.</author>
            <author>Willig, Robert D.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980420172808</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Railways</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 58</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Education,Environment</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Transportation</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Railways; Railway infrastructure; Government
            regulation; Prices; Price policy; Market competition; Contestability
            economic welfare,economies of
            scale,elasticity,fixed costs,government
            intervention,marginal cost,marginal cost pricing,marginal
            costs,market power,market pricing,natural monopoly,network
            infrastructure,opportunity costs,Price ceilings,production
            costs,profit motive,public policy,regulatory
            framework,replacement costs,revenue adequacy,sunk costs,thin
            markets,total costs,transport
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off of VP, FPD - WB (FPDVP)</owner>
        <repnb>16918</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Port Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Terminals</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Logistics and Transport Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport and Trade Logistics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Logistics Providers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Placement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport and Logistics Services</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>