<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. T-6590-E&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
-EXICO&#13;
INFRASTRUCTURE PRIVATIZATION TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
AUGUST 2, 1995&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Currency Equivalents&#13;
(As of July 21, 1995)&#13;
Currency Unit = Mexican New Peso (MexN$)&#13;
US$ 1.0 = MexN$ 6.10&#13;
Abbreviations and Acronyms Used&#13;
API               Autoridad Portuaria Integral&#13;
(Integrated Port Authority)&#13;
ASA               Aeropuertos y Servicios Auxiliares&#13;
(Airports and Auxiliary Services)&#13;
BANXICO           Banco de Mexico&#13;
BIS               Bank for International Settlements&#13;
CAPUFE            Caminos y Puentes Federales&#13;
(Federal Highways and Bridge Authority)&#13;
CFE               Comisi6n Federal de Electricidad&#13;
(Federal Electricity Commission)&#13;
CID               Comisi6n Intersecretarial de Desincorporaci6n&#13;
(Interministerial Commission on Privatization)&#13;
CRE               Comisi6n Reguladora de Energfa&#13;
(Energy Regulatory Commission)&#13;
DGAC              Direcci6n General de Aviaci6n Civil&#13;
(General Directorate of Civil Aviation)&#13;
FNM               Ferrocarriles Nacionales de Mexico&#13;
(Mexican National Railways)&#13;
FTAL              Financial Sector Technical Assistance Loan (ME-3838)&#13;
ICAO              International Civil Aviation Organization&#13;
ICB               International Competitive Bidding&#13;
IDB               Inter-American Development Bank&#13;
IFC               International Finance Corporation&#13;
IMF               International Monetary Fund&#13;
IPP               Independent Power Producer&#13;
MIF               Multilateral Investment Fund&#13;
NAFIN             Nacional Financiera S.N.C.&#13;
NCB               National Competitive Bidding&#13;
PCS               Personal Communications Services&#13;
PEMEX             Petr6leos Mexicanos&#13;
SCT               Secretaria de Comunicaciones y Transportes&#13;
(Secretariat of Communication and Transport)&#13;
SECODA            Secretarfa de la Contralorfa y Desarrollo&#13;
Administrativo&#13;
(Secretariat of the Controller General and&#13;
Administrative Development)&#13;
SECOFI            Secretaria de Comercio y Fomento Industrial&#13;
(Secretariat of Commerce and Industrial Development)&#13;
SHCP              Secretarfa de Hacienda y Credito Publico&#13;
(Secretariat of Finance and Public Credit)&#13;
TELMEX            Tehlfonos de Mexico S.A. de C. V.&#13;
TELECOMM          Telecomunicaciones de Mexico&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
INFRASTRUCTURE PRIVATIZATION TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE LOAN&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Pae&#13;
SECTION A: PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
Background  .....................................   1&#13;
Current Status of Privatization ..........            ..................  2&#13;
Project Design .....................................  4&#13;
Project Description ................................... 7&#13;
SECTION B: PROJECT ADMINISTRATION AND IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
Project Organization .................................. 12&#13;
Training Plan ..................................... 12&#13;
Project Costs and Financing ............................. 12&#13;
Procurement .....................................   12&#13;
Disbursements ..................................... 13&#13;
Accounts and Audits .................................. 13&#13;
ATTACHMENT: PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION  PLAN   .............. 15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MEXICO&#13;
INFRASTRUCTURE PRIVATIZATION TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE LOAN&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
SECTION A: PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
I.     Background&#13;
1.     Throughout the last decade privatization has been a key component of&#13;
structural reform policies in Mexico in the pursuit of productivity gains for the&#13;
economy. In the mid-1980s the Government complemented macro-economic&#13;
stabilization policy with structural reforms, including privatization, to spur&#13;
productivity growth. Sales of smaller state-enterprises dominated the period 1986 to&#13;
1988, after which followed a large scale privatization program of larger companies&#13;
operating in competitive markets, mainly manufacturing firms and banks. Between&#13;
1989 and 1992 total privatization proceeds amounted to 6.3 percent of average annual&#13;
national output. Proceeds were essentially used to repay debt and thus helped place&#13;
the Government's debt exposure on a sound footing. In 1990 the Government began&#13;
selling firms in sectors requiring economic regulation, most notably Telefonos de&#13;
Mexico, S.A. de C. V. (TELMEX), the national telephony operator. Though the&#13;
overall economic outlook brightened, the difficulties of selling other infrastructure&#13;
businesses without greater attention to the legal and regulatory aspects became&#13;
apparent. Consequently, the announced program, comprising power plants, roads,&#13;
airports and ports, slowed significantly in 1993.&#13;
2.     The successful implementation of these and other far-reaching structural&#13;
reforms, along with reduced interest rates paid on investment alternatives abroad,&#13;
induced a surge in net foreign capital inflows that averaged US$27 billion per year&#13;
during 1991-93. Until the end of 1994, these inflows enabled Mexico to run a large&#13;
current account deficit, which peaked at 8 percent of GDP in 1994. The capital&#13;
inflows also caused the real value of the peso to appreciate. Strong political conflicts&#13;
that arose in 1994, however, led to an abrupt slowing of the capital inflows, so that&#13;
Mexico was forced to finance its current account deficit through a loss of foreign&#13;
reserves. When the markets realized that the relative supply of pesos was growing too&#13;
fast, panic selling further depleted the foreign exchange reserves of Mexico in late&#13;
December 1994 and January 1995, and led to a major devaluation. Though the&#13;
market appears to have stabilized, the peso depreciated by about 77 percent, from&#13;
about 3.45 December 1994 to about 6.10 on July 21, 1995.&#13;
3.     In March 1995 the Government announced an austerity program to&#13;
reestablish trust in the economy and minimize the required macro-economic&#13;
adjustment. The main targets of the program are to: (i) achieve a primary budgetary&#13;
surplus of 4.4 percent of GDP for 1995; (ii) limit net domestic credit creation to a&#13;
maximum of MexN$10 billion for 1995; (iii) achieve equilibrium in the current&#13;
account; and (iv) restructure MexN$65 billion of outstanding debt of the private&#13;
sector, representing 13 percent of the total commercial bank loan portfolio. The&#13;
program is backed by unprecedented balance of payments support, announced to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2&#13;
amount to some US$50 billion, from sources including the International Monetary&#13;
Fund (IMF), US government, Bank for International Settlements (BIS), World Bank&#13;
and Inter-American Development Bank (IDB). As part of the program, the&#13;
Government has announced its intention to accelerate the privatization of major state-&#13;
owned enterprises, mainly in infrastructure. The program includes a large number of&#13;
entities in telecommunications, energy and transport. Compared with others in Latin&#13;
America and other regions, this is one of the most extensive privatization programs.&#13;
The ambitious goal is to obtain sales revenues of about US$6 billion in 1995 and&#13;
US$6-8 billion in 1996.&#13;
II.    Current Status of Privatization&#13;
4.     The Government is advancing at a very fast pace in preparing the various&#13;
sectors for privatization. The privatization of container terminals in four major ports&#13;
is most advanced and the call for tenders was published in the Official Gazette on&#13;
February 23, 1995. Concessions for two major terminals were awarded on July 7,&#13;
1995. Deregulation of basic telephone services and rail privatization are being&#13;
pursued aggressively with basic laws submitted to Congress in April 1995. In a&#13;
major departure from past policy, the Government also introduced a law on natural&#13;
gas deregulation in Congress in April 1995. Groundwork has started in the areas of&#13;
airports, roads, radio spectrum auctions, satellite privatization, power generation and&#13;
secondary petrochemicals. Now that the immediate efforts to put in place a macro-&#13;
economic program are no longer dominating the attention of top policy makers, the&#13;
pace of reform in infrastructure is accelerating further. In support of the privatization&#13;
process, however, a host of issues related to privatizing infrastructure firms with&#13;
natural monopoly characteristics need clarification and analysis, e.g., design of&#13;
market structures and regulatory arrangements, concession design, public procurement&#13;
rules, contracting practices, rules for issuing Government guarantees, and the&#13;
development of appropriate financial infrastructure for financing investments,&#13;
including means of securing credit, issuing insurance contracts, etc. Lack of clarity&#13;
about these matters has been a major obstacle for infrastructure privatization and the&#13;
conclusion of financeable deals.&#13;
5.     Electiricity and Secondary Petrochemicals. The Government's approach to&#13;
private participation in these sectors has been rather gradual. Since 1992, it has&#13;
introduced a number of measures to gradually open the electricity sector, within the&#13;
limits of Article 27 of the Constitution which reserves public electricity service for the&#13;
State. It has introduced a new legal and regulatory framework which provides the&#13;
basis for private ownership in power generation in the form of: (i) independent power&#13;
producers (IPPs); (ii) self-generators; (iii) cogenerators; and (iv) small power&#13;
producers. Power sales by IPPs are made exclusively to the state-owned electricity&#13;
monopoly, Comisi6n Federal de Electricidad (CFE), while sales under the remaining&#13;
three classes may be to private parties. While private companies have shown much&#13;
interest, lack of confidence in the fuel supply agreements (which would be with the&#13;
state-owned hydrocarbons monopoly, PEMEX) and questions about how power&#13;
purchase agreements might be managed by CFE have so far stalled progress. The&#13;
Government is now exploring ways to reform policy such that existing and new power&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3&#13;
plants may be privatized without the need for extensive government guarantees of&#13;
contractual performance under the required supply and offtake agreements. In&#13;
particular, the Government is exploring to what extent private power plants may be&#13;
given a choice of fuel suppliers, how to establish adequate tariffs to render CFE&#13;
creditworthy, and to what extent competition could be introduced in the power sector.&#13;
6.     In late 1992, the Government announced plans to privatize some 60&#13;
secondary petrochemicals plants. These plans were defacto shelved during 1993.&#13;
Meanwhile, PEMEX has internally been reorganized into four major profit centers,&#13;
one of which comprises secondary petrochemicals. Current discussions revolve around&#13;
how to privatize the secondary petrochemical business - as a whole or in parts.&#13;
7.     Transport. Since the late 1980s, the transport sector has been deregulated&#13;
and services increasingly provided by the private sector. The Bank had in particular&#13;
supported trucking deregulation with sector work and an adjustment loan in 1990&#13;
(Loan 3207-ME).&#13;
8.     Between 1992 and 1994 some 76 terminals outside the major ports were&#13;
concessioned to private operators. In the main port of Veracruz, three stevedoring&#13;
concessions were let in 1991. Tender announcements for concessions of container&#13;
terminals in Mexico's four major ports (Altamira, Veracruz, Manzanillo and Lazaro&#13;
Cardenas) were issued in February 1995. Two concessions were awarded on July 7,&#13;
1995 (Veracruz and Manzanillo). The legal underpinnings for this program are the&#13;
Port Law, Navigation Law, and Customs Law and their corresponding regulations.&#13;
The Port Law provides for the creation of integrated port authorities (APIs) to act as&#13;
landlord for each port and to be responsible for the concessioning and privatization&#13;
activities within their port. Airlines were privatized in the large privatization wave&#13;
around the turn of the decade. Airports are currently under the management of a&#13;
government agency, Aeropuertos y Servicios Auxiliares (ASA). The Government has&#13;
begun to consider options for privatizing ASA's operations.&#13;
9.     Until this year, privatization activities in the Mexican railways company&#13;
(Ferrocarriles Nacionales de Mexico, FNM), which is essentially a transporter of&#13;
freight, were limited to contracting out the operation of repair shops and some track&#13;
construction and maintenance. Now, the Government wants to proceed with the&#13;
privatization of FNM and is considering alternative plans to do this. Under the&#13;
current economic adjustment program, Congress, in early 1995, approved a change in&#13;
the Constitution to allow for railway privatization. A new railway law was presented&#13;
to Congress in April 1995.&#13;
10.    Telecommunications. Major reform of the telecommunications sector was&#13;
launched in 1989 with the privatization of TELMEX, the 56 percent state-owned&#13;
monopoly telephone company. A 20 percent, controlling interest in TELMEX was&#13;
sold in 1990 for $1.76 billion to a consortium of Mexican and foreign investors.&#13;
Public offerings in 1991 and 1992 fetched a further $4.5 billion, bringing total sales&#13;
proceeds to $6.3 billion. TELMEX now accounts for about 30% of the equity traded&#13;
in Mexico's stock exchange and also figures prominently in the US capital markets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4&#13;
11.    The results of this privatization have generally been satisfactory. Since 1990&#13;
TELMEX has invested in excess of $2 billion annually, telephone density increased&#13;
from 6.3 lines per 100 inhabitants to over 9, rural service was extended to some&#13;
8,000 rural communities, and the number of payphones increased from 83,000 to&#13;
205,000. However, while investment performance met expectations, steps towards&#13;
opening up the core telephone business to competition have proceeded rather slowly.&#13;
In particular, the agreed timetable for rebalancing TELMEX's tariffs has not been&#13;
met. Weighted average rates remain among the highest of OECD countries. High&#13;
connection fees stifle the demand for new lines. Quality of service has generally&#13;
improved but remains below targets in the Federal District.&#13;
12.    Other important elements of the 1989 reform were: (i) licensing an&#13;
independent private cellular service provider in each of nine regions; (ii) transferring&#13;
the remaining state telecommunications operations from the Secretariat of&#13;
Comunicacion and Transport (SCT) to Telecommuniciones de Mexico (TELECOMM,&#13;
a decentralized state entity); and (iii) expanding under TELECOMM the domestic&#13;
satellite system, including investments of about $0.7 billion.&#13;
In.    Project Design&#13;
13.    Project Objectives and Approach. The project aims to: (i) help the&#13;
Government choose structural options for sector reform; (ii) develop a sound legal&#13;
and regulatory framework in support of privatization; (iii) reduce, and if possible,&#13;
eliminate constraints to privatization in selected sectors (ports, airports, railway,&#13;
telecommunications, power, secondary petrochemicals); and (iv) provide support to&#13;
the privatization preparation process in each of these sectors, through the&#13;
Interministerial Commission on Privatization (CID, para. 16).&#13;
14.    The Government's overall framework on privatization is as follows.&#13;
First, those companies that operate in competitive markets for tradeable&#13;
goods and services can and will be sold as soon as possible with the goal of&#13;
maximizing sales revenues.&#13;
Second, all other firms and institutions in the subsectors listed above which&#13;
produce non-tradeable and largely monopolistic services, will require the&#13;
establishment of a suitable framework for economic regulation. In these&#13;
cases the Government will ensure that the establishment of efficient solutions&#13;
takes precedence over the quick generation of cash. The Government will&#13;
also maximize the scope for competitive forces and minimize the need for&#13;
economic regulation, if need be by relying on intermodal and inter-&#13;
concession competition rather than attempting to establish a system of&#13;
economic regulation, that requires significant fine-tuning. Forms of&#13;
privatization will be chosen that minimize reliance on explicit and implicit&#13;
government subsidies and guarantees so as to strictly limit the exposure of&#13;
the Government. This implies inter alia the need to set tariffs at levels&#13;
sufficient to cover competitive costs, including the cost of capital, and to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5&#13;
allow investors maximum freedom to choose creditworthy and reliable&#13;
suppliers and customers.&#13;
Third, the proceeds of privatization will be used to improve the composition&#13;
of the Government's balance sheet.&#13;
Fourth, while the establishment of sound regulatory systems requires careful&#13;
preparation, it will be undertaken with determination and without delay, such&#13;
that the process of privatization and deregulation will be initiated in 1995 in&#13;
some sectors and completed within three to five years in those sectors&#13;
requiring more upstream strategic work.&#13;
15.    The project's design builds on the conceptual approach adopted by the&#13;
Government. The focus on legal and regulatory frameworks is an essential first step,&#13;
aimed not only at identifying and eliminating obstacles to private sector participation&#13;
but also in ensuring that the "rules of the game" are applied transparently and&#13;
consistently.&#13;
16.    Institutional Framework. The privatization program is complex and wide&#13;
ranging, addressing issues of sector structure, competition and efficiency. To steer&#13;
this undertaking, provide policy guidelines and ensure a consistent, comprehensive&#13;
approach across sectors, the CID was established by Presidential Decree on April 7,&#13;
1995. It is chaired by the Secretary of Finance and Public Credit (SHCP), and its&#13;
permanent members include the Secretaries of Commerce and Industrial Development&#13;
(SECOFI), Control and Administrative Development (SECODA), and Labor. The&#13;
President of the Federal Competition Commission is a permanent observer. Sector&#13;
ministries and entities (e.g. SCT) participate in the CID for matters pertaining to&#13;
those sectors. The CID is supported by a small Technical Secretariat, headed by a&#13;
senior official in SHCP. The Technical Secretariat oversees the day-to-day affairs of&#13;
the CID, coordinate contracting of consultants and advisers, reviews proposals, and&#13;
ensures consistency throughout the process.&#13;
17.    The CID is charged with: (i) designing the privatization process and&#13;
supervising its implementation; (ii) naming a special commissioner (comisionado&#13;
especial) to coordinate each specific privatization; (iii) reviewing the regulatory&#13;
framework and proposing changes; (iv) reviewing concession designs and agreements,&#13;
particularly those aspects related to penalties for non-compliance with the conditions&#13;
of the concession agreement or the requirements of the basic laws under which it is&#13;
made; (v) establishing guidelines for valuation of state-owned entities and overseeing&#13;
the process; (vi) establishing and carrying out a communications strategy with respect&#13;
to privatization; and (vii) contracting the advisers necessary to support its work. The&#13;
decree also states that the CID has final approval of all privatizations and that&#13;
proceeds of the privatization process will revert to the federal treasury.&#13;
18.    The privatization activities to be supported in each sector (power and&#13;
secondary petrochemicals, transport and telecommunications) are directed by working&#13;
groups related to each ministry, under the direction of the special commissioner&#13;
appointed by the CID. The Technical Secretariat provides support to the working&#13;
groups. The decree requires that each working group: (i) define a sector strategy and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6&#13;
privatization plan; (ii) review the adequacy of the legal and regulatory framework;&#13;
(iii) recommend changes; and (iv) supervise the operational aspects of the actual&#13;
divestiture, concession or auction. Each working group is, therefore, the primary&#13;
locus of responsibility for identifying and implementing policy studies and other&#13;
analytical work, and for preparing and submitting options papers and decision&#13;
memoranda to the CID. In addition to hiring of consultants, workshops, seminars,&#13;
study tours and training would be organized and authorized by each working group.&#13;
19.    Bank and Other Multilateral Assistance. To support the immediate needs&#13;
for technical assistance, the Bank is providing substantial direct support to help in the&#13;
development of the overall strategy and sectoral policies, and in particular the drafting&#13;
of sound laws and regulations. This assistance, which will continue throughout the&#13;
project, has taken the form of policy notes in response to requests by the authorities,&#13;
draft terms of reference, the organization of consultations with international experts in&#13;
relevant areas, and comments on draft documents the Government has submitted to&#13;
Bank experts. Six workshops, on railways, power sector restructuring, regulatory&#13;
policy, telecommunications deregulation, spectrum auctions and satellite privatization&#13;
have already been organized.&#13;
20.    The Bank's assistance strategy is being coordinated with both IDB and the&#13;
IFC. It started with an aide-memoire on privatization strategy which was supported&#13;
by all three institutions and issued on January 13, 1995 to the Government at the end&#13;
of a joint mission. The IDB is exploring ways to utilize its Multilateral Investment&#13;
Fund (MIF) in support of the program. IFC is similarly exploring ways to support&#13;
the privatization process and to arrange financing and securitization for new&#13;
investment projects.&#13;
21.    Risks. The project faces several important risks. The first is that the&#13;
privatization program may be weakened in the face of opposition from unions, the&#13;
state owned enterprises themselves, private sector groups seeking to limit competition,&#13;
or other organized groups. The broad composition of the CID, however, and planned&#13;
activities (such as workshops, public relations campaigns, and briefings with the&#13;
domestic and international investors) will mitigate this risk. Continued macroeconomic&#13;
instability would also damage the program e.g. by increasing country risk for&#13;
investors and by giving greater urgency to quick - though ultimately damaging -&#13;
dispositions of assets before adequate legal and regulatory structures are in place. An&#13;
unfavorable public reaction to the Government's economic program, or to the&#13;
privatization program itself, may make it much more difficult to eventually effect the&#13;
sales or concessioning process. The Government's economic plan, which was&#13;
announced in March 1995, is currently succeeding in stabilizing the exchange rate.&#13;
The Government is also taking steps to improve its relations with international&#13;
investors by providing better access to central bank information and by undertaking&#13;
more frequent consultations, and is pursuing an active public information campaign.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7&#13;
IV.    Project Description&#13;
22.    The project provides support for: (i) the privatization preparation processes to&#13;
be undertaken in transport (ports, railways, and airports), electricity and secondary&#13;
petrochemicals, and telecommunications (basic services, satellites and radio&#13;
spectrum); and (ii) cross sectoral studies and coordination to be undertaken by the&#13;
CID. Depending on the readiness for privatization in each sector, the project supports&#13;
diagnostic studies, strategy formulation and implementation, and regulatory&#13;
institutional strengthening. The CID component also includes support for an&#13;
evaluation of the privatization process. The Attachment provides greater detail&#13;
concerning the objectives, activities, outputs, forms of assistance, timing and costs&#13;
associated with the project.&#13;
Transport&#13;
23.    Ports. A process of restructuring the ports has been under way since early in&#13;
the last administration. More than 70 port terminals dealing with single products, such&#13;
as fertilizers, grain and cement, have been concessioned and a new Ports Law was&#13;
approved in July 1993. This Law permits the creation of Integrated Port Authorities&#13;
(APIs), with full responsibility for the operation of the port(s) under their jurisdiction&#13;
and the possible concessioning of individual terminals or berths within the port and of&#13;
common port activities such as provision of navigation aides, pilotage and dredging.&#13;
APIs have already been formed for 17 ports. They are all functioning as public&#13;
companies with 100% state ownership, but the new law provides for private&#13;
participation in their ownership with up to 49% foreign capital. Recently, SCT has&#13;
issued a call, on behalf of the relevant APIs, for pre-qualification submissions for the&#13;
operation of container and general cargo berths in the four largest ports - Veracruz&#13;
and Tampico on the Atlantic/Gulf Coast and Manzanillo and Lazaro Cardenas on the&#13;
Pacific Coast. Two concessions were awarded in July 1995. The project would&#13;
support privatization preparation activities for terminals as well as port authorities.&#13;
24.    Railways. In February 1995 a Constitutional amendment was approved by&#13;
Congress allowing for the railways privatization. In April, a new Railways Law, that&#13;
would permit the concessioning of the railway as a whole or in parts, was presented&#13;
in Congress. The project would finance a series of studies needed to implement the&#13;
privatization process. (i) review of proposals. The project would finance a final&#13;
evaluation of the current recommendations (made by external consultants), which&#13;
divide the railways into a number of separate operations: three large concessions and&#13;
a number of short lines to deal with short distance bulk movements of specific&#13;
commodities and with regional lines that would not be viable as part of a larger&#13;
concession. (ii) details of each concession. While the consultants' recommendations&#13;
define the general extent of each concession, they leave open the details for the&#13;
bidding documents that are to be prepared. The project would finance this work. (iii)&#13;
alternative methods of dealing with current workshop concessions. As part of the&#13;
previous administration's process of out-sourcing ancillary railway activities, seven&#13;
locomotive workshops were concessioned in 1994 for a period of 15 years. These&#13;
concessions could be seen as a disincentive for potential concessionaires of the lines&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
and services supported by these workshops. At the least, it is likely that the terms of&#13;
the workshop concessions would need to be renegotiated. The project would review&#13;
the alternative ways of resolving this problem and recommend a solution that best&#13;
meets the Government's requirements. (iv) prepare and implement FNM&#13;
regionalization. It is likely that the concession agreements will be expressed in&#13;
regional terms, so that additional lines can be included or excluded from the&#13;
concession without a need to make revisions to the agreement. To facilitate the hand-&#13;
over process from FNM to the private concessionaires, FNM will be restructured on&#13;
the same regional basis as implied in the concession agreements, and operate on that&#13;
basis for as long as possible before the hand-over takes place. The project would&#13;
finance the work to prepare, implement and monitor this process. (v) inventory and&#13;
valuation of assets. The project would finance these inventories, including technical&#13;
assessments, and valuations. This work would include all present FNM assets and&#13;
would pay particular attention to the issue of land ownership, much of which is in&#13;
dispute between FNM and the local authorities in whose area it lies. (vi) plan for&#13;
resettlement of illegal settlers on FNM land. There is no reliable estimate of the&#13;
number of illegal settlers on FNM land, but whatever their real number, resettlement&#13;
issues will need to be resolved prior to awarding concessions. The project would&#13;
finance the studies needed for FNM to develop a policy on resettlement. (vii)&#13;
environmental assessment of railway facilities. As part of the preparation of a possible&#13;
Bank-financed railway project, and as an antecedent to the privatization of the railway&#13;
mechanical workshops in 1994, environmental assessments were carried out for&#13;
twelve workshops and associated installations. In addition, an Environmental Action&#13;
Plan was prepared, detailing the actions needed to remedy the problems. The project&#13;
would finance the required environmental updatings and assessments, as well as&#13;
advise on the most appropriate method of financing their resolution. (viii) training&#13;
schemes for FNM staff. The project would evaluate alternative ways of structuring&#13;
and financing retraining programs.&#13;
25.    Airports. The growth in air transport since the deregulation of the airlines&#13;
in 1989 has put pressure on the operational capacity and financing requirements of&#13;
many Mexican airports. The opening of direct services between the US and many&#13;
Mexican tourist destinations has also increased pressure on regional airports, although&#13;
it has provided some relief in Mexico City, where the airport is approaching both&#13;
runway and terminal capacity. The difficulty of finding public finance for the basic&#13;
non-commercial facilities has led to a reorientation of policy towards a possible&#13;
concessioning of airports, perhaps following the model of the APIs. The project&#13;
would finance the development of an airports privatization strategy, and following&#13;
completion of the report, a seminar would be held, with participation of&#13;
representatives of the Directorate General of Civil Aviation (DGCA), ASA, SCT and&#13;
SHCP and ICAO (International Civil Aviation Organization) and other specialists with&#13;
experience in airport management, operations and finance. The objective of the&#13;
seminar would be to recommend an appropriate structure for the management and&#13;
development of airports. The project would also finance studies of specific issues&#13;
critical to the implementation of a privatization process: (i) financial review and&#13;
inventory and valuation of regional airports' assets as part of the evaluation of their&#13;
attractiveness for future private participation; (ii) airport needs for Mexico City,&#13;
including the use of existing facilities and the possible development of a new airport&#13;
with private participation; and (iii) safety standards, to assess compliance with ICAO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9&#13;
standards. Finally, a restructuring of DGAC and ASA would be studied. Until now&#13;
the DGAC and ASA have acted as providers of airport services. In the future they, or&#13;
their successors, will need to act mostly as monitors and supervisors of services&#13;
provided by others. This will require a profound change in their structures and staffs.&#13;
The project will examine the future strategy for the provision of airport services, and&#13;
once this has been determined, will recommend a new supervisory structure both for&#13;
the management of airport concessions and for regulation of the sector, including the&#13;
possible creation of a Civil Aviation Authority as part of a broader regulation and&#13;
monitoring of the whole aviation sector.&#13;
Electricity and Secondary Petrochemicals&#13;
26.      Electricity. The effectiveness of past efforts to foster private investment in&#13;
power generation has been limited. While by no means unanimous, a consensus is&#13;
emerging in Mexico on the need to reassess basic policies in the sector. This is based&#13;
on a growing recognition of the powerful role direct and indirect competition could&#13;
play in fostering efficient private investment of the magnitudes required to meet the&#13;
prospective demand for electricity over the next decade. The power sector component&#13;
of the loan is designed to support the Government in identifying tractable options for&#13;
choosing the best possible sector structure, including opportunities for introducing&#13;
competition, and for initiating actions toward this end in the near term. More&#13;
specifically, the project will support the Government in: (i) the definition of desirable&#13;
future sector strategy and policy. The project will provide support for advisory&#13;
services to assist the Government in undertaking a diagnostic study of past&#13;
performance and future prospects of the electricity sector in Mexico. Guiding&#13;
principles for this effort include: (a) reliance on commercial incentives to govern the&#13;
operations of power sector companies with the goal of providing the best possible&#13;
service at the best possible price; (b) strictly limiting the financial burden the power&#13;
sector places on the Government; and (c) introducing competitive forces where&#13;
possible. (ii) near-term restructuring. The project will provide advisory services to&#13;
the Government to identify and evaluate options to restructure the power sector, in&#13;
particular the separation of generation, transmission, dispatch and distribution into&#13;
arms-length entities. This would include an assessment of options to introduce&#13;
effective competition among generating units and competition for customers. The&#13;
restructuring options would be based on an analysis of the current organization and&#13;
performance of the power system as well as ownership and competition options&#13;
possible under existing Mexican law (or suggestions for changes in such laws if they&#13;
would improve the range of desirable options). (iii) electricity pricing policy. The&#13;
project would finance advisory services to assist the Government in analyzing the&#13;
current tariff system and in developing proposals which would: (a) set tariffs at&#13;
economic levels, i.e. levels sufficient to cover the costs of capital required for system&#13;
expansion and all operations and maintenance costs; (b) use tariff policy to provide&#13;
incentives for companies to operate efficiently in the power sector; (c) enhance&#13;
creditworthiness.&#13;
27.    Three other issues related to sector structure would be considered under the&#13;
project. First, advisory services, training, and study tours would be financed to assist&#13;
the power sector regulatory entity in order to provide a credible commitment to: (i)&#13;
investors operating with reasonable efficiency that they will be allowed to recover&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10&#13;
their costs and earn a profit commensurate with the risks that they bear; and (ii)&#13;
consumers that they will be protected from the abuse of monopoly power by any&#13;
public or private entity that operates with a de facto or de jure monopoly. Care&#13;
would be taken to distinguish between activities that need to be regulated and those&#13;
that need not. The regulatory entity could be structured to rule in disputes about&#13;
contracts between participants in the power market relating to matters of economic&#13;
regulation. Second, to enhance the management autonomy of power sector companies&#13;
and to widen the scope for efficiency improvements, options to diversify fuel supply&#13;
sources would be investigated based on an analysis of the existing arrangements for&#13;
the supply of fuels. This would, in particular, cover the supply of petroleum products&#13;
and natural gas. Various options to deregulate prices and supply arrangements of&#13;
these products would be evaluated including deregulation of domestic distribution and&#13;
liberalizing trade and their consequences for the organization of these markets. Third,&#13;
the project would finance advisory services, study tours, and seminars to evaluate&#13;
ownership options in the power sector including means of creating arms-length&#13;
commercial relationships between Government and government-owned companies&#13;
through commercialization and corporatization as well as ways to use private&#13;
ownership to improve the performance of the power system. Privatization options&#13;
would include the use of licenses and/or concessions for providers of energy services&#13;
and new contracting options to allow retail consumers to enter into hedging contracts&#13;
with power producers in a competitive power system.&#13;
28.    Secondary Petrochemicals. After having temporarily abandoned plans to&#13;
sell secondary petrochemical assets in 1993 the Government has now revived such&#13;
plans. PEMEX has retained an investment banking firm to advise on the sale of all&#13;
secondary petrochemical assets. The current privatization effort is to lead to the sale&#13;
of all assets by the first quarter of 1996. To fully prepare a sound privatization&#13;
strategy a number of analyses have to be prepared. As a first step, market prospects&#13;
for petrochemicals would need to be assessed to help identify how best to package&#13;
plants for privatization and which types of investors to target. Other issues include:&#13;
(i) to what extent PEMEX might remain involved in the production of petrochemicals,&#13;
particularly inputs for secondary plants; (ii) how feedstocks are to be priced; and (iii)&#13;
to what extent there will be free trade in feedstocks.&#13;
29.    The privatization strategy itself would need to be based on an assessment of&#13;
the current state of the assets in Mexico, including operating, safety and security risks&#13;
as well as an assessment of environmental issues. To support the process, the project&#13;
would finance work that would complement that of the current advisors to PEMEX.&#13;
In addition it would finance: (i) environmental assessments, (ii) technical, security and&#13;
operational assessments and (iii) plant inventories.&#13;
Telecommunications&#13;
30.    The second phase of sector reform aims to liberalize the market for basic&#13;
telephone services and stimulate some US$4 billion in new foreign investment by the&#13;
year 2000, chiefly for competitive long distance and local services. Additionally, the&#13;
reforms are intended to generate significant revenue from the sale of radio spectrum&#13;
licenses and the privatization of the satellite business, as well as increasing tax&#13;
revenues from existing and new operators as sector growth accelerates. At the center&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I1&#13;
of this second phase of sector reforms lie four major tasks to be financed under the&#13;
project: (i) opening basic services to competition. The project will finance a review of&#13;
options for introducing competition in basic services. It will also finance the&#13;
preparation of guidelines and international benchmarks for technical and pricing&#13;
aspects of interconnection, with emphasis on facilitating new entry in basic services.&#13;
SCT will also retain consultants to assist in rebalancing TELMEX's tariffs and&#13;
negotiating revisions of the pricing rule under competition. (ii) privatizing the satellite&#13;
business. Under the project, SCT will retain economic consultants as well as&#13;
financial and legal advisers to help prepare the privatization of TELECOMM's&#13;
satellite operations. The economic consultants will help develop a privatization&#13;
strategy as well as maintain a policy and regulatory focus throughout the privatization&#13;
process. Legal and financial advisers will be retained to restructure TELECOMM's&#13;
satellite operations. (iii) auctioning part of the radio spectrum. The Government&#13;
intends to move from the traditional approach of managing the radio spectrum (on a&#13;
first-come first-served basis subject to relatively low flat fees or taxes) to an approach&#13;
more responsive to market forces. The project will finance consultants to help define&#13;
an economic approach to radio spectrum management, establish guidelines for&#13;
implementation, define the scope and modality of spectrum auctions, and oversee&#13;
initial auctions. SCT will also retain advisors to carry out the first auctions for&#13;
personal communication services (PCS). (iv) regulatory function. SCT's regulatory&#13;
capabilities have not kept up with sector development. Moreover, SCT's role as&#13;
policy maker and licensing authority increasingly conflicts with its regulatory&#13;
responsibilities. Under the project, consultants will be retained to help review options&#13;
for divesting SCT's regulatory functions to a new federal agency and related staffing,&#13;
financial, and legal matters; design the organization; outline a staffing and&#13;
development program; and monitor progress during initial implementation.&#13;
Cross Sectoral Activities&#13;
31.    This component consists of activities to strengthen the CID and ensure a&#13;
coordinated approach across sectors. The project will finance a diagnostic review of&#13;
existing legislation and institutional frameworks, past privatization experience and&#13;
sector specific privatizations plans and strategies, as well as consultations with the&#13;
investment community and key interest groups. Additional support would be rendered&#13;
to the CID in establishing and servicing the working groups. As appropriate,&#13;
workshops, seminars and short courses would also be financed. Support for the CID&#13;
would focus on three areas: (i) legal and policy issues arising from the privatization&#13;
process that affect more than one sector; (ii) key regulatory issues including the rules&#13;
governing the award, amendment and revocation of concessions, broader regulatory&#13;
approaches such as application of anti-trust norms in each sector and principles&#13;
governing the design and establishment of autonomous regulatory institutions; (iii) the&#13;
overall business environment for private participation in infrastructure and hence&#13;
affect the longer term sustainability of private capital flows in these sectors, e.g.&#13;
taxation measures and granting and enforcing security interests.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12&#13;
SECTION B: PROJECT ADMINISTRATION AND  IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
32.    Project Organization. The United Mexican States would be the Guarantor&#13;
for the loan made to Nacional Financiera, S.N.C. (NAFIN) a state-owned&#13;
development bank. Execution of the project would be undertaken by CID and the&#13;
working groups in each sector.&#13;
33.    To ensure that the activities financed under the project remain closely tied to&#13;
the evolving priorities for the privatization process, semi-annual reviews would be&#13;
undertaken to update the rolling program of work and evaluate the proposed indicators&#13;
of impact. A project launch seminar is planned as well. During the semi-annual&#13;
reviews, the Bank, the Executing Agency, the Borrower and each working group&#13;
would assess the status of project implementation, evaluate the workplan for the next&#13;
six months and agree on any needed modifications to the originally proposed&#13;
program. Project completion is targeted for December 31, 1998.&#13;
34.    Training Plan. The Technical Secretariat will be responsible for the&#13;
collection of relevant data and information regarding the training courses financed&#13;
through this project. Each working group will provide the Technical Secretariat with&#13;
a yearly training program, derived from the particular privatization strategy for its&#13;
sector. The Technical Secretariat will compile these plans (including its own training&#13;
needs), which will be evaluated at the time of the semi-annual review with the Bank.&#13;
While the training plan will be based on strategic objectives, the data required will&#13;
include: (i) historical information on training taken (or committed) to date; and (ii)&#13;
current year's plan, with title and budget for each course, number of participants to&#13;
be financed, name of individual or institution responsible for training, time and&#13;
location of training.&#13;
35.    Project Costs and Financing. Estimated total project costs are US$46.0&#13;
million. (Schedule A) They include: (i) cross sectoral support, US$6.0 million (13%&#13;
of total); power and secondary petrochemicals, US$15.25 million (33%); transport&#13;
sector, US$14.35 million (31 %); and telecommunications, US$7.7 million (17%); and&#13;
price contingencies, US$ 2.7 million (6%). The Bank would provide US$30 million,&#13;
the Government the remaining US$16 million.&#13;
36.    A fixed rate US dollars single currency loan is proposed in accordance with&#13;
the Government's request. The loan would have a repayment period of up to 15&#13;
years; and each semester's disbursements would have a maturity of 12 years from the&#13;
rate fixing date, including 3 years grace. The Government of Mexico is eligible for&#13;
single currency loans. The proposed US$30 million represents 3 percent of the FY96&#13;
lending program for Mexico (US$920 million).&#13;
37.    Procurement. Two types of procurement would be undertaken through the&#13;
loan: (i) consultant services; and (ii) goods, primarily computer hardware and&#13;
software. As financial agent, NAFIN would act as the coordinator and adviser to the&#13;
CID for all procurement activities under the loan. Selection and appointment of&#13;
consultants for studies, technical assistance and support of project execution would be&#13;
carried out in accordance with the Bank's "Guidelines: Use of Consultants by the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13&#13;
World Bank Borrowers and by the World Bank as Executing Agency (August 1981).&#13;
All contracts with lawyers or law firms will follow specific Bank guidelines for their&#13;
selection and appointment. Procurement of goods would follow the Bank Guidelines&#13;
for Procurement (January 1995). To the extent feasible and practical, the&#13;
procurement of goods would be done by grouping the various items in bid packages&#13;
estimated to cost US$350,000 equivalent or more. Packages in this category would be&#13;
required to follow International Competitive Bidding (ICB) procedures using the Bank&#13;
Standard Bidding Documents. National Competitive Bidding (NCB) would be&#13;
undertaken for goods estimated to cost more than US$150,000 but less than&#13;
US$350,000 using standardized bidding documents to be agreed upon with the Bank.&#13;
For equipment that cannot be grouped in packages valued at US$100,000 or more,&#13;
international and national shopping procedures would be followed by comparing price&#13;
quotations received from at least three suppliers.&#13;
38.    Bank review of procurement procedures would be as follows: (i) for&#13;
consulting services, the Bank would conduct prior review for all contracts exceeding&#13;
US$50,000 equivalent for individuals and US$100,000 equivalent for firms; and for&#13;
procurement of goods the Bank would review ex ante documentation pertaining to&#13;
each ICB and the first two NCBs; (iii) all other procurement documentation would be&#13;
subject to ex post review. This review process would result in a prior review of&#13;
approximately 75 percent of all Bank financed contracts for goods and 90 percent of&#13;
all Bank financed contracts for consulting services, both expressed in value.&#13;
39.    Disbursements. Proceeds of the loan would finance: (i) 100 percent of the&#13;
cost of foreign goods, consulting services, training and technical assistance; and (ii)&#13;
90 percent of the cost of local goods. The proceeds of the loan are expected to be&#13;
disbursed in accordance with the categories shown in Schedule B of the Memorandum&#13;
of the President. To expedite project execution, a special account in U.S. dollars&#13;
would be established at the Banco de Mexico, with an authorized allocation of US$2&#13;
million equivalent, representing the average amount equivalent to four months of&#13;
eligible expenditures that are expected to be paid from the account. Separate accounts&#13;
of all expenditures by the project would be maintained by the Borrower. Withdrawal&#13;
applications would be fully documented, except for contracts smaller than the&#13;
following specified levels: US$350,000 for goods; US$50,000 for individual&#13;
consultants; and US$100,000 for consulting firms. In the case of contracts below&#13;
these specified levels, NAFIN would prepare certified Statements of Expenditure&#13;
(SOE) to be used as the basis for disbursement. Supporting documentation for SOEs&#13;
would be retained by NAFIN and made available for examination by Bank staff&#13;
during supervision missions.&#13;
40.    Retroactive financing of up to US$3 million would be provided for eligible&#13;
expenditures incurred after April 1, 1995. Such financing is necessary to put in place&#13;
the institutional structure required to carry out the project and avoid delays in the first&#13;
year of project implementation. The project completion date would be December 31,&#13;
1998 and the closing date would be June 30, 1999.&#13;
41.    Accounts and Audits. NAFIN and the Executing Agency would maintain&#13;
adequate records to reflect all expenditures made under the project in accordance with&#13;
sound accounting practices. The accounts and statements of expenditures would be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14&#13;
audited each year by auditors satisfactory to the Bank, in accordance with appropriate&#13;
auditing principles consistently applied. The audit report would be submitted to the&#13;
Bank not later than six months following the close of the fiscal year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15&#13;
ATTACHMENT: PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN: CID&#13;
Matrix of Objectives, Activities, Timing and Costs&#13;
TIMING&#13;
OBJECTIVES                                          ACTIVITIES                                   OUTPUT                         FORMS OF&#13;
ASSISTANCE&#13;
Start I  Finish&#13;
A. CROSS-SECTORAL PRIVATIZATION FRAMEWORK: This sub-component will focus on key cross-sectoral issues raised by the proposed privatization transactions themselves. Examples of issues&#13;
that may be addressed under this sub-component include: (i) treatment of debt, environmental and other liabilities of enterprises; (ii) labor and tax issues; (iii) contracting approaches, including issues offorce&#13;
majeure, alternative dispute resolution procedures etc; (iii) strategic sequencing of programs etc.&#13;
Cost: US $2.5mm&#13;
1. Identification of legal and polcy issues raised by  Support to CI in establishing and servicing cross-   Diagnostic study                 Consultants/Legal advisors   05/95      12/95&#13;
privatization transactions in more than one sector which:   sectoral working groups&#13;
(i) raise important questions of policy coherence, (ii)&#13;
offer net benefits from adopting consistent approaches  Review existing and proposed legislative and&#13;
across sectors, or (tii) offer significant efficiency benefits  institutional frameworks, past-privatization                                 Seminars/Workshops&#13;
from dealig with issues centrally rather than on a sector   experience and sector-specific privatization plans&#13;
by sector basis                                       and strategies.&#13;
Consultations with investor community and other  Consultations&#13;
key interest groups.&#13;
2. Definition of strategy for elaborating a cross-sectoral    Support CID in working with cross-sectoral  Proposed implementation strategy,  Consultants/Legal advisors   08/95      12/95&#13;
privatization framework that deals effectively with  working groups and other interests.             including, as appropriate, cross-&#13;
issues identified in phase 1.                                                                        sectoral coordination mechanism and&#13;
Develop detailed recommendations on legal and    draft list of maters to be subject to&#13;
institutional responses to cross-sectoral issues  cross-sectoral policies, legislation or&#13;
regulation.&#13;
Seminars/Workshops&#13;
3. Effective implementation of cross-sectoral         Support CID by providing general legal counsel   Draft policies, legislation or       Consultants/Legal advisors   10/95      End of&#13;
privatization framework                            and in working with cross-sectoral working groups   regulations dealing with cross-sectoral                                    process&#13;
issues.&#13;
Liaise with sector working groups to promote     Dissemination products (eg, booklets,   Seminars/Workshops       10/95       06/96&#13;
effective cross-fertilization, communication and  pamphlets etc).&#13;
coordination&#13;
Draft policies, legislation and regulations&#13;
4. Evaluation of privatization process, including     Record analysis, surveys, econometric studies.   Final report(s).                     External consultants        06/96       One year&#13;
economic and social impacts                                                                                                                                                      after end&#13;
Seminars                               of&#13;
process&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN: CED&#13;
Matrix of Objectives, Activides, lming and Costs&#13;
OBJECTPIES                     I                 ACTIVITIES                                OUTPUT               F3ORNMS OF ASSISTANCE I              TIMNG&#13;
I                      I                                                      I                            I   Stant zI&#13;
B. CROSS-SECTORAL REGULATORY FRAMEWORK: This sub-cmponent winl focas on key ross-sectoral regulatory issues: it, those defining the longer-term relationship between investors,&#13;
consumers and the State. Examples of issues that may be addressed under this sub-component include: (Q) rules governing the award, amendment and revocation of concessions; (ii) broader regulatory&#13;
approaches, such as the rote of the Competition Commission in each sector, and (iii) principles governing the design and establishment of autonomous regulatory institutions.&#13;
Cst: US S2.Smm&#13;
1. Idlfdcation of polcy, legal and intbuional issues   Support to CID in establihing and servicing c-  Diagnostic study          Consultants/Legal advisors   05195         1V95&#13;
raised by the elaboration of regulatory frameworks    secoral workig groups&#13;
in more than ot ecor which: () raise important&#13;
queios of polic cohre, () offer net benefits   Review existing and proposed legislative and                                    Seninars/Workshops&#13;
from adop6ng ce _m ap   ccs   ectors,   instiiona framework, past privatization and&#13;
or (iii) offer sigifiat efficiency benefits from  regulatory experience and sector-specific&#13;
dealing with isue ceirlly rather than on a sector    privatization plans and regulatory strategies.&#13;
by ector bass&#13;
Consultations with investor community and oWher&#13;
key interest groups.&#13;
2. Definition of tategy for elaborating a cross-  Devdop detailed recommendations on legal nd     Proposed implementation        Consultants/Legal advisors   0S/95        06/96&#13;
ecal regulatory framework that deals effectively   institutional response to crosaecctoral regulatory    Strategy, including, as&#13;
with is   s idanified in phase 1.               framework issues                                appropriate, cros-aectoral&#13;
coordination mechanism and&#13;
draft list of regulatory matters&#13;
to be subject to croasedoral    Seminars/Workshops&#13;
policies, legislation or&#13;
regulation&#13;
3. Impleatation of cross-sectors regulatory       Support CID m working with crss-sectoral        Draft policies, legislation,   Consultants/Legal advisors   01/96        End of&#13;
frmavork                                        working groups. Liaise with sector working      regulations, organizational                                              process&#13;
groups to promote effective cros-fertilization,  arrangements etc deling with&#13;
commaunication and coordination                cross-sectoral regulatory issues&#13;
Draft poliaes, legishtion, regulations,                                       Seminars/Workshops&#13;
organztional arrangements etc&#13;
4. Dcvdopment of reglatory institutions           Formulate and implement a cross-wectord program    Outputs might include: )    Consultants/Legal advisors   01/96        Endof&#13;
to support the devdopment of institutional capacity    Training programs and                                            process&#13;
by regultors.                                  material; and (ii) Support to  Seminars/Workshops&#13;
developnment of research&#13;
As appropriate, coordinate assistance to regulatory   institute/program for regulators   Training programs &amp;&#13;
agencies.                                                                     materials&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN: CID&#13;
Matzix of Objecives, Activities, Timing and Costs&#13;
TEMING&#13;
OBJECTIVES                                        ACTIVITIES                                    OUTPUT                         FORMS OF&#13;
ASSISTANCE&#13;
start  I &#13;
C. GENERAL BUSINESS ENVIRONMENT FOR PRIVATE PARTICIPATION IN INFRASTRUCTURE (PPI) This sub-component will focus on legal, regulatory and institutional constraints to effective&#13;
private participation in infrastructure (PPI) that are not addressed by sub-components A and B. Given the potential breadth of this work, the focus will be on the key constraints that have a signflcant impact on&#13;
the PPI business environment. Examples of issues that may be addressed under this sub-component include approaches to granting permits; alternative dispute resolution processes; financing issues, including&#13;
the granting and enforcng of security interests; environmental aspects; transparency of legal system; and taxation.&#13;
Cose. US S1.Omm&#13;
1. Identification of key legal, institutional and  Support to C1D in establishing cross-aectoral  Diagnostic study indicating nature and   Consultants/Legal         05/95      12/95&#13;
regulatory constaints in the general business   working groups                                  relative significance of key constraints.  advisors&#13;
enviriomen that are not covered by A &amp; B (above)&#13;
but have a ignificant impact on efficient private  Review existing and proposed legislative and&#13;
participation in infradructure (PPI).           institutional frameworks and sector-spedfic                                              Seminars/Vorkshops&#13;
development objectives and privatization plans.&#13;
Consultations with investor community and other&#13;
key interest groups.&#13;
2. Definition of strategy for improving the general  Support CID in working with crosa-sectoral   Proposed implementation strategy,        Consultants/Legal        08/95      06/96&#13;
buins environment for PPL                      working groups.                                 including, as appropriate,               advisors&#13;
coordination/consultationmechanisms and&#13;
Develop detailed recommendations on legal,     draft list of matters to be subject to&#13;
institutiona and institutional responses to issues  priority reform.&#13;
identified in phase I                                                                   Seminars/Workshops&#13;
3. Implementation of strategy for improving the   As required, work with CID and other key entities    Draft policies, legislation or regulations  Consultants/Legal  I10/9      End of&#13;
genaal business environment for Pm.             in drafting policies, legislation and regulations  dealing with cross-sectoral issues.  advisors                             process&#13;
4. Promotion and dissemination of investment      Recompilation of relevant laws and regulations  Brochures, booklets, videos.             Road shows                08/95      12J96&#13;
opportunities&#13;
Presentations to financial intermediaries, consulting   Inventory of investment opportunities and    Seminars&#13;
firms and investment community                 appropriate databases.&#13;
Workshops&#13;
Liaise with Mexican Investment Board&#13;
TOTAL FOR SUB-COMPONENTS A-C                                                                                                                                                  $6. 0mm&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPIMiENTAlION PLAN: ElECTRICrTY AND SECONDARY PEITROCHEMICALS&#13;
Matrix of Objectives, Actiities, Thing and Costs&#13;
OBJECTIVES                     |                    AClIVrITES                        J                  OUP1UT                      |  FORMS OF ASSISTANCE  |&#13;
_ _ _ _ _ _ _   _ _ _   _     _      _     _     _    J                                                 j                                 ~~~~~ ~        ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Start  Finish&#13;
A. ELEC1RICrrY SECTOR: ThLis sub-comoetllsupport the review of key stategic options, sector restrcturing and preparation of privatization.&#13;
Cot US $12.25m&#13;
1. Identify appropriate policy framework for      Evauate amative suttural, ownership and market         Sector diagnostic.                             Local consultints.             05/95      12/95&#13;
private sector participation in the            coordmation options for introducmg competition mto the&#13;
electricity sector.                            electricity sector.                                    Sector restructuring sategy.                   External consultuats.&#13;
05/95      12/95&#13;
Identify regulatory and polcy/planning functions and                                                  ExLernal reviewers.&#13;
swttures commensurate with restructuring options.&#13;
|2. Define stategy for implementing revised policy  Analyze electricity pricig poliies                  Tariff polcy ad subsidy criteria.               External consultants           10/95      03/96&#13;
framework for the electricity sector.&#13;
Assess options and make recommendationa for grouping    Sector re=icturing strategy.                  Study tours                   07/95       06/96&#13;
upfaing Imits.&#13;
Inventory of assets                                                                                   External advisors&#13;
Review divestiture options and scquencing.            Privatization strategy, auction schemes and plmn  Seminars                    08/95       06/96&#13;
of action.&#13;
Evaluate options for ensng efficient fuel supply.                                                                                   10/95       03/96&#13;
Draft fuel supply contracts/agreements&#13;
Specify regulatory and institutional arrangements&#13;
Action plsa for implementing regulatory and                                   02/96      03/96&#13;
Identify ekmlems of publc relations strategy.         instiul modifications as needed.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3- Prepare strucijug and privatiation           Fmae legl/re  story    oriL                          Draft regulations.                            External consuants            06/95      1296&#13;
Estabish opeating entities.                         Prepare entities to point of divesure         Study tours                   01/96      09/96&#13;
Desgn qsyem  openticn/coordinationprocedures and                                                                                01/96      12/96&#13;
initiate  stial aragemcma.                                                                        Extermal advisors&#13;
Reommend apropriae tariff polices and wrvice                                                                                    01/96      12/96&#13;
staidards for distrbution, tmxsion (and genention                                                 Tnranng (regulation, systems&#13;
during t      ndtio pes                                                                           operations, setdement&#13;
systems)&#13;
Caduct mnat and mveannen prfecaabiIy stdies.                                                                                    01/96      12/96&#13;
Priorite existhg fwiliaew capacity to be offered to    PrivatiuAtion strategy.                                                  01/96      12/96&#13;
private investors.&#13;
Draft model cntracts for tr_inson services.                                                                                    01/96      12/96&#13;
Undertake saes promotion.                           InformAonMemorandsnn                                                        12/96      06/97&#13;
Prepa  bidding documents.                             une biddig documents.                                                     01/96      12/97&#13;
4. hwns     latetung                            Suportpolicy nd regulatoty insttin                                                                 Extemal consultnts            1          10/98&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROWECT IMELUITATION PLAN: XClRUCITY AND SICCONDARY FETROCUEWICALS&#13;
Nd  of &lt;Oedma, Ahid., IThg   i Cub&#13;
OBJECTIVES                                  ACTIVITIES                                    OUTPUT                      FORMS OF ASSISTANCE&#13;
I                                                                                       I                            I     Start       Fsidh&#13;
B: SECONDARY PETROCEM CAIS: Asidance would fous on support to prepare for privatization.&#13;
Cost US S3.0mm&#13;
1. Define privatization options and aess   Inventory of asses                                                                         ernal consultants         05/95         12/95&#13;
inveaet climate.&#13;
Speify grouping of auets and rnles of accs    Privatization strategy&#13;
and pricing of common use facilities&#13;
Specify feedstock supply arrangements       Draft feedstock supply contracts&#13;
Design auction/bidding pzocedures           Aucdion strategy&#13;
Prepare environmental assement&#13;
2. Prepa  privatiztion                     Sales promotion                             Information Memorandum                      External consultants         10/9S         06196&#13;
Prepae bidding do en-ts                    Ise bidding documents.&#13;
TOTAL FOR SUB CO (ONENTS A-B:                                                                                                                                            US S15.25mm&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLENENTATION PLAN: TELECOMMUNICAnONS&#13;
Mhbix of Objedvl, Ad tbsu T g g d COds&#13;
OBJECTIVES                                 ACTivnIES                               OUTPUT                        FORMS OF                          TINMNG&#13;
ASSISTANCE&#13;
sun       |      Fibb&#13;
A: BASIC TELEPHONE SERVICES: This sb-component will addres specific issues related to deregulation of local/long distance services.&#13;
Cost: US S2.5mm&#13;
1. Economic analysis of sector structure     Assess pricing, new entry, and social    Sector diagnostic report          Extemal consultants         7/95              6/96&#13;
obligations&#13;
2. Numbering and other technical plans       Design implementation of numbering,      Implementation of numbering,      External consultants         7/95              4/96&#13;
signalling, billing, routing and         signalling, billing, routing and&#13;
synchronization                          synchronization&#13;
3. Support for legal and regulatory framewori   Draft rtviews and comments                                              External consultants        07/95             4/96&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN: TELECOMMUNICATIONS&#13;
Mautix of Objectives, Activities, Timing and Costs&#13;
OBJECTIVES                                      ACTIVITIES                               OUTPUT                j        FORMS OF                  TIMING&#13;
ASSISTANCE&#13;
B: SATELLITES: Preparatory work has been undertaken. This sub-component will assist with preparing the privatization of the satellites.&#13;
COst US S1.0mm&#13;
1. Idedify appropriate policy framework and        Prepare recommendations for sector structure    Sector diagnostic               External consultants       05/95       02/96&#13;
istitutional arrangements&#13;
Prepare privatization option               Privatization strategy              Study tours&#13;
Prepare regulatory framework                                                   Seminars&#13;
2. Prepare privatization                            Inventory of assets                       Information Memorandum               External consultants       09/95        12/96&#13;
Sales promotion                                                                External reviews&#13;
Issue bidding documents            Investment Bank&#13;
Prepare bidding documents&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN:&#13;
Matrix of Objectives, Activitis, Timing and CO0ts&#13;
OBJECTIVES                                     ACTIVITIES                              OUTPUT                   FORMS OF ASSISTANCE&#13;
TIMING&#13;
Start       Finish&#13;
C: RADIO SPECTRUM: This sub-component will focus on the sector tucture and the design and implementation of the auction process.&#13;
Cost: US S3.0mm&#13;
1. Review of spectrum issues                     Economic analysis of spectrm management    Sector diagnostic                 External consultants             05/95        4/96&#13;
2. Formulation of auction strategy               Feasibility of auction of spectrum for new  Auction strategy including       External consultants             08/95        6/96&#13;
services                                   frequency planning&#13;
Establish auction rules&#13;
Define auction process&#13;
3. Prepare privatization                         Auction software and management            Information Memorandum            External consultants             08/95       03/97&#13;
Prepare bidding documents                  Issue bidding documents           External reviews&#13;
4. Investment promotion support                 Promote opportunities to potential investors  Maximize auction results        Investment bankers               07/95       06/96&#13;
5. Legal and regulatory support                  Draft reviews and comments                                                   External consultants             07/95       06/96&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLENENTATION PLAN: TELECOMMUNICATION&#13;
Matrix of Objecives, Adies, Tim  ad Cast&#13;
OBJECTIVES                  J               ACTIVITEES                                OUTPUT                         FORMS OF ASSISTANCE                        TIMING&#13;
D. REGULATORY STRENGTHENING: This sub-component will support the redesign and strengthening of a regulatory entity.&#13;
CosLd US S1.2mm&#13;
1. Strengthen regulatory and institutional   Analysis of existing institutions         Establishment of new regulatory       External Consultants                    10/95      03/97&#13;
development                                                                         entity&#13;
Create regulatory entity                                                        Short courses&#13;
Training                                                 .                      Seminars&#13;
TOTAL FOR SUB-COMPONENTS A-D:                                                                                                                                                US 7.7m&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN: TRANSPORT&#13;
Matix of Objectives, Activities, Timing and Costs&#13;
I                                                      ~~~~~~~~~~~~~TEIUNG&#13;
OBJECTIVES                                  ACTIVITIES                          OUTPUT                 FORMS OF ASSISTANCE&#13;
str       Finish&#13;
A: PORTS: This sub-component would support the privatization process that has been inhtiated.&#13;
Cost US S2.5m&#13;
1. Preparation of privatization and melated     Prepare APIs, terminals and other                                    External consultants            05/95           6/97&#13;
rgulatory framvwork                             faclities for privatization&#13;
Exteral reviews&#13;
Design regulatory framework (where&#13;
appropriate)                                                         Seminars&#13;
Regulatory framework&#13;
Prepa bidding documents&#13;
Information Memorandum&#13;
Bidding documents&#13;
2. Invedment promotion support                  Promote oppotunities to potential     Maximize auction results       Investment bankers              05/95           06/97&#13;
investo&#13;
3. Intionl Skengtening                          Support for pott planning and                                        Extenal consultants             10/95           12/97&#13;
supervison/adaptation of concessions (as&#13;
neceau7y)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN: TRANSPORT&#13;
Matrix of Objectives, Activities, Timing and Coets&#13;
TIMING&#13;
OBJECTIVES                                        ACTIVITIES                           OUTPUT                  FORMS OF&#13;
ASSISTANCE                               Finis&#13;
B: RAILWAYS: This sub-component would support the formulation of a privatization strategy and regulatory framework.&#13;
Cose US $6.5mm&#13;
1. Formulation of privatization strategy and     Review of market structure proposals for         Privatization strategy  External local consultants   04/95       12/95&#13;
regulatory framework                             privatization&#13;
Semiinars&#13;
Review alternatives for trackage and haulage rights                                               06/95          12/95&#13;
for each concession                                                     Study tours&#13;
Define passenger/freight service for social reasons                                              08/95           02/96&#13;
Design regulatory framework                      Regulatory framework                             05/95          03/96&#13;
2. Prepare privatization                         Prepare privatization plan                       Information            External consultants      07/95           12/95&#13;
Memorandum&#13;
FNM regionalization plan                                                                          07/95          09/95&#13;
Inventory of assets.                                                                              07/95          09/95&#13;
hinvestment banikers&#13;
Resettlement and environmental assessment                                                         07/95          12/95&#13;
Design auction/bidding procedures                Auction strategy                                 06/95          03/96&#13;
Sales promotion                                                                                   07/95          02/96&#13;
Issue bidding&#13;
Retraining proposals                             documents                                        11/95          03/96&#13;
3. Regulatory Strengthening                      Support regulatory institutions and process                             External consultants      10/95           12/97&#13;
12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROJECT EMPl4MfENTAT[ON PLAN: TRANSPORT&#13;
Matrix of Objectives, Actiitlies, Tbning and Costs&#13;
4ThllNG&#13;
OBJECThES                                             ACTIVIrEES                              OUIPtrl                FORMS OF ASSISTANCE&#13;
Start      |       flni6h&#13;
C: AERPORTS: This comiponent would emphasize the review of strategic options, preparation of a straegy, and dte regulatory fumntion.&#13;
Cost: US 5.35mm&#13;
1. Review of sector structure                               Disaggregation of ASA accounts by airport     Sector duignostic               External consultants          07/95               06/96&#13;
Review sources and uses of airport revenues                                                                10/95               06/96&#13;
Financial and economic assessment of airports                                                              11/95               06/96&#13;
Strategy for airport needs for Mexico City                                                                 11/95               12/96&#13;
ICAO review of safety standards at all passenger&#13;
airpons                                                                                                    8/95                06/96&#13;
2. Formulation of privatzation strategy                     Prepare concessioning plan                    Privatiation plan               External consultants          09/95               09/96&#13;
Detailed concessioning plan each airport&#13;
3. Prepare privaioatou                                      Inventory of assets                                                           Extemal consultants           07/95               06/96&#13;
Concesion design                                                             Investment bankers            06/96               12/96&#13;
Prepare bidding documents                    Issue Bidding Documents                                       06/96               06/97&#13;
Sales promotion&#13;
4. Regultory stngSthening                                   Design regulatory framework                   Regulatory framework and        External consultants          12/96               12/97&#13;
institntions&#13;
Seminar&#13;
Traning of staff in regulatory function.                                     Short courses&#13;
SUB TOTAL FOR SUB-COMPONENTS A-C:                                                                                                                                                           US $14.35mm&#13;
13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="697105">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/08/697105/mexico-infrastructure-privatization-technical-assistance-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/08/697105/mexico-infrastructure-privatization-technical-assistance-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/08/697105/mexico-infrastructure-privatization-technical-assistance-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1995/08/02/000009265_3961008053108/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1995/08/02/000009265_3961008053108/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>3937</loan_no>
        <docdt>1995-08-02T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2001-04-20T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Mexico - Infrastructure Privatization
            Technical Assistance Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Infrastructure Privatization
            Technical Assistance Project aims to: 1) help Government
            choose structural options for sector reform; 2) develop a
            sound legal and regulatory framework in support of
            privatization; 3) reduce, and if possible, eliminate
            constraints to privatization in sectors covered by the loan;
            and 4) provide support to the privatization preparation
            process. Project activities will include: 1) hiring
            consultants to assist in the analysis of sector structure,
            the development of strategic options, policies and
            regulations; 2) hiring consultants to design and participate
            in the privatization process; 3) financing participation in
            training programs and other human resource development
            activities; and 4) procurement of necessary software,
            hardware and related equipment.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Mexico - Infrastructure Privatization
            Technical Assistance Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Mexico - Infrastructure
            Privatization Technical Assistance Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1995/08/697105/mexico-infrastructure-privatization-technical-assistance-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>MX-Infra. Privatztn Ta -- P040685</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Municipal Financial Management,ICT Policy and Strategies,Public Sector Economics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Mexico</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>North America!$!80465</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3961008053108</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <subsc>Telecommunications,Power,Petrochemicals and fertilizers,General transportation sector,Central government administration</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Denationalization; Equipment; Human
            resources development; Infrastructure; Materials; Procurement
            accounting,accounting
            practices,Airports,assets,auctions,auditing,auditors,Audits,autonomy,balance
            of payments,balance sheet,Bank for International
            Settlements,banks,capital flows,capital
            markets,communication services,Competitive
            Bidding,competitive forces,competitive markets,computer
            hardware,consulting services,cost of
            capital,creditworthiness,debt,Electricity,environmental
            issues,equilibrium,exchange rate,expenditures,fiscal
            year,foreign exchange,foreign exchange
            reserves,fuels,Government guarantees,Industrial
            Development,insurance,interest
            rates,inventories,inventory,investment
            banking,laws,legislation,licenses,local
            authorities,management,maturity,now accounts,offtake
            agreements,operations,payphones,penalties,policy
            makers,power plants,private concessionaires,private
            sector,private sector
            participation,Privatization,producers,productivity,productivity
            growth,programs,public companies,public finance,public
            information,public procurement,radio,regulatory
            approaches,regulatory framework,regulatory
            systems,roads,rural communities,satellites,state owned
            enterprises,tax,tax revenues,taxation,Technical
            Assistance,telecommunications,telecommunications
            deregulation,telecommunications
            operations,telecommunications sector,telephone
            density,telephone services,training courses,Transport,treasury
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sector Cluster (LCSFR)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>North America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T6590</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Measures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental and Social Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Environmental and Social Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports and Air Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aviation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>APIs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems Technologies and Operations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Thermal Power Generation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal and Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Policy and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental and Social Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Air Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Application Programming Interfaces</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Mexico</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>