<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
Tlhe World Bank&#13;
FOR OFFICLIL USE ONLY&#13;
Reprt No. T-6377-AZ&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
AZERBAIJAN&#13;
PETROLEUM TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
MARCH 28, 1995&#13;
This document has a restricted distribution and may be used by recipients only in the performance of&#13;
their official duties. Its contents may not otherwise be disclosed without World Bank authorization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Currency Unit      =     Manat&#13;
US$1               =     4,300 Manats&#13;
MEASURES AND EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Metric System&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
bcm          =     billion cubic meters&#13;
CEM          =     Country Economic Memorandum&#13;
CIS          =     Confederation of Independent States&#13;
CPAR         =     Country Procurement Assessment Review&#13;
EU           =     European Union&#13;
FSU          =     Former Soviet Union&#13;
GoA          =     Government of Azerbaijan&#13;
ICB          =     International Competitive Bidding&#13;
IS           -     International Shopping&#13;
LPG          =     liquid petroleum gas&#13;
MOF          =     Ministry of Finance&#13;
mcm          =     thousand cubic meters&#13;
MIS          =     management information system&#13;
mt           =     million tons&#13;
PC           =     personal computer&#13;
PIU          =     Project Implementation Unit&#13;
PPF          =     Project Preparation Facility&#13;
SOCAR        =     State Oil Company of Azerbaijan Republic&#13;
SOE          =     statement of expenses&#13;
TA           =     technical assistance&#13;
TOR          =     terms of reference&#13;
toe          =     tons of oil equivalent&#13;
UNDP         =     United Nations Development Program&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January 1 - December 31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
AZERBAIJAN&#13;
PETROLEUM TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.  Country and Sector Background                ............................... 1&#13;
A. Marcoeconomic Developments and Country Background ..............1&#13;
B.  The Petroleum  Sub-sector  ................................1&#13;
II. The Project .......................5&#13;
A. Project Objectives and Structure  ............................5&#13;
B.  Project Description  .5.............  ...  ...  ..  ...  ...  ..  ...  .               .   5&#13;
C. Legal Aspects   ..........  .           ..  .  .  ..  .  ..  .  ..  .  .  ..  .  ..  .  .  ..  .  .     .   12&#13;
D. Project Costs, Financing, Procurement and Disbursements  ..... .               .  .  .     .   13&#13;
E. Project Management and Reporting   .......  .             .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .     .   15&#13;
F. Supervision Arrangements  ........  .            .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .     .   17&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
1   Lending Arrangements, Legal Documents and Flow of Funds  ..... .                .  .  .  .     .   19&#13;
2 Cost Estimate .20&#13;
3 Procurement Plan and Schedule .22&#13;
4  Key Project Activities and Implementation Schedule .24&#13;
5 Supervision Plan .26&#13;
6 Disbursement Schedule .27&#13;
7 Project Performance Indicators .28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
AZERBAIJAN&#13;
PETROLEUM TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
I. COUNTRY AND SECTOR BACKGROUND&#13;
A. Macroeconomic Developments and Country Background&#13;
1.          Azerbaijan lies on the southeastern flanks of the Caucasus mountains, bounded&#13;
on the East by the Caspian Sea. It is one of the smallest countries of the Former Soviet Union&#13;
(FSU), covering an area of 86,000 square kilometers, similar to Austria. Over half of its 7.2&#13;
million population is urbanized; the capital, Baku, has about two million inhabitants and is a&#13;
major harbor on the Caspian Sea. The country is endowed with fertile agricultural land, and&#13;
ample natural resources, particularly oil and natural gas. It also has a diversified industrial&#13;
structure and a relatively well educated labor force.&#13;
2.          Azerbaijan amended its constitution to legitimize its independence in August 1991.&#13;
It is a member of the Confederation of Independent States (CIS). The country's economy has&#13;
continued to be very closely tied to that of the rest of the FSU, given the deeply entrenched&#13;
economic interdependence established within the Soviet Union. Azerbaijan's industry is&#13;
dependent upon the FSU market for both inputs and final sales, and disruptions to trade and&#13;
payments within the FSU have contributed to sharp declines in industrial activity. The economy&#13;
has also been adversely affected by the conflict over Nagorno-Karabakh, which has led to an&#13;
increase in public expenditure for defence and to the migration of about one million refugees&#13;
from the areas affected by the conflict.&#13;
3.          As in other countries of the FSU, Azerbaijan's economy underwent a particularly&#13;
sharp contraction during 1992, following three years of smaller declines, with a rapid&#13;
acceleration of inflation. These trends continued into 1993 and early 1994. Gross Domestic&#13;
Product (GDP) in 1993 was only about 60% of its 1988 level. The worsening economic&#13;
situation in 1993 was also marked by a serious deterioration in both the fiscal and external&#13;
balances. In general, the pace of systemic reform and privatization has been relatively slow.&#13;
However, the Government is committed to moving to a market economy, and has been&#13;
conducting discussions with the IMF and World Bank on a comprehensive economic reform&#13;
program. Notwithstanding a relatively slow process of privatization, Azerbaijan has a buoyant&#13;
private sector.&#13;
B. The Petroleum Sub-sector&#13;
4.          The Need for Restructuring. Petroleum has historically played a key role in&#13;
shaping Azerbaijan's economy, and will continue to do so in future. Azerbaijan is one of the&#13;
oldest oil producing regions in the world, and supplied most of the requirements of the Soviet&#13;
Union until World War II. After World War II, Azerbaijan was eclipsed by new oil producing&#13;
regions in Russia, and investment in the country lagged behind other regions. Oil production fell&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
from 20 million tons (mt) in 1970, to 10 mt in 1993, just 2% of FSU production, and net&#13;
exports fell from 8 mt in 1981 to 1.5 mt in 1993. Most importantly, the Soviet industry failed&#13;
to exploit the large resources in the Caspian Sea efficiently, due to shortcomings in technology&#13;
and insufficient investment funds. As a result, undeveloped reserves in discovered fields offshore&#13;
total some 650 mt, while even larger reserves may exist in unexplored structures. The potential&#13;
production from these deposits holds the key to the development of Azerbaijan's energy sector&#13;
and of its economy.&#13;
5.           Oil production in the older oil fields has been declining for many years. The&#13;
largest mature offshore field, Oil Rocks, sustains a sizeable infrastructure and manpower base&#13;
on very little production, and is probably no longer economic to operate. It is likely that a large&#13;
proportion of the onshore producing wells are uneconomic at international costs and prices, and&#13;
should be shut down. There is substantial environmental pollution from the oil fields, through&#13;
oil spills and inappropriate disposal of formation water. A policy for dealing with the older oil&#13;
fields is urgently needed; this should incorporate strategies for dealing with the social and&#13;
employment consequences of restructuring, with the environmental issues and with the need to&#13;
attract foreign investment to exploit the substantial remaining reserves.&#13;
6.           Total oil production has been sustained by development of the large offshore&#13;
Guneshli field, found in 1979, which now accounts for 60% of national oil output. Yet this field&#13;
has been developed in a sub-optimal manner, using obsolete technology. Reservoir management&#13;
and production practices have been poor, and the field is entering a premature decline. The fall&#13;
in production from Guneshli, which amounted to 9% in the year to September 1994, is having&#13;
a serious effect on Azerbaijan's oil export revenues.&#13;
7.           While oil has been a key export item for Azerbaijan, natural gas has been the&#13;
main fuel for domestic use, and gas normally accounts for 60% of primary energy use. Gas&#13;
production has fallen along with oil production, from 14 billion cubic meters (bcm) in 1980, to&#13;
8 bcm in 1993. Insufficient attention has been given to system maintenance and utilization of gas&#13;
reserves; gas usage is thus extremely wasteful, due to inadequate processing, large losses in the&#13;
pipeline system, a lack of customer metering and inefficient gas-using equipment. As a result,&#13;
Azerbaijan has become a large net importer of natural gas, mostly from Turkmenistan, and the&#13;
country is thus only 90% self sufficient in energy, despite its large oil exports. The cost of gas&#13;
imports to Azerbaijan is rising rapidly as Turkmenistan attempts to raise gas prices to world&#13;
levels; at world prices gas imports could cost Azerbaijan about US$600 million per year, or 35 %&#13;
of total import costs. Inefficient gas and oil use makes Azerbaijan one of the least efficient of&#13;
the FSU countries in terms of energy usage, and energy consumption per unit of GDP is 20%&#13;
above that in Russia.&#13;
8.           Most oil exports from Azerbaijan have been in the form of oil products, processed&#13;
in the two large refineries located near Baku. The capacity of these refineries, at 20 mt per year,&#13;
has exceeded Azerbaijan's diminished oil production for many years, and the spare capacity was&#13;
used to process imported crude oil from Russia and Kazakhstan. This inward processing was&#13;
probably uneconomic and has largely ceased as prices in FSU oil trade have moved to world&#13;
levels. Moreover, the facilities at these refineries are old and lacking in upgrading capacity. The&#13;
continued viability of much of the current capacity within a market pricing environment must&#13;
be in question.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
9.          Azerbaijan's long history of oil production helped to make it the major center of&#13;
petroleum equipment manufacturing in the FSU. The industry supplied 65% of FSU&#13;
requirements of most types of production equipment. Since the break up of the Soviet Union,&#13;
the industry has suffered from a lack of investment funds, a collapse in trading arrangements for&#13;
inputs and increased competition in the FSU market both from foreign suppliers and from new&#13;
local manufacturers. A strategy for re-orientating the industry within the new market&#13;
environment is urgently required.&#13;
10.         Energy Pricing and Institutional Reform. Azerbaijan inherited from the Soviet&#13;
Union a highly distorted system of energy pricing. However, pricing reform has been ad-hoc,&#13;
and energy price rises tended to lag behind those in other FSU countries until the end of 1994.&#13;
Although substantial real price increases were implemented in early 1995, producer and product&#13;
prices for oil remain mostly well below international parities. Natural gas producer prices have&#13;
been kept extremely low to offset the rising cost of imports from Turkmenistan. Both gas and&#13;
electricity prices to residential consumers have been held down relative to prices to industry,&#13;
with growing cross-subsidization. The slow pace of price increases has led to rising financial&#13;
deficits in all the major energy enterprises, which has aggravated the long term problem of&#13;
inadequate investment in plant maintenance and replacement. It is important for Azerbaijan to&#13;
adopt a more coherent policy of moving energy prices towards economic levels to avoid further&#13;
subsidy costs to the Government and to encourage more efficient use of energy.&#13;
11.         Azerbaijan's energy sector institutions have begun the process of reorganization,&#13;
although enterprises continue to operate in much the same manner as before. The oil Producing&#13;
Associations from the Soviet system have been abolished, and an integrated State Oil Company&#13;
(SOCAR) has been formed, including both oil and gas production and the refineries. Gas&#13;
distribution and transmission have been merged into a single state company, Azerigaz, while the&#13;
power sector is under the control of Azenergo. Government coordination of the energy sector&#13;
is weak, with no energy ministry and a lack of high level policy making staff. There is an almost&#13;
complete lack of energy sector legislation. A Petroleum Law is particularly necessary, to define&#13;
institutional responsibilities in the sub-sector and to encourage foreign investment. A&#13;
strengthening of Government supervision and policy implementation in energy is important, as&#13;
is a restructuring of enterprises to improve efficiency, and the strengthening of the enterprises&#13;
through training and improvement of financial and information systems.&#13;
12.         Foreign Investment for Offshore Oil Development. Development by Azerbaijan&#13;
of the oil resources which lie offshore of its coastline would have a profound impact on the&#13;
country's energy sector, and could generate the revenues required to finance restructuring,&#13;
infrastructure investment and social policies during and after the transition to a market economy.&#13;
However, the development of the offshore fields is frought with difficulties, and it is unlikely&#13;
that Azerbaijan will receive significant benefits from any development before the next century.&#13;
Under current plans, which may be optimistic, bringing these fields into production would&#13;
require an investment of some US$10 billion (bn) over the next ten years. This investment would&#13;
allow production to rise from 9.5 mt in 1994 to 40 mt in the year 2005. Net oil exports would&#13;
rise from about 1.0 mt in 1994, to 34 mt in 2005, worth about US$4 bn and accounting for&#13;
some 60% of total exports. In the early years of development, much of the impact would come&#13;
from the large flows of inward investment (about US$1.0 bn per year). Because of Azerbaijan's&#13;
landlocked location, and its capacity to manufacture a wide range of equipment, about 30% to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
45% of investment may go to enterprises in Azerbaijan, resulting in a very large boost to&#13;
domestic industry. Local sources are also likely to supply much of the labor and offshore&#13;
services.&#13;
13.         Involvement of major foreign oil companies is the only means by which&#13;
Azerbaijan could obtain the technology, financing and project organization to develop the&#13;
offshore fields. Azerbaijan has therefore signed agreements with several major companies for&#13;
development of the Azeri and Chirag fields (the two largest undeveloped offshore oil fields). In&#13;
the short term, attention should also focus upon the implementation of a project to reverse the&#13;
premature decline of production from the Guneshli field. It is probable that foreign oil&#13;
companies, and service companies, will have a role in financing and executing a project led by&#13;
SOCAR for the rehabilitation of Guneshli. The terms of the agreements with the oil companies&#13;
on oil production will have a large effect on net revenues to Azerbaijan. Given the very large&#13;
sums involved, it is vital that Azerbaijan obtains the best possible advice in its negotiations with&#13;
the foreign oil companies, and that the assessment of agreements is integrated into an overall&#13;
macroeconomic framework.&#13;
14.          Large scale development of oil for export would require construction of a crude&#13;
oil export pipeline with access to world markets, at a cost of at least US$1.5 bn. This pipeline&#13;
would have to cross at least one other country. Azerbaijan's preferred route at present lies across&#13;
either Iran or Georgia to Turkey, with shipment through the Turkish Mediterranean port of&#13;
Ceyhan. The option of a route across Georgia or Russia to the Black Sea is also being&#13;
considered, but the environmental and safety concerns posed by a large increase in the transit&#13;
of oil through the Bosphorus straits in Turkey may limit the quantity of additional oil which can&#13;
be exported through the Black Sea. Oil companies represent the most effective means of&#13;
mobilizing capital for a pipeline, although commercial banks, export credit agencies and&#13;
multilateral institutions may also be involved, and Azerbaijan has been working in close&#13;
coordination with all of these in its pipeline planning. The offshore developments are also likely&#13;
to require a common infrastructure and an integrated development strategy. The organizational&#13;
and financing arrangements for the joint infrastructure and the export pipeline are critical issues&#13;
on which Azerbaijan should seek expert advice.&#13;
15.          Exploration of the Caspian Sea, and the of onshore areas, for new petroleum&#13;
fields should also be a priority. It is important that this activity is carried out within a coherent&#13;
legal, commercial and strategic framework. A licensing strategy would involve division of the&#13;
prospective areas into blocks, structured promotion to the international industry, and possibly&#13;
licensing rounds designed to ensure orderly and progressive exploration of key areas.&#13;
16.          Although Azerbaijan has signed agreements with foreign companies for&#13;
development and exploration rights in the areas allocated to it under the division of the Caspian&#13;
Sea in the Soviet era, this division has not yet been formalized through international treaty&#13;
among the states bordering the Sea. Negotiation of an agreement with other Governments on&#13;
appropriate international boundaries is critical to establish Azerbaijan's resource endowment and&#13;
to allow foreign investment in oil development to proceed. Azerbaijan should seek expert legal&#13;
advice concerning the application of international law to the Caspian boundaries, as the legal&#13;
issues arising are potentially highly complicated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
17.         While Azerbaijan's resource base could present attractive potential opportunities&#13;
for international petroleum companies, it is important that an appropriate business environment&#13;
is created to encourage actual investment. To date, Azerbaijan has been relatively successful in&#13;
following up on the interest shown by many foreign companies, although achievement of final&#13;
agreements and investment has been slow. Creation of an appropriate legal and contractual&#13;
framework through development of a Petroleum Law and standard contracts, and resolution of&#13;
related legal and fiscal issues, is vital if foreign investment is to be attracted promptly and on&#13;
the most suitable terms. Strengthening of local capacity is also essential, through training and&#13;
assignment of the most capable staff to this area.&#13;
II. THE PROJECT&#13;
A. Project Objectives and Structure&#13;
18.         The technical assistance (TA) to be provided under this Project will assist&#13;
Azerbaijan to develop its petroleum sub-sector in a manner which maximizes its contribution to&#13;
overall economic development. The main objectives of the Project are: (a) to accelerate foreign&#13;
private investment and financial participation in petroleum exploration and production through&#13;
providing TA to SOCAR, particularly for restructuring of the Guneshli field; (b) to strengthen&#13;
petroleum sub-sector institutions through development of petroleum legislation, training, and&#13;
improvements in information systems; and (c) to prepare investment projects in the petroleum&#13;
sub-sector, for financing by public and private investors, through joint studies between SOCAR&#13;
and foreign advisors. The focus of the Project will be to create an enabling policy and&#13;
institutional environment which would allow foreign private investment in the petroleum sub-&#13;
sector to be mobilized efficiently.&#13;
19.         The Project would provide advisory services, studies and training to SOCAR. In&#13;
addition, TA would be provided to the Government to develop a legislative framework for&#13;
petroleum exploration and production. Implementation would be over a 4 year period. The total&#13;
Project cost is US$22.9 million equivalent, of which the IDA credit would be US$20.8 million&#13;
equivalent. The Project's components are described below. It should be noted that in addition&#13;
to the identified components, the credit for the Project will contain a further sum of US$1.0&#13;
million equivalent, since it is expected that additional TA requirements will arise in the energy&#13;
sector during the Project implementation period.&#13;
B. Project Description&#13;
1.    Support for Foreign Investment in Petroleum Exploration and Production&#13;
a.    Advisory Services for Petroleum Projects&#13;
20.         Components under this heading will provide advice to SOCAR to allow the&#13;
development of projects involving investment and financial support from foreign petroleum&#13;
companies. The following types of advice will be included under the project:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
*     Financial and Contractual Advice. The objectives of this component are to assist&#13;
SOCAR in negotiations with foreign petroleum companies and other agencies as concerns&#13;
the economic, fiscal and financial aspects of contracts concerning: (a) the Guneshli field&#13;
re-development project, (b) other petroleum projects, and (c) the development of an oil&#13;
export pipeline. The assistance will also aim to build the capability of SOCAR staff in&#13;
this area, and to install suitable systems within SOCAR to facilitate this work. The&#13;
Advisors' work will include the following tasks:&#13;
(a)    Advising SOCAR and Azerbaijan Government officials on the principles and&#13;
practices of petroleum development and exploration contracts in the international&#13;
petroleum industry;&#13;
(b)   Calculation of cash flows, internal rates of return and net present values for&#13;
alternative terms being negotiated as they would apply to all parties involved;&#13;
(c)    Advising SOCAR officials on proposals to be put to foreign companies and other&#13;
entities in negotiations and attending negotiations as required; and&#13;
(d)   Advising SOCAR on financial aspects of petroleum projects, including the types&#13;
of finance available, the cost of this financing and its effect on the viability of&#13;
projects, and assisting in contacts with potential financiers.&#13;
*     Legal Advice for Petroleum  Project Development. The objective of this&#13;
component is to assist SOCAR in negotiations with foreign petroleum companies and&#13;
other foreign entities (banks, governments etc.) as concerns the legal aspects of contracts,&#13;
and of the development of an oil export pipeline. The assistance will also aim to build&#13;
the capacity of SOCAR staff in this area. The Consultants' work program will include&#13;
the following tasks to be carried out in conjunction with the advisors to SOCAR&#13;
providing financial and contractual advisory services:&#13;
(a)    Advising SOCAR on the principles and practices of legal aspects of petroleum&#13;
development and exploration contracts in the international petroleum industry;&#13;
(b)   Advising SOCAR on the legal implications of export pipeline routing and project&#13;
implementation; and&#13;
(c)   Advising SOCAR officials on proposals to be put to foreign companies in&#13;
negotiations, taking into account the full interests of SOCAR and Azerbaijan and&#13;
practice in the international petroleum industry, and attending negotiations as&#13;
required.&#13;
*     Legal Studies on Caspian Sea Boundaries. The objective of this component is&#13;
to assist SOCAR, in close coordination with other relevant government agencies, in&#13;
assessing its policies with regard to the determination of the Caspian Sea boundaries as&#13;
they apply to petroleum resources. The assistance will also aim to build the capacity of&#13;
Azerbaijani staff in this area. The Consultants' scope of work will include the following&#13;
tasks:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
(a)   Conducting a study on the legal, technical and commercial issues arising from&#13;
international, customary and national laws within the context of the determination&#13;
of the boundaries of riparian states on the Caspian Sea; and&#13;
(b)   Examining the potential riparian issues that may arise in connection with the&#13;
problem of boundary determination.&#13;
The Consultants' work will not include the preparation of an adversarial position&#13;
or the taking of any adversarial actions, and the consultants would be excluded&#13;
from assisting Azerbaijan with negotiations with other riparian states for the&#13;
establishment of boundaries of the Caspian Sea.&#13;
*     Technical and Costing Advice for Project Development. This component aims&#13;
to provide SOCAR with international engineering expertise to assist with project&#13;
preparation and management of the Guneshli field re-development and of other petroleum&#13;
projects. The advisors would also be expected to provide training of SOCAR staff in&#13;
international project design and management practice through joint work. The, most&#13;
significant part of the assistance will focus on project management support for the&#13;
Guneshli field re-development. The scope of work will be to support SOCAR with:&#13;
(a)   Reviewing the existing facilities, updating the concept studies done to date, and&#13;
preparing the technical basis for the project;&#13;
(b)   Preparing project execution plans, including contracting basis, project control&#13;
estimates and schedules, and cash flow forecasts, and establishing project&#13;
procedures and guidelines;&#13;
(c)   Preparing tender documents, tender evaluations and recommendations for tender&#13;
award;&#13;
(d)   Following-up contractor's performance and preparing status reports, and&#13;
conducting periodic meetings with contractors;&#13;
(e)   Reviewing and verifying contractors' cost estimates and reports, resolving&#13;
contractual issues and problems, and verifying contractors' progress reporting as&#13;
a basis for progress payments;&#13;
(f)    Ensuring that environmental and safety standards are met in the project, and&#13;
performing periodic quality assurance audits of project team and contractors; and&#13;
(g)   Participating during final commissioning of the work and start-up of facilities.&#13;
*     Advisory Services on Petroleum Licensing and Exploration Promotion. This&#13;
component is designed to provide Azerbaijan with advice to develop and implement a&#13;
comprehensive policy for petroleum exploration licensing and promotion. The advice&#13;
encompasses the following scope of work:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
(a)   Organization and evaluation of data as to its exploration utility, categorization of&#13;
prospect valuations, and the establishment and valuation of data packages for&#13;
petroleum industry use;&#13;
(b)   Establishing SOCAR objectives and desired pace of exploration licensing,&#13;
frequency and nature of bidding rounds, the configuration, number and size of&#13;
exploration blocks, and their respective bonuses and model work programs;&#13;
(c)   Evaluating alternative promotion strategies to the international oil industry, and&#13;
designing a promotion program schedule; assisting in implementation and in bid&#13;
evaluation and subsequent negotiations as necessary; and&#13;
(d)   Assisting in the establishment of a petroleum exploration policy making body, and&#13;
a contract compliance regulation agency.&#13;
2.    Institutional Strengthening of the Petroleum Sub-sector&#13;
a.    Advisory Services&#13;
21.         The following advisory services will be provided so as to strengthen the&#13;
fundamental institutional structures of the petroleum sub-sector:&#13;
*     Development of a Legal and Fiscal Framework for Petroleum Exploration and&#13;
Production. The objective of this component is to assist the Experts Group, which is&#13;
responsible within the Government for drafting a Petroleum Law, in drafting a&#13;
comprehensive legal framework for petroleum operations including the Regulations and&#13;
one or several variations of a model contract. The Consultants' assistance will include&#13;
the following tasks:&#13;
(a)   Advising the Experts Group on different legal regimes covering petroleum&#13;
exploration and development;&#13;
(b)   Assisting with the drafting of comprehensive petroleum legislation covering: the&#13;
institutional structure of the sub-sector; means of conducting petroleum&#13;
operations; concept and outline contents of a Model Contract; and fiscal/taxation&#13;
policies for petroleum operations;&#13;
(c)   Assisting with the drafting of enabling Regulations and the preparation of model&#13;
contracts; and&#13;
(d)   Training the key government and SOCAR officials in the implementation of the&#13;
petroleum law and regulations.&#13;
b.    Training and Equipment&#13;
22.         The following project components will meet a significant proportion of SOCAR's&#13;
immediate training needs, and initiate the computerization of key departments:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
Training of SOCAR Staff in Financial and Commercial Aspects of the&#13;
Petroleum Industry. The objective of this component is to help meet the needs of&#13;
SOCAR staff for substantial training in the links between the technical and economic&#13;
criteria for petroleum investment and operations, as well as in basic commercial and&#13;
financial management skills. The training should aim to enable a self-sufficient group of&#13;
petroleum economists to carry out project evaluations as well as oil trading and&#13;
marketing with limited help from outside advisors. The scope of work for the component&#13;
is as follows:&#13;
(a)   Assessing the training needs of SOCAR as well as selecting a core group of staff&#13;
with relevant skills (eg. engineering, economics, finance) for training, and&#13;
designing a training plan in conjunction with SOCAR;&#13;
(b)   Preparing courses, seminars and workshops which will cover the following areas:&#13;
(i) geo-political, economic and structural aspects of world petroleum markets, (ii)&#13;
international practices in exploration and production agreements and their fiscal&#13;
and contractual aspects, (iii) economic analysis of oil projects and operations, (iv)&#13;
oil company financial management, and international financial institutions,&#13;
banking systems and practices, and (v) crude and oil product trading methods and&#13;
commercial practice; and&#13;
(c)   Providing training abroad for a selected number of managers in advanced&#13;
programs along with a prior English language training program.&#13;
--    Provision of Computing and Communications Equipment. The objectives of&#13;
the work are: (a) to introduce approximately 80 personal computers (PC's) with an&#13;
appropriate number of printers, associated software and hardware to a number of key&#13;
SOCAR departments, and to train selected SOCAR staff in communications technology&#13;
and maintenance, (b) to strengthen the ability of SOCAR's information technology&#13;
officers to manage the computer requirements of SOCAR including training and&#13;
maintenance, (c) to provide SOCAR with satellite communication facilities including&#13;
telephone and facsimile lines which will enable SOCAR to handle its communications&#13;
with foreign oil companies, advisors and institutions. The Consultant's task will include&#13;
the following:&#13;
(a)   Establishing the work plan for the services to purchase and install PC's and&#13;
communication systems and assisting in supervising procurement and installation&#13;
of equipment, and&#13;
(b)   Training selected core information technology officers in SOCAR in PC and&#13;
communications technology and maintenance, and establishing a small training&#13;
center.&#13;
Following the conclusion of the Consultant's work plan, the PIU will undertake&#13;
procurement of equipment for: (i) supply of PC's and related equipment to key&#13;
departments of SOCAR; (ii) supply a satellite communication system with several&#13;
telephone lines and facsimile modem for SOCAR headquarters. The PIU will also&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
oversee the charging of incremental operating costs for the satellite communication&#13;
system to the Project budget, within the specified financing limits.&#13;
3.    Petroleum Project Investment Studies&#13;
23.          The following studies will be undertaken in support of petroleum  investment&#13;
projects. All studies will be undertaken by international specialist firms, working closely with&#13;
teams of SOCAR experts.&#13;
*     Oil Rocks and Other Older Offshore Oil Fields Restructuring Study. An&#13;
economic and engineering study of the older offshore fields will determine the remaining&#13;
exploitable reserves, where these reserves are located within the fields, and the most&#13;
efficient method of their production. The studies will investigate the surface facilities of&#13;
each field, and develop plans for their renovation, removal or modification which are&#13;
required to complete the exploitation of the field. These studies will form the basis for&#13;
a comparative economic ranking of offshore rehabilitation projects, and will serve as the&#13;
technical basis for developing financial options for their implementation. The studies&#13;
would each encompass the following scope of work:&#13;
(a)    A complete reservoir simulation study for each productive field unit, and an&#13;
optimized economic exploitation plan of infill and field extension drilling;&#13;
(b)   A surface facilities assessment, the design of a rehabilitation, modernization and&#13;
salvage plan, and the environmental assessment and development of an operations&#13;
plan to remediate and minimize pollution;&#13;
(c)    The design of a field renovation work schedule, field life production forecasts,&#13;
cash flow projections, and a personnel rationalization program; and&#13;
(d)    Presentation of alternative finance options, including potential for joint ventures&#13;
and assistance with field promotion.&#13;
*     Rehabilitation of the Old Onshore Oil Fields. A strategy will be developed for&#13;
the renovation and rehabilitation of the older onshore fields of Azerbaijan to improve the&#13;
economics of production and develop remaining reserves efficiently. The strategy will&#13;
include plans for the attracting foreign investment, with focused studies of the Bibi-Eybat&#13;
and Balkhanineft fields, two of the largest and oldest fields. The scope of work will&#13;
include the following tasks:&#13;
(a)    The development of a uniform methodology for the economic evaluation of each&#13;
onshore field and individual wells; including the decision-making processes for:&#13;
(i) working-over poorly producing wells, (ii) the abandonment of sub-commercial&#13;
wells; and (iii) the drilling of field-related delineation and exploration wells;&#13;
(b)   A detailed reserve determination to establish the remaining reserves, with a&#13;
comprehensive economic plan for their exploitation; articulation of a rationalized&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-11-&#13;
production scheme for the refurbishment, abandonment or replacement of surface&#13;
facilities;&#13;
(c)   The development of an environmental remediation plan to systematically abandon&#13;
uneconomic wells, the removal of related surface equipment and infrastructure&#13;
and the return of the surface to a condition suitable for other land use;&#13;
(d)   Recommending strategies for resolution of institutional issues related to field&#13;
management, and of social issues related to rationalization of labor; and&#13;
(e)   Preparation of initial bidding packages for offering to foreign companies for joint&#13;
venture participation with SOCAR, promotion of packages to the international&#13;
petroleum industry and evaluation of bids.&#13;
*     Gas Processing Facilities Reconstruction Study. The study will focus on&#13;
medium and long term solutions based on a least cost approach to gas processing needs.&#13;
The study will include a conceptual design for a gas plant, and comprehensive economic&#13;
and financial analysis. The output of the study will allow a project for reconstruction of&#13;
gas processing facilities to be presented to international oil companies and financial&#13;
institutions for financing. The study encompasses the following scope of work:&#13;
(a)   Physical survey and technical diagnosis of the existing gas plant and conceptual&#13;
design for plant reconstruction;&#13;
(b)   Financial and economic studies including sensitivity tests against pricing of gas&#13;
and LPG and capital investment costs, and assessment of options for financing the&#13;
investment; and&#13;
(c)   Preliminary environmental and safety assessment.&#13;
*     Feasibility Study of Project for Early Exports of Crude Oil. Given the urgency&#13;
of developing an economic outlet for crude oil exports, the main objective of this&#13;
component is to draw up a practical project implementation scheme together with&#13;
SOCAR and international oil companies. The main focus of the work is expected to be&#13;
the reversal of the existing pipeline designed to carry oil from Grozny (Russia) to Baku.&#13;
Legal, contractual and financial aspects will be covered by other Project components.&#13;
The component encompasses the following tasks:&#13;
(a)   Physical survey and technical diagnosis of the existing infrastructure and&#13;
transportation facilities, and review of studies done by institutes in the FSU and&#13;
by SOCAR;&#13;
(b)   Finalization of conceptual design for the pipeline and terminal facilities, and&#13;
initial environmental assessment;&#13;
(c)   Survey of domestic oil consumption and evaluation of amount of exportable oil;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-12-&#13;
(d)   Financial and economic analyses including sensitivity tests against oil price and&#13;
capital investment costs; and&#13;
(e)   Recommendations on the operation scheme including offtake arrangements, and&#13;
pipeline management.&#13;
C. Legal Aspects&#13;
24.         Lending Arrangements. The Azerbaijan Republic has not yet set up a Ministry&#13;
of Energy within the central government structure to oversee the energy sector and to develop&#13;
sector policies. Ministerial responsibility for energy lies with the First Deputy Prime Minister,&#13;
who is supported by a small staff of specialists. Other Ministries which play a role in the energy&#13;
sector include: the Ministry of External Economic Relations, Ministry of Finance (MOF) and&#13;
Ministry of Economy. A key enterprise in the energy sector is SOCAR, which was established&#13;
in September 13, 1992, through a Presidential Decree. SOCAR carries out all activities&#13;
connected with exploration and production of oil and gas, refining of oil and bulk transport and&#13;
storage of crude oil.&#13;
25.         The Charter of SOCAR, which sets forth its legal status, functions, assets,&#13;
structure, and management was approved by a Presidential Decree on November 14, 1992.&#13;
According to its Charter, SOCAR is established as a separate legal entity. The management of&#13;
the company belongs to its Board of Directors and to its Managerial Board. The members of the&#13;
Board of Directors, apart from the Vice-Presidents of the company and the President of SOCAR,&#13;
are appointed by the President of the Republic.&#13;
26.         SOCAR consists of a number of subunits, which may have different legal status,&#13;
either as "structural units" or as "state enterprises". While the state enterprises are separate legal&#13;
entities, structural units do not have independent status. SOCAR's structure has been evolving&#13;
as the management seeks to improve its organization in line with modern oil company practices.&#13;
Based on a Presidential Decree dated January 10, 1994, SOCAR is undergoing further structural&#13;
change. According to this Decree and an Order of the President of SOCAR, a number of&#13;
structural units and enterprises are being liquidated or restructured.&#13;
27.         SOCAR will be responsible for the execution of virtually all the Project&#13;
components. Thus the credit will be provided to the Azerbaijan Republic and onlent through a&#13;
Subsidiary Loan Agreement to SOCAR for the components of the Project which SOCAR is&#13;
responsible for implementing. Therefore, IDA will conclude: (a) a Credit Agreement with the&#13;
Azerbaijan Republic; and (b) a Project Agreement with SOCAR. A Subsidiary Loan Agreement&#13;
between the Government of Azerbaijan and SOCAR will set forth the onlending terms which&#13;
would be for an amount of US$20.225 million, for 12 years, including 5 years of grace, with&#13;
interest at 200 basis points above the prevailing yield on US 10-year Treasury Bills, with 6-&#13;
month variable interest rates. The preparation of the Petroleum Legislation component of the&#13;
Project will be implemented by the Experts Group established under the Secretary of the&#13;
Supreme Soviet (Parliament) of the Republic. For this component, the MOF will pass on the&#13;
proceeds of the credit to the Experts Group. Lending arrangements, legal documents and flow&#13;
of funds are shown in Annex 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
28.         Ability to Borrow. The Constitution of the Republic of Azerbaijan gives the&#13;
authority to conclude international treaties and agreements with international institutions to the&#13;
President of the Republic. Article 104 (28) of the Constitution requires the ratification of&#13;
international agreements by the Parliament. On December 29, 1992, the Parliament enacted the&#13;
Law on State's Debt and according to Article 3 of this Law, the MOF manages the foreign debt&#13;
of the Republic. This Law gives to the Government the authority to decide on foreign borrowing&#13;
up to a certain limit approved by the Parliament.&#13;
29.        Based upon discussions with the MOF, National Bank and the Supreme Soviet,&#13;
it is understood that the IDA credit would need to be submitted to the Parliament for formal&#13;
ratification unless the upper limit on foreign borrowing is decided by the Parliament.&#13;
D. Project Costs, Financing, Procurement and Disbursements&#13;
1.    Project Costs&#13;
30.         The total project cost is estimated at US$22.86 million equivalent with a foreign&#13;
exchange component of US$20.8 million, or approximately 91% of total costs. The project costs&#13;
are estimated on the basis of a four year implementation schedule. Unit costs of advisory and&#13;
consultant services are based upon consultations with firms doing business in Azerbaijan,&#13;
discussions with the UNDP who are active in providing TA to Azerbaijan, and from rates quoted&#13;
for other similar consultant services in the region. Price contingencies averaging 5% have been&#13;
assumed for all project components. Detailed project costs are shown in Annex 2.&#13;
31.         An unallocated amount of US$1.0 million has been set aside for additional&#13;
investment studies not yet identified, and for follow-up advisory services to emerging investment&#13;
promotion opportunities. Project costs also include the re-financing of a Project Preparation&#13;
Facility (PPF) of US$0.5 million, of which US$0.1 million had been committed by September&#13;
1994. The uncommitted amount under the PPF of US$0.4 million is being directed at early&#13;
consultancy services for structuring the approach to the rehabilitation of the Guneshli Field&#13;
(US$250,000), early consultancy services and support to SOCAR to accelerate project&#13;
implementation (US$75,000), and preparation of the component on petroleum legislation&#13;
(US$75,000).&#13;
2.    Project Financing&#13;
32.         The proposed IDA credit (US$20.8 million equivalent) would finance 91 % of the&#13;
total project costs, excluding any taxes or duties. Local costs will be in the form of support&#13;
services, office space and facilities, and seconded staff, and would be provided in large degree&#13;
by SOCAR. However, some logistical and training local costs will be included in the foreign&#13;
financed contracts for consulting services and the procurement of equipment, and would be&#13;
financed by the credit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
3.    Procurement&#13;
33.         The proposed procurement packages are detailed in Annex 3. The procurement&#13;
procedures are as follows:&#13;
(a)   Contracts for Consulting and Training Services (US$ 20.2 million). All&#13;
consulting services will be provided by firms. The selection processes for all&#13;
consulting, advisory and training services would be based upon the Bank's&#13;
"Guidelines for Use of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers and by the World&#13;
Bank as Executing Agency" (August 1981) based on technical merit;&#13;
(b)   Equipment and Supplies (US$0.6 million). Equipment to be procured under the&#13;
project consists of computers and office equipment of a varied nature, and an&#13;
international communications system, all of relatively low value. Given the varied&#13;
nature of the items, and that no particular item or package exceeds US$300,000,&#13;
these items or groups of items would be procured through International Shopping&#13;
based on the comparison of price quotations and servicing/training capabilities&#13;
obtained from at least three suppliers from at least three different eligible&#13;
countries, in accordance with Bank Guidelines.&#13;
34.         Procurement Status/Timing of Consultant Services. During Project appraisal&#13;
in May-June, 1994, the necessary Terms of Reference (TOR) were developed. Accordingly,&#13;
SOCAR now has for review all necessary TORs and early action to begin consultant selection&#13;
is possible. Given the urgency of arresting the production decline of the Guneshli Field, early&#13;
work on this component will be financed under the remaining funds of the PPF (at a cost of&#13;
US$250,000). However, the Project Management work on the Guneshli field is integrated and&#13;
sequential in nature. The first phase of the work (initial project preparation and definition) would&#13;
be financed under the PPF. A change of consultants after the PPF phase could result in&#13;
disruption of the work and of established working relationships, and also could lead to a delay&#13;
in implementation of the Guneshli project and to consequent greater loss of petroleum&#13;
production. It is therefore proposed that the component of the Project relating to Technical and&#13;
Costing Advisory Services for the Guneshli Field Rehabilitation Project (foreign exchange cost&#13;
US$6.0 million) be the subject of Advance Contracting, subject to the provisions outlined in OD&#13;
11.00. The Consultant selected under the PPF in accordance with Bank Guidelines would also&#13;
be awarded the Contract for the further work under this component within the Project, subject&#13;
to satisfactory completion of the work under the PPF, to effectiveness of the credit and to&#13;
appropriate progress with the Guneshli field rehabilitation project.&#13;
35.         Contract Review. As this is the first IDA credit to Azerbaijan, and no Country&#13;
Procurement Assessment Review (CPAR) has yet been completed, all contracts for services and&#13;
goods would be subject to the IDA's prior review of procurement documentation. However, as&#13;
experience is gained, this prior review requirement will be evaluated at the mid-term review,&#13;
or earlier if requested by SOCAR, and some modification may be determined at that time for&#13;
contracts or amendments of relatively low value to allow for post-review.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-15-&#13;
4.    Disbursements&#13;
36.         Disbursements against the proposed IDA credit are expected to be 100% of&#13;
expenditures on consultants' services and training, and for office equipment, communications,&#13;
computers and software 100% of the foreign expenditures or 100% of the ex-factory cost of&#13;
locally manufactured eligible goods or 75% of the cost of other domestic purchases. The IDA&#13;
credit will cover 100% of foreign expenditures (including local costs incurred within the&#13;
contracts not provided by SOCAR or the Experts Group). Disbursements for components&#13;
managed by SOCAR will be signed by the President of SOCAR, or a person designated by the&#13;
President. Disbursements for consulting services to the Experts Group will be signed by a&#13;
designated member of the Group. Disbursements will be fully documented, except for contracts&#13;
for consulting services and equipment not exceeding US$20,000 for which disbursements would&#13;
be on the basis of statements of expenditures (SOEs). The documentation for these expenditures&#13;
would be retained by the PIU for at least one year after receipt by IDA of the audit report for&#13;
the year in which the last disbursement was made. This documentation would be available for&#13;
review by the auditors and IDA upon request.&#13;
37.         In order to expedite urgent payments to be made locally, a Special Account with&#13;
a ceiling of US$500,000 will be established in a commercial bank acceptable to IDA and will&#13;
be replenished in accordance with Bank procedures. Urgent small payments in local and foreign&#13;
currencies will be effected locally through this Special Account. All other payments to&#13;
consultants and suppliers will be made directly through the Credit Account (direct payment&#13;
procedure). In the event that payments of goods are to be made through letters of credit, IDA&#13;
will effect payment directly to the commercial banks (special commitment procedure). At the&#13;
request of the Borrower and, based on the project needs, IDA would make an appropriate initial&#13;
deposit or deposits into the Special Accounts up to the amount of the authorized allocation. The&#13;
estimated schedule of disbursements is based on the Project being completed within four years&#13;
of credit effectiveness.&#13;
E. Project Management and Reporting&#13;
1.    Project Management&#13;
38.         Project Executing Responsibilities. The respective responsibilities of the MOF,&#13;
SOCAR and the Experts Group Commission are as follows:&#13;
(a)   The MOF will be the representative of the Borrower, the Azerbaijan Republic,&#13;
to IDA;&#13;
(b)   The funds will be on-lent to SOCAR, at the terms and conditions stated above and&#13;
SOCAR will be responsible for executing all aspects of the Project with the&#13;
exception of the Experts Group work on developing a new petroleum law;&#13;
(c)   SOCAR will establish a PIU with appropriate staff and responsibilities which will&#13;
manage and coordinate overall project activities; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
(d)   The Experts Group will manage and execute the consulting contract for the&#13;
petroleum legislation directly and will appoint at least one full time official for&#13;
this purpose.&#13;
39.          Project performance indicators to serve as a basis for the mutual monitoring and&#13;
supervision of the Project are shown as Annex 7. An outline implementation schedule is&#13;
provided as Annex 4. A detailed implementation plan and schedule will be developed by the PIU&#13;
for the Project showing the critical steps and dates required to meet the Project's objectives&#13;
within a 48 month period. An initial plan and schedule will be agreed during the project launch&#13;
mission planned for May 1995, and a final detailed plan and schedule will be submitted with the&#13;
interim progress report in September 1995.&#13;
40.          Overall Project Management. SOCAR will have overall responsibility for the&#13;
implementation of the activities to be financed, except for the Petroleum Law component which&#13;
will be under the responsibility of the Experts Group. SOCAR will establish and pay for a PIU&#13;
with appropriate staff and responsibilities which will support and coordinate overall project&#13;
activities including procurement, disbursements and reporting, and which will also ensure that&#13;
the requirements of Bank Guidelines on procurement of services and goods are met. The PIU&#13;
would also assist the Experts Group in their evaluation of consultant proposals.&#13;
41.          The PIU will report to the President of SOCAR through one of the Vice&#13;
Presidents or a top management official designated to oversee its activities, and will be headed&#13;
by an Executive Director who will be assisted by two technical professionals, a financial officer,&#13;
and a secretary. The PIU will be assisted by specialized international consulting services, to be&#13;
financed under the Project, to provide procurement and financial management advice. The PIU&#13;
will be provided by SOCAR with suitable office space, local communication and office&#13;
equipment, although the consultants should be prepared to arrange for their own logistical&#13;
support in transportation, international communications, lodging and computers.&#13;
42.          PIU Functions. The PIU will be the focal point for the Project and will be&#13;
responsible for its overall execution in cooperation with the concerned Departments of SOCAR.&#13;
In addition, it will also serve as the Secretariat to the President of SOCAR in reviewing reports&#13;
and recommendations, preparing summary reports and recommendations for policy level&#13;
consultations, and identifying any problems and solutions that develop in Project execution which&#13;
require action. In close cooperation and coordination with the respective Departments of&#13;
SOCAR, it will prepare and authorize Withdrawal Applications, manage the procurement and&#13;
arrange for signing of any contracts and payments. It will also monitor and ensure provision of&#13;
necessary and agreed upon financial and logistical support to the consulting services. The PIU&#13;
will also assist the Experts Group in managing the evaluation of the consultant services for their&#13;
work. The division of responsibilities between SOCAR management and the PIU will be as&#13;
follows:&#13;
(a)   SOCAR  will: (i) Formally establish the PIU  with specific authority and&#13;
responsibilities, and will assign the necessary designated individuals with&#13;
appropriate qualifications as Director and staff; (ii) Approve the consulting&#13;
contract for management advice to the PIU; and, (iii) Ensure that reports required&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
by IDA and the MOF are prepared in a timely manner, and that other interested&#13;
parties are informed of project activities to ensure donor coordination.&#13;
(b)   The PIU will: (i) Finalize TORs and specifications for services and goods; (ii)&#13;
Finalize bid packaging; (iii) Prepare short lists of proposed consultants; (iv)&#13;
Coordinate bid responses; (v) Arrange and manage evaluations of proposals; (vi)&#13;
Assist in preparing and reviewing contracts for signature by appropriate&#13;
authorities; (vii) Assist in the day-to-day contract execution; (viii) Prepare and&#13;
maintain a master schedule of project execution and monitoring; (ix) Maintain a&#13;
project cost accounting system; (x) Organize and direct a project reporting&#13;
system; (xi) Prepare and recommend to MOF for payment all Withdrawal&#13;
Applications; (xii) Arrange for and coordinate all necessary IDA approvals; (xiii)&#13;
Arrange for and pay any required taxes and obtain customs/immigration&#13;
clearances; and, (xiv) Prepare any required reports.&#13;
2.    Reporting and Monitoring&#13;
43.          The accounting for all Special Account transactions and for all other project-&#13;
related accounts will be maintained in accordance with accounting practices and standards which&#13;
are acceptable to IDA. Annual financial statements of IDA-financed components will be prepared&#13;
and audited in accordance with generally accepted accounting practices and standards commonly&#13;
used in Azerbaijan by suitably qualified independent auditors acceptable to IDA, and submitted&#13;
to IDA within six months of the close of the Government of Azerbaijan's fiscal year. Audits will&#13;
also be carried out, at the same time, and for corresponding periods in accordance with IDA&#13;
guidelines, for SOEs against which disbursements have been made or are due to be made out&#13;
of the Credit and Special Accounts. Each year SOCAR will submit to IDA the auditors' report&#13;
and audited financial statements for the Special Account, project accounts and SOEs for the&#13;
preceding fiscal year, not later than six months after the close of such year. Auditors acceptable&#13;
to IDA will be retained by SOCAR to review the accounting systems and supporting internal&#13;
procedures and practices for the Special and project Accounts and SOEs, and recommend any&#13;
needed changes.&#13;
44.         Quarterly reports will be required no later than one month after the close of the&#13;
relevant quarter, as well as consolidated reports on project implementation covering the status&#13;
of: (a) procurement; (b) the conduct of studies, advisory services and training; and, (c) decisions&#13;
taken or proposed to be taken on key findings and recommendations. A mid-term review will&#13;
be held in May, 1997.&#13;
F. Supervision Arrangements&#13;
45.         General. This will be the first IDA operation in Azerbaijan, and although the&#13;
main executing agency (SOCAR) has dealt with foreign firms to some extent, SOCAR and the&#13;
Government of Azerbaijan are unfamiliar with IDA/IBRD procedures. At present, Azerbaijan&#13;
has no major foreign debt and the Government is still developing systems of control and&#13;
management of foreign debt operations. IDA supervision will take into account the urgency of&#13;
preparing investment plans for the declining Guneshli Field which requires that advisory services&#13;
be provided at an early date, so as to be of use as SOCAR negotiates with foreign companies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
Government of Azerbaijan decision-making will be aided by frequent IDA visits. Nine Field&#13;
Supervision Missions are proposed during the four-year implementation period. A CPAR is not&#13;
planned for the moment but will be considered as the IBRD/IDA portfolio grows.&#13;
46.         Project Launch Workshop. It is proposed to hold a Project Launch Workshop&#13;
no later than one month after Board Presentation to review with SOCAR and the Government&#13;
the implementation arrangements for the Project.&#13;
47.         IIDA Supervision Input. The Supervision Plan for the Project is provided as&#13;
Annex 5. IDA staff input of 66 staff weeks (over four years) into the supervision of the&#13;
proposed project will take the following forms:&#13;
(a)   Project Initiation. Twelve staff weeks, including one Mission to Azerbaijan, are&#13;
determined necessary to have all the bid packages put into place and work&#13;
initiated. This will include the review of procurement documentation,&#13;
correspondence and internal reporting.&#13;
(b)   Guneshli Reviews. Given the importance and level of IDA financing of the&#13;
components relating to the Guneshli oil field, 10 staff weeks and two Missions&#13;
are dedicated to this activity specifically, although it is also included in other&#13;
review and supervision efforts.&#13;
(c)   Petroleum Legislation. This key activity will require two staff weeks of Legal&#13;
staff.&#13;
(d)   Progress Reviews. Thirty four staff weeks will be dedicated to periodic reviews,&#13;
including one major Mid-term Review of 8 staff weeks, to review with SOCAR&#13;
the progress of specific activities under implementation, and of key problem areas&#13;
and actions taken or planned to be taken to resolve them.&#13;
(e)   Final Inspection/Audits. Eight staff weeks will be dedicated to finalizing IDA&#13;
documentation and payments, and evaluating the impact of the Project activities.&#13;
48.         Government of Azerbaijan and SOCAR Contribution to Supervision. In&#13;
addition to the periodic reports to be provided to IDA, the PIU will prepare an issues paper in&#13;
preparation for each Field Supervision mission. At the end of each mission, an aide memoire&#13;
will be prepared summarizing the mission's major findings, the issues requiring the&#13;
Government's and IDA's attention and proposed actions to resolve identified problem areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
Annex 1&#13;
Page 1 of 1&#13;
LENDING ARRANGEMENTS, LEGAL DOCUMENTS&#13;
AND FLOW OF FUNDS&#13;
IDA              -- ----l--&#13;
........................................................  ........ .. . . .......&#13;
LEISDING                   AGREEMENT&#13;
EXPERTS    -_FUNDS-    Azerbaijan                                                                       / D&#13;
GROUP  r                                Republic&#13;
/ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~ACCOUNT\&#13;
ON LI NDING&#13;
/PROJEUI-a&lt;                                                                         &#13;
AGREEMENT&#13;
LOAN&#13;
AGREEMENT&#13;
ACCOUNT&#13;
SOCAR&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.. . . ....                          ...................       ......    ..    ............ -  --FNS,'&#13;
PIU               -                                                         E FUNDS  .  FUNDS&#13;
SUPPLIERS \T&#13;
OF OOODS&#13;
A     SERVICES..                  ............................ ....................................... .......................................... ............ -...................&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PETROLEUM TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
COST ESTIMATE&#13;
(US$ 000)&#13;
Local       Foreign          Total  Foreign as     Total as&#13;
% of Total    % of Total&#13;
Project Cost   Base Cost&#13;
A.    Support for Foreign Investment in              1,200         13,160         14,360            91            68&#13;
Petroleum Exploration and Production&#13;
Advisory Services                              1,200        13,200         14,400            91            68&#13;
1. Financial/Contractual Advice                 400          4,300          4,700            91            22&#13;
-Guneshli Field                           100          2,000         2,100            95             10&#13;
-Export Pipeline                          100          1,000         1,100             91             5&#13;
-Other Fields                             100           800            900             88             4&#13;
-Other Infrastructure                     100           500            600             83             3&#13;
2. Legal Advice                                 100          1,160          1,260            92             6&#13;
-Caspian Sea Boundaries                    50           400            450             88             2         T&#13;
-Project Development                       50           760            810             94             4&#13;
3. Technical/Costing Advice                     700          7,700          8,400            92            40&#13;
-Guneshli Field                           500          6,000         6,500             92            31&#13;
-Other Projects                           200          1,700         1,900             90             9&#13;
B.    Institutional Strengthening of the               160          1,440          1,600            90             8&#13;
Petroleum Sub-Sector&#13;
Advisory Services                                50            400           450             88             2&#13;
1 Petroleum Legislation                                                                                                CD&#13;
-Petroleum Law                             50           400            450             88             2          |&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Local       Foreign          Total  Foreign as    Total as&#13;
% of Total    % of Total&#13;
Project Cost    Base Cost&#13;
Training                                         50            400           450             84             2&#13;
1. Financial/Commercial                          50           400            450&#13;
ENuipment                                        60            640           700             91             3&#13;
1. Computers/Communications Advice               10            100           110             91&#13;
2. Computer/Communications Procurement           50            540           590             92&#13;
C.    Energy Sector Investment Studies                 300          3,050         3,350             91            14&#13;
Advisory Services                               300          3,050          3,350            91            14&#13;
1. Projea Preparation&#13;
-Oil Rocks/Old Offshore Field             50            800            850            94             4&#13;
Rehabilitation&#13;
-Old Onshore Fields Restructuring         50            800            850            94             4&#13;
-Gas Processing Facilities                100           650            750            87             4&#13;
Reconstruction Study&#13;
-Early Oil Exports                        100           800            900            89             4&#13;
D.    Components to be identified                                   1,000         1,000&#13;
E.    Project Implementation                           100            650           750             87             3&#13;
Advisory Services&#13;
1. Project Management/Procurement               100            600           700             86             3&#13;
Equipment&#13;
1. Office Equipment                                             50            50            100             1&#13;
Total Base Cost                                      1,760         19,300        21,060             92&#13;
Contingencies                                          100          1,000          1,100            91                      o x&#13;
Refinancing Project Preparation Facility               200            500           700             71                      N N&#13;
Project Total Cost                                   2,060         20,800        22,860             92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
AZERBALJAN&#13;
PETROLEUM TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
PROCUREMENT PLAN AND SCHEDULE&#13;
COMPONENT                                        ESTIM. PROCUREMENT  ISSUE              SELECT          SIGN&#13;
COST    METHOD             INVITES   CONSULTANT  CONTRACT&#13;
TO BID    (SUPPLIER)       (DELIVERY)&#13;
A. CONSULTING AND ADVISORY SERVICES&#13;
1. SUPPORT FOR FOREIGN INVESTMENT&#13;
IN PETROLEUM EXPLORATION AND&#13;
PRODUCTION&#13;
(a) Financial/Contractual Advice to SOCAR&#13;
-Guneshli Field                         2,000         Short List    5/15/95    8/30/95          10/14/95&#13;
Tech. Merit&#13;
-Export Pipeline                         1,000        ditto         6/15/95    9/30/95          11/04/95&#13;
-Other Fields                             800         ditto         6/27/95     10/15/95        11/27/95&#13;
-Other Infrastructure                     500         ditto         6/27/95     10/15/95        11/27/95&#13;
(b) Legal Advice to SOCAR&#13;
-Caspian Sea Boundaries                   400         ditto         6/15/95    8/30/95          10/14/95&#13;
-Project Development                      800         ditto         6/15/95     8/30/95         10/14/95&#13;
(c) Technical/Costing Advice to SOCAR&#13;
-Guneshli Field                         6,000         ditto         1/27/95     3/31/95         4/28/95&#13;
-Other Projects                           900         ditto         6/27/95     10/15/95        11/27/95&#13;
(d) Licensing/Exploration Promotion (SOCAR)    800        ditto         6/27/95     10/15/95        11/27/95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
COMPONENT                                      ESTIM. PROCUREMENT  ISSUE             SELECT          SIGN&#13;
COST    METHOD            INVITES   CONSULTANT  CONTRACT&#13;
TO BID    (SUPPLIER)    (DELIVERY)&#13;
2. INSTITUTIONAL STRENGTHENING OF&#13;
THE PETROLEUM SECTOR&#13;
(a) Petroleum Legislation and Framework     400         ditto        5/15/95     7/30/95         9/14/95&#13;
(b) Computers/Communications                110         Short List    6/15/95    8/30/95         10/17/95&#13;
Tech. Merit&#13;
(c) Financial/Commercial Training           400         Short List    7/16/95    9/29/95         11/2/95&#13;
Tech. Merit&#13;
3. ENERGY SECTOR INVESTMENT STUDIES&#13;
(a) Project Preparation&#13;
-Oil Rocks and old Offshore field       800          ditto        6/27/95    10/15/95        11/27/95&#13;
Rehabilitation&#13;
-Onshore Fields                         800          ditto        6/27/95    10/15/95        11/27/95&#13;
-Gas Processing Facilities Reconstruction  650       ditto        6/27/95    10/15/95        11/27/95&#13;
Study&#13;
-Early Oil Exports                      800          ditto        6/15/95    8/30/95         10/14/95&#13;
4. PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
(a) Project Management/Procurement          600         ditto         1/27/95    3/31/95        6/15/95&#13;
B. EQUIPMENT&#13;
1. Computer/Communications Equipment        540         International  10/15/95    12/15/95     2/15/96&#13;
and Training                                         Shopping&#13;
2. Project Management Support                 50        International  5/16/95   7/15/95         8/27/95&#13;
Shopping    _     _                                     w&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-                                         Annex 4&#13;
Page 1 of 2&#13;
AZERBAIJAN&#13;
PETROLEUM TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE PROJECT&#13;
KEY PROJECT ACTIVITIES AND IMPLEMENTATION SCHEDULE&#13;
Main Government Objectives    Project Component Activities     Expected ReauWt/lmpact        |Timing&#13;
A. SUPPORT FOR FOREIGN&#13;
INVESTMENT IN PETROLEUM&#13;
EXPLORATION AND PRODUCTION&#13;
Accelerate foreign investment   (i) Advisory services for      Implementation of               Oct. 1995 - May 1999&#13;
in petroleum exploration and  development and management of    well-structured project to&#13;
production, including        financial and contractual         reverse production decline&#13;
rehabilitation of producing  investment package for            in Guneshli field,&#13;
portion of Guneshli oilfield.  Guneshli oilfield              involving funancing from&#13;
rehabilitation.                  foreign companies.&#13;
(ii) Advisory services for       Selection of pipeline routing   Nov. 1995 - Dec. 1997&#13;
development and                  and initiation of pipeline&#13;
implementation of new oil        project, in collaboration&#13;
export pipeline project.         with international oil&#13;
companies and other investors.&#13;
(iii) Technical, financial       Conclusion of new petroleum     Nov. 1995 - Jan. 1999&#13;
and legal advisory services      exploration and production&#13;
to SOCAR for other petroleum     agreements, and development&#13;
projects involving foreign       of joint ventures in&#13;
investors.                       petroleum processing,&#13;
engineering and construction.&#13;
(iv) Legal study of Caspian      Improved understanding by       Oct. 1995 - Sept. 1996&#13;
Sea Boundaries issues.           SOCAR and Government of legal&#13;
issues connected with&#13;
(v) Advisory services on         Development of exploration      Nov. 1995 - Oct. 1997&#13;
petroleum licensing and          licensing framework,&#13;
exploration promotion.           including tendering&#13;
documents for structures&#13;
and blocks.&#13;
B. INSTITUTIONAL STRENGTHENING&#13;
OF THE PETROLEUM SUB-SECTOR&#13;
Development of legal         (i) Legal advisory services       Parliamentary approval of       Sept. 1995 - Sept. 199&#13;
framework for petroleum      for development of Petroleum      legal framework for&#13;
sub-sector and strengthening  Law.                             petroleum exploration and&#13;
of key institutions.                                           production, and associated&#13;
contractual, fiscal and&#13;
institutional regulations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-                                            Annex 4&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
Main Government Objectives    Project Component Activities        Expected Result/Impact           Timing&#13;
(ii) Training of SOCAR staff       Improvement of SOCAR staff       Nov. 1995 - Apr. 1997&#13;
in financial and commercial        capabilities to address&#13;
aspects of petroleum sector        economic, commercial and&#13;
operations.                        financial issues connected&#13;
with petroleum.&#13;
(iii) Purchase and                 Installation of 80 PCs with      Feb. 1996 - Mar. 1997&#13;
installation of PCs for            software and linked&#13;
SOCAR, and associated staff        hardware, and their routine&#13;
training.                          use by key SOCAR&#13;
departments in operations.&#13;
(iv) Purchase and                  Substantial improvement in       Feb. 1996 - May 1996&#13;
installation and operation of      SOCAR's ability to&#13;
satelite telecommunications        communicate with&#13;
system for SOCAR.                  foreign commercial counterparts.&#13;
C. ENERGY SECTOR&#13;
INVESTMENT STUDIES&#13;
Prepare key projects in       (i) Consultants for Oil Rocks       Concrete project proposals for   Nov. 1995 - Nov. 1997&#13;
petroleum sub-sector to        and other old offshore fields      addressing problems of Oil&#13;
address operational,          rehabilitation                      Rocks field, and other key&#13;
environmental and safety       study.                             older offshore fields, and&#13;
problems arising from                                             presentation to potential&#13;
deterioration of                                                  investors and financiers.&#13;
infrastructure, and&#13;
improve project preparation   (ii) Consultants for old            Concrete project proposals for   Nov. 1995 - Nov. 1997&#13;
capacity.                     onshore oil fields                  addressing problems of the old&#13;
rehabilitation study.              onshore fields, and&#13;
presentation to potential&#13;
investors and financiers.&#13;
(iii) Consultants for gas          Project proposals for            Nov. 1995 - Nov. 1996&#13;
processing facilities              reconstruction and expansion of&#13;
reconstruction study.              gas processing facilities of&#13;
SOCAR, in coordination with&#13;
international investors.&#13;
(iv) Technical and economic        Detailed feasibility study of    Oct. 1995-Oct. 1996&#13;
consultants for feasibility        options for development of&#13;
study of project for early         existing infrastructure to&#13;
oil exports.                       expand capacity for oil&#13;
exports, by mid-1996.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-26-&#13;
Annex 5&#13;
Page 1 of 1&#13;
SUPERVISION PLAN&#13;
Approximate  Activities          Staff Composition                     Staff&#13;
Dates                                                                  Weeks&#13;
5/95         Project Launch      Task Manager,                         8*&#13;
Workshop           Procurement/Disbursement/Component&#13;
Review             specialists&#13;
bid/proposal&#13;
packages&#13;
5/95-7/95    Review of work      Task Manager, Component specialists    4&#13;
progress: Final&#13;
timetables&#13;
9/95         Review Petroleum   Task Manager/Legal                     2&#13;
Legislation&#13;
9/95         Review progress,   Task Manager,                          6*&#13;
all components     Procurement/Disbursement/Component&#13;
specialists&#13;
3/96         Review Guneshli   Task Manager, Component specialists    5*&#13;
progress&#13;
9/96         Review progress,   Task Manager,                          8*&#13;
all components     Procurement/Disbursement/Component&#13;
specialists&#13;
5/97         Mid-term Review    Task Manager,                          8*&#13;
Procurement/Disbursement/Component&#13;
specialists&#13;
9/97         Review Guneshli   Task Manager, Petroleum specialists     5*&#13;
3/98         Review progress,   Task Manager, Component specialists    8*&#13;
all components&#13;
9/98         Review progress,   Task Manager, Component specialists    6*&#13;
all components&#13;
6/99         Review progress,   Task Manager,                          8*&#13;
all components,    Procurement/Disbursement/Component&#13;
Final inspection,    specialists&#13;
Final audits&#13;
TOTAL                                                                  66&#13;
= Mission)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
Annex 6&#13;
Page 1 of 1&#13;
DISBURSEMENT SCHEDULE&#13;
IDA fiscal year and        Semester       Cumulative      Cumulative&#13;
semester                     ------- (US $ million) ------    %&#13;
1995&#13;
First                      0.0                 0.0&#13;
Second                     0.1                 0.1               0.5&#13;
1996&#13;
First                       1.4                1.5               7.2&#13;
Second                     2.2                 3.7               17.8&#13;
1997&#13;
First                       3.0                6.7              32.2&#13;
Second                      3.7               10.4              50.0&#13;
1998&#13;
First                      4.2                14.6              70.2&#13;
Second                      2.4               17.0              81.7&#13;
1999&#13;
First                      2.2                19.2              92.3&#13;
Second                      1.6               20.8             100.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-28-&#13;
Annex 7&#13;
Page 1 of 4&#13;
PROJECT PERFORMANCE INDICATORS&#13;
The impact indicators for the project and measurements of its success are derived from the&#13;
key project objectives, which fall under the following categories:&#13;
(a)   Accelerating Foreign Private Investment and Financial Participation in&#13;
Petroleum Exploration and Production;&#13;
(b)   Strengthening Petroleum Sub-Sector Institutions;&#13;
(c)   Preparing Investment Projects in the Petroleum Sub-sector.&#13;
(A) Accelerating Foreign Private Investment and Financial Participation in Petroleum&#13;
Exploration and Production&#13;
Indicators                              Measurements&#13;
1. Develop and Implement Rehabilitation   i.  Technical and financial proposals&#13;
Project for Guneshli Oil field            developed and presented to financiers&#13;
and investors.&#13;
ii. Foreign financing (US$million)&#13;
committed and disbursed.&#13;
iii. Field oil production (rate of decline).&#13;
2. Develop Oil Export Pipeline and Early  i.  Pipeline project alternatives analyzed,&#13;
Oil Exports                               route agreed.&#13;
ii. Successful project implementation&#13;
structure established.&#13;
iii. SOCAR contributes fully to preparation&#13;
of early oil exports project.&#13;
iv. Early oil exports on target ( by mid-&#13;
1996).&#13;
v. Foreign financing (US$million)&#13;
committed and disbursed for major&#13;
export pipeline project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
Annex 7&#13;
Page 2 of 4&#13;
3. Attract New Foreign Investment in    i.  Acreage and field promotion packages&#13;
Petroleum Projects (Excl. Guneshli)     prepared and presented.&#13;
ii. Number of exploration and production&#13;
agreements concluded.&#13;
iii. Number of joint ventures in petroleum&#13;
processing, engineering, services etc.&#13;
iv. Foreign financing (US$million)&#13;
committed and disbursed.&#13;
(B) Strengthening Petroleum Sub-sector Institutions.&#13;
Indicators                             Measurements&#13;
1. Develop and Implement Petroleum      i.  Initial draft developed with foreign&#13;
Law.                                     advisors, and structured consultation&#13;
undertaken.&#13;
ii. Draft submitted to Parliament by&#13;
February 1996.&#13;
iii. Draft passed by Parliament.&#13;
iv. Number of petroleum agreements&#13;
passed under the new Law.&#13;
v. Clarification of responsibilities of&#13;
Government, SOCAR and other entities&#13;
under the Law.&#13;
2. Training of SOCAR Staff.             i.  Number of staff trained (target 200 by&#13;
Jan. 1997).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30-&#13;
Annex 7&#13;
Page 3 of 4&#13;
3. Installation of Computer and             i.  Detailed procurement and installation&#13;
Communications Equipment in SOCAR           plan for PCs developed.&#13;
ii. Number of PCs effectively installed&#13;
(incl. software and hardware- target 80&#13;
PCs by Jan. 1997).&#13;
iii. Number of staff trained in use of PCs.&#13;
iv. Installation of one satellite&#13;
communication system and staff trained&#13;
in use by Jun. 1996.&#13;
(C) Preparing Investment Projects in Petroleum Sub-sector&#13;
Indicators                                Measurements&#13;
1. Investment Projects for Rehabilitation    i.  Complete investment study by January&#13;
of Oil Rocks and Old Offshore Oilfields     1997.&#13;
ii. Follow up of investment study with&#13;
joint ventures with foreign companies&#13;
and/or projects with multilateral&#13;
financing.&#13;
2. Old Onshore Oilfield Restructuring       i.  Complete investment study by January&#13;
Projects                                    1997.&#13;
ii. Number of projects packaged and&#13;
presented to potential foreign investors&#13;
or financiers.&#13;
iii. Follow up with joint ventures with&#13;
foreign companies and/or projects with&#13;
multilateral financing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31 -&#13;
Annex 7&#13;
Page 4 of 4&#13;
3. Gas Processing Facilities             i.  Complete investment study by January&#13;
Reconstruction                           1997.&#13;
ii. Follow up of investment study with&#13;
joint venture with foreign companies&#13;
and/or projects with international&#13;
financing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="697524">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/03/697524/azerbaijan-petroleum-technical-assistance-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/03/697524/azerbaijan-petroleum-technical-assistance-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/03/697524/azerbaijan-petroleum-technical-assistance-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1995/03/28/000009265_3961008000645/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1995/03/28/000009265_3961008000645/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>P192</loan_no>
        <credit_no>2708</credit_no>
        <datestored>2001-04-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1995-03-28T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Azerbaijan - Petroleum Technical Assistance Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The main objectives of the Petroleum
            Technical Assistance Project are: 1) to accelerate foreign
            private investment and financial participation in petroleum
            exploration and production; b) to strengthen petroleum
            sub-sector institutions through development of petroleum
            legislation, training, and improvements in information
            systems; and c) to prepare investment projects in the
            petroleum sub-sector. The project will provide: 1) provision
            of resources to the State Oil Company of Azerbaijan Republic
            (SOCAR) to recruit financial, legal and technical advisors
            for: formulation and management of a project for the
            rehabilitation of the Guneshli field; exploration and
            development of other fields and construction of related
            infrastructure; legal studies on Caspian Sea boundary
            determination; development of an oil export pipeline; and
            petroleum licensing and exploration promotion; 2)
            development of a legislative and fiscal framework for
            petroleum exploration and production; 3) institutional
            strengthening of SOCAR through training, and introduction of
            information and communication systems; 4) detailed
            investment and restructuring studies of the older oil
            fields, gas processing facilities and oil export
            infrastructure improvements; 5) technical assistance for the
            Project Implementation Unit covering financial, procurement
            and project management services; and 6) an unallocated
            amount of US$1.0 million to cover additional project
            preparation activities and advisory services.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Azerbaijan - Petroleum Technical Assistance Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Azerbaijan - Petroleum Technical
            Assistance Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1995/03/697524/azerbaijan-petroleum-technical-assistance-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>AZ-Petroleum Ta -- P008282</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Energy Demand,Oil Refining &amp; Gas Industry,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Energy and Environment,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Energy</teratopic>
        <count>Azerbaijan</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Commonwealth of Independent States!$!80457</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3961008000645</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Oil and gas,Law and justice</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Energy</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Oil &amp; Gas</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Advisory services; Communication systems;
            Foreign investments; Information systems; Licencing;
            Petroleum; Petroleum engineering; Petroleum exploration;
            Petroleum exports; Petroleum legislation; Pipelines;
            Procurement; Project management; Technical assistance
            audits,banking systems,commercial
            banks,consumers,crude oil,crude oil exports,Debt,development
            strategy,domestic use,drilling,economic analysis,economic
            criteria,economic development,Economic Relations,economic
            situation,economics,economists,efficient use,efficient use
            of energy,electricity prices,employment,energy
            consumption,energy consumption per unit,energy prices,energy
            usage,energy use,engineering,environmental
            assessment,environmental
            issues,expenditures,exploitation,forecasts,fuel,gas and
            electricity,Gas distribution,gas imports,gas plant,gas
            prices,Gas Processing,Gas Processing Facilities,gas
            producer,Gas production,gas reserves,gas usage,GDP,Gross
            Domestic Product,inflation,interest rates,labor force,land
            use,liquid petroleum gas,national oil,natural gas,natural
            resources,net exports,Offshore Oil,Oil,oil and gas,oil
            companies,Oil Company,oil consumption,Oil Development,oil
            equivalent,oil exports,oil fields,oil industry,oil price,oil
            producing,Oil production,oil products,oil
            use,Petroleum,petroleum development,petroleum
            exploration,petroleum industry,Petroleum Law,petroleum
            legislation,petroleum markets,petroleum production,petroleum
            resources,pipeline,pipeline routing,pipeline
            system,pollution,price increases,primary
            energy,refineries,refining,Rocks,structural change,Technical
            Assistance,total costs,Treasury Bills,valuation
        </keywd>
        <owner>Infrastructure &amp; Energy Srvc Dpt (ECSIE)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Commonwealth of Independent States</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF035883-KAZAKSTAN - OIL AND GAS,TF034419-ECA REGION - PETROLUM AND
            PROJECT WORK,TF033097-RUSSIA - ENERGY,TF032455-AZERBAIJAN - OIL &amp; GAS,TF023074-PHRD-NATURAL GAS SYSTEM RECONSTRUCTION</trustfund>
        <repnb>T6377</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Demand</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Research and Surveys for Public Contracts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tracking Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mountains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Refineries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>State Associations</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Azerbaijan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>