<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>/ C Y3&#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
The World Bank         FPD Note No. 39                                            March 1995&#13;
0 e   Bettering Banking: Privatize Flows&#13;
___4_   and Let Sleeping Stocks Lie&#13;
Zlli&#142;&#142;..             S. Ramachandran&#13;
In transforming economies ...       In these circumstances, even if state-&#13;
This Note proposes that the immedi-  owned banks could be sold (and the&#13;
_    ._  i s~.  ate focus of financial reform in Cen-  reasons for pcssimiism on this score&#13;
tral and Eastern Europe should be   are set out in the box on page 2), it&#13;
on privatizing the flows of savings,    may be better to defer their sale. That&#13;
Banking reform is complex    which affect resource allocation, not  allows governments to credibly deny&#13;
and may require a variety of   on privatizing stocks, which repre-    deposit insurance to private banks that&#13;
solutions even in a single  sent sunk costs. It is easier for both   cannot be adequately supervised. And,&#13;
country. ThisNote suggests    technical and political reasons and    if state-owned banks were precluded&#13;
that at least in the reforming   more important for economic rea-    from intermediating flows, their priva-&#13;
economies of Central and  sons to redirect the flow of savings   tization could be deferred without&#13;
Eastern Europe, it may be  through private intermediaries, with  further rnisallocating resources.&#13;
better to concentrate on privVa-&#13;
tizing the intermediation of    better incentives to allocate credit&#13;
savingsflows ratber than  efficiently, than to privatize the stock  An alternative approach&#13;
banking stocks.         of accumulated savings in state-    Resource allocation depends on how&#13;
owned banks.                       flows of savings are invested-it matters&#13;
little whether the stock of earlier loans&#13;
The case for this approach to bank-   is in private or state-owned banks as&#13;
ing reform is based on the following  this reflects past decisions. The altema-&#13;
assessment: (1) prudential supervi-   tive to privatizing state-owned banks&#13;
sion will be inadequate for several   immediately, therefore, is to force the&#13;
years despite attempts to improve it,  intermediation of savings flows through&#13;
(2) private intermediation would    private entities that operate with the&#13;
improve resource allocation only if   right incentives, and to circumscribe the&#13;
the government does not (implicitly   activities of state-owned banks collec-&#13;
or explicitly) insure deposits, and if  tively while at the same time giving&#13;
it does, the familiar moral hazard  each state-owned bank the incentive to&#13;
problem appears, and (3) the politi-  improve its performance. Circumscrib-&#13;
cal pressures to protect deposits,  ing the activities of the state-owned&#13;
whether implicitly or explicitly, are    banks would be sufficient to largely&#13;
likely to be much lower if the bulk    privatize the flows of savings. Even if&#13;
of household deposits lie unthreat-   all savings flows were immediately&#13;
ened in state-owned banks.          privatized in this way, the stock of&#13;
m  =pD    Private Sector Development Department&#13;
H          FPD          Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
in the business of accepting cash from the public,&#13;
Privatization  pessimism   i            ;  -0    l=    their owners have both the incentive and the ability&#13;
Prompted byconcernsabout bank incentive  toallocate    to hide losses while attempting to recoup them&#13;
credit,a few bod reformersadvocateimmediateprivatiz    through overly risky ventures.2 When losses mount&#13;
tion,thoughtheyknowthatadequatebankingsuperision       and the pyramid-type scheme can no longer be cov-&#13;
is years away. Even if pri=atization of banks were deskered up, depositors lose spectacularly, and political&#13;
serviceintitutions,andpotentialbuyersmaypreferto srt    pressures to bail out depositors become inexorable.3&#13;
a bank fm scratch. Although a few state-owned banksSo governments must either supervise banks closely&#13;
thave been transforing themselves with remarkable alac-  to avert such failures-a technically difficult task,&#13;
rity, old abits die hard, andthestaffofstate-ownedbanks especially in transforming economies with fluctuat-&#13;
industry saff.(Restictingnewentrytoesure priatization  ing relative prices-or deny deposit insurance alto-&#13;
of existing state-owned banksisobviouslyshortsighted)  gether-a politically dicey choice.&#13;
fD;0:Secogn;d, potntial byr  oldb   ayo bingj for7cedto;&#13;
continuelending toinviable state-owned enterpises with  Setting up adequate prudential regulations and super-&#13;
;which the banik hashad along, cozy, incestuous reation- D vision is proving difficult for both technical and politi-&#13;
ship. These ties are more likely to be severed ifboththecal reasons. The technical difficulties stem from the&#13;
takestime. Even after three years,lesstan 30D percent of dearth of sufficiently skilled people and the migration&#13;
enterprise assetshavebee effectively prvatized intrans- of those trained in the requisite accounting techniques&#13;
0;;forming    00f economies,  ;  4;;;     z D:         to better-paying positions elsewhere in the economy.&#13;
Raising pay scales or contracting out banking supervi-&#13;
And0 even if these two problems are sovd privatizat Dion    1 aision is easier said than done. Political difficulties stem&#13;
from the tremendous clout of debtor enterprises, often&#13;
intres raesflutuae nde a tailiatin rogam  ndstate-owned, in pressing for additional bank loans and&#13;
many well-mn debtor enterprises become financially     averting defaults that threaten employment. Improve-&#13;
strapped. This happened in Mexico, where ex post real  ments in prudential regulations and supervision are&#13;
interest rates hovered beteen 20and 45 percent ayearfor therefore painfully slow and erratic, and while the&#13;
twoyeas fte te sccssfl tabliatin rogaminto- attempt should not stop, one should not count on&#13;
duced in 1988. After finlly falling, they aveshotupagan results for several years-too long for intermediation&#13;
when creditor banks re dragged downwit debtorenter-    by state-owned banks to continue unchecked.&#13;
prises, the poitca prssr oin tegovrnet t potc&#13;
households' savings-even jf deposits were not explicitThe altemative to supervision is for the government to&#13;
insured-becomes irresistile. Thus, implcit (or explicit)credibly deny deposit insurance to private intermediar-&#13;
deposit insurance makes the government the economic  .  ies. This is only possible if the government provides a&#13;
blypriate bak. o, venif  bak wre tivtizd nw, safe alternative, such as insuring the bulk of household&#13;
subsequent losses-very likely in turbulent times-would  deposits in state-owned banks. Rather than limit de-&#13;
cause the bank to boomerang back into govement ands.   posit insurance by amount, the proposed approach&#13;
limits it by type of institution.' Private banks would not&#13;
be covered by government deposit insurance simply&#13;
household savings would migrate only gradually (as    because the government cannot oversee them suffi-&#13;
deposits matured) to other banks, allowing all banks    ciently well. However, private banks should be free to&#13;
a fair chance to respond to the new, more credible        make alternative arrangements-for example, devising&#13;
rules of the game.                                        private insurance or mutual insurance schemes to reas-&#13;
sure depositors. At the same time, raising shareholder&#13;
Private intermediaries, but under different rules   equity ratios to the far higher levels that prevailed in&#13;
Banks generally have little equity (even the 8 per-       the early part of this century would both reassure de-&#13;
cent required under the BIS guidelines is far less        positors and reduce the incentive for fraud. Entry may&#13;
than in most nonbank firms), and because they are    still require some screening to prevent obviously inap-&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
propriate operators from defrauding depositors. Entry   others. Having a credible plan for later bank privati-&#13;
by foreign banks concerned with maintaining high  zation dangles a reward for the better bank manag-&#13;
international reputations would be an excellent ap-  ers, who may be retained by the private buyers on&#13;
proach, although many countries succumb to xeno-  more attractive terms. In addition to this somewhat&#13;
phobia and foolishly preclude it.               distant carrot, a more immediate stick of additional&#13;
strictures may be useful. Punishing the worst bank&#13;
Constrain state-owned banks collectively        both sets an example (dramatic acts attract attention)&#13;
There are many ways to restrict the intermediation of   and hastens its improvement. Setting a 100 percent&#13;
flows by state-owned banks. The best choice depends  marginal reserve requirement or a cap on nongov-&#13;
on the circumstances. One way is to set collective  emient lending (while simultaneously reducing&#13;
credit limits on state-owned banks, something akin to  state borrowings from, and reserve requirements on,&#13;
what is often done under stabilization programs. Im-   other banks) would do this effectively. Preventing a&#13;
posing such a nominal limit would shrink state-owned  bank from intermediating flows does not shut it&#13;
banks in real terms, and even if the limit were in-  down, but the resulting "liquidity crisis" requires&#13;
dexed to the price level, the share would fall as the    immediate central bank action.&#13;
economy grows. Alternatively, state-owned banks&#13;
could be limited to buying only government paper,    The salubrious effects&#13;
thereby automatically restricting their growth to less    The central bank not wishing to immediately close a&#13;
than the budget deficit (generally a smaller percentage  particular bank would have to fund it in one of three&#13;
of GDP than the GDP growth rate). Such a restriction   ways: (1) increase the monetary base-or print mon-&#13;
would also make the banks' portfolios less risky while  ey-which is inflationary, (2) direct other (better,&#13;
simultaneously allowing private banks to assess bor-   state-owned) banks to provide the funds, or (3) de-&#13;
rower creditworthiness-a discretionary task particu-   mand bits of the bank's physical assets (such as&#13;
larly responsive to market incentives. Despite such  branches) as a quid pro quo and sell them immedi-&#13;
limits, state-owned banks would still intermediate  ately to other banks. The first is ruled out for obvious&#13;
funds to the extent that their old loans were repaid    reasons; the second merely freezes the proportion of&#13;
rather than merely rolled over, but only those state-    flows controlled by each state-owned bank and elimi-&#13;
owned banks that made sound loans could do this.    nates any incentive to improve; so the third alterna-&#13;
tive is the best. The message to all banks would be&#13;
Restricting intermediation by state-owned banks  clear ("if you can't cut costs and operate more effi-&#13;
would automatically redirect intermediation through   ciently, you won't survive intact") and, equally impor-&#13;
private entities, whether formal or informal. The  tant, credible because the bulk of the existing stock&#13;
basic accounting identity-savings equals invest-  of household deposits would remain secure.&#13;
ment-always holds, and what is not channeled&#13;
through state-owned banks gets intermediated else-   Although all state-owned banks would not be priva-&#13;
where.5 Although some may worry that nonbank    tized immediately (especially if other state-owned&#13;
intermediaries, especially informal lenders, do not    banks buy the pieces offered for sale), they would&#13;
allocate credit efficiently, the comparison must be    face market pressures right away. With deposit and&#13;
with the poorly functioning state-owned banks, not  lending rates free, private banks would try to attract&#13;
with some ideal banking system.                 depositors by offering a higher interest rate (and to&#13;
attract borrowers by offering cheaper rates for&#13;
Punish the worst offender                       loans). State-owned banks would have to respond&#13;
State-owned banks are a heterogeneous group, and   with better service and lower spreads or see their&#13;
while most are overstaffed and inefficient, some are   depositors and borrowers migrate to private banks.&#13;
worse than others. Constraining state-owned banks&#13;
collectively but not individually provides each with   This approach essentially prescribes to banks the&#13;
an incentive to improve and grow at the expense of  same medicine that has proved effective with other&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
state-owned enterprises-a cash ("hard budget")                    kept at bay. State-owned banks are not replaced by&#13;
constraint. It works by confiscating incremental de-              laissez-faire banking overnight: rather, the two exist&#13;
posits through the proposed restrictions (100 per-                simultaneously but separately, allowing time for pru-&#13;
cent marginal reserve requirements, credit limits,                dential supervision to improve. The public is likely&#13;
limits on holdings of nongovernment paper). State-                to support this approach because it widens choice:&#13;
owned banks are thereby forced to service their                   they may have insured deposits in state banks or&#13;
deposits from  lending operations, and those that                 uninsured (though higher-yield) deposits elsewhere.&#13;
cannot are broken up gradually and sold.                          Any subsequent private bank failure only penalizes&#13;
those who chose a bank unwisely. Last but not least,&#13;
Central banks already have the necessary power to                 the government does not risk public "failure" as with&#13;
impose such penalties and restrict the activities of              an unsuccessful attempt to sell a state-owned bank.&#13;
insolvent banks. Such raw  power has politically un-&#13;
acceptable ramifications and so is rarely used. But a    ' A bank's negative net worth is not an impediment to privatization be-&#13;
subtle application by privatizing flows and letting                cause it is easily remedied. The government could either sell the bank to&#13;
sleeping stocks lie is just as effective as outright               whoever bids the least negative price (as the Resolution Trust Corpora-&#13;
tion in the United States does) or recapitalize the bank just before selling&#13;
privatization in improving resource allocation.                     it. Prematurely recapitalizing a state-owned bank, even if only to bling it&#13;
up to the minimum required, would likely have to be repeated (the well-&#13;
Risks and benefits                                                 known time inconsistency problem) and would relax the hard budget&#13;
constraint that lies at the heart of the proposed approach.&#13;
The main risks of this approach are (1) the possibility           2It is in this sense that "bad stocks could contaminate flows," but this&#13;
that politicians will backtrack on reforms and                      applies only to private banks with negative net worth whose owners&#13;
(2) bank fraud. It is easier for governments to quietly            or managers are gambling with other peoples' money without their&#13;
undo flow privatization because there is no explicit                knowledge or permission.&#13;
undo flo   privatiation beause thee is no  xplicitThere are two main reasons for treating banks differently than other&#13;
"public act," such as selling a bank. To help combat               enterprises in market economies. First, banks not only intermediate&#13;
fraud, promoters and managers of new banks must be                  between lenders and borrowers but also are often responsible for the&#13;
effectively screened. In addition, the personal liability           payments system (efficient check clearing and wire transfers) on which&#13;
effectively                                       ~~~~~~~~~~~~~commerce often depends. And second, the perverse incentives created&#13;
of managers and owners should be increased. This                    by deposit insurance require the govemment (or the central bank as its&#13;
could be done by lifting the minimum  required owner-    agent) to safeguard its own interests by supervising banks (often restrict-&#13;
ship stake to the 15-30 percent that prevailed early in            ing banks' activities to make such oversight easier), a role related to but&#13;
ihis century,before the arrival of deposit insurance,  conceptually distinct from the lender of last resort. However, the pay-&#13;
this century, before tearvlodpsiinunc.                              ments system in many countries is based on transferring suitcases of&#13;
currency notes without banks' involvement, so a banking failure in&#13;
On the benefit side, besides the economic merits                    these circumstances would not bring commerce to a halt.&#13;
outlinedabove, te propoed approch has plitical    Indeed, new (private) banks could even be free from reserve require-&#13;
outlined above, the proposed approach has political                 ments if they were outside the payments system and not eligible for&#13;
advantages that may make it more likely to succeed                  central bank rediscounts or refinancing. The central bank could allow&#13;
than earlier efforts to reform  the banking sector.                two different types of new private intermediaries: banks, which would&#13;
Each bank has the opportunity to survive by im-                     have some privileges and concomitant obligations, and nonbanks, which&#13;
would be free from all requirements of the banking laws (but subject, of&#13;
proving its own operations. Threatened bank man-                    course, to civil law of torts and criminal law in cases of fraud).&#13;
agers who might otherwise combine to oppose or                     If depositors strongly favor the safe and familiar state-owned banks,&#13;
sabotage reform, especially when they (understand-                 the restrictions would lower deposit interest rates in state banks (being&#13;
ably) resent being punished for obeying the govern-    forced to buy only treasury bills, they could only offer less) or raise&#13;
ably) resent being punished for obeying the govern-                 them elsewhere until the public was indifferent between the two-or&#13;
ment's earlier wishes, are less likely to collude when              both-but flows would be privately intermediated.&#13;
each is given the chance to improve. No new  laws&#13;
are needed, so populist parliamentarians may be                   S. Ramachandran, Senior Econoniist, Private Sector Development Department&#13;
This series is published to share ideas and invite discussion. It covers financial and private sector development as well as&#13;
industry and energy. The views expressed are those of the authors and are not intended to represent an official statement of&#13;
Bank policy or strategy. ® Printed on recycled paper.&#13;
Comments are welcome. Please call the FPD Note line to leave a message: 202-458-1111; or contact Suzanne Smith, editor, Room&#13;
G8105, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC 20433, or Internet address ssmith7@worldbank.org.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="697584">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/03/697584/bettering-banking-private-flows-sleeping-stocks-lie
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/03/697584/bettering-banking-private-flows-sleeping-stocks-lie</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/03/697584/bettering-banking-private-flows-sleeping-stocks-lie</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1995/03/01/000009265_3980420172942/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1995/03/01/000009265_3980420172942/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1995-03-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2001-04-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Bettering banking : private flows and let
            sleeping stocks lie
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This Note proposes that the immediate
            focus of financial reform in Central and Eastern Europe
            should be on privatizing the intermediation of savings
            flows, which affect resource allocation, not on privatizing
            banking stocks, which represent sunk costs. It is easier for
            both technical and political reasons and more important for
            economic reasons to redirect the flow of savings through
            private intermediaries, with better incentives to allocate
            credit efficiently, than to privatize the stock of
            accumulated savings in state-owned banks. The case for this
            approach to banking reform is based on the assessments that:
            1) prudential supervision will be inadequate for several
            years despite attempts to improve it; 2) private
            intermediation would improve resource allocation only if the
            government does not insure deposits; and 3) the political
            pressures to protect deposits are likely to be much lower if
            the bulk of household deposits lie unthreatened in
            state-owned banks. The main risks of this approach are the
            possibility that politicians will backtrack on reforms and
            bank fraud. On the benefit side, besides the economic
            merits, the proposed approach has political advantages that
            may make it more likely to succeed.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Bettering banking : private flows and let
            sleeping stocks lie
        </docna>
        <display_title>Bettering banking : private flows
            and let sleeping stocks lie</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1995/03/697584/bettering-banking-private-flows-sleeping-stocks-lie</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Financial Crisis Management &amp; Restructuring,Municipal Financial Management,Financial Intermediation,Hazard Risk Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Urban Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Europe and Central Asia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Ramachandran, S.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980420172942</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Privatization-DV</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector,FPD note No. 39</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Urban Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Private Sector Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Savings; Bank deposits; Stocks;
            Denationalization; Interest rates; Fraud; Deposit insurance;
            Allocation of resources; Banking reform; State-owned banks;
            Private intermediation; Supervision
            accounting,assets,bank failure,bank
            fraud,bank rediscounts,banking laws,Banking reform,banking
            sector,banking system,banks,central bank,Central
            banks,deposit
            insurance,depositors,deposits,employment,financial
            reform,foreign banks,gambling,guidelines,insolvent
            banks,insured deposits,interest rates,lender of last
            resort,liquidity,market incentives,migration,moral
            hazard,nonbanks,penalties,portfolios,private banks,private
            insurance,Privatization,prudential regulations,reserve
            requirement,reserve requirements,resource
            allocation,sabotage,savings,stabilization,state banks
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off of VP, FPD - WB (FPDVP)</owner>
        <repnb>16983</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>BoD</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Cost of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Impact of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>Carreer Guidance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Job Fairs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arms Length Agencies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Mapping</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting Out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Chains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Delivery Arrangements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Standards, Service Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking and Finance Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Burden of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outsourcing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Resolution and Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deposit Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Laws and Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Law</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>