<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Reprt No. T-6411-GUA&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
GUYANA&#13;
FINANCIAL SECTOR AND BUSINESS ENVIRONMENT PROJECT&#13;
NOVEMBER 22, 1994&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY AND EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Currency Unit - Guyana Dollar (G$)&#13;
Exchange Rate Effective November 22, 1994&#13;
US$1.00 = G$142.5&#13;
G$ 1.00 = US$0.0071&#13;
GOVERNMENT OF GUYANA FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January 1 to December 31&#13;
GLOSSARY OF ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
BOG           -    Bank of Guyana (Central Bank)&#13;
BSD           -   Banking Supervision Department&#13;
CAMEL         -   Capital Adequacy/Asset Quality/Management/Earnings/Liquidity&#13;
CAS           -   Country Assistance Strategy&#13;
CIF           -   Cost, Insurance and Freight&#13;
COFA          -   Cooperative Financial Institutions Act&#13;
ERP           -   Economic Recovery Program&#13;
ESAF          -    Enhanced Structural Adjustment Facility&#13;
FIA                Financial Institutions Act&#13;
FIAS          -    Foreign Investment Advisory Service&#13;
FISBEC        -   Financial Sector and Business Environment Credit&#13;
GAIBANK       -   Guyana Agricultural and Industrial Development Bank&#13;
GCIS          -   Guyana Cooperative Insurance Service&#13;
GDP           -   Gross Domestic Product&#13;
GBTI          -    Guyana Bank for Trade and Industry&#13;
GNCB          -   Guyana National Cooperative Bank&#13;
GOG           -   Government of Guyana&#13;
GUYMIDA    -    Guyana Business Promotion Agency (disbanded December 1993)&#13;
ICB           -    International Competitive Bidding&#13;
IDA           -   International Development Association&#13;
IDB           -    Inter-American Development Bank&#13;
IMF           -   International Monetary Fund&#13;
LATEN         -   LAC Technical Department: Environment Division&#13;
LCB           -   Local Competitive Bidding&#13;
LDP           -   Letter of Development Policy&#13;
MOF           -   Ministry of Finance&#13;
NBIC          -   National Bank for Industry and Commerce&#13;
PCRs          -   Project Completion Report&#13;
PFP           -    Policy Framework Paper&#13;
PPARs         -   Project Performance Audit Reports&#13;
PSDAC         -   Private Sector Development Adjustment Credit&#13;
SDR           -    Special Drawing Rights&#13;
UNDP          -    United Nations Development Programme&#13;
USAID         -   United States Agency for International Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
GUYANA - FINANCIAL SECTOR AND BUSINESS ENVIRONMENT PROJECT&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX - THE PROJECT&#13;
Introduction&#13;
1.          The objective of the Financial Sector and Business Environment (FISBEC) Project is to&#13;
establish an appropriate regulatory framework in the financial sector, and to encourage private sector&#13;
development, through assistance in (a) the strengthening of banking supervision and monetary&#13;
management functions, (b) privatization of public enterprises, and (c) facilitating foreign and domestic&#13;
investment in Guyana. The total project cost is estimated at US$ 4.0 million, of which, up to US$ 3.5&#13;
million would be financed through an IDA Credit and US$ 0.5 million would be funded by the&#13;
Government of Guyana. Based on discussions with other cofinancing sources during appraisal, some of&#13;
the project costs would likely be financed from other sources, namely the IMF and the U.K. The figures&#13;
shown in the cost tables below are therefore provisional and will be confirmed once the availability of&#13;
cofinanced funding is firmed up. The project would cover a three-year period, and would be completed&#13;
by end-1997.&#13;
Strengthening Banking Supervision&#13;
Background and Sector Strategy&#13;
2.           Supervision of the financial system  had been very limited until an institutional&#13;
strengthening program in the Banking Supervision Department (BSD) of the Bank of Guyana (BOG) was&#13;
initiated with IMF support in 1991. Inspection had been infrequent, reporting limited, scrutiny of&#13;
information provided and account reconciliation limited, and staff largely untrained. Moreover, the&#13;
supervisory capacity via the Cooperative Financial Institutions Act (COFA) has been limited to exercising&#13;
some input through positions in the management of individual institutions. Accomplishments since 1991&#13;
include: (a) development of improved information submission from commercial banks to the BOG for&#13;
purposes of tracking prudential variables; (b) development of a performance tracking system for offsite&#13;
analysis; (c) review of the 20 largest borrowers in each institution; (d) initiation of one round of credit&#13;
portfolio examinations in each institution, with loan classification in accordance with the criteria proposed&#13;
by the Center for Economic Studies in Latin America and the Caribbean; (e) completion of 3 full-scope&#13;
inspections: (f) recruitment of approximately half of the staff needed for the BSD, and (g) on-the-job and&#13;
external training of staff.&#13;
3.           The draft Financial Institutions Act (FIA) to be presented to Parliament would broaden&#13;
BOG authority to include all deposit-taking institutions, strengthen BOG's regulatory authority, mandate&#13;
minimum capital requirements and impose prudential standards including, inter alia, capital adequacy&#13;
requirements, limits on lending concentration, and limits on lending to related parties. Two fundamental&#13;
effects of the implementation of the Act would be the expansion in the scope of prudential regulations&#13;
applied and a similar expansion in the scope of institutions subject to BOG authority. The Government&#13;
has agreed to pass and begin implementation of the FIA prior to negotiations of the Private Sector&#13;
Development Adjustment Credit (PSDAC). In the draft Letter of Development Policy (LDP) of the&#13;
PSDAC, the Government would agree to strengthen the institutional capacity of the BOG.&#13;
4.           In order to ensure public confidence in the financial system and encourage efficient&#13;
financial intermediation, the program for institutional strengthening of the BOG's supervisory capacity&#13;
will be continued and expanded, including expansion of supervision to select non-bank financial&#13;
institutions in accordance with the revised FIA. To strengthen banking supervision on a sustainable basis,&#13;
11'22/94 9:51am&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
mechanisms for retaining qualified staff are under consideration, such as salary enhancement. In addition,&#13;
the continuity of this function would also need to be strengthened and eventually be made self-sustainable&#13;
via the establishment of banking supervision fees charged to financial institutions. These fees are aimed&#13;
at compensating the Government for the considerable oversight and risk identification/amelioration&#13;
responsibilities benefitting the banking sector as a whole, and would also be used to cover credit risk&#13;
information services provided to banks, as would be available once the central credit risk system was&#13;
established under the project.  In the meantime, BOG has set out a long term  budget plan for&#13;
implementation in BSD, with a substantial staffing complement of 18 individuals.&#13;
Technical Assistance Requirements&#13;
5.            Technical Assistance for the BSD will support a three-year program  to strengthen&#13;
supervision, including the following:&#13;
* A Banking Supervision Policy Advisor would continue to provide guidance in the development of&#13;
prudential norms through implementing regulations and circulars, develop prudential criteria for a&#13;
surveillance system with reports based on CAMEL indicators and industry and sectoral analyses; assist&#13;
in strengthening the management of BSD; and assist in the specific responsibilities of the BSD&#13;
including licensing of new institutions.&#13;
* An Operational Advisor and Inspector/Trainer would train staff in on-site and off-site examination&#13;
techniques including credit evaluation, account reconciliation, risk concentration and collateral&#13;
assessment.  Such individual would lead and provide guidance in general and specific on-site&#13;
examinations and in off-site operating procedures;&#13;
* A Legal Advisor would be engaged on a short-term basis to assist in the drafting of implementing&#13;
regulations;&#13;
* Overseas Courses would be used to supplement on-the-job training provided to staff by the two&#13;
advisors above, including the course program offered by the Federal Reserve of the U.S. and the&#13;
Center for Economic Studies of Latin America and the Caribbean;&#13;
* Select financing would be available for office equipment--desktop computers for offsite analysis, laptop&#13;
computers for onsite analysis, a laser printer and a fax machine; and&#13;
* The BSD will install a Credit Risk qualification system, whereby the outstanding credits by individual&#13;
exposure (individuals and companies) would be centralized across the financial system.  Such&#13;
information would not only greatly assist in prudential control of the financial system -- select&#13;
dissemination of the exposure of individual clients would also assist banks in managing their own&#13;
prudential risks. A specialized consultant and a desktop computer with significant capacity, application&#13;
software and specialized training would be financed for this purpose.&#13;
Cost Estimate&#13;
6.            The total estimated cost of the program  outlined below is US$ 996,800 of which&#13;
US$ 966,800 would be financed under the Credit. Potential IMF financing would likely fund about&#13;
US$ 200,000 of these costs.&#13;
Support to Strengthen Monetary Management&#13;
Background and Sector Strategy&#13;
7.            The IMF has to date provided significant support to the BOG in monetary management.&#13;
In April, 1993 a Technical Assistance Mission of the Monetary and Exchange Affairs Department&#13;
conducted an in-depth assessment of these specific needs and carried out a follow-up mission in January-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
Table 1 - Estimated Cost of Strengthening the Banking  February, 1994. Further, the IMF&#13;
Supervision Department of the Bank of Guyana (US$)   provided support for an advisor to the&#13;
Research Department from 1990-&#13;
1993, is currently supporting a&#13;
Item                        Total   Counter-  Proposed    macroeconomic  advisor  to  the&#13;
Cost     part    for IDA     Governor, and expects shortly, to&#13;
Financed    Credit    fund an advisor on the organization&#13;
Banking Supervision Advisor   363,600          363,600   and methods of BOG.  The IMF&#13;
Inspector/lTrainer/Advisor  363,600    30,000   333,600   assessment establishes a program of&#13;
Legal Advisor               12,000              12,000   measures to improve the monetary&#13;
Overseas Courses           125,000             125,000    management functions of BOG.  It&#13;
Credit Risk Sys. &amp; Advisor  70,500              70,500   also includes measures to improve the&#13;
Computers/Equip./Sys.      62,100               62,100   tender process and to improve the&#13;
Total               996,800    30,000   966,800   overall treasury management through&#13;
the  introduction  of  longer-term&#13;
instruments. Most important, the report indicates a process for initiating fluid and transparent open-&#13;
market operations and strengthening foreign exchange market integration through the establishment of&#13;
a foreign exchange trading unit.&#13;
Technical Assistance Requirements&#13;
8.            The Project would support assistance by two short term consultants with experience in&#13;
monetary management to work with the Central Bank's Research Department according to the strategy&#13;
developed with IMF assistance. The individuals' Terms of Reference would be to:&#13;
* Develop open market operations within a monetary programming framework, and establish a money&#13;
market unit with front office (dealer) functions and back office support;  develop systems and&#13;
procedures for Treasury Bill tenders, as well as secondary markets in T-Bills and other money market&#13;
instruments, and communication of such procedures to market participants;&#13;
* Develop and implement a schedule for the use of a separated portfolio of Treasury Bills for monetary&#13;
policy objectives, and develop improved monetary forecasting and reserve money programming&#13;
techniques; and&#13;
* Develop improved procedures, and train BOG staff in money and capital markets, and foreign&#13;
exchange trading.&#13;
9.            Consultant advice and training would be carried out through visits by experts on short-&#13;
term contracts. Selected office and computer equipment would be financed to enhance the execution and&#13;
analytical support for the above functions. The expected outcomes would include training of staff,&#13;
operationalizing the afore-mentioned processes, and preparing detailed manuals and technical guidelines&#13;
delineating implementation steps for carrying out and sustaining the above procedures.&#13;
Cost Estimate&#13;
10.          The estimated cost of the program outlined below is US$ 102,000 which would be&#13;
financed under the Credit. Potential identified IMF financing would likely cover about $30,000 of these&#13;
costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
Restructuring   State-owned   Financial      Table 2 - Estimated Cost of Strengthening&#13;
Institutions                               Monetary Management in the Bank of Guyana&#13;
Background and Sector Strategy                               (S$)&#13;
11.   Guyana's banking system has until  Item              Total    Counter-  Proposed&#13;
recently been dominated by State-owned                     Cost      part    for IDA&#13;
institutions.    The  Guyana  National                             Financed    Credit&#13;
Cooperative Bank (GNCB), established by   Dev. of Open&#13;
the Government in 1970, holds 55% of the    Market Oper.    51,700              51,700&#13;
deposit accounts in the country. GNCB has   Foreign Exchg.&#13;
faced significant difficulties including large    Operations  43,300            43,300&#13;
portfolio  losses   despite  repeated   Equipment           7,000                7,000&#13;
recapitalization.  Most important, GNCB&#13;
has suffered from a small level of earning    t&#13;
assets when compared to its large and&#13;
increasing deposit base. In 1990 the Government installed new management at GNCB and took measures&#13;
to financially and operationally restructure the institution. The institution has suffered from weak credit&#13;
control procedures, information systems and a potentially overdimensioned infrastructure. While GNCB&#13;
again faced severe losses in 1992, it returned to profitability in late 1993. The tightening of credit&#13;
procedures addressed many of the worst abuses. While the Government has initiated measures to improve&#13;
loan recovery, GNCB requires further financial and operational restructuring in order to place it on a&#13;
viable footing while seeking to minimize the fiscal exposure which the Government faces to cover&#13;
depositors and maintain depositor confidence.&#13;
12.          The Guyana Agricultural and Industrial Development Bank (GAIBANK) was&#13;
established as a development bank to provide credit and related advisory services for agricultural and&#13;
industrial projects. The institution has been prohibited from taking public deposits, and funded its lending&#13;
from donor funds, and more recently from Government resources and loan recoveries. Loan conditions&#13;
generally reflected the specified conditions mandated by the agency lending funds to GAIBANK. It has&#13;
had seven branches and 277 employees. GAIBANK has experienced severe financial difficulties, owing&#13;
primarily to the poor quality of its loan portfolio. The latter has reflected fluctuations in the spread&#13;
between its borrowing and lending rates, sharp changes in the valuation of assets and liabilities from&#13;
exchange rate depreciation, and problem loans.&#13;
13.          While GAIBANK has not suffered from high administrative costs, it has been very&#13;
inefficient. It reduced its branch network in 1992 from eight to seven branches and reduced the size of&#13;
selected branches. GAIBANK began a process of restructuring in 1990, including staff reductions and&#13;
improvements in operating procedures. A capital injection of G$100 million was provided in 1991 to pull&#13;
GAIBANK out of its negative equity position. However, the restructuring process did not go far enough.&#13;
A team of consultants was scheduled to begin development of a restructuring plan in early 1992, but&#13;
never started work. In early 1993, measures were adopted to monitor and improve loan recovery,&#13;
including improved tracking of loan arrears.&#13;
14.          The Government has agreed prior to negotiations of the PSDAC to announce the merger&#13;
of GNCB and GAIBANK into a new institution. The institution would be commercially run and would&#13;
undertake first-tier development banking only through a special window financed directly from the&#13;
treasury and managed as an off-balance sheet agency account. An Action Plan for the merged institution&#13;
has been agreed-to in the context of the PSDAC and progress has already been achieved in beginning the&#13;
classification and segregation of the loan portfolios, and the completion of 1993 audits for both&#13;
institutions. In addition, the capitalization and financial structure of the Loan Recovery Agency (see&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
below) will need to take into account the level of non-performing loans which it can administer while&#13;
simultaneously allowing the merged bank to function within a viable financial structure with positive net&#13;
worth and net earnings.&#13;
15.           Loan Recovery Unit. The Government has agreed to establish a Loan Recovery Unit&#13;
which would be expected to pursue loan recovery measures including negotiation with client parties&#13;
(according to guidelines to be established at start-up) and to initiate legal action for: (i) judgement against&#13;
loan collateral; (ii) judgement against a business' or individual's cash flow; and/or (iii) judgement against&#13;
other assets securing loan. Moreover, such Unit would be charged with tendering assets received in loan&#13;
recoveries through a process to be established upon start-up. Finally, the Unit would be charged with&#13;
maintaining up-to-date accounts and, where loans have been renegotiated, to maintain vigilance over&#13;
collections.&#13;
16.                  For other public sector financial institutions, the Government intends to implement&#13;
reform measures including privatizations where appropriate, as set out in its Policy Framework Paper for&#13;
1994-1996. For those institutions earmarked for privatization, technical assistance under the Privatization&#13;
Unit component (described below) would be provided.&#13;
Technical Assistance Requirements&#13;
17.           Under the Government's plan to merge GNCB and GAIBANK, and within the framework&#13;
of policy measures specified under the PSDAC, the project would support advisors as follows:&#13;
* A credit policy advisor would assist the merged institution in: (i) adopting uniform credit policies; (ii)&#13;
ensuring that such policies allow the effective control and management of portfolio risks; and (iii)&#13;
developing loan review and approval procedures that ensure that the credit policies are effectively&#13;
implemented.&#13;
* An accounting and financial control advisor would assist the merged institution in: (i) establishing a&#13;
uniform accounting system for the merged entity; (ii) developing new accounts and procedures manuals&#13;
for implementing the new accounting system; and (iii) developing existing, and purchasing new&#13;
computer equipment to implement the accounting and financial control system.&#13;
* A restructuring and rationalization advisor would assist the merged institution in: (i) establishing and&#13;
carrying out a strategy for staff rationalization; and (ii) establishing and carrying out a strategy for&#13;
branch rationalization based on a cost-benefit assessment of each branch.&#13;
18.   The Government would provide&#13;
countrpar funing o fun  an  dvisr toTable 3 - Estimated Cost of Technical Assistance to&#13;
counterpart funding to fund an advisor toSte-wdFiaclIistuon(U$&#13;
th   Lo. ReoeyU.tt rvd                           State-owned Financial Institutions (US$)&#13;
the Loan Recovery Unit to provide&#13;
specialist advice in: (i) valuation of&#13;
financial and fixed assets; (ii) investigatory  Item              Total    Counter-   Proposed&#13;
mechanisms  to  locate  borrowers  and                             Cost      part      for IDA&#13;
property, including collateral; (iii) legal                                Financed    Credit&#13;
procedures   for  initiating   court          Restructuring of    428,600               428,600&#13;
proceedings; (iv) moral suasion recovery       GNCB-Gaibank&#13;
mechanisms; and (v) asset sale procedures&#13;
for collateral seized in loan recoveries.     Dev. of Loan       201,700    194,600       7,100&#13;
Select financing would also be provided       Recovery Unit&#13;
for office equipment--desktop computers,             Total       630,300    194,600    435,700&#13;
a laser printer and a fax machine.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
Cost Estimate&#13;
19.           The estimated cost of the program outlined in the Table above is US$ 630,300 of which&#13;
US$ 435,700 would be financed under the Credit.&#13;
Strengthening the Privatization Process&#13;
Background anid Sector Strategy&#13;
20.           The State has dominated most aspects of economic life in Guyana, accounting for more&#13;
than three-fourths of GDP. In addition to its presence in public infrastructure, the Government of Guyana&#13;
(GOG) controls major industries such as sugar processing and bauxite mining as well as a myriad of other&#13;
commercial enterprises across sectors. The former Government began under the Economic Recovery&#13;
Program to privatize public corporations, privatizing or liquidating 14 enterprises between 1987 and&#13;
October 1992. However, the lack of clarity of the transaction process contributed to considerable public&#13;
dissatisfaction with privatization. The program was subsequently halted by the PPP/Civic administration&#13;
in November 1992. The new government has moved cautiously; the first announcement on privatization&#13;
was made in July 1993, when a policy framework for Privatization was passed by Parliament. This was&#13;
followed in August with the setting up of a Privatization Board--a Cabinet-level Committee--that would&#13;
oversee privatization and in January 1994 by a public announcement of the first entities to be privatized&#13;
under the new policy.&#13;
21.           The GOG, with the assistance of IDA, has adopted a framework which sets out the&#13;
organization and procedures for continuing the privatization process. The objectives of the privatization&#13;
policy, are to transfer to the private sector the management, ownership and control of all commercially-&#13;
oriented public enterprises. The GOG has put in place a special executing authority or "agent" to restart&#13;
the program and to work on behalf of the Government. A Privatization Unit (PU) within the Ministry&#13;
of Finance (MOF) has been set up for this purpose, which reports to the Privatization Board, chaired by&#13;
the Minister of Finance. The PU has prepared operational guidelines to ensure that each privatization&#13;
transaction adheres to a standard set of procedures that is transparent and subject to public scrutiny.&#13;
Under the Privatization Policy, the entities to be privatized are decided by the GOG through the&#13;
Privatization Board, supported by the PU. The aim of the first phase of the privatization program is to:&#13;
(a) bring to point-of-sale a group of four or more wholly-owned state companies; (b) sell Government-&#13;
owned minority shares in a further three companies; and (c) establish an action plan for bringing to the&#13;
point-of-sale the remaining enterprises with intermediate targets that form the basis for the second and&#13;
third tranches of the PSDAC. At this time, Government participation in one bank has been sold and&#13;
work is nearing completion in the other entities slated for privatization this year.&#13;
22.           The GOG has also decided on the selection and the sequencing of the enterprises to be&#13;
privatized in the first phase of the privatization program. The GOG intends to explain the scope, goals,&#13;
procedures and pace of the privatization program to the populace as one of the institutional safeguards&#13;
necessary to generate consensus for the program and ensure its success. GOG is therefore taking steps&#13;
to set up a public communication program. IDA has supported this effort through a grant from the&#13;
Participation Fund to mobilize resources for the campaign. The public launch of the program was&#13;
recently conducted and will provide an ongoing regular communication of privatization activities to the&#13;
public. The publicity campaign is under the purview of the PU.&#13;
23.           To date, the institutional results in the Privatization unit have been limited. While the&#13;
Unit has followed the procedures established, limited resources and weak institutional capacity has&#13;
resulted in a slow and cumbersome process. As a result of this process, the Government has decided to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
request assistance under the FISBEC to draw upon the expertise of a firm to provide advisory support&#13;
in this process. While IDA would provide guidance and supervision of the privatization component as&#13;
part of the overall project, the bulk of the advisory services have been proposed to be funded by the U.K.&#13;
Overseas Development Administration (ODA). In addition, Japanese Grant funds are currently being&#13;
used to fund an Executive Secretary, Financial Analyst and Corporate Lawyer. This funding will be&#13;
terminated once the FISBEC becomes effective.&#13;
Technical Assistance Requirements&#13;
24.           The aim of the technical assistance program is to assist in the process of institutional&#13;
support for the Privatization Unit. Support would consist of:&#13;
* Assistance by a Privatization Advisory Team who would be charged with guidance and technical support&#13;
of the privatization process. The Team would be responsible for overseeing the preparation of initial&#13;
audits of each company, expediting the legal process of preparation for privatization, overseeing the&#13;
process of and tender documents, and undertaking financial analysis on behalf of the Privatization&#13;
Board. The scope of work would include, for each of the 20+ enterprises: (i) legal due diligence; (ii)&#13;
financial due diligence; (iii) indicative valuation; (iv) recommended privatization strategy; (v)&#13;
preparation and mailing of bidding documents; and (vi) advice on implementation and conclusion of&#13;
sale;&#13;
* An Executive Secretarn would be supported under the Credit to manage the privatization process under&#13;
the guidance of the Privatization Board. The Secretary would be responsible for meeting the PU's&#13;
work program objectives, including reviews of each enterprise;&#13;
* A Finanicial Analvst would be contracted for a period of 30 months and would analyze the financial&#13;
position of public enterprises working under the guidance of the Advisory Team. This would include:&#13;
financial valuation, preparation of pro-forma financial statements and preparation of pro-forma financial&#13;
projections,&#13;
* A full time Accountant would assist in financial analysis and evaluate the valuation work undertaken;&#13;
* A Corporate Lawyier would be contracted for a period of 24 months to assist in the evaluation of legal&#13;
liabilities, design tender contracts, draft Ministerial Orders as appropriate or other legal documents as&#13;
needed. This lawyer would also review the legal position of each company to ensure that all legal and&#13;
contingent liabilities have been remedied so as to ensure the institution is saleable and not compromised&#13;
by contingent risks or obligations to the buyer; and&#13;
* Select financing would be available for office equipment--desktop computers a laser printer and a fax&#13;
machine.&#13;
Cost Estimate&#13;
25.    The total estimated cost of the program outlined below is US$ 785,100 of which US$ 765,100&#13;
would be financed under the Credit. Cofinanced funding for these costs is being sought from U.K. ODA,&#13;
who have expressed an interest to contribute to this component of the project.&#13;
Guyana Office of Investment (GO-INVEST)&#13;
Background and Sector Strategy&#13;
26.    The GOG disbanded the largely ineffective business promotion agency, GUYMIDA, in December&#13;
1993. A key role of GUYMIDA had been to decide on fiscal incentives on a firm by firm basis, a&#13;
practice which the Government decided to eliminate. The 1994 Budget replaced tax holidays and other&#13;
discretionary fiscal incentives with statutory tax and duty exemptions on specified capital goods available&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
to all firms operating in Guyana. The&#13;
Table 4 - Estimated Cost of Technical Assistance to   Goverm s  recogn  tipance&#13;
the Privatizationt Untit (US$)             Goverrnment has recognized the Importance&#13;
of fostering both domestic and foreign&#13;
investment in Guyana, and seeks to&#13;
Item                 Total    Counter-   Proposed      complement progress made in improving&#13;
Cost      part     for IDA        the   investment  climate  through&#13;
Financed    Credit       macroeconomic adjustments with measures&#13;
Prinati-ationi      500,000               500,000      to  facilitate  business  start-up   and&#13;
Advisor/Adi isorn                                       operations.   Recognizing  that lack of&#13;
Team                                                   information and standardized procedures&#13;
for business start-up have discouraged&#13;
Ex-ecutive Secretary    91,300             91,300      potential investors interested in Guyana&#13;
Consultants:        121.300     20,000    101,300      despite its infrastructure limitations, the&#13;
Financial AnalYsts!                                     Government resolved  to  establish  an&#13;
Accountants                                             investor service agency.&#13;
PuJblic anFd Labor   30,000                30,000      27.            In March 1994 the GOG&#13;
Relations Erperts                                      established  the   Guyana   Office   of&#13;
Corporate LaiwYer    30,000                30,000      Investment (GO-INVEST) to speed private&#13;
Office Equipmtient   12,500                12,500      investors through government regulation&#13;
and facilitate investment in Guyana.  A&#13;
Total             785,100     20,000    765,100      blueprint for the Agency was adopted, the&#13;
head for the Unit appointed and in place,&#13;
and enabling legislation and a budget approved. A staffing structure has been established, and a schedule&#13;
for operations in place. Funding for the GO-INVEST director has to date been provided by a Japanese&#13;
Grant administered by IDA. The Unit also received approval for assistance from the Foreign Investment&#13;
Advisory Service (FIAS). As of late September, 1994, GO-INVEST had progressed in its mandate to&#13;
promote Guyana for foreigni investment purposes.  Various private investor contacts and official&#13;
trade/investmenit promotion representatives have been contacted overseas, and the agency has been&#13;
providing support to interested individual investors through assistance on investment opportunities and&#13;
related regulations, and by liaising with other government agencies to expedite or resolve obstacles in the&#13;
establishment of investment enterprises. In addition, pamphlets and briefs on domestic industry and&#13;
sectoral developments have been produced, and GO-INVEST is now in the process of developing an&#13;
investor procedures guide in coordination with the Ministry of Finance. An intensive training program&#13;
is underway, covering a broad range of issues from customs and taxation regulations to industry-wide and&#13;
sectoral developmiients.&#13;
28.           The Government has agreed in the context of the PSDAC to strengthen the environment&#13;
for private sector development, and provide support across the relevant ministries and agencies to&#13;
facilitate GO-INVEST's role in attracting foreign investment.&#13;
Technical Assistanice Requiremtletnts&#13;
29.           Assistance would be provided to GO-INVEST to establish staffing and institutional&#13;
procedures, acquire equipment, and train Investment Service Officers. In coordination with IDA, FIAS&#13;
is providing technical assistance to streamline investment procedures, as well as providing limited&#13;
strategic guidanice.&#13;
Financing would be provided for the Advisor/Director of GO-INVEST who would develop institutional&#13;
procedures, lead and manage the operation of the Unit, and coordinate with Cabinet-level officials;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
* Four Investment Officers would be contracted for a period of 36 months each. Such individuals would&#13;
guide potential investors through administrative procedures, develop and maintain informational and&#13;
promotional materials, and investigate investment opportunities. A Specialist in Investment Promotion&#13;
and Public Relations would also be contracted to provide guidance on the materials developed, GO-&#13;
INVEST's strategy and its procedures;&#13;
* Staff Training would be provided, in the form of learning trips to effective regional one-stop shops&#13;
and courses outside the country; and&#13;
* Select financing would be available for office equipment--desktop computers, a laser printer and a copy&#13;
machine.&#13;
30.          In order to expedite the execution of the overseas training component for the above (as&#13;
well as under the Banking Supervision component), a commitment from the Government would be sought&#13;
for one-year block approvals of training/travel requests which are financed under this project.&#13;
Cost Estimate&#13;
31.           The total estimated cost of&#13;
the program outlined in Table 5 below is   Table 5 - Estimated Cost of Support to GO-INVEST&#13;
approximately US$ 532,100 of which US$                         (US$)&#13;
403,100 would be financed under the&#13;
Credit:                                         Item           Total    Counter-  Proposed&#13;
Cost     part    for IDA&#13;
Financing    Credit&#13;
Environmental Assessment of Public&#13;
Enterprises                               Advisors in          158,400              158,400&#13;
Investment Promotion&#13;
Background and Sector Strategy            Investment Officers-    252,000  36,000   216,000&#13;
Other Consultants&#13;
32.    A   preliminary  environmental&#13;
evaluation  of the  companies  to  be     Training - Field      8,500                 8,500&#13;
privatized  was carried  out by  IDA,     Visits to Other&#13;
identifying whether environmental actions  Territories&#13;
were needed during privatization, and if    Other Training      11,000               11,000&#13;
so, what form of action was necessary.&#13;
The report has been shared with the       Equipment             9,200                 9,200&#13;
Government  agency  responsible  for&#13;
environmental protection (in the Office of    Overhead &amp; Invest.    93,000  93,000&#13;
the President) and the Government has      Promotion Work&#13;
agreed  to  undertake  more  detailed       Total             532,100    129,000   403,100&#13;
environmental audits of the companies&#13;
identified.   Based on the preliminary&#13;
evaluation, 11 public enterprises were recommended as requiring either an environmental audit or&#13;
assessment for specified issues.  The objective of each audit would be to evaluate the identified&#13;
environmental issues. The objective of each environmental assessment would be to identify environmental&#13;
liabilities of selected enterprises of the Government prior to their privatization. The Government of&#13;
Guyana is also currently undertaking discussions in these areas with the ODA, which is prepared to&#13;
provide funding for the afore-mentioned activities. Therefore, while the norms and procedures which&#13;
would guide the progress of this component, would be based on IDA standards which are being used in&#13;
the development of Guyana's own environmental guidelines, the financing and expenditures of this sub-&#13;
component would be administered by the U.K. ODA.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10-&#13;
Technical Assistance Requirements&#13;
33.           The Government has agreed to contract with one or more environmental consulting firms&#13;
to conduct the environmental audits and assessments needed for the 11 companies above.  The&#13;
consultants' work shall consist of (i) identifying mitigatory measures for environmental issues associated&#13;
with current operating practices; (ii) environmental issues associated with past practices and inadequate&#13;
design features which may result in environmental liabilities; and (iii) building-up institutional capacity&#13;
in Guyana to supervise the implementation of agreed-upon clean-up or mitigatory measures. The&#13;
contractor will visit each facility and assess current and future compliance with expected national&#13;
environmental regulations, and IDA environmental guidelines which are being used in the formulation&#13;
of Guyana's regulations. The contractor shall conduct the necessary environmental characterization to&#13;
assess the scope of the environmental issue (eg. size of the contaminated area), develop the cleanup&#13;
criteria for the contaminated areas, and train local staff with documented procedures for supervision of&#13;
a clean-up plan. The output shall be a work plan, field investigation plan, and, most important, field-&#13;
specific reports.  These field specific reports should contain a detailed strategy for clean-up of&#13;
environmental liabilities, including an estimate of the costs of such a clean-up.&#13;
Cost Estimate&#13;
34.    The estimated cost of the audits&#13;
and assessments, and institutional capacity   Table 6 - Estimated Cost of Technical Assistance to&#13;
building above is US$ 470,000. Part of           the Office of the President -- Environmental&#13;
this would likely be financed by the U.K.         Assessments of Public Enterprises (US$)&#13;
ODA, as per discussions during appraisal:&#13;
Item                 Total    Counter-   Proposed&#13;
Cost      part    for IDA&#13;
Strengthening the Business Enviromnent                                   Financed    Credit&#13;
SEnvironmental      400,000              400,000&#13;
Background and Sector StrategyAsemnt&#13;
AXssessments&#13;
35.    Implementation   of  the&#13;
Companies Act. To date, amendments to       Clean-up             70,000               70,000&#13;
the Companies Act enacted in 1991 have      supervision&#13;
been  passed  by  Parliament but not        procedures/training&#13;
promulgated  owing  to  a  lack  of           Total             470,000              470,000&#13;
implementing regulations as well as a lack&#13;
of the implementation capacity to enforce such regulations. The current Registry of Companies which&#13;
is under the Deeds Registry, does maintain a registry of public and privately held corporations, and is&#13;
also responsible for registering deeds. However, the Registry does not enforce the Companies Act and&#13;
lacks organized cataloging and record-keeping systems. In accordance with the PSDAC, the Government&#13;
has agreed to draft and issue the implementing regulations to the Companies Act (as amended in 1991)&#13;
as well as to have the Act and such regulations under implementation. The Government has requested&#13;
support in the development of these regulations and subsequent implementation capacity.&#13;
Technical Assistance Requirements&#13;
36.           Support would be provided to assist in developing the regulations and implementation&#13;
capacity for the Companies Act as follows:&#13;
* A Corporate Lawyer with experience in Companies Law in the Commonwealth will be contracted to&#13;
draft the implementing regulations for the Companies Act.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
An Organizational Consultant will be     Table 7 - Estimated Cost of Technical Assistance to&#13;
contracted to develop a strengthening        Improve the Business Environment (US$)&#13;
program for the functions and staffing&#13;
of the Registry of Companies which will&#13;
include   a  program    for  the   Item                      Total    Counter-  Proposed&#13;
implementation   of  the  revised                             Cost     part    for iDA&#13;
Companies   Act,  implementing                                        Financed    Credit&#13;
regulations,  and   development  of   Dev. of implementation   150,000            150,000&#13;
procedures. Capability for&#13;
Companies Act&#13;
37.           A  key  requirement for&#13;
financing the costs under this component,  Total               150,000              150,000&#13;
would be for the Government to first&#13;
designate an adequately staffed Registry responsible for executing the required functions, and in addition,&#13;
to put in place a sustainable budget and staffing complement to carry out the necessary institutional tasks&#13;
and enforcement of regulations. The consultants funded under the component, would train such staff in&#13;
operationalizing the regulations pertaining to the Companies Act, and in implementing institutional&#13;
procedures, as well as record-keeping mechanisms and controls, to carry out the Registry's functions&#13;
effectively.&#13;
Cost Estimate&#13;
38.           The estimated cost of the program above is US$ 150,000, all of which would be financed&#13;
under the Credit.&#13;
Credit Administration - Operation of the Ministry of Finance Project Unit&#13;
39.           A Project Unit will be established in the Ministry of Finance with the responsibility for&#13;
coordination and oversight of: (i) procurement of goods and services supported by the FISBEC; (ii)&#13;
disbursement of funds under the FISBEC, and (iii) periodic auditing of the project accounts. The Unit&#13;
may also take on similar responsibilities with respect to cofinanced funds under the project.&#13;
40.   In order to support the Unit, uss    Table 8 - Estimated Cost of Technical Assistance to&#13;
77,800 of the Credit would be used to               Support the Project Unit (US$)&#13;
support the operation of this unit. This&#13;
would include: USS 36,000 to support the   Item                Total    Counter-  Proposed&#13;
head of the unit for 36 months, US$                             Cost     part    for IDA&#13;
18,000 for an assistant, USS 20,000 to                                 Financed    Credit&#13;
undertake external audits of the project,   Coordinator of     36,000               36,000&#13;
and US$ 3,800 for office equipment.      Project&#13;
Assistant Coordinator  18,000               18,000&#13;
Project Audits        20,000               20,000&#13;
Section B: Procurement and&#13;
Disbursement                Office Equipment        3,800                3,800&#13;
Total               77,800               77,800&#13;
41.    Procurement under the Project&#13;
will be according to IDA guidelines and&#13;
subject to normal IDA review procedures. The Credit would finance USS 3.5 million equivalent (87%&#13;
of total project costs of US$ 4.0 million), including 100% of foreign exchange costs and the remaining&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
US$ 0.5 million in local costs would be financed by Government counterpart resources. Consultant&#13;
services would be procured according to IDA procedures and would be subject to prior review for&#13;
contracts of US$25,000 equivalent and above. For consultant contracts, terms of reference for most of&#13;
the major activities to be financed under the proposed Credit have been prepared and are available in the&#13;
Project Files. IDA's standard forms of consultant contracts would be utilized, including a short-form&#13;
letter for direct contracting of individual consultants for short-term assignments. Goods/equipment valued&#13;
at less than US$25,000 would be procured through international shopping procedures acceptable to IDA.&#13;
Goods costing over US$25,000 equivalent are not expected to be financed under the project. However,&#13;
in the event that a contract package would exceed this amount, procurement procedures would be agreed&#13;
in consultation with IDA. Prior review would be mandatory for the first contract procured through&#13;
shopping.&#13;
42.           Disbursements will be administered by the Project Unit in the Ministry of Finance. A&#13;
Special Account would be established within the Bank of Guyana for the activities financed by this Credit.&#13;
The Special Account will have an authorized allocation of US$300,000 (equivalent to four months of&#13;
estimated disbursements). Disbursements would be made against Statement of Expenditures (SOEs) in&#13;
the case of goods and consultant services below US$25,000 equivalent for which detailed documentation&#13;
evidencing expenditures will be reviewed and kept by the Project Unit and made available for the required&#13;
audits and to IDA as needed. Credit disbursements would be made against 100% of the net-of-tax costs&#13;
of local and foreign consultants; 100% of training expenses; 100% of the CIF cost of imported goods&#13;
and of the ex-factory cost of local goods; and 85% of the cost of locally-procured goods. No retroactive&#13;
financing for consulting activities and related equipment is expected. The Project is expected to be&#13;
completed by end-1997. The closing date would be June 30, 1998.&#13;
43.           Project Implementation. The project would be a technical assistance facility managed&#13;
through the Project Unit to be established in the Ministry of Finance. The Project Unit would be&#13;
responsible for coordinating the requests from each of the counterpart agencies, ensuring that proper&#13;
procurement procedures are followed and oversee the disbursement process. Consultant contracts would&#13;
be directly procured and a procurement specialist would be contracted for the purchase of equipment.&#13;
The project implementation period is expected to last for a period of three years--the same as that for the&#13;
PSDAC. Project administration would be in close coordination with the proposed IMF, and U.K. ODA&#13;
parallel financing.&#13;
44.           Records and Auditing will be the responsibility of the Project Unit, which will establish&#13;
separate accounts for each component and will monitor all expenditures financed by the project. The&#13;
Ministry of Finance will maintain separate records and accounts for all transactions under the credit. The&#13;
Government will carry out annual audits of the Project accounts, the special account and statement of&#13;
expenditures and furnish the reports to the Association no later than three months after the close of the&#13;
financial year.  In addition to this financial reporting, a full progress report will be prepared and&#13;
submitted to IDA every six months. This report will detail all project and related activities, report on&#13;
progress in relation to agreed schedules, and identify any problems which may have been encountered&#13;
and which could adversely affect the overall impact of the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="697857">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/11/697857/guyana-financial-sector-business-environment-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1994/11/697857/guyana-financial-sector-business-environment-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1994/11/697857/guyana-financial-sector-business-environment-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1994/11/22/000009265_3961007145652/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1994/11/22/000009265_3961007145652/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>2669</credit_no>
        <datestored>2001-04-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1994-11-22T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Guyana - Financial Sector and Business
            Environment Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objectives of the Financial Sector
            and Business Environment Project are to implement
            sustainable institution building mechanisms supporting the
            financial and private sector, and to facilitate the
            effective implementation of policy measures supported by the
            private sector development adjustment credit. The project
            will achieve these objectives through the following
            components. The first component will seek to strengthen
            financial sector operation and regulation through: a)
            support to the Central Bank in banking supervision through
            regulatory advice, training and equipment; b) support the
            Central Bank in improving monetary management through
            assistance in developing procedures and related staff
            training; and c) support in restructuring of state-owned
            financial institutions. The second component seeks, through
            privatization, to transfer public ownership of a majority of
            public enterprises to private hands and in this manner, to
            also stimulate investment. The third component aims to
            strengthen the business environment through support to the
            Office of GO-INVEST (the Guyana Office Investment) with
            training of staff to help simplify procedures for foreign
            investors, and b) consultant support in the development of
            regulations under the Companies Act and training of staff of
            the Registry of Companies to strengthen its capacity to
            implement this Act.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Guyana - Financial Sector and Business
            Environment Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Guyana - Financial Sector and
            Business Environment Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1994/11/697857/guyana-financial-sector-business-environment-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>GY-Fin Sctr &amp; Bus Env -- P034605</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Financial Intermediation,Financial Crisis Management &amp; Restructuring</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Guyana</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3961007145652</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <subsc>General industry and trade sector,Banking</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Finance</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Banking; Central banks; Credit policy;
            Denationalization; Financial institutions; Investment
            promotion; Monetary policy; Private sector; Public
            enterprises; Training
            accounting,administrative
            costs,administrative procedures,auditing,audits,balance
            sheet,banking sector,Banking Supervision,banking
            system,borrowing,capital adequacy,capital goods,capital
            markets,capital requirements,Central Bank,commercial
            banks,contingent liabilities,credit control,credit
            policies,credit risk,deposit
            accounts,depositors,deposits,development banking,economic
            life,environmental evaluation,environmental
            issues,environmental protection,environmental
            regulations,Exchange Rate,expenditures,Financial
            Institutions,financial intermediation,financial
            reporting,Financial Sector,financial structure,FISCAL
            YEAR,foreign exchange,GDP,government regulation,Gross
            Domestic Product,guidelines,Insurance,legislation,lending
            rates,loan classification,macroeconomic adjustments,market
            instruments,market integration,monetary policy,net
            worth,open market operations,portfolios,potential
            investors,privatization,problem
            loans,profitability,prudential regulations,public
            enterprises,recapitalization,regulatory framework,Special
            Drawing Rights,Structural
            Adjustment,T-Bills,taxation,Technical
            Assistance,trading,Treasury Bills
        </keywd>
        <owner>Finance &amp; Private Sector (LCSPF)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T6411</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Insolvency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reconciliation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Resolution and Crisis Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Guyana</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>