<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>T .&#13;
; ' - ; 0 i f f :' " ' S Wf 1; A n  X~~~~~~~~~~.777-~&#13;
3X)ffSJo;~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
T7~~~~~~tllt  lq0-!|  &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
'' Annual Report&#13;
1993&#13;
1       ee&#13;
Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MIGA in brief&#13;
The Multilateral Investment Guar-&#13;
Contents                                         antee Agency (MIGA), a member of&#13;
the World Bank Group.'  promotes pri-&#13;
MIGA in brief  2                                 vateforeigndirect investmentforeco-&#13;
nomic and social development in its&#13;
member countries. Since April 1988&#13;
Letter to the Council of Govemors  5              MIGAhas workedtowardthisendby:&#13;
The global environment&#13;
for investnent  6                                  v Guaranteeing foreign invest-&#13;
The guarantee program   9                         ments against political risks in devel-&#13;
Promotionalandadvisoryservices  20               oping member countries?2&#13;
MIGA 1988-93: A five-year                           * Providingpromotional andadvi-&#13;
rerospective  26                                sory services to assist member coun-&#13;
Officers of the Agency  32                       tries in creating an attractive climate&#13;
Fiunacial statements  33                         for private foreign direct investment.&#13;
MIGA is owned by its member&#13;
Appendices                                       countries and is capitalized at SDR&#13;
1.0 billion (SI .CJI,2 billion)? Member-&#13;
Govemors and Altemates  48                       ship is open to all member countries of&#13;
Dieors and Alternates                            the World Bank&#13;
and teir 3voting power  51                         MIGA concluded its fifth fiscal year&#13;
Signatory countries to                           on June 30. 1993. A special five-year&#13;
the Convention  53                              retrospective is included in this an-&#13;
Fiscal 1994 Budget  54                           nual report&#13;
' The World Rank Group comprises the Interna-&#13;
Cover  o                                         uonalBankjforRecoonsrutonandDevelopment&#13;
(JBRD). rhelntenadonalDerelopmenrAssoca-&#13;
don (IDA). the Inrernaional Finance Corpora-&#13;
1. Miin equipmet P &amp; H shovels                   tion (IFC). the MuWilarcral Invemnemn Guaran-&#13;
teeAgency(MIGA).andthelnternationalCenre&#13;
2. Gold pouring at the Veziua mill, northwesten  for Seztlenwer of Investment Disputes (ICSJDJ.&#13;
QuEbc&#13;
2 Throghoutthisanulreport. thewords 'gmranl-&#13;
3. The entire Omai Mine complex is powered by    reC and 'inssrwrc are used inrrchangealy-&#13;
Ught diesd generators capable of providing a&#13;
total of 24 megawatts of electricity.          JAll dol/ar amowuns referto US. dollars.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
£&#13;
__ , :&#13;
__|_&#13;
_ _l ' :&#13;
- ',,&#13;
__&#13;
_!_&#13;
_ , 0&#13;
_&#13;
_&#13;
_ _&#13;
f.:&#13;
a,- ,.&#13;
.                                ,    _ _           .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
b%AL ^   ,&#13;
S~~~~&#13;
Organized three policy implemen-&#13;
r" EM PI                                 ton workshops&#13;
HIghlights of fiscal 1993                      * Cosponsored a mining conference&#13;
in Namibia and a workshop on investor&#13;
Country membership                           s&#13;
-                   ~~~~~~services in Uganda&#13;
* Twenty-fournewsignatoriestothe&#13;
MIGA Convention, brngngg the num-Copedtiyonavsrro&#13;
ber of signatory coutrines to 139            jects in twenty-eight countries through&#13;
b f ne Foreign Investment Advisory Ser-&#13;
* Membership requirements com-             vice (HAS)&#13;
pleted by twenty-two countries, bring-       Financial&#13;
ing the number of full members to 107&#13;
Guarantee operations                            - Subscribed capital of $948 million&#13;
* Assumed liabilies totaling $745&#13;
* MGA issued twenty-seven guar-            million&#13;
antee con .at, involving:&#13;
* Net income of $2.6 million before&#13;
. Fourteen host countries an.dtwelve    ...io~           ia rnuinafe&#13;
provisioning, $1.1 million after&#13;
investor countries&#13;
- Maximum contingent liability&#13;
assumption of $374 million&#13;
- Facilitation of$1.9 billion in direct&#13;
investment                                          Board of Directors&#13;
. First project assisted in Russia;&#13;
firseinsurecontrt signed with               Directors             Alternates&#13;
Japan                                       Nurcan Akturk         Mihaly Pali&#13;
Ibrahim A. AM-Assaf   Ahned ML Al-Ghannam&#13;
. .ive additional commitment let-  Faisn] A. Al-Kaled  Mohamcd W. Hosny&#13;
*Five additional commitnent let-         -E Patrick Coady       Mark bt Collins. Jr.&#13;
ters involving prospective coverage of        Suamba de Alwis        Erst Ako-djei&#13;
$105 million were issued.                     Boris G. Fcdorov       Alexander N. Dounmn&#13;
Jase-Rarrmon Fenrandlis  Emcgo lMartinez-Alas&#13;
Fritz Fischer         Harald Rehm&#13;
Promotional and advisory services             Nicolas Flafno        Julio Nogucs&#13;
Enzo Grilli           Femando S. Carmeio&#13;
* Held investment promotion con-            EvelineHerfkcens      Pietro Veglio&#13;
Yasuyuid Kawahar      Makato Nakajima&#13;
ference in Botswana                            can-Penie Landau     Jerome Haas&#13;
lean4Pierre Le Bouder  Ali Bourhanc&#13;
* Conductedexecutivedevelopment            Jomnm Mahtlum          HelgaJonsdotfir&#13;
O.K. Matambo          Harry Ni Mapondo&#13;
programs for five countries                   David Pretz            David Stanton&#13;
Frank Potter          Hubert Dean&#13;
* Organizedoneinvestmentmission            Wang Liansheng         Zhang Sbengnan&#13;
and cosponsored another                       Bong-Hee Won          Jannes Hutagalung&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Letter to the Council of Governors&#13;
June 30, 1993&#13;
Lewis T. Preston, President of the Agency and Chairman of thze Board of Directors. I&#13;
submits this reportand the accompanying audiredfinancial statementsforihefiscalyear&#13;
ending June 30,1993, on behalf of the Board to the Council of Governors in accordance&#13;
with the bylaws of the Agency.                                          j&#13;
The Board of Directors of the Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency is pleased&#13;
to report tiat MIGA's insurance, investment promotion. and advisory services grew&#13;
faster than planned during fiscal 1993.&#13;
MIGA's programs are designed to encourage the flowt of private foreign direct&#13;
investmentfor producrive purposes to and between developing member countries. MIGA&#13;
facilitates capital flows by providing insurance for private investors against noncom-&#13;
mercial risks, by promoting investment activity, and by helping counrries create an&#13;
attractive investment climate. MIGA thus complements the development activities of the&#13;
other memrber agencies of the World Bank Group.&#13;
A special five-year retrospective derailing the evolution of MIGA's growth and&#13;
program activitiesfrom April1988 toJune 30,1993, is included at the end oft/hisAnnual&#13;
Report.&#13;
Eg~~~ -', att;&#13;
HaGA Board of Directors, May 12,1993.&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The global environment&#13;
for investment&#13;
and red tape, high public sector debt that&#13;
crowds outprivatefinancing, inadequatetreat-&#13;
ment of intellectual and otherproperty rights,&#13;
inappropriate taxation ard repatriation poli-&#13;
cies, and uncontrolled inflation are all factors&#13;
The composition of investment flows to  that can deter potential investors.&#13;
the developing world has changed over the  The policy environment for foreign in-&#13;
past decade. Following the debt crisis of the   vestnent has become friendlier in recent&#13;
early 1980s, the level of commercial bank   years as govemments in developing coun-&#13;
lending to the developing world fell precipi-  tries have realized that FDI can be an engine&#13;
tously, and the large increase in public sector  for economic growth. At the same time, the&#13;
debt impeded the growth of public sector   emergence of new marketeconomies in East-&#13;
investment. Thus during the late 1980s, and   em and Central Europe has intensified com-&#13;
now into the 1990s, foreigndirectinvestment   petition among developing nations for scarce&#13;
(FDI) has become an increasingly important   capital, increasing the importance of an at-&#13;
form of investment The bulk of this invest-  tractive investment climate.&#13;
mertcomesfrommuldnationalcorporations,    Regional disparities in investment flows&#13;
in the form of equity, not debt        persist East Asia continues to attract more&#13;
FDI benefits countries in many important   EDI than odter developing regions. Invest-&#13;
ways. It brings in much-needed capital and   ment flows to that region climbed past $15&#13;
increases employmenL Itpromotes the irans-   billion in 1992, up more than 15 percent from&#13;
feroftechnologyandof managementknowl-  the previous year. Unlike the pattern in other&#13;
edge,whichtakeonincreasingimportanceas  regions, private investment is significantly&#13;
developing economies move to more ad-   higher than public investment as a percent-&#13;
vancedstages.ofeconomicdevelopment. And   age of GDP, approximately twice as high (18&#13;
it acts as acatalyst forexport growth, provid-   percent to 9 percent) for the period 1980-90.&#13;
ing access to foreign markets for both the   Newlyindustrializingeconomieshavetended&#13;
investorand the host country. In 1986 FDI to  to attract most of these investment flows.&#13;
developing countries totaled an estimated   China, because of the size of its domestic&#13;
$10billion; by 1992ithadreached $38 billion,   maiket, low laborcosts, andpro-marketpolicy&#13;
an increase of 280 percent over the six years  reforms, was the largest individual recipient&#13;
and 23 percent over the past year alone.  of FDI in the region in fiscal 1992.&#13;
Many factors influence the flow of pri-  While foreign investment flows to Latin&#13;
vate investment. Potential growth, market   America leveled off between 1988 and 1990&#13;
size, and relative costs are important consid-  in the aftermath of the debt crisis and low and&#13;
erations. So are infrastructure development  sometimes stagnant economic growth, FDI&#13;
and levels of industrialization and education.  into this region increased significantly in&#13;
Just as important are govermment macro-   1991 and 1992. After a slight rise in 1990,&#13;
economic and structured policies that pro-   FD!jumped by almost 70 percent in 1991 (to&#13;
vide a stable and attactive environment con-   almost$ 12 billion) and afurther25 percent in&#13;
ducivetobusiness.Inadditicntodirectrestric-   1992 (to nearly $15 billion). The composi-&#13;
tions on investment, too much regulation   tionof foreigndirectinvestmentintheregion&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
is also noteworthy. Unlike East Asia, where  Another important trend in investment&#13;
investment consists largely of new projects  flows is the increase in foreign investment&#13;
and expansions, Latin America has benefited   from one developing country to another.&#13;
from  debt-equity  conversions  and   Though there was a slight decline in invest-&#13;
privatizations which have stimulated foreign   ment flows from the developing world in&#13;
investment flows. Latin American countries   1991, outflows from developing couniries&#13;
effectively converted a significant percent-   were twice those from industrial countries&#13;
age of their debt into equity stakes. The   during the period 1 986-90. Since 1990, for&#13;
commitment of many Latin American coun-  example, the Republic of Korea has been a&#13;
tries to solving macroeconomic problems   net exporter of FDI. Moreover, though most&#13;
and their new economic policies emphasiz-  investment between developing countries&#13;
ing the private sector have fostered a more  remains regional, China made its first invest-&#13;
favorableinvestmentenvironmentand,hence,   ment in Latin America in 1992. Many devel-&#13;
higher investment inflows.             oping countries have no political risk insur-&#13;
Foreign investment flows in the Middle  ers oftheirown, soMIGAcanplayanimpor-&#13;
East and North Africa region fluctuated dur-  tant role in facilitating flows of FDI among&#13;
ing the 1980s, but the trend in the early 1990s  these countries by providing such insurance.&#13;
has been impressive. From just over S1 bil-  The disparity of investment flows to indi-&#13;
lion in 1990, FDT rose to more than $4 billion   vidual developing countries shows that con-&#13;
in 1992.                               sistent pro-investnent policies over a period&#13;
in contast to the upward rends in other  of years are needed to gain the confidence of&#13;
regions,Sub-SaharanAfricacontinuestohave  the private commercial sector. Many ulevel-&#13;
little success in attracting FDI outside of   oping countries have made considerable&#13;
natural resource projects. With the exception   progress in devising such policies, but others&#13;
of 1989, the level of foreign investment flows   need to make additional progress.&#13;
has remained below $2 billion since 1986.  In this environment MIGA has a unique&#13;
Finally, EDI flows to the emerging mar-  role to play because it provides services to&#13;
ket economies ofCental and Eastern Europe   both host governments and potential inves-&#13;
have increased as a percentage of worldwide  tors. Investors concemed with political risks&#13;
flows, but the flows have been very uneven.  seek to manage those risks through the pur-&#13;
While the Czech Republic, Hungary, and   chase of investment insurance. The increase&#13;
Poland have been reasonably successful in  in demand for these coverages (discussed&#13;
attracting foreign investment, concems about  later in this report) is evidenced by the grow-&#13;
the political and economic climate in a num-   ing number of applications MIGA receives&#13;
ber of countries in the region have con-   and projects it insures. The competitive envi-&#13;
strained investment flows. Nevertheless, all  ronment for attracting FDI is also increasing&#13;
countries in this region see FDI as important  the demand for the promotional and advisory&#13;
for their economic stability, recovery, and   services that MIGA can provide through its&#13;
growth. These economies will need many   own resources and dtrough the Foreign Invest-&#13;
forms of extemal support, including FDI and   ment Advisory Service (HAS), MIGA'sjoint&#13;
macroeconomic advice. in order to continue   facility with the Intemational Fmance Corpo-&#13;
their transformation.                  ration (IFC) and the World Bank. Govem-&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ments are becoming more aware of the need  increasing frequency to investnient insur-&#13;
to improve their investment environment.  ance organizations such as MIGA to provide&#13;
MIGA's experience is clear: eliminating   the comfort necessary for proceeding with&#13;
burdensome and unnecessary regulations,  their investments in such an environment.&#13;
un sound financial laws, and outdated institu-  MIGA's position as a m ultilateral institu-&#13;
tions that hamper business activity has a   tion means that it can offer investment cov-&#13;
profound effect on the flow of FDI.    erage in some circumstances in which other&#13;
Demand for MIGA's services is strong   investment insurers cannot. As a World Bank&#13;
andgrowing. Uncertainty still pervades parts   Group institution owned by its membergov-&#13;
of the international investment community  emments, MIGA has credibility in its deal-&#13;
despite some significant improvements in  ings with both govemments and potential&#13;
the investment climates of many developing   investors. As an adviser to governments on&#13;
countries in the last few years. While some   attracting private investnent, it possesses a&#13;
countries: have improveI their investment  knowledge base for diagnosing problems&#13;
climates, many investo.s remain cautious   and advising govemments on their policy&#13;
about the permanence of these changes.  options. These capabilities render MIGA&#13;
Emerging economies are providing many   uniquely capable of playing a larger role in&#13;
new business opportunities-and posing   facilitating private investmert in the mid-&#13;
new uncertainties. Lnvestors are tuning with   1990s.&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
--              The guarantee program&#13;
expropriation, and war andciviI disturbance.&#13;
In addition to new projects, MIGA can insure&#13;
investments in the expansion, privatization,&#13;
and financial restructuring of existing projects&#13;
that arc registered with MIGA before the in-&#13;
vestments are made or irrevocably committed.&#13;
Fiscal 1993 was a highly successful year  Eligibleinvestments include contributions&#13;
for the guarantee program. MIGA exceeded   in cash or in kind in t;.A form of equity, loans&#13;
its initial estimates for the year in every   made or guaranteed by equity holders, and&#13;
respect: in coverage issued ($374 million),  certain forms of non-equity direct invest-&#13;
income earned fiom premiums and commit-   ment. MIGA can insure a loan to a project&#13;
ment fees ($5.8 million), and commitments   made by a financial institution if the loan is&#13;
of potential coverage ($105 million). This  related to an investment covered--or to be&#13;
success is altributable to inany irnteracting,   covered-by the Agency. MIGA's standard&#13;
reinforcing factors. A more receptive intema-   policy covers investments for fifteen years,&#13;
tional investment envir-onment in many devel-  although coverage for a project may be ex-&#13;
oping countres, more atrcve investnent  tended to twenty years in exceptional cases.&#13;
opporunities (including many privatizations   MIGA actively seeks to cooperate with other&#13;
ofstateenterprises), a larger universeof coun-   investment insurers in coinsuring or&#13;
tries for MIGA's activities, more widespread   reinsuring eligible investments.&#13;
knowledge of MI&amp;A's programs, and the&#13;
maturaionofearlierMlGAmarketingeffoits-    The guaran-tee process&#13;
all contributed to MIGA's growth.&#13;
During the past year most public invest-  SecuringaMIGAguaraniteeisaninterac-&#13;
ment insurers experienced increased demand   tive process invo lving the investorand MIGA&#13;
for their coverages. For some, demand ex-   thatis triggered by the investor ssu bmission of&#13;
ceeded their capacity to provide coverage in   a preliminary application to MICA (figure 1).&#13;
certain situations. This demand was fueled by   MI5A responds within two working days by&#13;
a combination of unusual business opportuni-  issuing a notice of registration if its basic&#13;
ties and concems about political risk in devel-  eligibility criteria are met. The investor's sub-&#13;
oping countries and in the formerly centrally   sequentevaluation of the project's feasibility&#13;
planned economnies of Europe and Asia As an   and prospective returns can take from a few&#13;
investmentinsurercreated to complementother   months to many years. In reaching the deci-&#13;
investment insurers, MIGA was able to re-   sion to proceed, the investor typically con-&#13;
spondto manyprospective investors who were   siders the political risks associated with the&#13;
unable to obtain the type of political risk insur-   project and decides whether to seek invest-&#13;
ance protection they wanted.             ment insurance and from whom.&#13;
When the investorrequestsinsurarce from&#13;
Coverages                                MIGA, the Agency's underwriting process is&#13;
activated dtrough the filing of a definitive&#13;
MIGA's insurance program protects in-   application.Theensuingiliteractionsbetween&#13;
vestorsagainstlossesfromcurrencytransfer,   MICA and the investor are designed to:&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(Figure 1)&#13;
Trhe MICA guarantee process&#13;
'C'  Prject asesmie  phaseEvaltuation             Deion          Dcision&#13;
Investor  Ide,t (lation                                   of inmN-trnent        |&#13;
phase            Feasibilitv studies:o J   insurance option!    purchase       Invest 2&#13;
evaluationotlf project's      - rr;vimt l             ic&#13;
prospective risks and        * r, anal&#13;
I                returnlsprnliminrMv           * MICA&#13;
Pr*liminary       project negotiations&#13;
Application                                          Passiblc             I ':;:iblt  P1urchase&#13;
for Guarantee                                         Definitive           oiler ti        tif&#13;
I                                               Application          insurr    insurance&#13;
for Guarantee&#13;
MIGA       Notcetion to                              MIGA underwriting revietv &#13;
investor (within two davsl                   (two to four months)&#13;
t. This phase cn vary in duration from a few months to manv years.&#13;
2. TcdedLsionswhetherto invest ina prjsclxtrnd topurdi0a invet-mnt insurancare oftern mnde simultaneously.&#13;
* identify and serve the needs of the in-                Investors'preliminaryapplicationstoMlGA&#13;
vestor by customizing the terms and condi-    are a rough indicator of, inter alia, its past&#13;
tions of the coverage                                     marketing success and of the possible dimen-&#13;
a satisfy MIGA's need to be prudent in                sionsof itsfuture portfolio. Forthesecondyear&#13;
the offering and terms of the coverage                    in a row  MIGA  experienced a dramatic in-&#13;
- ensure that the project will have positive          crease in prelimninry applications, receiving&#13;
developmental effects for the host country                (g   2)&#13;
and that the project is financially viable and                        D                ol&#13;
environmentally sound (see box on pagelS).                                 by host countries&#13;
Portfolio distribution                                                   (as of June 30, 1993)&#13;
Chile   Bangladesh&#13;
Projects assisted in fiscal 1993 were rela-               CzEch Republic   6%         7c&#13;
tively well distributed by host country and                              8%                          Argentina&#13;
investor country. As aresultMlGA's portfo-                            2&#13;
lio both increased in size and broadened in                  Guyana&#13;
diversity. Although a new insurer, MIGA has                     -                                      Turkey&#13;
a portfolio that is reasonably well distributed              Indonesia                                   if;&gt;&#13;
by country and type of coverage (figures 2                         7%&#13;
and 3). MIGA's liability exposure is spread&#13;
among seventeen host countries and fifteen                       JaOaica     .       :O&#13;
investor countries. Its highest level of expo-                       P.c                    Po-and&#13;
sure is in Argentina, which accounts for 16                                 16%s             12%&#13;
percent of the portfolio. MIGA's sectoral&#13;
portfolio is also satisfactory for a relatively                China, Uganda Rusia Tanzania Madagascar. and Ghana&#13;
young institution (figure 4).&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
its one thousandth preliminary application in    was again spread broadly across all regions.&#13;
May 1993. (A minority of these applications    Distribution of project registrations by sector&#13;
will result in actual investments.) Active regis-    continued to be excellent (figure 5), and the&#13;
trations increased by 81 percent to546 during    quality and diversity of these prcliminary&#13;
the year. The projects involved investors from    applications bodes well for MIGA's future&#13;
forty-five countries with prospective invest-    growth and the development of a well-&#13;
ments in I OOdevelopingcountries.Thisgrowth    balanced portfolio.&#13;
(Figurc 3)                                       (Figurc 5)&#13;
To ta I exposu re by type o f coverage               Total registrations by industry&#13;
(as of June 30, 1993)                             (as of June 30, 1993)&#13;
Manufacturing&#13;
29¶;&#13;
Cu rrcnc  i:.-0           -   5]cation'&#13;
transfer   - -  H milleon     S"^   /                   A  ~~~~~~~~Tourism 71.&#13;
Expropriation                        $605.0                                            Finance &amp;&#13;
Wdaran.ddivil                $408.2 million         MinSgicusi e7&#13;
W,r and  ,l  -9.. i-.Powerr                             _    tl        Other&#13;
lC  100200 3(0I 00 500 600  700                           Oi &amp; C_ onrdo&#13;
(Figure 4)                                        Marketing&#13;
Distribution of portfolio by industry              MICA continued and intensified its suc-&#13;
(as of Junne 30, 1993)               cessful marketng efforts of earlier years. Pre-&#13;
viously initiated efforts to each financi al insti-&#13;
Finance &amp;Services             Agiuies&amp;          tutions and potential European investors con-&#13;
/ ~~~~~Forestby   tinne0d with considerable success, resulting in&#13;
t      /   &gt;         ,0     ~~~~~~the issuance of a large number of guarantees in&#13;
Tourism                                       fiscal 193, includig the firstcontacts issued&#13;
to Belgian, Dutch, Saudi Arabian, Spanish,&#13;
K   - - - t   ; ZS          ~~~and Swiss financial institutions.&#13;
Z -                                                     2To improve M GA's recognition among&#13;
Distbution of portfolioyind   y        potential business clients4 MIGA  intensified&#13;
_a nu lacturin                       its efforts to use ntermediary organizations&#13;
28an                                    such as tade associatons, chrpambers of con-&#13;
Commu;$attoin merce, and insurance brokers. MICA  also&#13;
substantially increased the volume and scope&#13;
11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of literature it distributed during the fiscal   Bank, MIGA informed prospective Chinese,&#13;
year. In particular, MIGA News, the Agency's   Korean, and Scandinavian investors inter-&#13;
quarterly newsletter, doubled its circulation   ested in Africa about MIGA's insurance pro-&#13;
to about 5,000 subscribers, and MIGA began   gram. To encourage investments within Af-&#13;
distribution of a Spanish version to an addi-  rica, MIGA also arranged a presentation to&#13;
tional group of subscribers.          the African Businessmen's Roundtable, a&#13;
group formed and supported by the African&#13;
Guarantees issued                      Development Bank.&#13;
MIGAissuedatotalofthirty-twoguaran-   Barclays Metals Ltd. and SEREM,&#13;
tees and commitment letters covering armaxi-   Uganda&#13;
mum liability of $479 million in fiscal 1993.&#13;
The guarantees will facilitate direct invest-  MIGA issued guarantees of $10 million&#13;
ments totaling some $1.9 billion. The invest-  againstthe risks of expropriation and warand&#13;
ments will provide the host govermnents  civil disturbance to Barclays Metals Ltd. of&#13;
with substantial benefits in foreign exchange  the Urited Kingdom and SEREM of France&#13;
in the form of increased taxes and dividends  foracobaltextraction project in Uganda. The&#13;
and are expected to directly create some 1,700   project involves separating cobalt and other&#13;
new jobs in the host countries (see rable 1 on   metals from mine tailings (which are cur-&#13;
page 28). The invesuments will also provide   rently an environmental hazard) for sale in&#13;
other critical, if less tangible, benefits to the   Europe and North America. With a total&#13;
host country through management and em-   investment of about $49 million the project&#13;
ployee trainiz:g and the transfer of technol-   will be the single largest private investment&#13;
ogy. Many projects also contibute to a   in Uganda since its independence in 1962. It&#13;
country'sdevelopmentbybuildingorstrengdh-  is expected to generate annual exports of&#13;
ening infrastructure (see box on page 18).  $160 million, and taxes and dividends for the&#13;
TheinvestmentprojectsinsuredbyMIGA    govemment of about $53 million annually.&#13;
in fiscal 1993 are described in the fo'lowing   The project should become the second larg-&#13;
sections, grouped by region. As part of   est expo t earner for the country and help in&#13;
MIGA's normal clearance process, the de-  the development of a remote part of Western&#13;
velopmental, financial, and environmental   Uganda. It will be the largest employer in&#13;
impacts ofeach investment project were care-   Kasese state, directly creating approximately&#13;
fully evaluated before guarantee coverage   260 new jobs and providing training at all&#13;
was extended.                         skill levels. The local community will also&#13;
benefit through the investors' provision of&#13;
Sub-Saharan Africa                     potable water, medical care, and education.&#13;
MIGA has given special attention over   Standard Chartered Africa plc,&#13;
the past several years to finding and assisting   Tanzania&#13;
prospective foreign investors interested in&#13;
projects in Sub-Saharan Africa. During fis-  Standard Chartered Africaplc., a subsid-&#13;
cal 1993, with the cooperation of the World  iaryof StandardChartered Bankof the United&#13;
12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Kingdom, opened a wholly owned subsid-   Many of the prospective projects in the&#13;
iary in Tanzania with MIGA's supporL The   region are privatizations of state enterprises.&#13;
first foreign bank to reenter the country since   Guarantees were issued to several large&#13;
the nationalization of all financial institu-   projects during the year, but MIGA's current&#13;
tions in 1967, Standard Chartered Africa will  pipeline contains many smaller projects. In&#13;
provide a variety of financial services and   fiscal 1993MIGAcompleteditsfirstprojects&#13;
stimulate competition in the banking sector.  in Russia and the Czech Republic.&#13;
When fully operational, the subsidiary will&#13;
employ about eighty people. MlGA's $2.7   Multiserv Russia, SA, Russia&#13;
million guarantee of Standard Charter's eq-&#13;
uity investment covers the risks of currency  MIGA issued its first coverage in Russia&#13;
transfer and expropriation.            to Multiserv Russia, S.A., a company incor-&#13;
porated in Belgium, for its investment in&#13;
GSM Gold Ltd, Ghana                    machinery and equipment for a steel slag&#13;
processing operation in Magnitogorsk. 'Te&#13;
MIGA and the IFC have jointly assisted   project will operate at the facilities of&#13;
GSM Gold Ltd., a company registered in   Magnitogorsk Metall Kombinat, the largest&#13;
Luxembourg, in its mining investments in  steel mill in the world, and will introduce&#13;
Ghana. The project will develop new gold   modem metal recovery systems in Russia to&#13;
mines at Iduapriem and explore another area   help process environmentally hazardous&#13;
in adjoining Ajopa inWestemGhana. MIGA   stockpiles of slag. MIGA has provided $9.9&#13;
has issued coverage for$9.85 million against  million in insurance to Multiserv Russia&#13;
the risk of war and civil disturbance. The   against the risk of war and civil disturbance&#13;
total investmnent for the project is $71.6 mil-  for fifteen years. MIGA's participation has&#13;
lion ($20.5 million of it contributed by the   playedacriticalroleinsecuringfinancingfor&#13;
IFC). Gold is Ghana's second largest export  the project&#13;
after cocoa and is a major foreign exchange&#13;
earner. The project is expected to increase&#13;
Ghana's gold production by 10 percent, and&#13;
annual exports are expected to be about $31                       r&#13;
million. The project is projected to generate  -&#13;
320 jobs directly and to create spinoffe   --   -&#13;
ployment benefits by helping to build up the    -               --&#13;
local economic infrastructure.       _                         f s  _&#13;
Europe and the Middk East&#13;
Investor interest in the formerly centrally&#13;
planned economies of Europe remained high&#13;
in 1993. Stimulated in part by the expansion   MlGA'sInt coverge in Raia  wd to Mutser&#13;
of NIGA country membersiup in the region,  R,uLif,SA*Jori ixvesbnentfin umchyandequipmnt&#13;
applications for MIGA coverage surged.  in Mauitgorsk&#13;
13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Ciments FranSais, Czech Republic       the United States against the risks of cur-&#13;
rency transfer, expropriation, and war and&#13;
MlGAassistedCimentsFranqais,aFrench   civil disturbance. IPI will assist in the&#13;
manufacturer, in the privatization and expan-   privaiization and modernization of Zaklady&#13;
sion of a cement production facility in the   Celulozowo Papiemieze KwidzynS.A.,once&#13;
Czech Republic. MIGA issued $50 million of   a wholly government-owned facility. EPI has&#13;
risk coverage against currency transfer, ex-   acquired 80percentoftheenterprisefor$120&#13;
propriation, and war and civil disturbance.  million, and may acquire additional shares&#13;
Total investment in this joint venture is about   under Poland's privatization law- With the&#13;
$90 million. Estimated revenues for the host  proposed modernization program, Kwidzyn&#13;
country include $12 million from exports and   will become one ofthe most modem pulp and&#13;
$29 million from taxes. The project will pro-   paper manufacturing facilities in Europe. In&#13;
duce ahigherquality cement than is currently   addition to the cost of acquisition, IPI will&#13;
available, helping to ma2ke the local cement  spend $175 nmillion on the modemization,&#13;
and construction industry more competitive   some of which will be for upgrading skills&#13;
and stimulating the use of local raw materials.  and establishing higher standards of effi-&#13;
ciency and quality. The project will use local&#13;
AVX Corporation, Czech Republic         raw materials and feedstocks, help fill&#13;
the growing demand for paper goods in&#13;
AVX Corporation, through subsidiaries   Poland, and provide PoIand with needed ex-&#13;
operating in the United Kingdom and Ger-  port opportnities. Additional political risk&#13;
many, invested in an assembly project in the   insurance was provided by the Overseas&#13;
Czech Republic with TESLA, a local com-   Private Investnent Corporation (OPIC), the&#13;
putercomponent manufacatring finn. Under   US. govemment national investment insurer.&#13;
two separate contracts, MIGA issued cover-&#13;
age of AVX's investments of $17.2 million&#13;
in macthinery and inventory. The raw materi- &#13;
als for manufacturing the capacitors will be&#13;
brought from Ger-nany ar `i die United King-            -&#13;
dom, and all the finished products will be&#13;
exported. Annual export revenues are ex-&#13;
pected to be about $47 million, and govern-&#13;
ment revenues from taxes about $1 .4 million. =&#13;
MIGA issued a total of $14.8 million                         __&#13;
of coverage against the risk of war and civil&#13;
disturbance. (In fiscal 1992 MIGA insured&#13;
AVX for an investment in El Salvador.)&#13;
International Paper Investments, Poland&#13;
MIGA issued coverages for $50 million   MIGA guarantee totaling $50 mMion is supporting the&#13;
privatization and modernization of a pulp and paper&#13;
to Intemational Paper Investments (IPI) of   manufacturing faciliey in Poland.&#13;
14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Ringnes A.S., Poland                   bution to expand its branch-banking opera-&#13;
tions in Istanbul, Turkey. Saudi American&#13;
MIGA issued guarantees for $2.7 million   Bank provides a wide range of advisory and&#13;
to Ringnes A.S., a Norwegian company and   financial services in Turkey The project will&#13;
Coca-Cola franchise holder, for its invest-  assist Turkey in expanding and diversifying&#13;
ment in a marketing and distribution com-   the financial resources available for produc-&#13;
pany in Lublin, Poland. The company will  tive investment in the country, will expose&#13;
distributesoftdrinks procuredfromRingnes's  domestic financial institutions to more inter-&#13;
two otherjoint venture bottling companies in   national competition, and will contribute to&#13;
Warsaw and Bydgoszcz, Poland, also previ-  improved trade and investment relations be-&#13;
ously insured by MIGA. The project is ex-  tween Turkey and Saudi Arabia. MIGA's&#13;
pected togenerate about seventyjobs. Ringncs   guarantee covers the risks of currency trans-&#13;
will provide both classroom and on-the-job   ferandexpropriation.Thisprojectrepresents&#13;
training in sales, marketing, and distribution   MI CPA's first coverage of an investment by a&#13;
for its new employees.                tirm from a developing member country in&#13;
another developing member country.&#13;
Saudi American Bank, Turkey&#13;
MIGA also issued a guarantee for S50&#13;
MIGA issuedaguaranteefor$45 million   million forMobil Corporation's new venture&#13;
toSaudiAmeticanBankforitscapitalcontri-  in Saudi Arabia.&#13;
MIGA and the environment&#13;
Since MIGA's inception it has taken steps to ensure that the projects it assists operate&#13;
in an environmentally sound manner and meet appropriate eavironmental standards. The&#13;
more stringent of the host country's requirements or the World Bank Group's environ-&#13;
mental guidelines are applied to each project&#13;
As anew institution, MIGA recognizes that its volume of business could not support&#13;
the establishment of a full-time environmental unit to assess each project's environmen-&#13;
tal impact on the host country. MIGA has therefore entered into an agreement with the&#13;
IFC for its Technical and Environmental Department to serve as MIGA's enviromnental&#13;
adviser. Both parties have benefited from this anrangement&#13;
15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Lain Amenica and the Caribbean        investment in Argentina. Generale Bank in-&#13;
sured its equity participation in the newly&#13;
MIGA country membership in the region   privatized telecommunications industry in&#13;
increased significantly in fiscal 1993, offer-  Argentina. The govemment of Argentina&#13;
ingthepromise ofexpandedoperationsinthe   privatized Empresa Nacional de Tele-&#13;
future. MIGA was particularly active in Ar-  comunicaciones (ENTEL) in November1990&#13;
gentina because of the many investment op-  and split it into two operating companies.&#13;
portunitiesthataroseasaconsequence of the   The project enterprise, Compania de&#13;
govemment's favorable policies toward the  Inversiones en Telecomunicaciones S.A_&#13;
private sector.                       (Cointel), has a 60 percent interest in&#13;
Telefonicade Argentina SA. (TASA). which&#13;
Hydro Aluminum A.S.. Jamaica          owns and operates the new southern system.&#13;
Generale Bank provided $48.2 million to-&#13;
MIGAissueditsfirstguarantee inJamaica   ward the funding by Cointel.&#13;
to Norsk Hydro A.S. of Norway for an alu-&#13;
mina and bauxite mining project Tbrough its  MIGA also assisted three other financial&#13;
subsidiary, Hydra-Alumrinum A_S of Ja-  institutions that made investments in&#13;
maica, Norsk Hydro expanded its joint ven-  Argentina:&#13;
ture with Phelps Dodge, AluminaPartners of  - Banco Espafiol de Cr6lito, a Spanish&#13;
Jamaica. Total project financing is $179 mil-  bank, for $15 million&#13;
lion, of which Norsk Hydro is providing  - Citibank, a U.S bank, for $25 million&#13;
$62.65 million. The mining project is ex-  - Internationale Nederlanden, a Dutch&#13;
pected to increase production capacity by 50   bank, for S15 million&#13;
percent, to 1.5 nillion metric tons a year.&#13;
Aluminaandbauxiteexportsaccountformuch   Asia&#13;
of Jamaica's exports and are critical sources&#13;
of foreign exchange.The project will gener-  MIGA's projects in Asia in fiscal 1993&#13;
ate annual exports valued at $12 million and   were dominated by contracts issued to finan-&#13;
pay additional taxes of$8.3 million annually.  cial institutions, particularly for their invest-&#13;
Seventy new jobs will be created, and local  mentsinPakistan. Theseinvestmentswillhelp&#13;
procurement is expected to increase substan-  expand and diversify the financial services&#13;
tially. The project will also be contributing   and resources available for productive in-&#13;
funds to improve the social infrastructure in  vestrnent and will stimulate comnpetition in&#13;
the region. MIGA has provided $20.2 million  the banking sector. In fiscal 1993 MIGA&#13;
of coverage against the risks of expropriation   pmovided coverage to the following investors&#13;
and war and civil disturbance         in Pakistan:&#13;
Generale Bank, Argentina                 - BankofAmerica,NT&amp;SA,aU.S.bank,&#13;
for $6.8 million&#13;
MIGA issued coverage for$15 million to  * Banque Indosuez, a French bank, for&#13;
Generale Bankof Belgium againsttheriskof  $9.0 million&#13;
currency transfer and expropriation for its  - Citibank Overseas Investment Corpo-&#13;
16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ration, a U.S. company, for two projects for  for $6.4 million&#13;
$3.5 million and $2.2 million            * Soci&amp;6 Generale. a French bank, for&#13;
- Habib Bank AG Zurich, a Swiss bank,  $11.0 million&#13;
Fmancial Institutions: Waiver of provisioning requirements for country risk&#13;
Private financial institutions, especially commercial banks, face a number of hurdles&#13;
when they consider doing business in a developing country-whether setting up or&#13;
expanding a branch or subsidiary bank, participating in a limited-recourse private&#13;
financing in a developing country, or even following a client to a developing country and&#13;
lending to its new ventum. One of the more difficult hurdles for such banks is the&#13;
provisioning requirements of their national regulatory banking authorities, which effec-&#13;
tively raise the banks' costs of lending to projects in developing countries or, in extreme&#13;
cases, preclude such lending.&#13;
To address this problem, MIGA initiated discussions with bankig regulators in a&#13;
number of industrial countries. So far MIGA has successfully concluded discussions in&#13;
seven countries-Belgium, F:rance, Japan, the Netherlands, Spain, Sweden, and the&#13;
United Kingdom. These countries have agreed to exempt their banks rom pmvisioning&#13;
requirements for country nsk (or to greatly reduce the provisioning requirements) if they&#13;
have aMIGA guarantee. MIGA is now working with the regulatory authorities of several&#13;
other European countries to obtain similar rulings.&#13;
These agreements have already had an impact on MIGA's volume of business with&#13;
banks establishing or expanding activities in developing countries. In the longer term the&#13;
agreements will also encourage more bank participation in limited-recourse financing&#13;
and allow banks to pursue opporunmities they would not otherwise be able to undertake.&#13;
Such MIGA-facilitated investments in the financial sector will promote competition&#13;
in developing countries and increase the pool of capital available for lending to private&#13;
sector projects. For large-scale private projects (in the energy sector, for example) the&#13;
increase in the potential pool of capital afforded by waiver of these provisioning&#13;
requirements could be significant in determining whether a given project wil proceed.&#13;
17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A MIGA-assisted mining venture in Guyana has a strong impact on development&#13;
in fiscal 1992 MIGA issued two reinsurance conract totaling $49.8 million for the&#13;
Canadian Export Development Corporation's insurance of Cambior's $163 million&#13;
equity and loan guarantee contributions to Omai Gold Mine, Ltd. in Guyana. MIGA's&#13;
reinsmancecovers Cambioragainsttherisksofcurrency transfer, expropriation, and war&#13;
and civil dinsturbance.&#13;
Cambior, Inc. established a Guyanese subsidiary, Omai Gold Mines, Ltd., to manage&#13;
and operate the mining facility in which it holds 65 percent ownership. The government&#13;
of Guyana and Golden Star Resources, Ltd. (a Canadian mining company) are the other&#13;
shareholders. The Omai Mine is in a remote area some one hundred miles south of&#13;
Georgetown, the capital of Guyana- It is Guyana's first major go1d mining operation and&#13;
is expected to become one of the largest gold mines in South America. Total investment&#13;
in the project is $181 million, and the annual average gold production over a ten-year&#13;
period is estimated to be 210,000 ounces.&#13;
The project is already having a strong developmental impact on the country and on the&#13;
local economy through the creation of jobs and the development of local infrastructure.&#13;
Eight hundred new jobs have resulted for Guyanese, many of whom will benefit from a&#13;
comprehensive $1.4 million training program. In addition, the local economy is being&#13;
stimulated through spending on goods and services estimated at more than $19 million&#13;
during the first three years of operation. Guyana is also benefiting from Cambiors&#13;
developmentoftelecommunicationsfacilities andthe constructionofdocksites, wharves,&#13;
roads, and a medical center. Net foreign exchange eamings from the project are estmated&#13;
to be about $35 million a year, and the project is expected to produce a cumulative net&#13;
cash flow forthe govermment from royalties, taxes, and dividends of about $100 million&#13;
over eight years.&#13;
Cambior is clearly committed to acting in an environmentally responsible fashion.&#13;
The Omai mining operation has implemented environmental procedures and measures&#13;
dtat seek to harmonize economic exploitation of the gold resources with protection of the&#13;
enviroment Cambior commissioned a comprehensive environmental impact study of&#13;
the project, which was approved by independent experts selected by the Govemment of&#13;
Guyana.&#13;
1 8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Other projects assisted in Asia included:&#13;
Non-Fluid Oil International, China&#13;
MIGAissuedequitycoveragefor$540,OO0I&#13;
against the risks of expropriation, and war |&#13;
and civil disturbance to Non-Fluid Oil of the&#13;
United States for its joint venture with&#13;
Shandong Yantai Glass Factory, owned by&#13;
the Yantai municipality. This small business&#13;
project will produce glass mold lubricants   The foundation of KAFCO's urea storage faclity near&#13;
and other specialized lubricants. The prod-   Chittagong Bangladesh.&#13;
ucts, which will initially be used by local   poration and Chiyoda Corporation, two Japa-&#13;
manufacturers, will be of higher quality than   nese equity investors in the Kamaphuli Ferdl-&#13;
currendy available irrQorted products. Other  izer Company, Ltd. (KAFCO) in Bangladesh.&#13;
economic benefits include annual revenues   This $500 million fertilizer facility experi-&#13;
for the Chinese govremment of about   enced delays in implementation that necessi-&#13;
$396,000, creation of twenty-six new jobs,  tated a restructuring of the complex project&#13;
and local procurement of 95 percent of the   financing. As a result, both Marubeni and&#13;
raw materials. Some personnel will receive   Chiyoda increased their contributions to the&#13;
trining abroad.                          project in fiscal 1992. MIGA issued $16.1&#13;
million of additional coverage to each of&#13;
X 3  these Japanese investors to cover their loans&#13;
to the project.&#13;
N  i j  _  Toyota Tsusho, Pakistan&#13;
--   MGAconcludedareinsurance agreement&#13;
with the Ministry of Intemrational Trade and&#13;
Industry (MITT) to provide $2.1 million in&#13;
currency transfer coverage to this Japanese&#13;
firm. Troyota will assemble vehicles from&#13;
knock-down kits in a facility in the Sindh&#13;
region of Pakistan. In addition to signifi-&#13;
TbeYantai-NFOlubricansproduction faduliyinYuntai.  cantly lowering the costofToyotavehicles to&#13;
Chin2.Theprojectpoducesavarietyorlubricantsforuse   Pakistani consumers and saving foreign ex-&#13;
in the domiestiindnstrial marketplacmt  change, the project will directly employ 476&#13;
Marubeni Corporation and Chiyoda         Pakistanis and indirectly stimulate the em-&#13;
Corporation, Bangladesh                  ployment of many others to supply auto parts&#13;
locally. Pakistani engineers, supervisors, and&#13;
In fiscal 1991 MIGA issued guarantees of   instructors will receive extensive training in&#13;
$9.9 million each to support Marubeni Cor-   Toyota facilities in other countries.&#13;
19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Promotional and advisory services&#13;
ence held in Botswana in May 1993, was&#13;
''EM                            MIGA's major promotional activity of the&#13;
year. The conference brought together repre-&#13;
sentatives of firms operating in the region,&#13;
potential investors, and Botswana govern-&#13;
MIGA provides a variety of promotional  mentofficials to discuss investmentopportu-&#13;
and advisory services to its developing mem-  nities and business development policies fo-&#13;
bercountries to support theirefforts to attract  cusing on tourism, financial and business&#13;
foreign direct investment. These services are  services. light manufacturing, and&#13;
provided both directly through the Policy   agribusiness.Foreignfirmswereattractedby&#13;
and Advisory Services unit (PAS) and inch-  the country's strong economic growth over&#13;
rectly through the Foreign Investment Advi-  the past two decades, its stable political cli-&#13;
sory Service (H:AS), MIGA's joint faclity   mate, and the emerging business sector. In&#13;
with the IFC and the World Bank. Services  addition to promoting specific opportunities&#13;
provided through PAS include the organiza-  in Botswana, the conference provided an&#13;
tion of investment promotion events (such as   opportunity for foreign firms to explore re-&#13;
investment promotion conferences and in-  gionalinvestmentopportunities,particularly&#13;
vestment missions), executive training pro-  in tounsm, with pnvate sector partcipants&#13;
grams, foreign  investment policy   from the neighboring countries of Lesotho,&#13;
implementors workshops, and institution-  Namibia, Swaziland, and Zambia. This&#13;
building activities.Duringfiscal 1993MIGA   multicountry approach proved successfiil,&#13;
conductedthirteensuchactivitiesintencoun-   and MIGA expects to repeat it in other parts&#13;
tries. Services provided thomugh FIAS in-   of the developing world.&#13;
clude a range of specialized policy advisory  Other promotional events held in Africa&#13;
assistance to governments,            mcluded a major mining investment confer-&#13;
In fiscal 1993 F.iS redirected its activi-  ence in Namibia, cosponsored by MICA and&#13;
ties toward a greater emphasis on capacity  the government and attended by more than&#13;
buildingforinvestmentpromotionandinten-   350 private investors and business execu-&#13;
sified collaboration with other agencies to  tives. A workshop on investor services in&#13;
expand its impact. Wherever possible PAS   Uganda provided a forum for sixty local&#13;
sought to engage in multicountry activities to  business leaders to hear from over a dozen&#13;
extendbenefitstoawidernumberofMIGA's  international and local agencies that provide&#13;
membercountries. Linkages to MIAg's guar-  financial and other services to home and host&#13;
antee operations and to other parts of the   country investors.&#13;
World Bank Group were strengthened in    To coincide with the annual meetings of&#13;
order to tap the synergistic benefits of such  the World Bank Group. MIGA organized a&#13;
cooperation.                          meeting promoting investment opportunities&#13;
in El Salvador. In cooperation with El&#13;
Promotional events                    Salvador's Foundation for Economic and&#13;
Social Development (FUSADES), MIGA&#13;
New Opportunities in a Changing South-   brought together high-level govemment of-&#13;
ern Africa, an investment promotion confer-  ficials, private business executives from Sal-&#13;
20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
vadoran finns, and representatives of U.S.  Programs held during fiscal 1993 in&#13;
fims,governmentagencies,andinternational  Namibia, Zambia, and Swaziland (also for&#13;
organizations. The meeting provided a fo-  executives from Lesotho) were attended by&#13;
rum for the Salvadoran private and govern-   more than 130 local business executives.&#13;
ment delegations to inform prospective U.S.  Several participants were able to apply the&#13;
investors about recent changes in El  knowledge and skillsdeveloped in these pro-&#13;
Salvador's political, economic, and social  grams to the search forforeign partners when&#13;
conditions.                            they attended the MIGA-organized invest-&#13;
As part of a broader promotional effort to   ment promotion conference in Botswana.&#13;
develop a work program for the Southem   Local counterparts (consultants, business&#13;
Caribbean, MIGA and Caribbean Latin  associations, and representatives of local&#13;
American Action (CLAA), anonprofit, U.S.-  development agencies) were included in these&#13;
based group, cosponsored an investment  programs with a view to developing their&#13;
mission to Guyana in April 1993. MIGA also  skils for conducting such programs in the&#13;
conducted an executive development pro-  future. MIGA also began to develop support-&#13;
gram in conjunction with that mission.  ive training materials for local use.&#13;
Executive development programs&#13;
MIGA's executivedevelopmentprogrami&#13;
series, How to Do Business with Foreign&#13;
Partners, is designed to complement its in-&#13;
vestment promotion conferences and to im-&#13;
prove communication between local manag-&#13;
ers in developing countries and potential&#13;
foreign investors. The programs give local&#13;
participants abetter understanding of how to&#13;
develop business plans, find the right foreign&#13;
business partner, market their finns, and   A Zambian ereeneur at the dose o!a sucessfrl&#13;
evaluateandnegotiateforeignbusinessdeals.    Ifldedopmveapart  uprats.&#13;
Policy implementors workshops&#13;
AMM- &amp;L                        As a follow-up to a foreign investnent&#13;
tO rt     sW    @°nO wc    policy roundtable for Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
-           -           arranged by MIGA in June 1992, MIGA and&#13;
EXECTIVE DEVELOPMENT PROGRAMME             FIAS organized workshops in Tanzania,&#13;
HOW TO W BUSINESS WITH FOREIGN PARNRS'   Uganda, and Zimbabwe in June 1993. Local&#13;
Xsat 6anWMn" Contina CQn., a81O'MQR 93  policy implementors discussed with their&#13;
counterparts in the private sector the kinds of&#13;
regulatory rules and procedures that inhibit&#13;
foreign direct investment Participants from&#13;
21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C"'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-            - -&#13;
MhV        IAY         QOlSki  NA  ltNETitT               ^-tr &#13;
The Dotswaa Investment Fronotion conference, focusd onopportunities in manufacturing. tonr~sun agriculture&#13;
fimucanlservces.,andiunfr.asrmcture developumnet,vwasattend ed by overl.50 international and regional investosaud 100&#13;
local busines executives&#13;
developing countries outside Africathat have   investmnenL Bangladesh, Fiji, Mauritania,&#13;
successfully undertaken deregulation shared    Pakistan, Sri Lanka, and Zambia are amnong&#13;
their experience. They discussed such issues   countries i-at received such assistance dur-&#13;
as how to revise and implement regulations   ing the past fiscal year-&#13;
after a policy change has been announced and    MIGA also developed a special training&#13;
how to replace traditional, control-oriented    program for government officials on the role&#13;
systemns with market-based alternatives,     and importance of bilateral and multilateral&#13;
treaties and other relevant components of a&#13;
Legal advisory activities                    country's legal framework for attracting for-&#13;
eign direct investment. By evaluating these&#13;
During the fiscal year MIGA's Legal   legal instruments in the country concerned,&#13;
Departmnent worked with HIAS to provide    offi-cials become familiar with the elements&#13;
assistance on the legal fr-amework for foreign    that are crucial to the encouragement of for-&#13;
direct investInent in a number of countries. It   eign direct investnent. The approach has&#13;
participated in evaluating the investment cli-   proved successful, and requests for this pro-&#13;
mateandrelevantinvestment regulationsand    gram have been received from a number of&#13;
helped countries draft specialized laws and    countries.&#13;
regulations appropriate for attracting foreign&#13;
22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Foreign Investment Advisory Service    stitutional development (C6te d'Ivoire and&#13;
Pakistan) and various specific investment&#13;
FIAS,whichisjointlyoperatedbyMIGA,   policy issues (Jordan and Tanzania).&#13;
the IFC, and the W. orld Bank, advises devel-  In addition to formal advisory work FIAS&#13;
oping member governments on how to at-  conducted a number of seminars and a&#13;
tract more foreign direct investmenL The   roundtable:&#13;
scope of FIAS's advisory activities mayrange  * Seminar on investment promotion in&#13;
from an examination of the whole of a   China, which introduced government offi-&#13;
country's investmentclimate, such as identi-  cials to international experience with invest-&#13;
fying high-priority aspects for which im-   ment promotion mechanisms and techniques&#13;
provements are likely to be most productive,  and reviewed the investment promotion ef-&#13;
to specific, localized advice on what needs to  forts of each province.&#13;
be done in such areas as the legal framework,  - Workshop on foreign investment pro-&#13;
taxation and incentives, foreign exchange   motion techniques in Bolivia, hosted by the&#13;
access, and institutions and strategies for   Minister of Exports and Economic Competi-&#13;
promoting the country as a place to invest.   tiveness.Theworkshopwasattendedbygov-&#13;
In fiscal 1993 FIAS completed thir-one   enunent officials and representatives of the&#13;
advisory projects in twenty-eight countries.  Investment Promotion Center of Bolivia and&#13;
It also conducted a number of seminars on   other private institutions engaged in invest-&#13;
foreign investment policy, including invest-   ment promotion. Presentations highlighted&#13;
ment promotion techniques and the legal  the experiences of other countries and the&#13;
framework necessary for improving the in-  lessons of their successes and failures.&#13;
vestment cimate.                         - Workcshopsonforeigninvestmentpolicy&#13;
Advisory projects covered a broad range  implementation in Tanzania, Uganda, and&#13;
of topics. Among them were overall reviews   Zimbabwe, a collaborative effort of FIAS&#13;
of the investment environment (Mauritania,  ztd MIGA.&#13;
Paraguay, and Russia-see box on page 24);  * RoundtablefiorAsian countries in tran-&#13;
development of proposals for foreign invest-  sition to a market economy, which provided&#13;
ment promotion agencies (Bangladesh and   an opportunity for officials from six coun-&#13;
Russia) and of investment promotion strate-  tries to discuss foreign investment policies in&#13;
gies (Sri Lanka); assistance in revising in-  the transition.&#13;
vestment codes (Zambia); and advice on in-&#13;
23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A new management information system for investment promotion agencies&#13;
During fiscal 1993 MIGA participated in the development of a state-of-the-art&#13;
computer-based management information system initiated and funded by HIAS. This&#13;
system will help investmentpromotion agencies around the world improve their capacity&#13;
to manage investmnent promotion and achieve world standards of effectiveness. The&#13;
computer-based system is both sophisticated and user-friendly, generic and readily&#13;
adoptable to specific county situations. YIGA and FIAS are working jointly to&#13;
introduce the two main opertional components of the system-4he investor tracking&#13;
system and the business operating conditions database-into investment promotion&#13;
agencies. A training package on how to conduct successful investment promotion&#13;
activities accompanies the software. Preparations are under way to introduce the new&#13;
system into countries in Africa, Asia, Europe, and Latin America.&#13;
FIAS's advisory assistance to the Russia Federation&#13;
Following its participation in the Study of the Soviet Economy, sponsored jointly by&#13;
the Organization for Economic Cooperaton and Development, the RIMF, the World&#13;
Bank, and the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development, FIAS has provided&#13;
advisory assistance to several counties of the former Soviet Union. As part of the&#13;
Technical Cooperation Program of the World Bank and the Russian Federation, FIAS,&#13;
with assistance from MIGA, conducted an extensive study of the foreign direct invest-&#13;
ment environment of Russia The study addressed questions of foreign exchange rates&#13;
and controls, legal impediments to foreign direct investment, the screening and approval&#13;
of foreign investment projects, and corporate income taxation and tax incentives. It also&#13;
offered comments on Russia's foreign investment law and on the role of foreign direct&#13;
investment in developing Russia's financial sector, notably in banking, leasing, venture&#13;
capital, and securities dealing and brokerage.&#13;
After the study was completed, the government requested FIAS's advice on the&#13;
institutional development of the Russian Agency for International Cooperation and&#13;
Development. Working closely with the agency, FHAS helped it define its role in&#13;
regulating and promoting foreign direct investment in Russia and in designting mecha-&#13;
nisms and structures for dealing with foreign investment.&#13;
FIAS has also provided advisory assistance to Russia on an informal basis, including&#13;
reactions to amendments of its foreign investment law being developed by a Committee&#13;
of the Supreme Soviet, and advice, at the request of the Privatization Ministry, on several&#13;
foreign investment issues related to privatization.&#13;
24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIAS expands its activities in Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
FIAS has advised more than two-thirds of the countries in Sub-Saharan Africa. In&#13;
fiscal 1993 FIAS began work in eight African countries in which it had not worked before&#13;
and completed projects in ten countries. Completed projects included general diagnoses&#13;
of investment policy issues in COte d'lvoire, Mauritania, Namibia, Sudan, Zambia, and&#13;
Zimbabwe; preparation of new investment legislation in Ghana and Zambia; formula-&#13;
tion of short-term measures to assist in investment promotion in C8te d'Ivoire; and study&#13;
of foreign exchange and debt-swap issues in Tanzania.&#13;
At the close of the fiscal year FIAS was developing assignments in C8te d'Ivoire,&#13;
Ethiopia, Ghana, and Swaziland and preparing follow-up projects in six countries. FIAS&#13;
also organized afour-session workshop forAfrican ambassadors to the United States on&#13;
foreign investment issues, sponsored by Africare and the Georgetown University&#13;
Institute for the Study of Diplomacy. In collaboration with MIGA, FIAS also organized&#13;
workshops in Tanzania, Uganda, and Zimnbabwe on the importance of deregulation in the&#13;
countries' overall efforts to improve their investment environment.&#13;
25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-              MIGA  1988-93: A five-year retrospective&#13;
investnent, and investment insurance, with&#13;
little enthusiasm (see box on page 27). The&#13;
increase in membership raised MIGA's sub-&#13;
scribed capital to $948 million by the end of&#13;
fiscal 1993.&#13;
The idea ofa multilateral investment guar-    i  6)&#13;
antee scheme dates back to discussions in&#13;
1948. Attempts to define the nature and func-&#13;
tions of such a scheme were revived in the   MIGA Membership growth&#13;
early 1980s by the World Bank. The MIGA  Number of countries&#13;
Convention-the legal doctument that estab-    150&#13;
lishedMIGA-wasagreedinSeptember1985           U Convention signatories&#13;
and opened for signature by World Bank       El[ Full members&#13;
member states and Switzerland (not then a    ioo-&#13;
member of the World Bank) in October.&#13;
Following signature by the United States in&#13;
April 1988, MIGA was fornally constituted,    so-&#13;
withtwenty-ninecountriescompletingmem-&#13;
bership.&#13;
Frora the beginning MIGA has pursued a  o&#13;
dual mandate of providing noncommercial     19ss  19s9 1990 1991 1992 1993&#13;
risk guuarntees and offering technical assis-&#13;
tance and specialized training to assist its&#13;
developing member countries in atracting&#13;
foreign private investment. To encourage  The creation ofanew international devel-&#13;
this investmcnt, MIGA deals with both host  opment entity has been a challenging under-&#13;
governments (helping them create an attrac-  taking. Chronicling the evolution of MIGA's&#13;
tive climate for foreign investment) and in-   activities is a useful means of assessing&#13;
vestors (providing guarantees for their in-   MIGA's success in meeting its founders'&#13;
vestments in host countries).          expectations for it as a development institu-&#13;
MIGA's growth has been significant in  tion. In this spirit the next two sections re-&#13;
the five years concluding June 30, 1993,  viewthechangingnatureofMIGA'sguaran-&#13;
country membership (the universe within  tees and promotional and advisory activities.&#13;
which guarantees can be issued) has grown&#13;
from 29 to 107 countries (flgure 6). A total of   Guarantee activities&#13;
139 countries have signed the MIGA Con-&#13;
vention, and 90 developing member coun-   Setting up any new enterprise is difficult&#13;
tries are now eligible to receive guarantees   MIGA was no exception. In MIGA's early&#13;
andpromotional and advisory services. These   days staff responsible for the guarantee pro-&#13;
signatory countries include many countries   gram were involved in establishing intemal&#13;
of the fonner Soviet Union and many Latin   operating and administrative procedures&#13;
American countries that once viewed foreign   while also infomning prospective investors&#13;
26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MIGA in Latin America&#13;
At the time of MIGA's founding there was considerable skepticism about a role for&#13;
the Agency in Latin America. Many observers were afraid that Latin America's&#13;
traditional resistance to investment insurance programs would keep a substantial number&#13;
of Lain states from joining MIGA.&#13;
This did not happen. MlGA's staff have made special efforts from the beginning to&#13;
demonstrate the compatibility of MIGA's operations with local laws and customs in&#13;
Latn  America. These efforts have bome fruit during the past three years virtually all&#13;
countries in the Latin America and Caribbean region have joined MIGA. Participation&#13;
in MCGA has gone hand in hand with recent efforts by the Latin states to open their&#13;
economies.&#13;
The results have been dramatic. Within two years Latin America has become the&#13;
region with the second largest number of MIGA-supported projects. Of the sixty-three&#13;
insurance contracts wntten by MIGA in its first five years, seventeen cover investments&#13;
in Latin America and the Caribbean. As of June 30, 1993, one-third of MIGA's&#13;
contingent liability was concentrated in the region. Similarly, Latin Amercan states are&#13;
increasingly drawing on the technical assistance services of MIGA and FIAS-&#13;
aboutMGGA'sguaranteeservices.Staffmcm-    The first guarantee projects were difficult&#13;
bers participated in scores of briefings, semi-  because of the need to establish, with the guid-&#13;
nars, and conferences worldwide to market  ance of the Board of Directors, procedures for&#13;
GICA's guarantee services. Direct mailings,  evaluating and analyzing investors' applica-&#13;
participation in business and trade forums,  tions for coverage, procedures covering board&#13;
and referrals by national export credit insur-  consideration of projects, and for issuing and&#13;
ers all contributed to increased awareness of  managing contracts. Product improvements&#13;
MIGA's guarantee program.              were also introduced dunng the lattr half of&#13;
MIGA staff also worked to build relation-  this five-year period, such as clarification and&#13;
ships with other investment insurers. In fiscal  enhancement of the coverage for war and civil&#13;
1990 MIGA signed both its first insurance   disturbance and arestructuring ofthe approach&#13;
contract and its first contracts with national  to standby coverage. In fiscal 1992 and 1993&#13;
investment insurers-from Canada and the   MICA developed and actively promoted an&#13;
United States. In fiscal 1992 MIGA entered  insurance brokers program and prepared a&#13;
into three more reinsurance arrangements,  marketing campaign directed at specific in-&#13;
including its first agreement with a private  dustries-bankingandenergy--throughcus-&#13;
political risk insurer. MIGA's acceptance  tomized contracts and targeted promotional&#13;
into the Beme Union as an observer in 1991   activities.&#13;
has provided a valuable forum for strength-  The effort to rach financial institutions&#13;
ening its relationships with national insurers,  was especially successfuL Because MIGA pro-&#13;
especially the smaller programs.        vides long-term, noncancelable insurance&#13;
27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
against political nsk, countries like France,  Promotional and advisory activities&#13;
Spain, Sweden, and the United Kingdom have&#13;
waived or exempted commercial banks rom   Since its establishment MIGA has also&#13;
provisioning requirements for investnents or   pursued its other mandate of offering techni-&#13;
loans for projects in a developing country if  calassistanceandspecializedtrainingtohelp&#13;
they are covered by a MIGA guarantee (see  its developing member countries atract for-&#13;
box on page 17).                       eign private investmenL These activities are&#13;
MIGA News, a quarterly publication for  cunrently carried out by two separate but&#13;
prospective investors, was launched in 1991   closely coordinated bodies, the Policy and&#13;
and has steadily expanded its subscription   Advisory Services unit (PAS) and the For-&#13;
list. The Agency also developed and widely  eign Investment Advisory Service (HAS).&#13;
disseminated several other publications, in-   MIGA's Legal Departmnenr working inde-&#13;
Table L Guarantee activities, fiscal 1990-93&#13;
Fiscal 1990    Fiscal 1991   Fiscal 1992  Fiscal 1993&#13;
Number of guarantees    4             11          21          27&#13;
Maximm contingent&#13;
liability              S132.3 million  $58.9 million  $313 million  $374 million&#13;
Aggrgate direct investment&#13;
facilited             S.O bilion    $0.9 billion   $1 billion    $1.9 billion&#13;
Jobs generated in&#13;
host counfties         2,700         3,680       2.920       1,720&#13;
cluding the Investment Guarantee Guide, the   pendently or with PAS or FIAS, has also&#13;
Insurance Brokers Program brochure, and   undertaken legal advisory work related to&#13;
the Financial Institutions brochure.   foreign investment&#13;
MIGA also devoted attention to market-  In the begining, because of limited re-&#13;
ing its products and simplifying its proce-  sources, MIGA concentrated its policy and&#13;
dures. An Applications Office, established in  advisory efforts on a small number of highly&#13;
1991, helps to expedite the processing of a   visiblemarketingactivities.MlGAorganized&#13;
rising number ofguarantee applications. The  investment promotion conferences in Ghana&#13;
steamlining of procedures, such as maldng   andHungary(1990),inJamaicaandPakistan&#13;
the basic contract more user-friendly, helps  (1991), and in Botswana (1993). During an&#13;
reduce the information burden on clients. As   early conference it became apparent that in&#13;
a result of all these efforts insurance cover-   many countries entepreneurs lacked the abil-&#13;
age has increased from $1323 million for  ity and know-how to do business with for-&#13;
four projects in fiscal 1990 to $745 million   eign partners. M1GA launched its executive&#13;
for fifty-seven projects (net of cancellations)   development program series in 1991 to raise&#13;
as of June 30, 1993 (table 1).         the awareness of local entrepreneurs and&#13;
28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
improve their skills in developing business  agencies in more advanced developing na-&#13;
plans, finding suitable foreign business part-  tions, and to establish stronger links to the&#13;
ners, and negotiating favorable foreign in-   MIGA guarantee program. Several elements&#13;
vestment dealts. MIGA has organized eight  of this new onentation were explored in&#13;
executive development programs involving   fiscal 1993:&#13;
several hundred domestic business execu-  * An initiative to form a consultative&#13;
tives-in Portugal, for five Lusophone Afri-  network of investment promotion agencies&#13;
can countries, and in Angola, Czechoslova-  to exchange information on business condi-&#13;
kia, Guyana, Hungary, Namibia, Swaziland  tions and other factors for attracting foreign&#13;
(also for Lesotho), and Zambia.       investment,with MGAprovidingsecretariat&#13;
In addition to these activities MIGA took   services.Theactivities of investmentpromo-&#13;
onothertasks.Itorganizedapolicyroundtable  tion agencies provide an excellent vehicle for&#13;
conference in Botswana in 1992 to enable   marketing MIGA's guarantee facilities.&#13;
high-level government officials from Africa  - Involvement in investment promotion&#13;
to leam from their peers in other developing   conferences only where members are com-&#13;
countries about what policies and programs   mitted to providing a policy environmnent&#13;
are most effective in attracting foreign m-   attractive to foreign investors. Whenever&#13;
vestment The conference was followed by   possible, conferences are being focused on a&#13;
separate policy workshops executed jointly  nan-ower range of investment opportunities&#13;
with FIAS in Tanznia, Uganda, and Zimba-  and taking on a multicountry and regional&#13;
bwe. MIGA also researched the policies of  institution-building emphasis.&#13;
industial countries thathave had the greatest  * Furtherdevelopment,withFIAS, ofthe&#13;
impact on foreign investment flows to devel-  computer-based management system for in-&#13;
oping countries and disseminated the results  vestment promotion agencies (see box on&#13;
widely. MIGA recently cosponsored a min-  page 24).&#13;
ing investment conference in Namibia, a  In short, PAS will focus on promotional&#13;
workshop on investor services in Uganda,  activities while FHAS concentrates on policy&#13;
and an investmnent mission to Guyana and   advisory services.&#13;
organized an investment mission on       Organizationally,FlAShasevolvedfrom&#13;
El Salvador, held in Washington, D.C.  an EFC activity, to a cosponsored activity of&#13;
As M[GA gained expenence over the   MIGA and the IEFC, to a jointly managed&#13;
past five years, a need to reorient its invest-  venture of MIGA, the IEFC, and the World&#13;
ment promotion activities began to become   Bank The three institutions now provide&#13;
evident PAS therefore embarked on a com-   about half the funding for FIAS's program,&#13;
prehensive effort to enhance the services it  with the other half coming from extemal&#13;
provides to MIGA's members. PAS is seek-  sources.&#13;
ing to improve the geographical and func-  Demand for FLAS's advisory services on&#13;
tional balance of its activities, to reach more  foreign direct investment has grown rapidly.&#13;
MIGA members, to emphasize capacity-   Project completions tripled from nine in fis-&#13;
building and other neglected aspects of in-  cal 1989 to more ta thirty in fiscal 1993&#13;
vestment promotion, to foster the establish-  (figure 7). In the five years since fiscal 1989&#13;
mentandstrengtheningofnationalinsurance  tne number of countries in which FIAS has&#13;
29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
been active has increased from five to thirty-  (Figure 8)&#13;
nine. FIAS launched programs in Eastern&#13;
Europe in fiscal 1989, and in the Latin         Completed projects by type&#13;
America and the Caribbean region and the                of project&#13;
Middle East and Norti Africa region in fiscal  :5&#13;
1991. Today, FIAS's advisory services reach  30   Promo st&#13;
all regions of the developing world.       3 -      tt&#13;
The geographical diversity of the pro-  A-  lgn-tic&#13;
gram is matched by a growing diversity in the   *Innent pol,li&#13;
types of assistance provided (fgure 8). Diag-  2 -* Other&#13;
is&#13;
(Figure7)&#13;
10 &#13;
Completed projects by regon           o -&#13;
Eg iLAC                                  fi6 Si7 88 89 90 91 92  9&#13;
30 -  B                       X                         Frical vear&#13;
9MENA&#13;
25 -    F- Eupe               Hment issues. HAS has also convened confer-&#13;
20 -    Sub-Saharan    -              ences, seminars, and workshops to inform&#13;
Afica            |govenmments about foreign investment is-&#13;
15 -                                  sues. It has produced aiing videos on suc-&#13;
o0 -              1|         iii      cessful models of foreign investment regimes&#13;
andon techniques for ating foreign invest-&#13;
5 -                 |                   =1 *--- ment and other types of foreign collaboration.&#13;
0           =      _RFAS has worked with MIGA, the IFC,&#13;
S6 S7 88 89 90 91 92  93         and the World Bank on a range of activities&#13;
Fiscal vear           that rely on the strengths of each institution.&#13;
One example is the MIGA-organized invest-&#13;
ment promotion conference held in Pakistan&#13;
nostic evaluations, which broadly identify  in 1992. Before the conference FAS, in its&#13;
obstacles to attracting foreign investment,  advisory capacity, verified that the country's&#13;
and more in-depth studies of specific invest-  policy franework, though not perfect, had&#13;
ment policies continue to constitute the bulk   progressedsufficientlyto makethesubsequent&#13;
of FIAS's business. FHAS has also engaged   investment promotion effort worthwhile.&#13;
in research to support its advisory work pro-&#13;
gram, in the dissemination of information   Legal activities&#13;
and expertise on foreign investnent issues,&#13;
and in product development                 MIGA's legal activities are relevant both&#13;
To share its accumulated knowledge and   to the Agency's guarantee operations and to&#13;
research findings broadly, FIAS publishes an   its promotional and advisory services. MIGA&#13;
Occasional Paper series on foreign invest-  has negotiated twenty-four legal protection&#13;
30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
agreements and twenty-five agreements on   the course of drafting their own domestic&#13;
the use of local currency received by MIGA   investmentlawsornegotiatingbilaterltrea-&#13;
in the event of a claim. These agreements  ties for protecting and promoting invest-&#13;
protect MIGA's right, as subrogee of a com-   ments. The guidelines are also used regu-&#13;
pensated guarantee holder, to compensation   larly by MIGA in evaluating the adequacy of&#13;
in a freely usable currency. The agreements  the legal protection of foreign investment in&#13;
on the disposition of local currency also   host countries for invtstments eligible for&#13;
allow MIGA to enter into arrangements with   MIGA guarantees, as required by the MIGA&#13;
otherintemationalentities ordiplomaticrep-   Convention.&#13;
resentatives accredited by the govemment&#13;
for the transfer and use of local currency that  Condusion&#13;
maybe acquired by the Agency. These agree-&#13;
ments strengthen MIGA's position as in-  During these past five years MIGA's un-&#13;
surer, since they offer the prospect of reduc-  derstanding ofthe kdnds of services investors&#13;
ing losses to MIGA should salvage opera-  anddevelopingcountriesrequire,andofhow&#13;
dons become necessary. Agreements of this  besttoprovidethem,hasgrownandmatured.&#13;
type, which are public law instruments, also   MIGA'sserviceshavebecomemorefocused&#13;
help to improve the investment climate in the   and more responsive to its clients, as evi-&#13;
signatory state. MIGA, alone or jointly with  denced by the number of contracts executed&#13;
FIAS, has also worked with many member  and the number ofcountries served. Guaran-&#13;
states to improve the laws relating to foreign  tee concracts signed by MIGA in the past five&#13;
investment                             yearsemphasizetheAAgency'sabilitytowork&#13;
In addition, MIGA has carried out sev-   on both large and small investments in loca-&#13;
eral special legal advisory activities. No-  tions around the globe. MIGA has also dem-&#13;
table among these was the preparation, in  onstrated its willingness to collaborate with&#13;
collaboration with the World Bank and the   other insurers through coinsurance and&#13;
IFC, of Guidelines on the Treatment ofFor-  reinsurance activities.&#13;
eign Direct Investment, following a request  MIGA is seeking to enhance its technical&#13;
from the Development Committee that  assistance activities to facilitate foreign in-&#13;
MIGA prepare a legal franework to pro-   vestment flows and augment its guarantee&#13;
mote foreign direct investment The Devel-  business. It is adapting its product mix to&#13;
opment Committee reviewed the guidelines   emerging requirements, focusing more on&#13;
at its September 1992 meeting and called   capacity-building within each developing&#13;
them to the attention of member countries.  country, adapting its approach to reach more&#13;
The committee also noted that the guide-   member countries by diversifying its ser-&#13;
lines should serve "as an important step in  vices, and following up on its operations&#13;
the progressive developmentof international   more systematically. In short, MIGA looks&#13;
practice in this area." Since then several  forward to the challenges of the next five&#13;
countries have consulted the guidelines in  years-indeed to the future generally.&#13;
31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Officers of the Agency&#13;
- _tt: *&#13;
*~~~~~~. E½j &#13;
Li*..&#13;
X- .&#13;
..  ,)t       .                     &#13;
. ~  ~ .r v&#13;
Standing (left to right): W. John Griffith, Chief Financial and Adm inae Ofi-ce Marfin *artigan, polic and&#13;
Advioy Services Admninslralor; rznothy T. Thahane, Secretay; Leigh P. Haywood, Vice President, Guarantees;&#13;
Akwi lds, Exectve vir Presdent; Dale Weigel, General Manager, Foregn Investmet Advsory Services; Luis&#13;
Doders, Vice President and General CounseL&#13;
32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Financial Statements of the&#13;
11Multiateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Balance Sheet 35&#13;
Statement of Incomec 36&#13;
Statement of Capita and Retained Earnings 36&#13;
Statment of Cash Flows 37&#13;
Staemntof SubscriptionstoCapitalStack and Voting Power 38&#13;
Notes to Financial Staements 41&#13;
Report of Independent Accountants 46&#13;
33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
| iAlinvnt ~~Gunara-ntee Agmeny&#13;
ilalanceSheet&#13;
&amp;um3Ds19935 mid June30.1992&#13;
E mu ads,ofUSdo11as&#13;
1993       1992&#13;
Assets&#13;
;: t    f CA SHH_                                             . S  4.404  $   3.653&#13;
INVESTIMENT - Notes A and B&#13;
Obligations of goverments and oder official entities ..........  -    51.325    -&#13;
rite deposits and otber obligations of banks&#13;
and financia istitutions                                       55.499     96.081&#13;
106.824     96.081&#13;
NONNEGOTIABLE, NONINTEREST-BEARING &#13;
DEMAND OBLIGATIONS - Noqe C -.                                   92.781      84,973&#13;
OTHIER ASSES                       _          _             .         634        244&#13;
T:OTALASSETS   _                                                S 204,643 $ 184,951&#13;
---Liabilit , Capital and Retained Earnings&#13;
Accounts payable and accrued expenses              .     .    S   1,446  S   2,650&#13;
Uneaned premiums and  mmitment fees - Not A                       4,313      2,131&#13;
Reserve for claims - Note A.._     2.528                                      1.079&#13;
Total liablities                                                8.287      5.860&#13;
CAPiTAL AND RETAINED EARNINGS&#13;
Capita stock - Note C&#13;
Authorized capital (100,000 shares - 1993 and 1992)&#13;
Subscnrbed capital (87,581 shaes - 1993,78,039 shares -1992)  947,626    844382&#13;
Less uncaled portion of subscrptions .                        758,101    675506&#13;
Less amounts due on caled subscriptions                          731       1.069&#13;
188,794    167,807&#13;
Payments on account of pending subscriptions .............-..     1.260        604&#13;
190,054    168,411&#13;
Remin  eaigs&#13;
Accumulated net mnome9.............................-  ...       9274       8.146&#13;
Cumulative translation adjustments .......                     (2,972)     2,534&#13;
6302      10.680&#13;
Total capita and retamed earnngs                         _    196356    179,091&#13;
CONTINGENT IABLITIES - Note D.--&#13;
TOTAL LIABILrTES, CAPTrAL AND RETAINED EARNINGS   ..     204.643  $ 184.951&#13;
See Nos to Funil Sta_t-em&#13;
=~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~' r&#13;
.   .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MUIIIJSI hInvestment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Statement of Income&#13;
Farte =fiscalc yars endedJurc 30.1993 and&#13;
: Je130.1992&#13;
' Expressed in danands of US daUas&#13;
1993       1992&#13;
INCOME&#13;
Pnemium and commitmentfee income-Note A_ .................. $  5,71   $  3,099&#13;
- - ~lmcme fion investmns -Notes A and B                  _........................ .4 955  5,355&#13;
Miscelaneous mcome.       ..                                        140        212&#13;
- Total income                                ..     ___..._    10.866  8.666&#13;
EXPENSES&#13;
Administratie and oher expenses - Note E.                         7,569       6,669&#13;
Pmvision for claims - Note A                       _ _            1,450       1,079&#13;
Contnbfionzto se calpno     nNoeEam-N oe E_                         719        400&#13;
- f t Total expenses                _                         .................. __ ..... _9,738  8,148&#13;
-:--- : NETINCOME                     _.___. s   1,128  $    518&#13;
Statement of Capital and Retained Earnings&#13;
For d fiscal yeaededJunc30, 1993 and&#13;
.,       Ju Ine30, 1992&#13;
Expressed infthOsmndsOFUSdolr&#13;
1993       1992&#13;
-CAPrIAL&#13;
Balance at beginning of fiscal year           _                 168,411  $ 156,908&#13;
: 0 ~ S Newsubscrpo                                                        203987     12,261&#13;
Payments on account of pendg ssions           _____                 656       (758)&#13;
Tota lcqital ............  190.054 S 168.411&#13;
RETAIND EARNINGS&#13;
Accumulated net income&#13;
Balance at begiming of fiscd year  .._ _ _           ..    $   8,146  $  7,628&#13;
NetincomeforfLscwayear............-....................._..     1.128        518&#13;
9.274      8.146&#13;
Cumulative trnslation adjustnents&#13;
Balance at beginning of fiscl year                              2,534     (2,121)&#13;
Trnslation adjustments for fiscal year                        (5506)       4.655&#13;
(2.972)     2.534&#13;
Totw retaind earnigs      ._. ..................-  $ _ 6.302  $ 10,680:&#13;
see Ntes to Funndal S_atenn&#13;
-   -t  - _   -  ---       &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
mfSPStatement of Cash Flows&#13;
Fordthe fisal years ended June 30, 1993 and&#13;
* 4-  June3C.1992&#13;
Eqcse ,i, 6onsandof USddhs&#13;
1993       1992&#13;
CASH FLOWS FROM OPERATING ACTIVnrIES:&#13;
---.~. :. -Netincome-   _._.._  ...............              .$ 1,128       S 518&#13;
Adjustments to reconcile net income to net cash&#13;
*- t ~ provided by opeating activities&#13;
-: - Pzovision for claims.r_.rr-                                       -.---. .               _--  -_ ._ _._ _1,450  1,079&#13;
(Increase) decasem  oder assets                                (426)      123&#13;
Increase in uneamed premiumc and commitment fees   2.  .      2r164       586&#13;
(Decreas) in accounts payable  .......................__...........  (1,152)   (1,061)&#13;
Netcash provided by opertg activities ........                    3,164      1245&#13;
CASH FLOWS FROM FINANCING ACfVrITIES:&#13;
Capital subscription paymenr s            _      _                12,46     5,3Z7&#13;
-Er; OF EXCHANGE RATE CHANGES ON CASH&#13;
AND INVESTrM            _____. _                                  (4,616)    1,947&#13;
Netireaseincashandinhesnnd.r.ens                                 11494     8,519&#13;
Cash and investments at beginig of fiscal year -                 99.734    91,215&#13;
CASH AND INVESTMENTS AT END OF  FISCAL YEAR----....-- $ 111,228 $ 99,734&#13;
COMPOSED OF:&#13;
Cash                               _                           $  4404 $  3,653&#13;
Tnvesnnent   .......................-...............             106,824    96,081&#13;
S 111,228 $ 99,734&#13;
SeeNotestoftane Stateenlts&#13;
37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Multiiateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Statement of Subscriptions to Capital Stock&#13;
and Voting Power&#13;
Jane 30, 1993&#13;
Expresd in tousands of US daLs&#13;
Snbsc-riptions (Note C)          Voting Power&#13;
Amount  Number  %&#13;
Total    Amount   Amount  Subject        or     or&#13;
Members                   Shaes Subscriled  Paid-In      Due    to Call    Votes  Total&#13;
Albania_. .    .................   58 S   628 $  126  $  - S    502        235    0.22&#13;
Angola_                     1......._.._ 187    2,023  404  -    1,619     364    0.34&#13;
Argentina..................._  1,254   13,568  2,714      -    10,854    1.431    1.34&#13;
Azeubaijan         .............  115    1,244  249       -       995      292    027&#13;
Bahndn ...._............     77      833        167       -       666      254    0.24&#13;
Bangdesh ...      .    ..  340    3,679         736       -      2,943     517    0.49&#13;
Barbados-.--                 68      736        147       -       589      245    0.23&#13;
Belars.. _                  233    2,521        504       -      2,017     410    0.38&#13;
Belgium _. 2,030   21,965                     4,393       -    17,57   2 2.2D7    2.07&#13;
Belie.   ......... ..        50      541        108       -       433      227    0.21&#13;
Bolivia                     125    1,353        271       -      1,082     302    0.28&#13;
Botswana                     50      541        108       -       433      227    0.21&#13;
Brazil    -1_ ,479   16,003                   3,201       -    12,802    1,656    1.55&#13;
Bulgaran                    365    3,949        790       -      3,159     542    051&#13;
BurkinaEso _so               61      660        132       -       528      238    0.22&#13;
Cameroon               ...  107    1,158        232       -       926      284    0.27&#13;
Canada ......             2965   32,081        6,416      -    25,665    3,142    2.95&#13;
CapeVerde. .                 50      541        108       -       433      227    021&#13;
Chile       _ __            45    5,248        1,050      -      4,198     662    0.62&#13;
China    ..                3,138   33,953     6,791       -    27,162    3315    3.11&#13;
Congo                        65      703        141       -       562      242    0.23&#13;
Cote d¶voire                176    1,904        381       -      1,523     353    0.33&#13;
Coaia      a_ _.. .         187    2,023        405       -      1.618     364    0.34&#13;
Cyprus -                    104    1,125        225       -       900      281    0.26&#13;
Czech Republic          .   445    4,815        963       -      3,852     622    0.58&#13;
Denmank.. .        ..       718    7,769       1,554      -      6,2[5     895    0.84&#13;
Dominica.  .. ...            50      541        108       -       433      227    0.21&#13;
Ecuador._ ...................  182    1,969     394       -      1.575     359    0.34&#13;
Egypt, Arab Republic of.............. 459    4,966  993   -      3,973     636    0.60&#13;
El Salvador .  _            122    1,320        264       -      1.056     299    0.28&#13;
Esonia .....           ...  65       703        141       -       562      242    0.23&#13;
Ethiopa                      70      757        152       -       605      247    0.23&#13;
Fi.i .                       71      768        154       -       614      248    0.23&#13;
Fildand.  .. ..........._____  600    6,492    1.299      -      5,193     777    0.73&#13;
France                 _  4860   52,585       10518       -    4ZO67    5,037    4.73&#13;
Gambia, The           ..........  50  541       ic8       -       433      227    0.21&#13;
GorxgiaI._ ........1...........,201             239       -       962      288    0.27&#13;
Gemnany                .... 5,071   54,868    10973       -    43,895    5,248    4.93&#13;
Ghana ..    . .....-_    245    2,651           530       -      2,121     422    0.40&#13;
Ghenada. _               .......... +.50  541   108       -       433      227    0.21&#13;
38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Multilateral investmnent Guarantee Agency&#13;
Statement of Subscriptions to Capital Stock&#13;
$and Voting Power&#13;
Eqxpsmed in dwousands of US dollus&#13;
Subscriptions (Note C)            Voting Power&#13;
Amount Number V.&#13;
Total    Amount   Ammmt  Subject          Of      of&#13;
Members                    Shares Subscribed  Paidd-In     Due    to Call    votes  TotIJ&#13;
Guyana-._-._....    __-....._n....   84 $   909 $  182 $-S$    727            261    0.25&#13;
Honduras     .       .       101    1,093         219       -874              278     0.26&#13;
Hung  .................  564    6,102            1.22       -      4,882      741    0.70&#13;
Indonesia                   1,049   11,50      .2,270       -      9,080     1.226    1.15&#13;
Ireland.. _....._- --..........  369    3,993     798       -      3,195      546    0.51&#13;
Tsrel.............................474    5,129  1.025  -    4,104      651    0.61&#13;
Izay............................. 2820   30,512  6,102  -  24,410    2.997     2.81&#13;
Jamaica.       ...........  181    1,958          391       -      1,567      358    0.34&#13;
Japa.  .....................5,095   55,128  11,026   -     44,102    5,272    4.95&#13;
*  Jordan            -----....--.--   97  1.050       210       -840              274     0126&#13;
*   Kenya._ _   ............172          1,861        372       -      1,489      349    0.33&#13;
Korea, Republic of   .. 449    4,858              971       -      3,887      626    0.59&#13;
Kuwait ........ 930   10.063                    2,013       -      8.050    1,10r7    1.04&#13;
Lesotho..................... 50       541         lOS                433      227    0.21&#13;
Libya._ ......................    549    5.940  [.188       -      4.752      726    0.68&#13;
Lithuania...................106      1,147        729       -        918      283    0.27&#13;
Lwxemibourg.................116    1,255          251       -      1,04       293    0.28&#13;
Madagascar..................100      1,082        216       -866              277    0.26&#13;
Malawi....._ ........... 77           833         167       -        666      254    0.24&#13;
Malaysia .......579    6,265                     1.253      -      5,012      756    0.71&#13;
Mali              .    .      81      876         175       -        701      258    0.24&#13;
Maltz................... 75           811         161       -        550      252    0.24&#13;
Mauritania   .    ~     .     63      682         136       -        546      240    0.23&#13;
Mauritius_..........    87            941         188       -        753      264    0.25&#13;
Moldova-__............... 96         1.039        208       -        831      273    0.26&#13;
Morocco_....... - .          348    3,765         753       -      3,012      525    0A49&#13;
Naria...........................107  14158  232      -       926       284    0.27&#13;
Neth darnds..___..................... 2,169   23.469  4,694  -    18,775    2,34      2.20&#13;
Nicaragua-_____.................  102    1,104    221       -      -883       279    0.26&#13;
Nigeria .............   44    9,132      1.826       -      7.306    1,021    0.96&#13;
Noray699    7,563                               1,513       -      6,050      876    0.82&#13;
Oman   ~...             94      1,018       204        -       814       271    0.25&#13;
Pakistan .................. 660    7,141         1,428      -      5.713      837    0179&#13;
Papua NewGue........... 96           1,039        208       -        831      273    0.26&#13;
Paraguay      ........ 80             866         173       -        693      257    0.24&#13;
PCU.  __373    4,036                              807       -      3,229      550    0.52&#13;
Polarid ....................  764    8,266      1,653       -      6.613      941    0.88&#13;
Portugal.     .              382    4.133         827       -      3.306      559    0.52&#13;
Romania....-----------------555    6,005        1,201       -      4,804      732    0.69&#13;
Russian Federaion ......3,137   33,942          6.788       -    27,154    3-314    3.11&#13;
39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
~Multilatc aInvestmnent Guarantee Agency&#13;
ix  Sateentof Subscriptions to Capital Stock&#13;
? andVoting Power&#13;
~V    Expmw  as ntousands Of US doll=n&#13;
Subscriptions (Note C)Voting Power&#13;
Amount Number %&#13;
Total      Amount    Amount  Subject             of      of&#13;
Members                       Shares Subscribed   haid-In          Due       to call     votes  Total&#13;
SL Lucia........ ....................   505541    $       1085       -$        433        227      0.21&#13;
SL ViwentmandtheOGenadines...   50          541           108        -433                 227      0.21&#13;
Saudi Arabia ........        .3,13?    33,942           6,788        -      27,154      3,314      3.11&#13;
Senlegal ....... ..........n......n..    145  1.569       314-                1.255       322      030&#13;
Seydhells ........      .......    50       541           10$                  433        22?      0.21&#13;
Slovak Republic.-.-...................  m2  2,402        480         -         ,922       399      0.37&#13;
1....    02   1,104          221         -883                 279      0.26&#13;
Spain ... .                     I'M....1,8  13,904      2,781        -       11,123      1,462      1.37&#13;
Sriana......................... 271  2,932       586         -       2,34         448      0.42&#13;
Sudan ........... 206                      2,229         446         -        1,783       383      0.36&#13;
Swnuand....................        58       628           126        -502                 235      0.22&#13;
Swieden               .         1,049    11,350         2,270        -       9,080       1,226      1.15&#13;
SWitzerland               ...1,500    16,230           3,246         -      12,984      1.677      1.57&#13;
Tanaa................... 141               1,526          305        -        1,221       318      0.30&#13;
Togo.-..                           77       833           167        -66                  24       02&#13;
Tdnidad andTobago._ __......   203         Z,196         439         -        1,757       380      0.36&#13;
Toisa........................... 156  16838-                         1,350        333      0.31&#13;
Toey............................   462  4,999      1,000        -       3.999        639      0.60&#13;
u                                 132      1A428          286        -        1,142       309      0.29&#13;
UnitedKingdom          . .4,860    52,585              10,517        -      42,068      5,037      4.73&#13;
United Stat. .        ........ .....20,519   222016    44,404        -     177.612    20,696    19A43&#13;
Uruguay                202      Z~2186         438         -       1,748       379      0.36&#13;
Vanualu _ __..._-    50     41          10                    433        227      0.21&#13;
Western Samoa ............         50       541           108                  433        227      0.21&#13;
zairet......................338            3.658            -      731       2,927        515      0.48&#13;
Zambia .......         . ........318       3,441          688         -      2,753        495      0.4.5&#13;
Zimbabwe................... 236            2,553          511         -      2042         413      OS9&#13;
TotI_-JMne 3O.1993b .        .87,58 1  $947.626    5188.794   $ 731   S 758.101    106,520        100.0&#13;
Total-Iun:3O, 1992          .78,039  $84,32    $167,807   $1,069   $ 675,506    93.084&#13;
a. Amounts      - the cequivalaicof 51260000have bean rived fromCi) nemuber cotmtyon accunt ofits initalsubscmiptimnthe'&#13;
-isin pmcess orcompletinrzaims 1,o0.(ii) countriesthathavesigdnedmoUr ratified theConvention andatin the processof&#13;
copleting their membershp r*cymnetrTheBahunas$513.00. Kazakhscan169.000. Kyrgyzsan 566M.00Micoeia iE5108.00&#13;
Turkmenistan 554,000 uid United Arah Emirates S402.00. Cim) crmiuies in dhe proces of succession to nrenbenhip: Republic of Bomni&#13;
and Hrzegawima 565.ODD, foines Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia 528,000. and Fedeal Republic of Yugoslavi (Serbia I Montenegro)&#13;
$187,000. &#13;
h. May difEr from thesum of indivirdua figures shown because of rounding.&#13;
See Notes to Pinnmda Statments&#13;
40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Notes to Financial Statements&#13;
qttmn of Agency rurpose&#13;
The Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency (MIGA), established on April 12, 1988,15s a member&#13;
of the Worlk oawk Grcup. The Agency is designed to help developing countries attract productFvc&#13;
foreign investmnent by both private investors and commercially operated public sector companies. Its&#13;
facilities includecguaranteesagainstnoncommcrciaI risks and aprogram of consul rative and advisory&#13;
services to promote improvements in mecmber countrices environments for foreign investmnent.&#13;
Note A: Summary of Signiricant Accounting and Related Policies&#13;
MIGA's financial statements have been prepared in conformnity with International Accounting&#13;
Standards. In the absence of such standards, then, subject to relevant legal requirements, the policy&#13;
adopted is that considered most appropriate to the circumstances of MIGA having regard to the&#13;
accounting principles used in the United States and the practices of other international insurance&#13;
entities. The following summary of policies adopted by MIGA is provided to assist readers in the&#13;
interpretation of these financial statements. The accounting policies followed generally am consis-&#13;
tent int all mLaterial repecs with accounting principles in the United States.&#13;
Translation of Currendes&#13;
MGGA's financial statements are expressed in terms of United States dollars solely for the purpose&#13;
of sumiaarizing financial position and the results of its operations for the convenience of its members&#13;
and other interested parties.&#13;
MIGA is an international or-ganization that conducts its operations in the currencies of all its&#13;
members. MIGA!s resources are derived from its capital and accumulated earniings in its memnbers'&#13;
currencies. MIGA strives to mintimize exchange rate risks in a multicurrency envirornment As such,&#13;
MIGA attempts to match its contingent obligations in any one cunrency with assets in the same&#13;
cunrrncy.&#13;
Accordingly, MIGA may periodically undertake currency conversions to match the currencies&#13;
underlying its reserves with those of the outstading contingencies. The purpose of these conversions&#13;
winl be to minirnizt. currency exposure that may occur though operations. Otherwise, MIGA win&#13;
not convert one currency into another except for small amounts required to meet certain operational&#13;
needs.&#13;
Assets and liabilities are tanslated at market rates of exchange at the end of the period. Capital&#13;
subscriptions are stated in accordance with th e procedures described below. Incomec and expenses are&#13;
generally traslated at an average of the market rates of exchange in effect during each month.&#13;
Translaton adjustmnents are charged or credited to retained earniings.&#13;
41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Vwm' LMultilaterl Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
p~  ~Wotes to Financial Statements&#13;
: .;t Notes &#13;
g- ~Valustion of Capital Stock&#13;
Under the MIGA Convention, all payments from members subscribing to the capital stock of MIGA&#13;
shall be settled on the basis of the average value of the SDRin terms of United States dollars forthe&#13;
period January 1, 1981 to June 30, 1985, such value being equal to $1.082 for one SDR. The&#13;
Convention fur  erstates that ten percentofthe members'shares be paid in cash, in fieely convertible&#13;
currencies, except that developing member countries may pay up to a quarter of the ten percent in&#13;
theirowncunrencies. Inaddition anothertenpercentofthemembers' sharesshalUbepaidin theform&#13;
.=*- 0 .  of nonnegotiable, noninterest4baing promissory notes. The notes are to be denominated in freely&#13;
convertile currencies and are due on demand. The policies relating to trnslation of cunrrncies&#13;
described above also apply to the cash and the promnissoy notes paid im&#13;
Investments&#13;
In fiscal years ended June 30, 1991 and 1992, investment holdings were valued at market&#13;
Commencing in the current fiscal year, MJGANs investment holdings are valLzed at cost or amortized&#13;
cost-as MIGA is extending the duration of its investments and generaly holds its investments to&#13;
maturity. There was no cumulative effect from this change. Gains or losses on sale of investments,&#13;
mneasured by the difference between the cost (on a last-in, first-out basis) and proceeds of sales, are&#13;
recorded as an element of income from investments.&#13;
Due to the nature of the investments held by the Agency and its policies governing the level and use&#13;
of such investments, the Agency classifies the investment portfolio as an element of liquidity in the&#13;
Statement of Cash FRows.&#13;
Revenue Recognition&#13;
Revenue fiom prerium payments for both direct and assumed reinsurance contrats is reognized&#13;
on a prorata basis over the contract period. Revenue from commitment fees, which are fees paid by&#13;
investors to reserve for a limited period of time guarntee capacity for future use, is recognized on&#13;
a pro rat basis over the commitment period.&#13;
Reserve for Claims&#13;
The reserve for claims provides for losses inherent in guarantee operations based upon claim&#13;
submissions, consideration of loss experiences by insurers engaged in similar underwritings, and&#13;
other factors including changes in the composition and volume of the insurance and outstanding&#13;
guarantees and worldwide economic and political conditions. The reserve is increased by provisions&#13;
charged to expense and deeased for claims settlements.&#13;
Recognizingthe fact that during the early years of theAgency's operations when its reserves are smal l&#13;
in relation to its obligations :ssumed under its insurance activities and when there is limited history&#13;
for estimation of losses, it is understood that the promissory note portion of the subscribed capital&#13;
would be utilized to pay any claims in excess of the reserve.&#13;
Acquisition Costs&#13;
Costs of acquiring investment guarantees are expensed in the year incurred, as such amounts are not&#13;
material.&#13;
-42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
.$Ln&#13;
Mutilatera Invesmnent Guarantee Agency&#13;
Notes to Financial Statements&#13;
Note B: Investments&#13;
hie maret value of investmnt securities at June 30, 1993 was $106,954,000 ($96,08 1,000 - June 30,&#13;
1992), compared with a cost or amortized cost of $106,824,000 ($96,081,000- June 30,1992). The&#13;
inmvestnt portfolio was denomiated primarily in United States dollars with instruments in&#13;
nondollar cureces representing 17.7 percent of the portfolio.&#13;
Note C: Capital Stock and Membership&#13;
Capital Stock At June 30, 1993, M[GA's authorized capital stock comprised 100,000 shares, of&#13;
which 87,581 78,039- 1992) shares hadbeen subscribed. Eachshare hasaparvalue ofSDR10,000,&#13;
valuedattherateof$1.082perSDR. Ofthe subscribed capitaL$188,794,000 ($167,807,000- 1992)&#13;
hasbeenpaidin;$73i,000($1.069,000- 1992)isdueandtheremaining,$758,101,000($675,506.000&#13;
-1992) is subject to call by the Agency when required to meet its obligations. Of the amounts paid&#13;
in, atJune 30,1993, $92,781,000 ($84,973,000 - 1992) is in the form ofnonnegotiable, noninterest-&#13;
bearing demand obligations.&#13;
Membership- Under the MIGA Convention, membership in the International Bank f -r Reconstruc-&#13;
tion and Development (IBRD) is a prerequisite for membership in the Agency.&#13;
On December 14,1992, the International Monetary Fund (RAF) decided that the Socialist Fedeal&#13;
Republic of Yugoslavia (SFRY) had ceased to exist and had therefore ceased to be a member of the&#13;
MWF.On February25, 1993,theSFRYceasedtobeamemberofthee BRD. On March 19,1993. the&#13;
Board of Directors decided that the SPRY had ceased to be a member of MIGGA As agreed among&#13;
the successorrepublics, Republicof Bosniaand Herzegovina, Republic ofCroatia, formerYugoslav&#13;
Republic of Macedonia, Republic of Slovenia and Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (Serbia/&#13;
Monteneagro), the subscription of the SFRY to the capital stock of MIGA shall be divided among the&#13;
successor republics. Each successorrepublic shall be authorized to succeed to the membership of the&#13;
SFRY, provided membership requirements are met TheBoard ofDirectors may decide toterninate,&#13;
at any time afterJune 30,1993, the successionprocess withrespecttosuccessorrepublics which have&#13;
not completed the membership requirements. No such decision is presendy envisaged. As of June&#13;
30, 1993, Croatia and Slovenia had completed their succession requirements and had become&#13;
members.&#13;
On January 1, 1993, the Czech Republic and the Slovak Republic becamne members of MIGA&#13;
succeeding the dissolved Czech and Slovak Federal Republic (Czechoslovakia). As agreed between&#13;
the succeeding republics, all rights and obligations attached to the membership status of Czechoslo-&#13;
vakia in MIGA will be divided between the successor republics. As a result of such agreement, the&#13;
subscribed shares of Czechoslovvaia were divided between Czech Republic (445 shares) and S lovak&#13;
Republic (222 shares).&#13;
Note P Guarantee Program and Contingent Liabilities&#13;
MICA offers guarantees against loss caused by noncommercial risks (political risk insurance) to&#13;
eligible investors on qualified investments in developing member countries. MIGA offers coverage&#13;
against four different categories of risk: currency transfer, expropriation, war and civil disturbance.&#13;
and breach of contract Investors may insure projects for any combination of the four types of&#13;
coverage. MIGAguarantees,otherthanthoseissuedasreinsurance,cannotbetemnted unilaterally&#13;
43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Notes to Financial Statements&#13;
within the first three years from the date of issuance- Premium rates applicable to issued contracts&#13;
are fixed for five years Payments against all claims undera guarantee may not exceed the maximum&#13;
amount of coverage issued under the guarantee.&#13;
In accordance with Article 22(a) of the Convention and paragraph 3.50 in the Operational&#13;
Regulations, the Agneny, unless determined otherwise by the Council of Governors, currently shall&#13;
not issue any guarantee that would raise the outstanding aggregate amount of contingent liabilities&#13;
above 150 percent of the sum of the Agency's unimpaired subscribed capital and retained earnings,&#13;
plus under certain conditions, 90 percent of the insurance ceded by the Agency through contracts of&#13;
reinsurance. Using this formula, at June 30,1993 the maximum leve ofguarantees outstanding shall&#13;
not exceed $1,430,892,000. The maximum amount shall not, under any circumstances, exceed five&#13;
times the amount of the Agency's unimpaired subscribed capital, its retained earnings, and such&#13;
portion of its insurance ceded as may be deemed appropriate.&#13;
The maximum amount of contingent liability of MIGA under guarantees issued and outstanding at&#13;
June 30,1993 totaled S745,135,000 (.$421,474,000 - 1992).&#13;
The composition of the contingent liability under guarantees issued and outstnding by host country&#13;
and by guarantee currency is summafized below:&#13;
Guarantee Currency (in USS thousands)&#13;
uS      Deutsche     French   Japanese    Pounds&#13;
Host CDnttry     Doflars    Marks       Francs     Yen        Sterling    Total&#13;
Argenfina      $12,000   $           $          $           $          $120,000&#13;
Pakistan         108,750     6,137                 2,312                 117,199&#13;
Poland           89,111                                                  89, 111&#13;
Turkey           84,500                                                  84,500&#13;
Czech Republic                          46,743                14,969     61,712&#13;
Bangladesh        19,800                          35,595                 55,395&#13;
Indonesia        51,458                                                  51,458&#13;
Guyana           49,878                                                  49,878&#13;
Chile            40,999                                                  40,999&#13;
Jamaica          20,23                                                   20,223&#13;
El Salvador      12,154                                                  12,154&#13;
Uganda            10,000                                                  10,.000&#13;
Russian Federafion   9900                                                 9,900&#13;
Ghana             9,850                                                   980&#13;
Tunzania          8,308                                                   8,308&#13;
Madagscar                                3,908                            3,908&#13;
China               540                                                     540&#13;
Total          $635,471   $ 6.137    S 50,651   $ 37,907    $ 14,969    $745.135&#13;
As of June 30,1993, additional guarantee capacity amounting to $10800,000 has been committed.&#13;
44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Mfutilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
i  Notes to Financial Statements&#13;
Note E: Other Matters&#13;
Contribution to SpecialPrograwn. This repsents grants to the Foreign Investment Advisory Service&#13;
(FIAS), whichwasestablishedto assistdevelopingcountries to improvetheirpolicies, programsand&#13;
institutions that relate to foreign direct investmenL FIAS was established by the International&#13;
Finance Corporation (IFC) in 1986, and became a jointly managed progran of IEFC and MIGA in&#13;
November 1988. MIGA's Board of Directors approved arecommendation on March 6.1992. under&#13;
which the Agency's management is authorized to contnrbute $2,790,000 to FlAS forthe fiscal years&#13;
1992 drough 1995. For the fiscal years ended June 30. 1992 and 1993. e'ie Agency contnrbuted&#13;
$400,000 and $719,000, respectively.&#13;
Service and Support Fee. The IBRD charges the Agency an annual Service and Support Fee, which&#13;
-: -      for the fiscal year ended June 30. 1993 amounted to $611,000 ($524,000 -1992).&#13;
SX-ffRedrementPl[wLTheIBRD has adefined benefitretirement plan (Plan) coveing substantially&#13;
al of the staff of the Agency, the IBRD and the IFC Under the Plan, benefits are based on years of&#13;
service and average compnsation, with the staff contributing a fixed percentage of pensionable&#13;
remuneaio, and the Agency, the EBRD and the IFC contnrbuting the remainder of the acuarially&#13;
determined cost of futre Plan benefits. The total contnbution is based upon the aggregate fumding&#13;
- s ~  -  method- All contributions to the Planand all otberassets andincomeheldforthe purposes ofthePlan&#13;
are held by the IBRD separately from the other assets and income of the Agency, the IBRD and the&#13;
IFC and can be used only for the benefit of the paiticipants in the Plan and their beneficiaries until&#13;
all liabilities to them have been paid or provided for. The total expense allocated to the Agency for&#13;
the fiscal year ended June 30, 1993 was $709,000 ($692,000 - 1992).&#13;
-- :      OtherPostEmploymernB,enejis. The IBRD also provides certain lifeinsurance and medical benefits&#13;
to substantially all retired staff of the Agency, the IBRD and the IFC and their spouses through&#13;
contributions to a Redred Staff Benefits Plan (RSBP). Commencing in 1990, the Agency, the IBRD&#13;
and the IFC began accruing and flmding, on an actuarialy detnnined basis, the expected fixture cost&#13;
of providing such benefits for future retrrees. All contributions to the RSBP and all other assets and&#13;
income held for purposes of the RSBP are held separately from the other assets and income of the&#13;
Agency, the IBRD and the IEFC and can be used only for the benefit of the participants in the RSBP&#13;
and their beneficiaries, until all liabilities to them have been paid or provided for. The total expense&#13;
allocated to the Agency for the fiscal year ended June 30, 1993 was S149,000 ($94,000 -1992).&#13;
45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Report of Independent Accountants&#13;
Price Watrbnou    The Hague  NewYork&#13;
(Interralonal Firm)  Beijing  Tokyo&#13;
Hong Kong      Washington&#13;
London&#13;
iPrice Waterouse&#13;
July 26, 1993&#13;
President and Board of Govemors&#13;
Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
In our opinion, the financial statements appearing on pages 35 to 45 of this report&#13;
present fairly, in all material respects, in terms of United States dollars, the financial&#13;
position of the Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency at June 30, 1993 and&#13;
1992, and the results of its operations and its cash flows for the years then ended in&#13;
Conformity with generally accepted accounting principles in the United States and&#13;
withIntemationalAccountingStandards. Thesefinancialstatementsaretherespon-&#13;
sibility of management of the MultHateral Investment Guarantee Agency; our&#13;
responsibility is to express an opinion on these financial stments based on our&#13;
audits. We conducted our audits of these statements in accordance with generaily&#13;
accepted auditing standards, including International Standards on Auditing, which&#13;
require that we plan and perform the audit to obtain reasonable assurance about&#13;
whether the financial statements are fre of material misstatement. An audit includes&#13;
exanung, on a test basis, evidence supporting the amounts and disclosures in the&#13;
financial statements, assessing the accounting principles used and significant&#13;
estimates made by management, and evaluating the overall financial statement&#13;
presentation. We believe that our audits provide a reasonable basis for the opinion&#13;
expressed above&#13;
46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendices&#13;
Governors and Alternates                                48&#13;
Dirctors and Alternates and their voting power          51&#13;
Signatory countries to the Convention                   53&#13;
Fiscal 1994 Budget                                      54&#13;
47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Multilateral Investmnent Guarantee Agency&#13;
Governors and Alternates&#13;
June 30. 1993&#13;
Member               Governor                     Alternate&#13;
Albania .............  GjCergi Kondo ....................   Niko Hobdari&#13;
Angola .............  Jose Pedro de Morais ................... Dumilde das Chagas Simoes Rangel&#13;
Argentina .............   Domingo Felipe Cavalo .............. Roque Benjamin Fernandez&#13;
Azerbaijan .............     Djavanshir Abduliayev ................ Vagif Ahmedov&#13;
Bahrain .............  Ibrahim Abdul Karim .................. Isa Abdutla Borshaid&#13;
Bangladesh .............     M. Saifur Rahman .................... Ayub Quadri&#13;
Barbados ............. L. Erskine Sandiford .................... George Reid&#13;
Belarus .............  Nikolai Filippovich Rumas .......... Nikolai K. Lisai&#13;
Belgium .............   Philippe Maystadt .................... Gregoire Brouhns&#13;
Belize .............  Ralph Fonseca ....................     Keith A. Arnold&#13;
Bolivia .............  Samuel Doria Medina .................. Fernando Campero Plrudencio&#13;
Botswana .............     Festus G. Mogae ....................  GJ. Stoneham&#13;
Brazil .....  ........ Femando Henrique Cardoso ........ Paulo CesarXimenesAlvesFerreira&#13;
Bulgaria .............   Stoyan Alexandrov .................... Emil M. Harsev&#13;
Burkina Faso .............  Roch Marc Christian Kabore ....... Djiga Haby Toure&#13;
Cameroon .............   Augustin Frederic Kodock ........... Esther Dang Belibi&#13;
Canada .............  Donald Mazankowski .................. Marcel Masse&#13;
Cape Verde .............   (vacant) ....................  (vacant)&#13;
Chile .............  Alejandro Foxley ....................  Jose Pablo Arellano&#13;
China .............  Liu Zbongli ....................   Jin Renqing&#13;
Congo .............  Clement Mouamba .................... Bernard Tchibambelela&#13;
Cote d'Ivoire .............  Kablan D. Duncan .................... N'Golo Coulibaly&#13;
Croatia .............  Zoran Jasic .....................Josip Kulisic&#13;
Cyprus .............  Phaedros Economides .................. George V. Hadjianastassiou&#13;
Czech Republic ............. Ivan Kocamik .................... J an Vit&#13;
Denmark .............   Helle Degn ....................  Ole Loensmann Poulsen&#13;
Dominica .............   Mary Eugenia Charles ................. Cary A. Harris&#13;
Ecuador .............   Mario Ribadeneira .................... Rodrigo Cor-ea Arteta&#13;
Egypt, Arab Rep. of ........ Atef Mohamed Ebeid ................... Maurice Makrain-Allah&#13;
El Salvador .............    Mirna Lievano de Marques ..........J ose Roberto Orellana Milla&#13;
Estonia .............  Madis Uurike ....................   Raivo Maine&#13;
Ethiopia .............   Alemayehu Daba ....................  Ezra Worku&#13;
Fiji .............   Paul F. Manueli ....................    Rigamoto Taito&#13;
Fmland .............  Iiro Viinanen ....................   Toimi Kankaanniemi&#13;
France .............  Jacques de Larosiere .................... Jean-Claude Trichet&#13;
Gambia, The .............  Bakary B. Dabo ....................   Abdoulai M. Touray&#13;
Georgia .............   Roman Gotsiridze .................... Michael Djibouti&#13;
Germnany ......................... Carl-Dieter Spranger .................... Horst Koehler&#13;
48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Multilateral hvestment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Governors and Alternates&#13;
June 30. 1993&#13;
Member                 Governor                     Alternate&#13;
Ghana .. .          ... Kwesi Botchwey ..............   Kwesi Bekoe Amissah-Arthur&#13;
Grenada . .         ... Nicholas Brathwaite ..............    Nolan K. Murray&#13;
Guyana .....          Asgar Ally ..............  Michael Sheer Chan&#13;
Honduras .....        Rene Andon Matute .. .............  Roberto Galvez Barnes&#13;
Hungary ..          ... Janos Martonyi ............  Csaba Repassy&#13;
Indonesia ........ Mar'ie Muhammad  .............. J. Soedradjad Djiwandono&#13;
Ireland .....         Bertie Ahem r......... .    ... Sean P. Cromien&#13;
Israel  . .... Jacob A. Frenkel  . ............. Aaron Fogel&#13;
Italy ...    .        Antonio Fazio   .     ........ Mario Draghi&#13;
Jamaica ...   ...     H Hugh Small . _  ..................... Omar Davies&#13;
Japan   .      ... .  Yoshiro Hayashi ..........    Koichiro Matsuura&#13;
Jordan ....   ..... ...Ziad Eariz _    ._.- ---     (vacant)&#13;
Kenya  . ...........Musalia Mudavadi ............    Wilfred Koinange&#13;
Korea Republic of .......... Jae-Hyong Hong .       Myung-Ho Kim&#13;
Kuwait .. .....    ..Nasser Abdullah Al-Roudhan .....Ali Rashaid Al-Bader&#13;
Lesotho ..   ...... ....Selometsi Baholo ..... ........ Thabo Louis Makhakhe&#13;
Libya ..... Mohamed  . Bait El Mal ..B Bashir Ali Khallat&#13;
Lithuania. .  . ...Julius Veselka        ..........  Gintautas Preidys&#13;
Luxembourg .       .ean-Claude Juncker .-........ Yves Mersch&#13;
Madagascar  ...... _ - _ Evariste Marson - - ---Jean Gerard Rabevohitra&#13;
vfaawi ....... Louis Joseph Chixnango .            . Ian Charles Bonongwe&#13;
'Malaysia  ....... ....Anwar Ibrahim .   ..........    .Mohd. Shariff Kassim&#13;
Mali .MahamarOumar Maiga ... ........... Issaga Dcembele&#13;
Malta .- .--   John Dali .......................... . Edgar Wadge&#13;
Mauritania ......     Kane Cheikh Mohamed Fadel .....Sidi Mohamed Ould Bakha&#13;
Mauritiuts .  ...... Rundeersing Bheenick .Jagnaden P. Coopamah&#13;
Moldova ........ Claudia Me[nic ........................ Andrei Keptine&#13;
Morocco .... Mohamned Berada .Mohammed Dairi&#13;
Namibia . .          .. Tsudao Gurirab .Paul WaIlter Hartmann&#13;
Netherlands   .. W. Kok .....                      . JP. Pronk&#13;
Nicaragua ..... ............ Emilio Pereira Alegria ................. Jose Evenor Taboada Arana&#13;
Nigeria . .           Oladele Olashore ...............   David A. Olorunleke&#13;
Norway  . .           Sigbjoern Johnsen ................    Kaxi Nordheim-Larsen&#13;
Oman  . ................... Qais Abdul-Munim Al-Zawawi .   Mohamed Bin MusaAl Yousef&#13;
Pakistan . ............... Saeed Ahmad Qureshi .Choudri Mueen Afzal&#13;
Papua New Guinea ......... Julius Chan .Gerea Aopi&#13;
Paraguay ..(vacant) ................... (vacant)&#13;
Peru  . .Jorge Camet Dickmann ................ Alfredo Jalilie Awapara&#13;
49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Mulilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Governors and Alternates&#13;
June30. 1993&#13;
Member                Governor                     Alternate&#13;
Poland ....   .      R yszard Michalski ...............    (vacant)&#13;
Pntuga .Jorge Brap de Macedo ...............Jose Manuel Alves EBias da Costa&#13;
Romania  ....         Florin Georgescu ...............     Vladimir Soare&#13;
Russian Federation ......... Aleksandr N. Shokhin ............ Viktor V. Gerashchenko&#13;
St. Lucia .  .........  John G.M. Compton ...............  Bemard Lacorbiniere&#13;
SL Vincent and&#13;
the Grenadines .    James F. Mitchell ...............     Maurice Edwards&#13;
Saudi Arabia .......... Mohammad Abalkhail ............... Jobarah Al-Suraisry&#13;
Senegal      .    .  Papa Ousmane Sakho ................ Awa Thiongane&#13;
Seychelles   .    ...... Bertrand Rassool ..............   Vilner Calixte&#13;
Slovak Republic .......... Julius Toth .............  Vladimir Masar&#13;
Slovenia .... . .  Mita Gaspa        .     . ...... (vacant)&#13;
Spain    ........ Jose C. Aranzadi Martinez  . M..i. ...... NGguel Angel Feito Hemandez&#13;
Sri Lanka . .. D.B. Wijetunga ..          ...... ...... Susantha de Alwis&#13;
Sudan  . ... Tag Elsir Mustafa .................. Mohamed Khair El Zubair&#13;
Swaziland.       ....... Isaac S. Shabangu .   ............ Adelaide Phindile Mhonza&#13;
Sweden ....          Anne Wibble . ..... . .     .. Alf Svensson&#13;
Switzerland ..... . Nicolas Imboden         ...........     Francois Rohner&#13;
Tanzania .... .      Steven A. Kibona   .......... Peter J. Ngumbullu&#13;
Togo .-.-     Yandja Yentchabre .. Kwassi Klutse&#13;
Trinidad and Tobago ...... Wendell Mottley   .... ... Reynold K. Rampersad&#13;
Tunisia ...           Mohamed Ghannouchi .  .  .Taoufik Baccar&#13;
Turkey ...           Tevfik Altinok .Kemal Kabatas&#13;
Uganda .........................J... ehoash Mayanja-Nk2ngi .............. Emmenuel Tumusiime-Mutebile&#13;
United Kingdom ............ Robin Leigh-Pemberton . ............... Timothy Lankester&#13;
United States ........... . Lloyd M. Bentsen ..................... Joan E Spero&#13;
Uruguay ....         Ignacio de Posadas ..... ....... Carlos A. Cat&#13;
Vanuatu .......................... Willie Jimmy ........  Sampson Ngwele&#13;
Westem Samoa ...    .Tuilaepa S. Malielegaoi .      Nonomalo Faiga&#13;
Zaire .              Celestin Tshibwabwa Kanyama - Mbonga Magalu Engwanda&#13;
Zambia .....         Ronald Damnson Siarne Penza ...... David Matongo&#13;
Zimbabwe .....       B.T.G. Chidzero ....................   Elisha N. Mushayakarara&#13;
50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Directors and Alternates and their voting power&#13;
June 30, 1993&#13;
%or&#13;
Director                  Alternate                     Casting Votes of                     Total Votes  Total&#13;
ELECTED BY THE VOTES OF FIVE LARGEST SHAREHOLDERS:&#13;
E Patri  Coady            Matk M4 Cois, Jr.             United States                                 20.696      20.46&#13;
Yasnyld  awahm           Malns Naitna J.p                                                             5272        5.21&#13;
Fritz FLscha              HumId Rm un                    Gernmay                                       5.248       5.19&#13;
kJanlierre L}dat          Jenme Hs                      Frnce                                          5.037       4.9&#13;
David Pcm                 David Senn                    United Kingdom                                 5.037       498&#13;
ELECTED BY THE VOTES OF OTHER SHAREHOLDRS:&#13;
Eveine Healkns            Ploao V ic                    Azabajijn.Bulgaria. CyprUS,rsael               7,462       738&#13;
(Nidheands)              (Swiand)                      Netherlids. Poland. Romania. Switzerland&#13;
Frnk Pone                 Huber Dean                    Barbados,EBizCanada, Domica.Grenda,            5.67        5.62&#13;
(Canada)                 (The Bahamas)                 Guyana,Ireland, Jamaica. SL I -da,&#13;
S-' Vincen and dte Gmaines&#13;
OIL M8anbo                Hnay M. Mapondo               Angola.Bowaa.Ethidopi.lieGabi.Kenya.    55O               5.52&#13;
(Bo.s_)                   (MaLaw)                      LIoho, Mal  Namibia. Nigeria. Seychls&#13;
Sudan, Swazilnd. Tanaia, Upnda, Zanbia.&#13;
Zimbabwe&#13;
Nmuran Alcirk             Mhaly Patai                   Be gium, h Republic. Hungary.                  4.60S       4.56&#13;
(TIMkey)                  (Hmngary)                    Slovak Rpblic. Tukey&#13;
Enzi Gri                  Fcmando S. Cameir             Albania. Italy. Luxmb=r Malta, Pxrtna          4336        4.29&#13;
(itaSy)                   (Pormgal)&#13;
Fasisa A. Al-KiwI           ohmed W. Bossy              Bhmain Egypt (Amb Republic of). Jdan.          4.237       4.19&#13;
(Kuwait)                 (Arab Repblic of Egypt)       KUwait, Morcce Oman, Pakisru.Tunisia&#13;
Nicolas lFIo              Julio Non                     Aqntina. Bolivia. Chile. Ecudor.               3941        3.90&#13;
(Caile)                   (Argentina)                  Paraguay. Pru. Trinid and Tobago&#13;
Jorun  Mlaclun            HelY Jonsdotir                Denmark, Flnand Norway, Swedcm                 3.774       3.73&#13;
(Norway)                  ([Iclan)&#13;
Wang lianahcng            Zhng Shnan                    China                                          3315        328&#13;
(China)                   (aims)&#13;
51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
a~~                                  4   ed .44s 4 .        &#13;
R    I       j  }   I         f   | w  |                I  S D&#13;
Ct                 tw                  i ;O -                    gtw&#13;
.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ .&#13;
?~~~~~* Al .UA &#13;
.,,, 4 ^, . '&gt; .~~~~aU   Ci.tS ,t   I ,,   &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-½ Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
Signatory countries to the Convention&#13;
June30, 1993&#13;
Albanias                       Guinea-Bissau                 Philippines&#13;
Angola*                        Guyanas                       PolandO&#13;
Argentina'*                    Haiti                         Portugal'&#13;
Amnnia**                       Honduras*                     Rormania*&#13;
Azerbaijan*                    Hungary'                      Russian Federation*&#13;
Bahamas, The"                  India                         Rwanda"&#13;
Bahrain*                      Indonesia                      SL Kitts &amp; Nevis&#13;
Bangladesh*                   Ireland*                       SL Lucia'&#13;
Barbados*                     Israel*                        St Vmincent and&#13;
Belarus*                       Italy*                        the Grenadines'&#13;
Saudi Arabia'&#13;
Belgium*                      lamaica*&#13;
Belize*                       Japan*                         Senegal'&#13;
Benin                         Jordan*                        Seychelles'&#13;
Bolivia*                       Kazakhstan**                  Sierra Leone&#13;
Bosnia-Herzegovina**           Kenya*                        Slovak Republic*&#13;
Slovenia*&#13;
Botswana*                      Korea, Republic of"&#13;
Brazil*                        Kuwait*                       South Africa&#13;
Btugaria*                     Kyrgynsa*"                     Spain*&#13;
Burkina Faso*                  Lesotho*                      Sri Lanka*&#13;
Cameroon*                      Libya*                        Sudan*&#13;
Swaziland*&#13;
Canada*                        Lithuania*&#13;
Cape Verde*                    Luxembourg                    Sweden*&#13;
Chile'                         Macedonia. fonner Yugoslav    Switzerland*&#13;
Chinae                          Republic of "                Syrian Arab Republic&#13;
Colombia                       Madagascar*                   Tajikistan&#13;
Malawi*                       Tanzania*&#13;
Congo'&#13;
Costa Rica"                    Malaysia*                     Togoa&#13;
Core d'Ivoire'                 Mali'                         Trinidad and Tobago*&#13;
Croatiae                       Malta*                        Tunisia'&#13;
Cyprus'                        Mauritaniae                   Turkey*&#13;
Mauritius*                    Turkmenistan"&#13;
Czech Republic*&#13;
Denmark*                       Micronesia                    Uganda'&#13;
Dominica*                      Moldova*                      United Arab Emirates&#13;
Ecuador*                       Mongolia                      United Kingdom*&#13;
Egypt, Arab Republic of*       Morocco*                      United States&#13;
Namibia*                      Uruguay'&#13;
El Salvador*&#13;
Equatorial Guinea"             Nepal                         Uzbekistan**&#13;
Estonia *                      Netherlands*                  Vanuatu*&#13;
Ethiopia'                      Nicaragua'                    Venezuela&#13;
Fiji*                          Nigeria*                      Westem Samoa*&#13;
Norway*                      Yemen, Republic oP*&#13;
Finland*&#13;
France*                        Oman*                         Yugoslavia,Fedeal Republic&#13;
Gambia, The                    Pakistan*                      of (Serbia/Montenegro)"&#13;
Georgia'                       Papua New Guinea'             Zaire*&#13;
Germany'                       Paraguay*                     Zambia*&#13;
Perun                         Zimbabwe*&#13;
Ghana*&#13;
Greece"*&#13;
Grenada'&#13;
Guatemala&#13;
Guinea&#13;
*    Member countries.&#13;
**   Countries that have ratified but rot yet completed membership requirements.&#13;
53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
fMei3hq VOIW      1 atp M p umPJo!3  U! u! 1o3aWl0 3p kq poAfadde             i8 plpng v6I pusy ouqL :MI0N&#13;
LZ9'6  5           -                                                 . .................................................... . . JW!pEUd3    1101&#13;
t'6L                                                                                                               SYIA  o: uo.1nq..Uuo3.........__ _ . --   --  ----o   ur kwuoo&#13;
98i-6   -.S.s.. 1..!P ni..o put i.uoia..s.p 10. .&#13;
ozvPlt .     *................................................---..-.-... ...   ............ --        .. ---    ----------------  S gnqS&#13;
£89  _--------- -----.--..      .           .............. .      ........................J . ..ddfls pue s233Iafs crn&#13;
9Z9          ..........................................d.....nx..............   ..   ..gj2cn)D     oj&#13;
..S                                                            . ......-...---..... ........s..       u .aaw P..O[u pue IpunooD&#13;
96ZC- ...-..... .                                                              - - .                                  sauaq.J&#13;
:sisoo nazip la.z&#13;
il           .-.-- Suundwsoa iuaumu&#13;
99X I        ......................------ --- ............   . .....--..... . ....... ..... . .....................................  I ol neunSUw   X! &#13;
E11          *    -----_----.---------           .--*----        ..------          --      ---      suonnealjqnd pue SunlaSuei&#13;
t'i          ............................ .................   . ..................   ...........................................--- .- - n u   -  -s auslt&#13;
96                                                                                                           S33IAflS jIfflhWOJ&#13;
9LS..'                                                              ' '       -        ..                     . -- -- -s~aJ l11tjlnSUO&#13;
ODI          ............2................................ ......... .............   ..............................................   uun)uasaJua&#13;
:SISOD ICIUOIIaDSI&#13;
.Sjo2anc Sq saxmn!p.adxsi&#13;
U £     .....   . ............   . ................. .............. ...... ... ..............................  ------qn   pu - 2 up2* m w }&#13;
L96........................................  ................. --.-- ................................ ----JO    --- ---  - - -- -- -    -s!uada z°. &#13;
981'6..                                                                                               '                    3lqfl$&#13;
E L I'I      ''' '''''' '                ''      ' '''  -!..                        *       w@@        UOiIluiiSiUiW        puef 3OU1Unj&#13;
ZL9* I.S IAl --£Io-^--                              -                                                 a!s        S o!APV pue kxaj1&#13;
:;!.n IBUOPUZ!U12J Sq sainj!puadx~&#13;
W£-*8.'4*-wn!wald- &#13;
00L'ti  S.RU3wISOAUI                                                                                                                                       ; &#13;
:wUoJj awUornq               0.  &#13;
uu:Iop snl JO SpuUsflO~ U! FiSS~dXES               -;  &#13;
Paflfl tb66T IE3S.I&#142;T~- &#13;
9u68v 93IUWl9 VJOWIS3AUI WflWHIION&#13;
9L  .................................................. ..........................salii:nw&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-tV &#13;
Prinle on reyce -ap&#13;
SS  10483&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="699155">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1993/01/699155/multilateral-investment-guarantee-agency-miga-annual-report-1993
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1993/01/699155/multilateral-investment-guarantee-agency-miga-annual-report-1993</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1993/01/699155/multilateral-investment-guarantee-agency-miga-annual-report-1993</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1993/01/01/000009265_3970716142205/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1993/01/01/000009265_3970716142205/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-04-20T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1993-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency
            (MIGA) annual report - 1993
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This report discusses the Multilateral
            Investment Guarantee Agency's (MIGA's) activities
            for the fiscal year ending June 30, 1993. Highlights
            discussed in this report are: (a) country memberships; (b)
            guarantee operations; (c) promotional and advisory services;
            and (d) financial statements.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency
            (MIGA) annual report - 1993
        </docna>
        <display_title>Multilateral Investment Guarantee
            Agency (MIGA) annual report - 1993</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1993/01/699155/multilateral-investment-guarantee-agency-miga-annual-report-1993</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>World Bank Annual Report</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Financial Intermediation,ICT Policy and Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3970716142205</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Macro/Non-Trade</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Investment; Guarantee agreements; Advisory
            services; Financial statements; Budgetary policy; Investment
            promotion; Foreign direct investments; Private investments
            banking sector,brokers,business
            development,business leaders,business opportunities,capital
            flows,centrally planned economies,collaboration,commercial
            banks,debt,dividends,economic growth,economic
            policies,economic
            stability,engineers,exploitation,expropriation,financial
            institutions,financial resources,financial
            restructuring,financial services,fiscal year,foreign direct
            investment,foreign exchange,foreign firms,Foreign
            Investment,foreign
            investors,income,inflation,insurance,inventory,laws,Metals,mines,Oil,policy
            environment,portfolio,potential
            investors,privatization,programs,project financing,state
            enterprises,statements,subsidiaries,subsidiary,taxation,telecommunications,telecommunications industry
        </keywd>
        <owner>Publishing and Knowledge (ECRPK)</owner>
        <repnb>13341</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment and Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tracking Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contingent Liabilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>