<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWVPE93&#13;
Interest Rate Management in Developing Countries&#13;
Theory and Simulation Results for Korea&#13;
Sweder van Wijnbergen&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 593&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 593&#13;
Interest Rate Management in Developing Countries&#13;
Theory and Simulation Results for Korea&#13;
Sweder van Wijnbergen&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright C) 1983&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing May 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Batik Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Banzk Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Sweder van Wijnbergen is an economist in the Development Research&#13;
Department of the World Bank.&#13;
LIibrary ot' Congress Cataloging in Plublitation [Wata&#13;
Wijnbergen, Sweder van, 1951-&#13;
Interest rate management in developing countries.&#13;
(WTorld Bank staff working papers ; no. 593)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Underdeveloped areas--Interest rates--Mathematical&#13;
models. 2. Interest rates--Korea (South)--Mathematical&#13;
models. I. World Bank. TI. Title. IIT. Series.&#13;
RB539.W49  1983          332.8'210724        83-6537&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0188-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
Much of the existing development literature follows 'McKinnon and Shaw&#13;
in claiming that higher time deposit rates raise output and lower inflation in&#13;
the short run and increase growth via their favourable impact on savings&#13;
rates. In this paper we show that this result depends crucially on the&#13;
assumption that the portfolio shift into Timne Deposits comes out of an&#13;
unproductive asset, providing less intermediation than the banking system.&#13;
We show that if instead TD's are closer substitutes to assets providing more&#13;
intermediation (such as loans outstanding on the curbmarket) raising TD rates&#13;
is contractionary. We further look at the impact of changes in TD rates on&#13;
inflation, capital accumulation and medium term growth. We show that a&#13;
negative impact on investment and growth and positive effects on inflation in&#13;
the short run are possible consequences of increased TD rates. The empirical&#13;
relevance of all this is demonstrated by simulation runs with a quarterly&#13;
macro-economic model of South Korea.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.     Introduction                                                 3&#13;
HI.    Time Deposit Rates, Bank Lending Rates and                   6&#13;
Economic Activity: a Simplified Short Run Model.&#13;
III.   Interest Rate Reform, Inflation and Growth.                 17&#13;
Short Term Effects on Inflation Long Run                17&#13;
Effects on Financial Deepening and Growth               23&#13;
IV.    The Structure of Asset Preferences                          31&#13;
in Korea: Empirical Evidence&#13;
V.     Simulation Exercises                                        38&#13;
VI.    Conclusions                                                 48&#13;
References                                                 52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INTEREST RATE MANAGEMENT IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
Theory and Simulation Results for Korea&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
Working Paper&#13;
Section 1&#13;
Establishing high time deposit rates    has become a standard part&#13;
of the policy advice given to LDCs by external experts, ranging from the&#13;
visiting academic economist via the World Bank to emissaries of the IMF. The&#13;
rationale behind this advice goes back to an eloquent be it occasionally vague&#13;
analysis presented by R. McKinnon in his well known book on financial inter-&#13;
mediation and economic development, McKinnon (5), and a similar book by E.&#13;
Shaw (8). Their argument rests on the assumption that higher TD rates will&#13;
increase the savings rate. If one goes on to assume that LDCs are in a&#13;
neoclassical type situation, where investment equals whatever is left over&#13;
from total output after consumption has taken its share, the conclusion&#13;
follows. McKinnon has added an additional argument, which points to the&#13;
importance of financial intermediation. Higher time deposit rates will, so&#13;
the story goes, lead to an influx of deposits into commercial banks. This&#13;
"raises the real size of the banking system and&#13;
hence the net flow of real bank credit to finance investment," to quote Kapur&#13;
(4). 2/ This, again, should help long run growth. Kapur does on to argue&#13;
that the increased availability of funds for working capital purposes will&#13;
I/ High compared to anticipated inflation.&#13;
2/ Kapur refers in this quote to investment in working capital. Via his&#13;
assumption of a fixed proportion between fixed and working capital, the&#13;
statement also applies to fixed capital formation (as is confirmed by his&#13;
dynamic analysis). Note by the way the stock/flow confusion embedded in&#13;
his statement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
also increase output and so reduce inflationary pressure given aggregate&#13;
demand.&#13;
It is this body of theory that has led to the almost universal&#13;
acceptance amongst those concerned with Development Economics of the&#13;
beneficial effects of increases in TD rates on ouitput and growth. short run&#13;
consequences are usually not taken into account, nor their possible conflict&#13;
with the professed long run targets. Local economists in LDCs, who cannot&#13;
afford to ignore these problems, have mostly resisted the rcommended&#13;
policies. As a result, a McKinnon-style stabilization policy (an increase in&#13;
time deposit rates coupled with tight money growth rules) has to my knowledge&#13;
never been implemented. _/&#13;
However, the results obtained by McKinnon/Kapur depend crucially on&#13;
one hidden assumption on asset market structulre, an assumption that is never&#13;
stated explicitly: all these authors assume that the portfolio shift into&#13;
T)'s is coming out of an "unproductive" asset like gold, cash, commodity&#13;
stocks, etc.&#13;
This seems an overly drastic simplification of the financial&#13;
structujre of most LflCs.  Official commercial paper or other primary securities&#13;
markets are usually in their infancy (with some Latin American exceptions),&#13;
but in most countries there are flourishing Unorganized Money Markets, UMM,&#13;
where the public can lend directly to firms or farmers. The existence of such&#13;
an alternative asset, providing more rather than less intermediation than the&#13;
banking system, may change the conclusions drastically. It is not at all&#13;
1/ Not even in Korea in 1965, one of the more celebrated monetary reforms.&#13;
Large capital inflows associated with an opening up of the capital market&#13;
a few months before the interest rate reform were allowed to feed into the&#13;
money supply, making for an essentially accommodating monetary policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
obvious that TDs are closer substitutes to cash, gold, etc., rather than to&#13;
loans extended on the curb markets.  Nevertheless, this assumption is always&#13;
made in this literature, albeit invariably implicitly.  Tobin has been arguing&#13;
many times more than ten years ago that assumptions like this are of crucial&#13;
importance in determining the effects of monetary policy.&#13;
In the first part of this paper we explicitly formulate the&#13;
portfolio allocation problem faced by wealthholders in a model that provides a&#13;
more realistc description of financial markets in LDCs. The public can either&#13;
hold cash, TDs, or curb market loans. The model is closed by a simple&#13;
Keynesian fixed price output determination mechanism. We analyze the&#13;
portfolio shifts that will occur when rTD changes, and the implications they&#13;
have for the impact of changes in TD rates on economic activity.&#13;
In Section 3 of this working paper we go beyond the Tobin-style&#13;
analysis and look at the impact of changes in Time Deposit rates on inflation,&#13;
capital accumulation and medium term growth, integrating the simplified&#13;
analysis of the first part in a medium term growth model. The model used&#13;
there stresses not only the portfolio structu-re analyzed in Part 1, but also&#13;
the importance of the link between monetary policy and the aggregate supply&#13;
curve via credit-financing of working capital. Recently, several authors have&#13;
found that incorporating this institutional detail characteristic of many LT)Cs&#13;
has unusual consequences for the link between monetary policy and inflation&#13;
(Cavallo (3), Bruno (2) or van Wijabergen (13)).&#13;
We will show that taking these institutional characteristics typical&#13;
for LDCs into account does lead to unorthodox results.  A "traditional"&#13;
analysis of inflation would simply add an expectation augmented Philips curve&#13;
to the model of Part 1, and come up with the straightforward result that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
higher time deposit rates will increase or slowdown inflation depending on&#13;
whether they have an expansionary effect on economic activity or not. As we&#13;
will see below, incorporating the influeace of real curb market rates on the&#13;
cost of financing working capital and from there on prices, drastically&#13;
changes these results. A further victim of our analysis is the optimistic&#13;
McKinnon view that higher TD rates (whatever their short run impact) will lead&#13;
to higher growth. If an increase in TD rates raises the real curb market&#13;
rate, it may slow down the growth rate, the higher savings rate out of income&#13;
not withstanding. A condition under which this is bound to happen is derived&#13;
and analyzed.&#13;
To indicate the empirical relevance of these phenomena I have run a&#13;
few simulations with a model of the Korean economy that incorporates the&#13;
financial structure outlined before (for a full description of the model see&#13;
van Wijnbergen (14)). The model is described briefly in Section 4. The&#13;
simulation results are presented in Section 5. Section 6 concludes.&#13;
Section 2&#13;
TIME DEPOSIT RATES, BANK LENDING RATES AND ECONOMIC ACTIVITY:&#13;
A SIMPLIFIED SHORT RIJN MODEL&#13;
In this section we will present a simplified model focusing mainly&#13;
on asset markets and the substLitution effects generated there by changes in&#13;
interest rates. The real sector is modeled by a sitmple Keynesian, demand&#13;
determined, output mechanism. In the next section inflation and LR&#13;
considerations will be brought in.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
The public is assumed to allocate its wealth over currency, time&#13;
deposits and loans in the curb markets, taking into account the rate of&#13;
returns on these three assets (minus the inflation rate - p , the real time&#13;
A                                      A&#13;
deposit rate rTD - p and the real curb market rate i - p , real income y and&#13;
real wealth W. 1/2/&#13;
The allocation is described by a Tobin-type portfolio model where we&#13;
impose unit wealth elasticities for simplicity:&#13;
(a)   C    =   fc(P, i, rTD, y)W&#13;
(1)        TD   =   fTD(P, i, rTD' y)W&#13;
(c)   L umm       f MM(p, i, rTD, y)W&#13;
where IJMM refers to the curb market (Unorganized Money Market) and with the&#13;
usual adding up conditions applying to these demand functions:&#13;
(la)      y f' = 0,     fi = 1&#13;
A subscript j indicates a partial derivative with respect to&#13;
argument j. Further, we impose the gross-substitute assumption, demand&#13;
functions have positive derivatives with respect to their own rate of return,&#13;
1/ In this section p is still considered exogenous. p will be&#13;
"endogenized" in Section 3.&#13;
2/ What really matters is the existence of a group of assets more&#13;
"productive" (i.e., leading to more pass-through into capital) than&#13;
time deposits, and a less "productive" group. Whether the latter&#13;
consists of cash, gold or commodity stocks is really not relevant.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
but negative with respect to the rate of return on the two alternative&#13;
assets. Finally, it is a well established empirical fact that currency and&#13;
time deposits holdings are positively related to income; this implies via the&#13;
consistency conditions (la) that the supply ofcurb market loans depends&#13;
negatively on income:&#13;
(lb)      fTTMM &lt; O&#13;
y&#13;
By assumption, banks have as their only source of funds private Time Deposits&#13;
against which they arerequird to hold reserves at a rate p. They allocate the&#13;
remainder of their assets over free reserves and loans depending on the&#13;
inflation rate and the bank lending rate   rL I so their supply of loans (in&#13;
real terms) becomes:&#13;
(2)       LSDMB = b(P, rL)(l - p)TD; 0 &lt; b &lt; 1&#13;
Finally, firms are supposed to snap up every loan the commercial&#13;
banks are willing to make, as they are offered at below market interest&#13;
rates. The remaider of their credit needs is met by the curb market. They&#13;
need credtt to finance working capital (fixed capital is brought in the next&#13;
section); the need for working capital depends positively on the real product&#13;
wage and output:&#13;
(3)       Df = Df(w, y)   Df    &gt; °&#13;
where Df is the business sector's demand for working capital in real terms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
If we put all this in a Tobin-type accounting framework, we get&#13;
Chart 1&#13;
DEMAND                                         SUPPLY&#13;
Asset Hol&#13;
ders           Public          Banks               Firms&#13;
Assets&#13;
Currency       fc    i, r    y)W + pTD + (l-b(P,rL))(l-p)TD                     MR&#13;
Time Deposit  fTD(P, i, rTD  y)W              _ TD                        &lt;     O&#13;
UMMM           f   (P, i, rTD,y)W + b(P, rL)(l-P)TD        - Df(w, y)         0&#13;
Where MR is the monetary base in real terms and TDS the supply of Time&#13;
Deposits by banks (also in real terms).&#13;
Chart 1 incorporates in the TD-row the assumption that Time Deposit&#13;
rate ceilings throw banks off their supply curve TDS and make TD's demand&#13;
determined. With TO determined by demand, we are left with te market clearing&#13;
equation for the monetary base MR and for the curb market. UJsing the various&#13;
balance sheet constraints with which the public, banks and firms are faced, it&#13;
is easy to show that equilibrium in the I1M implies equality of demand (by the&#13;
public and the banking system) and supply of Monetary Base, the two&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
equilibrium conditions are independent.  In what follows we use the TJlM&#13;
equilibrium condition:&#13;
(4)       fm (p, i, rt, y)W = Df(w,y) - LSMB&#13;
substituting (lb) and (2) in (4) gives (4a).&#13;
(4a)      fUM(p, i, r TD  y)W = fDf(w,y) - b(P,rL)(l - p)f P  i, r TD  y)W&#13;
The real sector part will be kept as simple as possible, to&#13;
highlight the portfolio aspects of the issue; a more extended analysis follows&#13;
in Section 3. All we do now is postulate a simDle fixed price Keynesian&#13;
output mechanism:&#13;
(5)       y = A(i - p, y)       Ai &lt; 0,  0 &lt; Ay &lt; 1&#13;
(5) gives the traditional downward sloping IS curve after differentiation: 1/&#13;
di    ~ (I-A )&#13;
(6)       dy            A      &lt;I &#13;
Differentiation of (4a) gives us the locus describing asset market&#13;
equilibrium (labeled LM-curve in Figure 1).&#13;
1/ Note that in this section inflation p is still exogenous.  p will be&#13;
-endogenized" in Section 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
Lt'&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
dii |(f    + b(l - p)f T)W - &#13;
(7)       dyi                                      fy&#13;
-|LM     (f ( M + b(l - p)fTD) w&#13;
(+)      (-)&#13;
Two of the 3 terms in the numerator are negative, one is positive. But the&#13;
consistency conditions (la) allow us to resolve the ambiguity:&#13;
fMM + b(l - p)f   = fUMM + fTD   (1 - b + pb)fTD&#13;
y               y      y      y                   y&#13;
fC   (1 - b + pb)fTD &lt; O&#13;
y                 y&#13;
Therefore       (fy   + b(l _ p)fT,)W _     &lt; )&#13;
y               y       ifyve&#13;
holds, so the numerator is always negative.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
A similar analysis shows that the denominator is positive:&#13;
TiMM            TD     UMM    TDI&#13;
fi   + b(l -    i    f    + fi    (1 - b + pb) f&#13;
C            ~~~~TD&#13;
= - fi - (1 -b + pb)fT  &gt;0&#13;
Taking all this together gives&#13;
(8)       di       &gt;0           or an upward sloping LM curve.&#13;
IT'-LM&#13;
Let us now analyze what happens when regulated interest rates are&#13;
changed. First the time deposit rate.&#13;
Clearly  rTD  has not direct impact on the goods market, so the IS&#13;
curves does not move. A change (say an increase) does however change the&#13;
asset portfolio people are willing to hold, as assetholders will move out of&#13;
currency and curb market loans into time deposits. The impact of this change&#13;
on asset market equilibrium can be read from equation (4a):&#13;
(fUMM + b(1 _ p)fTD&#13;
di                  rTD)              TD&#13;
dr |T-              (fumm + b(I-p)ff TD&#13;
Tfy = y               +  (1p)i &#13;
LM&#13;
(1 - b + pb)f r   - b(1 - p)fC &#13;
rTD              TD  &gt;&#13;
fc + (1 - b + bp)fT&lt; 0&#13;
1 &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
The direction of the shift of LM, and via that the impact of the&#13;
change of the time deposit rate on economic activity, will depend on the&#13;
relative sensitivity of the demand for the two alternative assets (currency&#13;
and curb market loans) to changes in time deposit rates:&#13;
/011/&#13;
. ,/ \ ~IS&#13;
Figure 2 &#13;
di&#13;
IfM                           djrT-D I-         &gt;  r&#13;
fr                                      Y=-Y      &lt;&#13;
(10)       +C&lt;1&amp;lp                        and      L&#13;
rTD                             dy               &gt; &#13;
T7              &lt;&#13;
The int.uition behind the algebra is quite simple. consider the case that&#13;
people shift mainly out of curb market loans after a rise in the time deposit&#13;
rates (f Ur  /fr   &gt; l-b(I-p)        In this case the total supply of funds to the&#13;
r TD  rTD   1-b(I-pI   -                       (&#13;
business sectot will decline as funds are shifted from the curb market which&#13;
provides one for one intermedaation (no reserve requirements) into the banking&#13;
system which provides only partial intermediation: partial because a fraction&#13;
is syphoned  off  into required  and free reserves rather than passed on to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
firms. As a result, the curb market rate will increase and economic activity&#13;
will decrease (case I in figure 1). If the banking system also provides&#13;
complete intermediation (p = 0, b = 1 or zero required and free reserves) and&#13;
C&#13;
the shift comes out of the curb market only (f    = 0), there will of course&#13;
rTD&#13;
be no net effect of  drTD  on economic activity as can be read from equation&#13;
(9).&#13;
fC                         di p = O,  b = 1   d  dy   =0&#13;
rTD                        TD   Y=y      TD&#13;
LM&#13;
In the opposite case, p = 1 , any shift out of the curb market into&#13;
time deposits will just lead to reserve accumulation by banks and will&#13;
therefore be contractionary: 1/&#13;
The opposite case (Case II) is the one where people mainly shift out&#13;
of currency into time deposits, not out of loans extending the curb market:&#13;
fumm&#13;
rTD    b(l-p)&#13;
fC     1-b(l-p)&#13;
rTT&#13;
Currency is an unproductive asset, so any shift out of it into time deposits,&#13;
which are partially passed through the business sector by the banking system,&#13;
leads to greater supply offunds to the business sector, a fall in the curb&#13;
market rate and an increase in economic activity.&#13;
The upshot of all this is that to predict the implication of changes&#13;
in time deposit rates, one has to have some insight in the financial structure&#13;
of the economy. Specifically, one wants to known which asset is the closest&#13;
1/ See the following footnote for a qualification.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
substitute to time deposits, and whether that asset provides more intermedia-&#13;
tion than the banking system; also of relevance of course is whether the&#13;
banking system will be allowed to play its intermediary role or not. The&#13;
latter case could obtain when for example the banking system is constrained by&#13;
direct limits on total lending (equivalent to p = 1 on the margin in our&#13;
model). Then an increase in time deposit rates is always contractionary. 1/&#13;
Before we incorporate our analysis of this section in the full blown&#13;
model of Section 3, and look at LR effects, we will look at the effects of a&#13;
lending rate increase. Under the financial structure found in most LDCs, bank&#13;
lending rates will not have much impact on demand for credit. Official bank&#13;
credit is extended at below market rates, which makes non-price rationing of&#13;
bank credit unavoidable. All a change in the lending rate does in such a&#13;
case, given the volume of credit extended, is change the "scarcity premium" on&#13;
the rationed loans received by those privileged firms who managed to have&#13;
access to bank credit. This is however not the end of the story, the&#13;
qualification "given the volume of credit extended" is a non-trivial&#13;
restriction. The reason is that if the banking system is not operating under&#13;
a system of direct credit limits, an increase in the lending.rate will induce&#13;
3b(p,rL)&#13;
banks to hold less free reserves and extend more loans (            a  &gt; 0) thus&#13;
increasing the volume of credit outstanding. This clearly has an expansionary&#13;
effect, may be a surprising result. Formally, we can see from (4a) that the&#13;
LM curve shifts to the right while the IS curve stays where it is:&#13;
1/ Unless people shift only out of currency (fUMM = 0) in which case&#13;
drTD &gt; 0 is neutral when combined with no intermdediation by banks:&#13;
fumm =O, p=l, b =o         di          dy   =0&#13;
rTDd                                  dr &#13;
TD                       dr TD y=y     TD&#13;
LM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
LY'&#13;
/1,&#13;
A                                       is&#13;
I&#13;
Figure 3&#13;
(1      )fTD  a b(p,rL)&#13;
(11)       di           =                     TL    &lt;  O&#13;
rL I Y      -y  fi + ( 1- b+ bp )fi&#13;
LM&#13;
and therefore that&#13;
(12)       dY  &gt; rL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
Section 3&#13;
INTEREST RATE REFORM, INFLATION AND GROWTH&#13;
In this section we will extend the model in several directions to&#13;
analyse the effects of an interest rate reform on inflation and medium rnn&#13;
growth. Aggregate supply responses and inflation are introduced in the model&#13;
in Section 3.2. 3.3 puts everything in a medium run growth context by&#13;
incorporating capital accumulation, monetary dynamics (via the government&#13;
deficit and the BoP) and relative price movements over time.&#13;
3.2 Short term effects on inflation&#13;
The key characteristic of the aggregate supply and inflation story&#13;
presented below is the incorporation of the link between the financial sector&#13;
and the supply side of the economy via the credit financing of working&#13;
capital. Cavallo (3) was the first one to point to both the empirical&#13;
relevance of this transmission channel and the unorthodox result it leads to.&#13;
Via this channel higher real rates will reduce output; if this effect on&#13;
aggregate demand, restrictive monetary policy and accompanying high real rates&#13;
may actually push inflation up in the short run, rather than slow it down. In&#13;
our model credit is needed to finance labour costs, so that total labour costs&#13;
will depend on the real wage w, output y and the cost of credit,   i - p : if&#13;
we use a Cobb-Douglas production function with share parameter   a&#13;
LC = WYa KK(a-l) (l + i - p              a        &gt; 1&#13;
LC labour costs in real terms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Firms determine output such that profits pY - LCp will be maximized, which&#13;
leads to the aggregate supply function -&#13;
(13) ~~a-I -(a-1) (^&#13;
(13)      1 = aYa   K(al)w(l + i - p)&#13;
a-i&#13;
= ay    w(1 + i + p)                       y = Y/K&#13;
or output will decline if either the real wage or the real rate go up.&#13;
Transformation in "per unit of capital" variables is done in anticipation of&#13;
the extension into a growth model presented in Section 3.3. The real wage w&#13;
is fixed exogenously reflecting the assumption of a Lewis-type surplus labour&#13;
economy.&#13;
Aggregate demand for domestic goods, Ad, consists of foreign demand&#13;
(exports E), domestic consumption of domestic goods Cd, investment   I   and&#13;
government expenditure (which, for simplicity, is assumed to fall on domestic&#13;
goods only). World demand for "our" goods depends on the terms of trade&#13;
q = p/(ep* ;  fixed capital formation   I   depends on the real rate   i-p&#13;
and the profit rate, which in turn depends on Y and K given the real wage. We&#13;
will assume  I   to be homogenous of degree one in Y and K for later&#13;
convenience.&#13;
Finally, the share of consumption that falls on domestic goods&#13;
depends on the terms of trade q, while total consumption depends on the real&#13;
rate (incorporating the McKinnon hypothesis of a positive savings response to&#13;
1/ Capital letters are used here because the corresponding lower case&#13;
letters      will be used to denote quantities "per unit of capital" in&#13;
3.3.  So       income per unit of capital becomes y = YK 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
a higher real rate), 1/ real income corrected for capital losses on nominal&#13;
A&#13;
assets   pMR, Yd = y - pMR 4nd wealth  K + MR  (capital plus the real value of&#13;
the monetary base MR). All this leads to an aggregate demand for domestic&#13;
goods Ad:&#13;
Ad = Cd(q, i-p, Y-pMR, K + MR) + I(i-p, Y, K) + E(q) + G&#13;
Finally, we assume the price level to be sticky, relative prices&#13;
change only gradually. The inflation rate however can change instantaneously&#13;
in respect to anticipated foreign inflation 1* or excess demand for domestic&#13;
goods:&#13;
(14)      P    * + X(Ad - y)&#13;
(14) also incorporates the assumption of fixed exchange rates. A micro-&#13;
economic rationale for equations like (14) is given in Barro (2) and&#13;
Sheshinsky and Weiss (9). Gradual price adjustment implies the possibility of&#13;
disequilibrium in the goods market. We ignore the implications this has for&#13;
the behaviour of the agents in this economy and make the simplifying&#13;
assumption that unsatisfied demand for domestic goods spills over into the&#13;
market for foreign goods leaving total expenditure unchanged, and vice versa&#13;
for the case of excess supply of domestic goods.&#13;
1/ The question of which real rate (curbmarket or the one on TDs) influences&#13;
savings propensities cannot be resolved within this model, because the&#13;
uncertainty that causes the different assets to be imperfect substitutes is&#13;
not explicitly incorporated here. Choosing the real time deposit rate rather&#13;
than the real curbmarket rate leaves the results unaffected however.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
The financial sector part of the model is left unchanged, with one&#13;
exception: firms now need to finance not only working capital Df but also&#13;
physical capital K. So asset market equilibrium is described by an equation&#13;
that is basically similar to (4a):&#13;
11mm                                                TT)&#13;
(15)     f   (p,i,r TD,Y,MR + K) = K + Df(w,Y,K) - (1 - p)f  (p,i,rTD,Y,MR + K)&#13;
or moving toward "per unit of capita" variables&#13;
UMM  ',                                 (_fTD A&#13;
(15a)    f    (p,i,rTD,y,mr+l) = l+Df(w,y,1) - (1p)f  (P,i,rTT,y,mr + 1)  1,&#13;
We can now analyse the impact of an interest rate reform using&#13;
equations (13), (14) and (15). Equations (13) and (14) can be combined to get&#13;
what we labeled the IS curve in Figure 4. This locus describes the&#13;
interaction between the curb market rate i, output (per unit of capital now) y&#13;
and inflation   p    via the goods markets:  /&#13;
(16)     dp              (1-Cdy - Iy + (Cd3 + I1)(1 + i - p)(a - 1) y&#13;
djy1                             I + Xmr C&#13;
The denominator is of course always positive. The numerator however&#13;
cannot be signed unambiguously.  If, in the short turn, supply effects of&#13;
1   (15) and (15a) also incorporate the simplifying assumption that banks hold&#13;
no free reserves: b # b(p, i) but b = 1 instead, ef equation (4a).&#13;
2/ UJse (13) to substitute out i in (14) and (16) comes out.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
tight credit policies via the working capital/curb market link (Cavallo-&#13;
effect) dominate the deflationary impact on aggregate demand of such policies,&#13;
the numerator is positive and our "IS-curve" slopes downward. This is the&#13;
case when tight credit policies lead to higher inflation and less output&#13;
initially, rather than lower inflation and less output as traditionally&#13;
assumed. The first case commands strong empirical evidence in the only two&#13;
cases where this Cavallo-effect was investigated at all (Cavallo (3) for&#13;
Argentina and&#13;
van Wijnbergen (14) for South Korea). In what follows we will assume that&#13;
this "Cavallo-effect" indeed dominates, so that  l    &lt; n. By inspecting (13a)&#13;
and (14a) it can readily be seen that changes in rTD do not affect the goods&#13;
market directly, so that IS curves does not shift when rTD changes.&#13;
/XL&#13;
Figure 4&#13;
If one uses (13) to substitute out the curb market rate in (15) one&#13;
gets a locus describing financial marke;ts equilibrium (labeled the LM curve in&#13;
Figure 4):&#13;
fC +PfTD +D   + (fC+ pf T      ±)1i i - P(-)_&#13;
(17)     dp {         y      y     fy      i      i&#13;
| LC                         T(    C      Ti)&#13;
ILM                (fp +pfp  + f i+pf j&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
The LM curve slopes upward: Assume output y goes up. Higher output&#13;
y leads to more demand for loans (Dfy &gt; 0) but on the other hand it also&#13;
increases the demand for money and so decreases the supply of loans on the&#13;
curb market. To get back towards equilibrium, the curb market rate i has to&#13;
go up, luring lenders back into the curb market and discouraging demand.&#13;
However, by assumption y went up which is only possible in the short run if&#13;
the real rate falls (equation (13)).  Accordingly,  p   will have to go up&#13;
even more than the curb market rate leading to a positive slope of the LM&#13;
curve.&#13;
A change in the time deposit rate leads to shift in this LM curve in&#13;
the same way the LM-curve in Section 2 was affected (Figure 2 and surrounding&#13;
text, p. 9).  If an increase in Time Deposit rates mainly leads to a shift out&#13;
of the curb market rather than out of cash, the interest rate on the curb&#13;
market will shoot up because the net supply of funds to firms is reduced&#13;
(banks soak up part of the influx as required reserves). This in turn will&#13;
lead to a reduction in output given the inflation rate: the LM curve shifts&#13;
to the left. In this case an increase in Time Deposit rates is not only&#13;
contractionary, it will also fuel inflation in the short run. What is going&#13;
on here the following: if TDs are closer substitutes to curb market loans&#13;
than to cash, higher TD rates will lead to an increase in the real rate, as&#13;
well also argued in Section 2. This in turn will reduce supply (because of&#13;
the higher real cost of credit), and, under our assumption of the predominance&#13;
of the Cavallo-effect, will do so more than it reduces aggregate demand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Accordingly, inflation will accelerate in the short run (see point A in Figure&#13;
4).&#13;
If however higher TD rates result mainly in a shift out of cash&#13;
(into TDs) rather than out of curb market loans, the net supply of funds to&#13;
firms will go up because banks will pass at least part of the deposits they&#13;
receive on to firms, while currency is an "unproductive" asset. This will&#13;
lead to a lower curb market rate and accordingly to higher output: the LM&#13;
curve shifts to the right in this case (Figure 4). In the new equilibrium (B,&#13;
Figure 4) the real rate will have gone down, output will have gone up and&#13;
inflation will in fact slow down (see point B in Figure 4) because of the&#13;
reduction of inflationary pressure brought about by the increase in aggregate&#13;
supply. As we noted in the introduction, this case, where the shift into Time&#13;
Deposits comes out of an "unproductive" asset, is really the one underlying&#13;
the McKinnon/Shaw/Kapur analysis.&#13;
A final point to note is that in the contractionary case the real&#13;
rate i -  p   will go up and output (and profits, given the real wage) down in&#13;
the short run.  Clearly, the growth rate I = I  = I(i-p, y, 1) will fall in&#13;
that case, which brings us to the subject of the next section, the effects on&#13;
financial deepening and growth in the medium run.&#13;
Long run effects on financial deepening and growth&#13;
Although the short run problems discussed in the previous sections&#13;
are of crucial importance for any policy maker considering the implementation&#13;
of an interest rate reform, the real issue is the medium to long run effect on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
financial deepening, savings and growth.  It is to that question that we will&#13;
turn our attention now. In what follows we will discuss these questions using&#13;
the model set up in Section 3.2 and the associated dynamic equations. The&#13;
time span considered is called the "medium run" because we do not require net&#13;
capital accumulation per capita to stop in the steady state; instead, we look&#13;
at the "medium run" in which capital will be accumulated at a constant&#13;
(endogenous) growth rate and in which all other real quantities grow at the&#13;
same rate ("balanced growth"). Similar techniques have been used before by&#13;
Sargent (7), Pyle and Turnovsky (6) and Taylor (10).&#13;
The crucial variables are the terms of trade q, the growth rate&#13;
I&#13;
I =  ,  and our indicator of financial deepening, mr, the real value of the&#13;
monetary base MR divided by the physical capital stock K: mr = MR/K.&#13;
The terms of trade q will change gradually over time if foreign and&#13;
domestic inflation rates differ (note our assumption of fixed exchange rates):&#13;
(18)     q   p&#13;
In the absence of private capital inflows changes in the monetary&#13;
base MR originates in the government deficit G and the current account, minus&#13;
inflationary erosion   pMR .&#13;
R =C  +  Y  -  C   -  I  -  C  -p           MR&#13;
government  current account    Inflationary&#13;
deficit    surplus (=income    erosion&#13;
minus expend.)&#13;
Also,  ifir   = - - mr K so that the financial deepening indicator mr(=MR/K)&#13;
K       K&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
evolves over time according to (19):&#13;
C   Y   cT   I G   A MR    -IA&#13;
Kr =    K+    I   K   P I -mr K = Y - p mr - cT - (1 + mr)I&#13;
(19)        = y     cT - (1 + mr)I&#13;
where yD denotes disposable income  (YD= y - p mr)           and lower case letters&#13;
indicate variables per unit of capital (y = y/K etc.). Our system is rounded&#13;
out by the growth rate equation n = K-&#13;
K&#13;
(20)          I (i-p, Y, K)&#13;
K&#13;
= I(i-p, y, 1)&#13;
The dynamic system is block triangular in q and mr versus n: the&#13;
evolution of q and mr can be determined from (19) and (20), independent from n.&#13;
Before we can analyze (19) and (2) however, we have .o express the&#13;
"short run variables" y, i, and   p   as functions of the state variables q&#13;
and mr and the policy variable rTD: 1/&#13;
y = y(q, mr; rTD)&#13;
- + +&#13;
(21)     p = p (q, mr; r  )&#13;
-  +&#13;
i = i (q, mr; rTD)&#13;
- +&#13;
1/ An appendix containing the exact analytical expressions is available&#13;
on request.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
The ambiguity of yTD   irTD and PrTD has been discussed extensively in the&#13;
previous section.  The sign of   Pmr        is uncertain too:  the credit/supply-&#13;
side link via working capital (Cavallo-effect) would tend to slow inflation&#13;
down immediately after a one shot increase in the Monetary Base (given the&#13;
capital stock), but wealth effects on spending may reverse this effect. In&#13;
our diagrammatical exposition we will assume that the first effect dominates&#13;
so  Pmr &lt;0;        it can however be shown that this does not affect any of the&#13;
results. The signs of the other partial derivatives are fairly self-&#13;
evident. (21) can be used to link the growth rate to the state variables&#13;
(substitute (21) in (20):&#13;
(20a)     n = n(q, mr; rTD)&#13;
-+ +&#13;
A loss in competitiveness reduces profitability and therefore investment and&#13;
medium run growth (a' &lt; 0) while the impact effect of higher TD rates on&#13;
growth and investment is positive or negative depending on what happens to the&#13;
real rate   i - p&#13;
Consider first equation (18):&#13;
q = p(q, mr; rTD) -  *&#13;
The locus of q - mr combinations compatible with constant relative prices&#13;
( q = 0, RP in Figure 5) is downward sloping, given the signs of the partial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
derivatives we just discussed.&#13;
dq  = _ 3p/3mr&#13;
dmr    3p/aq&#13;
An upward shift in q shifts world demand away from our goods which&#13;
will slow down inflation in the short run (ap &lt; 0); this can be offset by a&#13;
decrease in the monetary base (per unit of capital), as this causes inflation&#13;
to flare up again in the short run due to the higher real cost of credit&#13;
(Cavallo-effect). Accordingly, the RP curve has a negative slope.&#13;
In the case where higher TD rates are contractionary, the RP curve&#13;
would shift upwards in reponse to a higher TT) rate: the higher TD rate would&#13;
raise the real curb market rate which in turn would push up inflation via&#13;
Cavallo-effects. This could be offset by an upward shift in q (a decrease in&#13;
competitiveness) because that would shift world demand away and so reduce&#13;
inflationary pressure.  So the RP curve shifts up after an increase in TD&#13;
rates.&#13;
The AA locus gives those combinations of q and mr that are&#13;
compatible with constant monetary base/physical capital ratio mr.&#13;
Crucial both for the slope of the curve and for the direction in&#13;
which it shifts after an increase in rTD is the question of the impact effect&#13;
of a real rate increase on financial deepening mr. An increase in the real&#13;
rate i -  p  will slow down investment.   The issue is whether it will also&#13;
alow down financial asset accumulation (which, given the government deficit,&#13;
can only change via changes in the current account) and if so whether it will&#13;
do so more than it slows down capital accumulation. On the one hand it will&#13;
increase financial asset accumulation because a higher real rate leads to a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
higher savings rate. On the other hand a higher real rate leads to a lower&#13;
real income via Cavallo-effects and may so decrease savings the higher savings&#13;
rate not withstanding. Tf the latter effect is strong enough, mr could&#13;
actually decline. Consider first the tatter case, with the income effect&#13;
dominating.&#13;
An increase in mr will lower the real rate and so increase capital&#13;
accumulation. It will further decrease private saving both via wealth effects&#13;
and indirect effects via the real interest rate so on balance financial&#13;
deepening mr will slow down. This can, in the case under consideration, be&#13;
offset by a decrease in the terms of trade (increase in competitiveness,&#13;
dq &lt; 0):  this will lead to more aggregate supply and a lower real rate and&#13;
therefore to more financial deepening (mr) under the assumption of dominating&#13;
income effects and so bring us back on the AA-locus. The conclusion is that&#13;
in this case the AA locus slopes downward (Figure 5) -/&#13;
t i    \&#13;
c ,    N&#13;
Figure 5&#13;
1/ Stability requires that the RP-curve cuts the AA curve from below&#13;
(see Figure 5).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
Putting all this together, the long run effects become clear: the&#13;
initial decrease in financial deepening because of the higher curb market rate&#13;
persists over time and our indicator of "financial depth" mr declines in the&#13;
new steady state (point B in Figure 5). Also the initial outburst in&#13;
inflation caused by the higher real rate will lead to a permanent loss in&#13;
competitiveness (qB &lt; qA) Figure 5). The effects of the steady state growth&#13;
rate n and on output per unit of capital are unambiguously negative as medium&#13;
run profits fall and the real rate rises (cf equation (20a), p. 21 and&#13;
equation (21)).&#13;
Although it is an empirical question whether the negative Cavallo-&#13;
effects of a higher real rate on output really dominate the positive effects&#13;
of a higher savings rate in the short run, it is worthwhile to point out that&#13;
there clearly is a distinct possibility that higher time deposit rates will&#13;
lead to less rather than more financial depth (a lower mr) and lower growth in&#13;
the medium run.&#13;
Consider finally the case where these negative Cavallo-effects do&#13;
not dominate so that an increase in the real rate i- p indeed speeds up&#13;
financial deepening mr initially.&#13;
An increase in mr will still slow down financial deepening, but this&#13;
should now be offset by an increase in the terms of trade (decline of&#13;
competitiveness), because a decline would lower the real rate which would slow&#13;
financial deepening down further when Cavallo-effects do not dominate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Accordingly, the AA curve now slopes upward (see Figure 6).&#13;
I-N~ ~ ~ ~&#13;
/C/&#13;
Figure 6&#13;
For the same reason the shift after an increase in time deposit&#13;
rates reverses sign: the higher real rate that results initially now improves&#13;
financial deepening so that the AA curve shifts to the right (a higher mr would&#13;
slow financial deepening down, bringing us back to the AA curve). The long&#13;
run effects are now more in line with the McKinnon/Shaw analysis (see B in&#13;
Figure 6). With the savings rate effects dominating the increase in financial&#13;
deepening sticks and mr goes up in the long run. The initial outburst of&#13;
inflation and accompanying decline in competitiveness will be reversed later&#13;
on under the combined impact of lower world demand and higher domestic&#13;
savings; whether the initial position will be restored is not obvious&#13;
however:   qC t qA (see Figure 6).  Accordingly, the net effect on growth can&#13;
be either positive or negative: the financial deepening will stimulate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
growth, but this may be reversed if competitiveness is not restored&#13;
sufficiently. So even when the positive effect on the savings rate dominates&#13;
negative influences on financial deepening, negative consequences for output&#13;
(per unit of capital) and medium term growth cannot be excluded.&#13;
4. The Structure of Asset Preferences in Korea: Empirical Evidence&#13;
The Korean financial sector is dominated by the commercial banking&#13;
system and the curb market, the stock market has continued to play a minor&#13;
role. This implies that individuals can hold their wealth as currency, demand&#13;
or time deposits at "Deposit Money Banks" or DMB's (this is the phrase used in&#13;
Korean statistical publications) or as loans outstanding in the curb or&#13;
Unofficial Money Market (UMM). The latter option comes down to direct lending&#13;
to firms, bypassing the banking system.&#13;
The UMM is largely an urban phenomenon in Korea. In a survey done&#13;
by the Sogang university of Seoul, it was found that 79% of TJMM lending was to&#13;
the urban business sector, 7% to urban consumers and the remaining 14% -.o&#13;
rural households (the survey was undertaken in 1969). Kim (1976), from whom&#13;
this information is taken, does not provide information on sample design etc.,&#13;
so one should by careful in interpreting these data. Moreover he reports that&#13;
urban and rural credit markets are entirely separated. In what follows we&#13;
will confine our attention to the urban business sector.&#13;
In the same survey it was found that 75% of all firms responding had&#13;
some debts outstanding at the T1MM, while 10% had more than 50% of their debts&#13;
at the UMM.  The importance of the UMM has been declining over time however,&#13;
since the interest rate reform in 1965 improved the functioning of financial&#13;
intermediaries, and with increasingly easy access to foreign capital&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
markets.  Nevertheless the T1MM continues to play an important role.  For many&#13;
small firms the UN-1 is the only place to go when turned down by commercial&#13;
banks (which only happens to non-exporters, exporters have automatic access to&#13;
credit). In the same survey, 93% of the firms with T11M debts gave as the&#13;
reason for operating in the 1MIM the unavailability of (sufficient amounts of)&#13;
hank credit.  It seems clear that, from the demand side, the T M4 is largely a&#13;
spillover phenomenon kept alive by the occurrence of credit rationing by&#13;
commercial banks, which have no control over their lending rates.&#13;
So much for the demand for UMM loans, but who supplies them? In the&#13;
Sogang university survey, 73% of the loans made to the urban business sector&#13;
came from "relatives and friends and professional money lenders" with the&#13;
latter taking up 33%. 7.3% came from "men of same trade" and the remaining&#13;
19.3% from "miscellaneous", including merchants. So only about 20% represents&#13;
trade credit. According to Kim (1976), professional money lenders are usually&#13;
middlemen acting for wealthy businessmen. These results seem to lend support&#13;
to the approach taken here, where I assume that, in the absence of significant&#13;
securities markets and an open market in interest bearing government debt,&#13;
individuals can hold their wealth as currency, demand and time deposits at the&#13;
banks, or engage in direct lending to the business sector via the UMM. This leads&#13;
to traditional portfolio allocation equations for the different M2-components,&#13;
with RUMM, RT1, CPI, income and wealth (M2 + LSTJMM) as arguments. 11/ 2/  The loan&#13;
1/  RUMM:  nominal curb market rate; RTD:  nominal time deposit rate; CPI:&#13;
CPI inflation (= minus the real rate of return on cash balances); LSTJMM:&#13;
volume of loans outstanding at the curb market; GNPKN: nominal GNP.&#13;
2/ Simple acounting shows that within the financial structure assumed here,&#13;
M42 + LSUMM equals the monetary base plus the value of the capital stick;&#13;
accordingly this is an appropriate definition of wealth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
supply at the T JM can then be derived via the wealth constraint a private individual&#13;
faces. The empirical results (based on 2SLS estimates) for the TD demand&#13;
equation is given in equation 1:&#13;
(1)  ln(-) = 0.36 - 0.89  ln(1 + RUTI) + 1.63 ln(I + RO0)&#13;
CP I                        100                  100&#13;
(1.71) (2.42)                (4.08)&#13;
(0.91) (0.q8)                (1.00)&#13;
- 0.38 ln(1 + CPI ) + 0.02 ln( GNPN) + 0.93  ln( T(-1)&#13;
ino        ~~CPI               CPI(-l)&#13;
(3.51)              (0.53)            (42.4)&#13;
(1.00)              (0.40)            (1.00)&#13;
R2 = 0.997 p = 0.3 Estimation Period:  64-I/79-IV.&#13;
Reshuffling the variables to derive dependence on real rates of return of&#13;
course leaves the coefficients on the two interest rates unchanged, but results in a&#13;
negative coefficient for the real rate of return on currency (minus the CPI&#13;
inflation rate):  the coefficient on  ln(1 + CPI )  becomes + .36.  See Table 1.&#13;
Table 1: Elasticity of Demand for Time Deposits&#13;
with Respect to the Real Rate of Return on:&#13;
------------------------------------------------------------------__---------_&#13;
RUI4M  -ln(l + CPI         .8&#13;
Alternative asset 1 (the curb market); (ln(1 + FOO)&#13;
Alternative asset 2 (currency)        ; (-ln(1 +  C-0j))             : -0.36&#13;
Itself (time deposits)                ; (ln(1 + RT1)  - ln(1 + CPT       +1.63&#13;
i0t            100&#13;
Clearly, substitution between the curb market and time deposits Is of more&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
importance than substitution between currency and time deposits. This is of crucial&#13;
importance for the analysis of the effect of time deposit rate changes on inflation&#13;
and economic activity. The fact that TD's are closer substitutes to curb market&#13;
loans than to MI, together with the absence of wealth effects on the demand for time&#13;
deposits (via which increased savings could have been channeled into TD's over&#13;
time), is a strong indication that the phenomenal increase in time deposits after&#13;
the interest rate reform in 1965 was caused by a switch from lending at the TUMI to&#13;
time deposits at DMB's by private asset holders, and not by additional savings as is&#13;
usually claimed.&#13;
The equation for MI showed no significant wealth or interest rate effects,&#13;
but a strong dependence on the own rate of return, minus the CPI inflation rate:&#13;
(2)    ln(M)l  0.08 - 0.40 ln(I + xI) + 0.03 ln( GNPKN) + 0.97 ln ( M(1))&#13;
(0.81) (4.50)                (0.50)           (21.6)&#13;
(0.58) (1.00)                (0.38)           (1.00)&#13;
R2 = 0.998 Estimation Period: 64-I/79-IV.&#13;
Equations (1) and (2) imply a reasonable supply equation for loans&#13;
on the curb market via the wealth constraint, with positive dependence on its&#13;
own real rate of return, negative dependence on the real rate of return on the&#13;
two alternative assets (MI and Time Deposits) and a unit wealth elasticity.&#13;
This portfolio allocation model has been incorporated in a medium&#13;
sized econometric macro model of the Korean economy. The model structure and&#13;
the results of the econometric estimation have been presented extensively&#13;
elsewhere (van Wijnbergen (1982)). Here we will confine ourselves to a verbal&#13;
presentation of the model structure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
In addition to the private portfolio model a simplified model of the&#13;
banking system and of some aspects of the corporate sector's financial&#13;
decisions has been constructed to complete the financial sector. Firms are&#13;
assumed to have a total loan demand for working capital related to variable&#13;
costs (wages and intermediate input prices) and aggregate output. They use a&#13;
Tobin type allocation model to decide on how much to finance from abroad (via&#13;
private capital inflows from the Eurodollar market) or from the curb market,&#13;
after they have used up all the bank loans available. These are extended at&#13;
below market clearing rate but, at least for non-exporting activities, in an&#13;
aggregate quantity fixed directly or indirectly by the Bank of Korea (BoK).&#13;
Indirect measures are such things as BoK credit to commercial banlks, reserve&#13;
requirements, etc. The assumption that non-exporters first exhaust available&#13;
bank credit makes sense given the subsidy element it contains. The case is&#13;
different for exporters. There were no effective quantity constraints on&#13;
short term loans (rediscounting facilities) to exporters in the period under&#13;
consideration, so they have no incentive to enter the curb market. This is&#13;
also the assumption made in the model.&#13;
The model of the aggregate banking sector incorporates a substantial&#13;
amount of institutional detail. DMB's can be subdivided into domestic&#13;
commercial banks and branch offices of foreign banks. Although the size of&#13;
the loan portfolio of foreign banks is relative small, there is an important&#13;
difference between them and Korean banks that warrants special attention:&#13;
their liability structure is entirely different, with inter-office loans from&#13;
abroad making tip roughly 60% of their sources of funds (in 1980). Foreign&#13;
sources provide only 2% of the total of funds available to domestic banks.&#13;
These inter-office loans sky rocketed after the creation of special swap&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
arrangements, available to foreign banks only, under which foreign banks sell&#13;
foreign currency to the BoK under repurchase contracts. In the model&#13;
presented here we will treat inter-office loans from abroad separately from&#13;
other foreign borrowing by DMB's.&#13;
Inter-office loans to Korean branch offices by their parent banks&#13;
are determined in the portfolio allocation process of these parent banks.&#13;
This leads to an equation linking the volume of inter-office loans to the&#13;
total volume of loans made by foreign (mainly Japanese and U.S.) banks,&#13;
Korean, Japanese and IJ.S. interest rates and, in general, the expected rate of&#13;
devaluation of the Won versus the U.S. dollar and the Yen.&#13;
Borrowing abroad by domestic banks depends on domestic lending rates&#13;
and the costs of obtaining funds abroad: as long as the marginal cost of&#13;
borrowing abroad is less than the lending rate, the shock of foreign&#13;
liabilities should be increased. The costs of borrowing abroad depend on the&#13;
relevant Euro-dollar rate, a country-specific mark-up factor, and the cost of&#13;
obtaining government guarantees. These latter costs are assumed to be an&#13;
increasing function of the banks foreign liabilities. Further, there is&#13;
evidence (Kim (1976)), that the BoK encourages private banks and firms to&#13;
borrow abroad when the BoK's Net Foreign Assets (NFA) position is considered&#13;
tight. We tried to capture this by including the number of months of imports&#13;
that could be financed from the current NFA stock of the BoK as a proxy for&#13;
this effect. The appropriate scale variable in the equation is the net worth&#13;
of the DMB's, which we approximate by a time trend.&#13;
Other sources of ftinds are dominated by time and savings deposits&#13;
and, to a lesser extent, demarid deposits. These are covered in the section on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
private portfolio allocation. Finally the BoK is an important source of funds&#13;
(about 10% of total DMB liabilities is with respect to the BoK).  BoK to DMB&#13;
lending is considered a policy instrument.&#13;
Then the assets side. Loans extended to non-exporters will depend&#13;
positively on the lending rate and beginning of period availability of funds&#13;
from depositors and the BoK. They will further depend negatively on the BoK&#13;
discount rate and reserve requirements, all standard results. Finally, the&#13;
loan supply to non-exporters will, in the absence of reserve requirements&#13;
against foreign liabilities, depend one for one on current foreign&#13;
liabilities, the other policy instrument in the hands of the DMB's here&#13;
considered. The final component of domestic credit is credit to exporters.&#13;
Commercial banks extend loans to exporters at subsidized rates, but can&#13;
rediscount 80% of them at the BoK, also at subsidized rates. There is no&#13;
quantity constraint on that rediscounting facility. Accordingly loans to&#13;
exports are demand determined.&#13;
The remaining two items on the asset side are required and free&#13;
reserves. Required reserves clearly follow from the liability structure.&#13;
Free reserves then become the residual item, dictated by the behavioral&#13;
equations specified above and the balance sheet constraint stating that total&#13;
liabilities are equal to total assets.&#13;
The basic structure of the real sector model is as follows. On the&#13;
supply side, we distinguish between two sectors, exporters and non-&#13;
exporters. The distinction is made mainly because the government (and the&#13;
government controlled banking system) follows radically different credit&#13;
policies with respect to these two groups. Exporters have basically unlimited&#13;
access to bank credit as subsidized rates, which non-exporters face higher&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
rates and quantity constraints. The export sector is characterized by&#13;
monopolistic competition so that firms determine their output and prices&#13;
simultaneously subject to a downward sloping (foreign) demand curve, input&#13;
prices and prodtuction technology. The domestic sector, which has a much lower&#13;
degree of concentration as far as firm size is concerned, is assumed to price&#13;
its products following a simple mark up rule and also faces a downward sloping&#13;
demand curve (for the market as a whole), describing Korean's allocation of&#13;
their total expenditure over domestic and foreign goods. The output and&#13;
pricing decisions are based on a model of the firm that starts from the&#13;
assumption that primary costs (wages and costs of intermediate imports) are&#13;
financed via credit. This production model is also behind the intermediate&#13;
imports demand equation. The wage price sector is completed by an expectation&#13;
augmented Phillips curve.&#13;
5. The Simulation Exercises&#13;
To indicate the relevance of the phenomena discussed in the&#13;
introdtuction, I have run a number of simulations with the econometric model of&#13;
the Korean economy discussed in the previous section.&#13;
The variables singled out for presentation are first of all the&#13;
inflation rate and real output; then the current account to see whether&#13;
expenditure adjustment has also taken place; and finally investment to get&#13;
some idea of medium term costs.&#13;
I am presenting the results of three policy experiments. The first&#13;
is an increase in the time deposit rate while capital inflows and bank lending&#13;
are NOT restrained by direct ceilings. The experiment implemented is a 15&#13;
percentage point increase over actual levels, in the first quarter of 79 and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
sustained until the end of the simulation period, the 4th quarter of 1981.&#13;
In looking at the results the reader should keep in mind that a 15&#13;
percent increase (nearly a doubling of the rate) is an extremely drastic&#13;
policy measure.&#13;
The second experiment is set up to illustrate that the results are&#13;
much more contractionary if the banking system is prevented by direct credit&#13;
limits and capital controls to play its intermediary role. The same change in&#13;
time deposit rates if "fed" into a version of the model where capital controls&#13;
and direct credit limits are manipulated to hit the same credit and money&#13;
targets as were obtained in the absence of the change in the time deposit rate&#13;
increase.&#13;
The third experiment leaves the time deposit rate unchanged-dut&#13;
doubles the lending rate (adds 15 percentage points throughout the simulation&#13;
period).&#13;
The results of the first experiment are reported in Figures 1A-4A.&#13;
As can be read from the econometric results of the estimation of the portfolio&#13;
model, loans extended on the curb market are a closer substitute to time&#13;
deposits than cash (and demand deposits); the results conform to our&#13;
predictions for that case. Inflation shoots up in the quarter where the&#13;
(near) doubling of the rates hits, with (on an annualized basis) more than 20&#13;
percentage points. 2! This is clearly an impact effect, it dies out after 1&#13;
quarter. Curb market rates shoot up and stay high thoroughout the simulation&#13;
period, although inflation more or less returns to its base level after one&#13;
1/ The base level run does not pretend to approximate actual values in 79.&#13;
We used the version with an endogenous bank loan supply and capital flows,&#13;
while the Koreans switched to direct credit limits and capital controls in&#13;
79-I.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
quarter; accordingly real rates increase and output falls.&#13;
After an initial deterioration expenditure adjusts more than income,&#13;
so that the current account improves. Private investment falls initially when&#13;
the crunch hits, but on balance returns to its old level after the first few&#13;
quarters: on the one hand real interest rates are up, but so is the increase&#13;
in real credit extenAed via the banking system; this happens because the&#13;
influx of time deposits is partially passed through into capital via bank&#13;
loans.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
R-051( SVD)&#13;
INFL19TION(WPK) ANNUALIZED  RTE OCF  CHRNGE&#13;
-                   -                                            00.&#13;
SO.J O-                                                           S&#13;
a L O -                                                            Q dL     aL &#13;
mo-~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~e.&#13;
I   II  III  IV    I   II  III  IY    I   I1  III  1'i&#13;
REflL  GNP ( SE19S. flDJ.)&#13;
10.0-                               t0 -&#13;
I~              &#13;
38.D-                                . 1S3.D&#13;
40.0   &amp;I1.&#13;
3Q.D \ \j ^ l -3C :~~~~~~32.&#13;
'2S0 -                       _                                     M   2.n0&#13;
2..0 --2.&#13;
28.fl38f&#13;
I   I I  I' I  I z   I   I   III  r ly     I II0 III  rv&#13;
1                    1980ism&#13;
f l ......Vs.     &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
R-0 51( SVD)&#13;
CURRENT RCCOUNT DEF.&#13;
(pi.    n          I or us =&#13;
I        I0.0&#13;
-2. ,&#13;
-3..fl                                                ~~~~~~~~~~~~~-3.0&#13;
I    II   III   IV    a    II   III   IV    I    Il   III   IV&#13;
2S79                    2S80                    2a2&#13;
FS. R&#13;
RERL PRIVATE INVESTMENT&#13;
10. -                                                                   10.0&#13;
2.0                                                                      2 &#13;
I    11   III   IY    I    II   III   rv    I    ra    I    rv&#13;
Fig. 4A        1979                   isaC                    1981&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
In the second experiment this is not allowed to happen, credit&#13;
limits are imposed throughout the period to keep nominal credit to the private&#13;
sector at its base level run values. Now the contractionary effects are much&#13;
more severe: funds are withdrawn from the curb market, and deposited at the&#13;
commercial banks, but banks are prevented from passing them on to firms by the&#13;
credit limits. The results for investment are therefore disastrous (Figure&#13;
4B).&#13;
Real output drops significantly and stays low throughout the period&#13;
(Figure 28). The initial impact on inflation is of course a lot bigger&#13;
(Figure 1B), but once again dies out quickly. Again expenditure adjusts&#13;
strongly, after a small initial deterioration, the deficit on the current&#13;
account improves dramatically. The upshot of all this is clear: combining&#13;
increases in time deposit rates with restrictive monetary policies, at least&#13;
within the asset market structure prevalent in Korea has stagflationary&#13;
consequences.&#13;
The final experiment feeds a different kinds of shock into the&#13;
economy, a 15 percentage point increase in the bank lending rate. At the&#13;
moment of implementation, this amounts to a doubling of the rate, a larger&#13;
shock than any ever implemented in Korea (although the increased bank lendig&#13;
rate is still nowhere near curb market rates). The results are quite&#13;
dramatic, partly because of a shift by banks from free reserves towards loans&#13;
reserves, increase in loans), but much more because of another mechanism,&#13;
capital inflows via the banking system. The higher lending rates make it much&#13;
more profitable for foreign banks to lend to their Korean branch offices, and for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
R0 5 1(SjTTD)&#13;
INFLRTION (WPK) RNNUALIZED RRTE OF CHPNGE&#13;
-~~~ _____                        1~.&#13;
120.0 J                                           -                       122. D&#13;
ioo.o A                                                                   100.0&#13;
80.0 -                                              - ~~~~~~~~~~~~80.0&#13;
+B.O                                                - +O~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~6~.D&#13;
20.0                                                                     20.0&#13;
0.04-             _            ____-                                0.0&#13;
I  II      ~~III      IVI               II       III       IV&#13;
197                                 1X80&#13;
REAL GNP(SEflS. ADJ. )&#13;
3 .0              m+                                                      °5.&#13;
30.0]                                                                    M.&#13;
I       11       III      rv        r        IrI I2 &#13;
rsL 2B&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
R-051(SVD)&#13;
CURRENT  RCCCUNT DEF. &#13;
2.0O                                              I         2.0&#13;
1.3 -0                                                      1.0&#13;
0.0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
-3.0 --:1&#13;
REflL PRIVATE INVESTM1NT&#13;
WX-         -      _____&#13;
I. ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~C&#13;
2-0  -              I              I                  .0&#13;
_3Z             '&lt; 4| &#13;
Q.:                                         ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0.0&#13;
I      II     III    rv       I      II      EII     r v&#13;
Fig. 4B       1979&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
k-051(SVD)                       - 46 -&#13;
INFLRTIONCPK)9RNNUFL1ZED  RRTE CF  CHRNGE&#13;
K1&#13;
40.0                                                                40.0&#13;
40.0O2.&#13;
mc.3                                                                C. a   C,&#13;
1979                 18s                  1981&#13;
FIgC lC&#13;
REflL GNP (SEAS. 190J. )&#13;
I~~~ &#13;
I~   &#13;
,_   _    _    .       _          _             - ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~5.43&#13;
30.al                ,             \     XC                      0 3s.a&#13;
zi    _        |    :               &lt;1    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~25. n&#13;
III                 19v    I              'if    v I rI   iii&#13;
1n   7 ;n.                                     Sa&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
R-05 1 ( SVD)&#13;
CURRENT PCCOUNT CEF.&#13;
_lCoal I&#13;
CQ-  _ t \1  1          1                  1    -C~~~~~~~~~.3&#13;
-1.0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
-3.1:)&#13;
-5.-                         -          --      t-5.0&#13;
I    11  ~III  I'V    I 11     III     lV   I       III  rv&#13;
179                  1380                  1381&#13;
F;C SC&#13;
RERL PRIVATE INVESTMENT&#13;
20.0 -                       _     _ -    -_ -,-    -    - - -  -    20.0&#13;
10.0   I                                                             10.0&#13;
5.0                                               ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~S. 0&#13;
OX           - -    --  ~0.0&#13;
FIg.  II 1I   I    I    11  III          I       r&#13;
Fig. 4C     1373                  138                   1381&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Korean banks to borrow at the eurodollar market. In our simulation, inter-&#13;
office loans from Japanese and American banks more than double after 3 years&#13;
of higher lending rates (in 81-TV these loans increase 102 percent compared to&#13;
the base level run), while eurodollar and other foreign liabilities of the&#13;
domestic commerc.ial banks nearly triple compared with the base level run over&#13;
the same 3 year period (an 269% increase!). All this is passed through into&#13;
bank loans one for one, which is the main explanation for the dramatic&#13;
results. The total supply of loans to the business sector increases&#13;
substantially, pushing down the curb market interest rate. Investment goes up&#13;
and stays high under the combined impact of lower curb market rates and&#13;
increased availability of commercial bank loans.   The impact effect on&#13;
inflation is favourable because of lower real credit costs but dies out&#13;
quickly; output increases substantially, but so does expenditure leading to a&#13;
sustained deterioration in the current account (see Figures IC-4C).&#13;
Conclusions&#13;
In this paper we examined the likely impact of changes in bank&#13;
lending and deposit rates on economic activity, inflation and growth. The&#13;
results are to be contrasted with the Shaw/McKinnon/Kapur view of the world&#13;
(at least the LDC part of it); their point of view is, with some exaggeration,&#13;
that high time deposit rates, preferably positive in real terms, are a good&#13;
thing to establish in LDC's, a necessary precondition (and sufficient, one is&#13;
tempted to believe occasionally) for high growth. If short term effects of&#13;
higher rates are considered at all, they are believed to be favourable,&#13;
increasing output and reducing inflation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
Our results seriously qualify these claims. Explicit consideration&#13;
of the portfolio shifts to be expected shows that whether an increase in time&#13;
deposits is expansionary or contractionary depends on whether Time Deposits&#13;
are close substitutes to "unproductive" assets providing no pass through into&#13;
capital, like cash, gold or commodity stocks, or to "productive" assets like&#13;
loans extended in the curb market. The importance of asset market structure&#13;
for the effect of monetary policy was stressed a long time ago of course by&#13;
James Tobin (11).&#13;
We then incorporated the Tobin-type analysis in a macro-model&#13;
incorporating the link between credit and the supply side of the economy via&#13;
the financing of working capital, a transmission channel shown to be of&#13;
importance in LDC's, that causes often unexpected responses to monetary&#13;
policy. The outcome of this analysis is that when time deposits rate&#13;
increases are contractionary, they will also accelerate inflation; if they are&#13;
contractionary, they are so because they lead to tight credit conditions as&#13;
people shift out of the curb market rather than cash. The resulting high real&#13;
costs of credit lead to an acceleration of inflation in the short run,&#13;
indicating that in this case increases in time deposit rates will have a&#13;
stagflationary impact, in sharp contrast to the results obtained by for&#13;
example Kapur (4). The crucial difference is the implicit assumption made by&#13;
Kapur, and for that matter by McKinnon (6), that time deposits only substitute&#13;
with cash or other "unprodtuctive" assets.  In that case it is shown that&#13;
favourable short run effects on output and inflation indeed do obtain.&#13;
We then went on to analyse the effects on capital accumulation and&#13;
medium run growth. In the contractionary case, the initial outburst of&#13;
inflation after an increase in time deposit rates will lead to a loss of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
competitiveness, which, in itself, lowers the profit rate and therefore&#13;
investment and the medium run growth rate. Financial asset accumulation may&#13;
slowdown if the fall in income more than offsets the increase in the savings&#13;
rate; if this happens, the resulting "financial shallowing", to borrow Shaw's&#13;
phrase, will make slower growth inevitable, as it comes on top of the negative&#13;
effect of the loss of competitiveness. If however, the savings rate increase&#13;
dominates, financial deepening will result. The net effect on growth becomes&#13;
ambiguous in that case: the loss of competitiveness and the "financial&#13;
deepening" effect work at cross purposes. The important point to note is that&#13;
we showed there is a distinct possibility that the beneficial effects of a&#13;
higher savings rate after an increase in time deposits rate, will be thwarted&#13;
by the contractionary impact of the portfolio reallocation the higher TD rates&#13;
also cause.&#13;
We also looked at the effects of changes in bank lending rates.&#13;
With bank loans rationed because lending rates are invariably below market&#13;
clearing levels, there are no negative effects on demand for bank loans to be&#13;
expected after an increase in lending rates (although some firms may run into&#13;
cash flow problems). On the other hand banks will be induced to hold less&#13;
free reserves and borrow more abroad to be able to make more loans when&#13;
lending rates go up; therefore, the net effect is expansionary, maybe a&#13;
somewhat surprising result.&#13;
Finally, we demonstrated the relevance of these problems with some&#13;
simulation results obtained from a quarterly econometric model of the Korean&#13;
economy. Increases in Time Deposit rates were shown to be contractionary in&#13;
the short run there, because the portfolio shifts they lead to cause a&#13;
tightening of credit conditions and higher costs of financing working capital:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5i -&#13;
people shift out of the curb market rather than out of cash.  The higher costs&#13;
of financing working capital also push up inflation in the first quarter after&#13;
the change, making the increse in TD rates stagflationary. This effect dies&#13;
oit qu.;ck'0i icwe,7er   The persistence of the loss in output is shown to depend&#13;
on whether the commercial banks are allowed to play their intermediary role or&#13;
not: if credit limits prevent passing through into bank loans of the influx of&#13;
time deposits caused by the higher rates, substantial and persistent real&#13;
output losses and decreased private investment were shown to result.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
References&#13;
Barro, R. (1974) "A Theory of Monopolistic Price Adjustment," RES.&#13;
Bruno, M. (1979) "Stabilization and Stagflation in a Semi-Industrialized&#13;
Economy," in Dornbusch and Frenkel (eds.): International Economic Policy,&#13;
theory and evidence." Johns Hopkins Press 1979.&#13;
Cavallo, D. (1977) "Stagflationary Effects of Monetarist Stabilization&#13;
Policies," Unpublished Ph.D. Thesis, Harvard.&#13;
'Kapur, B (1976) "Alternative Stabilization Policies for less Developed&#13;
Economies," Journal of Political Economy.&#13;
Kim, P. (1976)  "Does Monetary Policy Work and How:  Towards a Model&#13;
of Monetary Management for Korea," Ph.D. dissertation, Princeton&#13;
University.&#13;
McKinnon, R. (1973) Money and Capital in Economic Development, Washington,&#13;
D.C.,, Brookings Institute.&#13;
Pyle, D. and S. Turnovsky (1976)  "The Dynamics of Government Policy in an&#13;
Inflationary Economy: an 'intermediate Run' Analysis," Journal of&#13;
Money, Credit and Banking.&#13;
Sargent, T.J. (1973) "Interest rates and prices in the long run," Journal of&#13;
Money, Credit and Banking.&#13;
Shaw, E. (1973) Financial Deepening in Economic Development, Oxford&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Sheshinsky, E. and Y. Weiss (1977) "Inflation and Costs of Price Adjustment,"&#13;
RES.&#13;
Taylor, L. (1980) IS/LM in the Tropics: Diagrammatics of the New&#13;
Structiiralist Macro-Critique," in Wieintraub and Cline (eds.): Economic&#13;
Stabilization in Developing Countries, Brookings Institute.&#13;
Tobin, J. (1975)  "A General Equilibrium Approach to Monetary Theory," Journal&#13;
of Monetary Economics.&#13;
Turnovsky, S. "Macro-economic analysis," Cambridge University Press.&#13;
van Wijnbergen, S. (1982)  "Stagflationary Effects of Monetary&#13;
Stabilization Policies: A Quantitative Analysis oF South Korea,"&#13;
Journal of Development Economics.&#13;
(1979)  "Credit Policy, Inflation and Growth in a Small Open&#13;
Economy," forthcoming, Journal of Development Economics.&#13;
(1983)  "Interest Rate Management in LDCs," forthcoming, Journal of&#13;
Monetary Economics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank                          Aggregate Demand and                   Capital Market Imperfec-&#13;
Macroeconomic Imbalances              tions and Economic&#13;
Publications                        in Thailand: Simulations               Development&#13;
of Related ,with the SIAM 1 Model                                       Vinayak V. Bhatt and&#13;
of Related                          Waflk Grais                           Alan R. Roe&#13;
Interest                            Focuses on the demand-side adjust-     World.Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
ments of the Thai economy to lower    No. 338. July 1979. 87 pages&#13;
agricultural growth and to higher     (including footnotes).&#13;
energy prices. Discusses policy&#13;
measures and structural changes that    Stock No. WP-0338. $3.00.&#13;
might enable the economy to over-&#13;
come these problems and continue to&#13;
maintain high GDP rates of growth.    The Changing Nature of&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Export Finance and Its&#13;
448. April 1981. 70 pages (including  Implications for Developing&#13;
2 appendixes).                        Countries&#13;
Stock No. WP-0448. $3.00.             Albert C. Cizauskas&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
409. July 1980. 43 pages (including&#13;
An Analysis of                        3 annexes).&#13;
Developing Country                    Stock No. WP-0409. $3.00.&#13;
Adjustment Experience and            Adjustment Experiences in&#13;
Growth Prospects of the               the 1970s: Low-income Asia&#13;
Semi-industrial Countries            Christine Wallich                      Compounding and Dis-&#13;
Frederick Jaspersen                  This background study for World        counting Tables for&#13;
This background study for World       Development Report 1981 examines      Project Evaluation&#13;
Development Report 1981 examines      low-income South Asia's adjustment    J. Price Gittinger, editor&#13;
the successful process of adjustment    to the external shocks of the 1970s,  Easily comprehensible, convenient&#13;
to external "shocks" of the 1970s     especially those factors that helped  tables for project preparation and&#13;
(rising prices of oil imports, reduced  make the effects of these external  analysis.&#13;
demand for exports, slower economic   developments less severe in the&#13;
growth in the OECD countries) in the    region than in other parts of the   The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
semi-industrial developing countries.   developing world.                   1973; 7th printing, 1982. 143 pages.&#13;
Presents an analytical framework for    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  LC 75-186503. ISBN 0-8018-1604-1,&#13;
quantifying the effects of demand     487. August 1981. iv + -39 pages      $6.00 paperback.&#13;
management and structural adjust-    (including references). &#13;
ment in forty-two countries, with par-                                      Arabic: World Bank,1973. (Available&#13;
ticular reference to Uruguay, Brazil,  Stock No. WP-0487. $3.00.            from ILS,1715 ConnecticutAvenue,&#13;
Republic of Korea, and Turkey.                                              N.W., Washington, D.C. 20009, U.S.A.)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Aspects of Development                $4.00 paperback.&#13;
477. August 1981. 132 pages (including    Bank Management                   French: Tables d'int&amp;ets composes et&#13;
3 appendixes).                        William Diamond and                   d'actualisation. Economica, 4th print-&#13;
Stock No. WP-04 77. $5.00.            V. S. Raghavan                        ing, 1979.&#13;
Deals exclusively with the manage-   ISBN 2- 7178-0205-3, 36 francs.&#13;
Adjustment in                         ment of development banks. The        Spanish: Tablas de interes compuesto v&#13;
Low-Income Africa                     book is divided into eight sections,  de descuento para evaluacion de proyec-&#13;
Robf,rt Liebenthal                    each dealing with one aspect of       de ditoria  evaluad6n de print-&#13;
management of its problems, and       tos. E~ditorial Tecnos, 1973; 4th print-&#13;
This background study for World       of the various ways of dealing       ing, 1980.&#13;
Developnment Report 1981 analyzes     with them.                            ISBN 84-309-0716-5, 380 pesetas.&#13;
the adjustment to external shocks&#13;
during the 1970s made by a group      EDI Series in Economic Development.&#13;
of middle-income and low-income       The Johns Hopkins University Press,   A Conceptual Approach to&#13;
African countries, with particular    1982. 311 pages.                      the Analysis of External Debt&#13;
reference to Kenya, Tanzania,                                               of the Developing Countries&#13;
Senegal. and Sudan.                   LC 81 -48] 74. ISBN 0-8018-25 71- 7,   fteDvlpn    onre&#13;
$29.95 hardcouer, ISBN 0-8018-2572-5,    Robert Z. Aliber&#13;
Word6 an Agstaff81 Working paperso    $12.95 paperback.                     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
486( August Il98.i + 56 pages                                               421. October 1980, 25 pages (including&#13;
(tncluding bibliography).                                                   appendix, references).&#13;
Stock NYo. WP-0486. $3.00.                                                  Stock No. WP-0421. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Development Banks                     Developments in and                   Food Policy Issues in&#13;
William Diamond                       Prospects for the External            Low-income Countries&#13;
Operating experiences that serve as a    Debt of the Developing             Edward Clay and others&#13;
practical guide for developing coun-  Countries: 1970-80                    A background study for World&#13;
tries, with a selected list and       and Beyond                            Development Report 1981. Discusses&#13;
summary description of some           Nicholas C. Hope                      food distribution-especially its&#13;
development banks.                                                          insecurity in the face of external&#13;
This background study for World&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Development Report 1981 analyzes       economic pressures and potential&#13;
1957; 5th printing, 1969.141 pages   the debt situation and its implica-    conflicts with internal production&#13;
(including 2 appendixes, index).      tions for future borrowing.          reference to Bangladesh, Zambia,&#13;
LC 57-13429. ISBN 0-8018-0708-5,      World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    and India.&#13;
$5.00 (i3.50) paperback.              488. August 1981. 70 pages (including  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
2 annexes, references).               473. August 1981. uii + 115 pages.&#13;
Development Finance Com-              Stock No. WP-0488. $3.00.             Stock No. WP-04 73. $5.00.&#13;
panies: Aspects of Policy&#13;
and Operation                         Energy Prices, Substitution,    A General Equflibrium&#13;
William Diamond, editor;              and Optimal Borrowing in              Analysis of Foreign&#13;
essays by E. T. Kuiper,               the Short Run: An Analysis            Exchange Shortages in a&#13;
Douglas Gustafson, and               of AdUustment in Oil-                  Developing Economy&#13;
P M. Mathew                           Importing Developing                  Kemal Dervis, Jaime de Melo,&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,   Countries                             and Sherman Robinson&#13;
1968.130 pages (including appendix,   Ricardo Martin and                    Examines the consequences of alter-&#13;
index).                               Marcelo Selowsky                      native adjustment mechanisms to&#13;
LC-68-27738. ISBN! 0-8018-0166-4,     Develops a short-term model for       foreign exchange shortages in semi-&#13;
$5.00 (43.25) paperback.              evaluating the adjustment (par-       industrial economies. Compares&#13;
French: Les societes financieres de  ticularly, external borrowing) of oil-  devaluation to two forms of import&#13;
developpement: quelques aspects de    importing developing countries to the    rationing and finds that adjusting by&#13;
leur politique et de leurs activites.  increases in oil prices during the   rationing is much more costly in&#13;
(Available free from the World Bank,  1970s. Discusses the borrowing        terms of lost gross domestic product.&#13;
(ashingtonl D. C)                     strategies that can be expected in the    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
future and the demands that will be   443. January 1981. 32 pages (includ-&#13;
Spanish: Las compafiias financieras   made on multilateral institutions.    in3 rences).&#13;
de desarrollo: algunos aspectos de su                                       ing references).&#13;
politica y de sus actividades. Editorial    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0443. $3.00.&#13;
Tecnos, 1969.                         466. July 1981. 77 pages (including&#13;
300 pesetas.                          footnotes, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0466. $3.00.                 NEW&#13;
Development Prospects&#13;
of Capital Surplus Oil-               Exchange Rate Adjustment              Growth and  Structural&#13;
Exporting Countries: Iraq.            under Generalized Currency    Adjustment in East Asia&#13;
Kuwait, Libya, Qatar,                 Floating: Comparative                 Parvez lasan&#13;
Saudi Arabia, UAE                     Analysis among Developing             Analyzes the economic performance&#13;
Rudolf Hablutzel                      Countries                             of the five large market economies of&#13;
Rudolf Habluizel             ome   M   BatitaEast Asia-Korea, Thailand, the&#13;
This background study for World       Romeo M. Bautista                     Philippines, Malaysia, and&#13;
Development Report 1981               Examines the experiences of twenty-   Indonesia-during the last two&#13;
discusses the production strategies  two developing countries in adapting   decades; focuses on the key factors&#13;
and the development policies of the   to the generalized floating of the    explaining their remarkable economic&#13;
capital-surplus oil-exporting         world's major currencies since 1973   and social progress; and identifies the&#13;
countries.                            and discusses the implications that   main economic issues for the 1980s.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    currency floatinig has on policymaking    WrdBn  tf  okn  ae  o&#13;
in these countries and indicates direc-    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
483. August 1981. 53 pages (including  tions for further research.          529.1982. 42 pages.&#13;
statistical tables).                  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    ISBN 0-8213-0102-0. $3.00.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0483. $3.00.             436. October 1980. 99 pages (including&#13;
appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0436. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
International Adjustment in    Notes on the Mechanics of                   ect appraisal. To give substance to&#13;
the 1980s                            Growth and Debt                       the applied and policy dimensions,&#13;
V.ay Joshi                          Benjamin B. King                     many of the readings are drawn from&#13;
VUgay Joshi                          Benjamin B. King                     the experience of development prac-&#13;
A backgound study for World          A practical model to explore the way  titioners and relate to such important&#13;
Development Report 1981. Analyzes    in which capital inflow from abroad   sectors as agriculture, industry,&#13;
the macroeconomics of international    affects economic growth.            power, urban services, foreign trade,&#13;
adjustment. Highlights potential                                           and employment. The principles&#13;
market failures and areas for        The Johns Hopkins University Press,   outlined are therefore relevant to a&#13;
intervention.                        1968. 69 pages (including 4 annexes).    host of development problems.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper Nio.  LC 68-8701. ISBN 0-8018-0338-1, $5.00    The Johns Hopkins University Press.&#13;
485. August 1982. 57 pages.          (      P3.00) paperback.              February 1983. About 304 pages.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0062-8. $3.00.                                                 LC 82-7716. ISBN 0-8018-2803-1,&#13;
The Policy Experience of             $35.00 hardcouer; ISBN 0-8018-2804-X,&#13;
_Twelve Less Developed               $12.95 paperback.&#13;
NEW                              Countries, 1973-1978&#13;
Bela Balassa                         Private Bank Lending to&#13;
The Nature of Credit                 Uses the methodology applied in the   Developing Countries&#13;
Markets in Developing                author's "The Newly Industrializing   Richard O'Brien&#13;
Countries: A Framework               Developing Countries after the Oil&#13;
for Policy Analysis                  Crisis" (World Bank Staff Working    A background study for World&#13;
Arvind Virmani                       Paper No. 473, October 1980) to       bevelopment Report 1981.&#13;
examine the policy experience of     Describes the evolution of relation-&#13;
The central purpose of the paper is to   twelve less developed countries in  ships between private banks and&#13;
analyze various forms of govemment   the period following the quadrupling  developing countries.&#13;
intervention in the loan market in   of oil prices in 1973-74 and the      World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
terrns of their effect on efficiency.  world recession of 1974-75.         4    auguSt191 Wing 54pes&#13;
482. August 1981. vi + 54 pages&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   (including appendix, bibliography).&#13;
524. 1982. 204 pages.                449. April 1981. 36 pages (including  Stock No. WP-0482. $3.00.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0019-9. $5.00.           appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0449. $3.00.&#13;
Private Capital Flows to&#13;
The rewly' Industrializing                                                 Developing Countries and&#13;
Developing Countries after    The Political Structure of                  Their Determinations:&#13;
the Oil Crisis                       the New Protectionism                 Historical Perspective,&#13;
Bela Balassa                         Douglas R. Nelson                    Recent Experience, and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   This background study for World       Future Prospects&#13;
43 7. October 1980. 5 7 pages (including    Development Report 1981       Alex Fleming&#13;
appendix).                           presenits af what has been called the  A backgound study for World&#13;
Stock No. WP-043 7. $3.00.           "new protectionism."                 Development Report 1981.&#13;
Discusses the nature and determina-&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   tion of recent private capital flows to&#13;
Notes on the Analysis of             471. July 1981. 57 pages (including   developing countries. Focuses on&#13;
Capital Flows to Developing    references).                                those flows passing through the&#13;
Nations and the                      Stock No. WP-04 71. $3.00.           international ban   nd examines the&#13;
"Recycling" Problem                                                        developing countries' continuing&#13;
Ralph C. Bryant                                                           access to the international capital&#13;
A backgound study for World               NEW                              markets.&#13;
Development Report 1981.                                                   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Summarizes and criticizes the con-   Pricing Policy for Develop-           484. August 1981. 41 pages.&#13;
ventional analysis of the interrela-  ment Management&#13;
tions between financial markets in   Gerald M. Meier                       Stock No. WP-0484. $3.00.&#13;
the industrialized countries and capi-&#13;
tal flows to the developing nations.  Presupposing no formal training in&#13;
economics, it explains the essential  Private Direct Foreign&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   elements of a price system, the       Investment in Developing&#13;
4 76. August 1981. 67 pages.         functions of prices, the various      Countiies&#13;
Stock No. WP-04 76. $5.00.           policies that a government mightConre&#13;
pursue in cases of market failure,   K. Billerbeck and Y. Yasugi&#13;
and the principles of public pricing of    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
goods and services provided by       348. July 1979. iv + 97 pages (includ-&#13;
government enterprises. It also pro-        Y&#13;
vides the would-be practitioner with  ing 2 annexes).&#13;
an appreciation of the underlying    Stock No. WP-0348. $5.00.&#13;
logical structure of cost-beneflt proj-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                              Structural Adjustment                implications in terms of income&#13;
__--      -                         Policies in Developing               generation, external deflcit, and&#13;
Short-Run Macro-Economic            Economies                            inflation.&#13;
Adjustment Policies in               Bela Balassa                         World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
South Korea: A Quantitative    Examines structural adjustment            513. June 1982. 93 pages (including&#13;
Analysis                             policies (policy responses to external    appendix).&#13;
Sweder van Wijnbergen               shocks, such as the quadrupling of   ISBN 0-8213-0023-7. $3.00.&#13;
oil prices and the world recession of&#13;
An analysis of the startling reversal of   the 1970s) of developing countries.&#13;
performance of the South Korean     Considers reforms in production      World Debt Tables&#13;
economy in 1979 and 1980 compared   incentives, incentives to save and to&#13;
with the preceding fifteen years, and    invest, public investments, sectoral  A compilation of data on the extemal&#13;
an exploration of the short-run     policies, and monetary policies, and  public and publicly-guaranteed debt&#13;
macro-economic policy options       comments on the interdependence of   of 101 developing countries plus&#13;
available to Korea in 1981. Highlights   the various policy measures and on  eighteen additional tables of private&#13;
the role of commercial banks, foreign   the international environment in  and nonguaranteed debt from the&#13;
capital inflows, and money markets  which they operate.                   World Bank Debtor Reporting&#13;
and the use of credit obtained from                                       System. Describes the nature, con-&#13;
these sources to finance fixed and   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   tent, and coverage of the data;&#13;
working capital.                    464. July 1981. 36 pages.             reviews the external debt of 101&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0464. $3.00.            countries through 198pL contains&#13;
510. November 1981. iv + 178 pages                                        standing, commitments, disburse-&#13;
(including 3 appendixes).                                                ments, service payments, and net&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0000-8. $5.00.               NEW                              borrowings of 101 developing coun-&#13;
tries, by country, 1972-1981.&#13;
Structural Aspects of                (EC-167/81). December 1982. Annual.&#13;
NEW                              Turkish Inflation:                   About 300 pages.&#13;
1950-1979                           ISSNY 0253-2859. $75.00.&#13;
State Finances in India              M. Ataman Aksoy                      Computer tapes containing the data&#13;
A three-volume set of papers that    Inflation has been one of the major  bases for the World Debt Tables are&#13;
explores a range of issues relating to    problems of the Turkish economy  available from the Publications&#13;
the nature of intergovernmental fiscal   during the postwar period. This paper   Distribution Unit, World Bank. The&#13;
relations in India.                  develops alternative inflation models   tapes are available to international&#13;
and analyzes their performance in    agencies and official nonproflt agen-&#13;
light of the Turkish experience in  cies of member govemments at a&#13;
VoL. I:- Revenue Shtaring           order to provide a framework on      nominal fee. For information concem-&#13;
in India                             which a more realistic macro model    ing fees for other organizations,&#13;
Christine Wallich                    can be developed.                   please write to the addressee listed&#13;
Deals specifically with the principles  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  above.&#13;
of revenue sharing in India.         540. 1982. 118 pages.                Supplements to World Debt Tables are&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0098-9. $5.00.           issued periodically as information&#13;
Vol. II: India-Studies In                                                 becomes available; the current&#13;
State Finances                                                            updates are included with orders for&#13;
Christine Wallich                        NEW                              World Debt Tables.&#13;
Examines in detail the implications of&#13;
revenue sharing for project finance.  Thailand: An Analysis of            Te Imp&#13;
Structural and Nuon-                 The lmpact of Contractual Savings on&#13;
Structural and Mon-        Resoum~e MobDizatlon and Allocation:&#13;
Vol. III: The Measurement of    Structural AdJustments                    The Experience of Malaysia&#13;
Tax Effort of State Govern-          Arne Drud, Wafik Grais, and          Social Security Funds in Singapore&#13;
ments, 1973-1976                     Dusan Vujovic                        and the Philippines: Ramifications of&#13;
Raja J. Chelliah and                 This study was prepared as a         Investment Polides&#13;
Narain Sinha                         background paper for the preparation   Investments of Sorial SecurLey giands&#13;
Attempts to evaluate the tax perfor-  of a    structural-adjustmnent loan to  and Experience&#13;
mance of particular states in terms of    Thailand and is a follow-up to a pre-  Parthasarathi Shome and&#13;
the average tax effort of all states.  vious paper entitled "Aggregate    Katrine Anderson Saito&#13;
Demand and Macroeconomic      .      World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 144.&#13;
World Bank Working Paper No, 523.    Imbalances in Thailand." Comparative   Reprinted from The Mlalayan Economic Review, vol.&#13;
September 1982. vol. 1, 85 pages, vol. II,   statistics are used, within the frame-    23, no. 1 (April1978).54-72, Labour and Society,&#13;
186 pages, uol. III, 85 pages.       work of a four-sector macroeconomic   vol. 5, no. I (January 1980):19-30: and The Indian&#13;
model, to assess altemative ways of    Joumal of Economics, vol. 60. part 3. no. 238&#13;
lSBN 0-8213-0013-X. vol. 1, $3.00, vol. II,   macroeconomic adjustment in the  (January 1980):349-60.&#13;
$5.00, vol. 111, $3.00.              Thai economy. Discusses specifically    Stock llo. RP-0144. Free of charge.&#13;
fiscal policy interventions, manipula-&#13;
tions of the exchange rate, and pro-&#13;
ductivity improvements and their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Policy Responses to External Shocks in&#13;
Selected Latin American Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number 221.&#13;
Reprinted from Quarterly Review of Economics and&#13;
Business, vol. 21. no. 2 (Summer 1981):131-64.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0221. free of charge.&#13;
Restructuilng the World Economy:&#13;
Round 11&#13;
Hollis Chenery&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number 204.&#13;
Reprinted from Foreign Affairs&#13;
(Summer 1981):1102-1220.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0204. free of charge.&#13;
Risk Assessments and Risk Premiums&#13;
in the Eurodollar Market&#13;
Gershon Feder and iKnud Ross&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number 220.&#13;
Reprinted from The Journal of Finance, vol. 37.&#13;
no. 3 (June 19821:679-91.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0220. Free of charge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                            WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
RO. BOX 37525                                                or                    66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                             75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                              Author, Title                          Qty.        Price           Total    1&#13;
'1'       __~~~~~~~~~~ ------&#13;
I   X-&#13;
___ I-~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
____   ___                   ___                   ___                   i                  _-&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies: _      _      Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers. libraries. and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:                                                                                _&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'Ilna&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: (1) 723-54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
N &#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0188-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="700888">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/05/700888/interest-rate-management-developing-countries-theory-simulation-results-korea
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/05/700888/interest-rate-management-developing-countries-theory-simulation-results-korea</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/05/700888/interest-rate-management-developing-countries-theory-simulation-results-korea</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1983/05/01/000009265_3980928162725/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1983/05/01/000009265_3980928162725/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1983-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>1983-05-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Interest rate management in developing
            countries : theory and simulation results for Korea
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Much of the existing development
            literature follows McKinnon and Shaw in claiming that higher
            time deposit rates raise output and lower inflation in the
            short run and increase growth via their favorable impact on
            savings rates. This paper shows that this result depends
            crucially on the assumption that the portfolio shift into
            time deposits comes out of an unproductive asset, providing
            less intermediation than the banking system.  If instead,
            time deposits are closer substitutes to assets providing
            more intermediation, such as loans outstanding on the curb
            market, raising time deposit rates is contractionary.  The
            paper also discusses the impact of changes in time deposit
            rates on inflation, capital accumulation, and medium-term
            growth.  A negative impact on investment and growth and
            positive effects on inflation in the short run are possible
            consequences of increased time deposit rates.  The empirical
            relevance of all this is demonstrated by simulation runs
            with a quarterly macroeconomic model of South Korea.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Interest rate management in developing
            countries : theory and simulation results for Korea
        </docna>
        <display_title>Interest rate management in
            developing countries : theory and simulation results for Korea</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/05/700888/interest-rate-management-developing-countries-theory-simulation-results-korea</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Financial Intermediation,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Korea, Republic of</count>
        <authors>
            <author>van Wijnbergen, Sweder</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Asia!$!80460</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980928162725</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Public Sector Management</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 593</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0188-8</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Assets; Interest rates; Mathematical models;
            Simulation; Time deposits
            accounting,accounting framework,affiliated
            organizations,affiliates,aggregate demand,aggregate
            supply,aggregate supply curve,assets,balance sheet,bank
            credit,Bank Lending,bank loans,Bank of Korea,banking
            system,capital accumulation,capital formation,Cd,commercial
            banks,competitiveness,consumers,CPI,credit markets,credit
            policies,credit rationing,debt,demand for
            money,Deposits,Development
            Economics,disequilibrium,disposable income,dynamic
            analysis,Economic Activity,economic
            development,economists,elasticities,Elasticity,Elasticity of
            Demand,Empirical Evidence,equilibrium,excess demand,excess
            supply,exchange rates,exports,financial asset
            accumulation,financial decisions,Financial
            Deepening,financial intermediaries,financial
            intermediation,financial markets,financial sector,financial
            structure,fixed capital,foreign capital,GNP,growth
            rate,imperfect substitutes,income,income
            effect,inflation,inflation rate,inflation rates,input
            prices,Interest rate,Interest rates,LDCs,Lending
            Rates,M2,market equilibrium,Mathematical models,monetary
            policy,money supply,nominal GNP,portfolio,positive
            effects,price rationing,production function,profit
            rate,profitability,real income,real interest rate,real
            product wage,real sector,reserve
            requirements,savings,savings rates,securities,securities
            markets,terms of trade,time deposits,total output,variable
            costs,wages,wealth,working capital
        </keywd>
        <owner>Development Economics and Chief Economist</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP593</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Carreer Guidance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Job Fairs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Counterterrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Counter-terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mediation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>