<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Sv/P7 a7&#13;
Indonesia&#13;
The Challenge of Urbanization&#13;
Andrew M. Hamer&#13;
Andrew D. Steer&#13;
David G. Williams&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 787&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 787&#13;
Indonesia&#13;
The Challenge of Urbanization&#13;
Andrew M. Hamer&#13;
Andrew D. Steer&#13;
David G. Williams&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1986&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing January 1986 Second printing April 1988&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'I6na, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Andrew M. Hamer is a senior economist and David G. Williams a senior urban&#13;
planner in the Operations Support and Research Unit of the World Bank's Water Supply&#13;
and Urban Development Department; Andrew D. Steer is a senior economist in South&#13;
East Asia Division of the East Asia and Pacific Regional Office.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data&#13;
Hamer, Andrew Marshall.&#13;
Indonesia, the challenge of urbanization.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 787)&#13;
1. Cities and towns--Indonesia--Growth. 2. Rural-&#13;
Urban migration--Indonesia. 3. Urban policy--Indonesia.&#13;
4. Urban economics. I. Steer, Andrew. II. Williams,&#13;
David G. (David Glyn), 1938-            ,  III. Title.&#13;
IV. Series.&#13;
HT371.H27  1986                    307.7'6'09598           85-29537&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0688-X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iii -&#13;
Abstract&#13;
Indonesia's urban population is growing rapidly. Almost 40 million residents&#13;
will be added to its cities in the last two decades of the century. This&#13;
growth is the outcome of millions of individual household and business&#13;
decisions. It is best managed inclirectly, through improved national sectoral&#13;
and urban management policies. Suggested policy modifications are included in&#13;
the text. Direct interventions to contain city size or redirect migration are&#13;
usually inefficient and counterproductive; most such initiatives should thus&#13;
be avoided.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iv -&#13;
Preface&#13;
Over the last two years, a number of reports have been produced&#13;
dealing with regional and urban issues in Indonesia. This work, in turn, has&#13;
been encouraged and closely followed by the Government, which is in the&#13;
process of reviewing certain policies and institutions dealing with these&#13;
matters.   Because other countries are facing similar questions,  it seemed&#13;
appropriate to repackage and, in part, to expand upon the findings of these&#13;
reports, making them available to a wider audience.&#13;
The Key reports on which this study is based include:&#13;
Indonesia: Policies and Prospects for Economic Growth and&#13;
Transformation, Report No. 5066-IND, East Asia and Pacific&#13;
Regional Office, The World Bank, April 26, 1984.&#13;
Indonesia: Urban Services Sector Report, Report No. 4800-IND, East&#13;
Asia and Pacific Regional Office, The World Bank, June 25, 1984.&#13;
Indonesia: Selected Aspects of Spatial Development, Report No. 4776-&#13;
IND, East Asia and Pacific Regional Office, November, 1984.&#13;
Indonesia: Policies for Growth and Employment, Report No. 5597-IND,&#13;
East Asia and Pacific Regional Office, The World Bank, April 23,&#13;
1985.&#13;
Please note that the documents cited as "reports" in this paper, such&#13;
as the foregoing, are for distribution within the World Bank only.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
v&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Preface&#13;
I.    Summary of Conclusions and Recommendations ........................ 1&#13;
General observations......           ........o...........  1&#13;
Industrial policy reforms  .... .o...... .  ..... .  ...... .... . .2&#13;
Reforming urban management. .. . . . ... .. ....... .......o. .4&#13;
II.   Urban Spatial Policies and {institutions:&#13;
An Introduction ......       ,                                       *7&#13;
III.  Human Settlement Patterns in Indonesia....... ...-................ 11&#13;
A.  Urban Growth:  Past Trends and Future Prospects...............11&#13;
Recent pattern of urban growth..... ....... o.....................11&#13;
The challenge of future urbanization....o.o.o................ 12&#13;
B.  Rural-Urban Migration and Urban Population Growth............. 17&#13;
Data limitations ....... .........................  ....  0.0..... .... 17&#13;
Permanent migration o..o...o.o.o.o..o...o  ... o......................... o....19&#13;
Unrecorded migration..........................................20&#13;
Urban quality of life and rural-urban migration...............21&#13;
C.  Urbanization and the Growth of Large Cities ...................29&#13;
Difficulties in defining urban growth by city size ....o .... 29&#13;
Trends in urban growth bly city size...........................29&#13;
IV.   Influencing Urban Development ............o..*...*oo .............. 33&#13;
A.  Some Basic Principles.................. ...................... 33&#13;
Determinants of city size in the course of development........ 33&#13;
The impact of natLonal production patterns..oo.........,....34&#13;
The relative attractiveness of cities and city size ...........37&#13;
Limits to public intervention in shaping city size............38&#13;
B.  Influencing Industrial Location ................... ......... . 41&#13;
Why focus on industrial location?           ....  .     . .*****4l&#13;
(Continued)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- vi -&#13;
(Table of Contents - Cont.)&#13;
Page No.&#13;
The spatial bias of sectoral policies ......................... 43&#13;
The trade regime and city size effects ................ 44&#13;
Impact of transport sector inefficiencies on city size..*..... 46&#13;
The locational impact of pervasive micro regulation........... 48&#13;
Industrial estates as tools for regional dispersal ......o..... 54&#13;
The role of public industrial investment in regional&#13;
development ....................... .................. oo.....*.ee..... *57&#13;
Regional development and the rationing of industrial&#13;
finance ..... o.--.... oo.... .o..o..................... ..o.o.o......59&#13;
C.  Management and Finance of Urban Services ...........-........ 62&#13;
The financial implications of REPELITA IV urban goals......... 62&#13;
Challenges facing public administration..o..o.. o....ooo...... 67&#13;
Alternative sources to finance urban finance ........l..........71&#13;
Local borrowing as a tool....o.-oo ..... o-o-oo-ooe ........ 77&#13;
Financing urban housing services. ...o.......o....o*.oo..o.... 84&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I.  Summary of Conclusions And Recomendations&#13;
General observations&#13;
1.       Though the urban share of Indonesia's population is still relatively&#13;
low, its absolute size and annual growth is significant enough to warrant&#13;
serious concern among policy-makers.   During the final two decades of the&#13;
century, almost 40 million residents are expected to be added to Indonesia's&#13;
cities.&#13;
2.       Urban growth is the outccome of millions of individual household and&#13;
business decisions concerning lociation for new or expanded activity.   This&#13;
process, which includes rural-urban and interprovincial migration, helps to&#13;
redirect population and employment growth toward areas of emerging economic&#13;
opportunity.   Such a redistribution of growth is a common feature in the&#13;
history of all nations and one whLch, in the main, yields the most efficient&#13;
and equitable outcomes when managed indirectly, through improved urban&#13;
management and national sectoral policies.   Direct interventions to force&#13;
growth to follow different paths is usually costly and counterproductive, and&#13;
forces already over-extended public administrators into areas where they are&#13;
at a comparative disadvantage.&#13;
3.       What is true about efforts to stem rural-urban migration in general&#13;
is equally true of any attempts the shape the city size distribution of the&#13;
urban population by crude administrative measures.   There is a tendency for&#13;
the share of urban population of different city size categories to become more&#13;
evenly distributed in the course of economic development.  Unfortunately this&#13;
results from a complex set of factors; most of the features that determine the&#13;
changing relative attractiveness of cities are exogeMus in the short-run.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2 -&#13;
Policy levers work best when they are applied indirectly, and when results are&#13;
allowed to emerge over an ample period of time.&#13;
4.       A set of policy recommendations are found throughout this paper, and&#13;
are summarized below.  Their net effect will be to modify the rate at which&#13;
different size cities will grow. Unfortunately, little can be said about the&#13;
precise way in which these changes will take place. There is no available&#13;
theoretical framework of city size distribution, no model that one could&#13;
estimate with data and use to predict reforms in relative city sizes in the&#13;
presence of policy changes, and then compared with actual Indonesian data.&#13;
Nevertheless, what is clear is that even marginal declines in the growth of&#13;
larger cities will result in the reallocation of millions of urban dwellers&#13;
over time. The lack of precise estimates of policy impacts is thus no grounds&#13;
for inaction or for the use of controls whose record is generally poor.&#13;
Industrial policy reforms&#13;
1.       Because  of  its  growing  importance,   its  inherent  locational&#13;
flexibility, and its multiplier effects, the industrial sector is a natural&#13;
focus for policy reforms aimed at managing urban growth. Certain measures are&#13;
to be avoided in this process.   Use of business location licenses or of&#13;
residence permits should be set aside. Public administrators rarely have the&#13;
foresight to manage urban growth so directly.   This is especially true in&#13;
countries like Indonesia, where the central bureaucracy is already over-&#13;
extended,  given  its  size  and  its  quality.    Instead,  industrial  policy&#13;
initiatives should concentrate on five areas.  First. large dividends can be&#13;
reaped from improving transportation and telecommunications access to domestic&#13;
and international markets.   This is important for a country like Indonesia,&#13;
where geographic fragmentation has resulted in an economic archipelago. with&#13;
fewer links between provinces and islands than required to help fulfill the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
goals of efficient and equitable development.  It is crucial that the planned&#13;
program of improving inter-island shipping and port performance be carried out&#13;
vigorously, along with an extension and upgrading of interregional road&#13;
links. Until access is significantly improved, physical proximity to the main&#13;
consumer markets, especially in and around Jakarta, will dictate the location&#13;
of all producers except those thaLt are resource-bound or those too small to&#13;
cater to more than a very localized market area.&#13;
2.       Second. improved physical access must be accompanied by measures to&#13;
reduce the incentives to operate businesses near the centers of government&#13;
power.   In the past, day-to-day access to customs officials, tax officials,&#13;
regulators, and sectoral policy-makers. especially those in Jakarta, was&#13;
necessary.   This type of incentive is counterproductive to spatial goals of&#13;
decentralized development, and has no other redeeming value.   It should be&#13;
neutralized through the continued simplification of rules and regulations.&#13;
3.       Third, the explicit price signals governing location behavior require&#13;
modification, especially those associated with trade regulation. The existing&#13;
trade regime encourages the premature growth of large cities by promoting the&#13;
growth of inefficient import-competing activities which are dependent on the&#13;
agglomeration  economies  found  in  economically pre-eminent  centers.    Once&#13;
again, such sweeping protectionist incentives are not justified on national&#13;
development grounds, and they retard decentralized growth as well.   Reforms&#13;
are needed if efficient and equiLtable growth is to occur, nationally and&#13;
across regions.&#13;
4.       Fourth, the government should be encouraged to develop and expand the&#13;
use of industrial zones and estates targeted selectively in areas of proven&#13;
growth or well-documented potential. At this stage of development, the areas&#13;
where industrial growth and diversification will tal place are clear. It is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
in these areas where improved infrastructure is a necessary, and almost&#13;
sufficient, condition for continued growth. Elsewhere, on the other hand, the&#13;
obstacles to industrial growth are so many that radical improvements in public&#13;
services will not be cost-effective.   Such areas should share in the gradual&#13;
upgrading of infrastructure that can be expected as economic development&#13;
constraints give way over time.&#13;
5.       Fifth, during this period, when the rules that govern the behavior of&#13;
financial institutions is changing, considerable attention is required to&#13;
improve access to investment and working capital for small and medium-size&#13;
firms. Particularly important is the consideration of proposals that would&#13;
promote long-term lending by the various regional development banks. For the&#13;
foreseeable future, other institutions do not have a sufficient incentive to&#13;
provide long-term funds for smaller firms.  The public sector, using own and&#13;
foreign resources, will be forced to demonstrate the profitability of such&#13;
lending activity over the next decade.&#13;
Reforming urban management-&#13;
1.       Improved access to public services in urban areas plays a crucial&#13;
role  in economic  development  by modifying  the relative attractiveness  of&#13;
particular centers over time.   This is true both directly, by reducing the&#13;
operating costs incurred by business, and indirectly, by helping to attractive&#13;
skilled workers and professionals to such centers.   At the same time, the&#13;
central government cannot continue to operate in this area as it has in the&#13;
past.   While cities require improvements,  the rural areas of the country,&#13;
where most of the population lives, are seriously deficient in services they&#13;
have a right to expect on equity grounds alone. This enormous task confronts&#13;
a central government that faces serious financial constraints and that cannot&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5 -&#13;
effectively make all the many decisions that each city investment strategy&#13;
requires.&#13;
2.       The solution most likely to achieve this goal of improved services&#13;
for the cities is one thal: incretases local autonomy and financial responsi-&#13;
bility.    The  government  should  give  serious  consideration  to  granting&#13;
kotamadya status to all urban areas with a threshold population of 20,000-&#13;
50,000 and above. At that point :Ln the development of a city, the demands for&#13;
local  coordination  of  investments,  maintenance,  and  cost-recovery  are&#13;
generally beyond the means of central, provincial or even district authorities&#13;
who have responsibilities for large rural populations as well. With increased&#13;
autonomy there should be consLderable attention paid to upgrading the&#13;
technical and planned skills for local government workers.   Very useful in&#13;
this regard would be the introduction of multi-year, rolling, consolidated&#13;
development budgets which would bring together financing and physical planning&#13;
information for all projects.&#13;
3.       In an age of central government austerity, plans should be put into&#13;
place for graduating urban areas from an intergovernmental fiscal regime based&#13;
heavily on straight central grants to one based on a combination matching&#13;
grants, loans, and increased local tax effort and user charges. Such a system&#13;
is well-established in many developing and most developed countries; it&#13;
appears practical for Indonesia. Once in place, it will allow improvements to&#13;
be made in urban areas while rural demands for basic needs are addressed. It&#13;
will permit improvements to be made in large cities, like Jakarta, without&#13;
subsidizing its residents well-being. It will make possible the extension of&#13;
services necessary for decentralized economic development across a large&#13;
number of cities without burying the central government in debt and&#13;
administrative red tape.  From this will emerge a stronger administration at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
all levels, and the central government will finally be able to fulfill its&#13;
mission to plan selectively and strategically for the enormous changes that&#13;
face the nation over the following decades.&#13;
4.       An integral part of any attempt to better provide for the needs of&#13;
the cities is a shelter plan which mobilizes the financial resources and the&#13;
potential sweat  equity available  in the urban areas.   In the past,  the&#13;
government has channeled public resources largely mobilized elsewhere to&#13;
finance new housing at high levels of subsidization.   Though the national&#13;
public housing authority has developed an innovative strategy to reach&#13;
households at the lower half of the urban income distribution, most of the&#13;
benefits of the housing programs have accrued to the upper two deciles.&#13;
5.       Reforms  are  now  necessary.    Housing  finance  programs  must  be&#13;
expanded, as the goals proposed for REPELITA IV have emphasized. Beyond that&#13;
there is a need to develop pioneering efforts to help the poor half of the&#13;
households through an imaginative mix of sites and services programs, core&#13;
unit construction, housing upgrading support and guided land development. The&#13;
macroeconomic realities inherent in the present climate of austerity, combined&#13;
with the need of meeting rural demands, both require financing mechanisms that&#13;
mobilize private resources for housing and allocate them to all income&#13;
groups.  This, in turn, means that housing finance institutions must operate&#13;
according to increasingly commercial principles, raising and lending funds at&#13;
market rates.   Equity concerns should be addressed by a limited amount of&#13;
cross-subsidization with higher income borrowers paying more for loans so that&#13;
low income borrowers can pay less.  Beyond that there is a need to structure&#13;
lending so that the profile of beneficiaries more closely resembles that of&#13;
the urban households as a whole.   This could be achieved by relying more&#13;
heavily on sites and services programs and core housing financing; by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
introducing home improvement programs; and by restricting the size of&#13;
individual loans.   In this manner, housing finance institutions can play an&#13;
active role in ensuring that labor markets within and across Indonesia's&#13;
cities function more smoothly by removing barriers to labor mobility.&#13;
II. Urban Spatial Policies and Instruments: An Introduction&#13;
1.       In Indonesia, and across the developing world, national policy-makers&#13;
tend to fear the rising tide of urbanization.   More specifically there is&#13;
apprehension that urbanization will concentrate population in one or a very&#13;
few centers, drawing resources away from other areas and thwarting attempts to&#13;
achieve political integration. Furthermore, the difficulties associated with&#13;
managing individual urban areas are often given as reasons for imposing some&#13;
type of control on urban development. Cities growing "uncontrollably" appear&#13;
to generate unmanageable problemsi whose symptoms include slums, congestion,&#13;
and pollution.   Given that urbanization patterns are shaped by millions of&#13;
individual decisions on where to live, work, and invest, the key issue is&#13;
whether this growth should be managed directly or deaTft with indirectly, by&#13;
improving national sectoral and urban management policies.&#13;
2.       Indonesia  provides  an  interesting  case,  1 cause it has actually&#13;
attempted to influence the rate of inmigration into the capital city.   An&#13;
early effort was made in 1970, when the Governor of Jakarta established a&#13;
system of formal urban residence permits.   New migrants were to receive a&#13;
temporary residence card, upon deposit with the authorities of a sum&#13;
equivalent to twice their return fare. After six months, a permanent card was&#13;
to be made available on proof of permanent employment.   Failing that, a&#13;
migrant was to be provided with funds to return to his home district. This&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
mechanism was allowed to lapse and was not rigorously enforced.   Linked to&#13;
this was another tool which is still being utilized. Attempts have been made,&#13;
over time, to limit new migrant employment opportunities by barring street&#13;
vendors and becak (bicycle rickshaws) operators from areas of the city.&#13;
3.       More systematic efforts to force economic activity out of Jakarta or&#13;
other large centers and into more peripheral locations were never undertaken,&#13;
except as a side-effect of industrial policies whose objective was a broader&#13;
one of regulating the degree of competition in each economic subsector by&#13;
creating licensing barriers-to-entry. For a growing number of these regulated&#13;
activities,  locations  in and  around  Jakarta were  deemed  "saturated"  and&#13;
further new investment was barred.&#13;
4.       This  example  is  but  one  in  which  the  government  has  pursued&#13;
ostensibly non-spatial policies that can have spatial effects, whether&#13;
intended or not.   Many, including licensing, are inspired by a belief that&#13;
Indonesia's low level of economic development,  combined with a history of&#13;
regional and ethnic unrest, requires a high level of central supervision over&#13;
many facets of economic and political life.  These policies are discussed in&#13;
this paper, but it is useful to review them briefly at this point.&#13;
5.       Historically, the macroeconomic environment has been characterized by&#13;
a fairly high degree of regulation which has exacerbated the tendency for the&#13;
production of tradeable goods and services to concentrate in areas where&#13;
scarce infrastructure facilities are present, namely the largest centers&#13;
(especially Jakarta). Thus at the same time attempts were being made to stem&#13;
migration into Jakarta, the trade regime in place provided a heavily&#13;
protectionist environment which encouraged the premature emergence of&#13;
otherwise unprofitable industrial activities whose requirements at this stage&#13;
of development can only be met in and around Jakarta and, to a lesser extent,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
Surabaya.   Businesses  also  found  it necessary  to have access to  central&#13;
bureaucrats not merely to facilitat:e the establishment or expansion of plants,&#13;
but also to negotiate customized treatment regarding taxation, additional&#13;
protection, processing of goods through ports, and industrial financing.&#13;
6.       Another fundamental barrier to decentralized development can be found&#13;
in the Indonesian system of intergovernmental fiscal relations.  Ir.. countries&#13;
where local governments are responsible for mobilizing a significant portion&#13;
of  public  sector  resources,  one  tends  to  observe  a  systematic,  and&#13;
coordinated, expansion of local public services with minimal reliance on&#13;
central government subsidies.,1/  Localities can compete among themselves to&#13;
attract entrepreneurs and skilled workers by offering different bundles of&#13;
local services, local taxes, and user charges.   In such settings, large&#13;
centers are likely to be relatively expensive places to do business and to&#13;
live, because they face diffiicult problems in dealing with congestion,&#13;
pollution, waste  disposal, and  crime.   Employers who do not require  the&#13;
special advantages of big cities, may find lower cost, alternative sites in&#13;
smaller centers, especially as interregional communications improve.  This in&#13;
turn, helps redirect migration flows.&#13;
7.       In  Indonesia,  city  resiLdents  have  received  priority  access  to&#13;
centrally funded, and heavily subsidized, public ser-ices, while the much&#13;
larger, and poorer populatiLon of the countryside, has failed to keep pace.&#13;
Metropolitan centers, in turn, have benefitted most of all.  Thus, at a time&#13;
when there is much concern about migration into large cities, a highly&#13;
centralized system of intergovernmental relations discriminates in their favor&#13;
1/ J.V. Henderson, A Framework for International Comparisons of Cities, Urban&#13;
and Regional Report No. 80-3, Wiorld Bank, March 1980; B. Renaud, National&#13;
Urbanization Policies in Developing Countries, New York, Oxford University&#13;
Press, 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
by providing relatively high levels of local services without commensurate&#13;
local cost recovery.   In this sense, the observed lag in the improvement of&#13;
local services elsewhere in the urban system, and even in the countryside, is&#13;
as much due to the lack of local resource mobilization and planning as to the&#13;
overall level of development of the economy.&#13;
8.       One additional instance of implicit spatial policy-making is found in&#13;
the  planning  of  infrastructure  investments  of  regional  or  national&#13;
significance.    Though one might argue about the overall level of effort&#13;
devoted to port development, highways, or industrial zones and estates, the&#13;
fact remains that current levels of development have forced the public sector&#13;
inevitably to favor some areas over others.   The best port, the best road&#13;
links, and the most extensive facilities for industrial estates exist in&#13;
Jakarta.   Other areas might have been given greater attention under other&#13;
scenarios, but few would argue against a spatial concentration of these types&#13;
of investments at early stages of development.   In fact, where aggressive&#13;
efforts have been made in poor countries to scatter these types of&#13;
investments, they have been uniformly criticized by outside observers. 1/&#13;
That having been said, it remains clear that the totality of policies that&#13;
impinge on urban development in Indonesia do not provide a consistent set of&#13;
signals to the millions of economic decision-makers in the country.   The&#13;
argument made in this paper is that a self-conscious review of the facts, and&#13;
careful attention to a framework for assessing spatial development, can lead&#13;
to improved policies that support the gradual and consistent increase in the&#13;
number of locational options for firms and workers.   In the final analysis,&#13;
the spatial configuration of urban settlements is seen to depend less on&#13;
1/  A.U. Sekhar, Industrial Location Policy:  The Indian Experience, World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper No. 620, 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
direct interventions by social engineers working at the center and more on the&#13;
indirect outcomes of a mult[plicity of policies, most of which merit adoption&#13;
on non-spatial grounds alone.&#13;
III. Human Settlement Patterns in Indonesia&#13;
A. Urban Growth: Past Trends and Future Prospects&#13;
Recent pattern of urban growth&#13;
1.       Population growth has accelerated  over the last two decades,  as&#13;
substantial reductions in mortality outpaced fertility declines.   Indonesia&#13;
grew at a rate of 2.3% per annum, in the 1970s, compared to earlier rates of&#13;
2.1% (1961-1971) and 1.5% (1930-1960).   Added to this has been a noticeable&#13;
expansion in economic activity, starting with the economic recovery of the&#13;
late 1960s.   These two factors haLve led to increasingly rapid urban growth.&#13;
According to census data, the percentage of population living in&#13;
desa I/ classified as urban has risen from roughly 15% in 1961 to 17% in 1971&#13;
and, more sharply, to 22% in 1981).  Measured urban population Increased at&#13;
2.6%/annum during 1961-1971, accelerating to 4%/annum in the next decade.&#13;
If attempts are made to count the rising tide of semi-permanent Javanese&#13;
migrants who flow to urban areas for the better part of each year, then the&#13;
1/ In Indonesia, the differentiation between urban and rural area is made at&#13;
the "village" or desa level; a desa is either urban or rural. Desa units&#13;
are agglomerated into sub-districts (Kecamatan), which are, in turn,&#13;
grouped into districts (Kabupat:en/Kotamadva) and then provinces.&#13;
2/  The average annual growth rate for 1971-1980 has been adjusted to take&#13;
into account changes in the definition of what constitutes an urban desa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
recent rate of growth would have to be modified upward, to perhaps 4.5% per&#13;
annum, or almost twice the national population growth rate.&#13;
2.       Using measured urban population for comparative purposes, Indonesia&#13;
is now more urbanized, on average, than all low income countries (17%), though&#13;
it still lags considerably behind the rate for all middle-income countries,&#13;
(45%).   More important for the future, however, is the growth rate of the&#13;
urban population, which already equals the total for middle income countries&#13;
as a whole and exceeds rates among East Asian and Pacific countries like the&#13;
Philippines (3.7%/annum) or Malaysia (3.3%/annum) (Table 1).&#13;
3.       Provincial data on measured urbanization are given in Table 2.  At&#13;
about 25%, the proportion of total island population defined as urban is&#13;
highest on Javal/. This reflects, in part, the presence of the capital city,&#13;
Jakarta, which alone accounts for over six million of the 33 million urban&#13;
inhabitants.   Excluding Jakarta,  the urban proportions do not vary greatly&#13;
among the most populous islands, and range from 16% on Sulawesi to 21% on&#13;
Kalimantan. The remaining Eastern islands have a lower average of 13%. Urban&#13;
growth rates, as captured by the census, exceed the national average in all&#13;
island groupings outside Java and range from 3.6%/annum on the Eastern islands&#13;
to 5%-6%/annum on Sumatra, Kalimantan, and Sulawesi.&#13;
The challenge of future urbanization&#13;
1.       The difference  in urban growth rates,  extended into the future,&#13;
implies a significant redistribution of the increasing urban population over&#13;
j  Since it is likely that Javanese urbanization is understated by the&#13;
failure to count semi-permanent residents, all data on urban Java must be&#13;
understood as providing lower bounds for actual totals.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Indicators of Urbani:ation: International Conparisons&#13;
Urban Population     Percent of    Average Annual Growth&#13;
as % of Total      Labor Force  Rate of Population 1970-81&#13;
Pbpulation, 1981    in Industry      Total           Urban&#13;
Indonesia                         23                  15            2.3            4.0&#13;
(4.5)&#13;
Middle Income Cbontries&#13;
Total                         45                  21            2.4            4.1&#13;
Asia and Pacific              32                  18            2.3             3.9&#13;
Lw Income Countries               21                  15             1.9            4.4&#13;
Comiparator Countries&#13;
Philippines                   37                  17            2.7             3.7&#13;
Malaysia                      30                  16            2.5             3.3&#13;
Thailand                      15                   9            2.5            3.4&#13;
India                         24                  13            2.1            3.7&#13;
Pakistan                      29                  20            3.0            4.3&#13;
Nigeria                       21                  19            2.5            4.8&#13;
Egypt                         44                  30            2.5            2.9&#13;
a/ Includes estimate of growth oif urneasted seasonal mlgration; see para 1.&#13;
Source: Wbrld Development Report 1982, 1983; Wbrld Atlas 1982; and Wbrld Hank's "Socdal&#13;
Indicators".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Table 2&#13;
Total and Masured Urban Ppulation and Adiusted Growth by Province&#13;
Average Amul Growth&#13;
1980 Census                     1971-1980&#13;
Total      Urban       %          Total       Urban&#13;
Population Population Urban        Population Population&#13;
(est) a&#13;
Aceh                          2,611         233     8.9            2.9&#13;
North Sumatra                 8,361      2,127    25.4             2.6&#13;
West &amp;mtra                    3,407        433    12.7             2.2&#13;
Riau                                      2,169     588           27.1        3.1&#13;
Jambi                                     1,446     183           12.0        4.1&#13;
South Sumatra                 4,630      1,267    27.4             3.3&#13;
Benr*ulu                                   768       72            9.4        4.4&#13;
Lanpung                                  4,625      577           12.5        5.8&#13;
TIUAL SIMA3RA                28.016      5.481    19.4             3.3        5.1&#13;
DKI Jakarta                   6,503       6,072    93.4            3.9         3.9&#13;
West Java                    27,455       5,771    21.0            2.7&#13;
Central Java                 25,373      4,756    18.7             1.6&#13;
D.I. Yogyakarta               2,751        607    22.0             1.1&#13;
East Java                    29,189      5,720    19.6             1.5&#13;
TOTAL JAVA                   91.270     22.926    25.1             2.0         3.0&#13;
(JAVA EMG.&#13;
JAKAREA)                  (84,767)   (16,854)   (19.9)          (1.9)       (2.6)&#13;
West Kalinantan               2,486        417    16.8             2.3&#13;
Central Kalimantan              954         98    10.3             3.4&#13;
South KalinEntan              1,218        485    39.8             2.2&#13;
East Kalimantan               2,065        441    21.4             5.7&#13;
TOTAL&#13;
KALIMANYN                   6,723       1.441    21.4            3.0         6.4&#13;
North Sulawesi                2,115        355    16.8             2.3&#13;
Central Sulawesi              1,290        115      9.0            3.9&#13;
South Sulawesi                6,062      1,096    18.1             1.7&#13;
South East Sulawesi             942         88      9.3            3.1&#13;
TIOAL SULAkESI               10.410       1.654    15.9            2.2         5.1&#13;
Bali                                      2,470     363           14.7         1.7&#13;
West Nusa Tenggara            2,725         383    14.0            2.4&#13;
East Nusa Tengra              2,737        205      7.5            2.0&#13;
Mbuku                                     1,411     153           10.8         2.9&#13;
Irian Jaya                    1,174        237    20.2             2.7&#13;
TOTAL EASTERN&#13;
ISLAS                      10.517       1.341    12.8            2.2         3.6&#13;
TDTAL INDNESIA              146.935      32.846    22.4            2.3         4.0&#13;
aI/ hese are estimates based on Imperfect informtion.&#13;
Sotce: 1980 and 1971 Population Censuses issued by Central Bureau of Statistics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
time.   Bank staff estimatesL/ suggest that, between 1980 and 2000, Java's&#13;
urban population will grow from 23 million to 41 million, while the urban&#13;
totals on the Outer Islands will rise from 10 million to 31 million. Though it&#13;
may be argued that the Outer IslaLnds will face difficulties in attempting to&#13;
urbanize at a rapid pace, the underlying policy message of the cited estimates&#13;
remains valid.  The growth of those Outer Island cities may help relieve the&#13;
pressure on the cities of Java, by diverting rural-urban migration toward&#13;
Outer Island centers.   Many of these migrants may not be interested in the&#13;
Outer Island rural transmigration sites now being promoted by the central&#13;
government; they might, however, welcome the opportunity to find urban&#13;
employment on the Outer Islands.&#13;
2.       Given the probable rates of decline in fertility and mortality and&#13;
the likely trends in the pattern of migration among provinces, estimates of&#13;
total and urban population can be made through to the year 2000 (Table 3).&#13;
Following such a scenario, the growth of Indonesia's population is projected&#13;
to decline from an annual rate of 2.3% in the 1970's to 2.0% and 1.8% in the&#13;
next two decades.  This decreased growth rate is unlikely to be matched by a&#13;
similar deceleration in urban population growth.   A conservative projection&#13;
would assume a continuation of the recent 4%/annum urban growth rate over the&#13;
remaining two decades of the century. By 2000 the urban population would then&#13;
total 72 million or 34% of the population.  Such a scenario implies that half&#13;
of the population increase in the 1980's and fully two-thirds of the&#13;
Population increase in the next decade will take place in urban centers.&#13;
1/ These estimates assume inter-lprovincial and rural-urban migratin patterns&#13;
are unchanged from 1975-1980 rates, and that Indonesia reaches a&#13;
stationary population by 2025.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
Table 3&#13;
Projected Growth of Total and Urban Population in the 1980s and 1990s&#13;
Mid-Year Population           Increase in Population&#13;
1971    1980    1990    2000       1980-1990    1990-2000&#13;
Total (million)       119.0   146.0   178.7   213.6          32.7         34.9&#13;
Urban (million)         22.9    32.6    48.6    71.9          16.0         23.2&#13;
Percent Urban           19.2    22.3    27.2    33.7          49           67&#13;
Source: Bank Staff estimates. Total population projected to grow at rates&#13;
of 2.04% and 1.78% per year in the 1980's and 1990's respectively.&#13;
Urban population projected to grow at 4.0% per year throughout the&#13;
period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
3.       These  projections,  based  on assumptions  about  likely rural-urban&#13;
flows on Java, may be modified marginally by actions taken to sustain the rate&#13;
of economic growth in rural areas.  Nevertheless, there is greater potential&#13;
for influencing the pattern of urbanization than for controlling the overall&#13;
total of urban population. Elements for such a strategy are discussed below.&#13;
B.  Rural - Urban Migration and Urban Population Growth&#13;
Data limitations&#13;
1.       Of the estimated 9.6 million increase in urban population between&#13;
1971 and 1980 roughly half was accounted for by the natural increase of the&#13;
existing population and half by migrants and their offspring.  By comparison,&#13;
between 1961-1971 fully two-thirds of the growth was due to natural increase&#13;
alone (Table 4). Migration is largely an intra-provincial phenomenon; twice&#13;
as many migrants moved within provincial boundaries as across them. Even this&#13;
exaggerates the importance of inl:er-provincial migration because Jakarta is&#13;
classified as a province separate from its hinterland, West Java province. If&#13;
Jakarta-West Java migration were considered as "local" in nature, then the&#13;
overwhelming bulk of migration would be intra-provincial. Unfortunately, the&#13;
data on migration to urban areas are fragmentary.   Little information is&#13;
available on within province migration. For inter-provincial migration, data&#13;
are available on provinces of origin and of destination but the breakdown into&#13;
urban and rural desa is available only at the point of destination. Thus, it&#13;
is not possible to say whether migrants came from urban or rural areas, nor is&#13;
it possible to identify the number of migrants leaving urban areas, with the&#13;
exception  of Jakarta.    Within  these  constraints,  some  conclusions  about&#13;
migration behavior can be reached.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Table 4&#13;
Components of Urban Growth:&#13;
1961-1971, 1971-1980&#13;
1971-1980                1961-1971&#13;
million        %         million         %&#13;
Increase in Urban Population               9.63       100           6.76        100&#13;
Natural Increase of Existing Urban&#13;
Population a/                            4.63        48           4.59         68&#13;
Migration and "Urbanization"               5.00        48            2.17        32&#13;
Migration from Other Provincesb/         1.66       17            n.a.        n.a.&#13;
Migration from within the Province LI  2.92         30            n.a.        n.a.&#13;
Natural Increase of Migrants .d          0.42       5             n.a.        n.a.&#13;
ia Based on estimated fertility and mortality in urban areas.&#13;
S/ Derived from 1980 census data on gross movement to urban areas.&#13;
Assumed that level of migration from urban areas is half level&#13;
of in-migration.&#13;
sc Derived as residual.&#13;
d/  Derived from age-specific fertility and mortality behavior.&#13;
Source: Central Bureau of Statistics and Bank staff estimates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Permanent migration&#13;
1.       Permanent   inter-provincial   migration   is   relatively   rare   in&#13;
Indonesia.  In 1980, less than 7% of the population (roughly 10 million) were&#13;
living outside their province of birth. Of these, approximately half&#13;
had migrated to urban areas.  In Eact, 96% of those living in rural desa and&#13;
84% of those in urban desa were born in the province of residence. However,&#13;
though the amount of inter-provincial migration is low, it does appear to be&#13;
accelerating.    Of  the  5 million  urban  migrants  who  crossed  provincial&#13;
boundaries, fully half had arrived in the previous decade alone, and one-third&#13;
had settled in the previous five years.1/   The 1980 census also provides&#13;
evidence that inter-provincial migration is sturdy enough to withstand&#13;
administrative controls.  Jakarta attracted 48% of the total interprovincial&#13;
migrants to urban areas over the last decade, a proportion similar to that of&#13;
the previous decade (47%).  This occurred in spite of attempts to stem the&#13;
flow of migrants to the capital through the introduction of residence permits.&#13;
2.       Movements from rural to urban centers within provinces are the most&#13;
important source of migration for all areas excluding Jakarta, which is itself&#13;
a  province.    Thus,  for example,  the majority  of migrants  to  Surabaya,&#13;
Semarang, or BOTABEK (suburban Jakarta) come from their respective immediate&#13;
hinterlands.   This is probably generalizable to all urban areas, except for&#13;
some of the transmigration centers in Sumatra and Kalimantan.   Furthermore,&#13;
this source of migration is growing over time.The estimated 3 million rural-&#13;
jJ A definitive judgment on trends would, of course, require information on&#13;
the rate of "return" migration and on migrant death rates. The 1980&#13;
census does suggest that a small portion (12-15%) of inter-provincial&#13;
migrants again move across provincial boundaries within five years of the&#13;
original move. This suggests that the rate of inter-provincial migration&#13;
has, in fact, accelerated over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
to-urban within province migrants recorded between 1971 and 1980 exceed the&#13;
total number of migrants to urban areas for the preceding decade by 750,000.1/&#13;
Unrecorded migration&#13;
1.       The above discussion severely underestimates  the degree of rural-&#13;
urban mobility on Java.   Seasonal migration to urban areas is an increasing&#13;
phenomenon; it makes conventional measures of urbanization an imperfect proxy&#13;
for actual city growth.   Seasonal migrants include a varied group of indi-&#13;
viduals; some spend only a month or two in urban areas during slack periods in&#13;
agriculture, while others spend most of the year in urban areas and return to&#13;
their rural homes for only a month or two. The census fails to include these&#13;
migrants for a variety of reasons:, city "residents" must have lived in an&#13;
urban area six or more months to be counted as migrants and many seasonal&#13;
migrants fail to qualify under this rule; in addition, unregistered workers in&#13;
Jakarta tend to exclude themselves from that city's total population count;&#13;
finally, many seasonal migrants, even those spending most of the year in a&#13;
city, continue to record themselves as residents of their home villages.&#13;
2.       Studies of rural and urban labor markets in Java, made during the&#13;
last few years, emphasize that circular migration is high and growing&#13;
rapidly. These studies suggest that at least 25% of rural households on Java&#13;
have at least one family member working part-time in urban areas. This would&#13;
imply a total of 3.75 million people, equivalent to 16.5% of the measured&#13;
urban population and just over 50% of the measured 1980 urban employment on&#13;
Java. Given the circular migration, the average impact on urban areas is less&#13;
severe, but it is quite likely that approximately 15-20% of the urban work&#13;
j/ There are no direct data available on within-province migration. However,&#13;
given estimated rates of urban growth, natural increase and&#13;
interprovincial migration, intra-provincial migration can be estimated as&#13;
a residual.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
force consists of temporary migrants.   Finally, the fact that this form of&#13;
migration apparently has grown rapidly over the last decade requires urban&#13;
population and labor force growthl rates be revised upward.  Under plausible&#13;
assumptionsl/ one can assume, for example, that Java's urban population grew&#13;
at 4% and not 3% over the last decade, while its urban labor force growth&#13;
exceeded 6% per year, instead of the 4.7% annual rate implied by the census.&#13;
3.       To  understand  why  this  phenomenon  is  not  likely  to  fade  in&#13;
significance, one need only lookc at the changing sectoral composition of&#13;
employment in rural and urban areas (Table 5). Although agriculture provided&#13;
three-quarters of rural employment in 1971, it accounted for less than one-&#13;
tenth of the increase in rural employment over the 1971-1980 period., During&#13;
that decade, over six million children of rural households entered the labor&#13;
force, but only one in nine found regular employment in agriculture.   These&#13;
new entrants into the labor force are the key to the urbanization process in&#13;
Indonesia today. Rough estimatesj/ suggest that of the 5.4 million "surplus"&#13;
workers, about 3.1 million stayed in rural areas, with half entering the&#13;
service sector and half joining the rural industry ranks. A portion of these&#13;
became seasonal workers in the cities of Java.   The remaining 2.4 million&#13;
moved permanently to urban areas; of these, less about 400,000 found&#13;
employment in urban industry, whiLe the remainder joined the service workers.&#13;
Urban quality of life and rural-urban migration&#13;
1.       The ability of Indonesia's urban areas successfully to absorb these&#13;
inmigrants is noteworthy. More imnportant is the fact that across the cities,&#13;
1/ The calculations that follow assume that the percentage of rural&#13;
households with at least one family member working in the cities rose from&#13;
15% in 1971 to 25% in 1980.&#13;
g   It is assumed that the new labor force entrants from non-agricultural&#13;
households joined the same sectors as their parents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Table 5&#13;
Structure and Growth of FWployment in Urban and&#13;
Rural Areas 1971-1980&#13;
Rural                             Urban&#13;
% of     Increase    X of          % of      Increas_   X of&#13;
Total   1971-1980   Total           Ibtal   1971-1.980  Total&#13;
Enployment   ('000)   Increase    Enployment  ('000)  Increase&#13;
(1980)                             ('000)&#13;
Agriculture, Forestry, Fishing      67.3       458        8.5           9.3        231       6.2&#13;
Industry                            13.0      2265       41.8          28.8       1191      31.9&#13;
Manufacturirig                    7.9        1062       19.6          14.1       679       18.2&#13;
Construction and Utilities        2.6        670        12.4          5.9        252       6.7&#13;
Other IndListry A                 2.5        533        9.8           8.8        260       7.0&#13;
Services                            19.7      2690       49.7          61.9       2312      61.9&#13;
Trade, Restaurants, Hotels        10.3       1197       22.1          24.9       859       23.0&#13;
Other Services                    9.4        1493      27.6          37.0       1453      38.9&#13;
Total                              100.0       5408      100.0         100.0       3738     100.0&#13;
.S    Tranuport, Storage and Camuunicaticns.&#13;
Sources:  1980 data from 1980 Census, Series S, No. 2; seasonally adjusted to&#13;
mid-year. In addition, ezployment in unspecified sectors is allocated proportionally&#13;
to all sectors. 1971 data from 1971 census adjusted to make consistent with&#13;
definiticm in 1980 cnsus. Total enployment is from series C while the sectoral&#13;
breadcmn is from series D. lhe data are also adjusted to include estimates for E.&#13;
Tivr, and nral Irian Jaya (exdluded frcm 1971 census).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
incomes and access to publLc services are higher among all groups than ever&#13;
before. Table 6 summarizes trendEs in rural and urban poverty during the last&#13;
decade. Through reductions in the! proportion of individuals with consumption&#13;
below poverty lines is broadly evident across Indonesia, regardless of&#13;
location, the urban poverty figures are particularly heartening.  While half&#13;
of all urban residents could be considered destitute in 1970, when the economy&#13;
was just entering a period of recovery after decades of neglect, the&#13;
proportion had fallen to only one in five by 1980.  Across urban Indonesia,&#13;
incomes of the poorest 40% of the population rose at 4% per annum for the&#13;
1970-1980 decade. The migration t:o the cities also facilitated the growth in&#13;
incomes of the poorest rural dwellers, whose incomes rose at an annual real&#13;
rate of 2.4%/annum.I These data can be supplemented by other which suggest&#13;
rising urban expenditures on consumer durables and decreasing proportions of&#13;
urban household budgets being devoted to food purchases.&#13;
2.       Complementing these findings, it is clear that urban dwellers have&#13;
experienced  improved public service  coverage,  in spite of the fact  that&#13;
overall urban population expanded from 23 million to 33 million over the 1971-&#13;
1980 period. In urban and, to a lesser extent, rural areas, the opportunities&#13;
for primary education are becoming universal (Table 7). As a result,&#13;
j/ It is possible that urban poverty is underestimated by the surveys from&#13;
which these data were derived. Seasonal migrants and semi-urban residents&#13;
in the periphery cities are likely to be ignored. In addition to the&#13;
extent that the very poor are highly clustered in particular&#13;
neighborhoods, the sampling techniques used may misestimate the number of&#13;
poor residents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Table 6&#13;
Trends in Pbverty Incidence in Urban and Rural Areas: 1970-1980&#13;
Percent of people with consumption below the desigiated&#13;
poverty cut-off line)&#13;
Region               1970 A/    1976._/      1978 b/    1980 -/&#13;
JAVA&#13;
Urban                 56.3        33.8        27.5        20.9 d/&#13;
Rural                 67.0        62.7        65.0        52.9&#13;
Total                 65.0        57.3        57.9        46.9&#13;
OTHER IANDS&#13;
Urban                 40.8        28.0        21.2        17.3&#13;
Rural                 43.9        39.6        34.3        30.3&#13;
Total                 43.2        37.3        31.8        28.0&#13;
Urban                 50.7        31.5        25.2        19.7 i&#13;
Rural                 58.5        54.5        54.0        44.6&#13;
Total                 57.1        50.1        48.5        39.8&#13;
a/ January-April.&#13;
b/ Average for year.&#13;
Cl February.&#13;
d/ In this table the 1978 SUSENAS definition of urban areas used for 1980 data.&#13;
Scrce: Social EXpenditure Surveys (SUSEMAS).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
Table 7&#13;
Perceritage of School Age&#13;
Population Attending School a/ by Age Group&#13;
5-9 Years       10-14 Years       15-19 Years       20-24 Years&#13;
Urban  Rural    Urban  Rural    Urban  Rural    Urban  Rural&#13;
1971 Census        43.8   33.1       75.4   58.5       42.3   18.1       16.1     3.2&#13;
1980 oensus        69.2   55.3       139.5   77.0      53.4   25.7       15.4    3.4&#13;
al Includes school, university, technLcal colleges and full-tdie training courses.&#13;
Source: 1971 Population Census, Series D (March 1975).&#13;
1980 Population Census, Serieis B, No. 2 (February 1983).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
illiteracy among urban dwellers aged 15-29 has fallen to 5%-7%, compared to&#13;
28% for older inhabitants.   New rural inmigrants are making a particularly&#13;
impressive contribution to the gradual upgrading of the labor force:  fully&#13;
42% of those who migrated to urban centers in the four years preceding the&#13;
1980 census had more than a primary education.&#13;
3.       Good progress has also been made in providing safer drinking water to&#13;
urban areas. Between November 1980 and the end of the Third Five Year Plan,&#13;
REPELITA III  (March 1984),  it is estimated that the proportion of urban&#13;
dwellers with access to reasonably clean water (piped or pumped) 1/ rose from&#13;
35% to 47%; coverage was extended to an additional 3.8 million individuals in&#13;
less than four years.&#13;
4.       Through  the Kampung  Improvement  Program,  initiated  in 1969,  the&#13;
government has put into effect a far-reaching national program to upgrade the&#13;
informal, unplanned, and unserviced "urban villages" which house over half of&#13;
Indonesia's city population.   Initial upgrading in the largest  15 cities&#13;
brought basic services -- especially improved access, drainage, and water --&#13;
to large numbers, including 3 million people in Jakarta and 400,000 in&#13;
Surabaya. The program has subsequently been extended over the last 5 years to&#13;
cover nearly 15,000 hectares across more than 100 cities, affecting another&#13;
10-15% of the estimated kampung population.&#13;
5.       Much, of course, remains to be done.   The urban road network, for&#13;
example, is inadequate, with survey results for areas outside Jakarta&#13;
suggesting that half of the facilities are either seriously deficient in&#13;
physical quality or unable to carry projected traffic loads without&#13;
1/ It is reasonable to assume that piped water and most pumped water is clean&#13;
enough to drink directly after boiling. Pumped water includes handpumps&#13;
installed by individual households.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
extensive, repeated congestion. In Jakarta, 60% of the road system is subject&#13;
to serious congestion. Such problems are being exacerbated by the 15% average&#13;
annual  increase  in  the number  of motor  vehicles  across  Indonesia.    In&#13;
addition, coverage of such services as formal solid wates disposal, safe human&#13;
waste disposal, and even electric power, is still only one-third to one-half&#13;
the level required for universal availability in urban areas. This gap must&#13;
be addressed even as absolute urban population growth over the next two&#13;
decades far outstrips the 10 million added in the 1970s.&#13;
6.       Simultaneously, the public sector must face the serious problems of&#13;
the rural areas. While much public concern is focused on disparities in per&#13;
capita regional gross domestic product, the evidence suggests that more&#13;
attention should be paid to the enormous rural-urban gap (Table 8).  Urban&#13;
areas across all regions have per capita consumption levels which are at or&#13;
considerably above the overall national average.  Furthermore, and excluding&#13;
the Eastern Island and Irian Jaya  (which includes only 7.5% of the nation's&#13;
population), there are few differences in urban per capita consumption across&#13;
regions.   By contrast, per capita consumption in rural areas is uniformly&#13;
below that found in urban areas in the same region.   In Java alone, rural&#13;
capita consumption levels are half those found in urban areas.  As noted, the&#13;
incidence of poverty in rural areas is much higher than in urban areas.&#13;
7.       To address these rural problems, and to cope with the macroeconomic&#13;
constraints created by stagnating oil export revenues, the central government&#13;
must reassess the whole question of who pays for public servicese  There is a&#13;
prima facie case for shifting resource mobilization for urban public services&#13;
down to the relatively prosperous urban areas themselves, leaving the center&#13;
free to target its grants to the rural and urban poor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Table 8&#13;
Regional Variations in Per Capita Oitput and Coisunption, 1980&#13;
(Index: Indonesia = 100)&#13;
Per Capita            Per Capita        Per Capita Cbnsuption&#13;
Regional Product      Regional Product     Total  Rural  Urban&#13;
(incldinng mining)    (excluing mining)&#13;
Java                           76                   89              97      66      129&#13;
Sumatra                       167                  127             116     102     138&#13;
Kalirantan                    226                  172             129     118     139&#13;
Sulawesi                       75                  100              87      80     120&#13;
Eastern Islands&#13;
and Irian Jaya               83                   82              77      72      98&#13;
Indonesia                     100                  100             100      77     129&#13;
Source: Central Bureau of Statistics, Bank Staff Estiiates.,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
C. Urbanization and the Growth of Large Cities&#13;
Difficulties in defining urban growth by city size&#13;
1.       Assessing the importance and growth rate of different size grouping&#13;
of  cities  in  Indonesia  is  di:fficult.    Apart  from  the  54  kotamadya&#13;
(municipalities), and the towns designated to become kotamadva, cities and&#13;
towns in Indonesia have no administrative identity or boundaries. Some major&#13;
urban centers, with populations in excess of 150,000 are not kotamadya, while&#13;
some kotamadya are small urban centers.  The roughly six hundred cities that&#13;
are not kotamadya each consist of one or several desa.   For statistical&#13;
reporting purposes, these cities are non-existent entities, and can only be&#13;
identified by a laborious aggregation of desa-level data, using arbitrary,&#13;
unofficial "city" boundaries.  Comparisons over time are further complicated&#13;
by the growth of official cities beyond their recognized boundaries, by&#13;
periodic changes in the boundaries of some official cities, and by changing&#13;
definitions of urban desa.  The information that follows uses unofficial but&#13;
realistic boundaries for existLng kotamadva and accepts the boundaries&#13;
employed by sub-district (kecamatan) heads in responding to a 1978 Ministry of&#13;
Interior survey of urban conditions in their area. The resulting breakdown of&#13;
city size distribution, for 1980, and of selected growth rates by size&#13;
category, for 1961-1980, are reported in Table 9.&#13;
Trends in urban growth by city size&#13;
1.       As of 1980, Indonesia had thirty-six medium and large sized cities,&#13;
with populations in excess of 100,000, and an additional 293 with populations&#13;
of between 20,000 and 100,000.  As a group these 329 centers include all but&#13;
13% of the 33 million urban residents of Indonesia. Five urban centers have&#13;
populations in excess of one million and house 40% of the urban population;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Table 9&#13;
A: Size Distribution of Indonesia's Cities and Towns. 1980&#13;
Size of CLty                     Total Inhabitants                       Number of Cities&#13;
in Cities of this Size&#13;
(million)&#13;
Less than 20,000                         4.3                                   369&#13;
20,000 - 100,000                         6.8                                   293&#13;
100,000 - 500,000                       6.1                                     27&#13;
500,000 - 1 million                     2.5                                      4&#13;
MDre than 1 million                     13.1                                      5&#13;
Total                                   32.8                                    670&#13;
Source: (a) 1980 Census for population of kotamdya roughly adjusted for the&#13;
major cities of Jakarta, Bandung, Surabaya, and Surakarta to take&#13;
acomunt of growth of metropolitan areas outside kotamsdya boundaries.&#13;
(b)  1978 Dalan Nbgeri "Cwiat" survey updated to 1980, assuming 8% growth&#13;
of all cities between 1978 and 1980.&#13;
B: Growth Rates of KbtgMaya by Size&#13;
Size of City                                        Average Population Growth i&#13;
(Percent per Year&#13;
1961-1971          1971-1980&#13;
Large Gities (over 500,000)                             3.5                4.1&#13;
Medium Cities (100,000 - 500,000)                       2.4                3.8&#13;
Snall Cities and Towns (below 100,000)                 3.0                3.2&#13;
Total                                                   3.2                3.9&#13;
i To the extent that kotmadya boundaries have in general not been eapended in line with&#13;
peripheral urban growth, these growth figures probably underestimate the growth of the&#13;
Kotmd  a. Instead of the 3.9% overall annual groeth rate presented here, a figure&#13;
of, say, 4.2% is probably closer to the truth, implying a rate of about 3.7% p.a. for&#13;
rnnkotanudya.&#13;
Sotwoe: 1961, 1971, 1980 Population Census documents issued by Central Bureau of Statistics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
DKI Jakarta alone, with 6.4 million residents, accounts for one-fifth of the&#13;
urban population.   Thirty-one medium-sized  centers  (100,000 - 1 million)&#13;
contain roughly one quarter of the urban population, with the rest found&#13;
largely in the small cities..&#13;
2.       In the absence of time series data for all urban areas, growth rates&#13;
over time can be proxied by the performance of kotamadya in different size&#13;
categories.   Growth rates in the 1970s exceed those in the 1960s for all&#13;
groups, coincident with the upsurge in economic growth in the recent past.&#13;
Large and medium cities are growing at or about 4% per annum, while small&#13;
cities are expanding at a slower rate of 3.2%/annum.  Significantly, in light&#13;
of repeated concerns that Jakarta is expanding too rapidly, the rate of&#13;
population increase in the capital area over the same period is 3.9%/annum, a&#13;
rate which would have to be adjusted marginally upward to take account of the&#13;
above-average performance of the excluded BOTABEK suburban hinterland and to&#13;
include the impact of the growth in seasonal migration.&#13;
3.       Judged by the standards of other developing countries, the 1980 share&#13;
of large cities in the total urban population of Indonesia is quite low (Table&#13;
10). While Jakarta included 19% of the urban population, the 1980 proportion&#13;
for low income countries as a group was 28%, while for middle income countries&#13;
it was 29%.   Jakarta's share is also quite low by the standards of other&#13;
countries in the region.  In addition, these proportions can be supplemented&#13;
by data which point to the level of population dispersal across city sizes.&#13;
In Indonesia, for example, the nine largest centers account for less than half&#13;
of the urban population, a level which is rarely matched in the developing&#13;
world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Table 10&#13;
Indicators of Urban Concentration-Selected Large Countries 1/&#13;
Share of Largest City&#13;
in Urban Population, 1980&#13;
Indonesia                                           23%&#13;
Bangladesh                                          30%&#13;
Brazil                                              15%&#13;
Mexico                                              32%&#13;
Nigeria                                             17%&#13;
Pakistan                                            21%&#13;
Philippines                                         30%&#13;
Thailand                                            69%&#13;
Vietnam                                             21%&#13;
Low Income Countries                                28%&#13;
(excluding China and India)&#13;
Middle Income Countries                             29%&#13;
j/  National populations vary from approximately 50 million to 150&#13;
million.&#13;
Source: World Development Report 1983, Annex Table 22, New York, Oxford&#13;
University Press (for the World Bank), 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
4.       Given these data,  there  is only limited evidence that Indonesian&#13;
urban growth to data has been in any sense unbalanced. Certainly mere size is&#13;
no grounds  for present  concern about the larger cities,  since there are&#13;
innumerable cases of multi-mill.Lon population centers in the developing&#13;
world.    In addition Jakarta's  share of urban population and of national&#13;
population is not so high as to elicit serious debate on geopolitical&#13;
grounds. The key issues instead are whether cities in each size category are&#13;
being efficiently managed, whether local governments can compete for skilled&#13;
workers and employment by tailoring local taxes and expenditures to suit their&#13;
demands, and whether the macroeconomic environment is neutral with respect to&#13;
the spatial distribution of economic activity.   This, rather than concerns&#13;
about optimum geography, should be the guiding principle for policy-makers.&#13;
IV. Influencing Urban Development&#13;
A. So=! Basic Principles&#13;
Determinants of city size in the course of development&#13;
1.       Such a perspective can b,e derived from an examination of how cities&#13;
of different sizes typically evolve as the pace of urbanization increases in&#13;
any given country.   While the degree of urbanization appears to be closely&#13;
associated  with  the  level  of  economic  development,  the  link  between&#13;
urbanization per se and urban concentration is not obvious. As the proportion&#13;
of urban population increases, the population of most individual urban areas&#13;
tends to grow, but the number of urban areas grows faster and thus the share&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
of any large urban area also falls.1/  This does not exclude the possibility&#13;
that a higher proportion of the urban population is housed in an increasing&#13;
number  of  larger  urban  areas.       More  important  than  these  indirect&#13;
relationships between urbanization and urban concentration are two other&#13;
factors:   the impact of national production patterns and the policies that&#13;
affect the relative attractiveness of different cities as centers of&#13;
production and consumption.&#13;
The impact of national production patterns&#13;
2.       Cities and their size are shaped by the tradeable goods and services&#13;
they produce for export to other areas and, through such base activities, by&#13;
the demand they generate for purely local goods and services. The development&#13;
process that increases overall urbanization also reshapes the nature of&#13;
tradeable goods and services produced in a nation's urban centers. Cities do&#13;
not grow primarily because of any sharp increase in the proportion of workers&#13;
employed in industry.  Instead the composition of national industry activity&#13;
changes; in addition, larger fractions of an increasing service sector are&#13;
devoted to business services.  This has implications for what types of urban&#13;
centers are likely to grow relatively rapidly at each stage in a nation's&#13;
development. A stylized version of this process can be explored at this point&#13;
so as to make the validity of recommendations in later sections more apparent.&#13;
3.       Given the existing resource base and the friction encountered in&#13;
transportation and communication between regions of a country, early&#13;
urbanization is built around resource-based tradeable activity dispersed&#13;
across the economy.   These include mining and agroprocessing activities,&#13;
.j/ Given the relatively low level of urbanization in Indonesia, it is not&#13;
surprising that Jakarta's share of the urban population has not yet&#13;
declined.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
construction materials, beverages, textiles and handicrafts, and the repair&#13;
and production of simple structures and machines. In addition, ports involved&#13;
in interregional or international trade, and administrative and agrobusiness&#13;
service  centers  proliferate.    Activities which  suffer  no  impediments  to&#13;
location in and around major ports are attracted by large, accessible centers&#13;
and begin to define the specialiZed profile of these larger cities; a good&#13;
example is the concentration of industrial processing of most food products at&#13;
this  stage.    Major  ports  are aLlso ideally located when the process of&#13;
substitution of imported consumer goods gets underway; this is so because&#13;
firms engaged in such activities frequently wish to use imported inputs while&#13;
avoiding the high costs of internaL trasportation. When promoted artificially&#13;
by heavy tariff barriers in a country with limited infrastructure, import&#13;
substitution will provide a significant boost to the rate of growth of major&#13;
ports, while "taxing" the rural sector and the smaller centers dependent on&#13;
its health.   There follows a stage when the most rapidly growing tradeable&#13;
urban activities are associated with the emergence of engineering and&#13;
metallurgy subsectors. In response to the relatively underdeveloped nature of&#13;
transport, communications, skilled labor supplies, and information on markets&#13;
and technology, the initial expansion of these sectors favor larger port&#13;
centers where savings associated with economies of agglomeration are abundant&#13;
and where imported inputs are available.  Larger urban areas act as economic&#13;
supermarkets,  providing  a wide  variety  of  inputs,  services,  skills,  and&#13;
clients for firms; and consumer goods, services, and opportunities for workers&#13;
of varying skills.&#13;
4.       As  consumer and producer goods'  production processes become more&#13;
standardized; as cheaper, more frequent, and reliable interregional transport&#13;
becomes  available;  as  other  national  infrastructure  is  improved  with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
development; and as education investments boost the supply of higher skilled&#13;
workers; a redistribution of growth takes place favoring medium sized centers&#13;
of 100,000 to one million residents.   This occurs both because of the fact&#13;
that such smaller centers can begin to cash in on their inherently lower costs&#13;
of living and because standardized production and marketing is less sensitive&#13;
to the economies of agglomeration provided by very large cities. Now the most&#13;
efficient locations for the dynamic sectors tend to be own-industry&#13;
concentrations of particular lines of activity in smaller centers. At a lower&#13;
cost than possible in big agglomerations, clusters of similar firms can&#13;
attract most of the special services and inputs they require. The result is a&#13;
landscape dotted with medium-sized centers that specialize in particular&#13;
activities and trade extensively with the rest of the urban system. At this&#13;
point in the development process, large cities come to depend on two sources&#13;
for  continued  growth:    new,  unstandardized  high  technology  and business&#13;
services, which benefit from the economies of scope provided by big cities;&#13;
and, more generally,  the attraction of resource-independent or "footloose"&#13;
activities in search of large consumer markets somewhat protected by the&#13;
nature of final delivery transport costs.&#13;
5.       Note should be taken of two additional phenomenon associated with the&#13;
changing profile of national output.  Decentralized development emerges less&#13;
from the physical relocation of activity from one type of urban area to&#13;
another than through the differential rates of growth of local-based&#13;
entrepreneurs and of new investors. Except for supporting deconcentration in&#13;
and around large centers, at distances unlikely to exceed 50-100 kilometers,&#13;
big city factories and service establishments do not transmit their dynamism&#13;
to  medium-sized  centers  through  relocation  or  branching.    Furthermore,&#13;
decentralized industrialization is limited in the earlier stages of economic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
development by the inherent locational inflexibility of most industrial&#13;
activity.   As  long as infrastructure ;constraints prevail,  especially with&#13;
respect to interregional access, firms will locate in historically preeminent&#13;
centers unless a) their resource-based inputs are highly perishable or suffer&#13;
large weight losses in processing; b) their product is a processed resource&#13;
going directly to export markets; or c) their output is marketed locally at&#13;
prices which are competitive with production coming from more distant and&#13;
larger urban centers.  In this environment it is quite useless to try to lure&#13;
or force activity away from large cities with easy access to a major port.-&#13;
The relative attractiveness of cities and city size&#13;
1.       While the changing profile of national production in tradeable goods&#13;
and services provides a basis for the emergence of medium-sized centers, there&#13;
is a second factor at work det:ermining the speed of such decentralized&#13;
development: the rate at which city attributes can be reshaped to attract new&#13;
types of activity. Crucial to this process is the improvement of local public&#13;
services and of regional and interregional access.  On one level this appears&#13;
to be an intuitively obvious matter:  better infrastructure reduces the costs&#13;
of  doing  business,  under  reasonable  tax and user  charge  regimes.    Less&#13;
apparent is the important role these improvements play in attracting and&#13;
1/ The applicability of this framework to Indonesia is implicit in the&#13;
various regional economic development studies performed over the last&#13;
decade. Examples include the Java Regional Study of East Java (1975) and&#13;
of Central Java (1977) and the, Southern Coast Development Plan for East&#13;
Java (1980), all prepared by t:he Japan International Cooperation Agency.&#13;
Also worth citing are the Sumatra Regional Planning Study (1977) by Robert&#13;
Nathan Associates, and the Sulawesi Regional Development Study (1979) by&#13;
the Canadian International Development Agency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
retaining high skilled workers, managers and entrepreneurs.j/  Work in other&#13;
developed and developing countries has demonstrated that high and low skilled&#13;
labor are poor substitutes for one another.   This means emerging tradeable&#13;
goods and services are associated with fairly rigid skill mix requirements.&#13;
Decentralized growth as described above thus depends on mechanisms which&#13;
overcome the disamenities of emerging centers. While some amenities critical&#13;
to urban development in economically advanced countries -- like climate or&#13;
natural recreational assets -- are beyond the scope of public intervention,&#13;
many amenities are associated with the quantity and quality of public&#13;
services.   As the level of amenities rises in any area, businesses in that&#13;
location are able to offer lower compensation packages to skilled workers than&#13;
would otherwise be the case.   At some stage, these reductions may mean not&#13;
merely greater scope for expansion of individual firms but the differences&#13;
between the existence or absence of many lines of activity.&#13;
Limits to public intervention in shaping city size&#13;
1.       Before contemplating specific courses of action by the public sector,&#13;
the Indonesian government should consider the large-scale replicability of any&#13;
potential action.   At any one point in time, only a few central initiatives&#13;
will be possible, and those must husband financial and administrative&#13;
resources  to  accomodate  all  the  other  competing  demands  for  public&#13;
intervention. Unfortunately the very conditions of development which call for&#13;
remedial action limit the funds and the competent personnel available to&#13;
implement such initiatives. In addition, many of the processes of development&#13;
1/ Recent work on the United States and Brazil confirm this assertion. See&#13;
V. Henderson, Urban Development in Brazil, Urban Development Discussion&#13;
Paper, Water Supply and Urban Development Department, 1983; and V.&#13;
Henderson, "Population Composition of Cities: Restructuring the Tiebout&#13;
Model," Working Paper No. 82-16, Brown University, 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
-- especially those described above -- are so complex and subject to so many&#13;
interactions that omniscience is impossible. For these reasons the temptation&#13;
to assign an optimal size to a city in any location as a goal of public policy&#13;
must be resisted. Government could try to throttle the growth of cities above&#13;
a certain size by banning a whole range of activities or licensing any&#13;
attempts at local expansion but the effort would mire the bureaucracy and its&#13;
subjects in red tape and the consequences of success might be very harmful to&#13;
national economic growth. Or, public officials could take it upon themselves&#13;
to declare a city to be too small and then attempt to flood the area with all&#13;
manner of integrated packages of subsidies and technical assistance so as to&#13;
create producers of "missing" services, parts, and components "necessary" to&#13;
reach an optimal size. That approach too would fail because the effort would&#13;
involve a level of resources that would doom any effort at replicability.&#13;
Among the most notable of these types of initiatives is that of "creating"&#13;
regional balance by building greenfield new cities of particular sizes needed&#13;
to provide for missing city sizes.&#13;
2.       In the end the spatial configuration of population and employment is&#13;
the indirect outcome of other policies, which shape the behavior of millions&#13;
of economic actions across the urban landscape.  What is needed is a set of&#13;
efficient policies across the difEerent sectors where government operates, at&#13;
all levels.   As argued below, tlhese policies should ensure a macroeconomic&#13;
environment supportive of efficLent and broadbased growth, backed by an&#13;
orderly expansion of interregional investments in transportation, communi-&#13;
cations, power generation, and education.   Cities, taken as entities, should&#13;
be free to grow and develop with as little regulation and control as is&#13;
consistent  with  a  sober  assesesment  of  national  goals.    The  amenities&#13;
represented by local public serv:Lces should continue to be extended over an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
increasing number of medium and small cities, without neglecting the&#13;
absolutely  large needs  of major centers.   This will require that public&#13;
service consumers at all levels pay a greater share of the cost of providing&#13;
such services.&#13;
3.       Local communities must take on a larger share of planning, executing,&#13;
and maintaining such investments, freeing the center to use its scarce&#13;
resources to intervene in a more selective fashion to shape the future of&#13;
Indonesia. One necessary ingredient is the extension of municipal status to a&#13;
larger number of de facto cities.   A major effort should be undertaken to&#13;
designate as kotamadva all urban areas above a certain size, say 20,000.1/&#13;
While it is true that in Indonesia the goal of increasing the involvement of&#13;
local governments in local affairs will require considerable efforts to&#13;
upgrade the proficiency of local government officials, there is no plausible&#13;
alternative. The central government bureaucracy is already overextended; the&#13;
detailed intervention in local affairs practiced at present cannot be&#13;
continued without incurring increasingly heavy efficiency costs. The time for&#13;
devolution of authority is at hand.2/  The problems of an urban community of&#13;
over 20,000 residents are surely more than enough to occupy local authorities&#13;
without superimposing the additional responsibilities of governing surrounding&#13;
rural areas.   The problem is all the more acute when the functional urban&#13;
areas cut across county boundaries and involve different local bureaucracies&#13;
1/ A Ministry of Home Affairs 1978 survey of subdistrict (kecamaten)&#13;
administrators identified the de facto boundaries and population of all&#13;
cities and towns. From this one can estimate that there are roughly 329&#13;
urban centers with 20,000 or more residents. By contrast, there are only&#13;
54 kotamadva. Some unofficial cities have population in excess of&#13;
150,000, including Cilacap, Purwokerto, Banyuwangi, and Sorong.&#13;
g/ Merely transferring powers to existing kabupaten (county) authority is&#13;
inadequate. Counties usually contain large numbers of rural and urban&#13;
dwellers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
B. Influencing Industrial Location&#13;
Why focus on industrial location?&#13;
1.       One way to affect the spatial pattern of economic activity is to&#13;
guide the location of tradeable commodities toward or away from particular&#13;
types of urban areas. Tradeable commodities generate export activity to other&#13;
areas of Indonesia and the world at large.   This,  in turn,  creates new&#13;
opportunities for non-tradeable commodity production, as new sources of demand&#13;
are generated for these "local" goods and services. This strategy is sensible&#13;
even when tradeable commodities constitute a small percentage of economic&#13;
activity in an area.  This is because the production of tradeable commodities&#13;
have multiplier effects, supporting several non-tradeable jobs for every job&#13;
devoted to "export" activity.&#13;
2.       Another reason for having a spatial policy grounded in the support of&#13;
industrial activity is the alleged flexibility of industrial as opposed to&#13;
service sector jobs.  Industrial jobs are supposed to be more "footloose" and&#13;
less tied to a particular location precisely because of their "export"&#13;
orientation.   In addition,  they are less reliant on proximity to natural&#13;
resources than agricultural actLvity, with the exception of industrial&#13;
establishments operating with inputs that are highly perishable or that suffer&#13;
considerable weight loss during processing.   This flexibility should not be&#13;
exaggerated.   With exceptions, most private,  domestic industrial activity&#13;
originates in the area of residence of the founder-entrepreneur. The quality&#13;
of the market serviced from that location will determine the degree of&#13;
realized activity.  Public and foreign investors do have more flexibility but&#13;
they too are severely circumscribed by perceived locational constraints at the&#13;
time of the establishment  of the firm.   The capital-intensive nature of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
ventures based on the exploitation of natural resource endownments (e.g.&#13;
fertilizer, natural gas, tin, nickel, copper, bauxite, pulp and paper, basic&#13;
chemicals and forestry products) tends to attract much public sector&#13;
investment and a significant portion of foreign investors.   These sectors,&#13;
however, are likely to require locations near the source of raw materials.&#13;
Other foreign and public investments may feel constrained by the same factors&#13;
that limit most location decisions, especially where the level of overall&#13;
development  is  still  low.   The few locations  offering  the best  initial&#13;
opportunities for profit-making will receive the bulk of the investments.&#13;
Once these investments, made in the early stages of development, are in place,&#13;
these firms tend to act very conservatively with respect to new investment&#13;
locations.   Great modifications in the environment across space may elicit&#13;
limited  responses  from  existing  entrepreneurs.         They  tend  to  favor&#13;
deconcentration of activity away from the initial centers of activity, to&#13;
locations rarely more than 100 kilometers from the headquarters location. New&#13;
opportunities in locations that are not historically preeminent will tend to&#13;
be exploited by entrepreneurs spawned in those regions.   The dynamism of&#13;
preexisting large centers is thus rarely transferred to new areas of activity,&#13;
regardless of how their relative attractiveness has been improved.&#13;
3.       These considerations are useful in assessing the relative merits of&#13;
different policy initiatives.   These fall into three categories:   sectoral&#13;
policies, microspatial initiatives, and urban service strategies.   Sectoral&#13;
policies  can  be  divided  into  five  major  areas:         trade,  regulation,&#13;
interregional transportation, government productive investment, and industrial&#13;
finance. Among the microspatial initiatives worth considering are industrial&#13;
zones and parks. The introduction of improved levels of urban services across&#13;
all city sizes is discussed in a final section.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
The spatial bias of sectoral policie!s&#13;
1.       Public policies need not be explicitly spatial to have major impacts&#13;
on the location of industry.   Sectoral policies can favor the industrial&#13;
development of some locations over others.   Where these "implicit" spatial&#13;
policies go unrecognized, their impacts can create barriers to decentralized&#13;
industrial growth.   These implicit spatial policy effects are difficult to&#13;
measure with precision.   The data problems involved are substantial and the&#13;
eventual impact of implicit policieas depends on the way in which factors of&#13;
production (labor, capital, land) adjust to them.   Some conclusions can be&#13;
reached, however.&#13;
2.       Looking across induistrial subsectors and across cities, it is clear&#13;
that the input requirements of dlifferent production processes will vary&#13;
widely,  as will  the supplies  of inputs  at different locations.   In the&#13;
extreme, some inputs, such as easy access to an international port, to&#13;
government officials, or to agglomeration economies, may be available at only&#13;
a few, specific locations.   At the same time, individual subsectors will&#13;
differ  in  the  emphasis  they  pLace  on  such  variables.    Under  these&#13;
circumstances, promotion policies favoring subsectors which feel location-&#13;
bound will result in long-term subsidies for particular urban areas. If the&#13;
individual industrial policies are ill-advised on macroeconomic grounds, the&#13;
differential urban impact is one more reason to consider reforms.   If the&#13;
promotion policies are justified but the economic environment is such that&#13;
economic agents, in urban centers other than those benefitted, are denied&#13;
access to resources on reasonably equal terms with which to remedy locational&#13;
deficiencies, then the public sector should act quickly to remedy the&#13;
matter.  Only where subsector promotion policies are lustified, and where&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
there is no cost-effective way to diminish the number of severely location-&#13;
bound factors, can the government remain passive to the spatial consequences&#13;
of particular  promotion policies.   For,  ignoring implicit spatial policy&#13;
impacts amounts to neglecting the important fact that the selective&#13;
reinforcement of particular urban centers increases the attractiveness of such&#13;
places relative to the rest of the urban system.&#13;
The trade regime and city size effects&#13;
1.       Ideally, for a country that combines a relative abundance of labor&#13;
and a bountiful supply of natural resources, trade policies in Indonesia&#13;
should support the development of a mix of labor-intensive and resource-&#13;
dependent capital-intensive subsectors. These would include areas where there&#13;
are comparative  advantages  over  the short and medium-term.   In fact,  in&#13;
Indonesia trade policy to date has been inappropriate, and needs reformulating&#13;
on macroeconomic grounds.  Such changes as have been suggested in other Bank&#13;
documentsL/ would encourage greater efficiency in investment decisions, a&#13;
better use of resources, and greater competitiveness in international trade.&#13;
2.       Work performed in other developing countries2/ suggests that heavily&#13;
protected sectors tend to locate in large urban centers, where they can&#13;
satisfy their exceptional need for imports, sophisticated factors of&#13;
production, and for access to government officials.  This locational pattern-&#13;
implies that the industrial value-added of a major metropolis, under such a&#13;
21 Especially relevant are the recommendations made in Indonesia: Selected&#13;
Issues of Industrial Development and Trade Strategy, Report No. 3182-IND,&#13;
1981.&#13;
2/  A summary of recent research can be found in A. Hamer, Decentralized Urban&#13;
Development and Industrial Location Behavior, Water Supply and Urban&#13;
Development Department Report No. 24, the World Bank, May 1983. For&#13;
evidence in East Asia, see Philippines: Industrial Development Strategy&#13;
and Policies, The World Bank, May 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
trade  regime,  will  be boosted by  artificial  inducements.    Elsewhere,  in&#13;
smaller centers away from the more developed core of the country, this value-&#13;
added bonus will be much smaller or non-existent. As noted, this promotion of&#13;
subsectors in particular locations has long-term developmental effects, which&#13;
encourage additional growth over and above that recorded at any one point in&#13;
time.   The benefits of a change in policies would take time to become fully&#13;
effective.  As long as access to national and international markets is poor,&#13;
as long as infrastructure services are available umt..dLlly across cities for&#13;
business and skilled workers, and as long as central government favoritism is&#13;
worth seeking, there will be constraints on diversified development outside a&#13;
handful of centers.&#13;
3.       Nevertheless,  a  reorientation  of  promotional  programs,  providing&#13;
roughly equivalent, moderate protection across all sectors, would allow&#13;
production to restructure iltself spatially over the long-term. Both the Outer&#13;
Islands and the smaller centers iLn Java would benefit.  The subsectors that&#13;
would be most favored have fewer ties to big city economies of scale and would&#13;
thus have less reason to locate near Jakarta than the present mix of national&#13;
output.  These include the labor intensive industries, such as wood and cork&#13;
products, saw milling and wood processing, tanneries and leather finishing,&#13;
processed   tobacco,   kretek  cigarette  production,   and  certain  textile&#13;
products.   One should add certain capital-intensive, natural resource-based&#13;
industries which are located on Sumatra, Kalimantan, and the less developed&#13;
islands:  fertilizers, petroleum refinery products, natural gas, tin, nickel,&#13;
copper, and bauxite. In contrast, incentives would be cut back for protected&#13;
sectors that presently cluster in and around Jakarta.   These would include&#13;
motor vehicle assembly, pharmaceuticals, paints, plastic goods, electronics,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
ref rigerators and washing machines, electrical appliances, and textiles and&#13;
garments dependent on imported inputs.&#13;
4.       With the passage of time, economic development will be accompanied by&#13;
a loosening of general locational constraints and by a gradual expansion of&#13;
the more sophisticated sectors of production. At that point, more cities will&#13;
be capable of accommodating the demands of such advanced production, and&#13;
modernization will no longer coincide with growth in one or two centers.&#13;
Impact of transport sector inefficiencies on city size&#13;
1.       Improvements in the trade environment need to be accompanied by other&#13;
changes, including those involving interisland and international shipping.&#13;
Under present conditions the largest urban areas benefit disproportionately&#13;
from the relative isolation of Indonesia's cities.  Historically, sea-borne&#13;
trade has been saddled with high costs.   The inter-island general cargo&#13;
scheduled service operates at high nominal rates and suffered from inadequate&#13;
schedules and inefficient routing.   The composition, size, and age of the&#13;
ships has not been adequate to meet local traffic needs. Compounding this and&#13;
accounting for the bulk of the problem, port costs were inflated because of&#13;
difficulties created by inadequate infrastructure, lack of sufficient&#13;
equipment, cumbersome stevedoring arrangements, and inefficient management of&#13;
overall  operation.   Pilferage,  damage,  and unofficial payments added yet&#13;
another layer to shipping expenses; some estimates placed these additional&#13;
charges at 100-150 percent of normal shipping costs.  These problems reduced&#13;
not only potential domestic trade but exports as well.&#13;
2.       The central government  is well aware  of these problems  and has&#13;
prepared an action program to deal with issues in the maritime sector.  A&#13;
hierarchy of ports has been developed, four of which are to be gateway ports&#13;
(Tanjung Priok in Jakarta, Surabaya, Belawan in Medan, and Ujung Pandang).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
These gateway ports will be supported by six to eight regional trunk ports,&#13;
serviced in turn by feeder ports. This should generate economies of scale in&#13;
operation, and reduce investment requirements at each location. In addition,&#13;
the multiplicity of port charges for piloting, mooring, stowing, and for small&#13;
boats and harbor-master fees, are to be simplified or eliminated.   Other&#13;
charges, such as those for loading or for storage at port warehouses, are to&#13;
be reduced. To accelerate cargo-handling, responsibility for round-the-clock&#13;
loading and unloading operations will be transferred from shipping companies&#13;
to specialized firms. Port labor wages will be increased and stevedoring fees&#13;
will be reduced. To facilitate ioreign trade, foreign flag vessels will face&#13;
a reduction and simplification of procedures.   To ease inter-island goods&#13;
transport, various requirements are being removed, including inter-island&#13;
freight documentation, fiscal statements and tax-payment receipts. To improve&#13;
the handling of goods and documentation, such tasks can now be performed by&#13;
forwarding companies, importers, and exporters, as well as appointed clearing&#13;
agents.    Finally,  major  ports  have  been  placed  under  autonomous  Port&#13;
Administrators, who will coordinate and improve operations.&#13;
3.       According to detailed studies by consultants working on the Maritime&#13;
Sector Development Program, reductions in direct transport costs of up to 50X&#13;
can be expected from the introduction of these measures.   The reforms will&#13;
also cut indirect transport costs, especially unofficial payments, by reducing&#13;
and simplifying customs procedureis and regulations, thus cutting the number of&#13;
needed contacts between officials and customers; and removing the ambiguity&#13;
and  discretion  inherent  in  the  regulations  that  remain  in force.    In&#13;
particular, new measures introduced in 1985 will drastically reduce the&#13;
required import and export procedures to a bare minimum. Export goods are no&#13;
longer subject to regular customs inspection.   Imports will be inspected at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
the points of origin by Government-appointed surveyors, who will also certify&#13;
the type, quality, and volume of goods, the prices at points of origin, the&#13;
tariff category applicable, and the appropriate import tariffs.  Under these&#13;
procedures, Indonesian customs officials will limit themselves to ensuring&#13;
that this minimal documentation is completed, whereupon the cargo will be&#13;
promptly released.   Assessment of import duties and other taxes will now be&#13;
made by the importers and exporters themselves, (on the basis of surveyors'&#13;
certifications) and payments will be made directly to designated banks.&#13;
4.       One other area could benefit from significant improvements.   Most&#13;
ports have heavily congested access roads that cause delays in and limit the&#13;
growth  of  traffic.   Many medium-sized ports./ are poorly linked  to the&#13;
surrounding hinterland, severely restricting their growth potential and, with&#13;
it, the potential for decentralized growth.&#13;
The locational impact of pervasive micro regulation&#13;
1.       In the past, Indonesia's industry has suffered from widespread and&#13;
poorly administered microregulation of production units.   The government is&#13;
now making efforts  to simplify and streamline  these  controls.   Numerous&#13;
licenses and regulations have tended to hamper decentralized development, by&#13;
making physical proximity to central government officials a factor in the&#13;
location decisions of large and medium sized firms and by using administrative&#13;
measures to attract investments away from or towards particular locations.&#13;
2.       An important characteristic of the regulatory and licensing system&#13;
has been its explicit lack of uniformity, a feature it shared with the trade&#13;
regime previously described.    Specific licenses  may be required for new&#13;
investments and expansions, which vary by product and by region.  Firms may&#13;
1/ This issue is raised repeatedly the earlier-cited regional economic&#13;
development studies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
also be subject to licenses regulating domestic trading, domestic and sea&#13;
transportation export-import activities, as well as the more common permits&#13;
governing wages, personnel nationality, worker safety, and pollution.   This&#13;
regulatory system is divided into two main groups, known commonly as the BKPM&#13;
and the BRO sectors.&#13;
3.       The BKPM  category of firms covers  those which have applied  for&#13;
licenses  through  the  Investment  Coordinating  Board,  the  BKPM.          All&#13;
manufacturing firms with any degree of foreign equity and all purely domestic&#13;
operations applying for tariff exemptions and other investment incentives must&#13;
work  through  the BKPM.   Other domestic firms whose size exceeds certain&#13;
capital stock limitsl/ must register under the provisions of the Company&#13;
Regulations Ordinance  (BRO).   Remaining firms must simply register their&#13;
existence with local governments.&#13;
4.       The BKPM operates in accordance to an Investment Priority List (DSP),&#13;
which is revised periodically, and includes inputs from various government&#13;
institutions.   The DSP explicitly reflects attempts to balance productive&#13;
capacity and demand, both nationally and by region, while protecting or&#13;
promoting  market  shares  of  firms  owned  and  operated  by  economically&#13;
disadvantaged elements of the community.  On this basis, the BKPM negotiates&#13;
with affected firms through its Jakarta office, and proceeds through pre-&#13;
application, licensing, and project implementation. As noted, once a project&#13;
reaches the production phase, a series of licenses are needed which regulate&#13;
the freedom to operate on a day-to-day basis.&#13;
5.       Companies regulated under the BRO are subject to licensing for both&#13;
new investments and capacity expansion. Licenses are issued primarily by the&#13;
1/ Total investment of below 10 million rupiah, excluding the cottage sector,&#13;
with investments of up to 500,000 rupiah.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
Directorate General of Miscellaneous Industries of the Ministry of Industry in&#13;
Jakarta.   Until recently no formal DSP system was used for BRO firms; since&#13;
1982 the Department of Industry has introduced investment restrictions; once&#13;
again, the guiding principle behind such a system is the avoidance of&#13;
significant excess capacity in industrial subsectors by controlling the degree&#13;
of competition.   Historically,  BRO firms have found licenses for new or&#13;
expanded capacity easier to obtain  than BKPM firms.j]  Experience with the&#13;
new DSP list is too recent to allow a judgement to be made as to its&#13;
liability.  In general, however, it is safe to assume that the net effect of&#13;
the DSP lists is harmful to economic development, in general, and regional&#13;
development, in particular.  A case can be made that very large, private or&#13;
foreign investments with substantial impacts on their region should be&#13;
reviewed  by  the  central  government.    Beyond  that,  licensing  entagles&#13;
entrepreneurs in the web of an overworked central bureaucracY that can ill-&#13;
afford the time to make seasoned judgments on each new proposed investment&#13;
involving, say, 10 or more employees.   Furthermore, the record is clear in&#13;
demonstrating that overcapacity problems have not been avoided by regulation;&#13;
problems occur inspite of the necessaril- imperfect forecasts of central&#13;
planners. Given this fact, the government should reconsider the argument that&#13;
widespread. official barriers to entry in different subsectors and regions&#13;
does much more than reward firms for mastering hurdles that have nothing to do&#13;
with performance.&#13;
6.       From  the  viewpoint  of  spatial  policy  two  issues  are  crucial:&#13;
regulation is used to control the location of investments; and regulation is&#13;
.jf As in the case of the more highly regulated BKPM firms, additional permits&#13;
are needed; the number varies depending on the geographic scope of&#13;
operations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
employed in a manner that rewards firms for maintaining close day-to-day&#13;
contact with government officials at Jakarta and at major ports. The process&#13;
of getting an investment license from BKPM or BRO forces firms to negotiate&#13;
with  government  officials  in  Jakarta.    But  recent  simplifications  of&#13;
investment procedures will drastically reduce the time and number of steps&#13;
required to receive approval for new investments.  Furthermore, this process&#13;
does not affect location behavior directly, since, once a license is granted,&#13;
only limited contact with the offLcials who granted those initial permits is&#13;
required. The use of locational constraints in allocating investment licenses&#13;
is, however, a major problem at this stage.&#13;
7.       BKPM restrictions on location have expanded over time.  A reading of&#13;
the 1982/1983 list of investment priorities suggests that 250 of the 1877&#13;
industrial items cited are subject to location restrictions, while another 75&#13;
items  are  closed  to  all  new  investment.    The  most  common  locational&#13;
restriction requires that particuLar investments be outside a given province&#13;
or island, or in a location outside a set of listed provinces or islands.l/&#13;
As an example, seventeen items in metal products and metal building materials&#13;
are restricted to locations outside Jakarta; sixteen categories are barred&#13;
from the JABOTABEK region, including various types of electrical appliances,&#13;
metal  products.  and  metal  building  materials.    Seventy-four  items  are&#13;
forbidden from locating in Java, and run the gamut from printing for cans,&#13;
printers ink, and plastic bags, to steel bars for concrete, metal desks,&#13;
ceramics,  roofing  nails,  and  gymnastics  equipment.    Such  restrictions,&#13;
whatever their intent, distort efficient location behavior by restricting&#13;
access to plentiful supplies of labor, large nearby potential markets, well&#13;
1/ A less frequent restriction specifies a particular location where&#13;
investment must take place.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
developed infrastructure, and abundant natural or semiprocessed resources.&#13;
Among the undesirable consequences one can list the following:   decreased&#13;
overall investment by firms which refused to invest in mandated areas; more&#13;
capital-intensive investment by firms forced to locate in inappropriate&#13;
locations and faced with costlier non-Java labor; reduced export potential&#13;
given  higher  costs;  and  reduced  realization  of  economies  of  scale.&#13;
Furthermore, because the regulatory system covers enterprises that are&#13;
responsible for much of the manufacturing value added but little of the&#13;
sector's employment, the primary impact of regulation is likely to be on&#13;
industrial productivity rather than on the industrial employment the&#13;
regulators wish to disperse. The appropriate response to a perceived pattern&#13;
of choices which is viewed as too narrow is to modify the external conditions&#13;
that bring about that reaction.   Microeconomic regulation is more likely to&#13;
impose dead weight' losses on the society at large than to encourage&#13;
decentralized development.&#13;
8.       Location  controls  aside,  there  is  a second  set of bureaucratic&#13;
barriers which has encouraged large and medium-sized firms to locate in and&#13;
around Jakarta or near major international ports.   Day-to-day operations in&#13;
the context of a permit-ridden environment encouraged ad hoc compliance and&#13;
the active search for rulings granting exceptions on an individual basis. In&#13;
addition, accounting practices followed for tax purposes have historically&#13;
required the obtaining of official letters of clarification from taxation&#13;
officials; in the extreme, tax liabilities sometimes were explicitly&#13;
negotiated with tax assessors.jJ   Furthermore, import procedures have been&#13;
cumbersome; the process of actually moving goods through the ports was helped&#13;
immeasurably by thorough familiarity with officials at major ports. Firms had&#13;
jj  It is hoped that the new tax code reforms will eliminate the more&#13;
unfortunate consequences of the system in place.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
to cope with the delays and invisible payments required to obtain a&#13;
multiplicity of stamps and approvals as imports move through 29 major steps.&#13;
Like  taxes,  tariff  liabilities  on imports were  often subject  to ad hoc&#13;
decisions  by  customs  officials.    These  problems  should  now  be  greatly&#13;
reduced.   However, individual industrial enterprises can still petition the&#13;
Ministry of Industry for reduced tariffs on their imported inputs, and/or an&#13;
increase in the protection of their output from competing imports.  As with&#13;
any ad hoc, discretionary goverrunent action, this encourages close face-to-&#13;
face negotiation with respomsible government officials in Jakarta.&#13;
9.       Casual empiricism suggests that the firms most susceptible to this&#13;
centralizing effect are medium-sized enterprises that are too large and too&#13;
dependent on imports to avoid controls, and, simultaneously, too small to be&#13;
able to afford a subsidiary office: devoted principally to expediting decisions&#13;
from the central government.   FLrms in subsectors which are not resource-&#13;
dependent processors are likely to use their "footlooseness" to gravitate to&#13;
Jakarta or the other major port cities to seek relief from the bureaucracy.&#13;
Highly regulated environment are often criticized on macroeconomic grounds.&#13;
One can now argue that there are spatial impacts which tend to preserve&#13;
historic distributions of invest:ments across regions, in spite of rapid&#13;
increases in "hinterland" interregional and local infrastructure. and in&#13;
market potential.   This bias is not likely to be reversed by administrative&#13;
fiat  at  the  investment  licensing  stage.    What  is  needed  instead  is  a&#13;
dismantling of most controls on competition, restricting the close supervision&#13;
now accorded BKPM firms, in general, to a high priority category of firms&#13;
engaged in large-scale, capital-intensive industries which require massive&#13;
investments and which have vast impacts on the national and/or regional&#13;
economy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
Industrial estates as tools for regional dispersal&#13;
1.       The existing literature on estates is in general agreement about the&#13;
constraints inherent in using estates to promote regional dispersal.l/ The&#13;
first is that the opportunity cost of underutilized public investment in&#13;
industrial infrastructure is so high that countries like Indonesia cannot&#13;
afford to rely on "leading infrastructure" as an inducement for regional&#13;
industrial dispersal.   Second, estates facilitate development only when the&#13;
absence of industrial sites and services is the major factor inhibiting&#13;
industrial growth.   Therefore estates need to be focused on major regional&#13;
centers or in areas where they promote natural resource processing for export&#13;
in products which the country has a distinct competitive advantage, such as&#13;
forestry products.   It is not useful to use estates as a device to develop&#13;
"pioneer" locations that rank low in market potential.&#13;
2.       In Indonesia the best guide to strategic growth centers is found by&#13;
examining the locations of large and medium establishments2/ whose expansion&#13;
fueled the rapid growth of industrial production during the first three Five&#13;
Years Plans. Such establishments account for approximately 80% of industrial&#13;
value-added and 60% of wage employment.   They represent the cutting edge of&#13;
industrial development, "introducing and adapting new technologies into the&#13;
Indonesian economy and providing a reliable supply of good quality, relatively&#13;
cheap and simple producer and consumer goods that are needed by other&#13;
/ Country experience is reviewed in the cited reports on the Philippines and&#13;
on Malaysia. See also A. Uday Sekhar Industrial Location Policy: The&#13;
Indian Experience  op.cit.&#13;
g/ Includes all establishments with 20 or more employees.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
sectors"*./ Finally they are, historically, the most likely to be willing to&#13;
pay for the industrial amenities that an industrial park tends to include.-/&#13;
3.       Evidence from the 1980 survey of medium and large establishments&#13;
suggests that 80X of that employment is concentrated in 15 areas, which are&#13;
either free standing or continuous clusters of cities and their counties.&#13;
Included are the: zones in and around Medan, Palembang, Greater Jakarta,&#13;
Bandung,   Cirebon,   Semarang,   Tegal-Pekalongan,   Surakarta,   Pati-Kudus,&#13;
Yogyakarta, Kediri', Malang, Greater Surabaya, Madium, and Pontianak.&#13;
4.       The existing industrial estates in Indonesia generally follow the&#13;
suggested  guidelines..I    Approximately  1300  hectares  are  available  for&#13;
industrial uses in six industrial estates in Jakarta. Two hundred forty five&#13;
hectares are available in one estate in Surabaya. Additional estates exist in&#13;
Semarang, (800 hectares), Cilacap (240 hectares), Cilegon (area around&#13;
Krakatau Steel Complex), Medan (80 hectares), and Ujung Pandang (86&#13;
hectares).   Various estate areas are being planned, some in areas earlier&#13;
defined as industrial complexes (Cirebon, Surakarta) and others in areas where&#13;
industrialization is in iLts infancy (Lampung and Padang in West Sumatra;&#13;
Samarinda and Banjarmasin in Kitlimantan).    These estate plans should  be&#13;
reviewed  carefully  to  determine  if  the  coordinated  availability  of&#13;
infrastructure is the key constraint whose removal will bring accelerated&#13;
development;   if  the  answer  is  negative  their  development  should  be&#13;
discouraged.&#13;
/  P. McCawley, "Industrialization in Indonesia:  Developments and&#13;
Prospects," Development Studies Centre, The Australian National&#13;
University, Occasional Paper No. 13, 1979.&#13;
2/ Small and cottage establishments in Indonesia almost never utilize&#13;
electric power, for example.&#13;
3/ Information based on data contained in Indonesia: Executive's Fact Book&#13;
1982/1983, The Chase Manhattan Bank, Jakarta, 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
5.       Another, less ambitious approach to easing industrial development  is&#13;
the so-called industrial zone.l/  In these areas infrastructure is provided&#13;
either jointly by major project owners and the government or by one of these&#13;
parties alone; no effort, is made, however, to prepare serviced lots as would&#13;
be the case in an estate. These zones are being developed as part of a build-&#13;
up of the basic chemical industries, rubber and cellulose, and organic and&#13;
inorganic chemicals.  They take advantage of the fact that these industries&#13;
attract large-scale investors whose infrastructure requirements can be&#13;
utilized most efficiently when shared with other users. Zones being developed&#13;
at this stage include areas in Aceh (Lhok Nga, Lhok Seumawe), West Sumatera&#13;
(Padang), South Sumatera (Palembang), West Java (Cibinong, Tangerang, Cilegon,&#13;
Bekasi, Cikampek), Central Java (Cilacap), East Java (Gresik. Madura,&#13;
Probolinggo), East Kalimantan (Bontang, Sesayap), South Sulawesi (Gowa,&#13;
Tonasa), and East Nusatenggara (Kupang).   Most of these areas can coincide&#13;
with identified centers of industry.   In other cases (including those yet&#13;
being planned) the locations are not traditional ones and their development&#13;
should be reviewed carefully before proceeding.&#13;
6.       New enthusiasm exists for developing export processing zones (EPZ)&#13;
and  export  estates.2/      EPZ  are  industrial  estates  that  operate  as&#13;
extraterritorial entities where inputs and outputs can enter and be exported&#13;
overseas without the payment of excises and duties, and with minimum customs&#13;
and regulatory procedures. Often the enterprises operate under rules (such as&#13;
100% foreign ownership or special tax treatment) otherwise inadmissable in the&#13;
1/  Information on areas drawn from Indonesia:  Executive Fact Book, op. cit.&#13;
2/ Shannon Free Airport Development Co., Limited, Export Processing Zone and&#13;
Export Estate Masterplan for the Republic of Indonesia, draft final&#13;
report, 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
nation's territory.   As such, the EPZ aim to attract internationally mobile&#13;
firms that face many competing offers; their existence is a frank admission&#13;
that the national industrial promotion and control procedures inhibit&#13;
initiative. Export estates would be geared at firms exporting half or more of&#13;
their output while selling the rest domestically.   Establishments in these&#13;
estates would not enjoy duty-free entry of materials. but they would be&#13;
subject to simplified customs and regulatory procedures, have nearby support&#13;
services,and participate, wiLth other exporters, in export certificate schemes&#13;
that provide rebates for duties of imported inputs incorporated into exported&#13;
goods. Often, such estates contain bonded warehouses where goods originating&#13;
within or outside the country may be stored without paying any taxes until&#13;
they are released.   To date,  Indonesia has an EPZ,  in the port area of&#13;
Jakarta,  as well as a bonded waLrehouse in the same area.   While export&#13;
processing zones would be useful as components of an outward-looking&#13;
industrialization strategy, their locations would tend to reward a handful of&#13;
preeminent   port   areas   with   excellent   transport   and   communications&#13;
facilities. Only in those cases where an export estate can be used to process&#13;
bulky and difficult-to-transport natural resources, such as forestry products,&#13;
would  non-traditional  locations  be  considered.    While  they  have  other&#13;
advantages, these estates have only a minor role to play in the future&#13;
dispersal of industry.&#13;
The role of public industrial investment in regional development&#13;
1.       If one combines wholly owned and joint venture public industrial&#13;
establishments, their total work force includes 143,000 jobs (1980) equivalent&#13;
to 15% of all medium and large enterprise employment (Table 11)  It can be&#13;
argued that these establishments have a special role to play in pioneering the&#13;
development of non-traditional locations. To the extent these firms are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
Table 11&#13;
Distribution of Employment&#13;
in Public and Private MediumrLarge Establishments by Province&#13;
(1980)&#13;
Publicl/             Private&#13;
D.I. Aceh                             1.1%                     i&#13;
Sumatera Utara                        0.8%                  4.4%&#13;
Sumatera Barat                        1.5%                  0.5%&#13;
Jambi                                  -                    0.6%&#13;
Sumatera Selatan                      3.9%                  1.7%&#13;
Bengkulu                               -                     -&#13;
Lampung                               0.2%                  0.4%&#13;
DKI Jakarta                           8.9%                  18.8%&#13;
Jawa Barat                           17.4%                  20.1%&#13;
Jawa Tengah                          18.2%                  19.1%&#13;
D.I. Jogyakarta                       2.4%                  1.5%&#13;
Jawa Timur                           40.7%                  26.2%&#13;
Bali                                  0.5%                  0.6%&#13;
Nusa Tenggara Barat                   0.1%                  0.2%&#13;
Nusa Tenggara Timur                                         0.2%&#13;
Kalimantan Barat                      0.1%                  1.7%&#13;
K.alimantan Tengah                    0.1%                  0.8%&#13;
Kalimantan Selatan                    0.1%                  0.9%&#13;
Kalimantan Timur                      0.2%                  0.6%&#13;
Sulawesi Utara                        0.1%                  0.2%&#13;
Sulawesi Tengah                        -                     -&#13;
Sulawesi Selatan                      2.5%                  0.4%&#13;
Sulawesi Tenggara                      -                    0.6%&#13;
Maluku                                 -                     -&#13;
Irian Jaya                            0.7%                   -&#13;
Total                               100.0%                100.0%&#13;
Total Jobs                          143,153              827,375&#13;
jj  Includes private-public joint ventures, with 20,223 jobs.  By&#13;
comparison fully-owned public enterprises have 122,930 employees.&#13;
2/ Percentages rounded off.&#13;
Source: Central Bureau of Statistics&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
resource-oriented,  the proposition is acceptable.   But if this is taken to&#13;
mean that public ventures should accept reductions in profits to promote&#13;
regional development then it is at more debatable proposition and, beyond a&#13;
limited point. an unacceptable one.   Already many public enterprises are&#13;
neither profitable nor well-managed.   To expect a further departure from&#13;
commercial goals is unrealistic. I'he constraints on the national treasury are&#13;
such that these ventures should be sited in existing areas of development&#13;
except where the resource orientat:Lon of the project justifies an alternative&#13;
location.   It does,  however,  make sense to coordinate the development of&#13;
priority industrial zones and estates with the emerging locations of major&#13;
employers, public and private, espiecially where non-traditional locations are&#13;
concerned.   This is likely to help minimize the danger of a dissipation of&#13;
effort and scale across an excessively large number of sites.&#13;
Regional development and the rationing of industrial finance&#13;
1.       Previous  studiesl/  have  provided  a  number  of  stylized  facts&#13;
concerning industrial finance in Indonesia, and these are relevant to any&#13;
regional dispersal strategy.   Undier the system rules which prevailed until&#13;
June 1983, public enterprises, jOint venture/foreign companies, and firms&#13;
controlled by non-ethnic Indonesians had relatively easy access to either&#13;
private or public industrial finance.   To meet their working capital and&#13;
investment fund requirements, they could rely upon at least some of the&#13;
following  major  sources:    state,  private,  and  foreign commercial  banks;&#13;
foreign-offshore  sources;  and the domestic informal market.   This system&#13;
operated best in the short-term funds market, though larger customers were&#13;
1/ A good summary is found Ln "Financing Policies for Industrial&#13;
Development", in Annex A of Indonesia: Selected Issues of Industrial&#13;
Development and Trade StrategS, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
granted "rollover" privileges that lengthened these credits.  Domestic long-&#13;
term lending was dependent on government guidelines and backed by infusions of&#13;
cheap liquidity credits. The system wrapped financial institutions in a maze&#13;
of restrictions weakening competition for lendable resources and dulling the&#13;
incentives to lend to the economically most attractive projects. As a result,&#13;
a key role was played by demands for customer credentials and by burdensome&#13;
collateral requirements, both to the detriment of loan evaluation.&#13;
2.       Under the new system, the banking community is supposed to operate in&#13;
a more competitive environment and rely heavily on deregulated interest rates&#13;
to mobilize and disburse funds; the role of liquidity credits for priority&#13;
sectors is to be sharply contracted. One interesting question is how the new&#13;
system differs from the old in the treatment of establishments outside Jakarta&#13;
and its West Java environs. Little is known about the regional differences in&#13;
the supply of short-and long-term credit, but some plausible assumptions can&#13;
be made.   Large scale customers,  regardless of location, are equally well&#13;
treated under either regime, having the collateral and connections needed to&#13;
obtain loans domestically and overseas.   The same should be true for the&#13;
larger of the medium-sized establishments, whose ranks include plants with 20&#13;
to  100  employees.    Smaller  establishments,  especially  the  small-scale&#13;
enterprises have always had limited access to the organized financial system,&#13;
with the result that their level of indebtedness is relatively low and their&#13;
accumulation of liquid assets is relatively high.   This is especially so&#13;
outside the Jakarta region, where branch banks have limited authority for&#13;
credit requests above a certain low threshold. Since smaller firms are less&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
concentrated across regions than larger establishments,l/ it follows that&#13;
regional development has been affected.   The new,  deregulated system,  by&#13;
modifying incentives to mobilize resources, may increase lendable funds across&#13;
all regions. However, in an environment of centralized banking accustomed to&#13;
short-term lending and procedures favoring high-visibility firms, the removal&#13;
of government support for longer-term lending could worsen the situation of&#13;
smaller firms  outside  the capital area.   Borrowable funds are likely  to&#13;
gravitate to prime customers as determined by the central bank offices.&#13;
3.       Among the many proposals that might be made to improve the results of&#13;
the system now in place, there are two which merit attention as encouraging&#13;
decentralized activity.   First,  rates for short- and longer-term loans for&#13;
smaller size firms could be allowed to rise sharply, to provide a commercially&#13;
acceptable spread over cost-of-funds.   This will encourage an expansion in&#13;
lending and reward financLal institutions that invest in loan evaluation,&#13;
supervision,  and  collection.   IPart of  the  annual  allocation  of  central&#13;
government funds for developmental purposes could then be used to reduced&#13;
eligible borrower costs.   In addition, the central government, through Bank&#13;
Indonesia, could work aggresively to upgrade the role of regional development&#13;
banks.  These banks should be capable of capturing a higher percent of gross&#13;
assets of the financial system (now 1%) and of diversifying away from its&#13;
concentration on working capital and local treasury functions, and into&#13;
longer-term loans.   To the extent that liquidity credits are preserved for&#13;
smaller-scale establishmenits, the GOI should consider channeling a higher&#13;
percentage to these entities, which place high priority on local development.&#13;
1/ For a review of the evidence see Indonesia: Selected Issues in Spatial&#13;
Development, O2. cit.; and Indonesia: Selected Issues of Industrial&#13;
Development and Trade Strategy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_.             -62-&#13;
C. Management and Finance of Urban Services&#13;
The financial implications of the urban goals of the Fourth Five Year Plan&#13;
(REPELITA IV)&#13;
1.       Indonesia has  made  progress  in extending  public  services,  in a&#13;
systematic way, from large to medium and then small cities. The record of the&#13;
last decade, reviewed above, makes the extent of this effort very clear. The&#13;
achievements during the third Five Year Plan, REPELITA III (1979-1984)&#13;
involved an average annual expenditure by all levels of government of 285&#13;
billion rupiahs (1982 prices)e-/ The government may be preparing to make even&#13;
greater commitments over the remainder of the decade, with potential spending,&#13;
as proposed by line agencies, averaging 529 billion rupiah per annum (1982&#13;
prices). This goal is consistent with decentralization objectives in that it&#13;
attempts to equip medium and small centers across Indonesia with the level of&#13;
amenities required to attract and retain higher skilled workers.  This, in&#13;
turn, will help promote the diversificatica of the economic base of such&#13;
cities, while meeting the basic needs objectives of population as a whole.&#13;
2.       These goals, though laudable, must share the arena with others.  The&#13;
improvement in service levels should not provide an indirect mechanism to&#13;
subsidize any one city or set of cities. Local government taxation and cost&#13;
recovery levels are low by international standards, and further provision of&#13;
subsidized urban servies would exacerbate urban-rural inequalities.   Urban&#13;
dwellers are, in material terms, much better off than their rural counter-&#13;
parts, and thus in a position to contribute more to the costs of meeting such&#13;
services.   Finally,  increasing the contribution of urban governments would&#13;
jj The approximate exchange rate was $1=Rp.630 (1979-March, 1983) and&#13;
$1Rp.970 (after April, 1983).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
help to release central resources for rural development.  This requires that&#13;
investments and recurring operating costs of urban services be paid for by the&#13;
users, to a degree consistent with equity concerns. The same conclusions are&#13;
forcibly reached by an examination of macroeconomic conditions and their&#13;
effects on short and mediumrterm government revenues.  The Fourth Five Year&#13;
Plan, REPELITA IV, will be implemented during a time of scarce foreign&#13;
exchange  resources  and  modest  domestic  economic  growth.    The  central&#13;
government can no longer expect to rely, as before, on large-scale programs of&#13;
grants to finance activities of local interest. Finally as more programs are&#13;
extended from a few dozen centers to hundreds of medium and small cities, the&#13;
administration capacity of the central government and its sectoral line&#13;
agencies in Jakarta will be fully, occupied with dealing with selected issues&#13;
that  transcend  local  boundaries;  by  necessity,  local  planning,  local&#13;
execution, and local operation and. maintenance of public service projects will&#13;
have  to become  the norm.   Increased local funding would heighten local&#13;
interest in the efficient management of its affairs.&#13;
3.       Local governments, at the provincial level and below, operate in the&#13;
shadow of the central governmenit.   As Table 12 makes clear, even in the&#13;
financing of urban services, the central government is the dominant force. In&#13;
the recent past this preeminent role has been built upon oil revenues which,&#13;
by 1980,  accounted for over half of all central resources.   The targets&#13;
outlined in Table 13 suggest that the transition from REPELITA III to REPELITA&#13;
IV could involve a potential increase in urban service investment expenditures&#13;
equivalent to an annual rate of real growth of 13%. These rates of growth far&#13;
exceed the expected growth rates3 for central government revenues.   After&#13;
growing for several years at an average real rate of over 142 per annum, the&#13;
central government development budget for the period 1981-1989 is estimated to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
Table 12&#13;
Annual Pattern of Spending for Selected Urban Services&#13;
(percent distribution)&#13;
Central     Local Govt       Item       Percent of&#13;
Govt        and Cost        Total    Overall Total&#13;
Recovery a/                 Spending&#13;
Water Supply         95              5            100          29&#13;
Sanitation and&#13;
Drainage           52            48            100           13&#13;
Kampung Improv.      66             34            100           7&#13;
Urban Roads and&#13;
Traffic Manag.    33              67           100           23&#13;
Public Transport    96               4           100            6&#13;
Others               10             90            100          12&#13;
Total                64             36            100         100&#13;
a/  Includes local borrowing from central government, and local spending&#13;
of central government, and local spending of central INPRES grants.&#13;
Source: Average 1979/80 expenditures in current prices, as reported in&#13;
Indonesia:  Urban Services Sector Report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
Table 13&#13;
Pbtential Financing ReciuiremEnts for Investnent in Urban Services in the 1980s i&#13;
Average Annual      Potential Average          Equivalent Annual&#13;
Expenditure a/    Amnal Expenditure i        Rate of Real Growth&#13;
1979/80-1982/83       1984/85-1988/89                 (Z)&#13;
- Rp. billions, constant 1982 prices -&#13;
Water Supply                       82                     220                       19&#13;
Drainage and Sanitation            38                      96                      13&#13;
Yampung Inproveient                19                      38                      13&#13;
Urban Roads (includirg&#13;
toll roads)                      62                     100                      12&#13;
Traffic Mnagement                   5                      10                      17&#13;
Public Trawsport                   45                     125                      15&#13;
Others b/                          32                      42                       4&#13;
Total                             285                     529                      13&#13;
a/ Development expenditure by all levels of goverment. Therefore, these totals do not&#13;
correspond to central government budget figures. Routine expenditures uthold be over&#13;
and above these levels.&#13;
b/ Assuied to grow in line with urban population growth.&#13;
Sobrce: Indaiesia: Urban Services Sector Report No.4800-IND, April, 1984. Derived from&#13;
government and World Bank staff estimates. In some cases, e.g. wter supply,&#13;
financial requirements are derived from physical targets (coverage) endorsed&#13;
by the central government.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
increase at an average real rate of only 5.5% per year.  So drastic has been&#13;
the combined effect of reduced oil production and lowered oil prices, that&#13;
even this low growth rate will require major central government initiatives in&#13;
new domestic taxation and in reduced subsidization.&#13;
4.       To  a degree,  it may be appropriate that a higher proportion of&#13;
central government development be allocated to urban services. A case can be&#13;
made, for example, that central investment in some services is very low by&#13;
international standards; in addition, one can argue that public funds in the&#13;
difficult  years  ahead  should  be  redirected  toward  less  import-intensive&#13;
activities, including public service investments. But clearly this shift can&#13;
only be limited in scope. Under REPELITA III central government expenditures&#13;
for urban service development accounted for 3.2% of central development&#13;
funds.   Under the new conditions of fiscal stringency, it would probably be&#13;
difficult to shift that share upward by more than one or two percentage&#13;
points.    If  one  assumes  the  share increases  to 4.5%,  then the central&#13;
government's role in funding potential urban services investments could fall&#13;
from two-thirds to one-half of the proposed average annual total. This would&#13;
leave an important gap that would either be filled by local government or by&#13;
loan funds accompanied by increased cost recovery.&#13;
5.       One waV to get the maximum impact out of these central resources is&#13;
to make use of matching grant formulas.j]  These grant formulas should allow&#13;
central revenues to be funnelled to localities that show initiative in taxing&#13;
their local resources.   Because this would reward tax effort, it would be&#13;
1/ The rapid expansion of INPRES grants for local projects, which often&#13;
require local donation of land; the creation and strengthening of&#13;
provincial planning authorities; and the introduction of catalyst funding&#13;
for kampung improvement and solid waste; are all important building blocks&#13;
for such an approach which are already in place.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
consistent with equity concerns as. well as developmental ones; disadvantaged&#13;
locations could be rewarded for the! ability to mobilize resources from a small&#13;
base, even if the absolute amounts collected were small. To meet legitimate&#13;
central government goals of ensuring that all localities meet certain minimum&#13;
service standards over time, the grant formulas could reward poorer areas more&#13;
heavily than wealthier areas, at any given tax effort level.&#13;
6.       The government should also consider other reforms in the management&#13;
of intergovernmental relations.   Historically,  Indonesia's need to promote&#13;
development  after  Independence,  while  relying  on  relatively  few  skilled&#13;
administrators, led to a relatively centralized approach to decision-making.&#13;
However, this was accompanied by a proliferation of specialized agencies&#13;
operating with different administrative and financial procedures, so than&#13;
centralization did not result in a coherent or coordinated approach to dealing&#13;
with local governments.&#13;
Challenges facing public administration&#13;
1.       Indonesia is divided into 26 provinces for administrative purposes.&#13;
These are further divided into 301 second level units, which are known as&#13;
regencies (kabupaten) or municipalities (kotamadva). Broadly speaking the 247&#13;
regencies are rural in character, while the 54 municipalities are pre-&#13;
dominantly urban.   There are sepaLrate regional administrations at both the&#13;
provincial and second level of government.   Both have their own legislative&#13;
and administrative arms.   The legislative arms consist mainly of locally&#13;
elected representatives.   The executive arms are headed by nominees of the&#13;
legislature who are appointed by the central government Ministry of Home&#13;
Affairs. These regional executive arms are in turn organized into a number of&#13;
local departments (the Linas) which parallel central departments in a number&#13;
of areas, but are responsible for the provision of local government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
services.  Thus most medium and large size cities have their own legislative&#13;
and administrative bodies.&#13;
2.       In keeping with the philosophy of Indonesian government, provincial&#13;
governors and the chief executive of municipalities and regencies exercise a&#13;
dual role.   They are responsible for the administration of local government&#13;
and are also the local representatives of the President. In this latter role,&#13;
they are responsible for generally overseeing the work of the central&#13;
government and for coordinating the effects of central and regional government&#13;
agencies. This means that the central government departments operating at the&#13;
regional level are subject to the authority of the regional heads of&#13;
government  ministries.      Although  this  structure  in  theory  permits  a&#13;
distinction to be made between central government and regional government&#13;
activities, in practical terms the division of responsibilities between&#13;
central and regional government is far from clear cut.  The arrangement has&#13;
two drawbacks. Firstly, the overlapping of central and local government means&#13;
that it is difficult to avoid some duplication of effort, inconsistencies and&#13;
omissions. Secondly, the process of coordination itself can often prove time&#13;
consuming and inefficient and it necessarily places considerable demands on&#13;
the   limited   administrative   resources   of  both  central  and  regional&#13;
governments.   Thirdly, this duplication in responsibility is compounded by&#13;
fragmentation of funding from central government.  Grants for local services&#13;
and administration are provided from several central ministries.   They are&#13;
usually not related to each other or to local priorities and do not constitute&#13;
incentives to local governments to plan for efficient and rational services,&#13;
or to improve local revenues.   In all, the system leads to a great deal of&#13;
confusion, and supresses potential initiative at the local level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
3.       Central government departments play a dominant role in the provision&#13;
of public services in Indonesia.   Responsibility for technical aspects of&#13;
urban services is vested largely in various departments of the Ministry of&#13;
Public  Works  (Pekeriaan  Umun,  P.U.).    However,  the  Ministry  of  Health&#13;
(Kesehatan) is involved in monitoring and improving the quality of water&#13;
supplies and sanitation facilities; it also constructs small-scale schemes for&#13;
water  supply  and human waste  disposal  in rural  areas.   The Ministry of&#13;
Communications (Perhubungan) is responsible for traffic control and public&#13;
transport.  And street liglhting is provided through the National Electricity&#13;
Corporation (PLN).   Almost  all these  central government departments have&#13;
established a set of branch offices at the provincial level and frequently&#13;
central government sub-branches have been set up in individual cities and&#13;
towns.   These local office are responsible for implementing the development&#13;
programs of the central departments, as well as administering ongoing&#13;
programs. There are strong vertical relationships within specific departments&#13;
which means that coordination between different departments tends to be weak,&#13;
especially at the local level.   This is a particularly serious problem for&#13;
urban services, because of the need to pursue an integrated approach to the&#13;
development of densely-populated settlements.&#13;
4.       As a country of  such great size and diversity,  Indonesia faces&#13;
difficult choices in trying to strike a balance in the degree of the&#13;
centralization of the publlc administration.  It is undoubtedly true that as&#13;
Indonesia develops, more responsibility for the implementation of local&#13;
services must be devolved to lower levels.   However, it is important that&#13;
central guidance on policy and resource allocation decisions be broadly&#13;
maintained.    Among  the  steps  ithat are  consistent  with  both  goals,  the&#13;
following can be mentioned. Across all sectoral programs, efforts should be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
made to reduce and even eliminate overlapping responsibilities for investments&#13;
at the local level between central line agencies and local authorities.&#13;
Furthermore, each sectoral agency should consolidate the multiplicity of&#13;
existing financing sources for local programs. into a single funding channel to&#13;
be disbursed through one allocation mechanism. In addition, local authorities&#13;
should create consolidated development budgets which would bring together&#13;
financing and physical planning information for all projects, thus providing a&#13;
means for monitoring, evaluation and considering future initiatives. Finally,&#13;
long-term planning should include multi-year forward, rolling programs which&#13;
would be prepared to cover all spending for all agencies.  Once approved by&#13;
the central government, then all annual budgets for local spending, regardless&#13;
of source, would be prepared within the guidelines. All these measures would&#13;
benefit   immeasurably   from   the   speeded-up   creation   of   autonomous&#13;
municipalities. as recommended earlier in this report.l/&#13;
5.       Given these new goals, it is clear that serious attention needs to be&#13;
devoted to training needs and manpower dzvelopment at the local level,&#13;
accompanied by systematic,  though selective, delegation of authority.   As&#13;
background to this exercise, three general points need to be kept in mind.&#13;
First, technical and managerial staff at the central level are less&#13;
constrained by skill deficiencies than by size. As the REPELITA IV investment&#13;
programs are put in place, the chief role of the central agencies must&#13;
increasingly be to advise and guide local implementation rather than to design&#13;
and approve contracts. Second, the technical staff at the kotamadva/kabupaten&#13;
level is adequate in size, but deficient in skills. These staff must be the&#13;
Ij In Jakarta and Surabaya, three-year rolling plans are being introduced.&#13;
This system will be extended to other large cities over the next two&#13;
years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
primary target for skill upgrading programs.  Finally, the local planning and&#13;
coordinating units will face expanded responsibilities over time; though their&#13;
skill mix and size are adequate at present, their training needs should be&#13;
periodically revaluated as devolution continues.&#13;
6.       Recognizing  these  factors,  the  central  government  has  already&#13;
embarked on a major expansion of training and manpower development programs.&#13;
The Ministries of Public Works and Home Affairs both have large programs, and&#13;
the Ministries of Finance, Commutnications and Planning also have organized&#13;
courses. The challenge now is to expand these to cover neglected sectors (eg.&#13;
sanitation programs), while strengthening the content of such courses.   In&#13;
addition, these initiatives must be accompanied by visible progress in&#13;
delegation of authority..  With the support from provincial agencies,  the&#13;
second level governments already have a substantial technical capacity to&#13;
design and supervise smaller projects. There is greater variability in local&#13;
managerial capacity.  Even here, however, it is possible to devolve certain&#13;
routine duties to local. administrators while assigning even greater&#13;
responsibilities to stronger provinces and, in turn, to stronger local&#13;
governments.   This approach will permit central and provincial manpower to&#13;
concentrate their energies on strategic planning and on assisting the weakest&#13;
local agencies.&#13;
Alternative sources to finance urban improvements&#13;
1.       There are three alternative sources of finance that could and should&#13;
increase  in  relative  importance:    local  taxation,  borrowing  by  local&#13;
authorities, and cost recovery.   The fact that these alternatives are being&#13;
considered now, because of the financial constraints being faced by the&#13;
central  government,  should  not  obscure  the  value  of  more  decentralized&#13;
financing and planning under any scenario.   Local economic development is a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
function, in part, of increased local government initiative and of the&#13;
ability, at the local level, to facilitate the expansion of the economic base&#13;
through timely, coordinated, and strategic interventions in the provision of&#13;
public services.&#13;
2.       A careful program of devolving of planning and financing authority to&#13;
the local level would also help the public sector to solve the critical&#13;
problems of choosing which areas will receive what investments. The central&#13;
government does not have the knowledge necessary to identify priorities and&#13;
execute programs in a coordinated fashion across hundreds of urban areas.&#13;
Instead, with appropriate arrangements dealing with technical assistance and&#13;
financial aid, localities should be encouraged to rely more heavily on local&#13;
taxes and user charges, and compete among each other for borrowable funds.&#13;
This will tend to minimize extravagance and planned investments that fail to&#13;
conform to local conditions and local economic prospects.&#13;
3.       At present local government  spending is based on central grants,&#13;
assigned taxes and royalties levied by the center for local use, direct&#13;
revenues, and loans. While the distribution of revenue sources varies across&#13;
local governments, the largest contribution, roughly 65 percent, comes from&#13;
central  grants.    Local  tax revenues  and charges  account  for another  25&#13;
percent, while borrowings and assigned revenues (mostly the property tax) each&#13;
add another 5 percent.  Non-grant local revenues have the greatest potential&#13;
for expansion over the medium-term, especially since they only amount to an&#13;
average of about 2.5% of personal per capita income across Indonesia.  This&#13;
low average level of effort is associated with remarkable variations in&#13;
provincial and district level revenue-raising per capita.  Excluding obvious&#13;
cases explained away by the extraordinary high or low level of local economic&#13;
activity, most variation is hard to understand.  It suggests that one way to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
encourage greater local taxation i,s to develop incentive systems that link an&#13;
increasing proportion of central grants or loans to local tax effort. One can&#13;
demonstrate quite easily that there is considerable scope for such improved&#13;
local performance.&#13;
4.       All the recommendations that follow assume increased local ability to&#13;
set tax rates and charges for existing. taxes; and to introduce&#13;
new taxes.   In addition it is assumed that incentives will be in place to&#13;
identify relevant taxpayers, to correctly assess their individual liabilities,&#13;
and to efficiently collect the assessments.   At present the incentives for&#13;
local effort are limited, as are the options for tax reform.   All possible&#13;
taxes and charges are specified in national legislation. These laws describe&#13;
the nature of taxes and charges; while rates are specified by local&#13;
legislation. Local tax legislation is subject to approval by the Ministry of&#13;
Home Affairs, in consultation with the Ministry of Finance in cases where a&#13;
tax is being introduced for the first time. Local service charges need to be&#13;
approved by the provincial governors.   In practice, most important tax and&#13;
charge rates are standardized nationally and are, effectively, national taxes,&#13;
locally collected and assigned to i:he regions.&#13;
5.       Using data on the kotarnadva as examples  of urban local  revenue&#13;
sources, one finds that 45% of average receipts are composed of taxes, with&#13;
the remainder being charges.  Of the taxes raised, on average half are Ipeda&#13;
land and  property  taxes.l/   Th4s  Ipeda property  tax is  the most widely&#13;
collected direct tax in Indonesia, and its rolls include 3.5 million&#13;
registered  urban  payers.      Unfortunately  this  type  of  tax  is  poorly&#13;
j/ Since DKI Jakarta is a province, the proportions there are different;&#13;
taxes account for the bulk (83%) of per capita revenues. Property tax&#13;
yields, in turn, are equal to only 9% of local tax receipts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
exploited.   As a result  this  type of  taxation, which provides  the most&#13;
important source of revenue (20-50 percent) for most developed cities in the&#13;
world, accounts for only 5 or 10 percent of total resources for Indonesia's&#13;
cities. There are various reasons for the poor performance of the property&#13;
tax. First, the tax rates are very low, both absolutely and relative to rates&#13;
prevailing in other countries.  The tax is assessed at a modest 0.18% of the&#13;
market value of commercial land and 0.09% for residential land; buildings are&#13;
taxed at even lower rates.   Second, the tax rolls are incomplete; a severe&#13;
problem of underregistration appears to exist.   Third,  there are a large&#13;
number of low assessments the collection of which is not cost-effective.&#13;
Fourth, there is evidence that higher-value urban properties are deliberately&#13;
underassessed. Finally, local authorities have only a limited role to play in&#13;
generating what are essentially central revenues assigned to localities. As a&#13;
result, the tax effort varies greatly by city, for reasons that are unclear.&#13;
In addition, the growth per capita in urban Ipeda yields are below recent GDP&#13;
growth rates, when the opposite should be the case.&#13;
6.       There seem to be considerable room for reform.  The setting of rates,&#13;
the determination of assessments, and the collection of taxes should be made&#13;
local in character. The central government should confine itself to creating&#13;
incentives for higher tax effort, and to providing technical assistance to&#13;
improve the quality and coverage of the local property cadasters.   Under a&#13;
reformed system, tax rates should be raised; the scope for increased tax&#13;
effort is illustrated by the fact that many cities in developing countries&#13;
have tax levels of 1% of market value.  A ten-fold increase in the property&#13;
tax efforts would be a major undertaking, but one which could be achieved over&#13;
a ten-year period. During that period, tax rates could be raised, assessments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
could be brought closer in line with market valuations, and collection efforts&#13;
could be redirected to more affluent taxpayers. By the early 1990s, receipts&#13;
from the urban property tax could finance about a third of all new investments&#13;
in urban services, and could, almost singlehandedly, compensate for any&#13;
declining relative contribution from the central government.&#13;
7.       Other sources of local revenues include vehicle taxes, particularly&#13;
the annual license fees and vehicle transfer fees collected by provinces.&#13;
There are, in addition, poorly exploited provincial gasoline sales surcharges&#13;
and kotamadya parking charges.  The license and transfer fees contribute 80%&#13;
of provincial tax receipts; they are particularly important to DKI Jakarta&#13;
where 19% of all registrations and 70% of all vehicle transfers occur.i1&#13;
Reliance on this source of revenues serves a dual purpose of diversifying the&#13;
local tax base, earmarking funds for local road improvements, and discouraging&#13;
the rate of increase in vehicular traffic.   The yield from taxes could be&#13;
increased by dropping current exemptions applicable to government vehicles and&#13;
by raising fees for trucks and buses to levels comparable to those applicable&#13;
to cars.&#13;
8.       At present the provincial surcharge on gasoline yields no more than&#13;
3% of provincial tax receipts and amounts to only Rp. 1.05 per liter.  The&#13;
same rationale presented above could be used to justify higher surcharges;&#13;
raising the rate to Rp 10 per liter would yield enough revenues to finance the&#13;
increase in the projected annual urban road investments for REPELITA IV.&#13;
Together with use of a portion of the license and transfer fees, this would&#13;
allow all road investment programs to be easily financed.&#13;
jj The license fee is equivalent to 2-3% of market value. The transfer tax&#13;
is 10% of assessed value at the time of the first transfer and 5%&#13;
thereafter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
9.       Other fiscal measures could also be contemplated which would help to&#13;
discourage vehicle use, especially in congested city centers. This course of&#13;
action would be consistent with the philosophy that it is easier to encourage&#13;
public transportation by penalizing private vehicle use than it is to provide&#13;
purely positive incentives for public vehicle use.  One simple measure would&#13;
be to raise parking charges in larger cities. Currently these vary from Rp.&#13;
50 to Rp. 200 (Jakarta only) and are invariant with length of stay.  These&#13;
rates, levied as they are on the affluent, could surely be raised to conform&#13;
with charges typical in other international centers, eventually reaching&#13;
levels of Rp 1000 - Rp 2000.  This would provide an attractive substitute for&#13;
the more difficult scheme of licensing vehicular access to city centers on a&#13;
daily, monthly, or yearly basis.&#13;
10.      Less  is  known  about  other  existing  taxes  at  the  local  level,&#13;
especially the reasons for marked variations in receipts per head and in&#13;
growth rates over time. These taxes are assessed primarily on entertainment,&#13;
recreation, and economic activity. It would be useful to undertake a set of&#13;
studies on the procedures involved in assessing, collecting, and accounting&#13;
for local revenues with a view to improving the efficiency of assessments and&#13;
collections, and of reducing the costs of collections.   In some cases some&#13;
taxes might prove to yield negative net revenues and be candidates for-&#13;
elimination (e.g. taxes on alcoholic drinks, radios, dogs, and non-motorized&#13;
vehicles).   In other cases, new taxes and/or improved collection procedures&#13;
would suggest themselves.   While many uncertainties exist concerning these&#13;
miscellaneous  taxes,  the  associated  receipts  per  capita  are  low  by&#13;
international standards. Special consideration should be given to unexploited&#13;
sources of revenues, such as that which could be derived from extending&#13;
present kotamadya/ kabupaten tax on economic activity from restaurants and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
hotels to retailing and manufacturing.   Even at a modest rate, such a tax&#13;
could yield revenues sufficient to finance a significant fraction of new urban&#13;
services investments over the nexi: decade.&#13;
Local borrowing as a tool&#13;
1.       In  global  terms,  borrowing  by  local  governments  is  presently&#13;
unimportant. It accounts for only 1%-1.5% of local government spending, and&#13;
2%-3% of kotamadya/kabupaten spending, in particular.   Most loans, however,&#13;
are directed at municipal servicies, and may account for up to 20% of water&#13;
supply and kampung improvement activities.   Such loans do not yet play an&#13;
appropriate role as a rationing device. Most funds are borrowed at subsidized&#13;
or zero interest rates and appear to be made without much relation to local&#13;
resource  availability.    It  would  seem  desirable  that  wealthier  local&#13;
communities be required to finance a higher proportion of their development&#13;
from loans rather than grants, foLlowing the example of Jakarta and Bandung in&#13;
water supply investments.&#13;
2.       Lending to local authorities has important advantages over grant&#13;
finance.  First, it encourages imcreased cost recovery for services, as well&#13;
as greater tax effort, especiaLly when debt service payments are linked&#13;
directly to charges for the services improved by the proceeds of the loan.&#13;
Second, the use of loans will help reduce the burden on the central government&#13;
budget, by generating new sources of funding in the form of debt repayment&#13;
with interest and in the form of bank loans.&#13;
3.       Third,  lending  to  local  authorities  provides  an  indication  of&#13;
relative needs and priorities at the local level, and thus encourages better&#13;
resource allocation.   Finally,  It provides an incentive to control costs,&#13;
improve   accounting   standards,   and  maintain  and  operate   the  system&#13;
efficiently.   In fact, consideraltion should be given to creating a municipal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
loan board or of expanding the role of existing regional development banks in&#13;
this  field.   While initially  the bulk of funds would come from central&#13;
government  loans,  grants,  and  foreign  aid  allocations,  in  the  long-run&#13;
attractive yields might draw new sources of funds, including institutional&#13;
savers (pension funds, insurance companies).   With this type of system in&#13;
place, and realistic cost recovery policies, it will be possible to encourage&#13;
urban service improvements across the hierarchy of cities, without fearing&#13;
that funds made available to large cities will consist of subsidies provided&#13;
at the expense of deserving populations in other centers.&#13;
4.       Ideally, such a financial institution should be linked to the entire&#13;
planning and budgeting process. Three-year rolling expenditure plans could be&#13;
prepared at the local level.   These could be appraised at the provincial&#13;
level.   At the central level, a municipal development board consisting of&#13;
relevant Directors General from the Ministries of Home Affairs, Finance,&#13;
Public Works, Communications and Planning, could review the proposals and&#13;
authorize financial packages consisting of grants and foreign or domestic&#13;
loans. The loan components could be channelled through holding banks (perhaps&#13;
the regional development banks) to the local authorities.  A revolving fund&#13;
would accumulate at the central level, permitting government grants to be&#13;
reduced gradually.   This approach would take time to implement.   In the&#13;
interim, preparatory work is needed to a) develop policies and procedures for&#13;
allocating such grants and loans; b) provide guidelines to local governments&#13;
for developing multi-year investment and revenue programs; c) define the&#13;
criteria and methods used by provinces in appraisal; and d) provide a&#13;
framework to coordinate external aid for urban development.&#13;
5.       With few exceptions there is virtually no direct cost recovery for&#13;
capital investments in urban services in Indonesia.   The general policy has&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
been that recurrent expenditures should be recovered through user charges,&#13;
where possible, but that the initial capital investment should be provided to&#13;
the users in the form of grants. This policy has been based on arguments of&#13;
affordability, fairness, and externalities.  The poor are deemed incapable of&#13;
paying their way; charging poorer communities for improvements earlier&#13;
provided freely to more affluent neighborhoods is considered unfair; finally,&#13;
some services are assumed to benefit the community at large and, it is argued,&#13;
should be paid by all.  Unfortunately, in the present environment of fiscal&#13;
stringency, communities face the choice between highly subsidized services for&#13;
the few and widespread services based on greater levels of cost recovery.&#13;
This can be illustrated for particular sectors.&#13;
6.       At present, the policy of the central government with respect to&#13;
water  tariffs  is  that  they  should  cover  operation,  maintenance  and&#13;
depreciation. Within those guidelines, local water authorities have widely&#13;
different tariff structures and installation charges, some of which encourage&#13;
waste (e.g. when unit charges are constant irrespective of consumption), some&#13;
of which discourage access to the system (e.g. when house connections exceed&#13;
the actual  costs of installation by a wide margin).   The government is&#13;
reviewing the degree of regressivity existing in such charges, with the intent&#13;
of improving the progressivity of the tariffs and of decreasing the practice&#13;
of excessive connection fees.  Bwt the principal issue is how to finance the&#13;
potential increase in urban water supply investments from Rp. 82 billion to&#13;
Rp. 220 billion per year (1982 prices).  The present policy of user charges,&#13;
when applied to forcasted investment programs, will recover less than 20X of&#13;
annual investments by 1991.   By contrast a policy based on replacing grants&#13;
with 20 year, 4% per annum loans would generate, in debt repayments alone,&#13;
enough to finance nearly 40X of annual investments by 1991. The effects would&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 80 -&#13;
not be immediately apparent in the first few years, but it would be necessary&#13;
to implement the system changes immediately in order to reap large advantages&#13;
within a decade.&#13;
7.       Planned carefully,  such improved cost recovery should not unduly&#13;
burden the poor.  Evidence from other countries indicates that consumers are&#13;
willing to pay about 4% for their income for clean water on a regular basis,&#13;
and up to roughly 7% when they are paying off debts for connection&#13;
charges.l/ Low income households are already paying much higher rates when&#13;
they rely on water sold by street vendors. These proportions can be preserved&#13;
for urban consumers with house connections.   An appropriate pricing policy&#13;
also needs to be developed for the poorest 20% of the population that cannot&#13;
afford house connection. A judicious combination of grants for the provision&#13;
of standpipes and tariffs paid by a small group of families responsible for&#13;
individual units would allow recovery of operating costs and of some capital&#13;
expenses.&#13;
8.       The same general principles can be applied to sanitation services.&#13;
Under an existing pit latrine program, beneficiaries contribute to investment&#13;
costs through the provision of labor, while maintaining the latrines after&#13;
construction. This arrangement is not excessively burdensome to the central&#13;
government and allows mass replication from a financial standpoint. Another&#13;
program provides for the construction of communal wash-house/toilets.  These&#13;
are presently financed by a grant except for the land, which must be&#13;
donated.  Operational cost recovery is not an issue, but the present method of&#13;
pricing has drawbacks,  being based on per use fees collected by a paid&#13;
1/  Survey undertaken in selected East Java cities in preparation for the&#13;
World Bank's First East Java Water Supply Project suggest these guidelines&#13;
could be met in Indonesia while covering all operation and maintenance&#13;
costs plus depreciation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
collector/cleaner; this limits use and increases expenses. If such facilities&#13;
were assigned to small groups of families, who would pay a fixed monthly fee&#13;
for unlimited use, it would be possible to recover most capital costs in&#13;
addition to operating and maintenance expenses.  For example, for roughly Rp&#13;
2000 per family per month, 5-7 families can pay for water charges, pay for&#13;
annual emptying of the pit, and repay an interest free loan in four years.&#13;
Only the most destitute households would require other solutions, such as&#13;
larger, multiple-unit communal facilities.&#13;
9.       Sewerage system coverage is very limited in Indonesia; however, the&#13;
upcoming Jakarta sewerage project provides an opportunity to consider cost&#13;
recovery options.   The government is committed to recovering operation and&#13;
maintenance costs plus depreciation or debt service, whichever is greater.&#13;
The plan envisions substantial cross-subsidization, with non-residential&#13;
customers paying considerably more than residential ones; this will keep&#13;
average household charge to about Rp. 800 per month (1982 prices), equivalent&#13;
to 1.4% of the household income at the 50th percentile. Such a program is not&#13;
replicable where non-residential. properties are proportionately fewer.&#13;
Extensive cost recovery, which is indisputably necessary where large-scale&#13;
extensions are contemplated, may limit sewerage system investment to pockets&#13;
of larger cities.&#13;
10.      Responsibility for house-ito-house collection of garbage lies with the&#13;
neighborhood association. Charges are levied and are designed to cover labor&#13;
costs of collection and transport to the transfer station or to the local dump&#13;
site. On the average Rp5O - Rp200 is collected per month from each household&#13;
benefitted from the system.  Capital investments, such as transfer stations,&#13;
and even hand-carts for house-to-house collections, have usually been provided&#13;
as a grant from the central and local governments. A major expansion of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
solid waste program is required and the government is encouraging neighborhood&#13;
solutions to hold down costs.  A gradual increase in charges could make an&#13;
important contribution to refinancing the expanded program.   In addition,&#13;
there is scope for increased cross-subsidy from high income residential and&#13;
commercial (markets) areas to poorer areas.&#13;
11.      An   additional   area   for   close   scrutiny   involves   public&#13;
transportation.   Bus fares are controlled for each type of service,  and&#13;
government owned systems in Jakarta and eight other large cities are&#13;
explicitly subsidized.   Publically-owned companies receive Rp. 30 billion a&#13;
year in capital grants, as well as subsidies to cover annual operating losses&#13;
and to purchase diesel fuel at below international market prices.jj This is&#13;
unfortunate from various perspectives.   There is little evidence that such&#13;
subsidies limit the diversion of passengers to private vehicles. Furthermore&#13;
the controlled fares system has done widespread damage to private bus&#13;
companies and obstructed the development of higher-quality, higher priced&#13;
microbus service; this is likely to increase congestion by reducing public&#13;
transit service.  Finally there is little reason to subsidize a "basic need"&#13;
for middle and lower income individuals who happen to live in a handful of&#13;
large cities.   It is precisely by placing the burdens of congestion on all&#13;
users of roads -- private and public vehicles -- that a balance is reached-&#13;
between the attractive features of large centers and its costs. The doubling&#13;
of fares on large city buses in January 1983 was an important contribution to&#13;
resolving the issues in this field, and points the way to full cost recovery&#13;
at some point in the future.&#13;
1/ Public transport is also assisted by generous access to subsidized credit&#13;
through the state banking system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
12.      There is one final candidate for cost recovery through user charges:&#13;
neighborhood improvements whose benefits cannot be allocated to each household&#13;
by  charging specific tariffs.   'Included among  these are  road surfacing,&#13;
drainage, footpaths, and water mains.  These investments do have one feature&#13;
that makes cost recovery possible:   they tend to increase land prices in the&#13;
adjoining areas.   In many parts of the world betterment or "valorization"&#13;
taxes are able to recoup most or all of the investment costs.&#13;
13.      Jakarta has the only example of a betterment tax in Indonesia.  It is&#13;
being used in particular areas of the city on an experimental basis; it allows&#13;
for the recovery up to 60X of tlhe cost of new or improved infrastructure&#13;
through the use of a special tax.   The recoverable cost is divided between&#13;
beneficiaries according to the length of road frontage, with properties&#13;
directly fronting onto the road paying more than those only indirectly&#13;
connected.   The tax is calculated and announced before  improvements  are&#13;
made;  it must be paid within threse years after completion of the work, with&#13;
financial penalties for late payment and denial of building permits until the&#13;
tax is paid.   The tax has been fairly successful in recovering costs where&#13;
applied.   The special tax could be extended both within Jakarta and other&#13;
cities.  If project standards are kept moderate, construction takes place in&#13;
stages, and the major burden is placed on middle and upper income&#13;
beneficiaries, the taxes should be affordable to all income groups even if the&#13;
proportion of cost recovery is increased substantially above 60%. Before the&#13;
program is extended it is important to review problems connected with&#13;
unregistered property owners and lack of data on land values.   Aggressive&#13;
action in this regard would have the welcome side-effect of improving property&#13;
tax collections, in general.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 84 -&#13;
14.      Existing legislation in Jakarta also allows for the collection of an&#13;
"excess" profits tax tied to land value increases in excess of 300% over the&#13;
first two years following the completion of public works; it would be&#13;
collected on change of ownership, and would thus be relatively painless.&#13;
Though this section of the special tax was never put into effect, it would&#13;
represent a useful way to recover additional costs while preventing&#13;
disproportionate windfalls gains from accruing to landowners.   It deserves&#13;
closer scrutiny.   It would be useful to consider, for example, lowering the&#13;
threshold to 200% and increasing the period of application.  In addition, to&#13;
avoid double taxation for betterment, landowners should be permitted to deduct&#13;
taxes already paid from the excess value surcharge.&#13;
Financing urban housing services&#13;
1.       Once resources are found to provide lower income groups with basic&#13;
services, there is a need to consider shelter issues. Residential investment&#13;
is tied to infrastructure investment and together they play a major role in&#13;
determining the level of internal efficiency and productivity of cities.&#13;
Looking across cities, one can argue that an important ingredient of national&#13;
spatial policy is the existence of a reasonably smooth mechanism that will&#13;
generate shelter options in the quantity, quality, and locations demanded by a&#13;
shifting and growing labor force.&#13;
2.       In Indonesia, 150,000-200,000 new urban households seek housing each&#13;
year,  be it shared,  rented,  or owned.   An unknown fraction of existing&#13;
households seek to change the characteristics of their shelter through moving&#13;
or upgrading of existing units.   Though information is scanty, it is clear&#13;
that most urban housing in Indonesia is built by individual households, using&#13;
incremental or staged construction, and ignoring the formalities associated&#13;
with building construction permits and orderly land registration.  Financial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
institutions play virtually no role in this "informal" market.  In fact the&#13;
major outside catalyst is provide-d by the provision of basic infrastructure&#13;
through programs like the Kampung Improvement Program.  Direct public sector&#13;
initiatives are largely confined to financing formal or licensed housing. The&#13;
public housing agency, PERUMNAS is producing fewer than 18,000 housing&#13;
solutions per year, roughly half' of which are serviced sites and half are&#13;
units of varying quality and size.  In addition, through the housing finance&#13;
institution, Bank Tabugan Negara (BTN), the government allocates public&#13;
resources largely obtained through liquidity credits from Bank Indonesia to&#13;
finance private construction of about 32,000 units yearly.  All told, about&#13;
one-quarter to one-third of new housing construction in urban areas involves&#13;
government financing. This resem'bles conditions in other East Asian countries&#13;
such as the Philippines and Thailand.1/ Except for a largely symbolic effort&#13;
by a new private mortgage company, the only additional institutional financing&#13;
available in these cities come through the efforts of some employers who help&#13;
their workers, and of insurance companies who lend to policyholders. There is&#13;
no formal assistance for home upgrading or for financing the transfer of&#13;
existing units.&#13;
3.       Not only is formal assistance limited, but it tends to be inequitably&#13;
distributed.   In fact, the bullk of the private units financed by BTN are&#13;
affordable to only the top quintile of the household the households in urban&#13;
areas. The smaller PERUMNAS program, because of its reliance or "sites and&#13;
services," and "core" units, is far more accessible; eighty percent of the&#13;
housing solutions financed are valued at less than Rp. 3 million and are&#13;
accessible to households with incomes at the median or less.   The average&#13;
jJ See B. Renaud, Housing and FLnancial Institutions in Developing Countries.&#13;
Urban Development Department Report No. 19, The World Bank, December 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
PERUMNAS solution is affordable to households with incomes low enough to place&#13;
them in the lowest quintile of the urban household income distribution. The&#13;
equity issue is all the more troublesome because both PERUMNAS and assisted&#13;
private construction are heavily subsidized.   Public housing solutions are&#13;
provided through mortgages carrying interest rates of 5 to 9 percent, while&#13;
private housing is financed at 9 percent.  By contrast, mobilizing resources&#13;
from other parties would force BTN to pay rates as high as 16 percent.jJ&#13;
Since the bulk of the financing goes to private construction activity, it is&#13;
not surprising that 60 percent of the implicit interest rate subsidy accrues&#13;
to households in the upper two deciles of the income distribution.&#13;
4. The challenge facing policymakers is how to devise a strategy to increase&#13;
housing production in Indonesia's cities so as to benefit households at all&#13;
income levels while decreasing the role of the public treasury, given&#13;
macroeconomic realities and the critical needs of the rural sector.   The&#13;
rewards for developing a successful approach are great. Not only is a basic&#13;
need met in the process but a dynamic housing construction "industry"&#13;
generated significant number of low and medium skilled jobs while requiring&#13;
only limited amounts of foreign exchange.&#13;
5. The government has set ambitious targets for itself. This is evident in&#13;
the goals established for REPELITA IV; with an estimated 350,000 units&#13;
scheduled for financing, this would more than double the effort expended&#13;
during REPELITA III.  While this would still be modest in terms of overall&#13;
demand, attempts to service a more significant share would be difficult. This&#13;
is particularly so because during REPELITA III the bulk of resources used to&#13;
1j During the period 1976-1983, the direct budget subsidy for public housing&#13;
units was Rpl20 billion, and the interest rate subsidy for private units&#13;
exceeded Rpl50 billion, or equivalent to more than one-third of the amount&#13;
lent for the latter units.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
finance public and private initiatives were either outright grants (34&#13;
percent) or Bank Indonesia funds (60 percent) lent at a nominal rate of 3&#13;
percent. The weighted average coEst of funds was therefore below 3 percent, a&#13;
situation unlikely to persist in the future give the macroeconomic&#13;
realities. Significantly larger resources must be mobilized for housing with&#13;
far less reliance on grants or heavily subsidized funds from Bank Indonesia.&#13;
In fact, World Bank estimates suggest that a fairly optimistic scenario would&#13;
still require that more than half of the new resources come from institutions&#13;
(pension funds, insurance companJies) and holdexs of new savings instruments&#13;
receiving rates of interest in the 15-16 percbnt range.   As a result the&#13;
average weighted cost of funds wrould more than triple to about 10 percent.&#13;
All borrowers will have to pay more for borrowed funds, with rates varying&#13;
from levels somewhat above the average weighted cost of funds to the&#13;
prevailing market lending rates (i.e. 12-18%). Additional resources could be&#13;
obtained by raising the prese!ntly very low down payment requirements&#13;
particularly for higher priced tnits.   For example, down payments could be&#13;
increased from the current 5-10% to 10-30% depending on the price of the&#13;
unit.   With this overall approach in place, there would be little need to&#13;
depend on the Ministry of Finance or Bank Indonesia for subsidies.&#13;
6.       World Bank estimates suggest that, even with higher interest rates,&#13;
it will be possible to provide affordable housing for the various segments of&#13;
the population with incomes above the first two deciles. The poorest of the&#13;
poor would benefit as well, through the greater availability of rental rooms&#13;
that characteristically accompany the expansion of housing construction&#13;
outside the wealthiest neighborhoods.   The remaining challenge will be to&#13;
provide incentives for, and to remove obstacles in the way of, developers who&#13;
wish to construct units for the lower half of the income distribution. Here,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
efforts are needed to remove regulatory barriers to private construction of&#13;
core units with less than 36 square meters.   In addition private access to&#13;
mortgage and construction finance should be made conditional on bona fide&#13;
efforts to build a range of housing, with special emphasis on units affordable&#13;
to urban households in the two deciles bracketing the median income levels.&#13;
Ceilings on the size of individual loans may be necessary to guarantee that&#13;
the wealthiest households do not receive a disproportionate share of the&#13;
available funds.&#13;
7.       Beyond that, more imaginative solutions must be sought.  As noted,&#13;
one can assume that in Indonesia's cities more than half of all new housing&#13;
accommodations (including rental of rooms newly added) is provided for by the&#13;
so-called  informal market,  especially  in  the Kampung  areas.    Given  the&#13;
continuation of vigorous Kampung Improvement Programs, which will provide&#13;
various public services to the sites, there is a critical need to mobilize and&#13;
relend funds for housing upgrading.  While there are a few precedents in this&#13;
area 1/, consideration should be given to schemes permitting financial&#13;
institutions to provide community lines of credit.  This would allow legally&#13;
constituted community organizations to borrow funds for housing improvements&#13;
by its members.   This system would significantly multiply the number of&#13;
beneficiaries receiving small loans, primarily for construction materials and&#13;
some skilled labor help. At the same time some of the paper work associated&#13;
with loan disbursements and collections could be passed down to the community&#13;
organizations.   While there are risks associated with involving community&#13;
groups in this way, the idea has enough merit to warrant testing on a pilot&#13;
basis.&#13;
1/ One country that has experimented with various pilot home improvement&#13;
programs is Colombia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
8.       Much of the housing problem, especially for lower income groups, does&#13;
not reside in the lack of housing units, but in the lack of serviced land&#13;
available for housing. Some of this deficit can be addressed by land purchase&#13;
and development of serviced sites by a public housing corporation (such as&#13;
PERUMNAS).   However this approach is time consuming,  places an additional&#13;
burden on the government budget, and has sometimes led to the selection of&#13;
inappropriate  sites,  which have  been  difficult  to  sell.    An  innovative&#13;
approach which would complement that of the public housing corporation and is&#13;
now being tried in Jakarta and Denpasar is "Guided Land Development." This,&#13;
in essense, is a simplified form of land readjustment whereby the government&#13;
provides coordinated infrast:ructure to growth corridors at the city perimeter&#13;
and establishes agreements with groups of landowners for the delineation of&#13;
public space for minor rights of way and community services. Through these&#13;
arrangements and by providing assistance to landowner associations on simple&#13;
subdivision layout, large volumes of minimally-serviced land can be released&#13;
onto the market through private sale. A betterment tax on the developed land&#13;
both encourages landowners to se11, and recoups the costs of   most of the&#13;
local services.&#13;
9.       These various initiatives, taken together, will begin to address the&#13;
varying demands of households that share rooms, rent units, and own homes.&#13;
Actions taken to promote informal housing are particularly beneficial because&#13;
experience elsewhere demonstrates that among households in the lowest half of&#13;
the income distribution, it is informal sector that provides most affordable&#13;
housing at many different locations for owners. renters, and roomers  while&#13;
economizing on scarce national administrative and financial resources.A/&#13;
Ij B. Renaud, op. cit.; WeP. Strassman, The Transformation of Urban Housing.&#13;
Baltimore, Johns Hopkins Press, 1982; A. Hamer, Bogota's Unregulated&#13;
Subdivisions: The Myths and Realities of Incremental Housing&#13;
Construction. World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 734, May, 1985.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                           European Office                 Tokyo Office                          U&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                    66, avenue d'Iena               Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.         75116 Paris, France             1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234              Telephone: (1) 47.23.54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK             Telex: 842-620628               Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                               Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN-'-3-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0688-X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="700805">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/01/700805/indonesia-challenge-urbanization
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/01/700805/indonesia-challenge-urbanization</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/01/700805/indonesia-challenge-urbanization</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1986/01/01/000009265_3980901130913/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1986/01/01/000009265_3980901130913/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1986-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Indonesia : the challenge of urbanization
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In Indonesia, and across the developing
            world, policymakers are apprehensive about increasing
            urbanization, fearing that it will concentrate population in
            one or very few centers, drawing resources away from other
            areas and thwarting attempts to achieve political
            integration. This paper describes urban spatial policies and
            instruments tried in Indonesia. It examines human settlement
            patterns, assessing past trends and future prospects in
            urban growth, rural-urban migration, and the growth of large
            cities. Factors influencing urban development are addressed,
            with emphasis on sectoral policies, microspatial initiatives
            and urban service strategies to influence industrial
            location. The report concludes with a set of recommendations
            for industrial policy and urban management reforms to be
            used to modify the rate at which different size cities will grow.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Indonesia : the challenge of urbanization
        </docna>
        <display_title>Indonesia : the challenge of urbanization</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1986/01/700805/indonesia-challenge-urbanization</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Urban Housing and Land Settlements,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,National Urban Development Policies &amp; Strategies,Municipal Financial Management,City Development Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Hamer, A.</author>
            <author>Steer, A.</author>
            <author>Williams, D.</author>
            <author>WUD</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980901130913</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other environment</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 787</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Environment</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Urbanization; Urban planning; Urban policy;
            Settlement patterns; Rural-urban migrations; Urban
            development; Industrial location; Industrial policy; Urban
            population; Population increase
            affiliates,agglomeration
            economies,autonomy,big cities,Cities,city investment,city
            size,debt,development banks,economic
            development,expenditures,financial institutions,income
            distribution,industrial activities,Industrial
            estates,Industrial Location,industrial sector,industrial
            zones,intergovernmental fiscal relations,intergovernmental
            relations,labor markets,land development,Large Cities,local
            government,local governments,matching grants,new
            entrants,operating costs,profitability,public housing,public
            services,quality of life,regional development banks,resource
            mobilization,service sector,slums,street
            vendors,taxation,towns,transport,transport
            sector,urban,urban area,urban areas,urban centers,Urban
            Development,urban dwellers,Urban economics,urban
            employment,Urban Growth,Urban growth rates,urban
            households,urban housing,urban issues,urban labor,urban
            labor force,urban management,Urban migration,Urban
            policy,urban population,Urban Population Growth,urban
            poverty,urban residents,Urban Services,urban
            settlements,urbanization,urbanization process,user
            charges,Utilities,waste disposal,Water Supply,working capital
        </keywd>
        <owner>Environ &amp; Soc Sustainable Dev VP (ESD)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP787</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Parks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance for Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mortgages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Housing and Land Settlements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Zones</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Congestion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>