<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Housing Demand in Developing Countries&#13;
Stephen Malpezzi    \WP 7  33&#13;
Stephen K. Mayo&#13;
with&#13;
David J. Gross&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 733&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 733&#13;
Housing Demand in Developing Countries&#13;
Stephen Malpezzi&#13;
Stephen K. Mayo&#13;
with&#13;
David J. Gross&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright ©( 1985&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing May 1985&#13;
Third printing July 1987&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'lena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Stephen Malpezzi and Stephen K. Mayo are economists in the Water Supply and&#13;
Urban Development Department of the World Bank. David J. Gross, a consultant to&#13;
that department, is assistant professor of public administration at Louisiana State&#13;
University.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Malpezzi, Stephen.&#13;
Housing demand in developing countries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 733)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Housing--Developing countries. 2. Housing&#13;
policy--Developing countries. I. Mayo, Stephen K.,&#13;
1942-       .  II. Gross, David J., 1958-&#13;
III. Title. IV. Series.&#13;
HD7391.M35   1985          338.4'769083'091724           85-9448&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0539-5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This paper reports on research conducted at the World Bank to&#13;
increase understanding of developing country housing markets; in particular,&#13;
of housing demand behavior. The objectives of the paper are (1) to review&#13;
previous evidence on housing demand parameters in developing countries, (2) to&#13;
present new evidence on housing demand parameters (e.g., price and income&#13;
elasticities, and demograpihic effects) based on application of standardized&#13;
models and comparable variable definitions in the cities in eight developing&#13;
countries (Colombia, Egypt, El Salvador, Ghana, India, Jamaica, Korea, and the&#13;
Philippines), and (3) to examine similarities and differences among cities in&#13;
housing demand and, in a preliminary way, etxplanations for place-to-place&#13;
differences. The analysis emphasizes differences in housing demand by tenure&#13;
(particularly for renters and owners, but also for squatters and non-&#13;
squatters) and, paralleling the literature in developed countries, stresses&#13;
the importance of accounting for the impact of income and relative prices on&#13;
housing demand.&#13;
The paper is based on research conducted as part of RPO 672-46,&#13;
Housing Demand and Finance in Developing Countries, the first phase of which&#13;
encompassed (1) the demand for housing as a "composite good," focusing on&#13;
expenditure patterns for housing, (2) determinants of land and housing rents&#13;
and values, focusing on estimating the implicit market prices of housing,&#13;
infrastructure, and neighborhood amenities using hedonic price indices, and&#13;
(3) demand for individual housing characteristics such as interior space,&#13;
quality of construction, utilities, and accessibility, focusing particularly&#13;
on estimating schedules of the public's "willingness to pay" for different&#13;
types of housing in different markets. The second phase focuses on (1)&#13;
applying first phase results to project design, and (2) extending the research&#13;
to policy issues, namely public and subsidized housing, rent control, tenure,&#13;
and housing finance.&#13;
The authors would like to thank Waleed El-Ansary, James Follain, Manny Jimenez,&#13;
Sungyong Kang, David Lebow, and Haeduck Lee for providing some of the results&#13;
reported herein. Valuable comments were provided by many colleagues, especially&#13;
Bertrand Renaud, James Shilling, Paul Strassman, and Anthony Yezer, but opinions&#13;
expressed are solely the authors'.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page&#13;
EXECUTIVE SUMMARY.... .. ******.*.....*............................ ix&#13;
I.    INTRODUCTION .....................................                   1&#13;
1.* Motivation ...........................................   1&#13;
2.  Previous Household Studies ................................  2&#13;
II.   HOUSING EXPENDITURE FUNCTIONS FROM EIGHT DEVELOPING COUNTRIES. ....11&#13;
1. A Simple Model of Housing Demand...... .....o*.*.*.**...s..11&#13;
2.  Evaluating the Simple Model With Data From Egypt and&#13;
the Philippines,..........................................,21&#13;
3. Alternative Price and Income Elasticities from Egypt&#13;
and the Philipp.ines................... ...................32&#13;
III.  CROSS-COUNTRY DIFFERENCES EXPLAINED ................................44&#13;
1. Previous Cross-Country Research... ..........e.44&#13;
2. A Kuznets-type Result... . . . .. . *. .. .. . .    .e    e. e*56&#13;
3. A Simple Cross-CountryModel.58&#13;
IV.   DIFFERENCES IN HOUSING DEMAND BY TENURE .........................70&#13;
1. The Concept of User Cost. .           ..........e            o71&#13;
2. Rent-to-Income Ratios By Tenures..........................78&#13;
3. Testing the Relationship Among User Cost, Market&#13;
Conditions, and Tenure Choice............ ......e.........82&#13;
4.  Tenure as a Set of Property Rights, and Disaggregated&#13;
Resultso    oeo*o**oooooooo**eooeo*e86&#13;
V.    CONCLUSIONS, AND IDIRECTIONS FOR FUTURE RESEARCH ........O............90&#13;
1. Summary JResults ............................ 90&#13;
2. Policy Implications .........o......................................91&#13;
3.  Ongoing and Future Research Directions....................93&#13;
DATA APPENDIXo................................................... .96&#13;
1. Household Data Sources.................................... 96&#13;
2. Macro Data Sourcese....................................... 99&#13;
3.      City    Level    Datao.   ............................10&#13;
REFERENCES  ..............................................e.... 10l3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
Table                                                                    Page&#13;
1.  Review of Previous Housing Demand Studies......       .... .    ......5-8&#13;
2. Estimated Parameters of Housing Expenditure Functions&#13;
for   Renters  .............................................. * * s * * * 13-14&#13;
3. Estimated Parameters of Housing Expenditure Functions&#13;
for  Owners   ooooooooo.........o........o..oo..oo......o......o........o..ool 5-16&#13;
4.  Comparison of Small and Large Demand Models:  Beni Suef Renters.....25&#13;
5.  Comparison of Small and Large Demand Models:  Beni Suef Owners ...... 26&#13;
6.  Comparison of Small and Large Demand Models:  Cairo Renters.........27&#13;
7.  Comparison of Small and Large Demand Models:  Cairo Owners..........28&#13;
8.  Comparison of Small and Large Demand Models:  Manila Renters.........29&#13;
9.  Comparison of Small and Large Demand Models:  Manila Owners...e..... 30&#13;
10.  Comparison of Micro Income Elasticities From Different Models.......34&#13;
11.  Micro Housing Price Elasticity Estimates.........ooo.o.............37&#13;
12.  Benefits from a Stylized Housing Subsidy, Under Alternative&#13;
Price Elasticities,  oooo.ot.*..oo...ooo*.a .............................o.o...o... 42&#13;
13. Cross-Country Housing Investment Equations, From Burns and Grebler..48&#13;
14.  Selected Results:  Housing Investment Equations, From Renaud........50&#13;
15. Effects of Financial Variables on Share of Housing Investment,&#13;
From Buckeley and Madhusudhan ...o.ooo.o .  o.. oo o ooo.o.oo.. . .. . . . . . . . .51&#13;
16. Annez-Wheaton Cross-Country Housing Investment Model: OLS Esti-&#13;
mates  From Their Larger Model... o..    o.9....................... . .54&#13;
17.  Cross-Country Housing Demand Estimates for Renters...o-. ........ 59&#13;
18.  Cross-Country Housing Demand Estimates for Owners...................60&#13;
19.  First Order Effects of Market Conditions on User Cost...............73&#13;
20. Alternative Explanations for Cross Tenure Differences in&#13;
Relative Real Housing Consumption. ..................................o74&#13;
21. Rent-to-Income Ratios by Income     .......     ..o. ............... 79-80&#13;
22. Imputed Rents, Opportunity Cost, and Value to Income, with&#13;
Homeownership Rates in Samples, and Recent Inflation ....... ........ 84&#13;
23. Income Elasticities from Demand Equations by Disaggregated Tenure...88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF FIGURES&#13;
Figure                                                                       Page&#13;
1.  Confidence Intervals for Income Elasticities, Renters..............19&#13;
2.  Confidence Intervals for Income Elasticities, Owners............... .20&#13;
3.  Demand Curves From Micro Price Elasticities ......................... 39&#13;
4.  Rent-to-Income Ratios by 'Income for Renters.........................45&#13;
5.  Rent-to-Income Ratios by Income for Owners..........................46&#13;
6.  Cross-Country Engel Curves, Renters.................................64&#13;
7.  Cross-Country Engel Curves, Owners ..................................65&#13;
8.  Cross-Country Demand Curves, Renters............................... .67&#13;
9.  Cross-Country Demand Curves, Owners.......        ******... ........e. ..........68&#13;
10.  Ratio of Owner R/Y to Rent:er R/Y by Log of Income...................83&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EXCECUTIVE SUMKARY&#13;
Cities in developing countries are growing at extraordinary rates,&#13;
often compressing into decades the urbanization process that has taken&#13;
centuries in developed countries. In coping with this growth, public&#13;
authorities have devised a wide range of policy instruments to influence the&#13;
rate and character of city expansion, to meet the needs of people for shelter&#13;
and urban services, and to allocate resources in ways that redistribute both&#13;
the costs and benefits of urban growth. Ideally, such policy formulation&#13;
should be informed by a careful understanding of the behavior of urban&#13;
markets; in fact, little information on market behavior is available to the&#13;
policymakers of developing countries. Such basic information is needed for&#13;
improved project design and, even more importantly, for improved sector-wide&#13;
policies.&#13;
This paper reports on research conducted at the World Bank to&#13;
increase understanding of developing country housing markets; in particular,&#13;
of housing demand behavior. Whi'Le the overall project examines both the&#13;
demand for housing characteristics and the demand for housing as a composite&#13;
good, this paper addresses only ithe latter. The objectives of this paper are&#13;
(1) to briefly review previous evidence on housing demand parameters in&#13;
developing countries, (2) to present new evidence on housing demand parameters&#13;
based on application of standardiLzed models and comparable variable&#13;
definitions in 16 cities in eight: developing countries (Colombia, Egypt, El&#13;
Salvador, Ghana, India, Jamaica, Korea, and the Philippines), and (3) to&#13;
examine similarities and differences among cities in housing demand and, in a&#13;
preliminary way, offer explanations for place-to-place differences. Limited&#13;
comparisons are also made to two U.S. cities in order to begin comparison of&#13;
- ix -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
developing and developed country market behavior. The analysis emphasizes&#13;
differences in housing demand by city and by tenure group. Simple models&#13;
which explain both of these observed differences are presented and tested. In&#13;
parallel with the literature in developed countries, this paper stresses the&#13;
importance of incomes and prices on housing demand.&#13;
This paper presents an abbreviated discussion of a larger&#13;
comparative study of housing demand in developing countries. Using a number&#13;
of high quality household-level data sets, a number of empirical regularities&#13;
are found within and among developing country cities. Among these are, at the&#13;
household level:&#13;
1. Income elasticities of demand among renters are generally small&#13;
(on the order of 0.3 to 0.6); income elasticities of demand&#13;
among owners are somewhat larger (on the order of 0.4 to 0.8);&#13;
these results are generally consistent with findings for&#13;
developed countries.&#13;
2. owners generally consume a good deal more housing than renters&#13;
at given income levels; this is not primarily a result of&#13;
differences in income elasticities of demand but rather a result&#13;
of differences in expenditure equation constant terms. This&#13;
suggests that variables such as tastes and assets play important&#13;
roles in causing consumption differences between renters and&#13;
owners.&#13;
3. Permanent income elasticities of demand for housing are somewhat&#13;
greater than current income elasticities, although in reasonably&#13;
"complete" models of demand including price terms and&#13;
demographic variables, permanent income elasticities are only&#13;
moderately higher than current income elasticities in simpler&#13;
models.&#13;
4. Price elasticities of demand for cities analyzed here are on the&#13;
order of -0.8 to -1.0, considerably higher than estimates&#13;
produced elsewhere in the literature. However, these estimates&#13;
may have an upward bias because of a specification problem.&#13;
Important results at the city level include:&#13;
1. Rent-to-income ratios rise across cities as income increases, a&#13;
result of upward-shifting Engel curves. This phenomenon appears&#13;
to be associated with increases in the relative price of&#13;
housing, with differences between current and permanent income&#13;
elasticities of demand, and with differences in the time period&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
associated with the two levels of analysis. mhe city level&#13;
analyses presumably model very long-run behavior.&#13;
2. Very long-run (cross-city) income elasticities of demand are&#13;
estimated to be one or greater. Very long-run price&#13;
elasticities are less than one in absolute value. Income&#13;
elasticities are measured with better precision than price&#13;
elasticities.&#13;
3.  owners generally pay a significant premium for ownership per&#13;
se. This premium, equal to the difference between the&#13;
opportunity cost of housing capital and the imputed rental value&#13;
of housing, is highly variable from place to place depending on&#13;
market conditions. In particular, ownership premia are high in&#13;
cities with high rates of housing inflation and significant&#13;
rates of asset formation through savings or workers'&#13;
remittances. Security of tenure also influences the magnitude&#13;
of the premium paid for ownership.&#13;
Comparing household level and city level results leads to the&#13;
following:&#13;
1. Income elasticities are much greater in the very long run than&#13;
within a market. The cross-section results are directly&#13;
relevant to behavior within a market, while the very long-run&#13;
results can be applied to make predictions as a country&#13;
develops. Both are necessary for correct analysis of projects,&#13;
as will be outlined below. This is not surprising, as it a&#13;
sound general principle that behavior is more responsive to&#13;
changes over longer periods of time.&#13;
2. Long-run price elasticities from the city level estimation are&#13;
lower in absolute vatlue than the cross-section price&#13;
elasticities. This is at variance with the principle just&#13;
enunciated. The price elasticity estimates suffer from more&#13;
severe errors in variables problems than the income&#13;
elasticities; because of the specifications used, the cross-city&#13;
specifications are probably biased towards zero, and the&#13;
household level estimates are likely biased towards one.&#13;
Policy implications of these and other results from the housing&#13;
demand research project will be spelled out in detail in forthcoming&#13;
reports. Here several obvious policy implications will be briefly mentioned.&#13;
Affordability calculations for target populations are a critical&#13;
element of project design. Until now, such projects relied on rules of thumb&#13;
often, for example, an assumption that households can spend between 20 and 25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
percent of income on housing. The results described above demonstrate the&#13;
inadequacy of any single ratio to predict consumption for different income and&#13;
tenure groups in different places. In many respects the best solution is to&#13;
do a careful household survey which includes the target population, and to&#13;
proceed with simple econometric models like the ones described here to get&#13;
project-specific estimates. If constrained, a second best solution can be to&#13;
estimate a variable rule of thumb from the results in this paper. Using the&#13;
elasticities for the felevant tenure group, the cross-city model can be used&#13;
to predict the city's average consumption given only an estimate of city&#13;
average income and a few readily available country level variables such as GDP&#13;
per capita. Income elasticities within samples do not vary by much from city&#13;
to city, so a typical cross-section elasticity can be chosen (say the&#13;
average), or the elasticity from a city deemed similar to the project&#13;
location. This elasticity can be used to move along the city specific Engel&#13;
curve to locate an estimate of the affordability ratio of the target&#13;
population in the target city.&#13;
Most current public sector housing projects contain subsidies,&#13;
implicit or explicit. How inefficient these subsidies are depends critically&#13;
on the demand and price elasticities of the participants. In general, larger&#13;
price elasticities imply larger benefits to participants to housing programs,&#13;
ceteris paribus, although it is well known that private benefits from a&#13;
subsidy are always less than the benefit from equivalent income transfers.&#13;
Larger income elasticities imply that unconstrained transfers will have larger&#13;
housing consumption effects, ceteris paribus. The current research has not&#13;
nailed down a single set of numbers which can be used to reliably estimate&#13;
precise measures of program efficiency, but future work can use a range of&#13;
estimates to examine costs and benefits of alternative programs qualitatively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The findings on tenure specific differences have several important&#13;
implications which will be spelled out in more detail in forthcoming work.&#13;
Note, for example, that affordability calculations that do not account for&#13;
tenure differences will be seriously biased in many cities. It is currently&#13;
common practice to use renter samples to make direct inferences about&#13;
affordability in owner occupied projects without adjustment for these cross&#13;
tenure differences; it is argued in this paper and in Mayo and Gross (1985)&#13;
that this is a good approximation if project target groups are limited to&#13;
current renters. Another implication is t$at the existence of highly variable&#13;
homeownership premia suggests that, in some markets, schemes that focus on&#13;
increasing the rental stock are appropriate and desirable, while in others&#13;
high premia suggest that the focus should be on increasing the homeowner&#13;
stock.&#13;
The outline of the paper is as follows. The introductory chapter&#13;
reviews the developing country literature on housing demand. Chapter 2&#13;
presents new estimates for many cities from a simple housing expenditure model&#13;
disaggregated by tenure (rent/own), and then evaluates the simple model using&#13;
data from three cities.  Chapter 3 examines and explains shifts in demand&#13;
parameters across cities. Chapter 4 examines at greater length differences in&#13;
housing demand by renters and owners, suggesting that owners' "asset demand"&#13;
for housing (as distinct from their demand for housing services) is highly&#13;
variable from place to place depending on market conditions. Chapter 5&#13;
summarizes our conclusions and suggests some policy implications of our&#13;
findings and future research directions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
1. Motivation&#13;
Cities in developing cotntries are growing at extraordinary rates,&#13;
often compressing into decades the urbanization process that has taken&#13;
centuries in developed countries. In coping with this growth, public&#13;
authorities have devised a wide rtnge of policy instruments to influence the&#13;
rate and character of city expansion, to meet the needs of people for shelter&#13;
and urban services, and to allocate resources in ways that redistribute both&#13;
the costs and benefits of urban growth. Ideally, such policy formulation&#13;
should be informed by a careful understanding of the behavior of urban&#13;
markets; in fact, little information on market behavior is available to the&#13;
policymakers of developing countries. Such basic information is needed for&#13;
improved project design and, even more importantly, for improved sector-wide&#13;
policies.&#13;
This paper reports- on research conducted at the World Bank to&#13;
increase understanding of developing country housing markets; in particular,&#13;
of housing demand behavior. While the overall project examines both the&#13;
demand for housing characteristics l/ and the demand for housing as a&#13;
composite good, this paper addresses only the latter. The objectives of this&#13;
paper are (1) to briefly review previous evidence on housing demand parameters&#13;
in developing countries, (2) to present new evidence on housing demand&#13;
parameters based on application of standardized models and comparable variable&#13;
definitions in 16 cities in eight developing countries (Colombia, Egypt, El&#13;
Salvador, Ghana, India, Jamaica, Korea, and the Philippines), and (3) to&#13;
1/   See, for example, Follain and Jimenez, forthcoming (a, b), Gross (1984).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
examine similarities and differences among cities in housing demand and, in a&#13;
preliminary way, offer explanations for place-to-place differences. Limited&#13;
comparisons are also made to two U.S. cities in order to begin comparison of&#13;
developing and developed country market behavior. The analysis emphasizes&#13;
differences in housing demand by city and by tenure group. Simple models&#13;
which explain both of these observed differences are presented and tested. In&#13;
parallel with the literature in developed countries, this paper stresses the&#13;
importance of incomes and prices on housing demand.&#13;
The outline of the paper is as follows. The next section of this&#13;
chapter reviews the developing country literature on housing demand.&#13;
Chapter 2 presents new estimates for many cities from a simple housing&#13;
expenditure model disaggregated by tenure (rent/own), and then evaluates the&#13;
simple model using data from three cities. Chapter 3 examines and explains&#13;
shifts in demand parameters across cities. Chapter 4 examines at greater&#13;
length differences in housing demand by renters and owners, suggesting that&#13;
owners' "asset demand" for housing (as distinct from their demand for housing&#13;
services) is highly variable from place to place depending on market&#13;
conditions. Chapter 5 summarizes our conclusions and suggests some policy&#13;
implications of our findings and future research directions.&#13;
2. Previous Household Studies&#13;
Housing markets have been intensively studied in developed&#13;
countries, especially in the U.S. and Great Britain 2t  For example, there are&#13;
many dozens of published studies of the income and/or price elasticities of&#13;
2/   See Quigley (1979) and Weicher (1979) for concise summaries of recent&#13;
housing market analysis. See DeLeeuw (1971) and Mayo (1981) for reviews&#13;
of the demand literature.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
the demand for housing. There are three reasons for the size of this&#13;
literature. First, the many practical difficulties in the specification of&#13;
econometric housing models (such as the correct measurement of prices,&#13;
quantities, incomes, and the choice of functional form) have led to a number&#13;
of alternative approaches by different investigators. Second, housing markets&#13;
are local and diverse.  What is true in one city, even within a country, is&#13;
not necessarily true in another, 13o it has been natural to extend demand&#13;
analyses to a wide variety of places. While divergent empirical estimates can&#13;
be expected because of heterogeneiity among markets, some stylized facts are&#13;
now broadly supported by empirical work in developed countries--for example,&#13;
that cross-section income and price elasticities of demand are less than one&#13;
in absolute value--but even consensus on this general conclusion has been slow&#13;
in coming. Third, the literature has grown because governments actively&#13;
intervene in housing markets, and efficient intervention requires detailed&#13;
knowledge of housing market parameters. In the U.S., in fact, the government&#13;
has sponsored major studies of housing demand and supply behavior such as&#13;
those of the Experimental Housing Allowance Program (Bradbury and Downs,&#13;
Weinberg and Friedman) which were explicitly designed to facilitate choices&#13;
among alternative housing policy instruments.&#13;
Despite the need for careful modeling of housing demand in&#13;
developing countries, only a small number of studies have been done, and these&#13;
are only rarely linked to policy applications. Research has tended to focus&#13;
on a small number of countries where data are available--often better off&#13;
developing countries. Even when data are available, analysis has often been&#13;
hampered by limitations in sample design, definitional problems, and poor&#13;
quality data. Even so, the modest amount of research that has been done has&#13;
suggested important similarities in patterns of housing demand both among&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
developing countries and between developing and developed countries.&#142;'  Were&#13;
these patterns to hold elsewhere, there would be some promise of developing&#13;
general patterns of prescription in dealing with developing country housing&#13;
problems. But whether or not these patterns hold for other countries is not&#13;
known, nor is much known concerning the relationship between idiosyncratic&#13;
features of local housing markets and housing demand parameters. Some results&#13;
will no doubt be found to be robust to market conditions, others not. Two&#13;
important functions of this research are (1) to categorize some results as&#13;
directly portable (the results which hold under most conditions), and (2) to&#13;
make seemingly non-robust results portable by explaining how market conditions&#13;
affect the result (hence making the result predictable).&#13;
Further, little is known concerning the impact on housing demand of&#13;
institutional features of housing markets such as the availability of housing&#13;
finance, rent control, or laws and practices concerning tenure and occupancy&#13;
rights; little is known concerning the role of inflation on housing demand;&#13;
and little is known concerning the impact of the sudden infusions of income&#13;
and wealth to local economies from foreign worker remittances that have&#13;
characterized a number of developing countries. Such work has also begun.4/&#13;
The first step in developing a systematic understanding of housing&#13;
demand in developing countries is to review previous studies. Table 1&#13;
summarizes information on housing demand studies in developing countries.  The&#13;
table is arranged by country; most studies of housing demand have been done&#13;
3/   See, for example, Ingram (1984) and Jimenez and Keare (1984).&#13;
4/   Hoy and Jimenez (1984), Friedman, Jimenez, and Mayo (1985), Malpezzi&#13;
(1984 b, c), Mayo, Struyk and Turner (1985), Renaud (1984), Struyk&#13;
and Turner (1984).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
hyva, of fravie.  .im _km  Stud,  carsctritLca med atoUt&#13;
City/          Lst Tear       Type aI acom                                               Frtie              Strati-             Sype o&#13;
Latbor        Country         of Dats       of Dits           Ilbdl               waeaure               Umasrs            catio               Esatlcity&#13;
so" sad       Guyaq.il          1968        pooled eim        la"                 total                 so"; price         6 strata.          evalsted&#13;
""sgrove      leuador            *      x     rias/?es                            *Zperditure           elasticity         beads a"           at &#13;
acttien                                                    derived frroe      iaeoa&#13;
sw. sWd       lAsa              1969        crome scties       ISIS               total&#13;
uAgrove       Peru                                                                *zpeadfter            soon, price        * strata,          evaluated&#13;
elasticity        bsds age            at m&#13;
derived fre       Imcon&#13;
EKlZ&#13;
SIw  and      Csracas           1966        er_*ectioe         luS                total                 eons price         S strata,          evaluated&#13;
flasgroe-     Wemecula                                                            ezpeaditure           elasticity        baad's age          at m&#13;
derived fro       ncose&#13;
uoeh          Mexico            19i         croes-asctioe      ELS                total                 none, price        24 strata.         evaluated&#13;
at *1.                                                                            *zperdlturc           *laticity         sedoecoeoae         at m&#13;
derived frog      status, locatioe&#13;
335&#13;
leteacourt    Central           1964        croes-sectioe      3UIS               total                 soae, prlee       6 strata: bead      evaluated&#13;
Chile                                                               espenditure          elasticity         beads as*.         at &#13;
4erived froe      1acom&#13;
BELS&#13;
Llueb         Korzs             1972        tim aetisa          3s3               total                 beuein8                               evaluated&#13;
St  l*.                                     of aggregated                         expeediture           compeonet of                          at m&#13;
croee-*ctlos                                               GNP price&#13;
deflator&#13;
Wuch          Urban             1971        croses-acties,    ILES                total                 price varies      6 strets:           evluated&#13;
et al.        households.                   9 large cities                        aupaditurs            by city           bead's age,        at &#13;
Korea                                                                                                      incoa  source,&#13;
h_ussbold siae&#13;
Llutb         Seoul,            1971        creos-sectioe     ELKS                total                  ons'; prite      * strata:           evaluated&#13;
St al.        Korea                                                               ezpenditure          elastieity         beads age,         at &#13;
derivd fre        iocoa  sourre,&#13;
ELES              bouhold mine&#13;
PO11-D        Koren             1976        croes-6actios      loirles            consuaption          varies by                             comoatct&#13;
et *1                                                                            *and current          housebold&#13;
- tco_&#13;
pellets       Korea             1976        crosa-actle        loirlos           consuaption          varies by                             coest et&#13;
*t *1                                                                                                  0&#13;
mayo at  . *    Cairo,          1980        croes-section     loj-log             current incosa       none                                  coustaat&#13;
Egypt                                                              and eatlted&#13;
persoant lacom&#13;
Mayo at *1.   8.01 Suef,        1980        cross-section     log-log             curront income       noe                                   Co_otant&#13;
lgypt                                                              and estisated&#13;
per_san*t incoa&#13;
Mayo at al.   Cairo,            1980        eroaa-saction     log-los             predicted            SomS                                  ceateat&#13;
Egypt                                                              curreant&#13;
loco"&#13;
Mayo at al.   seat Suef,        1980        CTOro-ctton       leg log             preadicted           nones                                 cmiant&#13;
Igypt                                                              currant&#13;
Falk&amp;e        Malaysia       ad 70s7        varies            varies              varies               none              astletes froe       varies&#13;
3 ether studies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Review of Previous NoUsira Dt_D4 StuIy Charatterisftcs ud OUttUC5&#13;
DoUD UMTICITI6S&#13;
Poed ao.rs &amp; Reuters                     Renters                   Owers                     Reslt of&#13;
City/&#13;
Luther          Coustry        Icome                Ow  Prtice         Income    Own Prlce      Income      Own Prlee        Stratificatios    Cinets&#13;
_ and           GOuyaqull,      1.10        _         .8 5&#13;
lsIirove        Ecuador        1-1.02 to 1.15       1-.96 to -.64&#13;
IQI.. 11IQR-.25&#13;
: sod           Lies. MUa-1.31                     _-.22&#13;
MeIreo          Peru           1-.89 to 2.35        1.-50 to .35&#13;
IQ1.96              IQ&amp;-.69&#13;
oem aud         Caracas,       N-1.09               M-.33&#13;
~I_iro,         V eDsula       R-.28 to 1.9         1-.67 to -.08&#13;
IQ1-.56             IQ1-.*0&#13;
L"ib            Mexlco         X-.93                I-.31                                                                    Only urbs results reported&#13;
at ea.             1..SI to 1.38                    1-.88 to .23                                                             bere.&#13;
1Q1-.I5             IQR-.26&#13;
central       Xt.79                M-.34&#13;
Ustammeat       Cblle           R-.6  to 1.05       R-.55 to -.28&#13;
IQR-.26             IQ1-.22&#13;
at *1.          Koea            2.48                 .53&#13;
Uerk            Orbsn e-.86                         N-.28                                                                    Only orb  results reportsd&#13;
*t ALI.         lores          1-.02 to 2.35        1-.50 to -.01                                                            here&#13;
IQR-1.24            IQR-.31&#13;
Lech            S5oul.         M-.54                1 -.22&#13;
at AL.          Korea          a-.39 to 2.00       1t1.28 to .12&#13;
IQR-1.78            IRQ-.64&#13;
PoIjale                        Conumtion: .58    -.13                  .42        -.06           .62         -.05            Other atstee sbw smee&#13;
at AI.          Korea                                                                                                        variaties by elty %hen&#13;
etrstitiod. See originsl&#13;
paper. ls  result troe&#13;
Tables 4 _   .&#13;
Curreat&#13;
inco_: .17          -.05               .12         .03           .21         .07&#13;
YeiJAl                         Roomm - .31          -.87                                                                     Dependet wariabls are&#13;
at al.          Knore          Roue Spem - .45   -.94                                                                        _a-or_w of spec&#13;
Lot Sit  -.41       -.35&#13;
!1m             Cairo.                                                            Current: .25&#13;
at AL.         ZEpt                                                               Perusnnt: .38&#13;
Roel Suet,                                                        Current: .50&#13;
*t ad.          Egypt                                                            P*runeut: .Z7&#13;
5555.           Calro.          .30                                    .30                       .31                         Depeudiw variable is&#13;
at AL.          Egypt                                                                                                        log of omber of room&#13;
Beni Suet,    .19                                     .25                       .17                         Depeede  variable is&#13;
at ALI.         RDpt                                                                                                         log of  _mer of room&#13;
PaRs            Malaysia       .88 to 1.12                                                                                   Revie artiele.  Primry&#13;
sores r   t easily Available&#13;
kN:  If estimates are stratified we pce"at mdiaD of al elasticitiee (X-), RanD (1-). sod iantsreLaosl cang  (tQ&amp;').&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table I&#13;
RnaDv  of! Preerm Siiusins D_ md Stud  Caracteristics and Outputs&#13;
City/          Lot Year       Type of                                lacom                 Price              Stratif1-           Ty" of&#13;
Author         Country         of Dcta       of Data            Model               MeSure                 seaure            cation              Elaticity&#13;
awe and         ogota,           1966        pooloid tim        ELKS1               total                 none; but          6 strata           evaluated&#13;
Meagrove       Coloebia                       erisl/cross       static              ezpendltures          Implied price      based on            at  _ae&#13;
section            estimtes                                 elasticities       head's age,&#13;
(date treted                             can be con-        Ieam&#13;
as single                                 Gtrufe from&#13;
cross section)                           ELE&#13;
mrr           Segota,            1978        crose-eectlon      llner deand         llnear and            none                                   evaluated&#13;
Coloabia                                         for spece;          quadratic                                                    at sae&#13;
-                    linear Ad           curr.nt income&#13;
quadratic&#13;
incoem term&#13;
Ingram        Bogota,           1978         cross-estion      liner demad         curraut incom         hedonic price                          evaluated&#13;
Colombla                                                                                   stratlfled by                          at mse&#13;
enploamet&#13;
Soso&#13;
Ingros        Bogota.           1978         croen-sectlon      log-log             current lacoe         '                                      cenatant&#13;
Colonbla                                         deamd&#13;
Ingrms        Cell.             1978         croes_ection       liner dm_nd         currsnt Inco_                                                evaluated&#13;
Clombia                                                                                                                           at mae&#13;
lagram        Call,             1978         eroee-section      log-log             currant Incom                                                conatant&#13;
Colooma&#13;
gamer         Bogota,           1978         crosa-eection      1a-log             current Incom         none                                  constant&#13;
Colombl                                         demad&#13;
Stra tama     Cartagena,         1976        crose-sectlon      log-log             current iDcam         cnoe               4 ower Incoum       conetant&#13;
Colombia                                         demand                                                       Classees   see&#13;
consent&#13;
Jimnex         Santa Ana,        1980        pooled tlm         llnear; inte-       waiShted average      none                                   evaluated&#13;
and  ear.      Cl Salvador                   s*erie/croos       grated treat-       of current and                                               at man&#13;
section. loU      m*nt of deemed       past Inco_&#13;
* mdi.m           and mobllity&#13;
lacoem&#13;
Jimene         Sant- Ana,        1980        pooled tim         log-log;            weighted av*erag      none                                   constant&#13;
and Keere     C1 Salvador                    serias/cross       comblnes dmand    of current and&#13;
actlon, low        mobllty             past incom&#13;
&amp; idlus&#13;
IACO_&#13;
Ji1me_         Soneo-net.        1960        pooled tim         liner; eoblnes   weighted avrage          cans                                   *valDatd&#13;
end  eare       l Salvdor                    series/cross       demad ad            of current  nd                                               *t mas&#13;
section, low      nobility            past Incom&#13;
a mdli&#13;
Inco_&#13;
Jimmes         So_orete,        1980         pooled tam         log-log; combines  weighted average       none                                   co_tast&#13;
and tre        El Salvador                   series/cross       demand and          of current ad&#13;
*ectlio. low      mobility&#13;
a ms_&#13;
incom&#13;
JAmma          Santa Ana,        1980        cross-eection      log-log;            wage                  none               3 strata:           co_taat&#13;
and Soneonate,                                   elasticitti         lecome                                   (1) hlred labor&#13;
E1 Salvador                                      derived from                                                 (2) O*lf-4.ip&#13;
odel of self-                                                (3) mixed&#13;
help houslg&#13;
productios&#13;
"ego ed        Sante Am,                     tim  series/                                                                                         ewvabted&#13;
J_l_mn             Salvador      1960        croe-_eactlo      3 year aerag        no"                                                           at m&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8&#13;
mavime of Previousn good            Sto    maftm  otinmd   me&#13;
oold         a  SUTOr                    lt                          Oo et .t&#13;
Clty/&#13;
utr             Country        nos                                Income Ow ce     Pices       I          ao.  ice    StratificatioS&#13;
and        ogota          I-.9             I-.20                                                                     1cee eleti-&#13;
-1jFevW         Colembia       1-.C5 to 1.0 W     -. 59 to 1.81                                                         city elihtl7&#13;
IQR-.17           IQB-1.29                                                               le  ftr older&#13;
houseaid."&#13;
_ir            BSogota.        .53                                .54                          .47                                           Dependent&#13;
Colome                                                                                                                        aribles i&#13;
L _In           Bogota,                                           .80 (197)   -. 0   (1975)    .60        -.19&#13;
Colombia&#13;
'ogota.                                           .72 (1975)   -.29 (1975)    .71         -.&#13;
Coloubia                                          .77 (1972)   s.A. (1972)&#13;
call&#13;
Egra            Colombia                                          .16          -.30            .&#13;
Call,&#13;
Colombie                                         .47           -.48            .76&#13;
Sogota.&#13;
T1grm           Colombia                                          .47                          .52                                             ariae       Its&#13;
duslils space&#13;
Cartate&#13;
Strasm          Colombia                                          *78                          1.19                      inom                 Our   del rern&#13;
(Cll Owners)             elootcity gEae       *tretifled by incom.&#13;
up with Income       Icome elasticities are .29.&#13;
for lot 3 grme         s, 1.42. .64 from lomeat&#13;
bigheat lncoe  group&#13;
Jimenez         Sante sa.                                         .42 .U4                                                                     Uao  Ilacbeen procedure&#13;
a" Iarue        C1 Salvador                                                                                                                   to correct tor eaaple&#13;
Asm.            Santa A.a0&#13;
a" ICaee        5l Salvador                                       .27                          1.05&#13;
Jimenez         Son-ants,&#13;
md har          El Salvador                                       .53&#13;
Mseum           SoeJonet*.&#13;
a"  Cre         Xl Scalvdor                                      .42&#13;
Santa LAM&#13;
and Soaomate.                                                                  .78 to I&#13;
Jiame           El Salvdor&#13;
Leant md        Santa An.,                                        .43                          .45                                            tatimetes by **aree of&#13;
name  51 Salvador                                                                                         in~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~1Come shone that NPC 1.&#13;
jImmuns  El  Salvador                                                                                     bloat~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~hihe  from bead's val&#13;
theJ  otber wages; htsbat&#13;
I@C is from rboh   lncome.&#13;
neinly tranafers&#13;
gftsj  if metimete   are stratlfigi -  Premsen  media at AUl GUialcctiea CE.). raa    (S.) and iatewerqstila raeg  (Ip.-).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
for Latin America, but others reported here have been done for Korea,&#13;
Malaysia, and Egypt. The lowest: income countries, and sub-Saharan African&#13;
countries, are underrepresented. To conserve space, we will not discuss the&#13;
results of these previous studies in detailo5/  Here, however, the following&#13;
points should be noted:&#13;
1.  Most income elasticities are between 0.5 and 1, indicating&#13;
generally inelastic demand.&#13;
2.  Income elasticities for renters are generally below those of&#13;
owners; the mediam renter elasticity is about 0.45, with two-&#13;
thirds of the estimates falling between 0.4 and 0.8. The median&#13;
owner income elasticity is about 0.65. While several of the&#13;
owner estimates are above 1.0, none of the renter estimates is&#13;
above 0.8.&#13;
3.  Price elasticities are small, with medians for owners and&#13;
renters equal to -.2 and -.3, respectively; price elasticities&#13;
are below income elasticities in absolute value.&#13;
Despite the regularities noted above, there is still quite a bit of variation&#13;
in parameter estimates from place to place and, depending on model&#13;
specification, variation for particular places. It is not known how much of&#13;
this is due to variation in data, variable definitions, model specification,&#13;
or underlying behavior.&#13;
In order to isolate underlying behavioral differences, we have&#13;
applied comparable model specification and, insofar as possible, comparable&#13;
variable definitions to data in 16 cities in eight countries. First, we&#13;
present results of simple models of housing expenditure which can be estimated&#13;
5/   See Mayo et al. (1983) for an extended discussion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
with each data set. Then we estimate more complete models which require&#13;
specialized data available for fewer places. Comparison of these latter&#13;
results with those of the simple models suggests how robust the results of the&#13;
simple models are.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
II. HOUSING EXPENDITURE FUNCTIONS IN EIGHT DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
A Simple Model of Housing Demand&#13;
Consider a utility maximizing household with income Y, which&#13;
consumes housing (Q) at relative price P, and a unit-priced numeraire good.&#13;
Straightforward maximization under the usual assumptions yields the demand&#13;
relation:&#13;
Q = Q(Y, P)&#13;
conditional on "demand shifters," usually separately denoted as tastes and&#13;
demographic variables. An Engel, or expenditure relation, can be derived by&#13;
shifting P to the left-hand side; also, assuming constant tastes, and that&#13;
household size dominates other d[emographic variables:&#13;
R = R(Y, H)&#13;
where R is rent (R = PQ), and H is household size. For estimation, a&#13;
particular functional form must be chosen. A straightforward logarithmic&#13;
specification is:&#13;
ln R = a + E (ln Y) + bH + cH + u&#13;
y&#13;
where Ey is the income elasticity of demand, a, b, and c are regression&#13;
coefficients, and u is an estimated disturbance.&#13;
While it may be desirable to include other demographic variables in&#13;
the specification, this is not possible in all cities because of data&#13;
limitations.i/ The major limitations of such a specification are well known&#13;
and include: omission of a price term; omission of other demographic&#13;
1/   Data are documented in the Appendix.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
variables; the effects of household participation in government subsidized&#13;
housing programs (or rent control); failure to account for permanent income&#13;
effects; and restriction of the functional form to a constant income&#13;
elasticity of demand. Many of these limitations are addressed in the next&#13;
section, which draws on the richer data sets available for some cities in the&#13;
analysis to evaluate this simple model. To anticipate those results, the&#13;
simple model appears remarkably free of major biases. Functional forms other&#13;
than loglinear have not been evaluated here.2/&#13;
Tables 2 and 3 present estimates of the parameters of Eq. (1) for&#13;
16 cities in eight developing countries...V Results for two U.S. cities are&#13;
also included for comparison. For renters, the dependent variable is net rent&#13;
(exclusive of utility payments). For owners, the dependent variable is either&#13;
(1) net imputed rent based on the owners' imputations, (2) predicted rent from&#13;
a hedonic price regression, or (3) constructed by applying a fixed&#13;
amortization rate to owners' estimates of housing value.A/ Because a common&#13;
definition of the dependent variable is used for renters, the estimated&#13;
parameters are more comparable for renters than for owners. For owners,&#13;
because amortization ratios (ratios of rent to value) sometimes decrease with&#13;
2/ See Hausman (1981) for detailed discussion of the implicit behavioral&#13;
foundation behind a logarithmic demand model.&#13;
3/ Kumasi, Ghana and Kingston, Jamaica owners are not included because the&#13;
sample size is too small.&#13;
4/ Table 3 shows which method was used for each city. For cities which used&#13;
amortized housing values, amortization rates were based on percentages of&#13;
value generally assumed to be between I and 1.5 percent of value per&#13;
month, with this amortization rate fixed for all units in the sample.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 2&#13;
ESTIMATED PARAMETERS OF HOUSING EXPENDITURE FUNCTIONS FOR RENTERS&#13;
LOG         HH    HH SIZE                                INCOME          ESTIMATED EFFECT&#13;
COUNTRY         CITY                   CONSTANT   INCOME         SIZE   SOUARED  R-SOUARED           N   CONF. INTERVALS    CHANGE IN HHSIZE&#13;
COLOMBIA      BOGOTA        (COEF)         1.11       0.66       0.09      -0.006       .40       1016   (LOWER)   0.60    (1 TO 2)    0.07&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                 23.53       2.49       1.97                          (UPPER)   0.72    (5 TO 6)    0.02&#13;
(1978)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.006      0.025                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.03&#13;
CALI          (COEF)         2.81       0.44      0.13      -0.006        .27       257   (LOWER)   0.33    (I TO 2)    0.11&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                   8.03       1.81      0.95                          (UPPER)   0.55    (5 TO 6)    0.06&#13;
(1978)        (PROB&gt;T)                  0.001     0.036      0.172                                             (9 TO 10)   0.01&#13;
EGYPT         CAIRO         (COEF)         0.25       0.46      -0.17      0.010        .16       303   (LOWER)   0.34    (1 TO 2)   -0.14&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                   7.37       1.79      1.22                          (UPPER)   0.59    (5 TO 6)   -0.06&#13;
(1981)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.037      0.112                                             (9 TO 10)   0.02&#13;
BENI SUEF    (COEF)          -1.2       0.51      0.38      -0.047       .25         63   (LOWER)   0.22    (1 TO 2)    0.24&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                   3.56       1.39      1.59                          (UPPER)   0.80    (5 TO 6)   -0.13&#13;
(1981)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.085      0.059                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.51&#13;
EL SALVADOR  SANTA ANA    (COFFI           0.37       0.48       0.13      -0.014       . I131   (LOWER)   0.27    (i TO 2)    0.08&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                   4.49       1.59      2.00                          (UPPER)   0.69    (5 TO 6)   -0.03&#13;
(1980)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.057      0.024                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.14&#13;
SONSONATE    (COEF)          0.79       0.50      -0.10      0.007       .16         83   (LOWER)   0.25    (I TO 2)   -0.08&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                   4.04       1.19      1.00                          (UPPER)   0.75    (5 TO 6)   -0.03&#13;
(1980)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.119      0.160                                             (9 TO 10)   0.03&#13;
GHANA         KUMASI        (COEF)         0.82       0.33       0.02       0.000       .11       814   (LOWER)   0.25    (1 TO 2)    0.02          W&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                   8.67      0.58       0.16                          (UPPER)   0.41    (5 TO 6)    0.02&#13;
(1980)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.281      0.436                                             (9 TO 10)   0.02&#13;
INDIA         BANGALORE    (COEF)          0.66       0.58      -0.08      0.003        .18      1041   (LOWER)   0.50    (1 TO 2)   -0.08&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                  14.89      2.38       1.21                          (UPPER)   0.66    (5 TO 6)   -0.05&#13;
(197S)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.009      0.113                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.03&#13;
JAMAICA       KINGSTON      (COEF)         -.12       0.70       0.16      -0.012       .30       223   (LOWER)   0.54    (1 TO 2)    0.13&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                   8.84      2.21       1.88                          (UPPER)   0.86    (5 TO 6)    0.03&#13;
(1975)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.014      0.031                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.07&#13;
KOREA         SEOUL         (COEF)         5.04       0.45       0.07      -0.004       .15       952   (LOWER)   0.38    (1 TO 2)    0.05&#13;
(CHONSEI)    (T-STAT)                  13.48       1.65      0.93                          (UPPER)   0.52    (5 TO 6)    0.02&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.050      0.176                                            (9 TO iO)  -0.02&#13;
SUSAN         (COEF)         6.26       0.31      0.05      -0.001       .08        508   (LOWER)   0.17    (1 TO 2)    0.05&#13;
(CHONSEI)    (T-STAT)                   4.47      0.89       0.25                          (UPPER)   0.45    (5 TO 6)    0.04&#13;
(1979)        (PRO0&gt;T)                 0.001      0.187      0.401                                            (9 TO 10)   0.02&#13;
TAEGW         (COEF)         4.95       0.44      0.03      -0.003       .23        292   (LOWER)   0.30    (1 TO 2)    0.02&#13;
(CHONSEI)    (T-STAT)                  6.52       0.41       0.41                          (UPPER)   0.57    (5 TO 6)   -0.01&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.341      0.341                                            (9 TO iO)  -0.03&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 2&#13;
ESTIMATED PARAMETERS OF HOUSING EXPENDITURE FUNCTIONS FOR RENTERS&#13;
LOG         HH    HH SIZE                                INCOME         ESTIMATED EFFECT&#13;
COUNTRY         CITY                   CONSTANT   INCOME         SIZE   SOUARED  R-SQUARED          N   CONF. INTERVALS    CHANGE IN HHSIZE&#13;
KOREA         KWANGUJU      (COEF)         2.70       0.62       0.09      -0.002       .32        134   (LOWER)   0.43    (1 TO 2)    0.08&#13;
(CHONSEI)    (T-STAT)                  6.75       0.68       0.18                          (UPPER)   0.80    (5 TO 6)    0.06&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                  0.001     0.249      0.429                                            (9 TO 10)   0.04&#13;
OTH. K. C.   (COEF)          3.33       0.54      0.04       0.002        .17      1000   (LOWER)   0.45    (i TO 2)    0.05&#13;
(CHONSEI)    (T-STAT)                  11.56      0.77       0.36                          (UPPER)   0.64    (5 TO 6)    0.07&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.221      0.359                                            (9 TO 10)   0.09&#13;
PHILIPPINES  DAVAO          (COEF)         -1.6       0.88       0.00     -0.002       .42       1376   (LOWER)   0.82    (1 TO 2)   -0.01&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                 30.59       0.02       1.02                          (UPPER)   0.93    (5 TO 6)   -0.03&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                  0.001     0.492      0.154                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.05&#13;
MANILA        (COEF)         1.27       0.56      0.01      -0.002        .22       605   (LOWER)   0.48    (1 TO 2)   -0.00&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                  13.08      0.14       0.85                         (UPPER)   0.65    (5 TO 6)   -0.02&#13;
(1983)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.446      0.197                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.04&#13;
U.S.          PITTSBURGH   (COEF)          3.07       0.26      -0.02     -0.002        .15       946   (LOWER)   0.22    (1 TO 2)   -0.03&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                  12.65      0.70       0.44                         (UPPER)   0.30    (5 TO 6)   -0.05&#13;
(1975)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.242      0.330                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.06&#13;
PHOENIX       (COEF)         3.68       O.19      0.12      -0.015       .13        918   (LOWER)   0.14    (I TO 2)    0.07&#13;
(NET RENT)   (T-STAT)                  10.70      3.67       3.22                         (UPPER)   0.21    (5 TO 6)   -0.05&#13;
(1975)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.001      0.001                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.17&#13;
NOTES:&#13;
(1) FOR RENTERS. RENTS ARE NET OF UTILITIES BUT INCLUDE AMORTIZED KEY MONEY                                                                 F&#13;
IN EGYPT&#13;
(2) (PROB&gt;T) IS THE PROBABILITY OF OBSERVING THE SAMPLE UNDER THE NULL&#13;
HYPOTHESIS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 3&#13;
ESTIMATED PARAMETERS OF HOUSING EXPENOITURE FUNCTIONS FOR OWNERS&#13;
LOG         HH    HH SIZE                                INCOME         ESTIMATED EFFECT&#13;
COUNTRY         CITY                  CONSTANT   INCOME         SIZE   SQUARED  R-SQUARED          N   CONF. INTERVALS    CHANGE IN HHSIZE&#13;
COLOMBIA      BOGOTA        (COEF)         0.77      0.75      -0.00      -0.003       .49       821   (LOWER)   0.70    (i TO 2)   -0.01&#13;
(IMPUTED)    (T-STAT)                 27.79       O.i4       1.03                         (UPPER)   0.80    (5 TO 6)   -0.03&#13;
(1978)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.444     O.152                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.06&#13;
CALI          (COEF)         1.25      0.69      -0.05      -0.000       .38       256   (LOWER)   0.57    (1 TO 2)   -0.05&#13;
(IMPUTED)    (T-STAT)                 12.32       0.63       0.08                         (UPPER)   0.80    (5 TO 6)   -0.05&#13;
(t978)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.265     0.468                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.05&#13;
EGYPT        CAIRO          (COEF)        0.89       0.17       0.12      -0.009       .06        76   (LOWER)  -0.06    (I TO 2)    0.10&#13;
(IMPUTED)    (T-STAT)                  1.47       0.58      0.48                          (UPPER)   0.41    (5 TO 6)    0.02&#13;
(1981)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.073      0.282     0.316                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.05&#13;
BENI SUEF    (COEF)          -.09      0.42       0.14      -0.003       .23        63   (LOWER)   0.16    (1 TO 2)    0.13&#13;
(VALUE)       (T-STAT)                 3.19       1.00      0.29                          (UPPER)   0.69    (5 TO 6)    0.11&#13;
(1981)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.161     0.386                                            (9 TO 10)   0.08&#13;
EL SALVADOR  SANTA ANA    (COEF)           -2.5       1.11     -0.06      -0.004       .37        I69   (inl FD    n.89    (1 TO 2)   -0.C7&#13;
(IMPUTED)    (T-STAT)                 10.05       0.50      0.44                          (UPPER)   1.33    (5 TO 6)   -0.10&#13;
(1980)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.309     0.330                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.13&#13;
SONSONATE    (COEF)         0.39       0.79      -0.13       0.001       .57        27   (LOWER)   0.49    (1 TO 2)   -0.13&#13;
(IMPUTED)    (T-STAT)                  5.23       0.78      0.08                          (UPPER)   1.10    (5 TO 6)   -0.12&#13;
(1980)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.222     0.461                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.11&#13;
GHANA         KUMASI        (COEF)               .          .          .               .            .   (LOWER)    .        (1 TO 2)      .&#13;
(IMPUTED)    (T-STAT)                    .         .          .                           (UPPER)    .       (5 TO 6)       .&#13;
(1980)        (PROB&gt;T)                  .          .          .                                              (9 TO 10)&#13;
INDIA        BANGALORE   -(COEF)           2.84      0.43      -0.17       0.007       .15       205   (LOWER)   0.27    (1 TO 2)   -0.15&#13;
(HEDONIC)    (T-STAT)                  5.34       2.85       2.13                         (UPPER)   0.59    (5 TO 6)   -0.09&#13;
(1975)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.002     0.017                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.03&#13;
JAMAICA      KINGSTON       (COEF)          .          .         .          .          .            .   (LOWER)    .       (I TO 2)&#13;
(T-STAT)                  .          .          .                           (UPPER)    .       (5 TO 6)&#13;
(1975)        (PROB&gt;T)                                                                                       (9 TO 10)&#13;
KOREA         SEOUL         (COEF)         6.06      0.44      -0.04       0.002       .12       952   (LOWER)   0.36    (1 To 2)   -0.03&#13;
(VALUE)       (T-STAT)                11.03       1.00      0.79                          (UPPER)   0.52    (5 TO 6)   -0.01&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.159     0.215                                            (9 TO 10)   0.00&#13;
BUSAN         (COEF)         5.93      0.45      -0.05       0.002       .10       296   (LOWER)   0.29    (I TO 2)   -0.04&#13;
(VALUE)       (T-STAT)                 5.55       0.49      0.19                          (UPPER)   0.62    (5 TO 6)   -0.03&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.312     0.425                                            (9 TO 10)  -0.01&#13;
TAEGU         (COEF)         6.32      0.47      -0.19       0.011       .18       152   (LOWER)   0.30    (1 TO 2)   -0.15&#13;
(VALUE)       (T-STAT)                 5.53       2.39       1.78                         (UPPER)   0.64    (5 TO 6)   -0.07&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.009     0.039                                            (9 TO 10)   0.02&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 3&#13;
ESTIMATED PARAMETERS OF HOUSING EXPENDITURE FUNCTIONS FOR OWNERS&#13;
LOG          HH    HH SIZE                               INCOME          ESTIMATED EFFECT&#13;
COUNTRY         CITY                   CONSTANT   INCOME         SIZE   SOUARED  R-SOUARED           N   CONF. INTERVALS    CHANGE IN HHSIZE&#13;
KOREA         KWANGJU       (COEF)         7.53       0.41      -0.27       0.018       .14         84   (LOWER)   0.19    (1 TO 2)   -0.22&#13;
(VALUE)       (T-STAT)                  3.69       1.51       1.13                         (UPPER)   0.64    (5 TO 6)   -0.07&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                  0.001      0.067     0.131                                             (9 TO 10)   0.07&#13;
OTH. K. C.   (COEF)          2.16       0.79      -0.12       0.003       .26       779   (LOWER)   0.69    (1 TO 2)   -0.11&#13;
(VALUE)       (T-STAT)                 16.20       2.14      0.58                          (UPPER)   0.88    (5 TO 6)   -0.08&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                  0.001     0.016      0.279                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.06&#13;
PHILIPPINES  DAVAO          (COEF)         -3.2       0.99       0.04      -0.004       .28       1968   (LOWER)   0.91    (1 TO 2)    0.02&#13;
(IMPUTED)    (T-STAT)                  26.98      0.91        1.37                         (UPPER)   1.06    (5 TO 6)   -0.01&#13;
(1979)        (PROB&gt;T)                  0.001     0.181      0.085                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.04&#13;
MANILA        (COEF)         2.46       0.57      -0.02      -0.000       .31       390   (LOWER)   0.48    (1 TO 2)   -0.03&#13;
(IMPUTED)    (T-STAT)                  13.34      0.53       0.06                          (UPPER)   0.65    (5 TO 6)   -0.03&#13;
(1983)        (PROB&gt;T)                  0.001     0.298      0.477                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.03&#13;
U.S.          PITTSBURGH   (COEF)          3.50       0.18       0.08      -0.005       .21       2378   (LOWER)   0.16    (1 TO 2)    0.07&#13;
(HEDONIC)    (T-STAT)                  16.89      5.06       2.83                          (UPPER)   0.20    (5 TO 6)    0.03&#13;
(1975)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.001      0.002                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.01&#13;
PHOENIX       (COEF)         3.62       0.18      0.13      -0.011        .24      2284   (LOWER)   0.16    (I TO 2)    0.10&#13;
(HEDONIC)    (T-STAT)                  18.92      9.52       6.89                          (UPPER)   0.20    (5 TO 6)    0.02&#13;
(1975)        (PROB&gt;T)                 0.001      0.001      0.001                                             (9 TO 10)  -0.07&#13;
NOTES:&#13;
(i) FOR RENTERS, RENTS ARE NET OF UTILITIES BUT INCLUDE AMORTIZED KEY MONEY&#13;
IN EGYPT&#13;
(2) (PROB&gt;T) IS THE PROBABILITY OF OBSERVING THE SAMPLE UNDER THE NULL&#13;
HYPOTHESIS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
income, it may be that income elassticities derived from amortized housing&#13;
value will exceed those derived from imputed rent.5/&#13;
Most of the columns in Tables 2 and 3 are self-explanatory except&#13;
for columns 7 and 8. Column 7 gives confidence intervals for the income&#13;
elasticity, whose point estimate is, of course, the coefficient of log&#13;
income. The upper and lower bounds are plus and minus two standard errors,&#13;
respectively. Column 8 contains estimates of the combined effects of the two&#13;
household size variables. For example, the point estimates for household size&#13;
and its square imply the following pattern for Bogota renters: adding an&#13;
individual to a one-person household increases housing consumption by an&#13;
estimated 7 percent; the corresponding increase for a 5-person household is&#13;
only 2 percent; and housing consumption declines 3 percent when household&#13;
sizes increase from 9 to 10.&#13;
In general, the results presented in Tables 2 and 3 are remarkably&#13;
consistent with results from developed countries (see Mayo, 1981). The&#13;
regression fits are typical for this type of equation: typical R-squared&#13;
statistics are in the .1 to .3 range (minimum is .06, maximum, 57). Fits are&#13;
similar for owners and renters.&#13;
The median of all renter income elasticities is .49; developing&#13;
country elasticities range from .31 (Busan) to .88 (Davao). Most are&#13;
clustered between .4 and .6. Interestingly, the U.S. elasticities are the&#13;
lowest. The income coefficients have been estimated with good precision;&#13;
typical standard errors are .05, and the largest is .14. The last column of&#13;
5/   Direct tests of this using data from Cairo indicate that income elasti-&#13;
cities of housing value and owners' imputed market rent are in fact&#13;
significantly different, with the former larger.  Forthcoming research on&#13;
household specific rent-to-value ratios will examine these issues in more&#13;
detail.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
the tables shows an income elasticity confidence interval of plus or minus two&#13;
standard errors. Among renter equations, all interval boundaries are within&#13;
the zero-one interval, and most are within the range .2 - .8. This is strong&#13;
evidence of inelastic demand for housing among renters.&#13;
The median of all point estimates of owner income elasticities is&#13;
.46 with extremes of .17 in Cairo and 1.11 in Santa Ana. The majority of&#13;
point estimates lie between .4 and .6. Again, the estimates are quite&#13;
precise. Typical standard errors for the log income coefficient are around&#13;
.07, and all are less than .14. Two-standard-deviation confidence intervals&#13;
reveal three cities where the interval contains unit elasticity: Davao,&#13;
Sonsonate, and Santa Ana. Figures 1 and 2 present these intervals graphically&#13;
for ease of comparison. Most of the estimated intervals are contained within&#13;
the interval [.2, 1]. In 9 of 14 cases where comparison is possible,&#13;
estimated developing country owner income elasticities are greater than those&#13;
of renters; this finding parallels findings in the literature for developed&#13;
countries (Mayo, 1981). The data from the U.S. cities is less conclusive:&#13;
all elasticities, renters and owners, are lower than expected. Comparing&#13;
expenditure equations across countries reveals practically no systematic&#13;
variation of income elasticities with country or city income level or size,&#13;
but considerable variation in intercepts, which are positively related to&#13;
average city income. Rent-to-income ratios therefore decline systematically&#13;
with income within cities, but increase with income across cities. This&#13;
relationship will be explored in detail in Section 3.&#13;
Household size is the sole demographic variable included in the&#13;
simple models (along with its square). While it is expected that consumption&#13;
of housing increases with household size, some analysts have hypothesized&#13;
that, for very large households, housing consumption is crowded out by food&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 1&#13;
INTERVAL ESTIMATES OF RENTER INCOME ELASTICITIES&#13;
1. 2-&#13;
E&#13;
L  0. 8-&#13;
AT&#13;
T  0.4 a                    i          t                 I&#13;
I                           I. 4-&#13;
0.0-&#13;
9    S    9    C    C    C    0    K    K    K    M    O    p    P    S    S                  S     T&#13;
A    E    0    U    A    A    A    I    U    W    A             T    H      I    A    E    0        A&#13;
N    N    G    S       I    L    V    N    M    A    N    H    0    T    N    0               N    E&#13;
G     I    0    A    R       I    A    c    A    N        I    .    E    T    T    U          S    c&#13;
A          T    N    0             a    S    S    G    L              N    s    A    L    0    U&#13;
L    S    A                             T     I    J    A    K        I    S                  N&#13;
a    U                                  a           U           .     X    U    A             A&#13;
R    E                                  N                                   R    N            T&#13;
E    F                                                          C           G    A            E&#13;
H&#13;
CITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 2&#13;
INTERVAL ESTIMATES OF OWNER INCOME ELASTICITIES&#13;
1. 2&#13;
E&#13;
L  0. O-&#13;
A&#13;
s&#13;
T  0. 1-&#13;
I~~j                      &#13;
I  °. 4-&#13;
0. 2- &#13;
0. 0-&#13;
e    9    9    9    C    C    D    K    K    K    M    0    P    P    S    S    S    T&#13;
A    E    0    U    A    A    A    I    U    W    A    T    H    I    A    E    0    A&#13;
N    N    G    S    I    L    V    N    M    A    N    H    a    T    N    0    N    E&#13;
G    I    a    A    R    I    A    G    A    N    I    .    E    T    T    U    S    G&#13;
A          T    N    0           0    S    S    G    L              N    S    A    L    0    U&#13;
L    S    A                            T    I    J    A    K    I    B                     N&#13;
a    U                                 a          U           .    X    U    A             A&#13;
R    E                                 N                                 R    N            T&#13;
E    F                                                        C          G    A            E&#13;
H&#13;
CITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
consumption. If this hypothesis is correct we expect a positive coefficient&#13;
for household size but a negative' coefficient for household size squared. In&#13;
fact, 11 of 16 LDC renter equations follow this pattern, but only in Bogota&#13;
and Santa Ana are both variables significantly different from zero and of the&#13;
expected sign. The "turning point," or size at which other expenditures begin&#13;
to crowd out additional housing, is a 6-person household in Santa Ana and a 7-&#13;
person household in Bogota, but in general the estimated relationships are&#13;
quite flat.  Among LDC owners household size appears to be negatively related&#13;
to housing expenditures, with 11 of 14 coefficients of household size&#13;
negative, although these relationships are extremely weak. The "crowding out'&#13;
pattern found for renters is evident in only 3 of 13 owner estimates (although&#13;
none of these are significant). These results for owners are not surprising&#13;
since higher adjustment costs presumably lead owners to make longer term&#13;
housing decisions less strongly related to current demographic&#13;
characteristics.&#13;
2. Evaluating the Simple Model Wfith Data from Fgypt and the Philippines&#13;
The simple model estimated in 16 cities and presented in Section 2.1&#13;
is easily criticized, but as noted, this model was chosen because it could be&#13;
replicated with many existing data sets. In this section we will present&#13;
estimates from a more complex model which can be estimated with data from&#13;
Egypt and the Philippines. These estimates are of interest in their own&#13;
right, but can also be used to evaluate the simple model. In particular, we&#13;
will compare income elasticities from the two models using these data sets to&#13;
test the robustness of the estimated income elasticity.&#13;
Possible criticisms of the simple estimates include the following:&#13;
1. Current income is inappropriate when estimating the demand for a&#13;
durable good. Some long-term measure, "permanent" income, or income adjusted&#13;
for place in the life cycle, is more closely related to the demand for&#13;
housing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
2. The simple model assumes no variation in the price of housing&#13;
within the sample. In fact, housing prices vary over space within a city, for&#13;
example due to variation in land prices. If, as in the Muth-Mills framework,&#13;
housing prices and income are correlated, then not only do we have no estimate&#13;
of the price elasticity, but our measure of the income elasticity is biased.&#13;
3. In addition to household size, other demographic characteristics&#13;
such as age of head and sex of head are related to housing consumption. To&#13;
the extent that these characteristics are correlated with household size,&#13;
household size results may also be biased.&#13;
4. Government programs which provide or subsidize housing&#13;
consumption may distort estimates which are implicitly assumed to be market&#13;
outcomes.&#13;
5. Much of the sample may be "out of equilibrium," and estimates&#13;
based on restricted samples such as recent movers or people satisfied with&#13;
their housing choices would be more appropriate.&#13;
6. The definition of a market used here is inappropriate. We&#13;
should estimate demand relations (a) for submarkets stratified by income, or&#13;
ethnic group, or location within the city, or (b) use national or regional&#13;
estimates which are more appropriate because the market is actually wider.&#13;
7. Housing consumption is a joint decision (with tenure choice, or&#13;
with moving, or with upgrading) and so simultaneous models of these choices&#13;
are appropriate.&#13;
8. Housing demand is better treated in a demand-for-characteristics&#13;
framework rather than as a composite good. Demands for space, location,&#13;
quality, and other attributes, however defined, are likely to differ from one&#13;
another.&#13;
9. Our choice of functional form is inappropriate. The log&#13;
expenditure function does not satisfy the postulates of demand theory except&#13;
as a local approximation. Linear models or systems of demand equations would&#13;
be more appropriate.&#13;
This is not an exhaustive list, but one which reflects much of the recent&#13;
literature on housing demand 6/&#13;
6/   Representative references on each respective point include:  (1) Mayo&#13;
(1981), deLeeuw (1971), and Muth (1960); (2) Polinsky (1977); (3) Pollak&#13;
and Wales (1981); (4) Olsen and Barton (1983); (5) Ihlanfeldt (1981),&#13;
Hanushek and Quigley (1978); (6) Straszheim (1975), Linneman (1981);&#13;
(7) Lee and Trost (1978), Weinberg et al. (1981); (8) Rosen (1974),&#13;
Quigley (1982); (9) Phlips (1974). Obviously this list is not&#13;
exhaustive.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
This section compares results for the simple model used above to&#13;
results from a more complete model which includes prices and other additional&#13;
variables. This so-called "complete" model is also the basis for detailed&#13;
estimates of price and income elasticities in Section 2.3.&#13;
How does this new model fare with respect to each of the nine&#13;
criticisms listed above? The responses corresponding to each criticism are as&#13;
follows:&#13;
1. Substitute total consumption for total income in the "complete"&#13;
demand equation. Since the permanent income hypothesis states that&#13;
consumption is strongly related to the unobservable permanent income, accept&#13;
the hypothesis and use consumption directly as a proxy for the unobservable&#13;
variable. Results for other permanent income measures are summarized in&#13;
Section 3 and will be the subject of a separate paper.&#13;
2.  Assume a simple two-factor model of housing production, where&#13;
one-factor price (land) varies over space, and other input prices do not. Use&#13;
the log of land price in the expenditure equation and use to derive price&#13;
elasticities, as explained in Section 3.&#13;
3. Add age of the household head, its square, and sex of the&#13;
household head to the equation.&#13;
4. Include dummy variables for government programs where&#13;
appropriate.&#13;
5. Include length of tenure, and its square, directly in the&#13;
expenditure relation. There are two possible problems with keeping recent&#13;
movers and long-time residents in the same sample, It may be that recent&#13;
movers are closer to equilibrium, on average, but that these departures from&#13;
equilibrium are symmetric about the average demand relation. Then estimates&#13;
from the pooled sample are unbiased but inefficient. On the other hand, large&#13;
negative departures may require adjustment of consumption immediately, while&#13;
those "overconsuming" feel lessE pressure to adjust. Then departures from the&#13;
equilibrium relation are not symmetric in the full sample, and results are&#13;
biased. Including length of tenure and its square corrects for this bias. It&#13;
does not necessarily improve efficiency.&#13;
6. Some choice must be made regarding market definition, and we&#13;
choose the common assumption that the market is coincident with the&#13;
metropolitan area. See FollairL and Malpezzi (1980) for tests of this&#13;
assumption using U.S. data.&#13;
7. Studies such as Lee and Trost, and Rosen, find modest impacts on&#13;
income elasticities of demand rhen simultaneous methods are used.  Estimated&#13;
income and price elasticities from this type of study are in line with single&#13;
equation estimates; this is an area we will explore in future work. For now,&#13;
a few very simple models (pooled samples, with and without dummy variables for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
tenure) were estimated, and income elasticities were reasonbly robust (results&#13;
are available upon request).&#13;
8. We view the characteristics demand approach and the composite&#13;
demand approach as complementary techniques. The definition of a good is&#13;
always problematic in real-world demand analysis. See Follain and Jimenez&#13;
(forthcoming, b) for estimates using Colombian, Philipppine and Korean data.&#13;
9. Mayo's (1981) survey highlights the fact that qualitatively&#13;
similar results are obtained using linear and log-linear models. Log models&#13;
have their own desirable properties such as reduced heteroskedastity, and&#13;
reducing the influence of extreme rents and incomes on parameter estimates.&#13;
Tables 4 to 9 present estimates for the "complete" models described&#13;
above for Cairo, Beni Suef and Manila. The results from simple models are&#13;
also presented for comparison. These results are for gross rents (including&#13;
utilities) and, hence, differ slightly from Tables 2 and 3. The tables also&#13;
present the differences in the estimates between the two models, and the&#13;
standardized differences, i.e. the difference in the coefficients divided by&#13;
the standard error of the complete model. Formal tests are not presented,&#13;
because the simple and complete models were estimated on different samples.&#13;
The larger models clearly fit the data better than the simple&#13;
models. R-squared statistics typically increase from the range .2--.3 to the&#13;
range .4-.6, and the increase is impressive even after adjustment for degrees&#13;
of freedom.&#13;
Estimated renter income elasticities of demand are larger in the&#13;
complete model, but owner elasticities are remarkably insensitive to&#13;
specification. No obvious pattern of change in the precision of the income&#13;
estimates emerges. Despite the increase in estimated renter income&#13;
elasticities in several samples, the results are still consistent with&#13;
inelastic demand, except in Manila where the point estimate now approaches&#13;
unity. Price elasticities implied by the land price coefficients are close to&#13;
-1. Section 2.3, below, presents alternative income and price elasticity&#13;
results in more detail.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
TABLE 4&#13;
COMPARISON OF SMALL A1D LARGE DEMAND MODELS:  BENI SUEF RENTERS&#13;
COMPLETE     SIMPLE       DIFFERENCE   SIANDARDIZED&#13;
MODEI,     MODEL                       DIFFERENCE&#13;
INTERCEPT  (COEFF)           0.371B      -.527           0.905         O.S52&#13;
(STD ERROR)      1.641)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.409&#13;
LOG INCOME (COEFF)           0.65'3      0.541           0.118         0.843&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.14        0.15&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.000       0.409&#13;
LOG PRICE  (COEFF)           0.105&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.09)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.125&#13;
AGE        (COEFF)           0.002&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.050&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.484&#13;
AGE,       (COEFF)           -.000&#13;
SQUARED    (STD ERROR)       0.001&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.504&#13;
HHSIZE     (COEFF)           0.092       0.125           -.033          -.165&#13;
(STO ERROR)      0.200        0.320&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.324       0.000&#13;
HHSIZE     (COEFF)           -.011        -.017          0.006          0.300&#13;
SQUARED    (STD ERROR)       0.020       0.030&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.708       0.124&#13;
FEMALE     (COEFF)           -.112&#13;
HEAD       (STO ERROR)       0.250&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.672&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           -.046&#13;
TENURE     (STD ERROR)       0.020&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.967&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           0.001&#13;
TENURE,    (STO ERROR)       0.0oco&#13;
SQUARED    (PROB&gt;T)          0.0114&#13;
GOVT.      (COEFF)           -.201&#13;
HOUSING    (STD ERROR)       0.3110&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.7410&#13;
PUBLIC     (COEFF)&#13;
HOUSING    (STD ERROR)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)&#13;
R-SOUARED                    .56          .16&#13;
ADJ. R-SQUARED               .47&#13;
SAMPLE SIZE                   60          55&#13;
1/ CURRENT EXPENDITURES USED IN COMPLETE MOOE4,, CURRENT INCOMES. IN SIMPLE MODEL&#13;
2/ PRICE=LOT PRICE-(EST. LAND VAiLUE*BLDG AREA)/NO. OF UNITS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
TABLE 5&#13;
COMPARISON OF SMALL AND LARGE DEMAND MODELS: BENI SUEF OWNERS&#13;
COMPLETE     SIMPLE        DIFFERENCE   STANDARDIZED&#13;
MODEL      MODEL                       DIFFERENCE&#13;
INTERCEPT  (COEFF)           6.058       0.047           6.011         2.783&#13;
(STD ERROR)      2.160&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.012&#13;
LOG INCOME (COEFF)           0.292       0.422           -.130          -.684&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.19         0.13&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.081        0.003&#13;
LOG PRICE  (COEFF)           -.007&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.140&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.519&#13;
AGE        (COEFF)           -.079&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.050&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.924&#13;
AGE.       (COEFF)           0.001&#13;
SQUARED    (STD ERROR)       0.000&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.055&#13;
HHSIZE     (COEFF)           0.235       0.142           0.093         0.581&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.160       0.142&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.090       0.065&#13;
HHSIZE     (COEFF)           -.018        -.003          -.015           -1.5&#13;
SOUARED    (STD ERROR)       0.010       0.010&#13;
(PRO8&gt;T)         0.945       O.S20&#13;
FEMALE     (COEFF)           0.307&#13;
HEAD       (STO ERROR)       0.300&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.168&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           -.066&#13;
TENURE     (STO ERROR)       0.020&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.995&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           0.001&#13;
TENURE,    (STO ERROR)       0.000&#13;
SQUARED    (PROB&gt;T)          0.014&#13;
GOVT.      (COEFF)&#13;
HOUSING    (STD ERROR)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)&#13;
PUBLIC     (COEFF)&#13;
HOUSING    (STD ERROR)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)&#13;
R-SOUARED                    .65          .23&#13;
ADJ. R-SQUARED               .34&#13;
SAMPLE SIZE                   20          63&#13;
1/ CURRENT EXPENDITURES USED IN COMPLETE MODEL. CURRENT INCOMES. IN SIMPLE MODEL&#13;
i/ PRICEaLOT PRICE-(EST. LAND VALUEsBLDG AREA)/NO. OF UNITS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
TABLE 6&#13;
COMPARISON tlF SMALL AND LARGE DEMAND MODELS: CAIRO RENTERS&#13;
COMPLETE     SIMPLE        DIFFERENCE   STANDARDIZED&#13;
MODEL      MODEL                       DIFrERENCE&#13;
INTERCEPT  (COEFF)           2.399        0.565           t.834         3.335&#13;
(STO ERROR)      0.550&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.000&#13;
LOG INCOME (COEFF)           0.508        0.420           0.098          1.760&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.05         0.05&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.000        0.000&#13;
LOG PRICE  (COEFF)           0.076&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.030&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.006&#13;
AGE         (COEFF)           -.018&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.010&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.963&#13;
AGE,       (COEFF)           0.000&#13;
SQUARED    (STO ERROR)       0.000&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.024&#13;
HHSIZE      (COEFF)           -.033       -.059           0.026         0.433&#13;
(STO ERROR)      0.060        0.080&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.708        0.000&#13;
HHSIZE      (COEFF)          0.005        0.003           0.002         0.420&#13;
SQUARED    (STD ERROR)       0.005        0.010&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.160        0.006&#13;
FEMALE     (COEFF)           0.174&#13;
HEAD       (STO ERROR)       0.080&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.016&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           -.059&#13;
TENURE     (STO ERROR)       0.010&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          1.000&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           0.001&#13;
TENURE,    (STD ERROR)       0.000&#13;
SQUARED    (PROB&gt;T)          0.000&#13;
GOVT.      (COEFF)            1.586&#13;
HOUSING    (STO ERROR)        1.670&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.172&#13;
PUBLIC      (COEFF)           -.083&#13;
HOUSING    (STD ERROR)        1.090&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.530&#13;
R-SQUARED                     .t;1        .17&#13;
ADO. R-SOUARED                .58&#13;
SAMPLE SIZE                  1i51         296&#13;
1/ CURRENT EXPENDITURES USED IN COMPLETE MODEL, CURRENT INCOMES. IN SIMPLE MODEL&#13;
2/ PRICE-LOT PRICE-(EST. LAND VJkLUf*BLDG AREA)/NO. OF UNITS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
TABLE 7&#13;
COMPARISON OF SMALL AND LARGE OEMAND MODELS: CAIRO OWNERS&#13;
COMPLETE      SIMPLE       DIFFERENCE   STANDARDIZED&#13;
MODEL      NODEL                        DIFFERENCE&#13;
INTERCEPT  (COEFF)           2.409         1.543          0.866          0.671&#13;
(STD ERROR)       1.290&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.032&#13;
LOG INCOME (COEFF4            0.3S0       0.372            -.022         -.169&#13;
(STD ERROR)       0.13        0.08&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.004       0.032&#13;
LOG PRICE  (COEFF)           0.112&#13;
(STO ERROR)       0.060&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.032&#13;
AGE        (COEFF)            0.006&#13;
(STD ERROR)       0.030&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.421&#13;
AGE,        (COEFF)           -.000&#13;
SOUARED    (STO ERROR)        0.000&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.630&#13;
HHSIZE      (COEFF)           0.120        -.258          0.378          2.520&#13;
(STD ERROR)       0.150       0.140&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.213       0.004&#13;
HHSIZE      (COEFF)           -.00o        0.024           -.032          -3.2&#13;
SQUARED    (STD ERROR)        0.010       0.010&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.787       0.033&#13;
FEMALE     (COEFF)            -.578&#13;
HEAD        (STO ERROR)       0.250&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.989&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)            -.003&#13;
TENURE     (STD ERROR)        0.020&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          0.560&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)            -.000&#13;
TENURE,    (STO ERROR)        0.000&#13;
SOUARED    (PROB&gt;T)           0.579&#13;
GOVT.       (COEFF)&#13;
HOUSING    (STO ERROR)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)&#13;
PUBLIC     (COEFF)&#13;
HOUSING    (STO ERROR)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)&#13;
R-SQUAREO                     .61          .18&#13;
ADJ. R-SOUARED                .58&#13;
SAMPLE SIZE                   151           97&#13;
1/ CURRENT EXPENDITURES USED IN COMPLETE MODEL, CURRENT INCOMES. IN SIMPLE MODEL&#13;
2/ PRICE-LOT PRICE-(EST. LANOD VALUE*SLOO AREA)/NO. OF UNITS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
TABLE 8&#13;
COMPARISON OF SMALL AND LARGE DEMAND MODELS: MANILA RENTERS&#13;
COMPLETE     SIMPLE        DIFFERENCE   STANDARDIZED&#13;
MODEL      MODEL                        DIFFERENCE&#13;
INTERCEPT  (COEFF)           -. 163       0.916           -1.08          -2.04&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.530&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.621&#13;
LOG INCOME (COEFF)           0.921        0.615           0.306          5.100&#13;
(STD ERROR)      O.06         0.042&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.000        0.621&#13;
LOG PRICE  (COEFF)           -.031&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.0310&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.849&#13;
AGE         (COEFF)           -.005&#13;
(STO ERROR)      0.020&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.5S99&#13;
AGE,        (COEFF)          0.OC0&#13;
SQUARED    (STD ERROR)       0.000&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.159&#13;
HHSIZE      (COEFF)           -.036       0.028           -.064          -1.28&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.050        0.040&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.764        0.000&#13;
HHSIZE      (COEFF)          0.002         -.001          0.003          0.750&#13;
SQUARED    (STO ERROR)       0.004        0.003&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.309        0.849&#13;
FEMALE      (COEFF)           -.0J0&#13;
HEAD        (STD ERROR)      0.100&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.71!8&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)            -.014&#13;
TENURE      (STD ERROR)      0.0 10&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          1.000&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           O.001&#13;
TENURE,    (STO ERROR)       0.OI0&#13;
SQUARED    (PROB&gt;T)          0.000&#13;
GOVT.       (COEFF)           -.4448&#13;
HOUSING    (STO ERROR)       0.110&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          1.000&#13;
PUBLIC      (COEFF)&#13;
HOUSING    (STD ERROR)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)&#13;
R-SOUAREO                     .41          .24&#13;
ADd. R-SQUARED                .40&#13;
SAMPLE SIZE                  659          740&#13;
1/ CURRENT EXPENDITURES USED IN CO3MPLETE MODEL. CURRENT INCOMES. IN SIMPLE MODEL&#13;
2/ PRICE-LOT PRICEw(EST. LAND VALIUE*BLDG AREA)/NO. OF UNITS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
TABLE 9&#13;
COMPARISON Of SMALL AND LARGE DEMAND MODELS: MANILA OWNERS&#13;
COMPLEIE     SIMPLE        DIFFERENCE   STANDARDIZED&#13;
MODEL      MODEL                       DIFFERENCE&#13;
INTERCEPT  (COEFF)           -3.91       0.145           -4.05          -6.54&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.620&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)          1.000&#13;
LOG INCOME (COEFF)           0.765       0.740           0.025          0.417&#13;
(STD ERROR)      0.06         0.03&#13;
(PROS&gt;T)         0.000        1.000&#13;
LOG PRICE  (COEFF)           0.350&#13;
(ST  ERROR)     0.040&#13;
4 ROB&gt;T)          0.000&#13;
AGE        (COEFF)           0.009&#13;
(STO ERROR)      0.022&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)'.       0.341&#13;
AGE.       (COEFF)           0.000&#13;
SOUARED    (STO ERROR)       0.000&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.159&#13;
HHSIZE     (COEFF)           -.068        -.027          -.041          -1.02&#13;
(STO ERROR)      0.040        0.030&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.955        0.000&#13;
HIHSIZE    (COEFF)           0.002        0.000          0.001          0.550&#13;
SOUARED    (STD ERROR)       0.002       0.002&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.212        0.000&#13;
FEMALE     (COEFF)           -.061&#13;
HEAD       (STD ERROR)       O.t10&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.710&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           -.009&#13;
TENURE     (STD ERROR)       0.008&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.870&#13;
LENGTH OF  (COEFF)           -.000&#13;
TENURE,    (STO ERROR)       0.000&#13;
SQUARED    (PROB&gt;T)          0.758&#13;
GOVT.      (COEFF)           0.509&#13;
HOUSING    (STO ERROR)       0.090&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)         0.000&#13;
PUBLIC     (COEFF)&#13;
HOUSING    (STD ERROR)&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)&#13;
R-SOUARED                    .44          .26&#13;
ADJ. R-SOUARED               .44&#13;
SAMPLE SIZE                  858          1674&#13;
1/ CURRENT EXPENDITURES USED IN COMPLEI-E MODEL, CURRENT INCOMES. IN SIMPLE MODEL&#13;
2/ PRICE*LOT PRICE-(EST. LAND VALUE'SLE,G AREA)/NO. OF UNITS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
In 5 of 6 sets of estimates, there is little change in the estimated&#13;
effect of household size on consumption. Cairo owners have large but&#13;
offsetting changes in the household size variable and its square. No&#13;
consistent story emerges about the effect of sex on housing consumption. Only&#13;
in Cairo does sex of the household head appear important, but it has the&#13;
opposite sign in the renter and owner results. Differences in sign as well as&#13;
lack of precision make interpretation of this coefficient difficult.&#13;
Length of tenure and housing expenditures are negatively related in&#13;
all estimates. Rents decrease with length of tenure, but at a decreasing&#13;
rate, in the Cairo and Manila renter results and in the Beni Suef owner&#13;
equation. In the other three estimates rents decrease with length of tenure&#13;
at a roughly constant rate. These results are consistent with any or all of&#13;
four explanations. First, as explained above, if positive and negative&#13;
departures from equilibrium (being "off the demand curve" in different&#13;
directions) do not imply symmetric changes in utility, or if adjustment costs&#13;
are different for increasing versus decreasing housing consumption, then long-&#13;
term residents--both owner and renters--may systematically consume more or (as&#13;
here) less than identical recent movers.  Second, in many markets landlords&#13;
customarily grant discounts to long-term renters. There may be lower expected&#13;
supply costs for landlords renting to tenants who are a known quantity; and it&#13;
is easier for landlords to raise new rents as new tenants move in,&#13;
particularly when a key money system is in effect.7/ Third, renters have an&#13;
obvious incentive to remain longer than usual in dwellings which rent for less&#13;
than market value. Fourth, it is plausible that owners who have not moved&#13;
recently fail to keep up completely with changing (and usually increasing)&#13;
71  CKey money is a lump-sum payment to the landlord, collected when the&#13;
tenant moves in.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
market values or imputed rents and thus tend to underestimate them in&#13;
household surveys. It follows that such errors would be greater for long-term&#13;
owners than recent movers.&#13;
Each of these four explanations is consistent with the negative&#13;
coefficients observed. Note that only the first explanation reflects an&#13;
actual diference in quantity consumed. The other three reflect differences in&#13;
actual or imputed prices. Future work using hedonic price techniques can&#13;
disentangle these influences; next, the income and price elasticities from&#13;
these larger models will be discussed in more detail.&#13;
3. Alternative Price and Income Elasticities from Egypt and the Philippines&#13;
The estimates presented above in Section 2.1 are from simple&#13;
expenditure functions (without price terms) and use current income. These&#13;
simple models were estimated because they could be replicated with a wide&#13;
variety of existing data sets, but esimating the same model in different&#13;
markets does not really facilitate comparisons if it is a poor model.&#13;
Fortunately, three of the datasets--Cairo and Beni Suef (Egypt) and Manila are&#13;
from questionnaires which have been designed especially for housing market&#13;
analysis, and a more complete model was estimated in Section 2.2. This&#13;
section will focus on additional estimates from those three cities, with&#13;
particular emphasis on (1) estimates using alternative income measures, and&#13;
(2) price elasticities of demand for housing.&#13;
Section 2.2 presented the full regression results comparing the&#13;
simple model from Section 2.1 to a model with a land price term and several&#13;
additional demographic variables. Since the new demographic variables were&#13;
discussed in some detail we will not discuss them here, in order to focus on&#13;
alternative income and price elasticities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Alternative income elasticities. It is now a standard tenet of the&#13;
theory of the demand for durable goods that the demand for such goods is&#13;
determined by permanent income rather than current income.N' Table 10&#13;
presents point estimates of the Lncome elasticity using various income&#13;
definitions. The first column presents the income elasticity estimate based&#13;
on the specification of Eq. (1) but with gross rent as the dependent&#13;
variable. The other three columnus present elasticity estimates from models&#13;
similar to those presented in Section 2.2, i.e., models which include price&#13;
terms and additional demographic variables. Only the income elasticities are&#13;
reproduced; the full results of each equation are available upon request.&#13;
The second column uses the same income definition as the simple&#13;
model, current income. This persmits direct assessment of the bias in the&#13;
income elasticity which was discussed by Polinsky: if intrametropolitan price&#13;
differences are not accounted for, then the income coefficient will be biased&#13;
downward to the extent that prices and incomes are correlated.  In fact, the&#13;
reverse is true; the estimated income elasticities are lower in the model with&#13;
the price term. This contrasts with the usual finding in IJ.S. markets that&#13;
incomes and prices are negatively correlated and that the simple model is&#13;
downward biased. The apparent paradox can be explained as follows. First,&#13;
income is correlated with the new demographic variables, but positively, so&#13;
bias from omitted demographic variables works in the other direction. Second,&#13;
there is no observed negative correlation between income and prices in these&#13;
samples.9/ If we added another column to Table 10 which contained the simple&#13;
model plus price alone, observed differences in the income coefficient would&#13;
not be significant.&#13;
8/   See Mayo (1981) for a review.&#13;
9/   Manila owners have a positive correlation between price and income (.37);&#13;
in all other samples the correlation is statistically indistinguishable&#13;
from zero.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
lABLE 10&#13;
COMPARISON OF MICRO INCOME ELASTICITIES FROM DIFFERENT MODELS&#13;
SIMPLE MOOEL         LARGE MODEL          LARGE MODEL           LARGE MODEL&#13;
CURRENT INCOME       CURRENT INCOME       CURRENT CONSUMPTION PREDICTED CONSUMPTION&#13;
OWNERS&#13;
BENI SUEF       (COEF)          0.42                 0.23                  0.33                 0.10&#13;
(STD ERR)     0.132                 0.156                0.204                 0.249&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)       0.001                0.070                0.053                 0.344&#13;
CAIRO           (COEF)          0.37                 0.18                  0.33                 0.49&#13;
(STD ERR)     0.084                 0.107                0.139                 0.222&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)      0.001                 0.046                0.009                 0.014&#13;
MANILA          (COEF)          0.61                 0.52                  0.77                 1.04&#13;
(STO ERR)     0.042                 0.050                0.063                 0.095&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)      0.001                 0.001                0.001                 0.001&#13;
RENTERS                             -.&#13;
BENI SUEF       (COEF)          0.54                 0.37                  0.68                 0.49&#13;
(STD ERR)     0.153                 0.100                0.149                 0.197&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)      0.001                 0.001                0.001                 0.006&#13;
CAIRO           (COEF)          0.42                 0.38                  0.55                 0.77&#13;
(STD ERR)     0.052                 0.060                0.051                 0.121&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)      0.001                 0.001                0.001                 0.001&#13;
MANILA          (COEF)          0.81                 0.62                 0.92                  0.77                                         A"&#13;
(STD ERR)     0.043                 0.043                0.056                 0.075&#13;
(PROB&gt;T)      0.001                 0.001                0.001                0.001&#13;
NOTES:&#13;
(1) DEPENDENT VARIABLES ARE LOG GROSS RENTS, INCLUDING UTILITIES.&#13;
(2) SIMPLE MODEL IS SIMILAR TO MODEL USED IN TABLES 2 AND 3. I.E. LOG  OF INCOME. HOUSEHOLD SIZE. AND HHSIZE SQUARED.&#13;
(3) LARGE MODEL IS SIMPLE MODEL PLUS PRICE AND DEMOGRAPHIC VARIABLES.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
The third and fourth columns of Table 10 present estimates from the&#13;
larger model, with income defined as current consumption expenditures and an&#13;
instrumental variable for consumption expenditures, respectively lf  These&#13;
are generally higher than t:he current income elasticities (except for Beni&#13;
Suef owners), but there is no clear pattern of higher or lower income&#13;
elasticities between consumption -and its instrument.&#13;
The evidence from Table 10 can be summarized as follows. There is&#13;
no severe downward bias evident im the simple current income models.&#13;
Permanent income proxies do yield higher elasticity estimates, but the&#13;
differences are comparatively modest. Further evidence on this point can be&#13;
found in Section 2.2. The largesit differences in income elasticity estimates&#13;
are found between models using consumption and those using current income,&#13;
rather than between "large" and "small" models or between models using actual&#13;
consumption and its instrument.&#13;
Price elasticity estimates. Untangling prices and quantities in&#13;
housing market studies is always problematical.  Here we use a simple but&#13;
appealing formulation due to Muth (1971), to estimate price elasticities.&#13;
Assuming a two-input homogeneous production function for housing, where the&#13;
price of one input (land) varies over the sample and the price of the other&#13;
input (structure) is fixed, Muth shows that the expenditure function can be&#13;
written:&#13;
10/  The instrument is formed by using predicted values from a regression&#13;
equation relating reported current household expenditure to variables&#13;
describing the household head's labor force, occupational and educational&#13;
characteristics, and on measures of household assets. It may be noted in&#13;
passing that while "permaneni income" elasticity estimates are generally&#13;
above current income elasticiLty estimates, they do not approach the&#13;
levels indicated in Section 3 which apply to cross-city results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
In R - a + kL (+E p) In pL + Ey ln y + XB&#13;
where kL is the share of land in housing, Ep is the price elasticity, XB are&#13;
the other demand shifters and their coefficients, and other variables are as&#13;
defined before.&#13;
Based on owners' estimates of land values in each of our samples, we&#13;
estimate land prices for each observation based on a regression of land prices&#13;
on several location-specific variables such as distance to central business&#13;
district, the percentage of units in that district with various services, and&#13;
the presence or absence of loational amenities 111 From these estimated land&#13;
prices and house values we estimate typical land shares (kL) in each market&#13;
for owners and for renters.&#13;
The next step is to convert the coefficient of the log of estimated&#13;
land price from the expenditure functions into price elasticities:&#13;
Ep - b/kL - 1&#13;
where b is the estimated coefficient. Table 11 presents these elasticity&#13;
estimates.-2/&#13;
Estimates of the price elasticity are close to 1 in absolute value,&#13;
ranging from -0.76 to -1.08, with the exception of Manila owners whose price&#13;
elasticity is estimated to be -0.4.&#13;
It should be noted that these price elasticity estimates suggest&#13;
that demand is considerably more elastic than previous estimates in the&#13;
ll/ Details of variable construction, and descriptions of the land price&#13;
regressions are available from the authors.&#13;
12/ Note that if land prices are measured with error, the price elasticity is&#13;
biased towards I.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Table 11&#13;
Micro HousiSy Price Elasticity Estimates&#13;
Coefficient of    Standard    Land's   Point!/   Interval-/&#13;
log land price      error       share       Ep           Ep&#13;
Cairo&#13;
Renters                 .076              .03         .60      -.87     (-.77,-.97)&#13;
Owners                  .112              .06         .80      -.86     (-.71,-i.01)&#13;
Beni Suef&#13;
Renters                 .105              .09         .43      -.76     (-.34,-1.17)&#13;
Owners                 -.007              .14         .36    -1.02      (-.25,-1.80)&#13;
Manila&#13;
Renters                -.031              .03         .40    -1.08      (-.93,-1.23)&#13;
Owners                  .350              .04         .55      -.36     (-.22,-.51)&#13;
Notes:  1.  Ep = (coefficient   - 1&#13;
2. Interval estimates are constructed using the coefficient of log price ±&#13;
2 standard errors. The estimate of land's share remains fixed across&#13;
all dwelling units.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
literature suggest. However, a shortcoming of this model is that a unitary&#13;
income elasticity is the null hypothesis, because a land price coefficient of&#13;
zero implies a price elasticity of one. Therefore, the tests of significance&#13;
of land price coefficients should not be interpreted as tests of zero pripe&#13;
elasticity. Neither are they tests of unitary elasticity, because the land's&#13;
share estimate, assumed fixed for the sample, actually has a distribution as&#13;
well. Testing the micro model price elasticities under alternative&#13;
specifications remains high on any agenda for future research.&#13;
Figure 3 presents the demand curves implied by several price&#13;
elasticities which are plausible according to these estimates. The benefits&#13;
or losses to consumers from price changes vary quite a bit depending on which&#13;
price elasticity is correct (indeed, assuming that a single price elasticity&#13;
suffices). Graphically, consider a household consuming one unit of housing&#13;
services at the unit price (i.e. at the point in Figure 3 where all three&#13;
demand curves intersect). The consumer's surplus, or area between the demand&#13;
curve and a horizontal line through the quantity consumed (here one) is a&#13;
measure of how much households would be willing to spend for that amount in&#13;
addition to what they do spend*13/ Programs change prices and quantities, and&#13;
comparing the two areas--before and after the program--is one way to measure&#13;
the benefits of any housing program (or any other event that changes prices&#13;
and quantities).&#13;
A numerical example will illustrate; to facilitate comparisons,&#13;
switch from geometry to algebra. Consider a project which reduces the&#13;
13/ See any microeconomics text for elaboration. Simply put, steep demand&#13;
curves imply that households would pay a high price for the first "bit"&#13;
of housing, a little less for the next bit, or down to the price actually&#13;
paid for the last bit. But they only pay the last, lowest price for all&#13;
"bits."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
FIGURE 3&#13;
DEMAND CURVE'S FROM MICRO PRICE ELASTICITIES&#13;
2. 2&#13;
2. 0-\&#13;
1.8\&#13;
U  1.4\&#13;
N&#13;
T 1.2\&#13;
T&#13;
1.0.&#13;
0. 8&#13;
0.6&#13;
0. 4&#13;
0.50                 0.75                 1.00                  1.25                 1.50&#13;
PRICE&#13;
LEGEND: 8    --1. 2    -             -0. 8    -   -0.4&#13;
CONSTANT ElASTICITIES: .4, .8 AND 1.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
effective price of housing by 50 percent. Assume further that participants&#13;
are free to consume any amount of housing services. The benefit of such a&#13;
program can be measured by the area under the demand curve, the familiar&#13;
consumer's surplus measure 141 If consumer demand is indeed well represented&#13;
by the log-linear demand function used above, then it can be shown that the&#13;
benefit of a program which changes price (and hence also changes desired&#13;
consumption) can be estimated as-15/&#13;
(l)     Benefit =          /(b ++ R - R&#13;
where&#13;
Benefit - cash equivalent value, a measure of change in&#13;
consumer's surplus&#13;
Q = predicted housing consumption in the&#13;
absence of the program&#13;
Q = housing consumption for program&#13;
participants&#13;
R - estimated rent in the absence of the&#13;
program&#13;
R - actual rent (subsidized) for program&#13;
s participants, and&#13;
b - price elasticity of demand.&#13;
14/ There are actually alternative empirical measures of consumer's sur-&#13;
plus.  We use cash equivalent value, or the amount of additional&#13;
purchasing power which would leave the consumer as well off at the old&#13;
prices as he is facing the new price set. See Freeman (1979), Chapter 3,&#13;
for a good introduction.&#13;
15/ See Mayo et al. (1980), pp. 96 ff. for details.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
The benefit may be thought of as composed of two .parts. The first, comprising&#13;
the terms in parentheses and brackets, depends on the amount of extra housing&#13;
provided by a program; that is, on the terms Q and Q, housing comsumption in&#13;
the program and housing consumption in the absence of the program. The second&#13;
is simply the additional disposable income brought about by paying a rent R&#13;
in a program rather than a rent (usually higher), R, in the absence of a&#13;
program. This is therefore not unrelated to a simple but incorrect measure&#13;
often used to estimate benefits, R - R , or the change in disposable income&#13;
following program participation. But whereas in the simple benefit measure an&#13;
extra dollar of housing is counted as being worth exactly a dollar by program&#13;
participants, in this benefit calculation (cash equivalent value), extra&#13;
housing is discounted based on a household's relative preference for housing&#13;
vis-a-vis other goods.&#13;
Table 12 presents results of this calculation under alternative&#13;
price elasticities. For conveniLence, starting values for price and quantity&#13;
were both normalized at one. A fifty percent unconstrained subsidy induces&#13;
households to consume more hous'Lng6/; they attach a value to the program&#13;
given in the benefit column. This benefit is, under quite general conditions,&#13;
less than the cost of providing the subsidy. The difference between benefit&#13;
and cost is deadweight loss. The ratio of benefit to cost is another useful&#13;
measure of program efficiency.&#13;
This oversimplified example is only meant to illustrate a few basic&#13;
concepts, and the consequences of variance in the key parameter, price&#13;
16/ The word unconstrained is key; most actual projects and programs reduce&#13;
the price but also constrain participants to consume "off their demand&#13;
curve," reducing the benefit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
Table 12&#13;
Benefits from a Stylized Housing Subsidy, Under&#13;
Alternative Price Elasticities&#13;
Price        Quantity       Program      Subsidy   Deadweight&#13;
Elasticity __Consumed         Benefit        Cost        Loss        Efficiency&#13;
-.4             1.2          .56          .60         .04             .93&#13;
-.8             1.4          .62          .70         .08            .89&#13;
-1.2             1.6          .69          .80         .11             .86&#13;
Program provides an unconstrained 50 percent subsidy. Before program, hous-&#13;
ing consumption and price were both normalized at 1.0.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
elasticity of demand.17 While at first glance the rows of Table 12 may not&#13;
seem to vary much, note t:hat if the implementing agency implicitly assumed&#13;
that the price elasticity was -.4 and it was in fact -1.2 (quite plausible,&#13;
given the general lack of precisie estimates), then the program cost to the&#13;
implementing agency would be 33 percent more than planned (a subsidy cost of&#13;
.8 versus .6); and the deadweight loss to society would be almost three times&#13;
the original calculation.&#13;
17/ For a more thorough treatment, see Mayo (1977); for an application to&#13;
Bank projects, see Mayo and Gross (1985).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
III. CROSS-COUNTRY DIFFERENCES EXPLAINED&#13;
In contrast to the broad similarity in income elasticities and&#13;
household size parameters across cities and countries, it is clear that there&#13;
are, in fact, systematic differences in housing demand that are related to&#13;
both income and city size. These differences are reflected not in the&#13;
parameters of income and household size, but rather in the constant terms of&#13;
estimated expenditure functions. Figures 3 and 4 illustrate the relationships&#13;
between rent-to-income ratios and incomes (based on estimated expenditure&#13;
functions) for renters and owners in representative cities, together with a&#13;
regression line fitted through the rent-to-income ratio at each city's mean&#13;
income. Upward sloping lines represent income elastic demand; downward&#13;
sloping, inelastic.&#13;
Note that: (1) as city mean incomes increase, mean rent-to-income&#13;
ratios also increase (i.e., Engel curves shift upwards as cities develop), and&#13;
(2) rent-to-income ratios of owners are consistently above those of renters at&#13;
given income levels. While the second point is discussed at greater length in&#13;
Chapter 4, this chapter considers possible explanations for the rather&#13;
striking result that rent-to-income ratios decline with income within cities&#13;
but increase with income across cities. After a review of previous cross-&#13;
country empirical research, and of several related behavioral models, a new&#13;
set of cross-country estimates is presented.&#13;
1. Previous Cross-Country Research&#13;
Several previous studies have documented cross-country differences&#13;
in housing consumption, notably Howenatine (1957), Kusnets (1961), Burns and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RENT-TrOINCOME RATIGS BY INCOME FOR RENTERs&#13;
2.0F&#13;
0.&#13;
R 0.8&#13;
E&#13;
N0.&#13;
r&#13;
N~~&#13;
c&#13;
O 0.5-1        s&#13;
I  O.   4   1{ ^            v&#13;
M                                S   --i-_  6 -- ---&#13;
E                                                                                  AA&#13;
0    1   ^   ---s    A A  AM F      i -  B -  *   4    +    --S _   _ _ i &#13;
50   loo   150   200   z50   300   350      400     _50      5  ,    550&#13;
INCOME IN 1i981 U. S. DOLLARS&#13;
LEGEND,  CITY   A-A-A  AVERAGE    88-B  SOU A       G.C4   CAIRO&#13;
ANSFC L AC    SCl. AT    1 SEOUL&#13;
AVERAGE IS FOR EACH LOC CITY AT ITS AVERAGE IN COME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 5&#13;
RENT-TO-INCOME RATIOS BY INCOME FOR OWNERS&#13;
1.0o&#13;
S%&#13;
R D. B&#13;
T D.a6-                 AS&#13;
T&#13;
N  0.4-                                                 A&#13;
C   10.3A&#13;
0.0-  t      §        1        1   -  -  Z       X        §     ---  X      -T  - ---   ----- -&#13;
50       100      150      201      250      300      350      400      450       500     550&#13;
INCOME IN 1981 U. S. DDLLARS&#13;
LEGEND: CITY     A A  AVERAGE      BBWB BOGOTA       &amp;GG- CAIRO&#13;
M-MAM MANILA      S-S-S SEOUL&#13;
AVERAGE IS FOR EACH LDC CITY AT ITS AVERAGE INCOME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
Grebler (1976), Strassman (:l970), Renaud (1980), Kravis et al. (1982), Annez&#13;
and Wheaton (1984), and Buckley and Madhusudhan (1984). This section briefly&#13;
reviews the five papers which test some models or exploratory hypotheses about&#13;
cross-country differences, namely Burns and Grebler, the extensions of their&#13;
model by Renaud and Buckley and Madhusudhan, the shelter results of the UN's&#13;
International Comparison Project (ICP) reported in Kravis et al., and the&#13;
model of Annez and Wheaton-1'L&#13;
Burns and Grebler's study examines the share of housing investment&#13;
(measured by new residential. construction) to gross domestic product, using&#13;
data from 39 countries, and two timne periods. Burns and Grebler regress the&#13;
share of housing investment against GDP per capita and its squares change in&#13;
population and its square, End a measure of urbanization, squared. They find&#13;
evidence that the share of housing investment increases at an early stage of&#13;
development but on average declines past about $1,600 per capita GDP (1970&#13;
U.S. dollars). Further, although there was a wide variance in their dependent&#13;
variable at different income! levels , their simple model explains that&#13;
variation quite well, and the turn:Lng point is quite sharp and precisely&#13;
measured (see Table 13).&#13;
Of course this turning point in the share does not imply that the&#13;
level of housing investment decreases with development, at least throughout&#13;
the observed range of the data. Aid implicit throughout this chapter is the&#13;
assumption that there is a direct and robust cross-country relationship&#13;
between housing investment and consumption. Since housing investment is a&#13;
derived demand, and cross-country comparisons are studies of very long-run&#13;
1/ Burns and Grebler review earliLer literature.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Table 13&#13;
Cross-Country Housing Investment Equations,&#13;
From Burns and Grebler&#13;
Coefficient    t-statistic       Prob &gt;|t|&#13;
Constant                                    2.80&#13;
GDP Per Capita                             38.14             3.95           .001&#13;
GDP Per Capita, Squared                     -.01215          3.53           .001&#13;
Change in Population                        -.315            1.57           .126&#13;
Change in Population, Squared                .047             .60           .553&#13;
Urbanization, Squared                        .005            1.14           .262&#13;
R2, unadjusted                               .51&#13;
Degrees of Freedom                          33&#13;
Dependent Variable: Share of new housing investment to gross domestic&#13;
product.&#13;
Source: Equation 2, Burns and Grebler, p. 108.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
behavior, this is not a bad approximation; but formal models of the&#13;
relationship between housing demand and investment could be undertaken in the&#13;
future, to make the link more precise.&#13;
Recent studies by Renaud and by Buckley and Madhusudhan have shown&#13;
the Burns and Grebler result to be qualitatively robust. Renaud analyzes time&#13;
series data from Korea and confirms the nonlinearity of the relationship&#13;
between the share of housing invelstment and per capita GDP, but finds the&#13;
exact turning point to be sensitilre to specification. Renaud also considers&#13;
several additional explanatory variables reflecting financial constraints&#13;
(Table 14). In general, the financial variables perform well in some&#13;
specifications but are not robust, which is not surprising given the&#13;
measurement difficulties involved and the modest number of degrees of freedom.&#13;
Buckley and Madhusudhan test the effect of additional financial&#13;
variables, namely the anticipated rate of inflation, changes in the rate of&#13;
inflation, and the extent of capit;al deepening (Table 15). Their analysis&#13;
confirms the importance of financial conditions in explaining housing&#13;
investment. In particular, they find that countries with deeper financial&#13;
markets invest relatively more in housing ceteris paribus. There is also weak&#13;
support for the hypotheses that the share of investment (1) is higher in less&#13;
egalitarian countries, (2) increases with anticipated inflation, and (3)&#13;
decreases with changes in inflation (presumed unanticipated in their model).&#13;
These three studies, which focus on the share of new housing&#13;
investment in GDP, provide a useful set of generalizations about housing&#13;
investment and development. In particular, the share of investment rises at&#13;
an early stage but declines as countries pass about $1,600 income per capita,&#13;
1970 U.S. dollars (or about $3,400 1981 U.S., the benchmark units used in this&#13;
study). To put this in perspective, upper middle income countries such as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
Table 14&#13;
Selected Results: Housing Investment Equations,&#13;
from Renaud&#13;
Equation (2)   Equation (4)   Equation (6)&#13;
Constant                           a        5.91              2.59            7.38&#13;
t       21.11             1.84             4.42&#13;
P&gt;JtJ       .001              .093            .001&#13;
Inverse GNP                        8      -22.27                            -31.41&#13;
t       10.97                              3.55&#13;
P&gt;JtJ       .001                              .004&#13;
Domestic Savings/GNP               8                         12.86           -6.06&#13;
t                         3.95             1.05&#13;
P&gt;Itt                         .002            .317&#13;
Inverse (Savings/GNP)              8        1.01&#13;
t        1.84&#13;
P&gt;JtJ       .084&#13;
Unregulated Money Market           8                          -.35             .17&#13;
t                         1.30              .74&#13;
P&gt;J tt                        .221            .475&#13;
R2, unadjusted                                .91              .78             .90&#13;
Degrees of Freedom                             16               11              11&#13;
Dependent Variable: Share of new housing investment to gross domestic product&#13;
Source: Renaud (1980), Table 4, p. 398.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
Table 15&#13;
Effects of Financial Facltors on Share of Housing Investment,&#13;
from Buckley and Madhusudhan&#13;
Coefficient    t-statistic    Prob &gt;|t|&#13;
Constant                                    -1.5&#13;
GDP Per Capita                              32.66            5.22             .001&#13;
GDP Per papita, Squared                      -.067           4.99             .001&#13;
Change in Population                          .38              .48            .126&#13;
Change in Population, Squared                 .02              .11            .553&#13;
Urbanization, Squared                         .11            2.94             .262&#13;
Gini Coefficient of Income                   1.75              .74            .001&#13;
Financial Deepening                           .0127          1.80             .001&#13;
Expected Inflation                            .04            1.26             .635&#13;
Change in Inflation                          -.09            1.46             .913&#13;
R2, adjusted                                  .68&#13;
Degrees of Freedom                           25&#13;
Dependent Variable:  Share of new housing investment to gross domestic&#13;
product.&#13;
Source:  Equation 3, Table 3, Buckley and Madhusudhan, p. 26.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
Argentina, Uruguay, South Africa and Yugoslavia were approaching this&#13;
estimated turning point in 1981 (the benchmark year for the present study),&#13;
and Venezuela, Greece, Israel and Hong Kong had recently passed it. Other&#13;
stylized facts from these previous studies include the following: over much&#13;
of the range of observed data, the relationship between income and investment&#13;
is stronger than between investment and demographic variables; time series&#13;
results from individual countries are at least qualitatively consistent with&#13;
the cross-section results; and in addition to income and population, the&#13;
structure of the financial sector affects housing investment.&#13;
The principal shortcomings of these studies have been discussed at&#13;
length by the authors themselves. Developed countries are overly&#13;
represented. Official statistics underestimate total housing investment,&#13;
because of large informal sectors and because new construction statistics fail&#13;
to count upgrading, maintenance, and depreciation of existing units. These&#13;
undercounting errors are doubtless largest for the poorest countries.&#13;
Also, these studies cannot be strictly compared with the present&#13;
paper because housing investment and housing consumption can diverge, although&#13;
qualitative results should be robust. Because of data problems, Burns and&#13;
Grebler, and those who followed them, ignored the effects of relative prices,&#13;
climate, and other variables (although they were careful to point out these&#13;
omissions). Finally, these models can be thought of as exploratory reduced&#13;
forms; there is no explicit behavioral model which is used to justify the&#13;
estimating equations.&#13;
Annez and Wheaton address several of these problems. They develop a&#13;
structural model with five endogenous variables (four stochastic equations and&#13;
an identity). Their model explains total growth in the housing stock, the&#13;
officially recorded growth, the average quality of new units, and the cost of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
construction. The share of new construction to national product, conceptually&#13;
similar to the Burns and Grebler dependent variable, then emerges from the&#13;
identity: share of investment equals the product of change in stock, average&#13;
size, and cost, divided by GNP.&#13;
Annez and Wheaton assembled data from 24 non-socialt9t countries&#13;
(largely developed), and estimated two variants of this model. The more&#13;
complete model includes several policy related variables (the share of public&#13;
housing in total production, credit cost, and typical loan-to-value ratios),&#13;
but could only be estimated for a smaller sample of 20 countries. These&#13;
results are reproduced as Table 16. Key results include the following. When&#13;
total stock is measured in the nummber of housing units, its growth is&#13;
determined by demographic, not economic variables. The reverse is true for&#13;
the quality of an existing unit. Demographics determine the number of units;&#13;
incomes and prices determine their quality.-2/  The fraction of production&#13;
officially recorded is positivelyr related to the level of economic&#13;
development, as expected. Costs also rise with development. There is no&#13;
evidence of any supply inelasticiLty; cost is unrelated to share of housing&#13;
investment.&#13;
Annez and Wheaton note that their estimates imply that as economies&#13;
develop, increasing incomes fuel housing demand; but, this is in large part&#13;
offset by increasing prices. The Burns-Grebler result--an inelastic&#13;
relationship between investment and income--may mask offsetting price and&#13;
income effects. These will be discussed in more detail in Section 3.3, below.&#13;
2/   Weicher and Hartzell (1980) report similar findings for the U.S.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
Table 16&#13;
Annez-Wheaton Cross-Country Housing Investment Model: OLS Estimates&#13;
from Their Larger Model&#13;
Independent&#13;
Variables                                       Dependent Variables&#13;
Change in      Recorded-to-Total   Average   Average&#13;
Hlousing Stock          Stock          Quality    Cost&#13;
GNP Per Household           8     -.0003               .000014            .34        .63&#13;
t        1.30                 2.85           1.96        2.6&#13;
P&gt;Itl       .215                  .011          .070       .020&#13;
Average Cost                8                                             .45&#13;
t                                             2.3&#13;
P&gt;jtl                                           .037&#13;
Population  Growth          8         .72&#13;
t         3.5&#13;
P&gt;Itl       .004&#13;
Household Size              8       -1.05*                              -.21**&#13;
t         3.3                                 .55&#13;
P&gt;Itl       .005                                .590&#13;
Public Housing Share        B        -.60                               -.02       .074&#13;
t         .67                                 .44       1.06&#13;
P&gt;ItI       .514                                .667       .305&#13;
Loan/Value                  8         .22                                .168&#13;
t         .87                                2.25&#13;
P&gt;ItI       .399                                .041&#13;
Share of Housing            B                                                       .04&#13;
Investment                 t                                                        .18&#13;
P&gt; tj                                                      .860&#13;
Inverse, Change            8                              .028&#13;
in Stock                   t                              1.56&#13;
P&gt; tl                             .137&#13;
Average Winter              B                                           -.23       .006&#13;
Temperature                t                                             3.3       1.66&#13;
P&gt;Itl                                           .005       .118&#13;
R2, unajusted                         .65                  .40           .69        .75&#13;
Degrees of Freedom                     14                   17             14        15&#13;
INote: intercepts not reported; all variables in logs.&#13;
*change in household size&#13;
l**average household size&#13;
Source: Annez and Wheaton (1984), Table 4, p. 762.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
Further evidence on tlhe cross-country price and income elasticities&#13;
of demand for housing is provided by the U.N. International Comparisons&#13;
Project (ICP, see Kravis et al.). The ICP is a major research effort which&#13;
makes international comparisons of consumption and prices. As part of that&#13;
effort, Kravis and his associates use hedonic index methods to decompose rents&#13;
for similar units into rental price and quantity indexes, as described in&#13;
detail in their Chapter 2. These indexes, and indexes of total consumption,&#13;
are used to estimate simple cross-country demand models, where housing&#13;
consumption is a function of total consumption and the price per unit of&#13;
housing services (see their Chapter 9). For example, using the familiar log&#13;
functional form, they obtain the following OLS estimates using their sample of&#13;
34 countries:&#13;
ln Q - -5.62 - 0.61 (ln P) + 1.40 (ln Y)       -2 _ .93&#13;
(0.54)  (.15)         (0.07)&#13;
where Q is the per capita quantity index, P is the rental price index, and Y&#13;
is the per capita total consumption index. Standard errors are in&#13;
parentheses.&#13;
Kravis et al. found this result--inelastic price, slightly elastic&#13;
income demand--to be robust to specification and econometric technique.&#13;
However, they do not report results from any functional form which can be used&#13;
to test for any turning point in demand similar to that found for investment&#13;
share by Burns and Grebler.__&#13;
3/   Kravis et al. report resuLts for log-linear and linear expenditure&#13;
functions, estimated as s:Lngle equations and as a system of demand&#13;
equations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
2. A Kuznets-Type Result&#13;
Figures 3 and 4, above, are very similar to the consumption patterns&#13;
extensively documented by Simon Kuznets (Kuznets, 1961, and his other works&#13;
cited therein). Qualitatively, housing consumption is remarkably similar to&#13;
total consumption; that is, there are markedly smaller within-country&#13;
differences at various income levels than the between-country differences at&#13;
different income levels.&#13;
The empirical work by Kuznets sparked several behavioral models&#13;
which could explain his results. Similar explanations may be advanced to&#13;
explain an apparent paradox: there is a strong positive relationship between&#13;
rent-to-income ratios and incomes across cities; but the relationship&#13;
within a given city is weak. These alternative explanations each stem from&#13;
the Keynesian hypothesis that the marginal propensity to consume (here on&#13;
housing) is less than the average propensity to consume. Several well known&#13;
models derive this hypothesis from models of optimizing consumer behavior,&#13;
namely the relative income hypothesis (Duesenberry, 1949), the permanent&#13;
income hypothesis (Friedman, 1957), and the life cycle model of consumption&#13;
(Ando and Modigliani, 1963). These models have been cogently summarized&#13;
elsewhere (e.g. Branson, 1979, ch. 10; Yotopoulos and Nugent, 1976, ch. 10),&#13;
so here we only point out the implications of the theories for cross-city&#13;
comparisons. The relative income hypothesis states that utility depends on&#13;
consumption relative to the surrounding population, or in other words, the&#13;
savings/consumption decision is driven by the consumer's perceived position in&#13;
the local income distribution. Within a city, utility maximizing consumers&#13;
consume higher fractions of their incomes as income falls, because they are&#13;
trying to attain average consumption with below average income. Conversely,&#13;
high income people can easily maintain average, or slightly better than&#13;
average, consumption while spending declining fractions of their incomes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
Across cities, however, as the entire local economy develops, the average&#13;
consumption-to-income relationship remains stable 41 implying a constant&#13;
consumption share, or a unitary Lncome elasticity.&#13;
The permanent income model separates income into permanent (expected&#13;
long-run) and transitory components. Friedman shows that if current and&#13;
transitory components are independent within a cross section, then consumption&#13;
will vary less than income under plausible assumptions, yielding the inelastic&#13;
within-city curves depicted in FLgures 3 and 4. When entire cross sections&#13;
are averaged out (the cross-city comparisons), the transitory components&#13;
cancel and the measured income elasticity rises. Cross-city elasticities&#13;
presumably correspond to permanent income elasticities.&#13;
The life cycle hypothesis postulates that typical individuals have&#13;
income streams which are largest in middle age. In the early years of a&#13;
person's life, they borrow against later income. In middle age, consumers&#13;
repay earlier borrowings, and save for old age, when consumption again exceeds&#13;
income. When household surveys are used to estimate housing demand functions,&#13;
the highest income sample members are disproportionately middle-age-headed&#13;
households, at peak earning power but low consumption-to-income. Low-income&#13;
panel members are often at the age extremes, earning less, with a high&#13;
consumption-to-income ratiLo. This reduces the observed cross-section income&#13;
elasticity. Again, when the city averages are observed, these transitory&#13;
effects cancel, and the measured income elasticity increases.&#13;
Demographic variLables and relative price can also account for shifts&#13;
in the rent-to-income ratios across cities. The Ando-Modigliani model focuses&#13;
4/   Most writers assume this stability; a more general relative income model&#13;
could obviously allow for non-unitary demand elasticities in the long&#13;
run.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
on one demographic variable in particular, age of household head, but&#13;
consumption can also vary with household size. However, if housing&#13;
consumption increases with household size and household size decreases with&#13;
income, then any positive relationship between housing consumption and&#13;
development is reduced. Alternatively, at large household sizes food could&#13;
crowd out housing consumption. It is not clear from the household estimates&#13;
that this is the case, but in any event this effect is easily controlled,&#13;
for. All comparisons in Figures 3 and 4, and in the next few pages, are done&#13;
at a single arbitrary household size of five.&#13;
Relative housing prices also increase with development (see Annez&#13;
and Wheaton, and the data appendix), so a model which does not include&#13;
relative prices has a downward biased income coefficient. Figures 3 and 4 are&#13;
not price adjusted, but the next few pages present several models which are.&#13;
3. A Simple Cross-Country Model&#13;
Tables 17 and 18 present a set of cross-city Engel curves, estimated&#13;
separately for owners and renters. For each tenure type and specification,&#13;
the estimates are presented separately for developing countries alone, and for&#13;
the total sample (including Pittsburgh and Phoenix, U.S.A.). The dependent&#13;
variable is predicted housing expenditure for a five-person household at each&#13;
city's mean income or its logarithm; these predictions are from the household&#13;
level equations presented in Tables 2 and 3, above. The income variables are&#13;
based on the city averages. Incomes and rents are converted to 1981 U.S.&#13;
dollars by using local CPIs and official 1981 exchange rates. Price, and its&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 17&#13;
Cross-Country Housing Demand Estimates for Renters&#13;
Dependent Variable          Log           Log            Log            Log            Log            Log             Linear         Linear         Linear&#13;
Sample                     Total         Total           LDCs          Total          Total           LDCs             Total          Total           LDCs&#13;
Log Income                  1.23          1.61           1.60&#13;
.12          .18             .18&#13;
.001         .001            .001&#13;
Income                                                                 .0087          .0080          .0149              .182           .086          -.092&#13;
.0013         .0014           .0038              .073           .048           .138&#13;
.001           .001           .002             .025            .096           .517&#13;
Income Squared                                                      -3.4E-6         -1.6E-6        -1.4E-5          -2.6E-5          2.1E-4         5.3E-4&#13;
6.0E-7         1.5E-6         6.6E-6           3.4E-5          5.1E-5         2.4g-4&#13;
.001           .301           .056             .458           .001            .047&#13;
Log Price                    .53           .15            .15            .26            .23             .09&#13;
.29          .29             .29            .34            .34            .31&#13;
.092         .610            .613          .456            .500           .783&#13;
Price                                                                                                                   26.7           21.2           24.9&#13;
19.6           12.0           11.9&#13;
.195           .101           .058&#13;
United States                            -1.27                                        -5.07                                          -676.3&#13;
(dummy)                                  .48                                         4.02                                           135.9&#13;
.020                                         .229                                            .001&#13;
Intercept                  -3.42         -5.40          -5.39           1.24           1.29             .58           -32.4           -21.7           -7.6&#13;
.70          .96             .98            .30            .30            .46             18.2           11.3            15.0&#13;
.001         .001            .001           .001           .001           .224             .097            .077           .619&#13;
R-Squared                    .89           .92            .90            .88            .89             .88              .89            .96             .86&#13;
(adjusted)&#13;
DF, Error                     15            14             13             14             13             12                14             13              12&#13;
SSe                    2.977507      1.989792        1.933157       2.880380       2.565938       1.966973         8480.154       2918.157        2521.953&#13;
SSE, adjusted          2.977507      1.989792        1.933157      2.880380        2.565938       1.966973           685.45         235.87          203.84&#13;
e       P-.5              -.47          -.85           -.85            -.74           -.77           -.91             -.64           -.72            -.59&#13;
p      p- 1              -.47          -.85           -.85           -.74           -.77            -.91             -.47           -.57            -.42&#13;
P-1.5             -.47          -.85           -.85           -.74           -.77           -.91              -.37           -.47           -.32&#13;
c       $222               1.23          1.61           1.60           1.60           1.62           1.93              1.13           1.37           1.38&#13;
y      $322               1.23          1.61           1.60           2.10           2.24           1.89             1.06            1.45           1.88&#13;
$422              1.23          1.61           1.60           2.46           2.81           1.30              1.02           1.52           2.05&#13;
Turning Point               N.A.          N.A.           N.A.          $1279          $2500           $532            $3500            N.A.            $87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 18&#13;
Cross-Country Housing Demand Estimates for Owners&#13;
fependent Variable           Log           Log            Log             Log             Log            Log             Linear          Linear         Linear&#13;
Sample                     Total          Total           LDCs           Total          Total            LDCs             Total           Total           LDCs&#13;
Log Income                    .98          1.38            1.38&#13;
.18           .34            .35&#13;
.001          .002           .003&#13;
Incoiqe                                                                  .0081          .0075           .0063              .327            .261          -.166&#13;
.0018          .0019           .0067              .146           .136            .433&#13;
.001           .002            .372              .045           .082            .711&#13;
Income Squared                                                        -3.3E-6         -1.3E-6          9.1E-7          -8.8E-5          1.2E-4          9.13-4&#13;
8.5E-7         1.8E-6          1.2E-5            6.9e-5         1.33-4          7.7e-4&#13;
.003           .482            .940              .225           .350            .264&#13;
Log Price                    1.03           .64             .65            .67             .62            .65&#13;
.41           .48            .50             .43            .42             .47&#13;
.025          .205           .223            .144           .171            .196&#13;
Price                                                                                                                      87.8            79.2          87.27&#13;
34.4           31.5           32.31&#13;
.026           0.29            .022&#13;
United States                             -1.18                                         -5.81                                           -653.3&#13;
(do-)                                     .86                                          4.86                                            341.5&#13;
.192                                          .256                                             .082&#13;
lntercept                  -1.44          -3.57          -3.57            2.04           2.05            2.18             -87.9          -79.0          -43.64&#13;
1.04          1.84           1.92             .43            .42             .80              30.6           28.1           44.08&#13;
.188          .076           .090            .001           .001            .021             .014            .017            .345&#13;
R-Squared                     .78           .80             .76            .83            .84             .80               .85             .88            .80&#13;
(adjueted)&#13;
UP, Error                      13            12             11              12              11             10                12              11             10&#13;
5SE                     4.721139      4.071022        4.052442       3.420485        3.026050       3.015042         19744.239       14814.483      13375.861&#13;
SE, adjusted            4.721139      4.017022        4.052442       3.420485        3.026050       3.015042           1147.34          860.86          777.27&#13;
E        P-.5                .03         -.36            -.35           -.33            -.38           -.35              -.16            -.31             .07&#13;
P      P- 1                .03          -.36            -.35           -.33            -.38           -.35              -.09            -.18             .03&#13;
P-1.5               .03         -.36            -.35           -.33            -.38           -.35              -.06            -.13             .02&#13;
t        $222               .98           1.38           1.38           1.48            1.54           1.49               .94            1.09            1.02&#13;
8322               .98           1.38           1.38           1.94            2.15           2.22               .91            1.13            1.60&#13;
$422                .98          1.38           1.38           2.28            2.70           2.98               .87            1.16            1.87&#13;
Tsrning Point               N.A.           N.A.           N.A.          $1227           $2885           N.A.             $1858            N.A.             $91&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
logarithm, are constructed from the rental price series devised by Kravis,&#13;
Heston and Summers (1982) 5!&#13;
Log-linear models were estimated for consistency with the household&#13;
level estimation, and quadratic models for comparison with the Burns and&#13;
Grebler results. A third model (log of rent, linear and quadratic income) was&#13;
also estimated.&#13;
The bottom rows of the t:ables include calculated income and price&#13;
elasticities for several income and price levels. The range of observed&#13;
relative prices corresponds roughly to the range presented in the tables (.5&#13;
to 1.5), and as noted above, the r elative price of one corresponds to the U.S.&#13;
relative price of a unit of housirng services. The median of the city average&#13;
incomes is $322 per household, and the range of income elasticities are&#13;
calculated at that median and at a hundred dollars above and below the&#13;
median. The turning point, where applicable, is the point where housing&#13;
consumption begins to fall with irncome (with an exception to be noted later).&#13;
The key results are straLightforward: in a very long run, housing&#13;
consumption is income elastic, or at least of unit elasticity. Price&#13;
elasticities are lower than income! elasticities in absolute value. Interval&#13;
estimates of price elasticities are quite wide. In this sample, which is&#13;
dominated by developing countries, it does not appear that owners have higher&#13;
5/   The construction of the price index is explained in detail in the data&#13;
appendix; the appendix also etxplains our choice of this index over two&#13;
other candidate indexes. Several shortcomings of this index deserve&#13;
mention: being a rental index, it includes all factors of production in&#13;
housing services, but it is salso a country specific, while a city and&#13;
tenure specific index would be preferred.  No city-tenure specific index&#13;
exists, to our knowledge.  This price index is a relative price index; it&#13;
is the rental price of a unit of housing services in a country, relative&#13;
to the price of a composite of all goods and services.  The U.S. relative&#13;
price has been chosen for normalization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
long-run responsiveness to changes in incomes and prices; if anything, the&#13;
reverse is true. Eight out of nine specifications yield a higher median&#13;
income elasticity for renters than owners; the differences are not great.&#13;
This does not mean that within a market renters consume less than owners, but&#13;
that as cities' economies develop over a very long run, owner and renter&#13;
consumption patterns increase at a similar pace, ceteris paribus. However, as&#13;
will be discussed in Chapter 4, because prices rise with income and estimated&#13;
renter price elasticities are also higher than owner elasticities, the net&#13;
effect of both incomes and prices rising as development proceeds is to&#13;
increase owner consumption faster than renter consumption through most of the&#13;
range of the data.&#13;
Another obvious result is that Pittsburgh and Phoenix are quite&#13;
different from the rest of the data. There are considerable differences in&#13;
fit and in coefficients between models with and without these cities in the&#13;
sample, and dummy variables for the cities have large effects. This is not&#13;
surprising, since the Burns and Grebler and related research lead us to expect&#13;
turning points in relative if not absolute consumption as city incomes rise,&#13;
and because the U.S. tax code distorts housing consumption 61 These U.S.&#13;
cities are the only cities in our sample which are past the Burns and Grebler&#13;
turning point. Since the Burns and Grebler turning point is for macro&#13;
investment, not household consumption, and because it is a relative measure&#13;
(share in GDP), direct comparison is difficult. In addition, the samples are&#13;
6/ Numerous studies document the effect of the U.S. tax code on housing&#13;
markets, e.g. Aaron (1972), deLeeuw and Ozanne (1981), Follain (1981),&#13;
and many others. In general, tax policy reduces the user cost of housing&#13;
capital for both owners and renters, although more for owners. This&#13;
after tax price is not well captured in the price index we have used.&#13;
Given this, the low predicted rents for the U.S. cities are somewhat&#13;
surprising.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
obviously quite different. For thiLs reason little confidence can be placed in&#13;
having estimated a precise turning point until this analysis is extended with&#13;
additional cities, particularly developed country cities.&#13;
The fits of the logarithmic models and the semilogarithmic models&#13;
are broadly similar, although the fits are noticeably improved when the U.S.&#13;
cities are dropped from the samples or "dummied out." The linear models,&#13;
estimated to be consistent with the Burns and Grebler specification, are&#13;
clearly inferior to the logarithmic fits, as can be seen by examining the&#13;
adjusted sum of squared errors from the different models.7/&#13;
Since factor proportions probably vary between tenure groups, and&#13;
also because in at least the U.S. the user cost of homeowner capital is much&#13;
less than the unadjusted rental rate used here, the renter price elasticities&#13;
are more reliable than the owner price elasticities. As noted in Chapter 2,&#13;
the micro estimates of price elasticities from three cities are probably&#13;
biased towards one, from errors in variables; here, the same econometric&#13;
problem may bias the owner price elasticity towards zero. Also, it is&#13;
dangerous to draw strong conclusioms from point estimates with such large&#13;
standard errors. Any interval estimate would contain elasticities which imply&#13;
radically different behavior, and cwner and renter intervals would overlap&#13;
considerably. The conclusion that very long-run renter price elasticities are&#13;
greater than owner price elasticities is therefore tentative.&#13;
For a better feel for the qualitative differences in the estimates,&#13;
Figures 6 and 7 present graphs of the long-run cross-country Engel curves from&#13;
7/   Adjusted R-squared value can be compared across logrithmic and semi-&#13;
logarithmic models, because the dependent variable is the same. To&#13;
compare log and linear models, the sum of squared errors must be&#13;
adjusted to account for the different variance in the dependent&#13;
variables. See Rao and Miller (1971), pp. 1070-1111.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 6&#13;
CROSS COUNTRY ENGEL CURVES, RENTERS&#13;
0. 6-&#13;
R&#13;
E  0.4&#13;
N&#13;
T&#13;
0&#13;
N&#13;
C  0. 2&#13;
0&#13;
M&#13;
E                                                                                                    -&#13;
0.0&#13;
0       50        100      150      200       250      300       350      400       450     500&#13;
INCOME IN 1961 U.S. DOLLARS&#13;
LEGENOt MODEL    A4s A ALL LOG          B -  ALL QUAD     G G G LOC LOG       D-D D LOC QUAD&#13;
MODEL REFERS TO SAMPLE. AND INCOME SPECIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 7&#13;
CROSS COUNTRY ENGEL CURVES, OWNERS&#13;
0.54&#13;
R&#13;
E  0. 4X&#13;
N&#13;
T &#13;
N&#13;
C  0.  A2&#13;
E               e--&#13;
4. .0                                          &#13;
0       50       100      150       200      250      300       350      400      450      500&#13;
INCOME&#13;
LEGENOD  MODEL    A A-A ALL LOG       9-B-0 ALL QUAD     G G G LOC LOG       D D D LOC QUAD&#13;
MODEL REFERS TO SAMPLE. AND INCOME SPECIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
four of the models of Tables 16 and 17, respectively. The four models&#13;
represent the simple log model on all data, with relative price set to one,&#13;
denoted "A" on the figures (column 1 of Tables 16 and 17), the quadratic model&#13;
on all cities ("B," corresponding to column 7), the log model on developing&#13;
countries only ("C," column 3), and the quadratic model on LDC cities ("D,"&#13;
column 9). The range of the data displayed in the graphs is limited to&#13;
developing country values. Through this range, the relationship between&#13;
housing consumption and income is remarkably robust for renters; for owners&#13;
the estimates diverge, particularly at higher incomes. Much of the divergence&#13;
depends on whether or not the U. S. is included in the sample. Since the U.S.&#13;
drives these results so strongly, it is essential that future cross-country&#13;
work include data from more high and middle income countries, in order to&#13;
obtain more precise estimation of the relationship between housing consumption&#13;
and development. However, within a reasonable range--within 100 to 200&#13;
dollars of the median household income, $322--the results are robust.&#13;
Price elasticities are less robust with respect to specification and&#13;
sample. Figures 8 and 9 graph demand curves for the four models described&#13;
above, at a typical income (U.S. $322). Note that adding the U.S. data&#13;
flattens the demand curve, especially for the logarithmic owner model.&#13;
These four figures highlight the following: slight changes to model&#13;
and sample do not radically alter the long-run income elasticity estimates.&#13;
The income estimates are more robust than price elasticities. Renters appear&#13;
to be more responsive to income than owners, but the opposite holds for&#13;
price. This conclusion is tentative because, as was discussed above, the&#13;
owner price elasticities are probably more affected by errors in variables&#13;
than are the renter price estimates. Adding the U.S. to the sample reduces&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67-&#13;
FIGURE 8&#13;
CROSS COUNTRY DEMAND CURVES, RENTERS&#13;
QURNT ITY&#13;
2DD&#13;
150&#13;
100&#13;
50&#13;
0&#13;
0.2                       0.4                       0.G                       0.8                     1.0&#13;
PRICE&#13;
LEGEND: MODEL        A-A-A RLL LOG         B--B  ALl QUAD         G-C LOC LOG           9-9-9 LOC QUAD&#13;
HODEI REFFRS TO SAIlPLE. RNO INCOME SPECIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
FIGURE 9&#13;
CROSS COUNTRY DEMAND CURVES, OWNERS&#13;
OURNTITT&#13;
200&#13;
150&#13;
100&#13;
A            A            A            A            A            A&#13;
50&#13;
0.2                       0.4                       0.6                       0.8                       1.0&#13;
PRICE&#13;
LEGEND: MODEL         A,A ALL LOG           B43-B ALL QURO         G-"   LOC LOG         D4D D LOC QUAD&#13;
MODEL REFERS TO SAMPLE, AND INCOME SPECIFICRTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
the estimated reponsivenesis of tlhe consumption to both incomes and prices, but&#13;
especially the latter, Adding more middle and high income countries, and&#13;
constructing city and tenure specific price indexes which account for taxes,&#13;
rent control, expected inflation and the like are natural extensions of this&#13;
work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
IV. DIFFERENCES IN HOUSING DEMAND BY TENURE&#13;
Chapter 3 discussed some of the differences that exist in housing&#13;
consumption between renters and owners, e.g., that both marginal and average&#13;
propensities to consume housing are generally greater for owners. This&#13;
chapter elaborates on differences that are found between the two groups in&#13;
consumption of real housing services, as measured by rents and imputed rents,&#13;
and focuses also on examining whether or not a premium exists for&#13;
homeownership per se. It is likely that most owners pay for more than just&#13;
the flow of housing services offered by their dwellings; they also pay for a&#13;
number of aspects of housing that accompany ownership of property rights in&#13;
their dwellings. Among these are: (i) freedom from inflation in rents which&#13;
would occur were they not to own (e.g., housing's value as a "hedge against&#13;
inflation"); (ii) the right to generate income from subletting commercial or&#13;
residential space; and (iii) the right to receive future income in the form of&#13;
capital gains realized upon sale of the property. It may be seen that all of&#13;
these motivations for placing a premium on housing (above a payment for its&#13;
rental value) are subject to the influence of both general economic conditions&#13;
and the conditions of particular housing markets. It is conceivable, in fact,&#13;
that under certain conditions (e.g., a depressed real estate market with high&#13;
vacancies, falling real rents, and net population out-flow) there could be a&#13;
discount for ownership. Similarly, there are conditions under which renting&#13;
is less risky than owning. It is important, therefore, not only to measure&#13;
the magnitude of any ownership premium but also to understand the factors&#13;
associated with its magnitude. Important policy implications follow from&#13;
knowing each.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
In this chapter the focus of our explanation of cross-tenure&#13;
differences is an attempt: to disentangle two features of renters' and owners'&#13;
housing consumption; the first is the difference in consumption of housing&#13;
services; the second, the premium (if any) paid by owners for homeownership&#13;
per se.&#13;
A key simplifying assiumption made for most of this section is that&#13;
the simple rent-own classificatLon is a useful one. In fact, tenure is a&#13;
continuum of property rights evien within a country. For example, in the U.S.&#13;
the simple rent-own dichotomy is a simplification accepted by almost all&#13;
analysts, but in fact actual temure rights vary greatly from tenant to tenant&#13;
because of the effects of zoning laws, length of tenure, rent control, laws&#13;
concerning tenant occupancy rights, housing standards, financial&#13;
considerations such as due on sale clauses, and many other possible&#13;
easements. / Later in this secition we will evaluate this simple model by&#13;
comparing results from the simple own-rent model to results from more&#13;
disaggregated models.  But firsl a brief discussion of the user cost of&#13;
capital will introduce the basic tools of analysis; then differences in&#13;
consumption by tenure will be estimated and explained.&#13;
1. The Concept of User Cost&#13;
The user cost of capil:al is the income foregone from the best&#13;
alternative use of that capital. The user cost of a unit of housing capital&#13;
is straightforwardly measured for renters: neglecting transactions costs, it&#13;
is the monthly rent paid for the unit(s) of housing capital from which the&#13;
tenant receives a flow of housing services. For owners, user cost is the&#13;
1/   See Furbotn and Pejovich (1975) for a-survey of the economic analysis of&#13;
property rights, and Hirsch (1979) for applications to housing markets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
opportunity cost of the household's owned asset, structure and land. ' The&#13;
gross differences in housing consumption (rents) observed in Chapter 3 could&#13;
be due to differences in real consumption (quantities) or differences in user&#13;
cost (prices). Why would differences in user cost persist? Households would&#13;
presumably have incentives to arbitrage by changing tenure. Why would&#13;
systematic differences in housing consumption persist? Certainly tastes can&#13;
be said to differ across tenure groups but this is not an informative&#13;
explanation. Much of the observed difference can be attributed to long lags&#13;
in housing markets. Developing country cities are growing very fast, with&#13;
severe supply side constraints (e.g. poor financial system, lack of infra-&#13;
structure). Under these conditions differences in user cost will not be&#13;
quickly arbitraged away. Tables 19 and 20 present summary explanations of how&#13;
user cost differences and quantity differences can arise. The existence of so&#13;
many potential explanations of price and quantity changes (and hence,&#13;
differences in observed rents) means that there is little possibility that&#13;
empirical work with a dozen or so cities will clearly sort out the relative&#13;
2/   For both renters and owners, consider structural capital as undistin-&#13;
guished from land in this section; also, ignore other inputs to the&#13;
production of housing services, and the existence of leases.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
'rable 19&#13;
First Order Effects of Market Conditions on User Cost&#13;
Owner's Real                    Renter's Real&#13;
User Cost                       User Cost&#13;
General Price Inflation        in abSence of taxes,            neutral&#13;
(Real Rents Constant)          neutral, if alternative&#13;
assets3 appreciate equal-&#13;
ly&#13;
Real Inflation in Rents        decreases, through              increases; as nominal&#13;
(unanticipated)                capital gains                   house values bid up,&#13;
landlord's opportunity&#13;
cost rises, and is&#13;
passed on to tenants in&#13;
a competitive market&#13;
Rent Control                   decreases income fore-          decreases user cost&#13;
gone by not renting but        initially but landlords&#13;
may increase demand in         adjust by decreasing&#13;
owner occupied sector;         maintenance or charging&#13;
in long-run rental price       key money&#13;
adjusl:s back up&#13;
Tax Treatment Favorable        initially lowers after          roughly neutral, but may&#13;
to Homeownership               tax cost of capital; in         decrease over inter-&#13;
long run, may be offset        mediate run if tax&#13;
by increase in house           treatment causes shift&#13;
valuei if supply not          to homeownership and&#13;
perfectly elastic              landlords do not sell&#13;
out to homeowners&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
Table 20&#13;
Alternative Explanations for Cross Tenure Differences in Relative&#13;
Real Housing Consumption&#13;
Effect on&#13;
Owner/Renter&#13;
Real Consumption                Explanation&#13;
Security of Tenure             positive                        secure tenure is&#13;
per se a good for&#13;
which households&#13;
pay a premium&#13;
Property Rights                Positive                        Ownership com-&#13;
prises additional&#13;
property rights&#13;
which have some&#13;
implicit market&#13;
value; secure&#13;
tenure is only one&#13;
of these&#13;
Alternative In-                negative                        developing&#13;
vestment Oppor-                                                countries with&#13;
tunities                                                       thin capital&#13;
markets have few&#13;
alternative vents&#13;
for savings and&#13;
remittances&#13;
Transactions Cost              positive                        consumption&#13;
changes with in-&#13;
come, life cycle&#13;
but larger trans-&#13;
action costs for&#13;
owners implies&#13;
less tendency to&#13;
adjust downward in&#13;
response to&#13;
changed cir-&#13;
cumstances&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
contribution of each, but it is important to identify them as clearly as&#13;
possible3&#13;
The first focus is on prices. Table 19 presents some hypotheses&#13;
about the effects of changes in market conditions on user costs for each&#13;
tenure group. They are first order in the sense that they are considered&#13;
independently from other market conditions in a partial equilibrium&#13;
framework. In long-run general equilibrium many of these hypotheses would&#13;
have to be qualified, especially if the supply of capital to each submarket is&#13;
elastic. Also, interactions between market conditions (for example, inflation&#13;
and the tax code) are not discussed here.4/&#13;
Recall that the user cost for renters is the monthly rental paid for&#13;
the dwelling. In the absence of leases (or for leases sufficiently short),&#13;
rents paid adjust quickly to the landlord's cost of capital, which lies behind&#13;
the renters user cost. Arn owner's implicit user cost, like a landlord's, can&#13;
be derived from a simple model:&#13;
c  = VO(r + d)  ~ddt + m&#13;
where c is user cost,&#13;
V0 is the purchase price of the asset,&#13;
r is the opportunity cost of capital,&#13;
d is the depreciation rate&#13;
3/   For ease of exposition changes which may be roughly neutral with respect&#13;
to tenure differences, such as population or income growth, or changes in&#13;
depreciation, are not considered here. Of course such changes are not&#13;
always neutral in the presence of other market conditions, notably taxes.&#13;
4/ See the U.S. literature citied above for analysis of interactions between&#13;
the tax code and market conditions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
dV is the real appreciation of the asset, and&#13;
m are monthly operating costs.&#13;
In developed countries the tax treatment of owner occupied housing&#13;
radically affects user cost, but this is a problem which can be ignored when&#13;
using data from developing countries. Specifically, the user cost expression&#13;
is simplified because the tax treatment of imputed rent, capital gains,&#13;
mortgage interest and property taxes are irrelevant. Since taxes can be&#13;
ignored and mortgage financing is uncommon in developing countries, user cost&#13;
consists of the opportunity cost of the equity in the house, plus operating&#13;
costs (e.g. utilities) and depreciation, and less expected real&#13;
appreciation. In a riskless world, expected real appreciation depends on the&#13;
expected future rents the house will command 5/&#13;
The first and the last effects of Table 19 will not be discussed in&#13;
detail: the neutrality of general inflation is straightforward, and the&#13;
effects of income tax treatments are not relevant in developing countries. If&#13;
there is a real increase in rents which is unanticipated, a renter's user cost&#13;
increases, although with lags due to leases. User cost decreases for sitting&#13;
owner occupants because unanticipated rental increases will be capitalized&#13;
5/   Adding resale to the model doesn't really change anything because resale&#13;
prices are also simply discounted present values. Parenthetically,&#13;
existing owner occupied houses trade less frequently in developing&#13;
countries than in developed countries. This may lead to a downward bias&#13;
in our estimates of user cost, as argued in Follain and Malpezzi (1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
into increased house values. These capital gains are a potential source of&#13;
income offsetting part of the ex ante user cost.6/&#13;
Housing market policy interventions can have quite complex effects&#13;
on user cost. For example, rent controls decrease user cost to renters to the&#13;
extent that they are effective price controls, but that is a big if.&#13;
Landlords can reduce the quantity of housing services produced by a unit to&#13;
negate the initial price decrease; the time path of renter's user cost in a&#13;
controlled market may even exceed the competitive price at some point (see&#13;
Malpezzi [1984 b], and the references therein). Even in the case where the&#13;
reduction in housing services exactly balances the original price decrease,&#13;
rent control regimes typically have winners and losers among tenants; long-&#13;
term tenants often have much lower user costs than recent movers, for example&#13;
(Ibid.). For owners, the effect on user cost of a controlled rental market is&#13;
uncertain, since it can be shown that real rents in the uncontrolled sector&#13;
can rise or fall after the imposition of controls (Fallis and Smith [19841),&#13;
although they are more like]Ly to rise (Ibid., and Malpezzi [1984 a]).&#13;
Table 20 lists some plausible explanations for differences in&#13;
quantities consumed by tenure. In general, property rights can be treated as&#13;
goods, and an owner living in a unit otherwise identical to a renter's&#13;
actually receives additional units of housing services, if such services are&#13;
broadly defined to include those generated by property rights. Alternatively,&#13;
they could be analyzed as a motivation for willingness to pay a price premium&#13;
for a unit with additional property rights, but treating the right as a good&#13;
6/   Of course in practice imperfect capital markets make it difficult to&#13;
actually turn the increased value into a stream of income without&#13;
selling the entire unit; but households certainly could conceptually&#13;
equate a given capital gain to some notional income stream, and such a&#13;
flow is easier to handle in the user cost model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
per se seems natural. Security of tenure is one of many possible property&#13;
rights inherent in owning.&#13;
Transactions costs are greater for owners than for renters. Under&#13;
plausible additional assumptions this can lead to a systematic divergence&#13;
between renter and owner consumption at different stages of the life cycle.&#13;
For example, as incomes decline late in life, renters will likely adjust&#13;
housing consumption downward faster than owners, leading to observed larger&#13;
consumption for owners at a given income level. However, counter examples&#13;
which work in the other direction are easily thought of (low-income earners&#13;
buying more housing in anticipation of future income growth), so the net&#13;
effect is uncertain. But given the difficulty of financing, there is an&#13;
interesting assymetry: young wage earners cannot easily borrow against their&#13;
expected future income, so they rent; older workers can easily hold onto an&#13;
already owned asset. This could yield a higher observed average consumption&#13;
for owners at a particular income level.&#13;
Finally, in countries which lack alternative investment&#13;
opportunities, housing becomes a vent for savings, and investment demand fuels&#13;
additional consumption by owners. Egypt is a clear example of such a&#13;
phenomenon, where large remittances from workers abroad have fueled a real&#13;
estate boom in Cairo in recent years.7/&#13;
2. Rent-to-Income Ratios by Tenure&#13;
Table 21 illustrates differences in housing consumption for owners&#13;
and renters at similar income levels. These are based on estimated housing&#13;
expenditure functions presented in Tables 2 and 3, where consumption for&#13;
7/   Mayo et al. (1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 21&#13;
RENT-TO-INCOME RATIOS BY INCOME (SUS PER MONTH)&#13;
$50       $100       S150      300             CITY AVERAGE&#13;
COLOMBIA&#13;
BOGOTA          (OWNERS)  0.32      0.27       0.24      0.20            0.20&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.33      0.26       0.23      0.18            0.18&#13;
(RATIO)   0.95       1.01      1.05       1.12           1.13&#13;
(1 320)&#13;
CALI            (OWNERS)  0.28      0.22       0.20      0.16            O.17&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.47      0.32       0.25      O.17            0.19&#13;
(RATIO)   0.59      0.70       0.78      0.92            0.89&#13;
(S 259)&#13;
EGYPT&#13;
BENI SUEF       (OWNERS)  0.22      0.15       0.12      0.08            O.16&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.11      0.08       0.06      0.06            0.09&#13;
(RATIO)   2.02       1.89      1.82       1.71           1.95&#13;
(t 74)&#13;
CAIRO           (OWNERS)  0.19      0.11       0.08      0.04            0.10&#13;
(RENTERS) O.1O      0.07       0.06      0.04            0.07&#13;
(RATIO)   1.82       1.49      1.33      1.09            1.47&#13;
(S 104)&#13;
EL SALVAOOR&#13;
SANTA ANA       (OWNERS)  0.09      0.10       0.10      0.11            0.10&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.17      0.12       0.09      0.07            0.06&#13;
(RATIO)   0.53      0.82       1.06       1.63           1.22&#13;
(S 188)&#13;
SONSONATE       (OWNERS)  0.30      0.26       0.24      0.21            0.24&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.1S      0.11       0.09      0.06            0.08&#13;
(RATIO)   2.02      2.47       2.78      3.41            2.87&#13;
(S 167)&#13;
INDIA &#13;
BANGALORE       (OWNERS)  0.33      0.22       0.18      0.12            0.25&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.12      0.09       0.08      0.06            0.10&#13;
(RATIO)   2.69      2.42       2.28      2.06            2.50&#13;
(S 81)&#13;
KOREA&#13;
SUSAN           (OWNERS)  1.31      0.90       0.72      0.49            0.41&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.68      0.42       0.32      0.20            0.16&#13;
(RATIO)   1.93      2.13       2.25      2.48            2.60&#13;
(S 416)&#13;
KWANGJU         (OWNERS)  2.16       1.44      1.13      0.76            0.66&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.46      0.35       0.30      0.23            0.21&#13;
(RATIO)   4.68      4.07       3.75      3.26            3.12&#13;
(S 375)&#13;
OTH. K. C.      (OWNERS)  0.61      0.53       0.48      0.42            0.41&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.38      0.28       0.23      0.17            0.16&#13;
(RATIO)   1.61       1.90      2.10      2.48            2.53&#13;
(S 323)&#13;
SEOUL           (OWNERS)  1.40      0.95       0.76      0.51            0.40&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.77      0.52       0.42      0.29            0.22&#13;
(RATIO)   1.82       1.81      1.80       1.79           1.79&#13;
(S 469)&#13;
TAEGU           (OWNERS)  1.41      0.98       0.79      0.55            0.50&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.53      0.36       0.28      0.19            0.18&#13;
(RATIO)   2.67      2.74       2.77      2.84            2.85&#13;
(S 349)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 21&#13;
RENT-TO-INCOME RATIOS BY INCOHE (WUS PER MONTH)&#13;
$50       $100       $150      300             CtTY AVERAGt&#13;
PHILIPPINES&#13;
DAVAO           (OWNERS)  0.04       0.04       0.04      0.04            0.04&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.09       0.09      0.08       0.08            0.08&#13;
(RATIO)   0.45       0.49      0.51       0.55            0.51&#13;
(5 142)&#13;
MANILA          (OWNERS)  0.53       0.51       0.42      0.31            0.27&#13;
(RENTERS) 0.23       0.17      0.14       0.10            0.09&#13;
(RATIO)   3.02       3.03      3.03       3.03            3.03&#13;
(S 432)&#13;
U.S.&#13;
PHOENIX         (OWNERS)  3.49       1.9f       1.42      0.81            0.17&#13;
(RENTERS) 3.05       1.73       1.24      0.70            0.1S&#13;
(RATIO)   t.14       1.15       1.f5      f.s5            1.17&#13;
($1972)&#13;
PITTSBURGH      (OWNERS)  2.71       1.53       1.10      0.82            0.14&#13;
(RENTERS) 1.47       0.86      0.65       0.39            0.10&#13;
(RATIO)   1.84       1.73       1.68      1.56            1.37&#13;
(51645)&#13;
NOTES:&#13;
(1) CITY AVERAGE INCOME IS SAMPLE AVERAGE FOR BOTH RENTERS AND OWNERS.&#13;
(2) RENTS ARE PREDICTEO fROM NET RENT EXPENDITURE EQUATIONS.&#13;
(3) ALL NUMBERS ARE CONVERTED TO 1981 U.S. DOLLARS USING LOCAL CPI AND&#13;
OFFICIAL EXCHANGE RATES.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
renters is in terms of net rents and, for owners, in terms of net imputed&#13;
rents. Imputed rents are based either on owners' direct imputation, hedonic&#13;
imputation, or capitalized value as discussed in Chapter 2 8/&#13;
Note the results for Pittsburgh and Phoenix. The rent-to-income&#13;
ratios predicted by the regression results are believable for the city average&#13;
income, but extrapolation to low iLncomes not observed in the sample yields&#13;
very high ratios. Prediction so far out of sample often leads to such&#13;
nonsensical results.&#13;
The table illustrates three major points regarding housing&#13;
consumption by renters and owners: first, owners consume more housing than do&#13;
renters in almost all cities at almost all income levels. The median ratio of&#13;
owners' consumption relative to renters' for the cities portrayed (evaluated&#13;
at respective city mean incomes) is 1.86-owners consume 86 percent more&#13;
housing than renters at comparable incomes. Second, the relationship between&#13;
income and the relative housing consumption of both owners and renters is&#13;
generally positive, although the relationship is not particularly strong.&#13;
This is a product of the general similarity in renters' and owners' estimates&#13;
of the income elasticity of housing demand. That is, even though owners are&#13;
estimated to have generally higher demand elasticities, elasticities are not&#13;
so much higher that relative consumption increases markedly for owners as&#13;
incomes rise. Third, relative housing consumption by renters and owners is&#13;
highly variable from place to place, bearing only statistically weak&#13;
relationships to the market conditLons discussed above.&#13;
8/   It should be noted that ownerus' imputed rents are not counted as part of&#13;
owners' income; thus the ratios of rent to income shown for renters and&#13;
owners represent housing consumption relative to cash income rather than&#13;
housing expenditure to total income (including the implicit return on&#13;
housing assets).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
Figure 10 explores the simple relationship between the consumption&#13;
differential and the (log of) city average income. The regression line omits&#13;
the two U. S. cities, which are the right-most points on the graph. Note that&#13;
if the U.S. cities are deleted, the consumption differential increases with&#13;
income. Is this consistent with the earlier statement that long-run income&#13;
elasticities were similar for owners and renters? Yes, because relative&#13;
housing prices also increase with development; and as prices rise renter&#13;
consumption falls faster than owner consumption (recall that the renter price&#13;
elasticities were consistently smaller in Tables 16 and 17), thereby&#13;
increasing the ratio of owner to renter consumption.&#13;
3. Testing the Relationships Among User Cost, Market Conditions, and Tenure&#13;
Choice&#13;
More careful modeling requires that the sample be restricted to&#13;
observations where imputed rents are observed for owners, either directly or&#13;
predicted from a rental hedonic index. Imputations from amortized house&#13;
values are misleading in this modeling because a single amortization rate was&#13;
used in each market, so relationships between rents and asset prices are fixed&#13;
by construction. Unfortunately this restricts our sample size to only&#13;
10 cities.&#13;
Table 22 presents approximations to user cost of housing capital by&#13;
city. The first column presents the ratio of homeowner's imputed rent to&#13;
income at the city's sample mean income. The second column is the opportunity&#13;
cost of owning housing (mean value times a discount rate) divided by income,&#13;
again at the city's average income. Note that the first column is from rent&#13;
net of utilities. Since the full user cost cannot be calculated without&#13;
knowing expectations, depreciation, etc., we chose to compare simply the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 1 0&#13;
RATIO OF OWNER R/Y TO RENTER R/Y BY LOG OF INCOME&#13;
3. 5-&#13;
-~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
3.0                                                     *&#13;
2.5-          *                                  *&#13;
R&#13;
A  2.0-&#13;
T                                                    *&#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
0&#13;
1.5'                                      &#13;
*k                                                          *&#13;
*&#13;
1. 0-&#13;
4.0       4.4       4.8       S.2       5.6       6.0        6.4       6.8        7.2      7.6&#13;
LOG INCOME, 1981 U.S. DOLLARS&#13;
RATIOS EVALUATED AT CITY MEAN INCOME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 22&#13;
IHPUTED RENTS, OPPORTUNITY COST. AND VALUE, TO INCOME&#13;
WITH HOMEOWNERSHIP RATES IN SAMPLES. AND RECENT INFLATION&#13;
NET IMPUTED    OPPORTUNITY    RATIO          AVG VALUE TO     INFLATION    HOMEOWNERSHIP&#13;
RENT / INCOME  COST / INCOME  COL2 / COLI    INCOME RATIO         RATE           RATE&#13;
COLOBIA&#13;
BOGOTA              0.19            0.53           2.81             4.4           23.5           45&#13;
CALl                0.16           0.39            2.50             3.2           23.S           SO&#13;
EGYPT&#13;
CAIRO               0.10           0.90            9.12             7.5           12.9           31&#13;
EL SALVADOR&#13;
SANTA ANA           0.11           0.09            0.82             0.7           13.0           56&#13;
SONSONATE           0.22           0.21            0.93             1.7           13.0           25&#13;
INDIA&#13;
BANGALORE           0.21           0.30            1.42             2.5           13.2           17&#13;
PHILIPPINES&#13;
DAVAO               0.04           0.09            2.14             0.7           9.6            59&#13;
MANILA              0.28           0.54            1.90             4.5           12.7           56&#13;
U.S.&#13;
PHOENIX             0.17           0.24            1.39             2.0           6.7            71&#13;
PITTSBURGH          0.14           0.20            1.43             1.7           6.7            72&#13;
NOTES:&#13;
(1) ALL RATIOS CALCULATED AT AVERAGE OWNER INCOME FOR EACH CITY.&#13;
(2) RATIOS ARE RATIOS OF AVERAGES. RATHER THAN AVERAGE RATIOS.&#13;
(3) OPPORTUNITY COST EQUALS 1 PERCENT OF HOUSING VALUE.&#13;
(4) HOMEOWNERSHIP RATES ARE UNWEIGHTED SAMPLE MEANS AND THEREFORE APPROXIMATE&#13;
(5) INFLATION RATE IS ANNUAL CHANGE IN CPI FOR S YEARS PRECEDING THE SURVEY.&#13;
(6) ALL NUNERS ARE ADJUSTED BY LOCAL CPI TO 1981 U.S. DOLLARS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
opportunity cost of the structure and land to the current rent for that&#13;
structure and land. The ratio oil opportunity cost to current rent (column 3)&#13;
is then a measure of the total ownership premium. What has not been done is&#13;
to estimate how much of this total premium is based on expectations of future&#13;
rents and how much is a payment for security per se.  Future work can explore&#13;
how these two components are related in a risky asset model.&#13;
The other columns of Table 22 are self-explanatory. The value-to-&#13;
income ratio is an alternative measure of the strength of asset demand in each&#13;
city. Recent inflation (column 5) is often hypothesized to be positively&#13;
related to asset demand. The homeownership rate may interact with asset&#13;
demand in several ways. Cities with high homeownership rates may have deeper&#13;
housing markets, i.e. markets witih more frequent trades; this should keep the&#13;
premium down at any given level of asset demand. On the other hand, high&#13;
homeownership rates may be an indLcator of high asset demand.&#13;
The most striking resull: from Table 21 is the extreme divergence of&#13;
Cairo from the pattern found elsewhere. The large apparent difference in&#13;
consumption is in part explained by the existence of rent control in&#13;
Cairo. 9 Controlled monthly rentsu there are extremely low relative to&#13;
opportunity costs; more detailed analysis elsewhere shows that the apparent&#13;
price discount to renters is illusory, and is offset by side payments such as&#13;
utilities, renter maintenance expenditures, and key money-IO/&#13;
Strong patterns are difficult to discern with only a few cities, but&#13;
there is a slight positive association between the ratio in column 3 and&#13;
inflation. Multivariate models relating the ratio to market conditions&#13;
9/  Bogota, Cali and Bangalore also have rent control, but Cairo's rent&#13;
control law is the most restrictive.&#13;
10/ See Malpezzi (1984 b) for detailed analysis of Cairo rent control.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
(inflation, income, relative prices, climate, rent control) were not able to&#13;
discriminate among alternative explanations for differences, which is not&#13;
surprising given the sample size.&#13;
An alternative test is to examine the relationship between the ratio&#13;
and homeownership. Large ratios of opportunity cost to current rent should&#13;
discourage homeownership, ceteris paribus, or equivalently provide incentives&#13;
to switch tenure. Such a relationship is found to exist, but is not&#13;
statistically discernible from zero, so numerical results are not reported&#13;
here.&#13;
Future research can profitably focus on careful modeling of these.&#13;
relationships with additional data. These data can also be improved on by&#13;
computing the various measures of user cost separately for each household in a&#13;
set of samples, rather than relying on ratios of averages as was done here.&#13;
4. Tenure as a Set of Property Rights, and Disaggregated Results.&#13;
Most housing studies focus on differences between owners and renters&#13;
(see Table 1, and Lim et al.), and that is the approach adopted so far in this&#13;
paper. However, a few studies have examined the more complicated tenure&#13;
arrangements found in developing countries (e.g. Doebele [19831, Jimenez&#13;
[19841) and the next few paragraphs explore how further disaggregation of&#13;
tenure into (1) renters, (2) formal owners, (3) informal owners (squatters, or&#13;
those without legal title to land or without legal authority to build), and&#13;
(4) government subsidized or provided units affect the basic results 11/ This&#13;
does not exhaust all possible tenure breakdowns; tenure can be argued to be a&#13;
continuum of property rights rather than several mutually exclusive&#13;
11/ It can be argued that simple disaggregation schemes which do not account&#13;
for the simultaneity of the tenure and demand decisions bias the&#13;
elasticity estimates (as discussed in Section 2.2). However, simple&#13;
models were estimated in Cairo, Seoul, and Manila using pooled owner and&#13;
renter samples, and income elasticities were found to be robust.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
categories. Current research (Jimenez [1983], and Friedman, Jimenez and Mayo&#13;
[19851) is exploring these breakdowns in more detail; here the purpose is&#13;
simply to indicate the robustness of the results presented above to further&#13;
sample stratification.&#13;
Two models were estimated with data from Cairo and Manila&#13;
(Table 23). The first model is the simple model of Section 2 (log income,&#13;
household size and its square), and the second model is similar to the "large"&#13;
model of Section 3. It contains additional demographic variables but no price&#13;
term, and is called the "medium" sized model. Table 23 presents the income&#13;
elasticities and fits from these models; complete results are available upon&#13;
request.&#13;
In Cairo, the new renter sample (less public housing) has about the&#13;
same income elasticity asE the combined sample in Table 2, but in Manila the&#13;
income elasticity goes down. This is because the original Manila renter&#13;
sample contains some households who rent land and own their structure, and&#13;
these are now in the informal owner sample. The key result is the difference&#13;
between formal and informal owners: do formal owners have higher marginal&#13;
propensities to consume? The answer is yes in both markets, although the&#13;
difference is more striking in Manila. This is plausible because even these&#13;
disaggregated tenure claEssifications mask important differences in the details&#13;
of the arrangements in different markets. Manila informal owners include&#13;
people who rent land and own the structure, whereas few people have this&#13;
arrangement in Cairo; informal owners there are predominantly those who build&#13;
on land that they "own" without legal title or that they are proscribed from&#13;
building on by law.&#13;
Another key result is that government provided or subsidized housing&#13;
is consumed without relation to the usual determinants of demand. The lowest&#13;
income elasticities and the poorest fits are for this tenure group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 23&#13;
Income Elasticities from Demand Equations by Disaggregated Tenure&#13;
Cairo                                                   Manila&#13;
Simple           Medium            Sample             Simple             Medium              Sample&#13;
Model            Model              Size              Model              Model                Size&#13;
(Elasticity)         .39               .36              274                 .66                .64                615&#13;
(Std Err)           .050              .049                                 .047               .045&#13;
(Prob&gt;T)            .001              .001                               .0001               .0001&#13;
(Adj R-2)            .18               .25                                  .27                .33&#13;
(Typical R/Y)        .13               .14                                  .15                .13&#13;
(E1asticity)         .18               .13               50                 .29                .26                180&#13;
(Std Err)           .187              .198                                 .111               .110&#13;
(Prob&gt;T)            .349              .504                                 .011               .020&#13;
(Mdj R-2)            .06               .03                                  .04                .06&#13;
(Typical R/Y)        .13               .16                                  .09                .05&#13;
(Elasticity)         .26               .22                35                .80                .77                625&#13;
(Std Err)           .099              .109                                 .053              .051                                 c&#13;
(Prob&gt;T)            .015              .055                               .0001               .0001                               co&#13;
(Adj R-2)            .10               .24                                  .27                .33&#13;
(Typical R/Y)        .13               .20                                  .14                .08&#13;
(Elasticity)         .04               .04               24                 .34                .35                255&#13;
(Std Err)           .193              .197                                .068               .069&#13;
(Prob&gt;T)            .828              .825                               .0001              .0001&#13;
(Adj R-2)           -.14             -.16                                  .09                 .09&#13;
(Typical 1/Y)        .08               .05                                 .07                 .07&#13;
Log of rent explained by log of income, household size, household size squared.&#13;
Simple model plus length of tenure, sex and age of household head.&#13;
Estimated rent-to-income ratios, for 5-person household, male head age 30, in unit 10 years, with monthly&#13;
income of 80 pounds (Cairo) or 2400 pesos (Manila).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
When average propensities to consume are examined (Table 23), the&#13;
conclusions about differences between formal and informal sector consumption&#13;
and about the public sector are broadly reinforced. At typical income levels,&#13;
formal sector owners spend perhaps a little more than informal owners, but the&#13;
difference is more pronounced in Manila than Cairo. Public sector tenants&#13;
spend only a fraction of the amounts spent in other sectors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
V. CONCLUSIONS, AND DIRECTION FOR FUTURE RESEARCH&#13;
1. Summary Results&#13;
This paper has presented an abbreviated discussion of a larger&#13;
comparative study of housing demand in developing countries. Using a number&#13;
of high quality household-level data sets, a number of empirical regularities&#13;
have been found within and among developing country cities. Among these are,&#13;
at the household level:&#13;
1. Income elasticities of demand among renters are generally small&#13;
(on the order of 0.3 to 0.6); income elasticities of demand&#13;
among owners are somewhat larger (on the order of 0.4 to 0.8);&#13;
these results are generally consistent with findings for&#13;
developed countries.&#13;
2. Owners generally consume a good deal more housing than renters&#13;
at given income levels; this is not primarily a result of&#13;
differences in income elasticities of demand but rather a result&#13;
of differences in expenditure equation constant terms. This&#13;
suggests that variables such as tastes and assets play important&#13;
roles in causing consumption differences between renters and&#13;
owners.&#13;
3. Permanent income elasticities of demand for housing are somewhat&#13;
greater than current income elasticities, although in reasonably&#13;
complete" models of demand including price terms and&#13;
demographic variables, permanent income elasticities are only&#13;
moderately higher than current income elasticities in simpler&#13;
models.&#13;
4. Price elasticities of demand for cities analyzed here are on the&#13;
order of -0.8 to -1.0, considerably higher than estimates&#13;
produced elsewhere in the literature. However, these estimates&#13;
may have an upward bias because of a specification problem.&#13;
Important results at the city level include:&#13;
1. Rent-to-income ratios rise across cities as income increases, a&#13;
result of upward-shifting Engel curves. This phenomenon appears&#13;
to be associated with increases in the relative price of&#13;
housing, with differences between current and permanent income&#13;
elasticities of demand, and with differences in the time period&#13;
associated with the two levels of analysis. The city level&#13;
analyses presumably model very long-run behavior.&#13;
2. Very long-run (cross-city) income elasticities of demand are&#13;
estimated to be one or greater. Very long-run price&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
elasticities are less than one in absolute value. Income&#13;
elasticities are measured with better precision than price&#13;
elasticities.&#13;
3. Owners generally pay a significant premium for ownership&#13;
per se.  This premium, equal to the difference between the&#13;
opportunity cost of housing capital and the imputed rental value&#13;
of housing, is highly variable from place to place depending on&#13;
market conditions. In particular, ownership premia are high in&#13;
cities with high rates of housing inflation and significant&#13;
rates of asset formation through savings or workers'&#13;
remittances., Security of tenure also influences the magnitude&#13;
of the premium paid for ownership.&#13;
Comparing household level and city level results leads to the&#13;
following:&#13;
1. Income elasticities are much greater in the very long run than&#13;
within a market. The cross-section results are directly&#13;
relevant to behavior within a market, while the very long-run&#13;
results can be applied to make predictions as a country&#13;
develops. Both are necessary for correct analysis of projects,&#13;
as will be outlined below. This is not surprising, as it a&#13;
sound general principle that behavior is more responsive to&#13;
changes over longer periods of time.&#13;
2. Long-run price elasticities from the city level estimation are&#13;
lower in absolute value than the cross-section price&#13;
elasticitieEs. This is at variance with the principle just&#13;
enunciated. The price elasticity estimates suffer from more&#13;
severe errors in variables problems than the income&#13;
elasticities; because of the specifications used, the cross-city&#13;
specifications are probably biased towards zero, and the&#13;
household level estimates are likely biased towards one.&#13;
2. Policy Implications&#13;
Policy implications of these and other results from the housing&#13;
demand research project will be spelled out in detail in forthcoming&#13;
reports X1   Here several obvious policy implications will be briefly&#13;
mentioned.&#13;
Affordability calculations for target populations are a critical&#13;
element of project design. UntiL now, such projects relied on rules of thumb,&#13;
1/   Mayo and Gross (1985).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
often, for example, an assumption that households can spend between 20 and 25&#13;
percent of income on housing. The results described above demonstrate the&#13;
inadequacy of any single ratio to predict consumption for different income and&#13;
tenure groups in different places. In many respects the best solution is to&#13;
do a careful household survey which includes the target population, and to&#13;
proceed with simple econometric models like the ones described here to get&#13;
project-specific estimates. If constrained, a second best solution can be to&#13;
estimate a variable rule of thumb from the results in this paper. Using the&#13;
elasticities for the relevant tenure group, the cross-city model can be used&#13;
to predict the city's average consumption given only an estimate of city&#13;
average income and a few readily available country level variables such as GDP&#13;
per capita. Income elasticities within samples do not vary by much from city&#13;
to city, so a typical cross-section elasticity can be chosen (say the&#13;
average), or the elasticity from a city deemed similar to the project&#13;
location. This elasticity can be used to move along the city specific Engel&#13;
curve to locate an estimate of the affordability ratio of the target&#13;
population in the target city '/&#13;
Most current public sector housing projects contain subsidies,&#13;
implicit or explicit. How inefficient these subsidies are depends critically&#13;
on the demand and price elasticities of the participants. In general, larger&#13;
price elasticities imply larger benefits to participants to housing programs,&#13;
ceteris paribus, although it is well known that private benefits from a&#13;
subsidy are always less than the benefit from equivalent income transfers.&#13;
Larger income elasticities imply that unconstrained transfers will have larger&#13;
housing consumption effects, ceteris paribus. The current research has not&#13;
2/   See Mayo and Gross (1985).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
nailed down a single set of numbers which can be used to reliably estimate&#13;
precise measures of program efficiLency, but future work can use a range of&#13;
estimates to examine costs and bentefits of alternative programs qualitatively.&#13;
The findings on tenure epecific differences have several important&#13;
implications which will be spelled out in more detail in forthcoming work.&#13;
Note, for example, that affordability calculations that do not account for&#13;
tenure differences will be seriously biased in many cities. It is currently&#13;
common practice to use renter samples to make direct inferences about&#13;
affordability in owner occupied projects without adjustment for these cross&#13;
tenure differences; this is probably not a bad approximation if project target&#13;
groups are limited to current renters-3/ Another implication is that the&#13;
existence of highly variable homeownership premia suggests that, in some&#13;
markets, schemes that focus on increasing the rental stock are appropriate and&#13;
desirable, while in others high premia suggest that the focus should be on&#13;
increasing the homeowner stock.4/&#13;
3. Ongoing and Future Research Directions&#13;
Two general directions for future research are suggested by an&#13;
analogy to the well used capital widening-capital deepening dichotomy in&#13;
development economics. Clearly there are large gains to expanding the present&#13;
work to more countries, especially to adding more developed countries to&#13;
obtain a clearer picture of how housing market behavior changes throughout the&#13;
range of development. From a purely statistical point of view, additional&#13;
3/   Homeowners in developing countries consume more housing at given income&#13;
levels than renters (Chapter 4), but many have required long periods to&#13;
build up equity. See Mayo and Gross (1985) for more on this point.&#13;
4/   See The Urban Edge (1984) and Gilbert (1983).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 94 -&#13;
cities in the sample will enable careful empirical analysis of the effects of&#13;
market conditions and housing policies on consumption.  More work on the&#13;
correct specification of prices is essential, both within cross sections and&#13;
across cities.&#13;
Capital deepening can be represented by more intensive analysis of&#13;
particular policies in one or several countries. The effects of financial&#13;
markets, rent control, and tenure systems is being studied concurrently.&#13;
Results from these studies are being applied to project design issues and to&#13;
policy analysis in the following areas:&#13;
Housing demand estimates and project design.  Mayo and Gross (1985)&#13;
apply the demand model of Chapter 3 in an evaluation of World Bank financed&#13;
shelter projects. They find that the rules of thumb used in affordability&#13;
calculations can be much improved, and that projects often have larger&#13;
implicit subsidies than is commonly assumed.&#13;
Housing finance. Struyk and Turner (1985), and Mayo, Struyk and&#13;
Turner (1985) estimate behavioral models of *the joint demands for housing and&#13;
associated finance. Both formal and informal financing mechanisms are&#13;
included. Among other findings, access to formal finance per se is shown to&#13;
have a positive effect on housing consumption even after controlling for&#13;
household characteristics that affect both access and housing demand.&#13;
Informal finance and formal finance are not perfect substitutes, but the&#13;
demand for formal finance is shown to be sensitive to interest rates; at&#13;
market rates some substitution does occur.&#13;
Demand for individual housing characteristics. Follain and Jimenez&#13;
(forthcoming a, forthcoming b) survey the literature on the demand for housing&#13;
character and present estimates of such models for several developing country&#13;
cities. Gross (1984) shows how these kinds of estimates can be integrated&#13;
into computerized planning models currently used for project design. Ozanne&#13;
and Malpezzi (1984) examine the robustness of characteristic demand models,&#13;
and their findings suggest (as do Follain and Jimenez's, and Gross's) that&#13;
further study of the stability of these models is needed for reliable use in&#13;
project design.&#13;
Tenure security*  Jimenez (1984) models and estimates the premium&#13;
paid for secure tenure by both owners as renters in Davao, the Philippines.&#13;
Formal sector units are priced 18 percent (renters) to 58 percent (owners)&#13;
more than equivalent units in the informal sector. A theoretical paper by&#13;
Jimenez (forthcoming) shows that some punitive government actions designed to&#13;
reduce squatting may actually increase it under certain conditions.&#13;
Additional work by Hoy and Jimenez (1984) suggests that increasing security of&#13;
tenure represents a net efficiency gain to society, not just a transfer to&#13;
participants.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 95 -&#13;
Rent control. Malpezzi (1984 b) has provided a detailed empirical&#13;
analysis of the rent control regime of Cairo, with a focus on explicit&#13;
estimation of the role of key money and other side payments by tenants. On&#13;
average these side payments largely equilibrate the market; when they are&#13;
included, average rental prices are! almost identical to the average of&#13;
estimates of the long-run competitive price. However, these averages mask&#13;
large welfare gains and losses to Individual tenants. Malpezzi (1984 c)&#13;
provides a framework for ongoing comparative work which studies alternative&#13;
ways markets adjust to rent control, and the implications of different&#13;
adjustment mechanisms for alternative methods of decontrol.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
DATA APPENDIX&#13;
1. Household Data Sources&#13;
The empirical findings of this study are based on household surveys&#13;
-conducted in Colombia, El Salvador, Egypt, Ghana, India, Jamaica, the&#13;
Philippines, and the United States between 1974 and 1983. Following is a&#13;
brief description of surveys conducted in each of these countries.&#13;
Colombia. The 1978 Colombian household survey covering Bogota and&#13;
Cali was conducted as a part of the regularly scheduled quarterly household&#13;
survey by the Colombian Statistical Office (DANE). The City Study research&#13;
team from the World Bank assisted DANE in updating the sample frame for Bogota&#13;
from 1973 to 1978, and also in designing a more detailed questionnaire with&#13;
added sections on housing and transport.&#13;
The interviewed households were selected by a two-stage random&#13;
sampling technique. Using an updated 1973 Census frame, the cities were first&#13;
divided into geographic units containing ten or more dwelling units. In the&#13;
first stage, a sample of these was chosen with equal selection&#13;
probabilities. Ten dwelling units were then selected randomly from each&#13;
section to be interviewed. Each unit was assigned an appropriate weight based&#13;
on the total number of households in the section in order to allow reweighting&#13;
to obtain population statisitics.&#13;
The survey originally produced 3,062 household records from Bogota&#13;
and 980 records from Cali. Of the8e, 1,446 households in Bogota and 498 in&#13;
Cali were owner households. Each record contains detailed data on building&#13;
and dwelling unit characteristics, infrastructure, transportation mode,&#13;
household characteristics with information on each household member,&#13;
employment, income, and housing expenditure.&#13;
El Salvador. The 1980 El Salvador household survey covering Santa&#13;
Ana and Sonsonate was a part of three-period longitudinal surveys conducted by&#13;
the Salvadorean Low Cost Housing Foundation (FSDVM) under the guidance of the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
The quasi-experimental design with a mixed panel sample of the&#13;
survey covered a random sample of 196 project households and 326 control group&#13;
households in Santa Ana. The stratified non-proportional sample of the&#13;
control group was chosen from the three main types of low-income settlements&#13;
in the city. These are mesones (tenement houses), colonias illegales (extra-&#13;
legal subdivisions), and tugurios (illegal squatter settlements).&#13;
Approximately 100 households were chosen from each group.&#13;
For Sonsonate, 180 randomly selected project families and 140&#13;
control group households were covered by the survey.  The survey includes&#13;
information on dwelling units, housing costs, the construction process,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
household characteristics, income and expenditure, and health. Only control&#13;
group data are used in the analysis presented here.&#13;
Egypt.   The 1981 EgyptiLan household survey was conducted jointly by&#13;
Abt Associates, Inc., Dames and Moore, and the General Organization for&#13;
Housing, Building, and Planning Research (GOHBPR) with assistance from the&#13;
Central Agency for Mobilization anid Statistics (CAPMAS).&#13;
The survey was conducted as a two-stage probability sample of&#13;
dwelling units in Cairo and in the! city and principal villages surrounding&#13;
Beni Suef. In the first stage, 50 CAPMAS census enumeration districts in&#13;
Greater Cairo and 20 in Beni Suef were randomly chosen as the sample frames&#13;
for the second stage. The probability of an enumeration district being chosen&#13;
was proportional to the 1976 enumeration district population of dwelling&#13;
units. There were 12,986 dwelling units in 3,386 buildings in the enumeration&#13;
districts chosen in the first stage sample for Cairo and 4,452 dwelling units&#13;
in 3,131 buildings in Beni Suef.&#13;
The household survey (occupant survey) was a simple random sample&#13;
with ten households chosen in each enumeration district based on the above&#13;
sample frame. In Cairo, 500 households were sampled; in Beni Suef, 250&#13;
households were interviewed. Of Beni Suef households, 130 were in Beni Suef&#13;
city and 120 in nearby villages. Of these, 154 households in Cairo and 184&#13;
households in Beni Suef were owner households. The survey contains detailed&#13;
information on household characteristics including data on income,&#13;
expenditure, consumer durables, houasing financed, demographic characteristics,&#13;
mobility and migration, attitudes and preferences regarding housing and&#13;
infrastructure, and informal sectoir attitudes and behavior. Also included in&#13;
the survey are detailed housing characteristics such as building&#13;
characteristics, access to infrastructure services, housing costs and cost&#13;
elements, process of land and building acquisition, and construction&#13;
processes. In all, data were collected on up to 420 data elements for each&#13;
household and dwelling unit.&#13;
In addition to the household level information, aggregate&#13;
characteristics of housing and inf2astructure in each sampled enumeration&#13;
district are included. Further documentation is contained in Mayo et al.&#13;
(1981).&#13;
Ghana. A survey of 1,534 households in Kumasi was collected by Dr.&#13;
Graham Tipple of the University of Newcastle upon Tyne. Data were collected&#13;
on housing and household characteristics; the sampling unit was the house, and&#13;
the frame was stratified by housing sector: tenement, indigenous, government,&#13;
and high cost. The tenement sector is comprised mainly of multistory compound&#13;
housing (about 20 percent of the stock); the indigenous sector is by far the&#13;
largest, and is mainly single story compound houses of traditional design.&#13;
The remaining sectors, much smaller, are the high cost sector (European style&#13;
single family design), and the government sector (bungalows and row houses).&#13;
The data are fully documented in Tipple (1982).&#13;
India. A survey of 1,745 households in Bangalore for the Bangalore&#13;
City Survey Project conducted by the Institute for Social and Economic Change,&#13;
Bangalore. The sample frame was conlstructed from updated census records in&#13;
two stages: first, 150 sample frame blocks were chosen, then households from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 98 -&#13;
within blocks. The survey has quite good information on income, assets, and&#13;
demographic variables, and some information on housing characteristics.&#13;
Professor V. K. Tewari is currently working on supplementing this survey with&#13;
additional data on structure age and type of rent control regimes. The data&#13;
are documented further in Prakasa Rao and Tewari (1979).&#13;
Jamaica. These data are from the Jamaican Government's 1975&#13;
Household Expenditure Survey. The survey contains detailed expenditure data,&#13;
but little information on housing characteristics. There are over 3,000&#13;
households in the total survey, but the estimates reported in this paper are&#13;
restricted to renters residing in either Kingston or its adjacent parish.&#13;
Monthly housing expenditures by renters was used as a proxy for rent.&#13;
Korea. The Korean household survey was conducted during November of&#13;
1979 by the National Bureau of Statistics of Korea on behalf of the Korea&#13;
Housing Bank.&#13;
The survey used 1975 census tracts as its sampling frame. The&#13;
sampling unit, household, was selected by a systematic sampling from the urban&#13;
households participating in the labor force which were first stratified by the&#13;
types of occupation. The survey covered around 2,000 dwellings in 36&#13;
cities. The data contains records for 5,935 households, of which 2,315 were&#13;
owner households. Of the total households, 41.5% were in Seoul.&#13;
The survey contains 99 variables for each household pertaining to&#13;
household characteristics, income, savings, total expenditure, expenditure on&#13;
housing, dwelling unit characteristics, infrastructure, and desired housing&#13;
characteristics.&#13;
Due to the use of the 1975 sample frame, the survey might not have&#13;
captured some areas where rapid growth has taken place since 1975. In&#13;
particular, a rapid increase in apartment units in the latter half of the&#13;
1970s (as occurred) might have resulted in some undersampling of such units.&#13;
Philippines: Davao. The 1979 Davao household survey was conducted&#13;
by the Davao Action Information Center, a non-profit foundation directed by&#13;
Professor Robert A. Hackenberg of the University of Colorado. The sample is&#13;
taken from a random drawing of 4,161 households from a sampling frame derived&#13;
by updating master lists of the Philippine Census. All socio-economic strata,&#13;
including squatters, were represented in the sample.&#13;
Of the 4,161 original households, 3,517 were classified as renters&#13;
or owners. The homeownership rate was 51 percent. Among 3,392 respondents&#13;
who reported non-zero rents or assessed sale values, 1,570 households were&#13;
squatting households.&#13;
Philippines: Manila. This survey of 1,688 households was conducted&#13;
in 1983, under the direction of Professor Mila Reforma of the University of&#13;
the Philippines, with inputs from World Bank staff and the National Housing&#13;
Authority. The sample was stratified by barangay (a neighborhood designation&#13;
which typically contains up to several thousand residents). one hundred fifty&#13;
of Metro Manila's 1,692 barangays were chosen randomly in the first stage;&#13;
then a sampling frame was constructed for each barangay, and a sample (average&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
about 10 units) was drawn from each. The exact number depended on the&#13;
population of each barangay., so that the sample is self-weighting.&#13;
The survey questionnaire has particularly detailed information on&#13;
the construction process and housing finance, in addition to the usual&#13;
questions on household characteristics, income, expenditures, and housing&#13;
characteristics.&#13;
United States. Pittsburgh and Phoenix (1974) were chosen as&#13;
representative U.S. cities from the 59 metropolitan areas covered by the&#13;
metropolitan Annual Housing Survey (AHS), which was carried out by the U.S.&#13;
Bureau of the Census for the Department of Housing and Urban Development.&#13;
Pittsburgh is an older, "slow growth" metropolitan area with a declining&#13;
industrial base; Phoenix is a fast growing "sunbelt" city.&#13;
Each metropolitan sample comprises about 5,000 households. The&#13;
sampling scheme is a stratified clujster design which is rather complex, but&#13;
described in U.S. Bureau of the Census (various issues). The samples for&#13;
these cities are roughly self-weighting, although the cluster sampling leads&#13;
to some unknown bias in the usual estimates of variances.&#13;
The survey has quite good data on housing characteristics (except&#13;
for location), and some data on household incomes. The AHS has undergone&#13;
numerous changes since the 1974-75 round of sampling, and current surveys,&#13;
when publicly available, will have more detailed information on housing&#13;
finance.&#13;
2. Macro Data Sources&#13;
Many of the city level variables are constructed from the household&#13;
survey data, and these are obvious from the context. This section describes&#13;
the sources of other city and country level variables, with particular&#13;
emphasis on the relative price of housing.&#13;
Three candidates were cornsidered for the relative price index: the&#13;
constuction cost index developed by, Annez (1981), and two indexes from the&#13;
work of Kravis et al., namely a rental index and an index of the cost of&#13;
residential capital. All three share an important drawback: they are only&#13;
available by country, rather than by city (even finer breakdowns would be&#13;
desirable, see Polinsky 1977). The Annez index and the residential capital&#13;
index do not account for land, which accounts for a large share in housing&#13;
production. The rental index does not account for differences in price&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 100 -&#13;
between tenure groups (neither do the other three), but it has the virtue of&#13;
including the land and other inputs as well as capital.&#13;
The construction of the rental price index using hedonic techniques&#13;
is described in detail in Kravis et al. The index was constructed as the&#13;
ratio of two purchasing power parity indexes, residential rent and total GDP,&#13;
from Table 6.3 of Kravis et al. The index was unavailable for Egypt, Ghana,&#13;
and El Salvador so an instrument was employed for these countries. The Kravis&#13;
1/&#13;
et al. sample of countries was used to estimate the following equation:-&#13;
Relative Price -  1.748&#13;
(1.088)&#13;
-.068 Log Population&#13;
(.069)&#13;
-.004 Percent Urban&#13;
(.007)&#13;
+.127 Urban Population Growth Rate&#13;
(.063)&#13;
+.044 Log GDP Per Capita&#13;
(.134)&#13;
-.180 (Exports + Imports)/GDP&#13;
(.414)&#13;
-.020 Average Temperature, Centigrade, Coldest&#13;
Month&#13;
(.009)&#13;
with an adjusted R-square of .19, and 21 degrees of freedom. This yielded&#13;
predicted relative prices of .88 for Egypt, .88 for El Salvador, and 1.09 for&#13;
Ghana.&#13;
Sources of other variables include the following:&#13;
Population, percent urban GNP per capita, exports, imports: World&#13;
Bank, World Development Report, various issues.&#13;
1/   Standard errors in parentheses.  Several socialist countries were found&#13;
to be outliers and were dropped from the sample.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 101 -&#13;
Climate: Average temperature over 5 years, coldest month, from&#13;
Clayton and Clayton (1947). In some cases, the nearest city with recorded&#13;
temperatures was used.&#13;
Urbanization rates: Dillinger (1979).&#13;
Exchange rates: International Monetary Fund, International&#13;
Financial Statistics, various issues. The single exception was Ghana. During&#13;
the sample period the Ghanaian ciedi was so grossly overvalued that we used a&#13;
conservative unofficial estimate of the exchange rate, 22 cedis to the dollar.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
DATA APPENDIX&#13;
CITY LEVEL DATA&#13;
RELATIVE           RENTER R TO Y OWNER R TO Y    HOME      AVG. ANNUAL  LOCAL CPI&#13;
RENT    AVERAGE   AT AVERAGE     AT AVERAGE   OWNERSHIP  CPI CHANGE    CHANGE      EXCHANGE&#13;
COWNTRY       CITY          POPULATION   INDEX   INCOME    CITY INCOME    CITY INCOME    RATE      OVER 5 YR5,  TO 1981  RATE (it9S1i&#13;
COLOMBIA&#13;
BOGOTA          3.440      1.16     320         0.18           0.20          45         23.5        2.0t        59.00&#13;
CALI            1.100      1.16     259         0.f9           0.17          50         23.5        2.0t        59.00&#13;
EGYPT&#13;
SENI SUEF       0.300      0.88      74         0.09           0.18          71         12.9         1.00        0.70&#13;
CAIRO           5.890      0.88     104         0.07           O.10          31         t2.9         1.00        0.70&#13;
EL SALVADOR&#13;
SANTA ANA       0.o110     O.88     18          0.08           0.10          56         13.0        1.15         2.50&#13;
SONSONATE       0.038      0.88     167         0.08           0.24          25         13.0        1.15         2.50&#13;
GHANA&#13;
KUMASI          0.590      1.09      79         0.03             .           32         68.4        2.16        22.00&#13;
INDIA&#13;
BANGALORE       2.700      0.41      81         O.1O           0.25          17         13.2         1.So        9.10&#13;
JAMAICA&#13;
KINGSTON        0.6       t1.29    502          0.27             .           1          13.8        3.05         1.78&#13;
KOREA                                                                                                                                    0&#13;
SUSAN           3.160      1.63     416         0.16           0.4t         36          16.6        1.56        700.5&#13;
KWANGJU         0.730      1.63     375         0.21           0.66          35         16.6        1.56        700.5&#13;
OTH. K. C.       .         1.63     323         0.16           0.41         42          16.6        1.56        700.5&#13;
SEOUL           8.370      1.63     469         0.22           0.40         39          16.6        1.56        700.5&#13;
TAEGU           1.610      1.63     349         0.18           0.50         33          16.6        1.56        700.5&#13;
PHILIPPINES&#13;
DAVAO           2.160      0.59     142         0.08           0.04         59           9.6        1.32         8.20&#13;
MANILA          6.000      0.59     432         0.09           0.27         56          12.7        0.79        8.20&#13;
U3.S.&#13;
PHOENIX         1.240      1.00    1972         0.15           0.17         71           6.7        1.69         1.00&#13;
PITTSBURGH      2.330      1.00    1845         O.1O           O.14         72           6.7        1.69         1.00&#13;
NOTES:&#13;
(1) POPULATION IN MILLIONS&#13;
(2) INCOME IN 1981 U.S. DOLLARS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 103 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Aaron, Henry J. Shelter and Su'bsidies: Who Benefits from Federal Housing&#13;
Policies? Washington: The Brookings Institution, 1972.&#13;
Ando, Albert and Franco Modigliani.  The Life Cycle Hypothesis of Saving:&#13;
Aggregate Implications and Tests. American Economic Review, March&#13;
1963, 53, pp. 55-84.&#13;
Annez, Philippe. Housing Investment: A Cross Country Comparison. Ph.D.&#13;
Thesis, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1981.&#13;
Annez, Philippe and William C. 'Wheaton. Economic Development and the Housing&#13;
Sector: A Cross-National Model. Economic Development and Cultural&#13;
Change, 32(4), July 1,984, pp. 749-766.&#13;
Bamberger, Michael, Edgardo Gonzalez-Polio, and Umnuay Sae-Hau.  Evaluation of&#13;
Sites and Services Projects: The Evidence from El Salvador. World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper No. 549, 1982.&#13;
Betancourt, Roger. Household Behavior in Chile: An Analysis of Cross-Section&#13;
Data. Lluch, et al. (eds.), Patterns in Household Demand and&#13;
Saving. New York: Oxford University Press, 1977. Chapter 8.&#13;
Bradbury, Katherine and Anthony Downs. Do Housing Allowances Work?&#13;
Washington: The Broo'kings Institution, 1981.&#13;
Branson, William H. Macroeconoimic Theory and Policy (Second Edition). New&#13;
York:  Harper tnd Row, 1979.&#13;
Buckley, Robert M. and RanJana G. Madhusudhan. The Macroeconomics of&#13;
Housing's Role in the Economy: An International Analysis. Paper&#13;
presented to the American Real Estate and Urban Economics&#13;
Association, December 1984.&#13;
Burns, Leland S. and Leo Grebler. Resource Allocation to Housing Investment:&#13;
A Comparative International Study. Economic Development and&#13;
Cultural Change, 25(1), October 1976, pp.-95-121.&#13;
Clayton, H. Helm and Frances L. Clayton. World Weather Records. Washington:&#13;
The Smithsonian Institution, 1947.&#13;
de Leeuw, Frank. The Demand for Housing: A Review of Cross Section Evidence.&#13;
Review of Economics and Statistics. February 1971, 53(1), pp. 1-10.&#13;
de Leeuw, Frank, and Larry Ozanne. Housing, in H. Aaron and J. Pechman, eds.,&#13;
How Taxes Affect Economic Behavior. Washington: The Brookings&#13;
Institution, 1981.&#13;
Diamond, Douglas B., Jr. A Note on Inflation and Relative Tenure Prices.&#13;
Journal of the American Real Estate and Urban Economics Association,&#13;
6, 1978, pp. 438-450.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 104 -&#13;
Dillinger, William. A National Urban Pattern Data File for 114 Countries.&#13;
Urban and Regional Report No. 79-5, The World Bank, September 1979.&#13;
Doebele, William. Selected Issues in Urban Land Tenure. In H. Dunkerley&#13;
(ed.), Urban Land Policy: Issues and Opportunities. New York:&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1983.&#13;
Duesenberry,.J. S. Income, Saving, and the Theory of Consumer Behavior.&#13;
Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1949.&#13;
Falke, Caj. Growth of Effective Demand for Housing in the Federal Territory&#13;
1975-80. Urban Development Authority, Kuala Lumpur. Mimeographed,&#13;
May 1976.&#13;
Fallis, George and Lawrence B. Smith. Uncontrolled Prices in a Controlled&#13;
Market: The Case of Rent Controls. American Economic Review,&#13;
74(1), March 1984, pp. 193-200.&#13;
Follain, James R., Jr. Does Inflation Affect Real Behavior: The Case of&#13;
Housing. Southern Economic Journal, January 1982.&#13;
Follain, James and Emmanuel Jimenez. Estimating the Demand for Housing&#13;
Characteristics: A Survey and Critique. Regional Science and Urban&#13;
Economics (forthcoming, a).&#13;
Follain, James and Emmanuel Jimenez. The Demand for Housing Characteristics&#13;
in Developing Countries. Urban Studies (forthcoming, b).&#13;
Follain, James and Stephen Malpezzi. Dissecting Housing Value and Rent:&#13;
Estimates of Hedonic Indexes for Thirty-Nine Large SMSAs&#13;
Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute, 1980.&#13;
Follain, James and Stephen Malpezzi.  Are Occupants Accurate Appraisers?&#13;
Review of Public Data Use, 9, June 1981, pp. 47-55.&#13;
Follain, James, Gill-Chin Lim and Bertrand Renaud. The Demand for Housing in&#13;
Developing Countries: The Case of Korea. Journal of Urban&#13;
Economics, 7(3), May 1980, pp. 315-336.&#13;
Freeman, A. Myrick.  The Benefits of Environmental Improvement:  Theory and&#13;
Practice. Resources for the Future, 1979.&#13;
Friedman, Joseph and Daniel Weinberg.  The Great Housing Experiment.  Sage&#13;
Publications, 1983.&#13;
Friedman, Joseph, Emmanuel Jimenez, and Stephen K. Mayo. The Demand for&#13;
Secure Tenure in Developing Country Cities. Mimeographed, 1985.&#13;
Friedman, Milton. A Theory of the Consumption Function. Princeton, N. J.:&#13;
Princeton University Press, 1957.&#13;
Furubotn, Eirik G. and Svetozar Pejovich. Property Rights and Economic&#13;
Theory: A Survey of Recent Literature. Journal of Economic&#13;
Literature, June 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-105-&#13;
Gilbert, Alan. The Tenants of Self-Help Housing: Choice and Constraint&#13;
in the Housing Markets of Less Developed Countries. Development&#13;
and Change, 14, 1983, pp. 449-477.&#13;
Grimes, Orville F., Jr. Housing for Low-Income Urban Families: Economics and&#13;
Policy in the De  e     n,opng World.  Washington:  The World Bank, 1976.&#13;
Gross, David J. Designing a Suitable Housing Project: Integration of a&#13;
Demand Module into a Supply Side Planning Model. Presented at the&#13;
31st Annual Meetings of the Regional Science Association, November&#13;
1984.&#13;
Hamer, Andrew.  Households and Housing:  Residential Mobility, Tenure Choice,&#13;
and Space Consumption in the Developing Metropolis. World Bank&#13;
Urban and Regional Report No. 80-20, December 1981.&#13;
Hanushek, Eric and John Quigley. An Explicit Model of Intra-Metropolitan&#13;
Mobility.  Land Economics, November 1978, pp. 411-29.&#13;
Hausman, Jerry A. Exact Consumer's Surplus and Deadweight Loss. American&#13;
Economic Review, (71:4), September 1981, pp. 662-675.&#13;
Hirsch, Werner Z.  Law and Economics:  An Introductory Analysis.  New York:&#13;
Academic Press, 1979.&#13;
Howe, Howard and Philip Musgrove.  An Analysis of ECIEL Household Budget Data&#13;
for Bogota, Caracas, Guayaquil, and Lima. Lluch, et al. (eds.),&#13;
Patterns in Household Demand and Saving. New York: Oxford&#13;
University Press, 1977.&#13;
Howenstine, E. Jay.  Appraising the Role of Housing in Economic Development.&#13;
International Labor Rev:Lew, 75, January 1957.&#13;
Hoy, Michael and Emmanuel Jimenez. Analytical Issues in Urban Land Tenure in&#13;
Developing Countries. 1Mlimeographed, 1984.&#13;
Ihlanfeldt, Keith Ray. An Empirical Investigation of Alternative Approaches&#13;
to Estimating the Equillbrium Demand for Housing. Journal of Urban&#13;
Economics, 9, 1981, pp. 97-105.&#13;
Ingram, Gregory. Housing Demand in the Developing Metropolis: Estimates&#13;
from Bogota and Cali, Colombia. World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
No. 663, 1984.&#13;
Jimenez, Emmanuel. The Economics of Self-Help Housing: Theory and&#13;
Some Evidence from a Developing Country. Journal of Urban&#13;
Economics, 11, 1982, pp. 205-228.&#13;
Jimenez, Emmanuel. Tenure Securilty and Urban Squatting. Review of Economics&#13;
and Statistics, 66(4), Niovember 1984, pp. 556-567.&#13;
Jimenez, Emmanuel. Urban Squatting and Community Organization in Developing&#13;
Countries. Journal of JPublic Economics (forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 106 -&#13;
Jimenez, Emmanuel, and Douglas Keare. Housing Consumption and Permanent&#13;
Income in Developing Countries: Estimates from Panel Data in El&#13;
Salvador. Journal of Urban Economics, 15, 1984, pp. 172-194.&#13;
Keare, Douglas and Emmanuel Jimenez. Progressive Development and Afford-&#13;
ability in the Design of Urban Shelter Projects. World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 560, 1983.&#13;
Korea Research Institute for Human Settlements. Interim Report on Housing&#13;
Policy Development Research. Seoul, Korea, 1982.&#13;
Kravis, Irving B., Alan Heston, and Robert Summers. World Product and Income:&#13;
International Comparisons of Real Gross Product. Baltimore: Johns&#13;
Hopkins University Press, 1982.&#13;
Kuznets, Simon. Quantitative Aspects of the Economic Growth of Nations.&#13;
VI. Long-Term Trends in Capital Formation Proportions. Economic&#13;
Development and Cultural Change, 9(4), July 1961.&#13;
Lee, Lung-fei and Robert Trost. Estimation of Some Limited Dependent Variable&#13;
Models with Application to Housing Demand. Journal of&#13;
Econometrics. December 1978, pp. 357-382.&#13;
Lim, Gill-Chin, James Follain and Bertrand Renaud. Determinants of Homeowner-&#13;
ship in a Developing Economy: The Case of Korea. Urban Studies,&#13;
17, 1980, pp. 13-23.&#13;
Linneman, Peter. The Demand for Residence Site Characteristics. Journal of&#13;
Urban Economics, 1981.&#13;
Lluch, Constantino, Alan Powell, and Ross Williams. Patterns in Household&#13;
Demand and Saving. Oxford University Press, 1977.&#13;
Malpezzi, Stephen. Rent Control and Housing Market Equilibrium: Theory and&#13;
Evidence from Cairo, Egypt. Mimeographed, 1984 (a).&#13;
Malpezzi, Stephen. Economic Analysis of Alternative Rent Control Policies,&#13;
With an Application to Cairo, Egypt. Presented at the 31st Annual&#13;
Meetings of the Regional Science Association, November 1984 (b).&#13;
Malpezzi, Stephen. Rent Controls: An International Comparison. Paper&#13;
presented to the American Real Estate and Urban Economics&#13;
Association, December 1984 (c).&#13;
Mayo, Stephen K. Housing Expenditures Under a Percent of Rent Housing&#13;
Allowance. Abt Associates, 1977.&#13;
Mayo, Stephen K. Theory and Estimation in the Economics of Housing Demand.&#13;
Journal of Urban Economics, July 1981, 10(1), pp. 95-116.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 107 -&#13;
Mayo, Stephen K. and David J. Gross. Applications of Housing Demand Research&#13;
to Project Design and Economic Analysis. Mimeographed, 1985.&#13;
Mayo, Stephen K. and others, Informal Housing in Egypt. Abt Associates,&#13;
1982.&#13;
Mayo, Stephen K., with Stephen Malpezzi and Sungyong Kang. Housing Demand in&#13;
Developing Countries. World Bank, Water Supply and Urban&#13;
Development Department. Mimeographed 1983.&#13;
Mayo, Stephen K., Raymond Struyk, and Margery Austin Turner. Housing Finance&#13;
and Household Behavior in Devloping Countries. Paper presented to&#13;
the American Real Estate and Urban Economics Association, December&#13;
1984.&#13;
Mayo, Stephen K., Shirley Mansfield, David Warner and Richard Zwetchkenbaum.&#13;
Housing Allowances and Other Rental Housing Assistance Programs--A&#13;
Comparison Based on the Housing Allowance Demand Experiment,&#13;
Part 1: Participation, Housing Consumption, Location, and&#13;
Satisfaction. ikbt Associates, 1980.&#13;
Mieszkowski, Peter and Mahlon Straszheim (eds.). Current Issues in Urban&#13;
Economics, Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1979.&#13;
Muth, Richard. The Demand for Non-Farm Housing. The Demand for Durable&#13;
Goods, ed. by Arnold Harberger. University of Chicago Press, 1960.&#13;
Muth, Richard. The Derived Demand for Urban Residential Land. Urban Studies,&#13;
1971.&#13;
Olsen, Edgar and David Barton. The Benefits and Costs of Public Housing in&#13;
New York City. Journal of Public Economics, 20(3), April 1983,&#13;
pp. 299-332.&#13;
Ozanne, Larry and Stephen Malpezzi. The Efficacy of Hedonic Estimation with&#13;
the Annual Housing Survey: Evidence from the Demand Experiment.&#13;
Mimeographed, 1985.&#13;
Phlips, Louis. Applied Consumption Analysis. North Holland, 1974.&#13;
Polinsky, A. M. The Demand for Housing: A Study in Specification and Group-&#13;
ing. Econometrica, 42, March 1977, pp. 447-61.&#13;
Pollak, Robert and Terence Wales. Demographic Variables in Demand Analysis.&#13;
Econometrica, 49(6), November 1981, pp. 1533-1551.&#13;
Quigley, John. What Have We Learned About Urban Housing Markets? in&#13;
Mieszkowski and Straszlheim (eds.), Current Issues in Urban&#13;
Economics. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1979,&#13;
pp.391-429.&#13;
Quigley, John. Nonlinear Budget Constraints and Consumer Demand: An&#13;
Application to PFublic Programs for Residential Housing. Journal of&#13;
Urban Economics, 12, 1982, pp. 177-201.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 108 -&#13;
Rao, Potluri and Roger Miller. Applied Econometrics. Belmont, California:&#13;
Wadsworth Press, 1971.&#13;
Renaud, Bertrand. Resource Allocation to Housing Investment: Comments and&#13;
Further Results. Economic Development and Cultural Change, 28(2),&#13;
January 1980, pp. 389-99.&#13;
Renaud, Bertrand. -ousing and Financial Institutions in Developing Countries.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 658, 1984.&#13;
Rosen, Harvey. Housing Decisions and the U.S. Income Tax: An Econometric&#13;
Analysis. Journal of Public Economics, 11, February 1979, pp. 1-23.&#13;
Rosen, Sherwin. Hedonic Prices and Implicit Markets: Product Differentiation&#13;
in Pure Competition. Journal of Political Economy, January 1974.&#13;
Shefer, Daniel. The Demand for Housing and Housing Characteristics in&#13;
Indonesia. Center for Urban and Regional Studies, Technion (Haifa,&#13;
Israel). Mimeographed 1983.&#13;
Strassmann, W. Paul. The Construction Sector in Economic Development.&#13;
Scottish Journal of Political Economy, (17), 1970.&#13;
Strassmann, W. Paul. Housing Improvement in an Opportune Setting: Cartagena,&#13;
Colombia. Land Economics, May 1980.&#13;
Straszheim, Mahlon. An Econometric Analysis of the Urban Housing Market.&#13;
New York: National Bureau of Economic Research, 1975.&#13;
Struyk, Raymond and Margery Austin Turner. Housing Finance and Housing&#13;
Quality in the Philippines and Korea. Working Paper No. 3401-02.&#13;
The Urban Institute, Washington, D. C., January 1985.&#13;
The Urban Edge. Rental Housing: A Rediscovered Priority. Vol. 8, No. 2,&#13;
February 1984.&#13;
U.S. Bureau of the Census, Annual Housing Survey: 1974 (various issues).&#13;
Villani, Kevin. The Tax Subsidy to Housing in an Inflationary Environment:&#13;
Implications for After-Tax Housing Cost. C. F. Sirmans, ed.,&#13;
Research in Real Estate (Greenwich, Connecticut: JAI Press), 1981.&#13;
Weicher, John. Urban Housing Policy, in Mieszkowski and Straszheim (eds.),&#13;
Current Issues in Urban Economics. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins&#13;
University Press, 1979, pp. 469-508.&#13;
Weicher, John and David Hartzell. Transactions in New and Existing Homes.&#13;
Urban Institute Contract Report 1291-2, 1980.&#13;
Weinberg, Daniel, Joseph Friedman, and Stephen Mayo. Intraurban&#13;
Residential Mobility: The Role of Transactions Costs, Market&#13;
Imperfections, and Hbusehold Disequilibrium. Journal of Urban&#13;
Economics, 9(3), 1981, pp. 332-348.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 109 -&#13;
The World Bank. World Development Report (various years).&#13;
Yotopoulos, Pan A. and Jeffery B. Nugent. Economics of Development:&#13;
Empirical Investigaltions. New York: Harper and Row, 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                           European Office                 Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                    66, avenue d'lena               Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.         75116 Paris, France             1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234              Telephone: (1) 723-54.21        Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK             Telex: 842-620628               Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                              Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
[5/ISBN 0-8213-0539-5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="700838">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/05/700838/housing-demand-developing-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/05/700838/housing-demand-developing-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/05/700838/housing-demand-developing-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1985/05/01/000009265_3980901130637/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1985/05/01/000009265_3980901130637/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1985-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-07-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Housing demand in developing countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper reports on research conducted
            to increase understanding of developing country markets,
            particularly housing demand behaviour. The objectives of the
            paper are: (i) to review previous evidence on housing demand
            parameters; (ii) to present new evidence on housing demand
            parameters (price and income elasticities and demographic
            effects) based on application of standardized models and
            comparable variable definitions in 14 cities in six
            developing countries; and (iii) to examine the similarities
            and differences and attempt explanations for place-to-place
            differences. The analysis emphasizes differences in housing
            demand by tenure and stresses the importance of accounting
            for the impact of permanent income on housing demand. The
            research on which the paper is based encompasses: (i) the
            demand for housing; (ii) determinants of land and housing
            rents and values; and (iii) demand for individual housing characteristics.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Housing demand in developing countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Housing demand in developing countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1985/05/700838/housing-demand-developing-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Public Sector Management and Reform,Urban Governance and Management,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Regional Governance</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>Philippines,Egypt, Arab Republic of,Korea, Republic of,Ghana,El Salvador,Colombia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Malpezzi, Stephen</author>
            <author>Mayo, Stephen K.</author>
            <author>Gross, David J.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe, Middle East and North Africa!$!107234</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Central America!$!80455</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Asia!$!80460</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>North Africa!$!80464</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>West Africa!$!80474</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000009265_3980901130637</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Urban housing</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific,Africa,Africa,Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa,Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 733</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Urban Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0539-5</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Comparative analysis; Demand; Household
            income; Housing; Housing policy; Market research; Africa
            Demand Curves,developed
            countries,econometric
            models,economists,elasticities,elasticity of demand,Engel
            curve,Engel Curves,Functional forms,FUTURE RESEARCH,GDP,GDP
            per capita,GNP,Housing,income,income elasticity,income
            elasticity of demand,income levels,inelastic
            demand,Inflation,market prices,Opportunity Cost,Permanent
            income,policy instruments,Price Elasticities,Price
            Elasticity,Property Rights,public sector,rent
            control,savings,shelter,urban growth,urban
            services,urbanization,utilities,wages,wealth,willingness to pay
        </keywd>
        <owner>Environ &amp; Soc Sustainable Dev VP (ESD)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe, Middle East and North Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Central America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>North Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>West Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP733</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance for Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mortgages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance &amp; Real Estate Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Controls</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Controls </ml:concept><ml:concept>Rental Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Markets</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>