<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                                                                                                                              37199&#13;
310&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       privatesector       P U B L I C       P O L I C Y      F O R       T H E&#13;
&#13;
   NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         NOTE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             2006&#13;
                                                                                                                          Phasing Out Subsidies&#13;
                 AUGUST&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              Robert Bacon and            Recent Experiences with Fuel in Developing Countries&#13;
                                                                                              Masami Kojima&#13;
                                                                                                                          Many developing countries subsidize petroleum products. The doubling&#13;
                       PRESIDENCY                                                             Robert Bacon&#13;
                                                                                                                          of world oil prices since January 2004 has had very high fiscal costs&#13;
                                                                                              (rbacon@worldbank.org)&#13;
                                 VICE                                                         is a consultant, and        for these countries, increasing public debt and squeezing other&#13;
                                                                                              Masami Kojima               government spending. The subsidies have also had unintended&#13;
                                                                                              (mkojima@worldbank.org)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              a lead energy specialist,   consequences: fuel adulteration, smuggling, and benefits that go&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              in the World Bank's Oil,    mostly to the better-off. But phasing out subsidies is politically&#13;
                                     DEVELOPMENT&#13;
                                                                                              Gas, and Mining Policy&#13;
                                                                                                                          challenging. This Note reviews some successful strategies for removing&#13;
                                                                                              Division.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          or reducing subsidies while protecting the poorest consumers.&#13;
                                                SECTOR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          The large and sustained increase in interna-        The government of Thailand introduced price&#13;
                                                      PRIVATE                                                             tional oil prices since late 2003 has led many      ceilings on petroleum products in January 2004.&#13;
                                                                                                                          developing countries to adopt pricing policies      Expecting that the price increase would be&#13;
                                                             AND&#13;
                                                                                                                          to protect users from the full impact. In a world-  short-lived, the government initially estimated&#13;
                                                                                                                          wide sample of 38 developing countries during       that the price control would last no more than&#13;
                                                                                                                          the period January 2004­May 2006, 14 coun-          two months and that the fiscal cost would be at&#13;
&#13;
                                                                FINANCIAL                                                 tries suspended market-based pricing that           most US$128 million. By the time it removed&#13;
                                                                                                                          linked domestic to international prices (for one    the subsidies--in October 2004 for gasoline and&#13;
                                                                                                                          or more fuels).1 They joined 12 others that had     in July 2005 for diesel--the bill had reached&#13;
                                                                                                                          already controlled prices, keeping them at lev-     US$2.2 billion. In the Arab Republic of Egypt&#13;
                                                                                                                          els that, by 2005, were below the international     the estimated cost of the subsidy on petroleum&#13;
                                                                         GROUP&#13;
                                                                                                                          equivalent. In addition, 23 countries reduced       products during the fiscal year ending June&#13;
                                                                                                                          taxes on petroleum products to help offset the      2006 was revised upward to US$7.1 billion in&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              BANK                                        higher costs (ESMAP 2006).                          February. And in Indonesia the government's&#13;
                                                                                                                             Many of the subsidy schemes were prompted        cost in 2005 was close to US$10 billion.&#13;
                                                                                                                          in part by incorrect assumptions about how             By mid-2006, with world oil prices having&#13;
                                                                                                                          large the price increase would be and how long      more than doubled since the beginning of&#13;
                                                                                  WORLD                                   it would last. So while the fiscal effects of the   2004, net oil importers had all concluded that&#13;
                                                                                                                          policies have varied, for some governments they     large fuel subsidies were unsustainable. So had&#13;
                                                                                       THE                                have been unexpectedly large and protracted.        some major oil exporters that were having to&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
P H A S I N G O U T S U B S I D I E S R E C E N T E X P E R I E N C E S W I T H F U E L I N D E V E L O P I N G C O U N T R I E S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      import refined products because years of subsi-                                         ing it with kerosene. This leads to a substantial&#13;
                                      dies had led to undercapitalization of their                                            leakage of the kerosene subsidy.&#13;
                                      refining sector.                                                                            A study of household surveys conducted in&#13;
                                                                                                                              1993/94 and 1999/2000 in India suggests that as&#13;
                                      Unintended consequences                                                                 much as half of subsidized diesel was diverted to&#13;
                                      Subsidizing fuels has high costs. Moreover, uni-                                        the automotive diesel and other sectors. This&#13;
                                      versal price subsidies almost always benefit high-                                      leakage cost the government close to US$1 bil-&#13;
                                      income households more than the poor, because                                           lion in fiscal 2000 (ESMAP 2003). These lucra-&#13;
                                      richer households consume more energy. Other                                            tive but illegal activities enable criminal elements&#13;
2&#13;
                                      adverse consequences include rampant abuses in                                          to flourish. Some become extremely powerful, as&#13;
                                      fuel markets (Kojima and Bacon 2001) and an                                             recent events in Iraq illustrate.&#13;
                                      inefficient downstream petroleum sector lan-                                                Because petroleum products are easy to store&#13;
                                      guishing for need of reform.                                                            and transport, another problem arises where a&#13;
                                            To provide a subsidy, a government must                                           neighboring country charges higher prices. Fuel&#13;
                                      increase its borrowing, raise additional revenue                                        price subsidies then create a strong incentive to&#13;
                                      elsewhere, or reduce spending on other public                                           smuggle out the subsidized fuel for resale at these&#13;
                                      goods. If the subsidy is used to stabilize or lower                                     higher prices, as governments of Argentina, the&#13;
                                      final prices, it frees consumers from having to                                         Islamic Republic of Iran, Iraq, Kazakhstan,&#13;
                                      adjust their purchasing behavior to the costs of                                        Malaysia, Nigeria, República Bolivariana de&#13;
                                      supply, instead giving them financial incentives                                        Venezuela, and Vietnam can attest. This results in&#13;
                                      to overconsume the subsidized commodity. The                                            higher apparent demand and the transfer of ben-&#13;
                                      result is the well-known deadweight loss.                                               efits to inhabitants of the neighboring states.&#13;
                                            Using a reduction in taxes to lower final                                             Another adverse consequence is suffered by&#13;
                                      prices, because it leads to a loss of revenue, sim-                                     the downstream oil sector. An essential part of&#13;
                                      ilarly requires a government to raise additional                                        improving sector efficiency is the introduction of&#13;
                                      revenue or reduce other public spending. If tax                                         relentless but fair competition. Subsidies deter&#13;
                                      rates were set near the optimal level overall                                           firms from entering the market--as in Nigeria&#13;
                                      before the price rise, this policy also results in a                                    and Sri Lanka, for example. Without new&#13;
                                      loss of welfare.                                                                        entrants and the infusion of capital, the sector&#13;
                                            The relative sizes of subsidies for different                                     becomes increasingly inefficient, undercapital-&#13;
                                      petroleum products also matter. Many govern-                                            ized, and, in some cases, corrupt. In the long run&#13;
                                      ments provide larger subsidies for diesel and,                                          governments and consumers pay a high price.&#13;
                                      even more so, for kerosene than for gasoline. The&#13;
                                      rationale is that diesel is used economywide--in                                        Policies to remove or reduce subsidies&#13;
                                      goods, public transport, agriculture, fishing, and                                      Historically, in countries where fuel prices are&#13;
                                      in some cases electricity generation--while                                             controlled and subsidized by the government,&#13;
                                      kerosene is used for lighting and cooking by poor                                       price increases have often met with broad oppo-&#13;
                                      households. By contrast, gasoline tends to be con-                                      sition from civil society and trade unions.&#13;
                                      sumed by better-off households.                                                         Consider the violent demonstrations against&#13;
                                            This approach helps target the subsidies in                                       fuel price hikes in Indonesia, Nigeria, and&#13;
                                      theory and can reduce the overall costs. But                                            Venezuela. Since the end of 2003 several gov-&#13;
                                      diesel is primarily a transport fuel and con-                                           ernments have attempted to reduce subsidies. A&#13;
                                      sumed more (directly and indirectly) by middle-                                         few have been able to do so without much oppo-&#13;
                                      and high-income households than by the poor                                             sition. Some have felt that their political posi-&#13;
                                      in many developing countries. The result is a                                           tion was too weak to risk opposition and have&#13;
                                      leakage of the diesel subsidy to higher-income                                          kept fuel prices frozen or increased them very&#13;
                                      groups. In addition, where the subsidy for                                              little.&#13;
                                      kerosene is substantially larger than that for                                              This experience points to the need for gov-&#13;
                                      diesel--as it is in many developing countries--                                         ernments to find a way of defusing potential&#13;
                                      there is an incentive to adulterate diesel by mix-                                      opposition to removing or reducing subsidies.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Two policy measures have been used to do so:&#13;
                                                       Table  Average retail price ratios for fuels&#13;
I Providing targeted subsidies or compensation.&#13;
                                                    1&#13;
I Using an effective publicity campaign.                       Fuels                                        Price ratio&#13;
   Providing a larger subsidy or lower tax rate                Diesel/kerosene                              1.3&#13;
for kerosene than for other fuels is the most                  Gasoline/diesel                              1.3&#13;
common way to target subsidies to lower-income                 Gasoline/kerosene                            1.6&#13;
&#13;
households. The international market prices&#13;
(net of taxes and transport costs) for diesel,              Note: The table reflects the most recent price information for 27 developing&#13;
                                                            countries for which data were available.&#13;
kerosene, and gasoline are very similar. In the             Source: ESMAP 2006.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                     3&#13;
sample of developing countries, however, many&#13;
governments, through taxation (and subsidy)          US$1.24­2.48 a month to offset the rising costs&#13;
policy, ensure that kerosene is sold at a discount   of liquefied petroleum gas. And in October&#13;
relative to diesel and at a sizable discount rela-   2005 the government of Indonesia launched an&#13;
tive to gasoline (table 1). Maintaining markedly     ambitious cash transfer scheme to compensate&#13;
different price levels for similar fuels results in  for raising product prices by an average of 114&#13;
significant adulteration.                            percent, though the final level was still below&#13;
   Another way to target subsidies is to issue       international market prices (box 1).&#13;
vouchers or smart cards that permit users to buy          Indonesia shows how an effective public rela-&#13;
a limited amount of certain fuels at a reduced       tions campaign, coupled with general trust in&#13;
price. The smart card can be limited to certain      the government, can help achieve public accept-&#13;
classes of users, for differing amounts of fuel.     ance of large price increases. In January 2003&#13;
Malaysia recently began using smart card systems     the previous administration had attempted to&#13;
for public transport vehicles and fishing boats.     increase prices amid widespread public dis-&#13;
   A different approach to protecting lower-         satisfaction with the government and with the&#13;
income households involves removing subsidies        corruption and inefficiency perceived to be per-&#13;
while providing targeted compensation, through       meating the political life and bureaucracy. A&#13;
a cash transfer or benefit in kind, to protect these public outcry led the government to roll back&#13;
households from the impact. If targeting is rea-     much of the diesel price increase. By contrast,&#13;
sonably accurate and administrative costs rela-      in 2005 the current administration more than&#13;
tively low, this approach is likely to be the most   doubled gasoline and diesel prices and nearly&#13;
efficient in nearly all circumstances. But that      tripled the kerosene price with no substantial&#13;
requires two things. First, there must be a rea-&#13;
sonably accurate list of low-income households to&#13;
                                                       Box    Launching a cash transfer scheme in Indonesia&#13;
ensure that only the needy, and most of the&#13;
                                                     1&#13;
needy, are compensated. Second, there must be                  Before raising fuel prices in October 2005, the government of Indonesia put into place a cash transfer&#13;
a low-cost mechanism for transferring the cash or              scheme targeting 15.5 million poor and near-poor households (some 28 percent of the population).&#13;
benefits to these households, or administrative                The transfers, quarterly payments of about US$30 per household, are to be continued for one year.&#13;
&#13;
costs could outweigh the benefits of targeting                 The scheme was widely publicized--through newspapers, village notice boards, television talk shows,&#13;
&#13;
compensation.                                                  and pamphlets with answers to frequently asked questions.&#13;
&#13;
   Several countries have used some variation of                   Though prepared quickly, the program has performed well. The rapid rollout was followed by many&#13;
                                                               media reports about initial problems, including mistargeting and leakage. The government responded&#13;
this approach. In 2005 Chile made a one-time&#13;
                                                               quickly, commissioning an early assessment of the program. The assessment pointed to satisfactory&#13;
payment of US$28 to low-income households to&#13;
                                                               results overall, with transfers on time and beneficiaries expressing satisfaction.&#13;
compensate for higher fuel prices and provided&#13;
                                                                   For poor recipients the cash transfers more than compensate for the fuel price increase. Even with&#13;
extra cash compensation to 1.4 million house-                  moderate mistargeting--with cash benefits randomly distributed to the poorest 40 percent rather&#13;
holds consuming less than 150 kilowatt-hours of                than the targeted 28 percent--the program is expected to prevent an increase in poverty due to the&#13;
electricity a month. In 2006 it announced                      price increase.&#13;
another round of cash transfers, US$35 to 1.25                     Thanks to the government's efforts, the sharp rise in fuel prices passed without major public&#13;
million families living on less than US$350 a                  protest.&#13;
month. For a short period in early 2006 some&#13;
provinces    in   China    gave   poor    residents         Source: ESMAP 2006.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
P H A S I N G O U T S U B S I D I E S R E C E N T        E X P E R I E N C E S W I T H F U E L I N D E V E L O P I N G C O U N T R I E S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
opposition, thanks to a cash compensation                                      Conclusion&#13;
scheme coupled with the government's greater                                   Fuel price subsidies help the poor, but at a large&#13;
popularity and its public relations campaign.                                  cost to society and to governments. Governments&#13;
   Some governments considering removing                                       should look for opportunities to move away from&#13;
or reducing subsidies have promised to                                         fuel price subsidies as rapidly as possible and                           viewpoint&#13;
increase social spending as compensation, par-                                 replace them with targeted assistance to the poor.&#13;
ticularly where the spending might support                                     Preparatory work to identify beneficiaries and&#13;
lower-income households. Two actions can                                       design efficient ways to deliver assistance should&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         is an open forum to&#13;
increase the effectiveness of this strategy. First,                            be given high priority, especially since high oil&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         encourage dissemination of&#13;
demonstrating to civil society that the present                                prices are likely to continue in the coming years.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         public policy innovations for&#13;
subsidies benefit mainly the better-off. And sec-&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         private sector­led and&#13;
ond, improving social spending in a way that is&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         market-based solutions for&#13;
transparent, immediate, effective, and pro-&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         development. The views&#13;
poor. Ghana provides an instructive example:                                   Note&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         published are those of the&#13;
it combined prior analysis of which groups                                           1. The 38 countries are Argentina, Bangladesh,                      authors and should not be&#13;
were benefiting most from the subsidies with a                                 Brazil, Cambodia, Cameroon, Chile, China, the Arab                        attributed to the World&#13;
campaign publicizing the measures that would                                   Republic       of   Egypt,       Ethiopia,       Ghana,     Guatemala,    Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
be used to compensate for removing the subsi-                                  Honduras, India, Indonesia, Kazakhstan, Kenya, the                        organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
&#13;
dies (box 2).                                                                  Kyrgyz Republic, the Lao People's Democratic Republic,                    the conclusions represent&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               Madagascar,        Malawi,         Malaysia,       Mexico,    Morocco,    official policy of the World&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               Mozambique,          Nicaragua,          Nigeria,        Pakistan, the    Bank or of its Executive&#13;
  Box   Removing subsidies in Ghana&#13;
                                                                               Philippines, Rwanda, Senegal, Sri Lanka, Tanzania,                        Directors or the countries&#13;
2        In 2004, when it became apparent that world oil                       Thailand, Tunisia, Uganda, República Bolivariana de                       they represent.&#13;
&#13;
         prices were unlikely to come down much and that                       Venezuela, Vietnam, and Zambia.&#13;
         Ghana could not maintain for long its policy of subsi-                                                                                          To order additional copies&#13;
&#13;
         dizing petroleum products, the government launched a                  References                                                                contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
&#13;
         poverty and social impact assessment (PSIA) for fuel.                       ESMAP (Energy Sector Management Assistance                          managing editor,&#13;
&#13;
         Guided by a steering committee of stakeholders from                                                                                             Room F 4K-206,&#13;
                                                                               Programme). 2003. "India: Access of the Poor to Clean&#13;
         ministries, academia, and the national oil company, the                                                                                         The World Bank,&#13;
                                                                               Household Fuels." Report 263/03. Washington, D.C.&#13;
         PSIA was completed in less than a year. By the time                                                                                             1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
                                                                                     ------. 2006. "Coping with Higher Fuel Prices."&#13;
         the government announced the 50 percent price                                                                                                   Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
                                                                               Report 323/06. Washington, D.C.&#13;
         increases in February 2005, it could use the PSIA find-&#13;
         ings to make its case for liberalizing fuel prices to the                   Kojima, Masami, and Robert Bacon. 2001. "Abuses in&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         Telephone:&#13;
         public--including the fact that the price subsidies                   Fuel Markets: How to Protect Consumers and Public&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         001 202 458 7281&#13;
         most benefited the better-off.                                        Health." Viewpoint series, Note 237. World Bank Group,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         Fax:&#13;
              The minister of finance launched the public relations            Private Sector Development Vice Presidency, Washington,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         001 202 522 3480&#13;
         campaign with a broadcast explaining the need for the                 D.C.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         Email:&#13;
         price increases and announcing measures to mitigate&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
         their impact. A series of interviews with government&#13;
         officials and trade union representatives followed. The&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         Produced by Grammarians,&#13;
         Energy Ministry used newspaper advertisements with&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         Inc.&#13;
         charts to show that Ghana's fuel prices were the lowest&#13;
         in West Africa after Nigeria's.&#13;
              The mitigation measures, transparent and easily                                                                                            Printed on recycled paper&#13;
&#13;
         monitored by society, included an immediate elimina-&#13;
         tion of fees at government-run primary and junior sec-&#13;
         ondary schools and a program to improve public&#13;
         transport. While the trade unions remained opposed to&#13;
         the price increases, the public generally accepted them,&#13;
         and no large-scale demonstrations occurred.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Source: ESMAP 2006.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    T h i s N o t e i s a v a i l a b l e o n l i n e :&#13;
                                                                                              h t t p : / / r r u . w o r l d b a n k . o r g / P u b l i c P o l i c y J o u r n a l&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="7039589">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/08/7039589/phasing-out-subsidies-recent-experiences-fuel-developing-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/08/7039589/phasing-out-subsidies-recent-experiences-fuel-developing-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2006/08/7039589/phasing-out-subsidies-recent-experiences-fuel-developing-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/09/07/000310607_20060907111939/Rendered/INDEX/371990VP0no03100Bacon1Kojima01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/09/07/000310607_20060907111939/Rendered/PDF/371990VP0no03100Bacon1Kojima01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2006-08-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2006-09-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Phasing out subsidies : recent experiences
            with fuel in developing countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Many developing countries subsidize
            petroleum products. The doubling of world oil prices since
            January 2004 has had very high fiscal costs for these
            countries, increasing public debt and squeezing other
            government spending. The subsidies have also had unintended
            results. But phasing out subsidies is politically
            challenging. This paper reviews some successful strategies
            for removing or reducing subsidies while protecting the
            poorest consumers.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Phasing out subsidies : recent experiences
            with fuel in developing countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Phasing out subsidies : recent
            experiences with fuel in developing countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2006/08/7039589/phasing-out-subsidies-recent-experiences-fuel-developing-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Oil Refining &amp; Gas Industry,Energy Production and Transportation,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Transport Economics Policy &amp; Planning,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Energy,Transport,Industry</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Bacon, Robert</author>
            <author>Kojima, Masami</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000310607_20060907111939</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 310</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Energy,Transport,Industry</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            adverse consequence, adverse consequences,
            agriculture, approach, automotive diesel, consumers,
            controlled prices, diesel, downstream oil, electricity,
            electricity generation, fair, financial incentives, Fuel,
            Fuel price, fuel price increase, fuel prices, fuel
            subsidies, fuels, gasoline, income groups, inefficiency,
            international market, international oil prices, kerosene,
            kilowatt-hours, liquefied petroleum gas, market prices,
            national oil, net oil, oil, oil company, oil exporters, oil
            importers, oil prices, oil sector, petroleum, petroleum gas,
            petroleum products, petroleum sector, price ceilings, price
            control, price increases, price levels, price subsidies,
            pricing policies, PRIVATE SECTOR, public relations, public
            transport, public transport vehicles, publicity, purchasing,
            refined products, refining, retail, retail price, tax, tax
            rate, taxation, transport costs, world oil prices
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off of VP, FPD - WB (FPDVP)</owner>
        <repnb>37199</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>SOE Oil Companies</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Oil Companies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oil Refining &amp; Gas Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cash Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuel Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Unions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Oil Companies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>