<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                    38195&#13;
                              THE DOMINICANREPUBLIC&#13;
&#13;
              ProgrammaticPower Sector Reform Loan (Loan 7292-DO)&#13;
               Release of the FirstTranche andRequest for One Waiver&#13;
&#13;
                                 Tranche Release Document&#13;
&#13;
1.      The Bank approved a Programmatic Power Sector Reform Loan (PPSRL) o f&#13;
US$l50 million for the Dominican Republic on May 10,2005 (Report No. 31741-DO o f&#13;
April 12, 2005). The PPSRL has yet to be declared effective due to the reversal o f a&#13;
number o f prior conditions to Board presentation. All prior conditions have now been&#13;
metwith the exception of one for which we seek awaiver.&#13;
&#13;
2.      The PPSRL supports the initial phase of the Government's strategy for the&#13;
financial recovery o f the power sector to stabilize electricity supply, by improving cash&#13;
recovery, controlling costs and dealing with arrears. The PPSRL i s part o f a program o f&#13;
assistance to the energy sector to assist the Government during the transition period&#13;
towards the financial recovery o f the sector to reestablish regular electricity services, and&#13;
restore trust among investors. It will assist the Government inthe provision o f declining&#13;
subsidies while strengthening the management o f the distribution companies to reduce&#13;
losses and improve collection by stabilizing power supply, and enforcing payment&#13;
discipline among consumers.&#13;
&#13;
3.      The PPSRL i s designed to be disbursed inthree tranches. The first tranche will be&#13;
disbursed at effectiveness, while the second and third floating tranches will be released&#13;
when the corresponding conditions are met. Although the Government initially met the&#13;
conditions prior to presentation o f PPSRL to our Board in May 2005, it took over six&#13;
months for the Loan Agreement to be presented to Congress and ratified. During this&#13;
period andinthe following months, the Government began to accumulate arrears with the&#13;
private generation companies inviolation o f one of the prior conditions, and decided not&#13;
to apply the formula for the automatic adjustment o f retail tariffs for variations in&#13;
exchange rate, fuel price and inflation, thereby violating another prior condition. The&#13;
Government recently cleared its arrears with the generation companies, and i s currently&#13;
providing compensatory measures in lieu o f the tariff adjustment to ensure that the&#13;
financial sustainability o f the distribution and generation companies will not be affected.&#13;
Inthe last few months, the fiscal situationdeteriorated, puttingat risk the macroeconomic&#13;
framework going forward; however a package o f revenue and expenditure measures for&#13;
2006 and 2007 was recently agreed with the IMF under its Stand-By Arrangement&#13;
(SBA), which should put the country back into a sustainable debt path and satisfactory&#13;
macroeconomic framework.&#13;
&#13;
4.      The following sections o f this memorandum summarize the progress in&#13;
implementing the reform program supported by the PPRSL.&#13;
&#13;
5.      Overall, implementation o f the policies supported by the PPSRL has shown&#13;
progress inreaching the objectives o f this program, despite the political difficulties o f the&#13;
Government, the dramatic increase inthe internationalprice o f oil, and the difficulties o f&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              - 1 -&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
reversing the culture o f non payment o f electricity bills by consumers. Arrears with the&#13;
generation companies have now been settled and the only unmet condition relates to the&#13;
application of the formula for the automatic adjustment o f retail tariffs for variations in&#13;
exchange rate, fuel price and inflation. The Government i s providing compensatory&#13;
resources to the sector to ensure that the financial viability o f the distribution and&#13;
generation companies will not be affected by the corresponding shortfall inrevenues.&#13;
&#13;
6.      Going forward, the Government has developed a comprehensive plan for the&#13;
sector to improve service quality and toughen sanctions for the theft o f electricity. As&#13;
part o f this plan and o f the combined 5th and 6th review o f the Stand-By Arrangement&#13;
with the IMF, the Government is committed to allow electricity tariffs to fluctuate inline&#13;
with the automatic adjustment formula. Incase electricity tariffs were temporarily lower&#13;
thanthereference tariffs, the Government will cover any additionaltransfers to the sector&#13;
by reducing non-priority spending. The Government also expects to complete a review&#13;
o f the tariff structure by June 2007, aimed at reducing incentives to commit electricity&#13;
fraud and at channeling subsidies to low-income households.&#13;
&#13;
7.      Based on the overall implementation o f the program, and in view of the recent&#13;
improved performance o f the distribution companies (see below) and progress in the&#13;
implementation o f a comprehensive program for the recovery o f the sector, a waiver i s&#13;
proposed for the following condition: "revision and implementation of aformula for the&#13;
automatic adjustment of retail tarvfs for variations in exchange rate, fuel prices and&#13;
inflation". Upon Board approval o f this proposal, the Bank would advise the Borrower&#13;
that the loan i s declared effective andthat the first tranche i s available for withdrawal.&#13;
&#13;
          I. RecentEconomicPerformanceandProspects&#13;
&#13;
8.      Inthe aftermath of the banking and macroeconomic crisis of 2003 and 2004, the&#13;
Dominican economy experienced a booming recovery in 2005 when it posted real GDP&#13;
growth o f 9.3 percent. Continued strong growth during the first three quarters o f this&#13;
year suggests an annual real growth rate o f at least 10 percent for 2006. Economic&#13;
stability has improved markedly during this period. Inflation returned to single digits in&#13;
2005 and 2006 fi-om average annual rates o f 27 and 51 percent in 2003 and 2004,&#13;
respectively, and the exchange rate stabilized to about RD$30/US$ in 2005 compared to&#13;
RD$49/US$ in early 2004 (the peso is currently trading at RD$33/US$).               Imports and&#13;
FDIhave largely recovered since the crisis. Whereas gross international reserves were&#13;
severely depleted during the 2003-04 macroeconomic crisis, dipping below US$300&#13;
million, the subsequent steady build-up has led to reserve levels o f US$2.3 billion&#13;
currently, providing a reasonable cushion for the Central Bank. Banking sector deposits&#13;
andcredit to the private sector have been increasing since end-2004, and interest rates for&#13;
both lending and deposits have declined dramatically.           Risk spreads on international&#13;
bonds have also fallen sharply, from highs o f around 1,100 basis points in2003 to current&#13;
levels of 200-250 basis points.&#13;
&#13;
9.      The strong growth performance in2005 and 2006 contributed to lower debt ratios&#13;
(also aided by key debt restructurings by the Paris and London Clubs), and two tax&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              - 2 -&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
reforms coupledwith the introduction o f expenditure controls andbetter budgetprocesses&#13;
led to a marked improvement in the fiscal balance, from an overall NFPS deficit o f 3.6&#13;
percent o f GDP in 2004 to near balance in 2005 (-0.4 percent o f GDP). Nevertheless,&#13;
fiscal pressures remained in2006, particularly due to the highenergy sector subsidies and&#13;
lower-than-anticipated revenues from the 2005 tax reforms and the foreign exchange&#13;
commission, leading to a 2006 projected overall NFPS fiscal deficit considerably larger&#13;
thanthe zero balance originally programmedunder the IMF Stand-By Arrangement. To&#13;
address this slippage, the authorities agreed to expenditure restraint for the remainder o f&#13;
2006 in order to achieve a 0.8 percent deficit, and have agreed with the IMF on a tax&#13;
reform package estimated to yield 1.5 percent o f GDP (beginningin2007). Furthermore,&#13;
the authorities are drafting a 2007 budget (in consultation with the IMF and to be&#13;
submitted to Congress in the coming weeks) that is consistent with the IMF program&#13;
target o f a 2007 primary surplus equal to 2.2 percent o f GDP.&#13;
&#13;
10.     Looking ahead, the prospects for sustained GDP growth and maintaining&#13;
macroeconomic stability are good.          Several institutional reform measures currently&#13;
pending Congressional approval will strengthen budget controls and thus solidify&#13;
progress on the fiscal front, and the forthcoming entry into effectiveness o f the free trade&#13;
agreement between the Dominican Republic, U S and Central American countries - DR-&#13;
CAFTA - will boost export demand and increase imports from the US, to the benefit o f&#13;
consumers and producers (albeit with an expected decline in tariff revenue).             The&#13;
Government intends to request an eight-month extension (through January 2008) o f the&#13;
IMF Stand-By Arrangement to support the implementation of its economic program&#13;
during2007.&#13;
&#13;
                             11. The Power Sector ReformProgram&#13;
&#13;
11.     The actions supported by the PPSRL aim at initiating the financial recovery o f the&#13;
sector to stabilize power supply, by improving cash recovery, controlling costs and&#13;
dealing with arrears.&#13;
&#13;
12.     The implementation o f the PPSRL program has been satisfactory, particularly in&#13;
the recent months when the distribution companies started to obtain tangible results in&#13;
terms o f loss reduction and collection improvement. As mentioned above, although the&#13;
Government initially met the sectoral conditions prior to presentation o f the PPSRL to&#13;
our Board in May 2005 (see Table 1 below), subsequently the Government decided to&#13;
discontinue the applicationo f the formula for the automatic adjustment o f retail tariffs for&#13;
variations in exchange rate, fuel price and inflation, thereby violating a prior condition.&#13;
The Government however i s providing compensatory measures to ensure that the&#13;
financial sustainability o f the distribution and generation companies will not be affected.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 3 -&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1- Summary of Status o f the Conditions for FirstTranche Release&#13;
&#13;
FirstTranche Conditions                          Summaryof Present Status andProgress&#13;
Maintenance        o f    a      satisfactory Achieved&#13;
macroeconomic framework&#13;
A viable and binding agreement between Achieved&#13;
the Government and 15 out of 18 operators&#13;
to record arrears in the electricity sector,&#13;
schedule payment of interest and provide&#13;
one year moratorium on debt repayment&#13;
Government has remain current on its&#13;
electricity   bills and has       transferred Achieved&#13;
budgetary funds via CDEEE to the&#13;
distribution companies, in accordance with&#13;
the Power Sector RecoveryPlan&#13;
Plans for the financial recovery o f the&#13;
sector    approved    and   implementation&#13;
started, including:&#13;
&#13;
a) Plans o f the Distribution companies to Achieved&#13;
reduce losses and improve collection while&#13;
controlling costs; and&#13;
b) Cash Recovery Index o f the distribution&#13;
companies combined (cumulative over six&#13;
months) increased from 45 percent in&#13;
Aurmst 2004 to 50 Dercent&#13;
Revision and implementation o f a formula Not achieved, but budgetary compensatory&#13;
for the automatic adjustment o f retail tariffs measures allocated to ensure the provision&#13;
for variations in exchange rate, fuel prices o f corresponding additional revenues to the&#13;
and inflation                                     distributioncomDanies&#13;
Formulation o f a contingency plan in case Achieved&#13;
performance       o f   the    nationalized&#13;
distribution companies does not improve&#13;
simificantlv&#13;
Creation o f a Crisis Committee to oversee Achieved&#13;
the   implementation    o f  the    financial&#13;
recovery plan, and appointment o f its&#13;
coordinator&#13;
Launch o f a communication campaign to Achieved&#13;
build sumort for the recoveryplan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              - 4 -&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13.     Progress has been slow in the first year of the program implementation due to&#13;
political factors, including the minority representation o f the Government in the lower&#13;
house of the Congress and the presence o f only one representative out o f thirty-one inthe&#13;
Senate. However, a number o f steps were taken to change the management of the state-&#13;
owned utilities and prepare for an aggressive loss reduction campaign. Private sector&#13;
management with international experience was contracted by the Government to lead&#13;
EdeSur and EdeNorte, two o f the three distribution companies. The third distribution&#13;
company, EdeEste whose majority shareholding is private, also changed its top&#13;
management to ensure more focused attention on theft reduction, particularly by large&#13;
consumers. Outsourcing to private contractors in the two utilities to detect theft, and&#13;
increase billing and collectionwas undertaken. Support from the Government interms o f&#13;
more personnel and resources to the Office o f Consumer Protection (PROTECOM) who&#13;
accompany the utilities to certify connection irregularities was also provided. Inaddition,&#13;
power supply was stabilized at about 80-85 percent o f demand. However, in 2005,&#13;
overall subsidy requirements topped US$600M (2.1% o f GDP), due to the increase inthe&#13;
international oil prices (fuel oil price escalated from US$21.8/bbl in January 2005 to&#13;
US$42.6/bbl in December 2005), and the lower than expected performance (though still&#13;
positive) of the distribution companies interms of loss reductionandbill collection.&#13;
&#13;
14.     Since May 2006, results have started to become more visible. The Cash Recovery&#13;
Index - which measures the percentage o f power purchases paid for by consumers - has&#13;
improved from 51.7% in May 2006 to 53.8% in September 2006.                   Recently the&#13;
Government has also re-launched a communication campaign against theft of electricity.&#13;
During a stakeholders meeting held last September, it was concluded that some&#13;
legislative changes to facilitate the anti theft campaign by the distribution companies&#13;
were needed. Under the leadership o f the Government through the ComisidnNacional de&#13;
Energia, the distribution companies have formulated the proposed amendments to the&#13;
Law to criminalize theft and establish special courts to prosecute those stealing&#13;
electricity. The proposed amendments will be presented shortly to the Congress.&#13;
&#13;
15.     After adjusting electricity tariffs to reflect the variations in international&#13;
petroleum prices, in February 2006 the Government decided to freeze them. This was&#13;
because electricity tariffs in the Dominican Republic are extremely high (at around&#13;
US$0.22/kWh), and a further increase would have resulted in larger non-payment o f&#13;
electricity bills and therefore counteracted the ongoing efforts made by the distribution&#13;
companies to increase collection.&#13;
&#13;
16.     Inthe next few months, the Government will continue to facilitate the anti theft&#13;
campaign by the distribution companies and require tangible results. Monitoring will be&#13;
assured by the Comisidn Nacional de Enevgia (the agency in charge o f energy policy)&#13;
together with the Supevintendencia de Electricidad (the regulatory body), and the&#13;
CDEEE. Other steps that the Government plansto implement inthe short term include:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    0   defining and implementinga nationalantitheft strategy;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           - 5 -&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       removing remaining legal and regulatory barriers to facilitate the loss reduction&#13;
       programby the distribution companies;&#13;
       expanding the communication strategy focused on anti theft;&#13;
       providingadequate financial resources for investment indistribution;&#13;
       implementingprograms to improve collectionand service;&#13;
       designing and implementing a new tariff structure and measurement of quality o f&#13;
        service; and&#13;
       defining a package to protect and facilitate access by the poor, including tariffs,&#13;
        and service.&#13;
&#13;
17.    Through these measures, a reduction inthe losses and an improvement inthe bill&#13;
collection by the distribution companies are expected to be accelerated, thereby&#13;
improving the financial performance o f the sector and the reliability o f power supply.&#13;
The resulting improvement in the quality o f power supply would in turn create more&#13;
favorable conditions for the Government to adjust tariffs in line with variations in fuel&#13;
prices.&#13;
&#13;
18.     Inlight of the above and despite the original delays in effectiveness, the overall&#13;
program, as well as the conditions spelled out for second and third tranches, i s still&#13;
achievable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          - 6 -&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="7269336">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/12/7269336/dominican-republic-programmatic-power-sector-reform-loan-release-first-tranche-waiver-one-condition
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2006/12/7269336/dominican-republic-programmatic-power-sector-reform-loan-release-first-tranche-waiver-one-condition</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2006/12/7269336/dominican-republic-programmatic-power-sector-reform-loan-release-first-tranche-waiver-one-condition</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2007-01-31T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/12/14/000090341_20061214102157/Rendered/INDEX/38195.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2006/12/14/000090341_20061214102157/Rendered/PDF/38195.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>7292</loan_no>
        <datestored>2006-12-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2006-12-13T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Dominican Republic - Programmatic Power
            Sector Reform Loan - release of the first tranche : waiver
            of one condition
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The programmatic power sector reform
            loan for Dominican Republic is designed to be disbursed in
            three tranches. The first tranche will be disbursed at
            effectiveness, while the second and third floating tranches
            will be released when the corresponding conditions are met.
            Although the Government initially met the conditions prior
            to presentation of PPSRL to our Board in May 2005, it took
            over six months for the Loan Agreement to be presented to
            Congress and ratified. During this period and in the
            following months, the Government began to accumulate arrears
            with the private generation companies in violation of one of
            the prior conditions, and decided not to apply the formula
            for the automatic adjustment of retail tariffs for
            variations in exchange rate, fuel price and inflation,
            thereby violating another prior condition. The Government
            recently cleared its arrears with the generation companies,
            and is currently providing compensatory measures in lieu of
            the tariff adjustment to ensure that the financial
            sustainability of the distribution and generation companies
            will not be affected. In the last few months, the fiscal
            situation deteriorated, putting at risk the macroeconomic
            framework going forward; however a package of revenue and
            expenditure measures for 2006 and 2007 was recently agreed
            with the IMF under its Stand-By Arrangement (SBA), which
            should put the country back into a sustainable debt path and
            satisfactory macroeconomic framework.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Dominican Republic - Programmatic Power
            Sector Reform Loan - release of the first tranche : waiver
            of one condition
        </docna>
        <display_title>Dominican Republic - Programmatic
            Power Sector Reform Loan - release of the first tranche :
            waiver of one condition</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2006/12/7269336/dominican-republic-programmatic-power-sector-reform-loan-release-first-tranche-waiver-one-condition</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>DO-Dominican Republic Power Sector Program -
            Second Generation Ref -- P082712</projn>
        <docty>Tranche Release Document</docty>
        <subtopic>Energy and Poverty Alleviation,Energy Production and Transportation,Economic Adjustment and Lending,Infrastructure Economics,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Energy</teratopic>
        <count>Dominican Republic</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Caribbean!$!80452</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20061214102157</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <subsc>Power</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Energy</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Energy and mining</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            balance, bill collection, Borrower, Central
            American, Consumer Protection, contractors, debt repayment,
            distribution companies, Economic Performance, electricity,
            electricity bills, electricity sector, electricity services,
            electricity supply, electricity tariffs, expenditure,
            financial resources, financial viability, fiscal deficit,
            foreign exchange, fuel, fuel prices, generation, generation
            companies, Government plans, high energy, inflation,
            international reserves, Loan, Loan Agreement, low-income
            households, oil, Outsourcing, petroleum, petroleum prices,
            Power, power purchases, Power Sector, Power Sector Reform,
            retail, retail tariffs, surplus, tariff adjustment, tariff
            structure, Tranche, utilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Energy (LCSEG)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Programmatic Structural Adjustment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Caribbean</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>38195</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Free Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Poverty Alleviation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Balance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contingency Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outsourcing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumer Protection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Dominican Republic</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>