<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>""; ;421482&#13;
014~~~~~&#13;
z &#13;
-                                                                                           1&#13;
pal                                 Multiservice Infrastructure&#13;
Lourdes Trujillo and      Privatizing  Port Services&#13;
Gustavo Nombela&#13;
Ports have become increasingly capital intensive. Economies of scale&#13;
Lourdes Trujillo is Professor&#13;
Lofrdens aruo DisProfetor of    have led to  larger, more specialized  ships. And competition  between&#13;
of Economics and Director of&#13;
the Department ofApplied  ports has started  to grow. As a result, governments are reorganizing the&#13;
Economics at the University&#13;
Eo                    Uway ports are run and permitting more private ownership and service&#13;
of Las Palmas de Gran&#13;
Cataria. GustavoNombela   delivery. Because ports provide multiple services, if governments are to&#13;
is Professor ofEconomics at  design  an efficient legal and  regulatory  framework for private participa-&#13;
the same university and&#13;
spent 1999 asavisitingfel-  tion it is important to study all these activities to evaluate the best&#13;
low at the World Bank     approach. Moreover, because these activities must take place in a small&#13;
Institute. Both authors have&#13;
published extensivelT oni  space, it is important to study  how  they are best coordinated.&#13;
transport restructuring and&#13;
regulation a. d have advised  More competition                              nections. Therefore, modern  ports must be&#13;
rentaion at .i            In recent decades therc have been profound         extremely competitive to be able to offer optimal&#13;
ogovernmenits in Latin&#13;
America on port refonrms  changes in maritime transport. Ports, once labor-    combinations of time and price for those firms&#13;
intensive, have become more capital-intensive,    demanding their services.&#13;
making much port labor redundant. The develop-       Somewhat less widely understood is the potential&#13;
ment of containerized transport has dramatically    for intraport competition. Seaports offer many serv-&#13;
reduced the cost of cargo handling, but it has also    ices to ships. The potential for competition in pro-&#13;
X.                                  required much investment in equipment (gantry    viding these services depends largely on the assets&#13;
O                                   cranes, specialized terminals, improved pavement,   required to provide them, the space available in the&#13;
II:                                 and so on). The economies of scale obtained by    port, and the volume of traffic. A defining physical&#13;
the transport of large quantities of containers and  characteristic of ports is that space is limited. Partly&#13;
z                                   bulk cargoes have led to the building of larger and    this is because many of the activities must take place&#13;
more specialized ships that require substantial    around the ship. But it is also because port infra-&#13;
a                                   port investments in new infrastructure and equip-    structure is expensive to build, and much of it can&#13;
ment. Moreover, the development of integrated     only be expanded in discrete units.&#13;
O                                   and intermodal transport chains has reduced&#13;
transport costs so much that it is often preferable  Multiservice operations&#13;
ui       rE31                       for a shipper to use a distant port instead of a closer    For the purposes of analysis, it is usefiul to divide&#13;
one, if the distant port has better facilities and con-    port  activities  into  infrastructure,  ser-vices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MULTISERVICE  INFRASTRUCTURE  PRIVATIZING PORT SERVICES&#13;
Maritime access infrastructure&#13;
Channels, approximation zones&#13;
*Sea deFense (breakwaters, locks)&#13;
Signaling  (lights, buoys)&#13;
Port              Port infrastructure                  Port superstructure&#13;
area               Berths, docks, basins                Cranes, pipes&#13;
* Storage areas                                                                                    Terminals, sheds&#13;
2  Internal connections (roads, other)&#13;
Berthing         Ancillar, services       Cargo haing ng        Consignees&#13;
services         * Suppliers               Stevedoring            Administrative paperwork&#13;
* Pilotage       * Repairs                 Terminals             for ships and cargo&#13;
* Towing           C Cleaning and refuse   Storage               Permits (sanitary,&#13;
* Tying           collection               Freezing               customs and so forth)&#13;
*Safety                                         Service hiring&#13;
Land access infrastructure&#13;
* Roads, railways&#13;
* Inland navigation channels&#13;
Source: Estache and de Rus 2000.&#13;
provided using the infrastructure, and coordina-    for a ship to enter and exit a port safely. In some&#13;
tion between the activities at the port.                ports pilots are public employees, and in others&#13;
they are private agents licensed by the port author-&#13;
Many kinds of infrastructure                            ity. Towage is the operation of maneuvering a ship&#13;
A port obviously needs good access by sea (chan-    using tugs. Like pilotage, it can be provided by pri-&#13;
nels, locks, aids to navigation, and so on) and by    vate firms or operators hired by the port authority.&#13;
land (roads, railways, and canals). The port also          Cargo handling includes all activities related to&#13;
has internal infrastructure, such as docks and stor-    the movement of cargo to and from ships and across&#13;
age yards, and internal superstructure. The super-    port facilities. The historic distinction between&#13;
structure can be classified into fixed assets built on  stevedoring-moving goods within a ship-and&#13;
the infrastructure, such as sheds, fuel tanks, and      loading-moving  goods onto  a ship from  the&#13;
office buildings, and fixed and mobile equipment    quay-has been eroded by modern cargo handling&#13;
such as cranes and van carriers.                        techniques like containerization. Because the tech-&#13;
In general, the port authority is responsible for    nique used depends on the type of cargo, it is effi-&#13;
the port, and the state or municipal government is    cient to use specialized equipment. This has led to&#13;
responsible for the land access infrastructure.    the formation of terminals that specialize in partic-&#13;
They divide responsibility for the maritime access    ular cargoes. Because cargo  handling  charges&#13;
infrastructure, with the port authority responsible     account for between 70 percent and 90 percent of&#13;
for breakwaters, lights, and buoys and the govern-    the cost of moving goods through a port, regulators&#13;
ment responsible for the rest.                          concerned with cost-efficiency of the port must pay&#13;
cargo handling particular attention.&#13;
Many kinds of services                                     A further range of services is provided by agents&#13;
Many services are provided by different operators.    who handle the docuimentation for port tasers-&#13;
First, there is a group  of services related  to    the health clearances, import and export require-&#13;
berthing, which include pilotage, towing and tying.    ments, and  customs duties. These agents are&#13;
They can be provided by the port authority or pri-    known as consignees, and are hired by shipping&#13;
vate firms. Pilotage covers the operations required     companies to arrange in advance the administra-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
tion and all matters related to the use of port facil-    * Build (or Rehabilitate), Operate, and Transfer.&#13;
ities by a ship. A modern port must minimize red       Private operators build or rehabilitate facilities,&#13;
tape for port users. Delays cost money.                which are eventually transferred to public own-&#13;
Finally, there are ancillary services, including    ership. Also known as a concession.&#13;
supplies to ships such as fuel and water, cleaning,    * Joint ventures. Operators create a new inde-&#13;
and refuse collection.                                 pendent company. This type of agreement&#13;
arises when two or more parties with common&#13;
Coordination                                           interestsjoin forces (for example, one firm sup-&#13;
With many activities being performed in a limited      plies technology and know-how, while another&#13;
space, there is a need for a coordinator responsible   supplies market knowledge).&#13;
for the proper use of common facilities, for safety,    *  Leasing. The port authority leases port assets to&#13;
and for the design of the port. In most ports, this is  private operators for a given period. In contrast&#13;
the role of the port authority. It is generally a pub-  with a concession, the private operators do not&#13;
lic institution, with representation of local interests,  usually make investments, and therefore they&#13;
but in some ports the authority is purely private.     only assume commercial risks.&#13;
The common forms of organization are known    *  Licensing. Private operators provide services&#13;
as landlord, tool, and services ports.                 requiring basic equipment, which they own.&#13;
*  Landlord port. The port authority owns and          The port authority owns the port infrastructure&#13;
manages the port infrastructure. Private firms      and superstructure and charges the private&#13;
provide all other services and own the port         operators for their use. Stevedoring companies,&#13;
superstructure.                                     pilots, tug operators or consignees can work&#13;
*  7ool pot. The port authority owns both infra-       under this type of agreement.&#13;
structure and superstructure. Private firms pro-    * Management contract. The port authority&#13;
vide services by renting port assets, through       remains the owner of the port, but the port is&#13;
concessions or licenses.                            run by a private firm which can provide a more&#13;
&#149;  Seroices port. The port authority is responsible    commercial approach  to  operations. Both&#13;
for the port as a whole, owning the infrastruc-     investment and commercial risks are faced by&#13;
ture and superstructure and hiring employees        the public sector, since managers do not invest&#13;
to provide services.                                their own capital in the port.&#13;
In landlord and tool ports, the port authority is&#13;
usually public and the port operators are private    Shared or exclusive use&#13;
firms. Services ports are more likely to be privately    A basic consideration in choosing the best form of&#13;
owned, with one private firm operating the port as    privatization is whether the service to be privatized&#13;
a single unit. The role of port authorities should    requires the exclusive use of the port's fixed assets.&#13;
be confined to the provision of infrastructure and     Activities in which the fixed assets can be shared&#13;
the coordination of port services. However, in    include services such as pilotage, towing, consignee&#13;
many countries where there is no regulatory insti-   services and ancillary services to ships and crew.&#13;
tution for seaports, port authorities perform many    Under a system of licenses, several operators can be&#13;
other tasks, such as investment planning and    authorized to provide these services. The prices&#13;
financing, or regulation of the tariffs that private   they charge and the quality of their services can be&#13;
operators charge to port users.                     regulated. In cases where competition is possible,&#13;
for example between consignees or pilots, strict reg-&#13;
Privatization options                               ulation of prices would not be necessary unless col-&#13;
The options for privatizing port services depend    lusive practices were detected. In ports where space&#13;
on the size of the port and the services involved,   limits the number of operators, prices and condi-&#13;
and include:                                        tions of service need to be regulated to prevent mar-&#13;
*  Full privatization. All assets and liabilities are    ket domination by a few firms who may try to exploit&#13;
transferred to the private sector.               their position to extract rents from port users.&#13;
*  Build, Operate, and Own. Parts of the port are      Because space is so scarce in ports, exclusivity in&#13;
sold to private operators to be developed.       the use of some fixed assets may be necessary. Such&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MULTISERVICE  INFRASTRUCTURE  PRIVATIZING PORT SERVICES&#13;
berths and can manage them better. The terminals&#13;
compete with each other. When a company serves&#13;
Type of competition  Level of traffic (TEUs)   all ships using a given berth, the port authority can&#13;
Intra-terminal     Above 30,000 per year       make it responsible for collecting port tariffs-&#13;
Inter-terminal     Above 100,000 per year      charges for the use of the port-as well as the oper-       ew     oin t&#13;
Inter-port         Above 300,000 per year      ator's own charges. At this volume of traffic, it is&#13;
Note: TEU is a Twenty Foot Equivalent Unit. This is a unit of measurement equivalent  also possible to provide incentives for private oper-&#13;
to one 20-foot shipping container.&#13;
tourne: Kent and Hochotein (998).                ators  to  finance  projects  for  infrastructure      i                                 l l&#13;
enhancement or construction.&#13;
Finally, in a region where container traffic is    ecuaedseiaino&#13;
Y'  g                              ~~~~~~~~~~~~ublic policy innovations for    &#13;
assets and associated services include terminals for    above 300,000 TEUs a year, the market size allows    private-sector led and   for&#13;
cargo handling, storage areas, repairing docks and    for the existence of several ports that can compete    market-based solutions for&#13;
fuel suppliers. It is more complicated to introduce    for traffic. Such inter-port competition  again       development. The views&#13;
private participation in these services, since opera-    reduces the need for control over private opera-    published are those of the&#13;
tors need to use assets that are considered to be    tors' prices. However, even in this optimal case,    authors and should not be&#13;
optimally owned by the port authority. Therefore,    attention is still needed for the proper drafting of    attributed to the World&#13;
concession contracts need to be written carefully in    concession contracts, since private operators must    Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
order to reconcile private operators' interests with    be compelled to fulfill their obligations not only    organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
port authorities' objectives. At the same time, con-    on service conditions and charges, but also on       the conclusions represent&#13;
tracts must include incentives for private operators    equipment maintenance, safety, quality of serv-    official policy of the World&#13;
to maintain or enhance assets as required.            ices, and all other matters which are costly for the   Bank or of its Executive&#13;
The number of operators for these services is by    concessionaire, and could be underprovided.           Directors or the countries&#13;
definition extremely limited, although it depends                                                            they represent.&#13;
on port size. Similarly, the need for regulation of&#13;
charges and quality depends on the type of port                                                              To order additional copies&#13;
and how many alternative ports are nearby. In a    References                                                contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
port in a highly competitive environment, the reg-       Drewry Shipping Consultants. 1998. World Container    managing editor,&#13;
ulator need not be too concerned about over-    Terninals: Global Growth and Private Profit. London.          Room 19-216,&#13;
charging, because operators that overcharge risk          Estache, Antonio, and Gines de Rus, eds. 2000.    The World Bank,&#13;
losing customers.                                     Privatization and Regulation of Transport Infrastructure:    1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
Guidelines for Policymakers and Regulators. World Bank    Washington, DC. 20433.&#13;
Rule of thumb for competition                         Insfitute, Washington, D.C.                            Telephone:&#13;
The privatization strategy should maximize the            Kent and Hochstein. 1998. "Port Reform  and         Te e pho n&#13;
potential for competition. There is no universal rule    Privatization in Conditions of Limited Competition: The  Fax:&#13;
for the degree of competition and regulation desir-    Experience of Colombia, Costa Rica and Nicaragua."    00 1 202 522 3181&#13;
able in a port with a particular volume of traffic, but   Journal of Maritime Policy Management 25 (4): 313-33.  Email:&#13;
for container ports there is acceptance of some                                                               ssmith7@woridbank.org&#13;
thresholds (box 1). A port handling fewer than         This Note is based on a chapter in Estache and de Rus 2000.&#13;
30,000 TEUs a year is too small to have several ter-&#13;
minals and operators. The best solution is to have a    Lourdes Trujillo (lourdes@empresariales.ulpgc.es) and Gustavo  Printed on recycled paper&#13;
single operator and to regulate its charges.          Nombela (gnombela@empresariales.ulpgc.es), Universidad de&#13;
In a port handling between 30,000 and 100,000    Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Spain.&#13;
TEUs a year, it is feasible to have several operators,&#13;
possibly sharing a single terminal. There would be&#13;
intra-terminal competition, with stevedoring com-&#13;
panies competing  to  provide  cargo  handling&#13;
services.&#13;
A port handling more than 100,000 TEUs a year&#13;
is big enough to have a number of terminals oper-&#13;
ated by several companies that can use separate&#13;
This  Note  is  available  online:&#13;
www.worldbank.orglhtmil/fpd/notes/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="729358">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/10/729358/multiservice-infrastructure-privatizing-port-services
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/10/729358/multiservice-infrastructure-privatizing-port-services</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2000/10/729358/multiservice-infrastructure-privatizing-port-services</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/12/22/000094946_00121301484119/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/12/22/000094946_00121301484119/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2000-12-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2000-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Multiservice infrastructure - privatizing
            port services
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Ports have become increasingly capital
            intensive. Economies of scale have led to larger, more
            specialized ships, and, competition between ports has
            started to grow. As a result, governments are reorganizing
            the way ports are run, and permitting more private
            ownership, and service delivery. Because ports provide
            multiple services, if governments are to design an efficient
            legal, and regulatory framework for private participation,
            it is important to study all these activities to evaluate
            the best approach. Moreover, because these activities must
            take place in a small space, it is important to study how
            they are best coordinated. The note outlines privatization
            options, such as: full privatization, i.e., all assets and
            liabilities are transferred to the private sector; build,
            operate and own, i.e., parts of the port are sold to be
            developed; build or rehabilitate, on a concession basis;
            joint ventures; leasing, i.e., no investments, only
            commercial risks; licensing, (provision of equipment); and,
            management contract, i.e., both investment and commercial
            risks are faced by the public sector.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Multiservice infrastructure - privatizing
            port services
        </docna>
        <display_title>Multiservice infrastructure -
            privatizing port services</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2000/10/729358/multiservice-infrastructure-privatizing-port-services</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Ports &amp; Waterways,Transport Security,Airports and Air Services,Transport and Trade Logistics,Public Sector Economics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Public Sector Development,Transport</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Trujillo, Lourdes</author>
            <author>Nombela, Gustavo</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_00121301484119</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Private Infrastructure</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 222,Private infrastructure notes</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Public Sector Development,Transport</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Private Sector Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Infrastructure privatization; Ports; Capital
            investments; Economies of scale; Port facilities; Port
            management; Competitiveness; Private ownership; Services
            delivery; Legal &amp; regulatory framework; Private sector
            participation; Build, own, operate; Build, operate,
            transfer; Joint ventures; Leasing arrangements; License fee;
            Management contracts
            aids to
            navigation,berth,Berthing,Berths,breakwaters,bulk
            cargoes,buoys,canals,cargo,cargo
            handling,carriers,Channels,concessionaire,construction,container
            traffic,containerization,containers,customs,customs
            duties,docks,export,fuel,fuel tanks,Inland
            navigation,intermodal transport,Landlord
            port,licenses,loading,Maritime Policy,Maritime Policy
            Management,maritime transport,municipal
            government,navigation channels,pilots,port,port
            activities,port assets,port authorities,port authority,port
            competition,port facilities,port investments,port
            operators,Port Reform,port services,Port superstructure,port
            users,Ports,private sector,provision of
            infrastructure,public sector,range,regulatory
            framework,roads,Safety,Seaports,ship,shipping,ships,Stevedoring,terminal,terminals,TEU,Towing,Transport
            Infrastructure,tugs,Twenty Foot Equivalent Unit
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Participation in Infrstr (INFPI)</owner>
        <repnb>21482</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Port Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Terminals</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Logistics and Trade Facilitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Facilitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Logistics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Logistics Providers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Facilitation and Logistics</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>