<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>*  2 1467 &#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 211                                                                                    June mIs "&#13;
Designing Direct Subsidies for the&#13;
Poor-A Water and Sanitation Case Study&#13;
Vivien Foster,    Direct subsidies are an increasingly popular means of making infrastructure services more&#13;
Andres Gomez-      affordable to the poor. Under the direct subsidy approach, governments pay part of the water bill&#13;
Lobo, and&#13;
Jon athan          of poor households that meet certain eligibility criteria. This approach was first used in water&#13;
Halpern           sector reforms in Chile in the early 1990s and is an alternative to the traditional method in which&#13;
governments pay subsidies directly to utilities, often allowing the price of water to fall below&#13;
economic costs indiscriminately. This Note illustrates how simulation techniques can be used to&#13;
inform the design of direct subsidy schemes, ensuring that they are both cost-effective and&#13;
accurate in reaching the target population.&#13;
Universal access to adequate water and sanitation   mize distortions in the behavior of water utilities&#13;
services has long been recognized as essential to   and their custorners. The main drawbacks of&#13;
public health and individual welfare. In most   direct subsidies are higher administrative costs&#13;
countries government policy has traditionally   and the difficulty of designing suitable eligibility&#13;
been to keep water companies in public owner-   criteria.&#13;
ship, and to keep tariffs artificially low through a&#13;
range of more or less explicit subsidy measures.   Despite the growing interest in direct subsidies,&#13;
The results have often been unsatisfactory. Service   their administrative cost and accuracy of targeting&#13;
quality and coverage remain inadequate in many   have, as yel, been little studied. This Note attemnpts&#13;
countries, and subsidies directed at public water   to fill the gap by presenting the results of a simu-&#13;
companies have often benefited the middle  lation performed in Panama in 1998. The simula-&#13;
classes rather than the poor, who remain uncon-   tion is based on a willingness-to-pay survey and&#13;
nected to the public network. This has led to a   complementary informnation from the 1997 Living&#13;
search for alternative subsidies that would guar-   Standards Measurement Study (LSMS) survey and&#13;
antee access to basic services for the poorest.  the customer database for Panama's national&#13;
water utility IDAAN (Instituto de Acueductos y&#13;
In the direct subsidy system introduced during   Alcantarillados Nacional). The work was done in&#13;
the Chilean reforms in the early 1990s, prices are   the context of efforts to reform IDAAN, which still&#13;
allowed to signal their true economic scarcity   operates as a traditional utility. It considers the rel-&#13;
costs while subsidies are paid to consumers who   ative merits of a water consumption subsidy ver-&#13;
cannot afford their bills rather than to water util-  sus a sewerage connection subsidy.&#13;
ities. Government funds are used to cover part&#13;
of the cost of subsistence consumption for   Assessing need for a subsidy&#13;
households that meet certain poverty-related cri-&#13;
teria. The main advantages of direct subsidies are   As a general rule, the case for a water subsidy is&#13;
that they are transparent and explicit, and mini-  something that needs to be assessed rather than&#13;
The World Bank Group * Private Sector and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Designing Direct Subsidies for the Poor-A Water and Sanitation Case Study&#13;
TABLE 1   ZONAL AND INDIVIDUAL CRITERIA IN PANAMA, 1997&#13;
(percent)&#13;
,__                sutners would be willing to pay up to US$0.46.&#13;
The imnplication is that the price of potable water&#13;
would have to rise sul)stantially before it became&#13;
Errors oa exclusion       94                  6                unaffordable  to  low-income  households  in&#13;
Errors of inclusion       31                 93                urban Panama. For sewcrage conncctions the&#13;
current cost is US$1,000 (including cost of&#13;
Source: Encuesta Nacional de Niveles de Vida, Panama, 1997.    huse      nt    inobt  willing    t p i&#13;
household plumbDing) but willingness to pav is&#13;
only LS$270. Thus sewerage connections are&#13;
already well beyond the means of low-income&#13;
assumed. It is not axiomatic that water services    households. Subsidies might therefore be justi-&#13;
are unaffordable to low-income households, nor   fiecl to the extent that the wider social benefits&#13;
that subsidizing water consumption is the best   of expanding the sewerage network- were at&#13;
way of promoting access to sanitation or improv-   least as high as the associated subsidy.&#13;
ing public health among the poorest.&#13;
Designing eligibility criteria&#13;
An important starting point is to review existing&#13;
subsidy arrangements and consider how effec-   The intended beneficiaries of subsidy schemes&#13;
tively they reach the poor. A review of basic data   are invariably those living below the poverty&#13;
in Panama revealed a number of important   line, usually expressed as an annual threslhold&#13;
points. The first was that poverty in Panama is   for per capita income or expenditture. In practice&#13;
primarily rural, but IDAAN  operates almost   it is very difficult to measure income levels&#13;
exclusively  in towns. Only  16 percent of   directly and, therefore, to determine whether a&#13;
IDA-AN's customers live below the poverty line.   particular household should benefit from  the&#13;
Nevertheless, at least two-thirds of IDAANs CUS    subsidy. To get around this problem, it is neces-&#13;
tomers are subsidized. With the exception of a    sary to develop eligibility criteria that show a&#13;
pensioner discount. the determination of eligi-   high degree of correlation with the uniderlying&#13;
hility for these subsidies has been largely at the    poverty variable of interest, can be measured&#13;
discretion of IDAAN, and has often been based    objectively and observed easily. and are difficult&#13;
on payment history. The sheer number of ben-   to falsify or misrepresent.&#13;
eficiaries relative to the number of poor house&#13;
holds served by IDAAN indicates that the vast   Eligibility criteria can either he zonal (based on&#13;
majority of subsidy beneficiaries are not poor, by   the characteristics of the area where the house-&#13;
the strict standard provided above.              hold lives) or individual (based on the charac-&#13;
teristics of the household itself). The key issue is&#13;
To find out how  many people are excluded from    the extent to xw hich the criteria succeed in iden-&#13;
water and sewerage services because they gen-   tifying the target group. There are two forms of&#13;
uinelv cannot afford them, a contingent valua-   targeting errors. Perhaps the most serious are&#13;
tion survey was conducted. It sought to establish    errors of exclusion, when members of the target&#13;
the maximum  amount that households were    group are not captured by the eligibility criteria&#13;
willing to pay to consume a typical volume of   and hence fail to receive tlie subsidy. A subsidy&#13;
piped water and to obtain a connection to the    scheme with a high exclusion error clearly fails&#13;
sewerage network. Willingness to pay is com-   on its own terms. Errors of inclusion occur wlhen&#13;
pared with current prices to provide an indica-   people outside the target group fortuitously&#13;
tion of affordability. The premise is that a    comply with the eligibility criteria and conse&#13;
subsidy is only justified when willingness to pay    quently receive thie subsidy. Such leakage of&#13;
falls short of true economic cost. The results of   funds to unintended beneficiaries redtuces the&#13;
the survey show that while the current cost for   efficiency of die subsidy. to particular, it inflates&#13;
water is t-S 0.21 per cubic meter; poorer con-   the cost of the subsidy to taxpayers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 2    HOUSEHOLDS WITH PROPOSED INDIVIDUAL CRITERIA OF ELIGIBILITY FOR SUBSIDIES IN PANAMA, 1997&#13;
Extreme poverty         Poverty             Non-poor              Total&#13;
Thou-      Per-     Thou-               Thou-      Per-      Thou-      Per-&#13;
Criterion                                sands      cent      sands               sands      cent     sands      cent&#13;
Poor-quality floor materials              10.6      88.6       24.3      78.3      187.6     56.0      222.6     58.8&#13;
Lack of telephone connection               9.6      79.8       21.7      69.8      113.2     33.8      144.4     38.2&#13;
Primary educated head of household         7.8      65.3       15.2      49.1       85.2     25.4      108.3     28.6&#13;
Toilet facilities located outside house    7.2      60.4       18.3      58.9       82.3     24.5      107.8     28.5&#13;
Lack of sanitation beyond most basic       7.1      58.9       15.0      52.7      52.7      15.7       74.8     19.8&#13;
None of the above                          0.0       0.0        1.0       3.3      98.8      29.5       99.8     26.4&#13;
One or more of the above                  12.0     100.0       30.0      96.7      236.3     70.5      278.4     73.6&#13;
Two or more of the above                  11.3      93,9       25.9      83.5      140.7     42.0      178.8     47.3&#13;
Three or more of the above                 9.5      78.8       20.2      65.2       80.1     23.9      110.5     29.2&#13;
Four or more of the above                  6.8      56.1       13.2      42.6       47.6     14.2       68.3     18.1&#13;
All five of the above                      2.9      24.1        5.2      16.9       16.2      4.8       24.3      6.4&#13;
Source: Encuesta Nacional de Niveles de Vida, Panama, 1997.&#13;
As a criterion, zone of residence has the advan-    proxies and poverty levels, using data from  the&#13;
tage of being easy to observe and relatively hard         LSMS survey. The results for the most successful&#13;
to falsify. How well it correlates with the under-    proxy variables are repolted in table 2. As the&#13;
lying poverty measure of interest depends on the         table illustrates, it is difficult to find a single vari-&#13;
size of the zones used and the extent to which            able that performs well in minimizing both errors&#13;
poverty  is  geographically  concentrated.  In            of exclusion and errors of inclusion. For exam-&#13;
Panama, simulations were performed using zones            ple, poor quality floor materials have a very low&#13;
defined by the 1997 LSMS survey, comprising               error of exclusion, being found in 88.6 percent&#13;
approximately 15 households eaclh. The simula-    of extremely poor households, but a high error&#13;
tions explored the effect of giving a subsidy to all    of inclusion, also being found in 56.0 percent of&#13;
households in zones that met a particular set of    non-poor households. Clearly, the most power-&#13;
socioeconomic criteria; for example, zones where    ful eligibility criterion is one that combines infor-&#13;
more than 50 percent of households were living            mation on all of these characteristics. For the&#13;
in extreme poverty. Such zonal eligibility criteria       purposes of the Panama simulation, the eligibil-&#13;
were found to have Iiigh errors of exclusion, with    ity criterion was taken to be that the household&#13;
as much as 94 percent of the target population            should meet two or more of the criteria identi-&#13;
being  excluded  from   the  scheme  (table  1).    fied in table 2. The main benefit of moving from&#13;
However, errors of inclusion were comparatively           zonal to individual criteria is a dramatic reduc&#13;
low; only 31 percent of the subsidies would go to    tion in the errors of exclusion, which fall from 94&#13;
households above the extreme poverty line.                percent to 6 percent. This comes at the cost of&#13;
much higher errors of inclusion, with a very high&#13;
While reliable information about poverty levels    proportion of the subsidy funds (93 percent)&#13;
at the zonal level may be obtained based on cen-    leaking to households outside the target group.&#13;
sus or survey data, it is much harder to obtain a&#13;
reliable estimate of individual household income          Estimating administrative costs&#13;
and expenditure in orcler to assess eligibility for&#13;
individual subsidies. In Panama, an extensive             Using individual eligibility criteria requires an&#13;
search for proxy variables was conducted by               administrative  apparatus for the  screening  of&#13;
making  cross-tabulations  between  candidate             potential candidates. Typically, a standardized&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Designing Direct Subsidies for the Poor-A Water and Sanitation Case Study&#13;
household interview  is conducted by a social    households. The subsidy should be capped at&#13;
worker to collect the information needed to apply    some pre-determined subsistence consumption&#13;
the eligibility filters. This selection process can be    level.&#13;
expensive. In Panama, some initial estimates sug-&#13;
gested that the interviews could cost as much as    Third, the shorter the duration of the subsidy and&#13;
US$10 per household. To this must be added the    the higher its absolute level, the greater the prob-&#13;
fixed costs of running the subsidy program.             ability that the potential loss of the subsidy may&#13;
act as a disincentive for households to attempt to&#13;
Since administrative costs do not vary signifi-   improve  their economic  circumstances. This&#13;
cantly with respect to the size of the subsidy          effect, known as the "poverty trap," suggests that&#13;
given, schemes that pay out very little to each         eligibility for subsidies should not be reassessed&#13;
beneficiary tend to be highly inefficient from an    too frequently. In Chile, for example, eligibility&#13;
administrative point of view. A  simulation  of    is reassessed every three years.&#13;
administrative costs for different types and illus-&#13;
trative levels of subsidies in Panama shows that    Conclusion&#13;
for a water consumption subsidy of US$1.50 per&#13;
month, the administration costs absorb 40 per-    The case of Panama shows how useful simula-&#13;
cent of the total value of the subsidy, whereas for    tion techniques can be in informing choices&#13;
a  one-off  sewerage  connection  subsidy  of    between  alternative  policy  instruments. The&#13;
US$750 the costs fall to 7 percent. These simula-    main lessons from the experience in Panama are:&#13;
Viewpoint is an open  tions illustrate that low value subsidies are hard    * Before jumping to the conclusion that a sub-&#13;
forum intended to     to justify in administrative terms, unless the selec-     sidy is required. policymakers should examine&#13;
enicourage            tion procedures can be shared and jointly admin-          the poverty profile of water utility customers&#13;
dissemination of and&#13;
debate onideas,       istered across a number of stubsidy schemes.              and collect evidence on willingness to pay in&#13;
innovations, and best                                                           relation to the true costs of service provision.&#13;
practices for expanding  Preserving economic incentives                       * It is extremely difficult to find sound individ-&#13;
the private sector The&#13;
views published in this                                                         ual or zonal eligibility criteria. However, cal-&#13;
series are those of the  It is important, in determining how high a sub-        culating the errors of inclusion and exclusion&#13;
authors and shoald not  sidy to pay, to avoid the perverse incentives that      is a helpful way of assessing the options.&#13;
be attributed to the&#13;
World Bank or any of its    can be created by subsidies. First, a subsidy that    * Given significant fixed administrative costs in&#13;
affiliated organizations.  covers the full cost of the service will eliminate   subsidy programs, direct subsidies of relatively&#13;
Nor do any of the con-  incentives for the efficient use of water, and is       low value are unlikely to be cost-effective.&#13;
clusions represent                                                                              ulkl&#13;
official policy of the  likely to create a non-payment habit that may be&#13;
World Bank or of its  difficult to break at a later date. Therefore, full-    References&#13;
Executive Directors or  scale subsidies should  be  avoided. Pavment&#13;
the coLintries they                                                           Foster, vivien, Andres G6mez-Loho, and Jonathan 11a1pern.&#13;
represent.            should also be encouraged by making the sub-              Fortlcoming. Designing Direct SLhsidies for Water and Sanitation&#13;
sidv conditional on the household1 paying its             Services: lessons from Panama" Policy Research Working Paper.&#13;
Ta order additionalWolBak  asign,DC&#13;
copies please call    own share. In Chile, water subsidies are capped           \\orcLl Bank, Washington,  e C&#13;
202 458 1111 orcontact  at 85 perceint of the bill and are onily disbursed      lorthcoming  information and Nodeling Issues in )esigning&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,  upon proof that the household has paid its share.       'o ntec and Sanitation Subsidv Schemes." Policv Research Working&#13;
Room FtlK-208, The                                                              Piper. World Bank, Washington, D.C.&#13;
World Bank, 1818 H&#13;
Street, NW, Washington,    Second, a subsidy that applies to all levels of con-&#13;
D.C. 20433, or Internet  sumption may encourage excessive use of the          Vivien Foster (ffoster@worldbank.org) and&#13;
address ssmith7@&#13;
worldbank.org. The    service. In Argentina a subsidy of utility bills for   Jonathan Halpern (jhalperngzworldbank.org),&#13;
series is also available  pensioner households had to be discontinued         Latin America and the Caribbean Region, and&#13;
org/html/fpd/notes/).  because  consumption  levels rose  as family,    Andres Gomez-Lobo (agomezlo&amp;&#13;
@ Printed on recycled  friends, and neighbors took advantage of the    deconfacea.uchilecl). Department of&#13;
paper                 lower cost of using utility services in pensioner    Economics, University of Chile&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="729348">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/06/729348/designing-direct-subsidies-poor-water-sanitation-case-study
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/06/729348/designing-direct-subsidies-poor-water-sanitation-case-study</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2000/06/729348/designing-direct-subsidies-poor-water-sanitation-case-study</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/12/22/000094946_0012130148389/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/12/22/000094946_0012130148389/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2000-12-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2000-06-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Designing direct subsidies for the poor : a
            water and sanitation case study
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Direct subsidies are an increasingly
            popular means of making infrastructure services more
            affordable to the poor. Under the direct subsidy approach,
            governments pay part of the water bill of poor households
            that meet certain criteria. This approach was first used in
            water sector reforms in Chile in the early 1990s and is an
            alternative to the traditional method in which governments
            pay subsidies directly to utilities, often allowing the
            price of water to fall below economic costs
            indiscriminately. This Note illustrates how simulation
            techniques can be used to inform the design of direct
            subsidy schemes, ensuring that they are both cost-effective
            and accurate in reaching the target population.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Designing direct subsidies for the poor : a
            water and sanitation case study
        </docna>
        <display_title>Designing direct subsidies for
            the poor : a water and sanitation case study</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2000/06/729348/designing-direct-subsidies-poor-water-sanitation-case-study</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>Panama,Chile</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Foster, Vivien</author>
            <author>Gomez-Lobos, Andres</author>
            <author>Halpern, Jonathan</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Central America!$!80455</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_0012130148389</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Water Supply &amp; Sanitation</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 211</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Targeted subsidies; Payments systems; Water
            pricing; Needs assessment; Eligibility criteria; Water
            service connections; Sewerage; Survey data; Household
            income; Household expenditure surveys; Administrative costs;
            Interviews; Economic incentives; Simulations
            adequate water,administrative
            terms,alternative policy instruments,connection
            subsidy,consumers,consumption levels,cubic meter,economic
            circumstances,economic incentives,Economics,efficient use of
            water,Extreme poverty,fixed costs,households,income,income
            levels,low-income households,per capita income,perverse
            incentives,Policy Research,potable water,poverty line,price
            of water,Private Sector,public health,public water,service
            provision,sewerage network,sewerage services,simulation
            techniques,Toilet facilities,towns,utilities,utility
            services,water companies,water consumption,water
            services,water utilities,water utility,Willingness to pay
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Central America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>21467</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>