<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Vie2wp o int&#13;
i!rr;if No. 209                                                                               May 74 I;II&#13;
Does Reform of Energy Sector Networks&#13;
Improve Access for the Poor?&#13;
Stepbenz Powtell    Unless energy can be produced and delivered more cheaply, it will stay beyond the reach of many&#13;
andrkas          of the poor. For energy delivered through networks, the costs that matter are not only the unit&#13;
Starks&#13;
energy costs, but the costs of extending the network-into an urban slum, for example, or to a&#13;
rural town. Extending a network can be very expensive-a major barrier to access for poor&#13;
households and small or isolated communities. A central goal of the reform of electricity and gas&#13;
networks, now occurring in an increasing number of developed and developing countries, is to&#13;
provide incentives to reduce the costs of producing energy and getting it to consumers. New&#13;
technologies in electricity are drastically reducing costs. But transmission costs are still a major&#13;
hurdle to expanding networks in isolated or lightly populated areas. As a result it is the urban poor&#13;
who stand the greatest chance of benefiting from network reform. For the rural poor, alternative&#13;
solutions, including mini-grid and off-grid services, may be required.&#13;
Electricity reform is based on the premise that mar-  electricity cheaper for the poor who already&#13;
ket mechanisms supply electricity much more effi-  have access to it, and provide it to those who&#13;
ciently than central planning can.1 But how will  do not. It analyzes the fundamental costs of gen-&#13;
the poor, who have the least purchasing power,  erating electricity and distributing it through a&#13;
fare in a competitive electricity market? Will those   grid to rural and poor populations. It describes&#13;
without access continue to be denied it as elec-   how electricity reform and technological devel-&#13;
tricity supply changes from a public service to a   opments have reduced these costs in recent&#13;
profit-seeking business? And will the poor who   years and discusses institutional arrangements&#13;
have access suddenly find it unaffordable?  to ensure that lower costs are passed to cus-&#13;
tomers. It examines whether reform will&#13;
One response to these general concerns is that a   increase access to electricity for poor house-&#13;
well-functioning power sector is crucial to macro-   holds and comments on policies to further the&#13;
economic stability and growth. It is precisely  interests of the poor in the context of electricity&#13;
because poorly run, state-owned electric utilities   reform.&#13;
have been such an impediment to growth that so&#13;
many countries are trying to reform them. For   As context for this discussion, map 1 shows the&#13;
those who believe that the best way to make the   extent of power sector reform in developing&#13;
poor richer is to make everybody richer, that is  countries. Network reform is most advanced in&#13;
how electricity reform helps the poor.      Latin America, least advanced in Africa, and is&#13;
quite mixed in Eastern Europe and South and&#13;
However, this Note concentrates on the micro-   East Asia (also see Izaguirre 2000 for private par-&#13;
economic effects: whether reform will make   ticipation in energy by country).&#13;
The World Bank Group * Private Sector and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2                              Does Reform of Energy Sector Networks Improve Access for the Poor?&#13;
MAP 1    SCORECARD FOR POWER SECTOR REFORM IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES, 1998&#13;
IBRD 3H&#13;
0MAY 2000&#13;
9 1&#13;
This map was pndcad by she Map Osign uail of The Wasd lank.&#13;
Th. ba... sdlem,  dnimatin.asn ay'' , a iforimi shw ml this map&#13;
d.amso imply, as th. pars t ofThe Wodd hats Greep, nay Judgmermalno lIse legal ratms&#13;
af asp tersitrsy, or any enlDarsoast or acceptlasof a sabh boundaries&#13;
The World Bank surveyed power reform ie 115 countries to see which of the followiag six reform slops had been toke    n:NNumh er of reform steps&#13;
&#149;Corporatization.                                                                                                                     0 0&#13;
a Laws permitting divestiture and onhuodling.                                                                                           C'1&#13;
Regalations.                                                                                                                          @ 2&#13;
* Vertical and horizontal anbundling.                                                                                                     3&#13;
a Laws permittieg concessions or greenfield investment.&#13;
* Privatization of existing assets.                                                                                                    CD4&#13;
Note that:&#13;
The score does oot indicate the quality of reform or the sequence of steps taken.                                                        Countries not icl SUFvey&#13;
a Fur simplicity, seccess in one region cuaints as saccess for the country.&#13;
a Sectors under private ownership for lIt years are not considered part of the current reform movement and are omitted from the survey.&#13;
Source: Bacon 1999.&#13;
Generating and selling electricity:                                          Box 1 summarizes the cost characteristics of the&#13;
what it costs                                                                fouir fuinctions. it has been estimnated that in&#13;
England and WX,ales generation accouints for&#13;
The   provision   of  electricity   through   a   grid                        about 65  percent of the  total cost of electricity,&#13;
involves four functions:                                                     tratisimission  10 percent, distribution  20 percent,&#13;
* Generation: converting primaryT energy into    ancti suipply  5 percent (New~berv and Green&#13;
electricitv.                                                               1996). These  proportions vary  in  different sys-&#13;
*  Transmission: the  high-voltage, long-distance                            tentis. In particuilar, the start-up  costs of a grid are&#13;
transport of electricity,                                                 high and fixed, which means that grids have big&#13;
* Distributtion:, the low-voltage transport of elec-    economies of scale, in terms of both the num-&#13;
tricity from the high-voltage system to the user.    her of houiseholds connected and the amount of&#13;
*  Suppl,y:  the  selling   of  electricity  to   uisers-                     energy   transMitted.  Thuis  for  grid   systems  in&#13;
metering, billing, and  so  on.                                           dcx ,elopinig  couintries, one  mighit expect trans-&#13;
mission andI distribution costs to he a greater&#13;
This Note's main concern is wAith reformi of the                              propor-tion of the total.&#13;
transmission and distribuition svstems-'the&#13;
grid"-but it also  dliscuisses  the  innovations  in                         There are twokev points here. First, physical fac-&#13;
electricity  generation that made reform  possible.                          tors m-ake the fixedi costs of transmission and dis-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                             3&#13;
BOX 1       COST CHARACTERISTICS OF ELECTRICITY PROVISION&#13;
Generation&#13;
The costs comprise fixed capital costs and variable operational costs including fuel. Because each type of plant has a different balance between&#13;
fixed and variable costs, for each type the optimal size-giving the maximum economies of scale-is different.&#13;
Transmission&#13;
Transmission costs cover building and maintaining the transmission system and operating it (dispatching plant and maintaining voltage and&#13;
frequency within predetermined limits). The cost of building and maintaining the system depends on physical factors such as its size and the ter-&#13;
rain. The cost of extending it depends on the expected peak demand, but once the grid is built, the cost is sunk and so does not vary with the&#13;
number of users or the volume of electricity transmitted. The high fixed costs make it unprofitable for more than one transmission system to&#13;
compete in an area. Furthermore, the technicalities of minute-to-minute balancing of supply and demand together with the high cost of system&#13;
failure mean that the natural monopoly extends over the whole integrated system.&#13;
Distribution&#13;
As for transmission, the high fixed land low variable) costs depend primarily on the physical coverage of the system (both distance and terrain) and&#13;
the level of local peak demand. However, because the operating function is much simpler (it does not involve generator dispatch), the economies of&#13;
scale are not as great. A country that supports only one transmission system can support a number of (non-overlapping) distribution systems.&#13;
Supply&#13;
Many supply costs, such as bad debts and the costs of payment collection, vary with the number of customers. These costs are disproportion-&#13;
ately high for low-income households, which are more likely to experience payment difficulties and suffer disconnection. But some supply&#13;
costs are fixed: once supply has been extended to a village, the extra cost of reading another meter in that village is low. Supply costs vary with&#13;
the distance of customers from the nearest demand center. The more remote and dispersed the customers, the more expensive it is to administer&#13;
meter reading and bill collection centrally.&#13;
tribution particularly high for grid extensions to         As the demand for electricity increases, the fixed&#13;
remote rural populations. Thc population den-    costs can be spread. In dcveloping countries,&#13;
sity in rural areas is typically low, which means          howvever, it takes time for demand to grow once&#13;
that the fixed costs are shared among relatively           access is provided: people have to wire their&#13;
few  people.                                               houses and  buy  electrical appliances before&#13;
they start to buy electricity. Demand for elec-&#13;
Second, the poor tend to have verv low demand              tricitv  entails both  a switch  (not necessarily&#13;
for electricity, which means that the average cost    complete) from other fuels for cooking, heating,&#13;
per unit consumed will be high because the                 and  lighting  and  new  demand  for electrical&#13;
fixed  costs  are  divided  among  few   units.    appliances such as televisions. Over time, as&#13;
Furthermore, for the rural poor, this demand               incomes rise, loads will increase. andl load fac-&#13;
tends to be concentrated at peak tirmes (mainly    tors will also rise as people buy appliances with&#13;
in the evenings as people switch on lights). Since         conistant loads such as refrigerators. However.&#13;
the fixed costs of transmission and distribution           this progression is difficult to predict and there-&#13;
depend in part on peak demand, this demand                 fore the returns to investment in extension of&#13;
pattern results in still higher costs for poor rural    electricity grids to rural and poor people are&#13;
populations.                                               uncertain.&#13;
These points are illustrated in table 1, which             To summarize, providing access to electricity for&#13;
gives indicative figures for the relative distribu-    low-income households-in particular the exten-&#13;
tion costs of connecting different numbers of    sion of the grid to rural areas-depends critically&#13;
rural households at different distances from  the          on the balance between the fixed and variable&#13;
transmission system. The central column shows              costs of transmission and distribution. The fun-&#13;
the unit costs of distribution. The riglht-hand col-    damental cost characteristics of grid provision do&#13;
umn shows the unit costs including generation              not faxvor the provision of access to rural and poor&#13;
and high-voltage transmission.                             populations. Can reform make any difference?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4                   Does Reform of Energy Sector Networks Improve Access for the Poor?&#13;
TABLE 1   EFFECTS OF LINE LENGTH AND CONSUMPTION LEVELS ON THE RELATIVE COSTS OF&#13;
ELECTRIFICATION IN INDONESIA&#13;
(U.S. cents per kilowatt-hour)&#13;
Generation and transmission                                  10&#13;
Medium-voltage extension and low-voltage distribution&#13;
3-kilometer spur line, 20 households                       45                 55&#13;
3-kilometer spur line, 50 households                       20                 30&#13;
1-kilometer spur line, 20 households                       15                 25&#13;
1-kilometer spur line, 50 households                       7                  17&#13;
Note:These costs are indicative averages for most developing countries with relativelyflat terrain. Afew countries are now adopt-&#13;
ing new, lower-cost network designs.&#13;
Source: World Beak 1996, p. 50.&#13;
Buying electricity: why it is getting              began to want to build power plant-large&#13;
cheaper                                            industrial users as well as independent power&#13;
producers (IPPs).&#13;
The recent wave of electricity reform was facili-&#13;
tated by innovations in technology.                Competition and private participation have had&#13;
fur.her effects on costs. Rather than buying&#13;
Generation                                         equipment from a favored national supplier, as&#13;
state-owned monopoly generators had done,&#13;
'Until the 1980s the electricitv industrv was    new entrants import it if that means lower cost.&#13;
viewed as a unified natural monopoly that pro-    In turn, this has increased competition between&#13;
duced and delivered electricity. For decades    equipnment manufacturers, and  thermal effi-&#13;
economies of scale had increased in electricity    ciency has increased, further pushing unit costs&#13;
generation, reinforcing the view that it was a nat-   down. The thermal efficiency of CCGT stations&#13;
ural monopoly.                                     is now nearly 60 percent (compared with 30 per-&#13;
cent or more for other thermal stations ), and the&#13;
In the 1980s improvements in turbine technology    cost of installing the latest CCGT technology is&#13;
were imported from the space progratn and mate-    nowv about US$375450 per kilowatt.3&#13;
rials science and the price of gas fell (in part&#13;
because of gas market liberalization in developed    Thus generation market reform should cut costs&#13;
economies). This had a radical effect on the    and reduce prices for customers. Following the&#13;
economics of generation: the fixed cost of   introduction of competition in generation and&#13;
installing a combined-cycle gas turbine (CCGT)    the establishment of a bulk power market in&#13;
plant in the early 1990s in the United Kingdom    Argentina, bulk electricity prices have fallen&#13;
was around USS600-650 per kilowatt. compared    fairly consistently (figure 2).&#13;
with US$750-800 for oil-fired plant, US$900-1,200&#13;
for coal plant, and USS2,250 for nuclear. Falling    In other cases there have been difficulties, how-&#13;
gas prices reduced the variable costs as well.2    ever. In England and WXales, for example, antici-&#13;
pated reductions in bulk electricity prices failed&#13;
Combined-cycle gas generating units of 50-100    to materialize after competition was introduced&#13;
megawatts could by the 1990s be built and run    and the bulk power market cstablished, even&#13;
economically-at one-tenth the size of the ther-   though primary fuel prices were falling (figure&#13;
mal plants (1,000 mnegawatts or more) of the    3). Tiis has been blamed on the manipulation of&#13;
1980s (figure 1). This meant two things. First,   bulk power prices by the larger generators. In&#13;
generation could be a competitive activity even    other words, competition was not fully func-&#13;
in relatively small electricity systems. Second,   tioning. Trading arrangements intended to elim-&#13;
developers other than the state monopoly utility   inate such behavior are planned.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                    5&#13;
FIGURE 1  COST CURVES SHOWING OPTIMAL PLANT SIZE, 1930-90&#13;
U.S. dollars per megawatt&#13;
Thermal plants&#13;
1930&#13;
Combined-cycle&#13;
gas generation                                                                          1980&#13;
50                          200                             600                               1,000&#13;
Megawatts&#13;
Source: Hunt and Shuttleworth 1996.&#13;
Some developing  countries have also  had    ernments have begun to separate transmission,&#13;
difficulties in harnessing the full benefits of IPPs.   distribution. and supply.&#13;
A key question in generation reform is how to&#13;
set up a bulk power market that delivers the    While transmission and distribution have in&#13;
benefits of reduced costs while still attracting    many cases been separated. and distribution&#13;
private investors. Offering long-term power pur-   split among a number of companies, both func-&#13;
chase agreements to IPPs attracts investors, but   tions retain their natural monopoly characteris-&#13;
the greater the security (in terms of guarantecd   tics in any one area because of their high fixed&#13;
purchase volumes and prices) offered by the    costs. However, the introduction of private par-&#13;
contract, the less sharp the incentive for cost   ticipation through competitive tendering for&#13;
reduction and the less scope for the power pur-   concessions (to identify the least-cost provider)&#13;
chasing agency to adjust its purchasing to    has captured many benefits in terms of lower&#13;
achieve least-cost dispatch.4                    costs.&#13;
To ensure that the full benefits of competitive    Increased competition in the equipment markets&#13;
generation reach customers, it is necessary to    has reduced the price of many of the fixed cost&#13;
introduce competition in supply. If supply is pro-   components.  Installation  has  also  proved&#13;
vided through the local monopoly distribution    cheaper w hen done by private contractors rather&#13;
company, customers cannot shop around for   than utility employees.9&#13;
cheaper electricity. The monopoly distribution&#13;
company can shop around, but has no incentive    More generally, the private sector is simply&#13;
to do so as it can pass on generation costs to its   more efficient as a consequence of its profit&#13;
captive customers. However, competitive sup-   seeking. For example, when private distribution&#13;
pliers will need to purchase power as cheaply as    began in Buenos Aires there was a dramatic&#13;
possible, thus ensuring that lower generation    reduction in theft. Since theft was particularly&#13;
costs are passed to retail customers.            prevalent in slum areas, this reduction in theft&#13;
cut the difference between the cost of supply-&#13;
Transmission and distribution                    ing these areas and the electricity tariff and&#13;
enabled the distributor to supply slum areas&#13;
Having recognized that the electricity industry    with reduced subsidies (Albouy and Nadifi&#13;
comprises a number of distinct functions, gov-    1999).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6                   Does Reform of Energy Sector Networks Improve Access for the Poor?&#13;
FIGURE 2 BULK ELECTRICITY PRICES IN ARGENTINA, 1992-99&#13;
U.S. dollars per megawatt-hour&#13;
60&#13;
50&#13;
40&#13;
30&#13;
20&#13;
August       August        August        August        August        August        August        August&#13;
1992         1993          1994          1995          1996          1997          1998          1999&#13;
Source: CAMMESA 2000.&#13;
Equipment costs can also be reducecl by relax-   acted on in many countries (partial opening of the&#13;
ing equipment specifications and adopting inter-   market to supply competition is a requirement of&#13;
national standards. In the United Kingdom, for   the European Union directive on the single mar&#13;
example, over the past five years the cost of elec-   ket for electricity, for example). As a result of com-&#13;
tric plant in real terms has fallen by 10-15 per-   petition, in the United Kingdom1 the cost of meters&#13;
cent (Fairbairn 2000).                           has fallen by 39 percent over the past five years.&#13;
Ilowever, transmission and distribution remain    However, competition in supply is so far con-&#13;
local or national monopolies. This means, first, that   fined largely to more developed markets, where&#13;
incentives to reduce costs are not as sharp as they    companies can offer a number of sutpply services&#13;
wxould be under competition (although the profit   (such as electricity and gas) together and can dif-&#13;
motive supplies some incentive), and second, that   ferentiate themselves by service quality and&#13;
savings that are made will not be freely passed to   brand. In developing countries the costs of sup-&#13;
consumers. Therefore, where these monopolies    ply can be reduced in other ways, notably&#13;
are privately owned, regulation is necessarv.    through increased local involvement. Employing&#13;
someone to read meters in a village is cheaper if&#13;
Incentive-based regulation, such as the CPI-X    that person does not have to travel a long dis-&#13;
price cap methodology, involves a balance   tance from the nearest town. Local participation&#13;
between giving utilities the incentive to reduce   in bill collection and maintenance can also be&#13;
c(osts and ensuring that cost reductions are   effective. For example, in Bangladesh locally&#13;
passed to the consumer. The utility keeps some    managed cooperatives buy power from the grid&#13;
of the savings, but must pass the rest to the con-   and distribute it locally. They have a better&#13;
sumer.i In the tJnited Kingdom incentive-based    record on billing, maintenance, and reducing&#13;
regulation has been broadly successful in reduc-   losses than that of the main power utility in&#13;
ing prices to domestic consumers, even though    charge of urban distribution (World Bank 1996).&#13;
bulk prices have not fallcn (figure 4).&#13;
Electricity for the poor: does cheaper&#13;
Supply                                           mean better?&#13;
The potential for competition in supply, which,   Cheaper generation has reduced the total cost of&#13;
with relativelv low fixed costs, is not a natural   providing electricity. That should mean lower&#13;
monopoly, has been recognized and is being    prices for the poor who are already served by a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                             7&#13;
FIGURE 3 AVERAGE ANNUAL DEMAND-WEIGHTED ELECTRICITY POOL OF ENGLAND AND&#13;
WALES PURCHASE PRICE, 1991-2000&#13;
Pounds per megawatt-hour&#13;
30&#13;
25&#13;
20&#13;
15&#13;
10&#13;
5&#13;
0&#13;
1991      1992       1993      1994       1995      1996       1997      1998      1999      2000a&#13;
Note: The years refer to fiscal years, ending in March.&#13;
a. Average for April to October 1999.&#13;
Source: Electricity Pool of England and Wales 20.&#13;
FIGURE 4 ELECTRICITY PRICE FOR STANDARD DOMESTIC TARIFF CUSTOMERS IN THE&#13;
UNITED KINGDOM, 1990-99&#13;
Pence per kilowatt-hour (1989-90 prices)&#13;
8&#13;
6&#13;
4&#13;
2&#13;
1990      1991       1992       1993      1994       1995      1996       1997      1998       1999&#13;
Note:The years refer to fiscal years, ending in March.&#13;
Source: U.K. Department ol Trade, Statistical Office 1999.&#13;
grid. Reductions in the fixed costs of transmis-           affordable. One solution is to direct electricity sub-&#13;
sion and distribution equipment, and innova-               sidies much more precisely to the poor, for exam-&#13;
tions to reduce the costs of supplying remote              ple. through thc introduction of lifcline tariffs.8&#13;
areas, improve the prospects that grids will be            More generally, the design of the tariff system  is&#13;
extended to rural areas.                                   crucial in determining how  the benefits of elec-&#13;
tricity reform (in terms of lower costs) are distrib-&#13;
However, there are two important caveats. First,    uted   among   different  customer  classes.  If&#13;
for the poor to benefit, lower production costs    electricity reform  is to benefit the poor, tariff pol-&#13;
must be passed on as lower prices. In many devel-    icy must be designed with their needs in mind.&#13;
oping countries tariffs have risen following reform&#13;
as subsidies have been withdrawn (despite cost    Second, the fixed costs of transmission and dis-&#13;
reductions). In many respects this benefits the            tribution equipment have not fallen enough to&#13;
poor,' but it does make access to electricity less    make it profitable to extend the grid to all areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8                           Does Reform of Energy Sector Networks Improve Access for the Poor?&#13;
Given the huge difference between cost of sup-                           particularly if the ftinds are redirected tossard social policies. For&#13;
ply and (socially or politically) acceptable tariffs                     ftirer disctlsston of energy subsidies see 19orld Bank 1990 arc&#13;
International Energy Agency 1999.&#13;
for some  rural populations, extensions  of the                          Lifeline tariffs essentially invols e subsidizing electricitv only at rite&#13;
grid to these people must be subsidized if they                          very loss levels of constirnption typical of poor hotiseholds The&#13;
are  to  happen  at all. There  are  two  ways  in                       suhsidies apply to secv small amotonts of electricitn and do not&#13;
bycost too MLuch. This po)licy has been suiccessfuil in Titailandl: see&#13;
which  this  can  happen:  within  the  utility  bv                      luntivate and Barnes 199.&#13;
cross-subsidy from profitable customers (under&#13;
an  obligation  to  extend  service) or with  subsi-&#13;
dies from  outside the utility, for example, from                     References&#13;
a rural electrification fund.                                         Albuy, Yves, and Nadia Nadifi. 1999. "Impact of Power Sector&#13;
Reform on the Poor: A Resiews of IssLues ancl the Literatuire. ' borld&#13;
Bank. Energy, Mining, and Telecommuinications Depanmert,&#13;
Conclusion                                                               Washington. D.(-&#13;
Bacon, Robert. 1995. 'Competitive Contracting for Privately&#13;
Reform  of grid-based  electricitypr nCGenerated Posser.' Vies point 47. \Xorld Bank, Finance, Private&#13;
Reformn  of grid-based  electricity  provision  will                     Sector, and InfrastrICtuIre NetworIk, Washington, D.C&#13;
not revolutionize access by  the poor. The cost                       --. 1999. "Global Energy Sector Refornm in Developing Countries:&#13;
structure  of grid  provision, so  unfavorable  to                       A Scorecard.' World Bank, Energy Sector Management Assistance&#13;
Frogramame, Washington, D.C.&#13;
extending access to rural populations, is not fun-                    CANINILSA (Compania admic iictralora del mercado noasorista elec&#13;
damentally    altered    by    electricity    reform.                    trico sociedad anonima) 2000 wwwv.canimesacom&#13;
However,  reform   unambiguouslv  moves  the                          Eleciricitv Pool of England and Wales 2000. wsvw  elecpuolicorn&#13;
overall level of costs in the right direction. At the                 Fairbairn. Richard. 2000. "Analysis of Electrical Trade Price Indices&#13;
Viewpoint is an open        margin, cost reductions  imply  both  increased                          PB Poser Ltd.&#13;
forum intended to           affordability of grid services and  increased via-                    Hunt, Sally, and Graham ShUitlewornh. 1996. CompentitionanrdChoice&#13;
encourage                   biiyii' E/ectnlcity Chichester, England: John Wiley and Sons&#13;
bilitv  of grid  extensions. As long  as the  intro-                  International Energy Agency  1999  Lookhtg cit Eoergl Srmhaia/ies&#13;
dissemination of and                                                                               ItrainlEeg     gny    99   okn    tFeg,Sbil~&#13;
debate on ideas,            duction   of   competition   and   profit-seeking                        Getting the Prices Right-  Rot-ld Energy Oztlook 1999 Insights. Paris.&#13;
innovations, and best       private participation is combined with regulation                     Izagtiirre, Ada Karina. 2003. "Private Participation  in Energys'&#13;
practices for expanding     and tariff design that is sensitive to the needs of                      Viewpoint 208   orld Bank, Posvare Sector and InfrastcrucCe&#13;
the private sector. The                                                                              Nemwork. WEashington. D.C.&#13;
vievvs published in this    the poor, electricity reform  is a positive step.                     Nel bert-, David MI, and Richard Green. 1996. "The English Electricity&#13;
series are those of the                                                                              Industrv ." In Richard J. Gilben and Edssard P. Kahn, eds.,&#13;
authors and should not                                                                               international Comparisors of Flectrcitc Regul/ation Cambridge:&#13;
be attributed to the           Reform of grid-based energy services has concentrated on the gen      C:ambridge Universirs Press.&#13;
World Bank or any of its       eration and distribution of elecuricity. Electricity nets'orks are far  Tuntivate. Voravate Tig. and Douglas F Barmes. 1997.  I'¶hailand s&#13;
affiliated organizations.      more extensive rhan gas netisorks in most pails of the develop        Approach to Rural Electrification' Hoss was It Successfuld" World&#13;
Nor do any of the con-         ing wsorld and reform of gas netwsorks has been less ssidespread      Bank, Inergy  Sector  tlanagenment Assistance  lirogramme,&#13;
clusions represent             This Note therefore discusses electricitv reforns, although many of   Washington, D.C.&#13;
official policy of the        the important points apply to both indtistries, gisen the parallels  U.K. Department of 'rade and Industry, Statistical Office. 1999 Dige:st&#13;
World Bank or of its          in terms of network econoniics.                                        of U.K. Energy Statistics London.&#13;
Executive Directors or      2 Although the wsidespread adoption of CCGT as the new technol-        Wordcl Bank. 1996. RurralEnergl andDeve/opmentt Inproti ngEttergy&#13;
the countries they             ogy of choice was linked to the fall in the price of gas. the tech-   Sitppliea for TAo Billion People. NVashington, D.C.&#13;
represent.                     nology can run on diesel This discussion therefore also applies&#13;
to countries ssith no access to gas&#13;
To order additional         3 The cost estimates are from Richard Fairbairn of PB Power Ltd       Stephen Powell (stephenpowellfnera.corn) and&#13;
copies please call             For a more detailed discussion of this issue see Bacon 1995.        Mary Starks (mary.starks@nera.com), National&#13;
202 458 1 1 1 1 or contact     This is one reason whv employment in the electricity industry has  Economic Research Associates. London&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,        fallen dramatically following reformn  This is a controversial social&#13;
Room Fl 1 K-208, The           effect of reform and one that has direct implications for the poor.&#13;
World Bank, 1818 H             ffowever, the subject is beyond the scope o this Note&#13;
Street, NW, Washington,     6 CPI-X achieves this by fixing allowed prices for a given period,     This .tote originally appeared as a chapter in&#13;
D.C. 20433, or Internet        dLoring sshich the utilitr can retain the profits arising from any  Energy Sector ,14anagement Assistance&#13;
address ssmith7@               cost reduction. At the end of this period the price cap is&#13;
worldbank.org. The             reviewed to ensure that over the long term  the benefits are       Programme (ESi1APJ, Energy and Development&#13;
series is also available       passed to consumers.                                               Report 2000: Energy Services for the World's&#13;
on-lhim lwfdldbe/)nk.          Since energy subsidies are a larger proportion of GDP in many      Poor (Washington, D.C.: World Bank, 2000).&#13;
org/html/fpd/notes/).          developing coLntries and benefit the swell-off more than the poor&#13;
@ Printed on recycled         (because the well off use more energy-, particularly electricity),  For more inforrration on                      1        A  A  D&#13;
paper.                         reductions in subsidies will tend to benefit the poor in fiscal terms,  ES AlAPgo to www.esmap.org.               LtJaiI 11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="729346">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/05/729346/reform-energy-sector-networks-improve-access-poor
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/05/729346/reform-energy-sector-networks-improve-access-poor</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2000/05/729346/reform-energy-sector-networks-improve-access-poor</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/12/22/000094946_0012130148387/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/12/22/000094946_0012130148387/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2000-12-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2000-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Does reform of energy sector networks
            improve access for the poor?
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Unless energy can be produced and
            delivered more cheaply, it will stay beyond the reach of
            many of the poor. For energy delivered through networks, the
            costs that matter are not only the unit energy costs, but
            the costs of extending the network--into an urban slum, for
            example, or to a rural town. Extending a network can be very
            expensive--a major barrier to access for poor households and
            small or isolated communitieds. A central goal of the reform
            of electricity and gas networks, now occurring in an
            increasing number of developed and developing countries, is
            to provide incentives to reduce the costs of producing
            energy and getting it to consumers. New technologies in
            electricity are drastically reducing costs. But transmission
            costs are still a major hurdle to expanding networks in
            isolated or lightly populated areas. As a result it is the
            urban poor who stand the greatest chance of benefiting from
            network reform. For the rural poor, alternative solutions,
            including mini-grid and off-grid services, may be required.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Does reform of energy sector networks
            improve access for the poor?
        </docna>
        <display_title>Does reform of energy sector
            networks improve access for the poor?</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2000/05/729346/reform-energy-sector-networks-improve-access-poor</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Energy and Poverty Alleviation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Power &amp; Energy Conversion,Energy and Environment</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Energy,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Powell, Stephen</author>
            <author>Starks, Mary</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_0012130148387</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Distribution &amp; Transmission</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 209</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Energy,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Energy sector reform; Networks; Service
            delivery; Incentives; Energy production; Technological
            change; Transmission; Power generation; Power distribution;
            Electricity pricing; Grids; Fixed costs; Supply &amp;
            demand; Competition (economic); Private sector participation
            acceptable tariffs,access to
            electricity,bulk electricity,bulk power,bulk power
            market,bulk prices,captive customers,central
            planning,coal,coal plant,competitive electricity
            market,consumers,CONSUMPTION LEVELS,CPI,demand for
            electricity,distribution company,distribution
            systems,dollars per megawatt,dollars per
            megawatt-hour,economic effects,Economic Research,economies
            of scale,electrical appliances,electricity,electricity
            generation,electricity industry,ELECTRICITY POOL,electricity
            prices,ELECTRICITY PROVISION,Electricity reform,electricity
            systems,electricity tariff,employment,energy costs,energy
            sector,Energy Sector Management Assistance,energy sector
            networks,energy services,Energy Statistics,energy
            subsidies,fixed costs,fuel,fuel prices,fuels,gas generating
            units,gas generation,gas market,gas market
            liberalization,gas networks,gas prices,gas
            turbine,GDP,generation costs,generation
            market,generator,generator dispatch,generators,grid,grid
            extensions,grid provision,grid services,grid
            systems,heating,high-voltage system,high-voltage
            transmission,income,independent power
            producers,International Energy Agency,kilometer spur
            line,Lifeline tariffs,lights,low-income
            households,low-voltage,low-voltage distribution,meter
            reading,monopolies,natural monopoly,new entrants,oil,peak
            demand,poor populations,power plant,power sector,power
            sector reform,price cap,price of gas,private
            ownership,production costs,PURCHASE PRICE,purchasing
            power,rural electricity,rural electrification,rural
            electrification fund,rural households,rural
            populations,savings,thermal efficiency,Thermal plants,total
            cost of electricity,transmission costs,utilities,utility
            employees,variable costs
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>21465</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Servers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Switches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Service</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Poverty Alleviation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Electrification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Network Management</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>