<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>. 2 1469 &#13;
Viewpoint&#13;
Note No. 214                                                                                     July MTX&#13;
Promoting Private Investment in Rural&#13;
Electrification-The Case of Chile&#13;
Alejandro         Reform of the energy sector and reform of subsidies ideally go hand in hand. Structural, ownership,&#13;
Jfdrlesic          and regulatory reforms aimed at making services more efficient should lead to a rethinking of both&#13;
the delivery mechanism and the level of subsidy. Chile, one of the earliest and most thorough&#13;
energy reformers, has also been one of the more innovative in restructuring its subsidy schemes. It&#13;
has seen electrification as a key measure in alleviating poverty in rural areas-in 1992 about 47&#13;
percent of its rural population had no access to electricity. Its rural electrification program includes&#13;
subsidies designed to be consistent with the broad principles of energy reform-decentralization of&#13;
decisions to the regional and community level, competition (between technologies as well as&#13;
suppliers), and a requirement that all partners in the process-users and private companies as well&#13;
as the state-contribute to the financing of expansion projects. The short-term result: an increase&#13;
in rural electrification of about 50 percent in the first five years of the program.&#13;
In the 1980s Chile liberalized its markets. priva-   or cross-subsidies from tariffs set ahove cost in&#13;
lized state-owned electricity companies, and   urban areas. Lack of funding and pressure from&#13;
allowed the private sector the key role in invest-   other priorities made electrification slow.&#13;
ment. Before selling the electricity companies, the&#13;
state split them into generation and transmission   By the early 1990s more than 1 million people&#13;
companies and distribution utilities. The distribu-   almost half the rural population-still had no&#13;
tion utilities were divided according to the areas   access to any source of electricity (figure 1). By&#13;
in whiclh they operated. but no exclusive distrib-   contrast, 97 percent of urban households had&#13;
ution rights were granted. The National Energy   electricity supply. The lack of access was con-&#13;
Commission (Comisi6n Nacional de Energia.   centrated in a few regions where most of the&#13;
CNE) was created as the main policymaking and   rural population lives. It affected mainly lower-&#13;
regulatory body. A new; electricity law" established   income families, since the wealthier could usu-&#13;
free etitry and comiipetition in geineration, a nonex-   ally afford to install generators or pay for&#13;
clusive concession system for distribution, and a   extension of the distribution grid.&#13;
pricing scheme based on marginal costs, with&#13;
gencration charges reviewed every six months   To increase rural access to electricity, Chile&#13;
and distribution charges every four years.   launched a rural electrification program in 1994.&#13;
The design of the program is compatible with the&#13;
Rural electrification in Chile had traditionally been   overall electricity sector reforms-that is, based&#13;
the domain of the state-owned power companies,   on competition, private investment and decen-&#13;
which followed centrally developed plans and   tralized decisionmaking. The goal was, with the&#13;
relied on subsidies from the central government   help of a subsicly, to turn rural electrification into&#13;
WM_________    The World Bank Group * Private Sector and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Promoting Private Investment in Rural Electrification--The Case of Chile&#13;
FIGURE 1  ELECTRICITY COVERAGE IN CHILE, 1952-92&#13;
Percentage of households&#13;
100                         Urb                a    n&#13;
But where the costs of this solution are too high,&#13;
80                                                                alternative technologies are considered. These&#13;
alternatives, mainly for self-generation in iso&#13;
lated communities, include:&#13;
60                               *                                  Photovoltaic  solutions  for  isolated  ruLral&#13;
dwellings.&#13;
* Hybrid systems that recduce fossil fuel depen-&#13;
40                            Rural                                 dence and operating costs.&#13;
* Small hydcroelectric power stations, indepen-&#13;
20                                                                  dent or combined with other energy sources.&#13;
2  Experimental solutions hased on wind power&#13;
and biomass systems, which would require a&#13;
a                                                                  resource assessment program  before being&#13;
1952        1960         1970         1982          1992          applied.&#13;
Source: Chilean National Statistics Institute, census data.&#13;
Tc ensure sustainability, all costs over the life of&#13;
the projects are considered in the appraisal, as&#13;
well as organizational schemes for operating and&#13;
an attractive business opportunity. The state, pri-    maintaining the projects.&#13;
vate investors and users would all contribtute to&#13;
funding.                                           The program  in action&#13;
The state's contribution-the subsidies and the    The central government s tasks of providing&#13;
cost of managing the program-is delivered    funds and technical assistance and coordinating&#13;
through a special fund set up to competitively   the program are handled mainly by the CNE. The&#13;
allocate a one-time direct subsidy to private    CNE prepared a planning and management&#13;
electricity clistribution companies to cover part   model for the technical units of the regional gov-&#13;
of tlheir investment costs in rural electrification    ernments that would lead the process. It also cre-&#13;
projects. Bids are conducted annually. To apply    ated methodological tools to ensure efficient&#13;
for a subsidy companies present their projects    allocation  of the state subsidies, based  on&#13;
to the regional governments. which allocate the    national ancl international experience. And it&#13;
funds to those scoring best on several objective    prepared preinvestment studies to generate ini-&#13;
criteria: cost-benefit analysis, amount of invest-   tial project portfolios for each region.&#13;
ment covered by the companies, and social&#13;
impact. The central government allocates the    The target was to reach 75 percent rural cover-&#13;
subsidy funCds to the regions on the basis of two    agc by 2000. and 100 percent after 10 years (the&#13;
criteria: howi much progress a region made in    program is expected to run until 2004). It was&#13;
rural electrification in the previous year and    estimated that the state would have to invest&#13;
how  many  households still lack  electricity.   about US$150 million, which woould allow elec-&#13;
Regional governments also allocate their own    trification of roughly 110,000 rural dwellings.&#13;
resources to the program. The state cloes not&#13;
endi up owning or operating any facility.          Communities in areas lacking electricity supply&#13;
generally propose the rural electrification pro-&#13;
If technically and economically feasible. the first   jects, supported by local distribution companies&#13;
choice is to priovide service at the standards    interested in providing the service. A community&#13;
offered by the distribution gricd (220 volts effec-    presents a project to its municipalityv which then&#13;
tive monophasic alternate voltage and 50 hertz    asks the distribution company to prepare a tech-&#13;
freqiuencv, with twenty-four-hour availability).   nical proposal, at no cost to the municipality, or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 2 RURAL DWELLINGS OBTAINING ELECTRICITY AND RURAL ELECTRICITY COVERAGE IN CHILE,&#13;
1992-99&#13;
Dwellings (thousands)                                                           Coverage (percentage of households)&#13;
25                                                                                                       80&#13;
20&#13;
70&#13;
i5&#13;
Dwellings     Coverage&#13;
10&#13;
60&#13;
o                                                                                                        50&#13;
1992        1993         1994         1995        1996         1997         1998        1999&#13;
Note: Data for 1999 are estimates.&#13;
Source: Chile, National Energy Conunission 1999.&#13;
contracts for this service with an independent       the grid. These expenditures, nearly 10 percent&#13;
consulting company. Once the proposal is pre-        of the costs of each project, are initially financed&#13;
pared, the municipality lists the project in a pub-  by the distribution company and repaid by the&#13;
licly accessible register.                           users over time. Once the project is operating,&#13;
the users have to pay the regulated tariffs.&#13;
Using the prescribed criteria and tools, the         The distribution company is required to invest&#13;
regional planning agency evaluates the projects,     at least the amount calculated using a formula&#13;
analyzing their economic and financial costs and     set by the government-to avoid cheating.&#13;
henefits and calculating the contribution of the     The company also must operate the projects.&#13;
company and the subsidy required. Only pro-    * The state has to provide a subsidy for the invest-&#13;
jects with a positive social return but a negative   ment costs that is no more than the (negative)&#13;
private return are considered for subsidies. The     net present value of the project, which in any&#13;
program allows a 10 percent real rate of return      case has to be smaller than the total investment.&#13;
on investment, similar to that used for setting tar-&#13;
iffs for the projects, over a thirty-ycar horizon.  Grants from  international organizations have&#13;
also been used in the program, especially for&#13;
After being analyzed, the projects are submitted    experimental projects based on self-generation&#13;
to the head of the regional government in a port-   systems using alternative energy sources.&#13;
folio of all those meeting the minimum require-&#13;
ments. The head of the regional government then    Once a project has been implemented, the dis-&#13;
presents a proposal to the regional council, which    tribution  company  takes care of operation,&#13;
has to allocate the state funds among the projects,    management, and maintenance, recovering its&#13;
taking into account the number of beneficiaries,   costs through the tariffs charged consumers,&#13;
the unit cost, and the financing needs. The re-   which are set by the CNE.&#13;
gional govemment then allocates the funds to the&#13;
companies that presented the projects selected.    Results&#13;
The responsibility for financing the projects is    The program has increased the coverage of elec-&#13;
split up as follows:                               tricity systems in rural areas from 53 percent in&#13;
* Users have to cover the costs of the in-house    1992 to 76 percent at the end of 1999, exceed-&#13;
wiring, the electric meter, and the coupling to   ing the 75 percent target set for 2000. And it has&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Promoting Private Investment in Rural Electrification--The Case of Chile&#13;
sh own that it is possible to create market incen-    Mlost of the projects have involved extension of&#13;
tives that lead to efficienit private solutions to    the grid, asolution that usually mieans a lower-cost&#13;
rurLl electrification-an  important lesson at a    per connected dwelling and a higher quality of&#13;
time xxwhen so many developing countries are    service. BLut several projects have relied on alter-&#13;
reforming their power markets and privatizing    native technologies, priimarily one-house phloto-&#13;
their state-owned electric utilities.                  voltaic  systems.  These  systems  have  been&#13;
installed in isolated areas in the northlern part of&#13;
An innovative aspect of the program  has been    the country (for nearly 1,000 clwellinigs). wlviclh&#13;
the use of competition. It has successfully intro-    has some of the strongest solar racliation in the&#13;
cducecl competition at several levels: among corn-    world. The nonconventional technologies gener-&#13;
munities, for financing for their projects; among    ally provide electricity at a higher cost and poorer&#13;
distribution companies, for implementation of    quality (lowxer voltage, fewer hours of selrice).&#13;
their projects; antI among regions, for the funds    But they have heen an attractive alternative wlhel-e&#13;
provided by the central government.                    extencling the grid is too costly because of the clis-&#13;
tance from the existing grid or the high dispersion&#13;
The state has contributed the most funding to the    of dwellings. Both these causes have increasecl&#13;
program, investing USS112 million in rural elec-    the marginal cost of rural electrification in Chile.&#13;
trification in 1995-99, sometlhing less than what    In 1995 thie average state subsidy per dwelling&#13;
was estimated at thie beginning of the program.    ami)unted  to  UTSS1,080;  in  1999  it reached&#13;
For their part, the companies have helped clefine    IUSS1,510.This outcome is nevertheless consistent&#13;
Viewpoint is an open  the projects, invested resources, ancl untdertaken i   with the program's goal of maximizing rural elec-&#13;
forum intended to     the commercial risk, and continue to own and    tric'ty coverage witlhin budget constraints, wxxicll&#13;
encourage             manage the installations. Private investment in    mandates first implementing the projects with the&#13;
sisseminadion of ard&#13;
debate on ideas,     the programn so far has totaled US$60 million.    highest impact per unit of investment. At the same&#13;
innovations, and best  Companies have participated in the program as    time, however, it allows a growing role for non-&#13;
practices for expanding  a strategic move to protect their existing distrib  conventional technologies in ruLral electrification&#13;
the private sector The&#13;
views published in this  Ltion area and tliscourage entry by cornpetitors.    projects, as improvements in these teclhnologies&#13;
series are those ofthe  From the companies' perspective rural electrifi-    reduce their costs and make them  increasingly&#13;
authors and should not  cation is a riskier business than traditional distri-    competitive xxwitlh conventional solutions.&#13;
be attributed to the&#13;
World Bank or any of its  bution. Customer payments are generally low&#13;
affiliated organizations.  vvhile operating and maintenance costs are high   References&#13;
Nor do any of the con-  compared with those in urban areas. But com-&#13;
clusionrsrepresent                                                           Chile, sL iOnal  l'nei-gy  Cni sailiossn. 1999.) I'-grgll.n l d  lectrifi-&#13;
officialpolicyofthe   panies expect consumption to increase as users           caci6n1 rLir.il I'cUil cIlcC(trifiC i( l 91 ItrIn I). S&gt;aili 1I&#13;
World Bank or of its  realize the potential for income generating activ-&#13;
Executive Directors or  ities SILch as fisliing and forestry.&#13;
the countries they&#13;
represent.                                                                   AlejandroJadresic (jacl5ic@ctcreuna.cl),&#13;
As hoped, users have participated in identify'ing    former minister ofen)zergy q/ Chile (1994-98S&#13;
To order additional   ancl defining the projects-helping to establish&#13;
copies please call&#13;
202458 1111 or contact  the needs ancl priorities in each region-antI in    77.his Vote is based on a chapter in Energy&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,  financing the investments. Regional governments    Sector MlIanagemnent Assistance Program me&#13;
Room F11 K-208, The&#13;
World Bank, 1818 H    have promoted the program  among communi-    (FS1IAP), Energy and Development Report&#13;
Street, NW, Washington,    ties, provided basic assistance in preparing the    2000): Energy Services for the NWorlt's Poor&#13;
D.C.20433rInteret     projects. decided wlhich woould be implemented         (Wasbington, D.C... World&#13;
address ssmith7a &#13;
worldbank.org. The    ancl allocated resources accordingly. They' halve    Bank, 2000).                          EL.  N  A1&#13;
seres is also avai able  also coortlinated andI monitored the implemen&#13;
on- ine (www.worldbank.&#13;
orgl'html/fpd/notes/).  Lation of the projects. Essential m  ivolvig&#13;
8 Printed on recycled  regional authorities is the fact that stucccss in the&#13;
paper                 program has become a key political achievement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="729350">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/07/729350/promoting-private-investment-rural-electrification-case-chile
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/07/729350/promoting-private-investment-rural-electrification-case-chile</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2000/07/729350/promoting-private-investment-rural-electrification-case-chile</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/12/22/000094946_00121301483911/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2000/12/22/000094946_00121301483911/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2000-12-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2000-07-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Promoting private investment in rural
            electrification : the case of Chile
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Reform of the energy sector and reform
            of subsidies ideally go hand in hand. Structural, ownership,
            and regulatory reforms aimed at making services more
            efficient should lead to a rethinking of both the delivery
            mechanism and the level of subsidy. Chile, one of the
            earliest and most thorough energy reformers, has also been
            one of the more innovative in restructuring its subsidy
            schemes. It has seen electrification as a key measure in
            alleviating poverty in rural areas-in 1992 about 47 percent
            of its rural population had no access to electricity. Its
            rural electrification program includes subsidies designed to
            be consistent with the broad principles of energy
            reform-decentralization of decisions to the regional and
            community level, competition (between technologies as well
            as suppliers), and a requirement that all partners in the
            process-users and private companies as well as the
            state-contribute to the financing of expansion projects. The
            short-term result: an increase in rural electrification of
            about 50 percent in the first five years of the program.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Promoting private investment in rural
            electrification : the case of Chile
        </docna>
        <display_title>Promoting private investment in
            rural electrification : the case of Chile</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2000/07/729350/promoting-private-investment-rural-electrification-case-chile</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Energy and Poverty Alleviation,Energy and Environment,Engineering,Public Sector Management and Reform,ICT Policy and Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Public Sector Development,Science and Technology Development,Energy,Information and Communication Technologies</teratopic>
        <count>Chile</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Jadresic, Alejandro</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_00121301483911</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Power &amp; Energy Conversion</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 214</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Public Sector Development,Science and Technology Development,Energy,Information and Communication Technologies</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Private investments; Rural electrification;
            Energy sector reform; Subsidies; Regulatory reform;
            Decentralization; Community participation; Technological
            change; Supply contracts; Competitiveness; User participation
            access to electricity,alternate
            voltage,alternative energy,alternative energy
            sources,assessment program,biomass systems,business
            opportunity,concession system,consumers,distribution
            companies,distribution company,distribution
            utilities,ELECTRICITY COVERAGE,electricity law,electricity
            sector,electricity sector reforms,electricity supply,Energy
            Services,energy sources,fossil
            fuel,fuel,generators,income,innovations,municipality,Photovoltaic
            solutions,power companies,power markets,power
            stations,pressure,principles of energy reform,regional
            government,regional governments,regional planning,rural
            dwellings,RURAL ELECTRICITY,RURAL ELECTRICITY COVERAGE,rural
            electrification,rural electrification program,source of
            electricity,technical assistance,tools,urban areas,wind power
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>21469</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Service</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Poverty Alleviation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Electrification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Chile</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>