<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                     38753&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Sector Finance Working Papers: No. 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water Supply and Sanitation Inputs for&#13;
           Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Background Report for the Ministry of Water Resources&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   The Water and Sanitation Program is an               February 2002&#13;
                   international partnership for improving water&#13;
&#13;
                   and sanitation sector policies, practices, and&#13;
&#13;
                   capacities to serve poor people&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                           CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Abbreviations                                                          ii&#13;
    Acknowledgments                                                        iii&#13;
    Executive Summary                                                      iv&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.  Introduction                                                           1&#13;
&#13;
2.  Situation Assessment ­1: WSS and Poverty Linkage&#13;
&#13;
     ·  Nature of linkage between WSS and poverty reduction                1&#13;
     ·  Priorities expressed by the poor                                   1&#13;
     ·  Status of water supply and sanitation in Ethiopia&#13;
                 o Ethiopia's comparative performance                      2&#13;
                 o Overall changes in WSS status over time                 2&#13;
                 o Rural water supply status ­ regional variations         2&#13;
                 o Variations across urban areas                           4&#13;
                 o Sanitation and hygiene practices                        5&#13;
&#13;
3.  Situation Assessment ­2: Policy, Institutional and Financing Issues&#13;
&#13;
     ·  National Water Policy ­ key highlights                             5&#13;
     ·  Institutional arrangements within decentralization framework       6&#13;
     ·  Sector financing and flow of funds                                 8&#13;
     ·  Key Sector Issues                                                  11&#13;
     ·  Approach to Operationalization of the WSS component in WSDP        14&#13;
&#13;
4.  Priorities for Poverty Reduction:&#13;
    Action Plans, Targets and Expenditure Requirements&#13;
&#13;
     ·  WSS Sub-sector Priorities for Poverty Reduction                    15&#13;
     ·  Outcome linked Action Plans                                        15&#13;
     ·  Coverage targets and investment requirements                       15&#13;
&#13;
5.  WSS Sector Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
     ·  Issues in developing a sector M&amp;E                                  18&#13;
     ·  Institutional arrangements for sector M&amp;E in WSS                   18&#13;
     ·  Development of key M&amp;E indicators                                  19&#13;
&#13;
    References                                                             21&#13;
    Annex 1: Notes and sources for Table 1                                 22&#13;
    Annex 2: Notes and sources for Table 6                                 22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                i&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                        ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
&#13;
AAWSA     Addis Ababa Water and Sewerage Authority&#13;
&#13;
CPC       Community Planning Committee&#13;
&#13;
CRDA      Christian Relief Development Association&#13;
&#13;
CSA       Central Statistical Authority&#13;
&#13;
DPPC      Disaster Prevention and Preparedness Commission&#13;
&#13;
ESP       Environmental Support Project&#13;
&#13;
ESRDF     Ethiopian Social Rehabilitation and Development Fund&#13;
&#13;
FINNIDA   Finnish International Development Agency&#13;
&#13;
GOE       Government of Ethiopia&#13;
&#13;
HHICE     Household Income Consumption and Expenditure Survey&#13;
&#13;
HIPC      Heavily Indebted Poor Countries&#13;
&#13;
M&amp;E       Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
MFI       Micro-Finance Institutions&#13;
&#13;
MWR       Ministry of Water Resources&#13;
&#13;
NGO       Non-Governmental Organizations&#13;
&#13;
NRW       Non-Revenue Water&#13;
&#13;
O&amp;M       Operations and Maintenance&#13;
&#13;
PPA       Participatory Poverty Assessments&#13;
&#13;
PRSP      Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper&#13;
&#13;
RWB       Regional Water Board&#13;
&#13;
RWS       Rural Water Supply&#13;
&#13;
RWSS      Rural Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
&#13;
SCM       Supply chains and maintenance&#13;
&#13;
SDP       Sector Development Program&#13;
&#13;
SIMS      Sector Information Management Systems&#13;
&#13;
SWB       Scheme Water Board&#13;
&#13;
TWSU      Town Water Service Unit&#13;
&#13;
UWASNET   Uganda Water and Sanitation NGO network&#13;
&#13;
UWSU      Urban Water Service Unit&#13;
&#13;
VWC       Village Water Committees&#13;
&#13;
VWSC      Village Water and Sanitation Committee&#13;
&#13;
WB        Water Board&#13;
&#13;
WMS       Welfare Monitoring Survey&#13;
&#13;
WMU       Welfare monitoring unit&#13;
&#13;
WSDP      Water Sector Development Program&#13;
&#13;
WSP       Water Supply and Sanitation Service Providers&#13;
&#13;
WSS       Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  ii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                       ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This document was prepared in response to a request from the Ministry of Water Resources, Government of&#13;
Ethiopia to provide inputs to the preparation of water supply and sanitation inputs to the full Poverty&#13;
Reduction Strategy Paper (PRSP) of the Government of Ethiopia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
We have benefited from detailed discussions and feedback from staff of Ministry of Water Resources: Ato&#13;
Mesfin Tegene, Vice Minister for Water Resources, Ato Gulilat Berhane, Head, Department of Planning and&#13;
Projects, Ato Tesfaye Wolde Meheret, Coordinator of the Water Sector Strategy and Development Program,&#13;
Ato Yohaness G. Medhen, Head, Department of Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Services. We have also&#13;
benefited from comments on the draft report provided by Duvvuri Subbarao, Catherine Revels and Yitbarek&#13;
Tessema of the World Bank, and Jean Doyen of WSP-Africa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The task team comprised Meera Mehta as Task Manager and Belete Mulune of WSP-Africa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Production assistance was provided by Shamis Salah and Jecinter Hezron.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       iii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                      WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.        Introduction&#13;
&#13;
Water has been recognized as a priority area within the PRSP process in Ethiopia. Government of Ethiopia,&#13;
through the Ministry of Water Resources (MWR) has requested WSP-AF assistance in developing the&#13;
background materials for preparation of the WSS inputs for the full PRSP. This report has been prepared in&#13;
response to this request, based on discussions with various stakeholders and a synthesis of available studies&#13;
and consultant reports. It also draws on reports and proceedings of a number of consultations that the MWR&#13;
has had with different stakeholders at federal and regional levels.&#13;
&#13;
2.        Situation Assessment ­ 1: WSS and Poverty Linkage&#13;
&#13;
Nature of Linkage between WSS and Poverty Reduction&#13;
&#13;
Sustainable improvement in water and sanitation conditions is essential to the poor to: i) reduce income&#13;
losses due to excessive time spent collecting water, ii) increase income earning potential through increase in&#13;
productivity, iii) reduce the cost of health services especially for water related diseases such as diarrhea, iv)&#13;
increase income from cattle that depend on water, and v) increase the quality of life of the poor through:&#13;
positive impacts on maternal and child health, improvements in education enrollment and attendance through&#13;
better school sanitation, reduced home duties for water collection or caring for siblings, especially for girls,&#13;
and reduced drudgery and time spent on collection of water, especially for women.&#13;
&#13;
Priorities Expressed by the Poor: The poor also accord priority to these activities in Ethiopia. The priority for&#13;
health among the poor also indirectly reflects the priority required for water and sanitation activities. A study&#13;
of the perceptions of the poor in Ethiopia, highlights the importance of water for the poor: lack of clean&#13;
water sources near their villages was a matter of deep concern among women in rural communities; women&#13;
carry water on their backs resulting in considerable drudgery; poor urban women stated absence of water and&#13;
sanitation as a key problem that results in worsening health conditions; lack of water was among the top five&#13;
priorities in all woredas and in urban sites, and sanitation was also ranked high.&#13;
&#13;
Status of Water Supply and Sanitation in Ethiopia&#13;
&#13;
As per official statistics, coverage of water and sanitation services in Ethiopia is very poor, among the lowest&#13;
in the world, especially for rural areas, where only 18 percent of population had access to safe water.&#13;
Conditions in urban areas are on paper better with 80 percent of population having access. However, even in&#13;
urban areas, most households have access only through common taps, consumption levels are low and&#13;
unscheduled disruptions in services are common. While Ethiopia fares poorly on most social indicators, its&#13;
performance on water and sanitation is particularly dismal, particularly in rural areas.&#13;
&#13;
Rural water supply in Ethiopia is provided mostly through point sources. Time and effort spent on fetching&#13;
water is a major concern among poor women in rural areas. Results from the 1998 welfare monitoring survey&#13;
suggest that a third of rural population has to walk more than one kilometer to fetch water. Another problem&#13;
is poor sustainability of sources in rural areas with an estimated 26 to 57 percent of the RWS schemes not&#13;
functioning. A key issue in urban areas is the poor reliability of supply, both in terms of quantity and&#13;
breakdowns, also highlighted vividly in consultations with the poor.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       iv&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                           WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
For sanitation, the available information suggests a better performance in urban area, whereas only 8 percent&#13;
of the rural population had access to sanitation facilities. Within the wider perspective of poverty reduction,&#13;
accrual of benefits through improved health, education and income will depend to a great extent on access to&#13;
wider environmental sanitation and hygiene awareness.&#13;
&#13;
3.      Situation Assessment ­ 2: Institutional and Financing Issues&#13;
&#13;
National Water Policy ­ key highlights&#13;
&#13;
Within the framework of the Constitution of the Federal Democratic Republic, the Ministry of Water&#13;
Resources has adopted a National Water Resources&#13;
&#13;
 Management Policy in 1999. One of its main objectives for the WSS sub-sector is to ensure that every&#13;
Ethiopian citizen has access to water of acceptable quality to satisfy the basic human needs. Key aspects of&#13;
the policy, which are important for the WSS sub-sector, include:&#13;
&#13;
        ·    Allocation of water resources: envisages high priority to water supply and sanitation for human,&#13;
             livestock and industrial needs for both economic and social benefits;&#13;
&#13;
        ·    Institutional framework for management: visualizes devolving ownership and management autonomy&#13;
             to the lowest possible level with a related emphasis on capacity building, and participation of all&#13;
             stakeholders, including the private sector;&#13;
&#13;
        ·    Financing, water pricing and cost recovery policies: envisages a move to full cost recovery for UWS and&#13;
             partial capital cost sharing and full O&amp;M cost recovery for RWS schemes;&#13;
&#13;
        ·    Technology and maintenance aspects: envisages development of appropriate technologies for local level&#13;
             development and management as well as meeting appropriate standards;&#13;
&#13;
        ·    Integrated water and sanitation policy: emphasizes the need for an integrated approach to water,&#13;
             sanitation and hygiene promotion.&#13;
&#13;
Institutional Arrangements within Decentralization&#13;
&#13;
Within the emerging framework of demand responsive approaches, the role of government is changing from&#13;
service provision to facilitating and providing an enabling environment. Within the decentralization&#13;
framework in Ethiopia, different responsibilities are emerging for different levels of government: policy and&#13;
strategy development, project implementation and monitoring and evaluation. At the federal level,&#13;
responsibility for the water sector is with the Ministry of Water Resources (MWR). Responsibility for&#13;
ensuring the provision of these services is with the regions and will be increasingly with woredas.&#13;
&#13;
At the regional level, Regional Water Bureaus (RWBs), along with their other responsibilities for water&#13;
resources, are also responsible for water and sanitation. In some of the larger regions, woreda water offices&#13;
with a small staff of two persons have been established. This trend to woreda level will be strengthened in the&#13;
coming years. Within the context of Ethiopia, NGOs have been an important player in the WSS sector. For&#13;
RWS schemes Ethiopia Social Rehabilitation and Development Fund (ESRDF) has also played a major role&#13;
in recent years.&#13;
&#13;
With the government moving away from direct service provision, notion of service providers for WSS&#13;
services becomes important. In Ethiopia, a number of different forms of service providers exist with&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            v&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                       WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
considerable inter and even intra-regional variations, including: Addis Ababa Water and Sewerage Authority&#13;
(AAWSA), Urban / Town Water Service Unit (TWSU), some Scheme Water Boards (SWB) and at the very&#13;
local level Water Board (WB) and Village Water and Sanitation Committee (VWSC). There has been limited&#13;
involvement of the private sector to date, though there is an emerging interest.&#13;
&#13;
Sector Financing and Flow of Funds&#13;
&#13;
Though the National Water Policy envisages financing from domestic financial institutions, so far sector&#13;
financing has been largely through: budgetary allocations, external debt or grants from bilateral donors and&#13;
international NGOs sometimes provided either directly to communities or local levels of government, and&#13;
more recently other off-budget mechanisms such as ESRDF. MWR also proposes to establish a water&#13;
resource development fund (WRDF). It is envisaged that the WRDF will pool the government and donor&#13;
resources and channel these in line with the overall sector policy. In the longer term it is visualized that&#13;
WRDF will also mobilize additional resources.&#13;
&#13;
With decentralization, a large share of federal resources is transferred to regional governments, and regional&#13;
and woreda governments allocate funds for the WSS sector from their own budgets. However, an effective&#13;
decentralization process is constrained by: the lack of medium term federal subsidy estimates and donor&#13;
practices that inhibit multi-year planning. WSS allocations within this emerging decentralization framework&#13;
depend on the planning process at these levels and the issue of relative preparedness of the WSS sector at this&#13;
level will be an important determinant.&#13;
&#13;
Based on available information, preliminary and indicative estimates suggest that the current level of funding&#13;
allocation to the sector is about 34 million US $ per annum. Clearly, to achieve improvements in poverty&#13;
reduction, water supply and sanitation deserves an equal attention as other sectors such as education, health&#13;
and roads. However, WSS allocations do not compare favorably with these sectors. This more likely reflects a&#13;
lack of sector readiness to absorb larger resources rather than a low priority for water supply and sanitation.&#13;
The priority actions and programs within the sector will have to focus on strengthening overall sector&#13;
capacity along with specific investment strategies linked to coverage targets.&#13;
&#13;
Key Sector Issues and Potential Measures:&#13;
&#13;
Institutional roles, forms and capacity: Clarity is required in appropriate roles, related forms and capacity of&#13;
different entities within the decentralization framework. A critical issue is the notion of a service provider,&#13;
their legal basis with the necessary powers, and their links with the appropriate government units. Key aspects&#13;
to be addressed are: a) defining institutional models and strengthening capacity of service providers, b)&#13;
strengthening sector monitoring and regulation, and c) developing and implementing a sector information&#13;
management system (SIMS) linked to planning and monitoring&#13;
&#13;
Poor sustainability of investments: Measures to enhance sustainability of RWS schemes include: a) emphasis on&#13;
promotion and participatory and informed demand articulation during the planning stage to improve&#13;
technology choices, b) improved collection of user fees, c) development of supply chains (in relation to&#13;
technology choices) that makes access to spare parts easier and cost effective, d) technical support to VWSC&#13;
and WBs, and e) access to credit for bridge finance for sudden or major repairs and augmentation; and&#13;
measures for UWS schemes include: a) implementation of tariff setting based on full cost recovery, b)&#13;
development of guidelines for urban tariff setting including issues related affordability and financial&#13;
sustainability, c) institutional incentives for urban WSPs to achieve financial viability, d) strengthening&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        vi&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                        WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
technical and financial capacity of the urban service providers to improve operational efficiency and reduce&#13;
unaccounted for water (UFW), and e) introduction of consumer services.&#13;
&#13;
Private sector capacity: Capacity of private sector is poor, and a detailed assessment is necessary to identify&#13;
capacity strengthening measures with an emphasis on local and small scale operators. Possible measures to&#13;
provide incentives for contracting the private sector as well as building their capacity are necessary.&#13;
&#13;
Neglect of sanitation and hygiene: While integration of sanitation and hygiene with water schemes is mentioned in&#13;
the Water Policy, institutional responsibilities are currently with the Health sector. Resolution of institutional&#13;
and financial responsibilities requires a critical emphasis.&#13;
&#13;
Clarifying financing rules to align with WSS policy and priorities: While developing the detailed financing strategy,&#13;
rules for allocation of and access to public finance will need to be developed to address these sector issues.&#13;
Some principles that need to be considered are: a) principle of capital subsidies for rural water: with a move&#13;
to a ceiling on per capita subsidy linked to the notion of basic service levels, b) within urban water the need to&#13;
reconsider the large capital subsidies to urban water suppliers and move to appropriate subsidy measures to&#13;
enhance access for the urban poor to improved services and sustainable measures to enhance financial /&#13;
commercial viability of urban water service providers (UWSUs), c) adequate financial provision for sanitation&#13;
and hygiene promotion, d) adequate share of management (software) support in project costs, and e)&#13;
adequate share of sector strengthening and capacity building in total investments.&#13;
&#13;
Linking public finance to results: Within the HIPC and PRSP framework, it is important to shift the traditional&#13;
emphasis of public finance on inputs to `results' and from `controls' on inputs to achieving the agreed targets&#13;
for welfare improvement. In WSS sector this is of great importance, as often in the past, issues related to&#13;
sustainability of capital investments were not addressed leading to poor results even though the input and&#13;
output targets were reached.&#13;
&#13;
Approach to operationalization of WSS component in WSDP&#13;
&#13;
Following the adoption of National Water Policy, MWR has developed a national water strategy and is&#13;
currently finalizing the Water Sector Development program (WSDP) through a consultative process. The&#13;
WSDP preparation process has identified a detailed list of sub-projects through extensive regional&#13;
consultations. Based on a preliminary review of the SDPs for education, health and roads sectors,&#13;
operationalizing the WSS component of the WSDP will require further development of:&#13;
&#13;
·   an action plan with measures to address institutional and financing issues within the WSS sub-sector,&#13;
&#13;
·   model implementation guidelines with details of financing principles, funding and procurement&#13;
    modalities and monitoring arrangements, and appropriately adapted by each region, and&#13;
&#13;
·   a detailed annual and periodic review process with adequate stakeholder consultation, a process of donor&#13;
    dialogue as has been developed for other sectors and linked with planning and budgeting cycle and&#13;
    medium term expenditure framework (MTEF).&#13;
&#13;
4.        Priorities for Poverty Reduction: Action Plans, Targets and Expenditure&#13;
          Requirements&#13;
&#13;
The water sector development program has identified direct investment requirements for water and sewerage&#13;
projects in relation to region-wise targets for improved coverage for access to `safe' water for a 15-year time&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         vii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                      WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
frame. It has also identified an institutional component for the overall program including both human&#13;
resource development plans and institutional strengthening programs.&#13;
&#13;
WSS Sub-sector Priorities for Poverty Reduction:&#13;
&#13;
Issue of poor sector capacity and low levels of expenditures for WSS are interlinked and lead to a vicious&#13;
circle ­ as low levels of investments create low demand for technical and manpower inputs in WSS sector and&#13;
thus capacity remains underdeveloped. The resulting low sector capacity, means low allocations and&#13;
expenditures are further curtailed. The action plans for WSS will need to be developed to break this vicious&#13;
circle through simultaneous development of overall sector capacity and gradual increases in investments for&#13;
improved services for the poor in rural and urban areas. The three priority areas of focus for PRSP within the&#13;
WSS sub-sector are:&#13;
&#13;
·    Sector Strengthening: to enhance and strengthen overall sector capacity&#13;
&#13;
·    Rural Water Supply and Sanitation: to enhance the access to safe water, sanitation and hygiene, and&#13;
&#13;
·    Urban Water Supply and Sanitation: to enhance access of the urban poor to improved water supply,&#13;
     sanitation and hygiene promotion&#13;
&#13;
Outcome linked Action Plans for the Institutional Component:&#13;
&#13;
The WSDP has also identified an institutional component for the water sector as a whole with an allocation&#13;
of about 65 million $ during the first five year phase. While this component is common to all water sub-&#13;
sectors, a part of this allocation would be for the WSS sub-sector that has a much larger share (46 percent) of&#13;
envisaged investments. To support the PRSP priorities in the WSS sector within this overall institutional&#13;
component, outcome linked action plans need to be identified. To meet this need, within each of the three&#13;
PRSP priority areas for WSS sub-sector, key issues, related action plans over a three-year period and related&#13;
outcomes to be achieved have been identified. These include:&#13;
&#13;
·    Sector Strengthening:&#13;
&#13;
         o development of: a financing strategy, and&#13;
&#13;
         o development of a sector information and M&amp;E systems&#13;
&#13;
·    Rural Water Supply and Sanitation:&#13;
&#13;
         o strengthening WBs and VWCs,&#13;
&#13;
         o development of a maintenance strategy,&#13;
&#13;
         o improved integration of sanitation and hygiene promotion&#13;
&#13;
         o development of a strategy for effective supply chains&#13;
&#13;
         o investment strategy for new RWS schemes to achieve agreed targets&#13;
&#13;
·    Urban Water Supply and Sanitation:&#13;
&#13;
         o financially sustainable urban water service providers,&#13;
&#13;
         o assessment and implementation of measures to enhance access of the poor to WSS services,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       viii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                        WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         o independent framework for economic regulation for urban water supply starting with&#13;
              comparative performance assessment of UWS service providers, and&#13;
&#13;
         o investment strategy for new/augmentation of UWS schemes to achieve agreed targets&#13;
&#13;
Detailed costing for these actions plans within the institutional component will need to be developed later.&#13;
&#13;
Coverage Targets and Investment Requirements:&#13;
&#13;
As a part of the ongoing preparation of WSDP region-wise targets for enhanced coverage of water in rural&#13;
and urban areas, and urban sewerage, as well as total resource requirements based on these targets and&#13;
projects have been identified. The targets for access to `safe' water during the short-term five-year period are:&#13;
88 percent in urban and 37 percent in rural areas respectively by 2006. The total requirements during the first&#13;
phase to achieve the targets are estimated to be 742 million $, or about 150 million $ per annum. Similar long-&#13;
term investment assessments have also been made under the WSS master plan being prepared under the&#13;
Environment Support project (ESP). Though this estimation uses a different approach focusing on the&#13;
technology choices and household affordability considerations, the overall investment requirements are in the&#13;
same broad range.&#13;
&#13;
Based on preliminary estimates of past allocations to the WSS sector, these requirements are about 5 times&#13;
the current level of allocations for the sector. PRSP linked priorities discussed above would suggest a greater&#13;
focus on rural areas and on access for the poor within urban areas. Further priorities may also suggest that&#13;
greater attention is needed on the needs of pastoral communities. MWR is currently engaged in exploring&#13;
different priority scenarios within these overall estimates to align more closely with the possible resource&#13;
envelope for the water sector.&#13;
&#13;
Such scenario assessments would need to include aspects such as: priorities across different sub-sectors&#13;
(particularly rural areas and a focus on the urban poor), appropriate technology choices and financing / cost&#13;
recovery rules (as discussed above). It developing these estimates, it would also be necessary to include&#13;
adequate provision for project development / management costs, including the `software' costs of social&#13;
mobilization and community support.&#13;
&#13;
Discussion of investment requirements also needs to take into account the offset approach used for federal&#13;
subsidy allocations to regions, as an increase in regional WSS allocations would be done by reducing other&#13;
investments, unless there is a significant increase in availability of total resources. At present to overcome this&#13;
issue, off-budget mechanisms such as ESRDF or the proposed Water Resources Development Fund, are&#13;
being used. Another preferred option of the Government is to use the `third channel' of direct grant funding&#13;
by bilateral agencies or NGOs.&#13;
&#13;
5.       Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
A clear shift is required within the PRSP framework and WSDP approach from an input based to anoutcome&#13;
linked expenditure strategy. To make this effective, a shift is required from the project linked M&amp;E systems&#13;
that have been common in the WSS sector, to a sector-wide M&amp;E. A strong M&amp;E system that is&#13;
participatory and linked to the overall sector strategy as well as a strong SIMS will enable better program&#13;
planning along with accountability of those implementing programs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         ix&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                  WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Current sector capacity for M&amp;E seems to be very weak, though one or two regions have developed input&#13;
and output monitoring systems in a systematic manner. These existing efforts will need to be assessed to&#13;
develop proposals for SIMS and related institutional responsibilities. MWR, through its planning department&#13;
will take the lead in designing and coordinating the development of SIMS and a full M&amp;E system. It would be&#13;
important to ensure adequate resources allocation for this and develop strong incentives for different actors&#13;
to collect, analyze and use the information effectively and systematically.&#13;
&#13;
Based on the PRSP linked proposals, indicators have been identified to reflect the outcomes related to&#13;
achieving better access to improved water and sanitation for the poor in Ethiopia. These will need to be&#13;
developed consultatively with different stakeholders. Appropriate details related to disaggregation of&#13;
information and frequency of monitoring will also need to be identified. Additional indicators linked to the&#13;
inputs and outputs in the sector will also be developed further within the sector M&amp;E strategy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   x&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                     WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.       Introduction&#13;
&#13;
Government of Ethiopia completed its Interim PRSP in November 2000. It is currently engaged in the&#13;
process of preparing the full PRSP based on an Action Plan, detailing the process of consultation and&#13;
technical preparation. GOE has formed two committees for overseeing and managing the PRSP preparation&#13;
process: federal steering committee and federal technical committee (FTC). Similar committees have also&#13;
been formed in each region. In accordance with the Action Plan, GOE has initiated consultations with a&#13;
number of different stakeholders at federal, regional and district (woreda) levels. These consultations focus on&#13;
understanding local problems and are to be completed by end December 2001. Further consultations at the&#13;
federal level are planned with other stakeholders and development partners. Detailed poverty analysis and&#13;
diagnostic are being undertaken through the Central Statistical Authority and Welfare Monitoring Unit in the&#13;
Ministry of Finance and Economic Development. The federal technical committee (FTC) will develop a&#13;
framework for the full PRSP and expects to initiate drafting of the full PRSP from February 2002.&#13;
&#13;
Water has been recognized as a priority area within the PRSP process and Ministry of Water Resources&#13;
(MWR) will have representation in these committees at both federal and regional levels. It is in this&#13;
background that the MWR has requested WSP-AF assistance in developing the background materials for&#13;
preparation of the WSS inputs for the full PRSP. This report has been prepared in response to this request,&#13;
based on discussions with various stakeholders and a synthesis of available studies and consultant reports. It&#13;
also draws on reports and proceedings of a number of consultations that the MWR has had with different&#13;
stakeholders at federal and regional levels.&#13;
&#13;
2.       Situation Assessment ­ 1: WSS and Poverty Linkage&#13;
&#13;
2.1      Nature of Linkage between WSS and Poverty Reduction&#13;
&#13;
Sustainable improvement in water and sanitation conditions is essential to the poor to: i) reduce income&#13;
losses due to excessive time spent collecting water, ii) increase income earning potential through increase in&#13;
productivity, iii) reduce the cost of health services especially for water related diseases such as diarrhea, iv)&#13;
increase income from cattle that depend on water, and v) increase the quality of life of the poor through:&#13;
positive impacts on maternal and child health, improvements in education enrollment and attendance through&#13;
better school sanitation, reduced home duties for water collection or caring for siblings, especially for girls,&#13;
and reduced drudgery and time on collection of water, especially for women.&#13;
&#13;
2.2      Priorities Expressed by the Poor&#13;
&#13;
These inks also underlie the priority generally accorded by the poor to these activities in Ethiopia. The&#13;
        l&#13;
priority for health among the poor also indirectly reflects the priority required for water and sanitation&#13;
activities. A study based on consultations with the poor in 1999 highlighted the importance of access to water&#13;
and sanitation as expressed by the poor themselves. Among the rural communities, drought was identified as&#13;
the most important factor that causes poverty, and an important impact of drought was stated to be: "rivers&#13;
dry up and women have to travel for hours to get a pot of water; cattle die due to the lack of water; and&#13;
backyard gardens that had been a major source of food security for many become useless". Lack of clean&#13;
water sources anywhere near their villages was a matter of deep concern among women in rural communities,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
as a result of which their "valuable time is spent on fetching water from distances that could easily take them&#13;
more than two hours one way".&#13;
&#13;
Women carry water on their backs resulting in considerable drudgery. Among the groups of poor women in&#13;
urban areas, absence of water and sanitation was stated as an important problem that results in worsening&#13;
health conditions. Lack of water was among the top five priorities in all woredas and in urban sites, sanitation&#13;
was also ranked high.1 Consultations at woreda and regional are being conducted at present. Their results as&#13;
and when available need to be assessed for possible WSS priorities.&#13;
&#13;
The priority for water perceived by the poor is also reflected in the operation of Ethiopian Social&#13;
Rehabilitation and Development Fund (ESRDF) that finances activities in different sectors on a demand&#13;
responsive basis. Among the applications received by ESRDF over the past five years, more than 50 percent&#13;
were for rural water supply related sub-projects2.&#13;
&#13;
2.3         Status of Water Supply and Sanitation in Ethiopia&#13;
&#13;
Ethiopia's comparative performance: As per official statistics, coverage of water and sanitation services in Ethiopia&#13;
is very poor, among the lowest in the world, especially for rural areas. Among the key indicators for&#13;
International Development Goals, Ethiopia's performance on `sustained' access to safe water sources and&#13;
sanitation services is one of the worst in the region. Further, the poor performance on the child and maternal&#13;
health indicators may at least partially be due to poor water and sanitation in Ethiopia. Thus, while Ethiopia&#13;
fares poorly on most social indicators, its performance on water and sanitation is particularly dismal (refer to&#13;
Table 1).&#13;
&#13;
                  Table 1: Performance of Countries in Sub-Saharan Africa on Selected Social Indicators&#13;
&#13;
  Country         Access to Safe Water   Access to        Adult Illiteracy    Net     Malnu    Infant     Under-5      Maternal&#13;
                  Urban       Rural     Sanitation        Male       Fem.  Enrollment trition Mortality  mortality     Mortality&#13;
                                                                            Primary            Rate                      Rate&#13;
 Benin              41           53          20             62        46      63        29           87     140          500&#13;
 Burkina F                                   18             78        68      31        33         104      210          930&#13;
 Ethiopia           90           18           8             64        58      32        48         107      173          1400&#13;
 Kenya              67           49          77             20        12      65        23           76     124          590&#13;
 Malawi             52           44          53             42        27      103       20         134      229          620&#13;
 Mozambiq.          17           40          21             58        42      40        26         134      213          1500&#13;
 Rwanda                         44*          na             36        29      Na        29         123      205          1300&#13;
 Tanzania           65           45          86             26        17      48        31           85     136          530&#13;
 Uganda             47           32          57             35        24      Na        26         101      170          510&#13;
 Zambia             64           27          23             24        16      75        24         114      192          650&#13;
 SSA                na           na          na             32        32      55        33           92     151          778&#13;
Notes and sources:    Refer to Annex 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall changes in WSS status over time: Even this low status represents an improvement over the past five years.&#13;
Particularly, access to rural water supply increased by almost 24 percent. For urban areas, which have a&#13;
relatively much better level of access, the increase was less. The low coverage probably reflects centralized&#13;
institutional arrangements in the past, low allocations and expensive technology choices and a greater focus&#13;
on urban services. For sanitation, the available information again suggests a better performance in urban&#13;
whereas only 8 percent of the rural population had access to sanitation facilities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1Rahmato and Kidanu, 1999, PP. 70, 71 and tables 4.1 to 4.3.&#13;
2Sima (2001).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                 2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                      WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Rural water supply status ­ regional variations: Rural water supply in Ethiopia is provided mostly through point&#13;
sources. However, there are significant variations across regions with regions such as Dire Dawa and Somali&#13;
in particular relying more on larger systems with distribution network (refer to Table 3). On the other hand,&#13;
Harari region has a high level of access to safe sources mainly though point sources. There variations need to&#13;
be understood better as they would have considerable impact on investment and O&amp;M costs as well as long-&#13;
term sustainability.&#13;
&#13;
Time spent on water collection: As evident from the consultations with the poor, time and effort spent by women&#13;
on fetching water is a major concern among poor women in rural areas. The limited information available&#13;
from the 1998 welfare monitoring survey (WMS) suggests that a third of rural population has to walk more&#13;
than one kilometer to fetch water3.&#13;
&#13;
                                 Table 2: Coverage for Water Supply and Sanitation in Ethiopia&#13;
&#13;
    Region             Percent of population with access to a "safe" source of                                 Percent of population with access&#13;
                                                            water                                                        to sanitary facilities&#13;
                                         1994                                       1998                                            1994&#13;
                       Rural              Urban          Total     Rural         Urban           Total           Rural           Urban               Total&#13;
 Addis Ababa             35.6               98.4          98.0       54.6          98.8                           5.0              75.0               74.0&#13;
 Dire Dawa               23.6               98.1          78.0       84.8          99.6                           3.0              75.0               55.0&#13;
 Harari                  11.2               98.2          63.0       37.7          97.3                           1.0              69.0               42.0&#13;
 Gambella                21.3               72.4          26.0       21.1          62.4                          11.0              31.0               15.0&#13;
 Benishangul             14.8               55.0          18.0       14.1          61.0                          15.0              63.0               19.0&#13;
 Gumuz&#13;
 Tigary                  10.6               73.9          21.0       19.2          96.4                           3.0              29.0                7.0&#13;
 SNNPRS                  15.5               71.1          19.0       21.4          73.8                           9.0              63.0               13.0&#13;
 Amhara                  15.2               80.2          21.0       13.0          85.0                           3.0              37.0                6.0&#13;
 Oromiya                 15.8               76.2          22.0       20.0          85.8                           7.0              59.0               13.0&#13;
 Somali                   9.0               47.9          15.0       34.9          98.8                           4.0              48.0               11.0&#13;
 Affar                    5.2               73.1          13.0       16.2          83.0                           4.0              37.0                8.0&#13;
 Total                   14.8               81.0          23.8       18.3          86.0          28.3             6.0              57.0               13.0&#13;
Source:   For water: ESP (2001), Volume III Table A5.2.1 to A5.2.33, ESP(2001), Volume I,Table 4.2. original sources are CSA (1994) and&#13;
         CSA (1998).&#13;
         For sanitation: ESP (2001), Volume II, Tables 2.3 and 2.4, original source is CSA (1994) and CSA (1998).&#13;
Notes:   For water: Definition of safe for 1994 includes: all protected springs and wells, yard or shared taps and taps in the house.&#13;
         For 1998, safe includes: own tap, public tap, protected springs and wells, as well as `others' as it seems to include shared taps (ESP, 2001). For&#13;
         sanitation, facility refers to a sanitary latrine.&#13;
         Details for the region totals for water supply are not available due to the adjustments made in `safe' source. Region-wise details for sanitation for&#13;
         1998 are also not available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Definition of a `safe' source: A key issue in the choice of source and technology is the definition of a `safe' source.&#13;
Most surveys and statistics define traditional sources as being unsafe and only either piped systems or&#13;
`protected' springs and wells are considered as safe. It may be good to review this definition as emphasized by&#13;
ESP (2001). It is possible that the traditional source is safe and the input required is in the handling of water&#13;
while collecting and transporting. Publicly provided `safe' water on the other hand will not result in desired&#13;
health benefits if issues of handling during collection and transportation are not adequately addressed.&#13;
Selection of the source and level of service will also need to address the issues of `adequate' consumption&#13;
levels and the time that the users need to spend in collecting water.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3ESP (2001), Volume II, Table 1.10, original source CSA (1998).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                          WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   Table 3: Regional Variations in Source of Water Used for Rural Water Supply, 1998&#13;
&#13;
          Region                                                Percent of population using the source&#13;
                                                    Point sources                         Distribution                  Total&#13;
                                  Protected        Unprotected             Rivers,         Network                "Safe" Sources&#13;
                                                                          Lakes, etc.&#13;
Addis Ababa                           10.1               32.2               49.5               8.2                        18.3&#13;
Dire Dawa                              5.8               10.9               34.5               48.8                       54.6&#13;
Harari                                43.9               15.2               20.0               20.9                       64.8&#13;
Gambella                              19.8                3.8               75.2               1.2                        21.0&#13;
Benishangul Gumuz                      7.4               25.5               60.4               6.7                        14.1&#13;
Tigary                                11.1               33.1               47.8               8.0                        19.1&#13;
SNNPRS                                10.5               26.4               52.2               10.9                       21.4&#13;
Amhara                                 9.7               38.2               48.8               3.3                        13.0&#13;
Oromiya                               10.2               30.8               49.2               9.8                        20.0&#13;
Somali                                 2.0               47.1               18.0               32.9                       34.9&#13;
Affar                                  5.1               24.1               59.7               11.1                       16.2&#13;
Total Rural                           10.1               32.2               49.5               8.2                        18.3&#13;
Source: Based on ESP (2001), Volume III, Table A5.2.2. Original source of information is CSA (1998).&#13;
Note: See the notes for Table 2..&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sustainability of RWS schemes: Inappropriate choice of technology is also reflected in poor sustainability of&#13;
sources in rural areas. While monitoring of sustainability is not regular, a 1996 survey by MWR4 suggests that&#13;
26 percent of the RWS schemes were not functioning. There was a greater propensity for the hand-pumps&#13;
and boreholes to have problems as compared to capped springs. Surprisingly, however, the capped springs&#13;
fared worse in Amhara and Tigary regions. Of the seven regions surveyed, conditions were the worst in&#13;
Benishangul and Gembela regions. A later survey in Amhara region, however, found the situation worse with&#13;
57 percent of the schemes being non-functional5. An inventory of 700 completed RWS schemes supported&#13;
by the Ethiopian Social Reconstruction and Development Fund (ESRDF) also showed that about 33 percent&#13;
were not functioning6. It is likely that with the sustainability problems, the actual status of access to safe water&#13;
is even worse than information reported above.&#13;
&#13;
Variations across urban areas: Based on the official statistics, condition with respect to access to safe water in&#13;
urban areas is higher in terms of coverage, with about 84 percent having access to safe water sources, though&#13;
there are some variations across different town size classes. This needs to be, however, treated with caution as&#13;
most households rely on shared services, consumption levels are very low, seasonal variability is very high and&#13;
unscheduled disruptions to services are very common. Smaller towns with less than 2000 population have&#13;
access levels of only 40 percent and those with less than 10000 population have a level of around 60 percent.&#13;
Interestingly, except for the very small `towns' with less than 2000 population, most other towns have some&#13;
form of piped systems, and access to piped systems is over 75 percent in towns with more than 10,000&#13;
population. Outside of Addis Ababa, three categories of towns may be distinguished:&#13;
&#13;
·    Rural towns: Towns with less than 2000 population where 60 percent of towns have piped system, but&#13;
     coverage levels in terms of population with access to piped system is low at about 20 percent;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4Survey was done by MWR in 1996, and analyzed by consultants Ernst and Young in 1997, as reported in ESP (2001), Volume II, pp. 21-22.&#13;
5Sahle and associates (1999), as reported in ESP (2001), Volume II, p. 22.&#13;
6Based on information from Sima (2001).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                    WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
·      Small towns: Towns with 2 to 10000 population that mostly have piped systems but the access to piped&#13;
       system is only about 50 percent; and&#13;
&#13;
·      Medium and large towns: Medium and large towns, which all have piped systems but do require some&#13;
       improvement in access. Even among these towns `access' is largely confined to yard taps or shared&#13;
       connections, with the resultant implications for cost recovery and financial viability.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Table 4: Water Supply Status in Urban Areas, 1994&#13;
&#13;
           Population size                             Total           Number            % of towns                   Percent of housing units with&#13;
                of towns                         Population                of            with piped           Individual              Piped                  "Safe"&#13;
                                                   (in '000s)           towns               system           connections             Supply                   water&#13;
           Less than 2,000                                     349              282           58                     2                   22                      43&#13;
                2 ­ 5,000                                    1093               338           90                     3                   43                      61&#13;
               5 - 10,000                                    1077               153           98                     5                   55                      69&#13;
              10 - 20,000                                    1192                 85          100                   10                   73                      82&#13;
              20 - 30,000                                      754                30          100                   13                   74                      83&#13;
              30 - 80,000                                    1176                 26          100                   16                   76                      84&#13;
             80 ­ 250,000                                    1334                 10          100                   19                   89                      94&#13;
             Addis Ababa                                     2495                   1         100                   27                   98                      98&#13;
             Total Urban                                     9470               925           83                    15                   76                      84&#13;
Source: Adapted from ESP (2001), Volume II, Annex II-1.2, Original source ­ CSA (1994), Census&#13;
Note: While the MWR uses a population of more than 2500 to define urban centers, available information based on the census uses more than 2000 as the population size for&#13;
defining urban settlements. The census also classifies about 282 settlements with less than 2000 population as urban. These have been referred as Rural towns in this report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Defining `urban': The above analysis uses the Census definition for distinguishing urban areas. However, in the&#13;
WSS sector operations, the very small settlements defined as `urban' by the census are not considered urban.&#13;
This analysis, however, helps to highlight the special circumstances of these small `towns' that often have&#13;
piped water schemes that are different than the prevalent point sources in rural areas. This aspect may need&#13;
further attention due to the different financial and institutional arrangements proposed for rural and urban&#13;
areas as per the national Water policy and strategy7.&#13;
&#13;
Service reliability: Another key issue in urban areas is the reliability of supply. Consultations with the poor also&#13;
highlighted this aspect vividly. Limited available information suggests that reliability of supply is likely to be&#13;
quite poor, both in terms of quantity and breakdowns8.&#13;
&#13;
Access for the poor: On the whole, relative level of access to water and sanitation in urban areas is estimated to&#13;
be high in Ethiopia. However, in some the larger urban centers, the poor may lack access. In future a more&#13;
detailed assessment of the access to these services by the poor through special studies is necessary. These&#13;
need to focus on their level of access, existing sources/ services used, level of current expenditure, and nature&#13;
of demand and willingness to pay for services. Other related studies to assess the existence of small-scale&#13;
service providers who cater to the urban poor may also be needed.&#13;
&#13;
Sanitation and hygiene practices: Available information suggests that access to sanitation facilities is very poor in&#13;
rural areas. Within the wider perspective of poverty reduction, accrual of benefits through improved health,&#13;
education and income will depend to a great extent on access to wider environmental sanitation and hygiene&#13;
awareness. Unfortunately, information on their current status is not readily available. Focus on these in&#13;
further poverty related monitoring is necessary.&#13;
&#13;
7See the discussion on this issue in ESP (2001), Volume II, section 1.2.2. This is also discussed further below in sections 2.1, 2.3 and 2.4.&#13;
8ESP (2001), Volume II, section 1.2.2, based on original information from MWR (1997), a report by Ernst and Young /Tropics.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                              5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                             WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.        Situation Assessment ­ 2: Institutional and Financing Issues&#13;
&#13;
3.1       National Water Policy ­ key highlights&#13;
&#13;
Within the framework of the Constitution of the Federal Democratic Republic, the Ministry of Water&#13;
Resources has adopted a National Water Resources Management Policy in 19999. Its overall goal is to&#13;
enhance and promote "efficient, equitable and optimum utilization of water resources" for sustainable socio-&#13;
economic development. It recognizes water as an economic good and encompasses water supply and&#13;
sanitation (WSS), irrigation and hydropower sub sectors. One of its main objectives for the WSS sub-sector is&#13;
to ensure that every Ethiopian citizen has access to water of acceptable quality to satisfy the basic human&#13;
needs. The policy provides a guiding framework within which more detailed sub-sector strategies and&#13;
institutional reforms will need to be developed. Key aspects of the policy, which are important for the WSS&#13;
sub-sector, are:&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Allocation of water resources: gives high priority to water supply and sanitation for human, livestock&#13;
                and industrial needs. It recognizes that the allocation needs to be based on both economic and&#13;
                social benefits;&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Institutional framework for management: visualizes devolving ownership and management autonomy&#13;
                to the lowest possible level within the emerging decentralization framework, effective&#13;
                coordination mechanisms for collaboration among different stakeholders, and related emphasis&#13;
                on capacity building;&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Financing, water pricing and cost recovery policies: envisages a move towards full cost recovery for urban&#13;
                water supply and partial capital cost sharing and full O&amp;M cost recovery for rural water supply&#13;
                schemes as well as promotion of domestic commercial and micro-finance institutions in&#13;
                financing water investments;&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Technology and maintenance aspects: envisages development of appropriate technologies for local level&#13;
                development and management as well as meeting appropriate standards;&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Integrated water and sanitation policy: puts an emphasis on the need for an integrated approach to&#13;
                water and sanitation, and a clear identification of responsibilities of government and other&#13;
                stakeholders for sanitation and hygiene promotion.&#13;
&#13;
MWR has prepared a national water strategy to articulate implementation of the Water Policy. Some regions&#13;
plan to adapt the strategies to address the regional context. Detailed implementation guidelines are also&#13;
planned to be developed first at the federal and later in each region.&#13;
&#13;
3.2       Institutional Arrangements within Decentralization Framework&#13;
&#13;
Within the emerging framework of demand responsive approaches, the role of government is gradually&#13;
changing from service provision to being a facilitator and providing an enabling environment. Actual service&#13;
provision is with different service providers in rural and urban areas.&#13;
&#13;
Role of Government, NGOs and the Private Sector: Within the decentralization framework in Ethiopia, different&#13;
responsibilities are emerging for different levels of government, ranging from policy and strategy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9Ministry of Water Resources (1999).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                           WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
development, to project implementation and effective monitoring and evaluation. Within the context of&#13;
Ethiopia, NGOs are an important player in the WSS sector.&#13;
&#13;
Federal Government (MWR): At the federal level, responsibility for policy and strategy development for the&#13;
water sector is with the Ministry of Water Resources (MWR). It also coordinates with external agencies for&#13;
financing the sector investments. MWR is responsible for developing the Sector Development Program for&#13;
WSS sector for Ethiopia. With the enhanced role of regional government, role of MWR is also to ensure&#13;
effective monitoring and evaluation and provide capacity building support. With the envisaged policy&#13;
emphasis on appropriate pricing in urban areas the federal government will also need to explore the&#13;
possibility of an independent framework for economic regulation in the sector10.&#13;
&#13;
Regional and Woreda Governments: Under the emerging decentralization framework, responsibility for ensuring&#13;
the provision of these services will be increasingly with the regions and woredas (districts). The Regional&#13;
Water Bureaus11, along with their other responsibilities for water resources, are responsible for water and&#13;
sanitation at the regional level. At the zonal level there are Water Departments, which were established in&#13;
1996 to support development, implementation and regulation of WSS activities. Zonal level essentially&#13;
represents a deconcentration of administration. Gradually, with recent developments, the emphasis is shifting&#13;
from the zone to transferring responsibilities to the woreda level. In some of the larger regions, Amhara,&#13;
Tigray, Oromiya and SNNPR, woreda water offices, with a small staff of two persons have been established.&#13;
Cooperation with woreda education and health offices, especially for sanitation, hygiene promotion and small&#13;
water schemes, needs to be explored.12&#13;
&#13;
Ethiopia Social Rehabilitation and Development Fund (ESRDF): Government of Ethiopia established ESRDF in&#13;
1996 to fund demand driven small community sub-projects on a grant basis. Its proposed portfolio included&#13;
rural water supply and sanitation with a focus on simple technologies that would be cost-effective and be easy&#13;
for community management. ESRDF has attempted to follow the principles of demand responsive approach&#13;
by ensuring community participation in demand expression, community share of at least 10 percent in capital&#13;
costs and complete community responsibility for O&amp;M. Over the past 5 years, it has funded nearly 2000&#13;
small schemes serving an estimated 2 million population. Its approach has demonstrated the possibility of&#13;
using the DRA in practice, and is likely to have influenced the development of national water policy. Over the&#13;
years, in some regions, there has been a trend to have a larger proportion of larger and more complex&#13;
schemes. In future operation, further attention may, however, be required for: strengthening support to&#13;
communities during planning of sub-projects, better integration of the sanitation and hygiene components,&#13;
ensure supply chains for more effective maintenance and closer links with the sector institutions at the region,&#13;
zone and woreda levels.&#13;
&#13;
Non-Governmental Organizations: NGOs are an important actor in the WSS sector in Ethiopia, with about 125&#13;
active NGOs in 1994; with some presence in all the regions, though a few large ones dominate. Almost all are&#13;
externally funded and provide both technical and funding support in the sector. Funding by NGOs may be&#13;
an important source, though recent details of its extent are not available. While NGOs need to register with&#13;
the Ministry of Justice and their projects are reviewed at the regional level, issues of coordination and varying&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10Economic regulation would enable moving towards a pricing structure that ensures financial viability of service providers while ensuring that&#13;
consumer access is enhanced within affordability constraints.&#13;
11There are variations across regions ranging from an independent Regional Water Bureau (RWB) in some to a Regional Bureau for Water, Energy&#13;
and Mines in others. The scope of even a RWB also includes small-scale irrigation besides WSS.&#13;
12Under the model schemes being taken up by the ESRDF, such links have already been established in some regions.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                               7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                          WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
approaches used by different NGOs may of concern. Some efforts at national level coordination have been&#13;
initiated by the MWR13.&#13;
&#13;
Private Sector: Private sector in Ethiopia is in a nascent stage and mainly involved in consultancy and&#13;
construction sector. To a large extent this reflects a lack of demand during the past two decades, though&#13;
during the nineties efforts have been made to promote private sector. Considerable efforts and capacity&#13;
building support, along with a better development of opportunities to nurture demand for private sector&#13;
services, will be needed in the coming years. A detailed assessment of nature of support measures and&#13;
capacity building requirements is essential. An assessment of small-scale providers and operators in the&#13;
informal sector would also be useful.&#13;
&#13;
WSS Service Providers (WSP): With the government moving away from direct service provision, notion of&#13;
service providers for water and sanitation services becomes important. In Ethiopia, a number of different&#13;
forms of service providers exist with considerable inter and even intra-regional variations. In most cases,&#13;
however, there seems to be a separate `entity' that is recognized as a service provider. Table 5 highlights the&#13;
different forms of service providers in relation to different settlement contexts. Some of the prevailing&#13;
institutional arrangements for water service providers are:&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Addis Ababa Water and Sewerage Authority (AAWSA): is a chartered public authority with an&#13;
                independent board and sole exclusive rights to supply water to the metropolis. It is the largest&#13;
                water service provider in Ethiopia with about 187,000 private connections and nearly 1100&#13;
                public standposts.14. The existing tariff structure attempts to only cover operation and&#13;
                maintenance costs. Preliminary studies have been done to identify a tariff system that will cover&#13;
                full costs. Adequate details of the overall financial status of AAWSA and the service levels for&#13;
                the urban poor are not available at this stage.&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Urban / Town Water Service Unit (TWSU): essentially performs as a `utility' for a large town with&#13;
                the responsibility to provide water supply to its population. In some regions, it may also provide&#13;
                technical support and monitors activities of smaller water boards / services within its immediate&#13;
                influence area. Its administrative links are either with the RWB or with the town (municipal)&#13;
                administration. In the latter case, it is likely that it functions more as a municipal department&#13;
                rather than a utility;&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Scheme Water Board (SWB): manages the bulk supply in case of larger scheme serving a number of&#13;
                WBs and VWCs. Management includes operation, maintenance and levy and collection of&#13;
                charges from WBs. Its membership is generally drawn from the WBs and VWCs whom it serves.&#13;
                For financial sustainability, SWBs would need to cover their operational costs from bulk supply&#13;
                charges. While these are less commonly found, some good practice examples are available (e.g.&#13;
                Dodotta) and provide lessons for future possibilities.&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Water Board (WB): Water Boards are generally the service providers in small and medium towns&#13;
                that have piped water schemes. Water boards are drawn from government officials and&#13;
                municipalities from the communities they serve. They are visualized as small utilities. The WB&#13;
                concept was initiated in Tigray region and is now being explored and developed in most regions.&#13;
&#13;
13For example the NGOs working in the WSS sector in Uganda have established a national level coordination network, Uganda Water and Sanitation&#13;
NGO network (UWASNET) with a similar aim.&#13;
14Based on Sahilu (2001), ESP (2001), volumes III and IV.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                 WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 MWR is preparing model legislation for WBs. This will help strengthen the legal basis as has&#13;
                 been done in Tigray and Amhara regions.&#13;
&#13;
           ·     Village Water and Sanitation Committee (VWSC): Within rural areas, there is a general acceptance of&#13;
                 the notion of community involvement during planning, implementation and operation phases of&#13;
                 a scheme. This approach was initiated through the ESRDF's RWSS component and through&#13;
                 different NGO projects. This form of service provider is articulated through a Community&#13;
                 Planning Committee (CPC) during the planning stage of a scheme, which is later converted to a&#13;
                 VWSC to manage the scheme operations. VWSCs are often elected and membership of women&#13;
                 is ensured.&#13;
&#13;
                           Table 5: Institutional Form of Service Providers by Settlement Contexts&#13;
&#13;
 Item                    Metropolis                Large               Medium                  Small             Rural Towns        Villages&#13;
                                                   Towns               Towns                   Towns&#13;
 Population                &gt;2.0 million               80,000 to            10,000 to               2,000 to      Less than 2,000     Less than&#13;
 range                    (Addis Ababa)               250,000                80,000                 10,000                             2,000&#13;
 Number of                         1                      10                  141                    491               282               ??&#13;
 centers&#13;
 Addis Ababa                Metro level&#13;
 Water                     independent&#13;
 Authority                      utility&#13;
 Urban Water                                        Utility for a         Utility for a           Technical support to smaller&#13;
 Service Unit                                        large town         medium town                        water boards&#13;
 (UWSU)&#13;
 Scheme Water                                                             Provision of bulk water supply to different WBs and VWCs&#13;
 Board (SWB)&#13;
 Water Board                                                             Water utility          Water utility     Water utility&#13;
 (WB)                                                                     for a town              for a town       for a town&#13;
 Village Water                                                                                                    Committee of      Committee&#13;
 and Sanitation                                                                                                      users to       of users to&#13;
 Committee                                                                                                        manage O&amp;M          manage&#13;
 (VWSC)                                                                                                                                O&amp;M&#13;
Source: Based on discussions with local resource persons. For population and number of centers see Table 4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.3        Sector Financing and Flow of Funds&#13;
&#13;
Funding for water supply in Ethiopia seems to be largely through federal and regional budgets and some off&#13;
budget mechanisms such as the ESRDF or bilateral agencies and NGOs. There is a critical need to identify an&#13;
appropriate financing strategy for the sector to address the key issues discussed below.&#13;
&#13;
Funding and Transfer Mechanisms: Though the National Water Policy envisages financing from domestic&#13;
financial institutions, so far WSS sector financing in the past has been largely through: budgetary allocations,&#13;
external debt or grants from bilateral donors and international NGOs sometimes provided directly either to&#13;
communities or local levels of government, and more recently, other off-budget mechanisms such as the&#13;
ESRDF. MWR also proposes to establish a water resource development fund (WRDF). It is envisaged that&#13;
the WRDF will pool the government and donor resources and channel these in line with the overall sector&#13;
policy. In the longer term it is visualized that WRDF will also mobilize additional resources.&#13;
&#13;
Fiscal Decentralization: With decentralization, a large share of federal resources is transferred to regional&#13;
governments. For example, during the current financial year, about 30 percent of total federal resources are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                     WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
transferred as federal subsidy, essentially as block grant15, to regions and administrative councils. The regional&#13;
subsidy is divided among the regions according to a formula approved by the Council of Federation using&#13;
criteria related to: population, level of development and level of revenue effort16. An established tradition of&#13;
bottom-up identification of priorities and flexibility in implementation allows shifting resources across&#13;
projects. However, an effective decentralization process is constrained by: the lack of medium term federal&#13;
subsidy estimates and donor practices that inhibit multi-year planning17.&#13;
&#13;
In principle, the regional governments also allocate funds for the WSS sector from their own budgets, and the&#13;
woreda governments are likely to do so in the future. Some regions have initiated block transfers to zone&#13;
levels and on a pilot basis to woreda level. Further developments in decentralization will depend on both on&#13;
greater predictability of transfers and external funds, as well as improved local capacity for planning and&#13;
implementation. WSS allocations within this emerging decentralization framework depend on the planning&#13;
process at these levels and the issue of preparedness of the WSS sector will be important also at this level.&#13;
Unfortunately, a detailed analysis of WSS financing at the regional level is constrained, as most readily&#13;
available information for regional level allocations and expenditures do not give a disaggregated analysis for&#13;
WSS18. In more recent development, the Government intends to further deepen the fiscal decentralization&#13;
process to the woreda level with transfer of woreda block grants.&#13;
&#13;
Flow of External Funds: External funds are an important source for Ethiopia's development expenditure. World&#13;
Bank (2000b) identifies three channels used for aid disbursements: i) funds disbursed through the federal&#13;
ministry of finance (either earmarked or unearmarked assistance), ii) aid negotiated and disbursed directly&#13;
through sector bodies, and iii) funds disbursed directly (outside the budget process) by donors or NGOs for&#13;
development purposes. Government has a clear preference for resources through the first channel (and&#13;
preferably unearmarked) that would help to maintain integrity of and strengthen the overall planning,&#13;
budgeting and accounting systems.&#13;
&#13;
For the current financial year (2001-02), external loans and grants are expected to account for 31 percent of&#13;
the total budget, 61 percent of the federal capital budgets and about 28 percent of the federal subsidy to&#13;
regions19. Donor funds included in the regional budgets are essentially offset against the treasury&#13;
subventions20. For the Ministry of Water Resources, external aid constituted over 80 percent of its capital&#13;
expenditure allocations, and over 95 percent for the WSS sub-sector. A number of efforts have been made by&#13;
Government of Ethiopia to improve coordination and management of external aid, including the move to&#13;
sector development programs for at least three sectors. However, several issues still need to be addressed:&#13;
better capture of all external assistance into planning and budget process21, advance information on medium&#13;
term plans of external aid, implementation delays linked to donor projects and lack of fungibility in aid&#13;
resources that hamper region's ability for effective implementation,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
15To the extent that the external resources within the federal subsidy are earmarked for specific sectors / projects, that proportion of the subsidy does&#13;
not remain a block grant.&#13;
16World Bank (2000b), p. 36.&#13;
17World Bank (2000b), p. 34-35.&#13;
18Estimates in Table 6 have been made as discussed below on the basis of an assumed share of WSS in the total budgets of the regional water bureaus.&#13;
19Based on Government of Ethiopia (2001), Federal Budget for 2001-02.&#13;
20The offset system, while rational for ensuring inter-regional equity, provides a negative incentive to regions to pursue external aid, as treasury&#13;
resources are preferred at regional level. It also provides an incentive to regions to pursue direct grants channel for external aid. (World Bank, 2000b, p.&#13;
56-57).&#13;
21For example, World Bank (2000b) points out that during 1999-00 budget only about 45 percent of total estimated assistance was captured in the&#13;
budget. Similarly, an old study for the water and sanitation sector showed that during the early part of the last decade, nearly a third of&#13;
the sector resources were provided by the NGOs, assistance that was probably not reflected in the federal budgets (CRDA, 1997).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                   WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Level of Resources for WSS: Adequate information on the actual resource availability to the sector is not available&#13;
in a systematic manner at present. Based on available information, preliminary and indicative estimates&#13;
suggest that the current level of funding allocation to the sector is about 34 million US $ per annum (refer to&#13;
table 6).22 This does not take into account any contributions by the WSPs themselves, as information is not&#13;
readily available. Of the total 90 percent is estimated to be for capital expenditure.&#13;
&#13;
Based on the available evidence it is likely that any significant increase in allocation will probably be&#13;
constrained by sector's absorptive capacity. Clearly, to achieve improvements in non-income dimensions of&#13;
poverty reduction water supply and sanitation deserves an equal attention as other comparable sectors such as&#13;
education, health and roads. However, WSS allocations compare very unfavorably with these sectors. This&#13;
more likely reflects a lack of sector readiness to absorb larger resources rather than a low priority for water&#13;
supply and sanitation23. It needs to be pointed out that the for ESRDF the resources&#13;
&#13;
            Table 6: Preliminary Estimates of Allocations to the WSS Sector, 2001-02 (In million US$)&#13;
&#13;
          Source of funds                         Source of information /                    Recurrent                  Capital              Total&#13;
                                                         Assumptions                       Expenditure               Expenditure&#13;
  Federal Budget&#13;
    Total                                 Federal budget                                                   873                    373            1246&#13;
   Ministry of Water Resources            Federal budget                                                      3                     21              24&#13;
    Water supply                          Federal budget                                                      1                      3                4&#13;
  Regional Budget&#13;
    Total                                 Federal subsidy to regions from the                                                                      801&#13;
                                          federal budget, and share of own&#13;
                                          resources assumed to be 30 percent&#13;
    Regional Water Bureau                 Share of regional water bureau in total                                                                   64&#13;
                                          regional budget assumed to be 8&#13;
                                          percent&#13;
    Water supply                          Share of water and sanitation in RWB                                3                     10              13&#13;
                                          budget assumed to be 20 percent and&#13;
                                          share of capital expenditure in WSS&#13;
                                          budget assumed to be 80 percent&#13;
  Water service providers&#13;
  (WSP)&#13;
  Addis Ababa Water Authority                                                                               Na                     Na               Na&#13;
  Urban Water Service Units                                                                                 Na                     Na               Na&#13;
  Water Boards                                                                                              Na                     Na               Na&#13;
  Village water Committees                Community share of 10 percent for                                 Na                     1.2              1.2&#13;
                                          ESRDF projects&#13;
  ESRDF                                   From actual allocations to RWSS for                                                       12              12&#13;
                                          the year&#13;
  NGOs / bilateral projects               Share in total water and sanitation                                                        5                5&#13;
                                          capital budget (excluding WSPs)&#13;
                                          assumed to be 20 percent&#13;
  TOTAL                                                                                                       4                     30              34&#13;
Source and notes: Refer to Annex A2. These estimates are preliminary and indicative. However, this approach provides a framework and indicates the nature&#13;
of information that will be required to arrive at such estimates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22Estimates of allocations to the sector are difficult due to inadequate availability of regional disggregated information. This is surprising, and may&#13;
require further assessment, as Ethiopia is said to have "a rigorous financial management and budget coding system that makes it possible to track the&#13;
public funds being spent on sectoral programs by the center and the regions" (World Bank, 2000b, p. 67). Also, while it is likely that the share of direct&#13;
(off public budget) funding by bilateral agencies and NGOs is high, no detailed current estimates are available. For details of assumptions made to&#13;
arrive at these estimates, refer to Annex A2.&#13;
23For example, while the share of total (federal and regional) resources to these other sectors range from about 5 to 15 percent, water sector receives&#13;
only an estimated less than 1 percent (refer to Table A1), including the allocations for capacity building and other sector support.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                 WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
originally estimated for the RWS sector as per the Bank project document were almost twice compared to the&#13;
actual allocations. This probably reflects a constraint on the sector's absorptive capacity for sustainable&#13;
investments. The priority actions and programs within the sector will, therefore, have to focus equally on&#13;
strengthening overall sector capacity as specific investment strategies.&#13;
&#13;
Financing and Cost Recovery Policy: The National Water Policy provides a basis for developing a framework for&#13;
financing and cost recovery. The guiding principles in this regard are:&#13;
&#13;
          ·    Demand responsive financing: to enable effective expression of demand, the need for some level of&#13;
               self financing of projects and the need to ensure full coverage of operation and maintenance&#13;
               costs by service providers;&#13;
&#13;
          ·    Leverage domestic private and community finance: promote participation of "local banks, other investors&#13;
               as well as popular and traditional self-help associations through appropriate incentive packages";&#13;
               and&#13;
&#13;
          ·    Tariff setting and cost recovery: promote site-specific tariff setting along with full cost recovery for&#13;
               urban water supply and at least full operation and maintenance cost recovery for rural water&#13;
               supply while ensuring affordable access for the poor through appropriate mechanisms for cross&#13;
               subsidization&#13;
&#13;
The policy for financing of water supply suggests different approaches for rural and urban areas: to ensure&#13;
full cost recovery for urban water, and to cover partial capital costs and full O&amp;M costs for rural water.&#13;
However, this is not clearly laid out in actual guidelines. It is likely that the large number of urban water&#13;
projects provide subsidized funding to urban water service units. In urban areas another constraint has been&#13;
the difficulty with expanding coverage in the emerging informal areas. It would be useful to explore&#13;
innovative and locally relevant measures to achieve such expansion within poverty reduction agenda. It is also&#13;
necessary to assess affordability and willingness to pay for differing levels of service and technology choices in&#13;
the design of these systems. In this context, concept of a continuum from rural to urban needs to be&#13;
developed to identify the level of cost recovery in relation to service levels and affordability.&#13;
&#13;
It is also not very clear whether these rules are applied to rural water schemes financed through regional&#13;
budgetary resources and that at least a part of the maintenance costs for rural schemes are actually met&#13;
through regional budgetary allocations. To achieve these principles in practice operational guidelines will need&#13;
to be developed within the available resource envelope for public finance and overall coverage targets that&#13;
need to be achieved within a medium term framework.&#13;
&#13;
3.4       Key Sector Issues&#13;
&#13;
Institutional roles, forms and capacity: Despite the attempt made to clarify the institutional roles in the paragraphs&#13;
above, considerable more clarity is required in appropriate roles, related forms and capacity of different&#13;
entities. A critical issue is the notion of a service provider, their legal basis with the necessary powers, and&#13;
their links with the appropriate government units within the decentralization framework. Some of the&#13;
important sector roles related to regulation, M&amp;E and information management require further attention as&#13;
these are being neglected at present.&#13;
&#13;
          ·    Defining institutional models and strengthening capacity of service providers: Different institutional forms of&#13;
               service providers exist in regions. Appropriate institutional models need to be developed with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                  12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                         WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                legislative basis to address key aspects such as: functional autonomy, links with decentralization&#13;
                framework, right to levy user charges, transfer of assets, independence in recruitment,&#13;
                procurement and pricing decisions. Efforts have been now initiated in most regions. Along with&#13;
                this clarity, support is required to strengthen their capacities for planning, consumer services,&#13;
                operations and financial management.&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Poor monitoring and regulation: With the emergence of a large umber of service providers, it&#13;
                becomes essential to monitor their operational performance. Such monitoring may be done&#13;
                within the decentralization framework through the existing RWBs, zonal departments and the&#13;
                planned woreda offices. While this is envisaged as per existing arrangements, in most regions&#13;
                monitoring does not receive adequate emphasis. For urban WSS service providers, an&#13;
                independent regulatory framework becomes essential to ensure that the tariffs are set to reflect&#13;
                consumer preference as well as viability of the provider. Maximizing the operational performance&#13;
                becomes important in this context. Development of such a regulatory framework will also enable&#13;
                gradual entry of the private sector in urban water supply provision.&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Lack of sector information management systems (SIMS): Better sector planning needs to be based on&#13;
                well managed and regularly updated sector information systems. MWR, as it moves away from&#13;
                direct participation in water projects, and shifts its role to planning and strategy development,&#13;
                needs to be at forefront of managing this. Such a system should include: periodic assessment of&#13;
                the sector resources and operational performance.&#13;
&#13;
Poor sustainability of Investments: Decapitalization of investments in the sector is common both in rural and&#13;
urban areas. For rural areas, studies done during the last five years indicated that a large proportion (ranging&#13;
from a third to a half) of water schemes are not functional24. For urban areas, the problems are related to&#13;
poor financial viability, and technical and managerial capacities.&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Rural water: In rural areas, poor maintenance appears to be a common problem. A number of&#13;
                issues that need to be addressed in this regard: i) Inadequate emphasis on promotion and&#13;
                participatory and informed demand articulation during the planning stage results in poor&#13;
                technology choices and a lack of community `ownership' of the scheme, ii) poor user fees&#13;
                collection, both due to inadequate management and up-front clarity of rules results in lack of&#13;
                resources to undertake timely maintenance of assets, iii) lack of or poorly developed supply&#13;
                chains (in relation to technology choices) that makes access to spare parts difficult and unduly&#13;
                costly, iv) inadequate technical support available to VWSC and WBs, and v) lack of access to&#13;
                credit for bridge finance for sudden or major repairs and augmentation.&#13;
&#13;
          ·     Urban Water: In urban areas sustainability of investments is also threatened, as timely and regular&#13;
                maintenance is not undertaken. The problems that underlie this trend have been: i) inappropriate&#13;
                tariff setting without an emphasis on full cost recovery, ii) lack of clear guidelines for urban tariff&#13;
                setting including issues related to affordability and financial sustainability, iii) inappropriate or&#13;
                lack of institutional incentives for urban WSPs to achieve financial viability and improved&#13;
                operational performance, iv) poor technical and financial capacity among the urban service&#13;
                providers that leads to high levels unaccounted for water (UFW), and v) poor or non-existent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24See footnotes 4, 5 and 6.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                 WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  consumer services and grievance redressal system leads to a lack of willing to pay user charges.&#13;
                  The Water policy visualizes full cost recovery for water in urban areas in a phased manner, if&#13;
                  necessary. Appropriate guidelines and capacity building support are needed to support&#13;
                  implementation of this policy.&#13;
&#13;
             ·    Private sector capacity: Improvements in operational performance of especially urban water systems&#13;
                  will be enhanced, if appropriate opportunities for private sector participation to enhance&#13;
                  efficiency are developed. However, it is not very clear whether such capacity exists domestically,&#13;
                  and a detailed assessment is necessary. Particular emphasis is needed on the possible role of small&#13;
                  scale and local private sector for a variety of support services such as: professional support to&#13;
                  operators of town systems and to rural communities for maintenance and provision of spare&#13;
                  parts.&#13;
&#13;
Neglect of sanitation and hygiene: A key issue in evolving a better response to the sanitation and hygiene needs of&#13;
the population appears to be the lack of clarity in institutional responsibilities. While integration of sanitation&#13;
and hygiene with water schemes is mentioned in the Water Policy, institutional responsibilities appear to be&#13;
with the Health sector. At the local level, all regions have a far better presence of the health sector at the&#13;
woreda level through the woreda health office. There are some successful pilot examples of better&#13;
coordination at the local level from bilateral and ESRDF projects. Lessons from these need to be used to&#13;
develop greater clarity in institutional roles at all levels. This will then help to also address the issues related to&#13;
financing, especially of continued hygiene promotion.&#13;
&#13;
Clarifying financing rules to align with WSS policy and priorities: WSS status and its poverty linkages and the&#13;
outstanding institutional issues suggest some clear WSS priorities such as: i) priority for rural water,&#13;
particularly due to its relatively lower coverage levels, ii) within urban water, with relatively better coverage&#13;
levels, focus needs to be on improved access for the poor and overall sustainability of urban WSPs, iii) need&#13;
to better integrate sanitation and hygiene promotion to ensure accrual of full health benefits, iv) need to&#13;
improve the participatory planning and implementation of WSS investments through adequate software&#13;
support, and v) need to strengthen overall sector capacity through improved management and M&amp;E systems.&#13;
While developing the detailed financing strategy, rules for allocation of and access to public finance will need&#13;
to be developed in response to these priorities25. Some principles that need to be considered are:&#13;
&#13;
·     Level of capital subsidies for rural water: need to reconsider the current system of a minimum community&#13;
      share in capital costs (generally 10 percent) and move to a ceiling on per capita subsidy linked to the&#13;
      notion of basic service levels26, and a minimum cash contribution requirement; to some extent similar&#13;
      (though lower) subsidies may also be relevant for the rural and small towns with less than 10000&#13;
      population;&#13;
&#13;
·     Nature of support for urban water: need to reconsider the large capital subsidies to urban water suppliers and&#13;
      move to appropriate subsidy measures to enhance access for the urban poor to improved services and&#13;
&#13;
25These will need to be developed in detail at the federal and regional level as a part of the implementation guidelines for SDP as discussed below in&#13;
Section 3.5.&#13;
26This suggestion is based on the discussions in a recent ESRDF National workshop for "Performance of RWSS sub-component" in November 2001&#13;
held in Addis Ababa. The notion of basic service level would have to be defined in terms of time spent on water, quantity and quality of water and&#13;
technical possibilities in a given local area. This would need to be backed by adequate hydrological studies, especial ly in regions known to face&#13;
difficulties with water sources. Such a measure would also provide incentives for maximizing resource leverage by exploring community based credit&#13;
and micro-finance. It would also help to attain more demand based community technology choices. Recent information from ESRDF suggests that&#13;
there may be an undue shift to more complex technologies that are more expensive and difficult for community management (Lium and Garvey,&#13;
2001).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                              WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     sustainable measures to enhance financial/ commercial viability of urban water service providers&#13;
     (UWSUs). This may be usefully done within an output-based assistance approach;&#13;
&#13;
·    Provision for sanitation and hygiene: water sub-projects need to make an adequate investment provision for&#13;
     sanitation and hygiene promotion sub-components, and ensure continued support to hygiene promotion&#13;
     through recurrent budgets of water service providers, if necessary through appropriate subsidies;&#13;
&#13;
·    Share of management support in project costs: to address the constraint of poor planning and implementation,&#13;
     especially in rural WSS projects, adequate provision needs to be made for project planning and&#13;
     implementation management in total project costs, especially for community preparation for planning,&#13;
     formation of management committees and systems of accountability27; and&#13;
&#13;
·    Share of sector development in sector investments: to address the overall sector capacity constraints, an&#13;
     appropriate share of total WSS investments needs to be made for activities such as: capacity building,&#13;
     sector information and ME systems and development of supply chains28.&#13;
&#13;
Linking public finance to results: Within the HIPC and PRSP framework, it is important to shift the traditional&#13;
emphasis of public finance on inputs to `results' and from `controls' on inputs to achieving the agreed targets&#13;
for welfare improvement. Such an emphasis makes it possible to track welfare improvements as outcomes of&#13;
specific expenditure priorities. Such an approach also makes it possible to explore alternative means of&#13;
achieving the results and in changing and adapting the inputs to ensure sustainability. In WSS sector this is of&#13;
great importance, as often in the past, issues related to sustainability of capital investments were not&#13;
addressed leading to poor results even though the input and output targets were reached. Such an approach&#13;
would also require a clear identification of results / outcome indicators that need to be monitored as&#13;
discussed further in Section 3.3.&#13;
&#13;
3.5        Operationalizing the WSS Component of the Sector Development Program (SDP)&#13;
&#13;
MWR has recently developed a water sector development program (WSDP). It covers all the key sub-sectors&#13;
including: water resources, irrigation, hydropower and water and sanitation. MWR through its consultants&#13;
have carried out detailed consultation at the regional level to identify the local priorities, articulation of targets&#13;
and linked sub-projects. Water and sanitation is an important component within the WSDP.&#13;
Operationalization of this component within the SDP provides an opportunity to address some of the key&#13;
institutional and financing issues discussed above.&#13;
&#13;
Background of Other SDPs in Ethiopia: Ethiopia has taken lead in developing sector development programs&#13;
(SDPs) for some of its important sectors to facilitate strategic planning for the sectors and a framework for&#13;
coordination of donor funding. SDPS have been developed and operational for three sectors: education,&#13;
health and road construction. The SDPs were generally preceded by a number of studies related to&#13;
institutional and financing issues in each sector. These have been operational for a few years now and provide&#13;
valuable lessons in future preparation of other sector SDPs. Some of these lessons are: i) preparation of SDPs&#13;
need to be done in consultation with regional governments so that their priorities are also adequately&#13;
reflected, ii) the initial period presented considerable problems in donor consultation and commitment, iii)&#13;
&#13;
27For example, for rural water supply investments in Uganda, a provision of 12 percent is made for project planning and management: community&#13;
mobilization (3%), engineering design and contract supervision (5%), water quality testing and surveillance (1%), monitoring and accountability (3%)&#13;
(Government of Uganda, 2001, p. 6).&#13;
28For example, for rural water supply investments in Uganda, a provision of nearly 14 percent is made for expenditures related to national programme&#13;
support (Government of Uganda, 2001, p. 6). This will of course need to be properly assessed in relation to the costs of critical activities for sector&#13;
development under the Action Plan for WSS sector development program (see section 2.5 below).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                       15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                    WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
donor discomfort with the initial lack of a common and consultatively agreed implementation manual, iv)&#13;
many of the standards and modalities in the implementation guidelines were developed at the federal level,&#13;
and considerable efforts were required to incorporate the required regional variations, v) considerable&#13;
additional demand on financial information flows, and the need to simplify and stream line procurement&#13;
procedures, and vi) need for a well articulated transition phase for introducing some of the critical&#13;
institutional reforms. This proved to be critical as considerable capacity building support was required at&#13;
regional and woreda levels within the decentralization framework. Further development in these SDPs&#13;
visualizes a streamlining with the federal government's five-year plan process. Close links of SDPs are also&#13;
envisaged with the other governance and financial management related reforms such as civil service reforms&#13;
and medium term planning framework.&#13;
&#13;
Approach to operationalization of WSS component in WSDP: The WSDP preparation process has identified a&#13;
detailed list of sub-project ideas through extensive regional consultations. Based on a preliminary review of&#13;
the SDPs for education, health and roads sectors, operationalizing the WSS component of the WSDP will&#13;
require further development of:&#13;
&#13;
·    an action plan with measures to address institutional and financing issues within the WSS sub-sector,&#13;
&#13;
·    model implementation guidelines with details of financing principles, funding and procurement&#13;
     modalities and monitoring arrangements, to be developed at the federal level and appropriately adapted&#13;
     by each region, and&#13;
&#13;
·    a detailed annual and periodic review process with adequate stakeholder consultation, and particularly a&#13;
     process of donor dialogue as has been developed for other sectors. This review process should preferably&#13;
     be also linked with other important stages in the planning and budgeting cycle such as presentation of the&#13;
     federal and regional budgets and medium term expenditure framework (MTEF).&#13;
&#13;
Implementation of the WSDP can usefully be done through a demand responsive, decentralized approach.&#13;
Appropriate financing mechanism need to be identified for this.&#13;
&#13;
4.       Priorities for Poverty Reduction: Action Plans, Targets and Expenditure&#13;
Requirements&#13;
&#13;
The water sector development program has identified direct investment requirements for water and sewerage&#13;
projects in relation to region-wise targets for improved coverage for access to `safe' water for a 15-year time&#13;
frame. It has also identified an institutional component for the overall program including both human&#13;
resource development plans and institutional strengthening programs.&#13;
&#13;
4.1      WSS Sub-sector Priorities for Poverty Reduction:&#13;
&#13;
Issue of poor sector capacity and low levels of expenditures for WSS are interlinked and lead to a vicious&#13;
circle ­ as low levels of investments create low demand for technical and manpower inputs in WSS sector and&#13;
thus capacity remains underdeveloped. The resulting low sector capacity, means low allocations and&#13;
expenditures are further curtailed. The action plans for WSS will need to be developed to break this vicious&#13;
circle through simultaneous development of overall sector capacity and gradual increases in investments for&#13;
improved services in rural and urban areas. The three priority areas of focus for PRSP within the WSS sub-&#13;
sector are:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                     WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
·   Sector Strengthening: to enhance and strengthen overall sector capacity to improve WSS service in a&#13;
    decentralized environment&#13;
&#13;
·   Rural Water Supply and Sanitation: to enhance access to safe water, sanitation and hygiene, and&#13;
&#13;
·   Urban Water Supply and Sanitation: to enhance access of the urban poor to improved water supply,&#13;
    sanitation and hygiene promotion&#13;
&#13;
4.2      Outcome linked Action Plans for the Institutional Component:&#13;
&#13;
The WSDP has identified an institutional component for the water sector as a whole with an allocation of&#13;
about 65 million $ during the first five year phase. While this component is common to all water sub-sectors,&#13;
a part of this allocation would be for the WSS sub-sector that has a much larger share (46 percent) of&#13;
envisaged investments. To support the PRSP priorities in the WSS sector within this overall institutional&#13;
component, outcome linked action plans need to be identified. To meet this need, within each of the three&#13;
PRSP priority areas for WSS sub-sector, key issues, related action plans over a three-year period and related&#13;
outcomes to be achieved have been identified (refer to Table 7). These include:&#13;
&#13;
·   Sector Strengthening&#13;
&#13;
         o development of a financing strategy,&#13;
&#13;
         o development of a sector planning and information management system and linked sector M&amp;E&#13;
              system, with related capacity building for MWR, regions and local governments&#13;
&#13;
·   Rural Water Supply and Sanitation:&#13;
&#13;
         o strengthening VWSCs,&#13;
&#13;
         o development of a supply chains and maintenance (SCM) strategy,&#13;
&#13;
         o improved integration of sanitation and hygiene promotion and, and&#13;
&#13;
         o investment strategy for new RWS schemes to achieve agreed targets&#13;
&#13;
·   Urban Water Supply and Sanitation:&#13;
&#13;
         o financially sustainable urban water service providers,&#13;
&#13;
         o strengthening capacity of water boards,&#13;
&#13;
         o assessment and implementation of measures to enhance access of the poor to WSS services,&#13;
&#13;
         o framework for economic regulation for urban water supply starting with comparative&#13;
              performance assessment of UWS service providers, and&#13;
&#13;
         o investment strategy for new/augmentation of UWS schemes to achieve agreed targets&#13;
&#13;
Detailed costing for these actions plans within the institutional component will need to be developed later.&#13;
&#13;
4.3      Coverage Targets and Investment Requirements:&#13;
&#13;
As a part of the ongoing process of preparation of WSDP region-wise targets for enhanced coverage of water&#13;
in rural and urban areas, and urban sewerage, have been identified. The total resource requirements based on&#13;
these targets and projects have also been identified (refer to Table 8). The targets for access to `safe' water&#13;
during the short-term five-year period are: 88 percent in urban and 37 percent in rural areas respectively by&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                   WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2006. The total requirements during the first phase to achieve these targets are 742 million $, or about 150&#13;
million $ per annum. Similar long-term investment assessments have been also made under the WSS master&#13;
plan being prepared under the Environment Support project (ESP). Though this estimation uses a different&#13;
approach focusing on the technology choices and household affordability considerations, the overall&#13;
investment requirements are in the same broad range.&#13;
&#13;
                              Table 7: Priority Areas, Action Plans and Outcomes&#13;
&#13;
  Action Area         Issue                               Actions                               Outcomes&#13;
  (Objective)&#13;
                                          Year 1             Year 2          Year 3&#13;
Sector Strengthening&#13;
To strengthen   Lack of clear      Financing strategy  Financing         Measures to    Sector financing strategy&#13;
the sector      financing rules,   with clear          strategy          support        developed and identified&#13;
capacity for    incentives for     financing rules     operationalized   resource       measures implemented&#13;
planning,       WSPs and           developed           and adapted for   leverage&#13;
financing and   inadequate                             regions as        explored&#13;
regulation      leveraging of                          necessary&#13;
                additional&#13;
                resources&#13;
                Poor or non-       Development of a    SIMS and M&amp;E      Sector         Sector planning&#13;
                existent sector    sector level        system            comparative    information and M&amp;E&#13;
                information and    information         operational       performance    system with related&#13;
                M&amp;E system         management                            assessment     capacity developed and&#13;
                resulting in poor  system (SIMS)                         system         operational for at least&#13;
                planning           and M&amp;E system                        initiated      one year&#13;
Rural Water Supply and&#13;
Sanitation&#13;
To enhance      Weak legal basis   Develop model       All regions adopt                Clear legal basis for rural&#13;
access of the   and inadequate     legislation (or     appropriate                      WSPs in all regions&#13;
rural           capacity of rural  amendments) for     legislation for                  established&#13;
population to   WSPs (WBs and      rural WSPs for      rural WSPs&#13;
WSS services in VWCs)              regional&#13;
a sustainable                      adaptation&#13;
manner                             Support to rural    Develop a         Operationali   Capacity building&#13;
                                   WSP through the     framework of      ze the         support to rural WSPs&#13;
                                   decentralized       capacity building capacity       institutionalized&#13;
                                   system (RWBs,       support to        building&#13;
                                   ZDs and WWOs)       decentralized     framework&#13;
                                   identified          system&#13;
                Poor               Supply chains and   Operationalize    Institutionali SCM strategy for rural&#13;
                maintenance of     maintenance         measures in       ze measures    WS operational&#13;
                completed RWS      (SCM) strategy for  approved RWS      in the SCM     Improved maintenance&#13;
                schemes leading    rural WS schemes    SCM strategy      strategy       results in higher&#13;
                to failure and     developed and                                        functionality and user&#13;
                poor               approved                                             satisfaction&#13;
                sustainability&#13;
                Neglect of         Situation           Develop a         Adopt and      Sanitation and hygiene&#13;
                sanitation and     assessment          sanitation and    operationaliz  components integrated&#13;
                hygiene            prepared for        hygiene           e strategy in  in RWS schemes&#13;
                promotion          sanitation and      promotion         regions        Hygiene promotion&#13;
                leading to         hygiene, including  strategy within                  incorporated in rural&#13;
                reduced health     institutional       decentralization                 WSP responsibilities&#13;
                benefits           sanitation in       framework, test&#13;
                                   coordination with   in some regions&#13;
                                   MoH&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                       WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Action Area             Issue                              Actions                                Outcomes&#13;
  (Objective)&#13;
                                              Year 1             Year 2         Year 3&#13;
Urban Water Supply and&#13;
Sanitation&#13;
To enhance          Poor service       Support             Operationalize    Institutionali Financially viable urban&#13;
access of the       performance        framework for       the framework in  ze support to  WSPs (UWSU) achieve&#13;
urban poor to       and financial      urban WSPs to       selected regions  urban WSPs     significant&#13;
improved WSS        viability of urban improve their                         on a           improvements in&#13;
services by         WSPs and           service                               commercial     operational performance&#13;
financially                            performance and                       fees basis&#13;
sustainable                            financial viability&#13;
urban WSPs                             including PSP&#13;
                                       management&#13;
                                       models developed&#13;
                    Poor capacity of   Identify measures   Develop a         Adopt and      Strong Water Boards&#13;
                    Water Boards to    to strengthen       strategy for      operationaliz  able to contract with and&#13;
                    contract and       capacity of water   capacity building e strategy in  monitor water service&#13;
                    monitor water      boards to work      and test in       more regions   providers&#13;
                    service providers  with WSPs/          selected regions&#13;
                    (WSPs)             UWSSs and a&#13;
                                       related monitoring&#13;
                                       framework&#13;
                    Inadequate         Situation           Strategy          Strategy       Urban poor gain&#13;
                    access for the     assessment          developed for     operationaliz  improved access to&#13;
                    urban poor to      prepared for        access of the     ed including   piped water supply at&#13;
                    piped water        urban poor access   urban poor to     restructured   affordable rates&#13;
                    supply schemes     to WSS services     improved WSS      subsidy&#13;
                                                           services          mechanisms&#13;
                    Lack of a          Detailed            Develop and       Developmen     Framework for&#13;
                    framework for      assessment of       implement a       t of a         economic regulation&#13;
                    economic           situation of UWS    comparative       framework      developed&#13;
                    regulation         in all the regions  performance       for economic   Urban water tariffs&#13;
                                       in terms of         assessment        regulation     within the regulatory&#13;
                                       pricing, financial  framework on a    for UWS        framework&#13;
                                       viability and       regular basis&#13;
                                       investment needs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Table 8a: Phase-wise Targets and Investment Requirements for WSS: MWR Sector Development Program&#13;
&#13;
                                                           Urban            Rural                  Total&#13;
Coverage Targets (% to total population with&#13;
`sustainable' access to `safe' water)&#13;
Existing situation (2001)                                         74                 23                      31&#13;
Short term (2002-2006)                                            88                 37                      45&#13;
Medium term (2007-2011)                                           97                 52                      60&#13;
Long term (2012-2016)                                             98                 71                      76&#13;
Investment Requirements (in million US$)&#13;
Short term (2002-2006)                                           300                443                     743&#13;
Medium term (2007-2011)                                          311                1059                   1370&#13;
Long term (2012-2016)                                            162                1444                   1606&#13;
Total                                                            773                2946                   3719&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                               WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Table 8b: Short Term Regional Targets and Investment Requirements for WSS: MWR WSDP&#13;
&#13;
    Region            Existing coverage 2001               Target Coverage 2005                      Investment requirements for&#13;
                             % of population                    % of population                             2002-2006 (million US$)&#13;
                        Urban             Rural            Urban               Rural             Urban                Rural              Total&#13;
Dire Dawa                       68                37                 78                 49                    2                 1                  3&#13;
Harari                          25                19                 25                 37                  28                  1                 29&#13;
Gambella                        35                14                 45                 24                    3                 2                  5&#13;
Benishangul                     43                18                 63                 38                    5                 2                  7&#13;
Gumuz&#13;
Tigary                          59                29                 85                 45                    6               65                  71&#13;
SNNPRS                          83                24                 95                 33                    5              101                 106&#13;
Amhara                          96                23                 99                 36                  30               128                 158&#13;
Oromiya                         76                24                 84                 42                  28               115                 143&#13;
Somali                          46                 7                 56                 17                    5               23                  28&#13;
Affar                           44                14                 59                 30                    4               18                  22&#13;
Addis Ababa                     70                 0                 95                  0                 183                  0                183&#13;
Total                           74                23                 87                 39                 300               443                 743&#13;
Sources: MWR (2002), Sector Development program: Main Report, Draft Final, Executive Summary, mimeo, p. 38. Urban investment estimates also&#13;
include some proposals for urban sewerage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Based on preliminary estimates of past allocations to the sector (refer to Table 6), these requirements are&#13;
about 5 times the current level of allocations for capital investments in the sector. PRSP linked priority&#13;
discussed above would suggest a greater focus on the rural areas and on the access for the poor within urban&#13;
areas. Further priorities for example may also suggest that greater attention is needed on the needs of pastoral&#13;
communities. MWR is currently engaged in exploring different priority scenarios within these overall&#13;
estimates to align more closely with the possible resource envelope for the water sector. Such scenario&#13;
assessments would need to include aspects such as: priorities across different sub-sectors, appropriate&#13;
technology choices and financing/ cost recovery rules (as discussed above). For developing these estimates, it&#13;
would also be necessary to include adequate provision for project development / management costs,&#13;
including the `software' costs of social mobilization and community support.29&#13;
&#13;
Any discussion of total investment requirements also needs to take into account the approach of offset used&#13;
for allocations of federal subsidy to regions30 as an increase in regional WSS allocations would be done by&#13;
reducing other investments, unless there is a significant increase in availability of total resources. At present to&#13;
overcome this, off-budget mechanisms such as ESRDF or the proposed Water Resources Development&#13;
Fund, are being used. Another preferred option of the Government is to use the `third channel' of direct&#13;
grant funding by bilateral agencies or NGOs.&#13;
&#13;
5.         Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
5.1        Issues in Development of a Sector M&amp;E&#13;
&#13;
A clear shift is required within the PRSP framework and sector development program approach from an&#13;
input based to an outcome linked expenditure strategy. To make this effective, a shift is required from the&#13;
project linked M&amp;E systems that are common in the WSS sector, to a sector-wide M&amp;E. A strong M&amp;E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
29From global experience these may be at least 10 to 15 percent of project investments. These costs will also need to be accounted for in projections&#13;
of investment requirements.&#13;
30See the discussion above in footnote 21.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                     WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
system that is participatory and linked to the overall sector strategy will enable better program planning along&#13;
with accountability of those implementing programs.&#13;
&#13;
A review of PRSPs in Africa suggests that often PRSP linked proposals for M&amp;E system seem to focus&#13;
mainly on monitoring poverty impacts, especially through special household surveys and participatory poverty&#13;
assessments (PPAs). However, there is inadequate attention on implementation monitoring, especially related&#13;
to inputs, outputs and outcomes. To really measure strategy effectiveness an emphasis is needed equally on&#13;
the latter. For an effective sector M&amp;E system, institutional responsibility (across MWR, RWB, ZD, WWO&#13;
and WSPs) and flow of information needs to be clearly articulated. While some innovations exist at different&#13;
levels in Ethiopia, a systematic and linked M&amp;E system does not exist at present. At each level appropriate&#13;
participatory mechanisms need to be developed and institutionalized over time to ensure wider accountability.&#13;
Finally, as observed earlier, it is necessary to improve the impact monitoring for WSS through country level&#13;
household surveys and poverty analysis already being carried out.&#13;
&#13;
To address these issues, development of the institutional framework for M&amp;E needs to be developed within&#13;
three guiding principles:&#13;
&#13;
·   Information collection and analysis at every level of government with a three-way flow of information for&#13;
    dissemination­ upwards and downwards, and to other stakeholders;&#13;
&#13;
·   Selection of institutions at each level with an adequate institutional capacity and budget allocation to&#13;
    ensure reliable and timely collection and analysis of information&#13;
&#13;
·   Need to link with other multi-purpose and inter-linked M&amp;E tools, such as welfare monitoring surveys&#13;
    and public expenditure reviews, to enable adoption of more cost-efficient tools and also to provide a&#13;
    comparative picture across different sectors.&#13;
&#13;
5.2      Institutional Arrangements for Sector M&amp;E in WSS&#13;
&#13;
Within an overall M&amp;E system, three components may be identified:&#13;
&#13;
·   Sector Performance: a WSS internal sector level M&amp;E that is integrated with the WSS institutional&#13;
    arrangements and hierarchy (MWR, RWB, Zonal Department, TWSU and woreda water offices). In the&#13;
    future as an independent regulatory framework is developed and made operational, it will also take on&#13;
    independent performance monitoring responsibilities for urban water supply services;&#13;
&#13;
·   Sector Outcomes: links with wider and multi-sectoral M&amp;E systems such as: welfare monitoring surveys,&#13;
    PPAs (if taken up), public expenditure reviews (PER), census and joint donor reviews. This will help&#13;
    ensure that information for WSS related concerns and outcome/impacts are better coordinated and the&#13;
    quality of information is ensured. Responsibility for this should vest with MWR, planning department;&#13;
&#13;
·   Sector Networking and Influence: Use of M&amp;E to influence decisions related to the sector is essential. This&#13;
    requires efforts on two fronts: i) to link effectively with the overall sector planning process, both&#13;
    internally to the sector and as linked to wider macro planning. This necessitates that information and&#13;
    reports from the sector M&amp;E system are made available to key stakeholders at different levels in the&#13;
    planning process and to match with the planning and budget cycles, and ii) links are necessary to be&#13;
    developed with key stakeholders through appropriate forums, such as networks and associations,&#13;
    including promotion of such bodies, as appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                   WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 9 suggests a broad framework for WSS sector M&amp;E within the PRSP framework that takes into&#13;
account all the elements of a sound M&amp;E system. It also suggests broad institutional responsibilities.&#13;
&#13;
                Table 9: WSS Sector Monitoring and Evaluation Systems within PRSP Framework&#13;
&#13;
     M&amp;E Component and level of            Illustrative examples of monitoring     Institutional responsibility&#13;
                monitoring                                  tools&#13;
 Sector Performance&#13;
 Inputs:&#13;
 ·   Resources required to achieve       ·    Expenditure reporting               ·   MOFP&#13;
     suggested outputs on the policy          (disaggregated for WSS from         ·   MWR (planning&#13;
     matrix and sub-sectoral actions          regional levels)                        department, finance&#13;
     plans                               ·    Resource flows assessment (see          department)&#13;
                                              Table 6 estimates)                  ·   RWB&#13;
                                         ·    Periodic cost studies&#13;
                                         ·    Public expenditure tracking&#13;
                                         ·    Participatory social oversight at&#13;
                                              region / woreda levels&#13;
 Outputs:&#13;
 ·   Policy milestones achieved as a     ·    Reports on outputs produced (from   ·   MWR (planning&#13;
     result of implementation of policy       regional level)                         department, WSS&#13;
     matrix                              ·    Periodic special studies for            department)&#13;
 ·   Goods and services generated as a        sustainability and functionality    ·   ESRDF&#13;
     result of action plans              ·    WSS annual sector review with       ·   RWB&#13;
                                              GOE and development partners&#13;
 Sector Outcomes&#13;
 Outcomes:&#13;
 ·   What policy outcomes are achieved   ·    Service delivery surveys            ·   MWR&#13;
 ·   Who benefits from the action plans  ·    Welfare Monitoring Surveys (WMS)    ·   DAG&#13;
     ­ Access, Utilization and           ·    Participatory povertyassessments&#13;
     Satisfaction                             (PPAs)&#13;
                                         ·    WSS annual sector review with&#13;
                                              GOE and development partners&#13;
 Impacts:&#13;
 ·   Impacts on living standards through ·    Welfare Monitoring Surveys (WMS)    ·   MWR&#13;
     improved water and sanitation       ·    Demographic and health surveys      ·   WMU, MOFP&#13;
     services ­ time, health, income and ·    Census of Ethiopia&#13;
     empowerment&#13;
 Sector networking and influence&#13;
 Dissemination:&#13;
 ·   Dissemination of M&amp;E results and    ·    Periodic reports and publications   ·   MWR&#13;
     reports to stakeholders in                                                   ·   RWB&#13;
 Stakeholder networking:&#13;
 ·   Links with appropriate networks /   ·    WSS annual sector review with       ·   MWR&#13;
     associations of key stakeholders         GOE and development partners        ·   NGO association (e.g.&#13;
                                         ·    Occasional consultation workshops       CRDA)&#13;
                                              on key issues                       ·   DAG&#13;
                                         ·    WSS annual sector review at         ·   Regional associations of&#13;
                                              regional level with stakeholder         UWSUs/WBs/VWCs&#13;
                                              associations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Current sector capacity for M&amp;E seems to be very weak, though one or two regions have developed input&#13;
and output monitoring systems in a systematic manner. These existing efforts will need to be assessed to&#13;
develop ideas for appropriate institutional responsibilities for M&amp;E. In addition MWR, through possibly its&#13;
planning department will need to take on the responsibility of designing and coordinating the development of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                     WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
a full M&amp;E system. It would be important to ensure that adequate budget resources are allocated for this&#13;
purpose and that adequate incentives exist for different actors to collect, analyze and use the information&#13;
effectively and systematically. These aspects will be developed as a part of the sector M&amp;E system.&#13;
&#13;
5.3      Development of Key M&amp;E Indicators&#13;
&#13;
Based on the proposals suggested in section 4 above, indicators have been identified to reflect the outcomes&#13;
related to achieving better access to improved water and sanitation for the poor in Ethiopia. These will need&#13;
to be discussed further with different stakeholders through appropriate consultations. Appropriate details&#13;
related to disaggregation of information and frequency of monitoring will also need to be identified.&#13;
&#13;
Additional indicators linked to the inputs and outputs as per aspects detailed in Table 9 above will also be&#13;
developed further within the sector M&amp;E strategy.&#13;
&#13;
                            Table 10: Illustrative PRSP Linked Outcome Monitoring Indicators&#13;
&#13;
 Broad Area                                   Suggested Outcome/ Indicator                                               Possible Source&#13;
 Rural Water Supply and                       Access to (use of and satisfaction with) `safe' source                     WMS&#13;
 Sanitation                                   of water in rural areas                                                    Demographic and health&#13;
                                              Access to (use of and satisfaction with) `safe'                            surveys&#13;
                                              sanitation facilities in rural areas                                       Census of Ethiopia&#13;
                                              Percent of RWS schemes fully `operational' and                             MWR special surveys and&#13;
                                              `sustainable'                                                              annual review reports&#13;
                                              Time spent on collecting water&#13;
                                              Status of hygiene practices in rural communities&#13;
 Urban Water Supply and                       Access to (use of and satisfaction with) `safe' source                     WMS&#13;
 Sanitation                                   of water in urban areas                                                    Demographic and health&#13;
                                              Access to (use of and satisfaction with) `safe'                            surveys&#13;
                                              sanitation facilities in urban areas                                       Census of Ethiopia&#13;
                                              Status of hygiene practices in urban poor                                  MWR special surveys and&#13;
                                              communities                                                                annual review reports&#13;
                                              Financial and operational performance indicators for                       MWR ­ (later regulator?)&#13;
                                              urban WSPs&#13;
                                              Access to (use of and satisfaction with) for the urban                     MWR ­ (later regulator?)&#13;
                                              poor to `safe' water and sanitation&#13;
  Note: These monitoring indicators are based on the proposals above. However, these will need to be defined in greater detail and in consultation with key&#13;
                                                                      stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                           23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                  WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            REFERENCES&#13;
&#13;
1. Christian Relief Development Association (CRDA, 1997), "Watsan: Challenges and opportunities",&#13;
    March, mimeo.&#13;
2. CSA (1994), Census of Ethiopia : Population Tables.&#13;
3. CSA (1996) Results of the HHICE.&#13;
4. CSA (1998), Results of the Welfare Monitoring Survey.&#13;
5. Environmental Support Project (2001), "Status Report, Volume 1: Summary, Volume II: Physical&#13;
    Resource Base, Volume III: Financial and Economic Resource Base, Volume IV: Legal, Institutional and&#13;
    Human Resource Development", Report of the ESP, by DHV Consultants for MWR, GOE.&#13;
6. Government of Ethiopia (2001), Federal Budget 2001-02, author.&#13;
7. Government of Uganda (2001), "Strategy for rural water investment', mimeo.&#13;
8. Lium T. and Garvey G (2001), "ESRDF supervision mission report: Rural water supply and sanitation&#13;
    component", mimeo.&#13;
9. Ministry of Water Resources (MWR, 1997), "Data compilation and analysis project, January, a report by&#13;
    consultants Ernst and Young / Tropics.&#13;
10. Ministry of Water Resources (2000), "Water Sector Development Program: Sector Review Report",&#13;
    February, Federal Republic of Ethiopia. Report done by Water Works Design and Supervision&#13;
    Enterprise.&#13;
11. Ministry of Water Resources (nd), "Ethiopian Water Resources Management Policy", Federal Republic of&#13;
    Ethiopia.&#13;
12. Ministry of Water Resources (2001a), "Water Supply and Sanitation Development Strategy", April,&#13;
    Federal Republic of Ethiopia.&#13;
13. Ministry of Water Resources (2001b), "Water Sector Development Program: Methodological&#13;
    Framework", mimeo.&#13;
14. Ministry of Water Resources (2001c), "Water Sector Development Program", Draft, Volumes I to IV,&#13;
    Federal Republic of Ethiopia. Report done by Water Works Design and Supervision Enterprise.&#13;
15. Ministry of Water Resources (2002), "Water Sector Development Program", Draft Final ­ Executive&#13;
    Summary, Federal Republic of Ethiopia. Report done by Water Works Design and Supervision&#13;
    Enterprise.&#13;
16. Rahmato D. and Kidanu A. (1999), "Consultations with the Poor: A study to inform the World&#13;
    Development Report 2000-01 on Poverty and Development", National Report, Ethiopia, mimeo.&#13;
17. Sahilu T (2001), "The challenge of designing a pro-poor tariff structure", paper presented at the Regional&#13;
    Workshop on `Building partnerships to provide WSS services to the urban poor, at Abidjan, November,&#13;
    mimeo.&#13;
18. Sahle Sisay and Associates (1999), "Study on operation and maintenance strategies of rural water supply&#13;
    schemes", study for the Amhara State Water, Mines and Energy Resources Development Bureau, May,&#13;
    mimeo.&#13;
19. Sima G (2001), "ESRDF - RWS Performance", presentation at the national workshop on RWSS&#13;
    Performance Review in Addis Ababa, November, mimeo.&#13;
20. World Bank (1999), "Ethiopia: Public Expenditure Review", Volume I and II, author.&#13;
21. World Bank (2000a), "Ethiopia: Regionalization Study", author.&#13;
22. World Bank (2000b), "Ethiopia: Public Expenditure Review", Volume I and II, author.&#13;
23. World Bank (2000c), "World Development Report", author.&#13;
24. World Bank (2001a), "The Woreda Study: main Phase", October, mimeo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                         WSS Inputs For Ethiopia Full PRSP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Annex 1: Notes and sources for Table 1&#13;
&#13;
Access to safe water: Share of population with reasonable access (distance/time) to an adequate amount (20&#13;
lpcd) of safe water (World Development Report, 2000). 1993-99 or the latest available year.&#13;
&#13;
Access to sanitation facilities: Percentage of population with access to sanitation facilities (ADI, p. 316). 1993-97&#13;
or the latest available year.&#13;
&#13;
Adult Illiteracy Rate: Percentage of population 15 and above who are illiterate (WDR, 2000, p. 276). For 1998.&#13;
&#13;
Net enrollment ­ primary: Ratio of no. of children enrolled to no. of children of official school age in population&#13;
(UNESCO data) ­ 1990-94 or the latest available year.&#13;
&#13;
Malnutrition: Percentage children under five years of age suffering from moderate to severe underweight&#13;
(ADI, p. 315) ­ 1990-97 or the latest available year.&#13;
&#13;
Infant Mortality Rate (IMR): Number of children who have died between birth and first birthday expressed per&#13;
1000 live births (IDG, p. 14). For 1998.&#13;
&#13;
Under-5 mortality rate: No. of deaths of children under 5 yrs of age per 1000 live births in a given year. ADI,&#13;
p. 313, for 1998.&#13;
&#13;
Annex 2: Notes and sources for Table 6&#13;
&#13;
1.       Estimate of WSS share in federal budget:&#13;
         ·     Source: Federal budget reports.&#13;
         ·     Notes: For water supply within MWR, allocations to department of WSS and capacity building&#13;
               and support are both included.&#13;
2.       Estimate of total regional budget and share of RWB and WSS:&#13;
         ·     Source: for total federal subsidy to regions: Federal budget; for share of own resources in total&#13;
               region budget: Ministry of Finance.&#13;
         ·     Total regional budget is estimated by using the total federal subsidy to regions (as reported in the&#13;
               federal budget ­ 6.7 billion birr) and the share of region own resources in the total regional&#13;
               budget is assumed to be 30 percent.&#13;
         ·     For share of capital budget in total regional WSS budget, information from the World Bank&#13;
               database for actual expenditure during the period 1996-97 to 1999-00 for regional water bureau&#13;
               has been used. Share of capital expenditure has been assumed to be 80 percent. The same source&#13;
               has been also used for share of RWBs in total regional budget, assumed to be 8 percent.&#13;
&#13;
3.       Estimate of ESRDF budget for RWSS: Estimated to be 98 million birr, based on an average of 108.3&#13;
         and 87.3 million birr during the previous two years. (Source: Sima, 2001).&#13;
&#13;
4.       Estimate of NGO / bilateral expenditure: No current information is readily available. The share of&#13;
         20 percent is based on a old CRDA study that had estimated that the NGO expenditures were higher&#13;
         than the government's own budgets.&#13;
&#13;
5.       Exchange rate used: 1 US$ = 8.3 ET birr.&#13;
&#13;
6.       Other notes:&#13;
         ·     Sanitation and hygiene promotion have not been covered in these estimates.&#13;
         ·     Estimates for WSP expenditures need to be added&#13;
         ·     Estimates of possible allocations by municipal authorities also need to be added.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
     About The Sector Finance and Resource Flows Series                                                          Africa Region&#13;
                                                                                                                 World Bank Hill Park Building&#13;
The Sector Finance and Resource Flows reports are based on country                                               Upper Hill Road&#13;
studies on water and sanitation sector financing in Africa. The aim is to                                        Nairobi&#13;
provide assistance to sector leaders, policy makers and development                                              Kenya&#13;
partners to help African countries meet the Millennium Development&#13;
Goals on water and sanitation through: rationalizing allocation of public                                        Phone: +254-20-3226306&#13;
funds, leveraging non-public resources and improving targeting of                                                Fax: +254-20-3226386&#13;
required subsidies.                                                                                              E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Other Sector Finance Publications by WSP-AF&#13;
                                                                                                                  WSP MISSION&#13;
Sector Finance and Resource Flows Publications                                                                    To help the poor gain sustained access to&#13;
                                                                                                                  improved water and sanitation services.&#13;
Strengthening Budget Mechanisms for Sanitation in Uganda.&#13;
                                                                                                                  WSP FUNDING PARTNERS&#13;
Sector Finance and Resource Flows Assessments for Water Supply ­ A pilot                                          The Governments of Australia, Austria,&#13;
application for Kenya.                                                                                            Belgium, Canada, Denmark, Germany, Italy,&#13;
                                                                                                                  Japan, Luxembourg, the Netherlands,&#13;
Ethiopia Water Supply Sector Resource Flows Assessment.                                                           Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United&#13;
                                                                                                                  Kingdom, the United Nations Development&#13;
                                                                                                                  Programme, and The World Bank.&#13;
Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Finance and Resource Flows Assessment;&#13;
Zambia                                                                                                            ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
                                                                                                                  This document was prepared in response to a&#13;
PRSP Publications ­ Available online at www.wsp.org                                                               request from the Ministry of Water Resources,&#13;
                                                                                                                  Government of Ethiopia. We have benefited&#13;
Water and Sanitation in PRSP Initiatives-A Desk Review of the Emerging                                            from detailed discussions and feedback from&#13;
&#13;
Experience in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA)                                                                            staff of Ministry of Water Resources: Ato&#13;
                                                                                                                  Mesfin Tegene, Vice Minister for Water&#13;
                                                                                                                  Resources, Ato Gulilat Berhane, Head,&#13;
Water supply and Sanitation in Poverty Strategy Papers in Sub-Saharan Africa:                                     Department of Planning and Projects, Ato&#13;
Developing a Benchmarking Reviewand Exploring the Way Forward                                                     Tesfaye Wolde Meheret, Coordinator of the&#13;
                                                                                                                  Water Sector Strategy and Development&#13;
Factors behind the Poor Integration of the Water and Sanitation Sector in                                         Program, Ato Yohaness G. Medhen, Head,&#13;
PRSPs in Sub-Saharan Africa-Lessons from Uganda, Malawi and Zambia-Brief                                          Department of Rural Water Supply and&#13;
(with ODI at www.odi.org.uk)                                                                                      Sanitation Services. We have also benefited&#13;
                                                                                                                  from comments on the draft report provided by&#13;
&#13;
Sector Financing-Global and Regional Reviews - Available online at                                                Duvvuri Subbarao, Catherine Revels and&#13;
                                                                                                                  Yitbarek Taseema of the World Bank, and&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                       Jean Doyen of WSP-Africa.&#13;
&#13;
The challenge of Financing Sanitation for Meeting the Millennium Development                                      The task team comprised Meera Mehta as&#13;
Goals                                                                                                             Task Manager and Belete Mulune of WSP-&#13;
                                                                                                                  Africa.&#13;
Meeting the Financing Challenge for Water Supply and Sanitation (Full Report)&#13;
                                                                                                                  Production Assistance: Shamis Salah,&#13;
&#13;
Meeting the Financing Challenge for Water Supply and Sanitation (Summary)                                         Jecinter Hezron and Florence Makokha&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Financing Small Water Supply and Sanitation Service Providers: Exploring the                                      Created by: WSP - Africa&#13;
Micro-Finance Option in Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
&#13;
Financing the Millennium Development Goals for Water and Sanitation: What&#13;
will it take? Synthesis paper for Global WASH Forum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The WSP working papers disseminate the findings of work in progress to encourage the exchange of lessons&#13;
and experiences on water and sanitation issues. An objective of the series is to get the findings out quickly,&#13;
even if the presentations are less than fully polished. The findings, interpretations and conclusions expressed&#13;
in the papers are entirely those of the authors. Dissemination of the material is encouraged and the Water&#13;
and Sanitation Program will normally grant permission promptly. For questions about this report, including&#13;
permission to reprint portions or information about ordering more copies, please contact the Water and&#13;
Sanitation Program by e-mail. The WSP Working Papers are available online at http://www.wsp.org                                                    1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="7412482">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/02/7412482/water-supply-sanitation-inputs-ethiopia-full-prsp
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/02/7412482/water-supply-sanitation-inputs-ethiopia-full-prsp</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/02/7412482/water-supply-sanitation-inputs-ethiopia-full-prsp</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2007/02/23/000310607_20070223125717/Rendered/INDEX/387530ET0Water1tion0inputs01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2007/02/23/000310607_20070223125717/Rendered/PDF/387530ET0Water1tion0inputs01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2007-02-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2002-02-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Water supply and sanitation inputs for
            Ethiopia Full PRSP
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Water has been recognized as a priority
            area within the PRSP process in Ethiopia. Government of
            Ethiopia, through the Ministry of Water Resources (MWR) has
            requested WSP-AF assistance in developing the background
            materials for preparation of the WSS inputs for the full
            PRSP. This report has been prepared in response to this
            request, based on discussions with various stakeholders and
            a synthesis of available studies and consultant reports. It
            also draws on reports and proceedings of a number of
            consultations that the MWR has had with different
            stakeholders at federal and regional levels. This paper
            includes the following headings: introduction; situation
            assessment 1 - WSS and poverty linkage; situation assessment
            2 - policy, institutional and financing issues; priorities
            for poverty reduction - action plans, targets, and
            expenditure requirements; and WSS sector monitoring and evaluation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Water supply and sanitation inputs for
            Ethiopia Full PRSP
        </docna>
        <display_title>Water supply and sanitation
            inputs for Ethiopia Full PRSP</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/02/7412482/water-supply-sanitation-inputs-ethiopia-full-prsp</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Systems,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Ethiopia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000310607_20070223125717</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program sector finance
            working paper ; no. 2</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            acceptable quality, access to safe water,
            access to sanitation, access to sanitation facilities,
            access to water, adequate provision, adequate stakeholder
            consultation, Allocation of water, appropriate technology,
            augmentation, bilateral agencies, bilateral donors,
            boreholes, broad range, capacity building, child health,
            clean water, collection of water, community management,
            community participation, connections, cost recovery, cost
            recovery policies, cost sharing, distribution network,
            drought, environmental sanitation, facility, financial
            viability, food security, hand-pumps, health conditions,
            households, hygiene, hygiene promotion, investment
            requirements, irrigation, lack of water, Lakes, large towns,
            Mortality Rate, National Water, National Water Policy,
            National Water Resources, National Water Resources
            Management, operational efficiency, operators, piped water,
            protected springs, public tap, regional government, rivers,
            rural communities, Rural towns, Rural water, Rural water
            supply, sanitary facilities, sanitary latrine, sanitation,
            sanitation activities, Sanitation Committee, sanitation
            facilities, sanitation policy, Sanitation Program,
            sanitation sector, sanitation sector policies, Sanitation
            Service, Sanitation Service Providers, Sanitation Services,
            service provider, service provision, Sewerage, Sewerage
            Authority, Small towns, Smaller towns, spare parts, springs,
            Supply water, taps, tariff setting, Town, Town Water, towns,
            urban area, urban areas, urban centers, urban services,
            urban settlements, urban sewerage, Urban Water, Urban Water
            Supply, users, water, Water Board, Water Boards, water
            collection, Water Departments, water investments, Water
            Policy, water pricing, water resource, Water Resources,
            Water Resources Development, Water Resources Management,
            water schemes, Water Sector, Water Sector Development, Water
            Service, water service providers, water sources, water
            strategy, Water Supply, wells
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water - Water &amp; Sant. Prgrm-AFR (GWASA)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>38753</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Handwashing Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural &amp; Small Town Water &amp; Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Ethiopia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>