<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>CapDev No14 12.14.05.qxd     12/14/05    4:32 PM  Page 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 38910&#13;
&#13;
                    Capacity Development&#13;
                                                                                   B R I E F S&#13;
                      S H A R I N G K N O W L E D G E A N D L E S S O N S L E A R N E D&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               APPLYING A CAPACITY-RESULTS FRAMEWORK&#13;
               IN LAO PDR AND OTHER PILOT COUNTRIES&#13;
               Chirine Alameddine and Moira Hart-Poliquin, World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       Achieving the Millennium Development Goals (MDG) and poverty reduction objectives of develop-&#13;
                     ing countries requires a substantially greater investment in capacity development. This translates&#13;
                     into action at three levels: improving the skills of individuals, developing organizational processes&#13;
                     and systems, and creating an enabling environment that can support the achievement of these goals.&#13;
                     The process of planning and implementing strategies for strengthening capacity can seem over-&#13;
                     whelming for development practitioners. Unbundling the capacity elements into actionable compo-&#13;
                     nents at the institutional, organizational, and individual levels and linking them to specific results&#13;
                     can eliminate much of the perceived complexity that often accompanies the planning process. One&#13;
                     way to begin is by using a capacity-results matrix to work through the process. Such a matrix is&#13;
                     designed to help prioritize results, disaggregate capacity constraints, determine needed capacity&#13;
                     interventions, and agree on indicators to measure progress.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 A series of consultations with the East Asia-Pacific            the need to (a) communicate to the client that&#13;
               Regional operations of the World Bank that began in               capacity is critical to the success and sustainabil-&#13;
               2003 focused on the need to develop a strategy to                 ity of the project and (b) encourage stakeholders&#13;
               incorporate capacity development at the heart of                  to invest resources for bridging the capacity gap.&#13;
               Bank operations. The Region had decided to make                   For example, the Forest Management and&#13;
               Lao PDR a capacity development pilot country and to               Conservation Project emphasized the importance&#13;
               test this more comprehensive approach at integrat-                of communicating to government officials and&#13;
               ing capacity into Bank work. A new country assis-                 other stakeholders the multiple benefits of&#13;
               tance strategy (CAS) would provide the instrument                 investing in capacity development, particularly&#13;
               for testing the strategy. As a starting point, WBI                at the community level. Building capacity for vil-&#13;
               conducted an internal assessment of ten completed                 lage-based management would result in more&#13;
               and ongoing sample projects from a cross-section of               efficient tax and royalty collection, which would&#13;
               service delivery sectors, including a review of project           enhance regional and central budgets.&#13;
               appraisal documents, implementation completion               ·    Implementation: Assessment of the implementa-&#13;
               reports, Operations Evaluation Department reviews,                tion stage revealed the vital role of committed&#13;
               and supervision reports. WBI also conducted inter-                leadership in generating client cooperation, the&#13;
               views with task team leaders to assess the impact                 higher effectiveness of learning-by-doing com-&#13;
               that capacity development interventions had on pro-               pared with lecture-style training, the importance&#13;
               ject results. Key findings from the assessment                    of effective monitoring and evaluation of capacity&#13;
               include the following:                                            development interventions to measure perfor-&#13;
                                                                                 mance gains, and the importance of defining&#13;
               ·   Design: An assessment of the planning stages of               clear, up-front objectives for client training. For&#13;
                   projects in the Lao portfolio revealed that only a            instance, in the Land Titling Project, compensa-&#13;
                   few of the projects identified specific capacities            tion for external technical advisers was based not&#13;
                   needed for achieving results. Lessons included&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       D E C E M B E R 2 0 0 5&#13;
&#13;
                       NUMBER 14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CapDev No14 12.14.05.qxd                  12/14/05  4:32 PM     Page 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            only on completing the training, but also on mea-                         What Is the Capacity-Results Framework?&#13;
            surable learning gains among the trained clients.                           The capacity-results framework is a tool for use&#13;
        ·   Monitoring: Many of the projects lacked adequate                          jointly by Bank staff and the client to facilitate dia-&#13;
            indicators to measure capacity development.                               logue and strategic thinking on critical capacity&#13;
            Where measurable indicators were present, the                             issues. The framework strategically focuses on capac-&#13;
            timelines provided were often overly ambitious.                           ity and knowledge at the institutional, organizational,&#13;
            Main lessons included the importance of setting                           and individual levels (see table 1).&#13;
            realistic targets and timelines, identifying&#13;
            resources required to achieve the project goals,                          ·    At the institutional level, the enabling environ-&#13;
            and encouraging effective communication with                                   ment helps shape how organizations and individ-&#13;
            the client to ensure that performance targets and                              uals can effectively perform their functions and&#13;
            timelines are clear and achievable.                                            solve problems in any given sector.&#13;
        ·   Sustainability: One of the most notable lessons                           ·    At the organizational level, issues relevant to&#13;
            was the need for sustained involvement through-                                task-oriented organizations, such as management&#13;
            out the life of the project, which allows for better                           systems and business processes, need to be&#13;
            monitoring of performance. In the transport sec-                               assessed. The way all these organizations collec-&#13;
            tor, for example, the key to attaining this                                    tively interact and operate to generate target out-&#13;
            involvement was convincing the stakeholders                                    comes ultimately determines overall organiza-&#13;
            that maintenance of roads is as essential as con-                              tional capacity.&#13;
            struction and is best achieved through an&#13;
            increased focus on capacity development. Those                            ·    At the individual level, key learning areas, motiva-&#13;
&#13;
            projects with an increased focus on capacity                                   tional factors, assessment tools, and learning de-&#13;
&#13;
            development proved more effective in sustaining                                livery mechanisms need to be thoroughly assessed&#13;
&#13;
            project outcomes.                                                              as part of a comprehensive well-structured and&#13;
                                                                                           results-oriented capacity-building program.&#13;
&#13;
          In light of the findings of the project portfolio&#13;
        review, a simple capacity-results matrix was devel-                             The results chain, on the left of the table, focuses on&#13;
&#13;
        oped as a tool for engaging clients on a results-ori-                         assessing the current level of capacity of ministries,&#13;
&#13;
        ented capacity development approach. The objective of                         agencies, and other local institutions; designing inter-&#13;
&#13;
        this matrix is to (a) identify capacity gaps that con-                        ventions to address capacity gaps; and agreeing with&#13;
&#13;
        strain project outcomes, (b) design interventions to                          the client on a realistic timeline and set of indicators&#13;
&#13;
        address these gaps, and (c) develop indicators that                           to monitor progress toward achieving the desired&#13;
&#13;
        can be jointly monitored with the client.                                     results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Table 1: The Capacity Results-Framework&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Institutional                     Organizational                    Individual&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Incentives, norms, laws,         Processes and systems             Targeted skills and&#13;
                                                      rules, or policies that          enabling task-oriented            knowledge required&#13;
                                                      enable organizations and         organizations to manage           for individuals to&#13;
                                                      individuals to achieve           resources, perform                perform functions&#13;
                                                      development results              functions, and achieve&#13;
                                                                                       and sustain outcomes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Baseline                            Current level of capacity relative to what is&#13;
                                         Capacity                            required to achieve the desired outcome&#13;
                Chain&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Inputs/                            Menu of interventions and strategies&#13;
                     Results      Interventions                              to redress constraints&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Outcome/                             Simple, customized, and measurable indicators&#13;
                                      Indicators                             that proxy for progress toward results&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            D E C E M B E R 2 0 0 5&#13;
&#13;
                            NUMBER 14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CapDev No14 12.14.05.qxd    12/14/05     4:32 PM     Page 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Table 2: Example of a Capacity-Results Framework (Lao PDR)&#13;
&#13;
                 Objective: Strengthening capacity of the Ministry of Communication, Transport, Post, and Construction (MCTPC) to sustain and&#13;
                 scale up the road maintenance culture&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            Institutional                        Organizational                               Individual&#13;
                                      (norms, incentives, rules)        (business processes and systems)                        (skills)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Capacity         · Lack of clarity and weak            · Low management capacity in              · Low levels of technical,&#13;
                 constraint         accountability of provinces           provinces in procurement,                 administrative, and managerial&#13;
                                    for managing the Road                 monitoring, and financial                 skills in planning, reporting,&#13;
                                    Maintenance Fund (RMF)                management in the private                 procurement, monitoring,&#13;
                                  · Continued dependence on               sector and at the village level&#13;
                                    donors to finance RMF               · Weak performance measurement&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Capacity         · Country-to-country dialogue to      · Consultant report assessing             · Training for staff by MCTPC&#13;
                 development        share and demonstrate good            needs and baseline capacities             in the above key functions&#13;
                 interventions      practice in maintenance culture       of core and support functions             provided&#13;
                                  · Public information strategy         · Workshop to disseminate                 · Series of formal events&#13;
                                    through periodic reporting            results and implement                     and informal learning&#13;
                                    to broaden awareness of               performance measurement                   activities implemented&#13;
                                    RMF status                            system across provinces                   by MCTPC for multiple&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        · Study completed on functional             stakeholders (government&#13;
                                                                          benchmarking to improve                   and contractors) in key&#13;
                                                                          performance                               support functions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Intermediate     · Increased clarity by MCTPC          · Standardized indicators used            · Improved competence in&#13;
                 outcome            and other stakeholders on             by MCTPC to benchmark                     performing technical&#13;
                                    roles and responsibilities            and measure performance                   administrative and managerial&#13;
                                    for managing the RMF                  of core and support functions             functions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Indicators       · Increase in share of RMF            · Increase in number of provinces         · Increase in number of qualified&#13;
                                    covered by national budget            using performance indicators              staff in performing core and&#13;
                                                                        · Increase in the number                    support functions&#13;
                                                                          of provinces autonomously&#13;
                                                                          managing core and support&#13;
                                                                          processes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 For example, one of the objectives of the Second&#13;
               Road Maintenance Program (RMP2) is to scale up the                     Expected Benefits of a Results-Oriented&#13;
               road maintenance culture and strengthen capacities at                  Approach to Capacity Development&#13;
               the provincial levels for managing the road mainte-&#13;
               nance fund (see table 2). During the pre-appraisal                     · Expands focus beyond building individual skills to strength-&#13;
                                                                                        ening organizational systems and creating an enabling envi-&#13;
               mission, the World Bank and the Ministry of                              ronment in which individuals and organizations operate&#13;
               Communication, Transport, Post, and Construction                       · Encourages country ownership of results by jointly devel-&#13;
               designed a comprehensive human resource strategy                         oping indicators for monitoring program interventions and&#13;
&#13;
               intended to institutionalize skills and processes                        tracking progress on developing capacity at each level&#13;
&#13;
               required for decentralization in all provinces. The                    · Acts as an analytical process tool that (a) helps assess&#13;
                                                                                        capacities needed to achieve specific development results,&#13;
               World Bank and the government reached an explicit                        (b) facilitates the design of interventions and clarifies&#13;
               agreement to submit a satisfactory capacity develop-                     accountabilities at each level, and (c) can be used by the&#13;
&#13;
               ment proposal. The client has welcomed using this                        country to improve communication and coordination with&#13;
                                                                                        donors around critical capacity issues&#13;
               systematic capacity-results tool, which is embedded                    · Is replicable for capacity gaps or problems regardless of&#13;
               both in the project document and in a capacity-build-                    sector.&#13;
               ing Policy and Human Resources Development grant.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CapDev No14 12.14.05.qxd         12/14/05       4:32 PM     Page 4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Table 3: Examples of Application of a                                Table 4: Examples of Application of a&#13;
           Results Approach in Madagascar                                       Results Approach in Chad&#13;
&#13;
             WBI is engaged in ongoing governance work in                         WBI is working with local counterparts in the civil service&#13;
           Madagascar and is providing support to the Governance and            and representatives from public and private local institutes&#13;
           Institutional Development Project (known by its French ini-          that provide training in the field of public financial manage-&#13;
           tials PGDI) management team, contributing to the develop-            ment. The objective is to define and prioritize clearly the&#13;
           ment of a clear results framework at the national level. This        capacity development needs in the civil service, while assist-&#13;
           includes the alignment of capacity investments with priority         ing local training institutes on building their capacities to&#13;
           results of the country.                                              respond to this demand.&#13;
&#13;
             At the level of the PGDI, the capacity-results framework is          In the first phase of this work, WBI worked with a number&#13;
&#13;
           currently being used in the development of annual work pro-          of local training institutes to internalize the capacity-results&#13;
&#13;
           grams, curriculum reform, and monitoring frameworks for              approach and help them better focus their capacity develop-&#13;
&#13;
           two civil service training institutes supported by the project.      ment programs. This work has resulted in the institutes com-&#13;
                                                                                ing together to create a confederation of Chadian training&#13;
                                                                                institutes with the aim of improving access to and exchange&#13;
                                                                                of information and expertise nationally and internationally.&#13;
&#13;
        This approach has also been introduced in                               Representatives from this confederation are currently partici-&#13;
                                                                                pating in intensive in-country consultations with civil service&#13;
        Madagascar and Chad, where capacity development                         representatives to develop a comprehensive action plan for&#13;
        activities are currently under implementation. (See                     improving the public financial management system.&#13;
&#13;
        tables 3 and 4)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          The 2005 Lao PDR CAS presented an opportunity to                   and sequence actions and inputs at the three levels.&#13;
        pilot a process of integrating capacity development                  Although this method may prove useful in prioritizing&#13;
        into different CAS instruments. This is a dynamic                    capacity issues for Bank teams, ownership of the&#13;
        learning process that will be continuously reviewed                  approach by the client will be critical to its successful&#13;
        and updated as new lessons emerge during imple-                      implementation. This approach will also enable gov-&#13;
        mentation. The capacity-results framework was intro-                 ernments to communicate to development partners&#13;
        duced as a tool to help initiate dialogue with the client            their priorities for external assistance in capacity&#13;
        on critical capacity issues. One way of helping clients              development.&#13;
        grapple with the capacity problem is by directly link-&#13;
        ing capacity constraints with priority results. The&#13;
        results chain, as illustrated earlier in the capacity                Peer reviewers: Zafar Ahmed, senior economist in&#13;
&#13;
        results framework, allows development practitioners                  the East Asia-Pacific Region of the World Bank,&#13;
&#13;
        to think backward from the outcome and to prioritize                 and Dorte Kabell, a Danish evaluation specialist.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            About World Bank Institute (WBI): Unleashing the Power of Knowledge to Enable a World Free of Poverty&#13;
&#13;
            WBI helps people, institutions, and countries to diagnose problems that keep communities poor, to make&#13;
            informed choices to solve those problems, and to share what they learn with others. Through traditional&#13;
            and distance learning methods, WBI and its partners in many countries deliver knowledge-based options&#13;
            to policymakers, technical experts, business and community leaders, and civil society stakeholders; fos-&#13;
            tering analytical and networking skills to help them make sound decisions, design effective socioeconomic&#13;
            policies and programs, and unleash the productive potential of their societies.&#13;
&#13;
            WBI Contacts:&#13;
            Mark Nelson; Program Manager, Capacity Development Resource Center&#13;
            Tel: 202-458-8041, Email: mnelson1@worldbank.org&#13;
            Pinki Chaudhuri, Coordinator&#13;
            Tel: 202-458-5787, E-mail: pchaudhuri@worldbank.org&#13;
            Visit our website for more information and download the electronic copies of all Capacity Development Briefs:&#13;
            http://www.worldbank.org/capacity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 D E C E M B E R 2 0 0 5&#13;
&#13;
                 NUMBER 14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="7444037">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/12/7444037/applying-capacity-results-framework-lao-pdr-other-pilot-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2005/12/7444037/applying-capacity-results-framework-lao-pdr-other-pilot-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2005/12/7444037/applying-capacity-results-framework-lao-pdr-other-pilot-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2007/03/08/000090341_20070308142958/Rendered/INDEX/389100LAO0CapacityBrief0No1401PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2007/03/08/000090341_20070308142958/Rendered/PDF/389100LAO0CapacityBrief0No1401PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2007-03-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2005-12-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Applying a capacity-results framework in
            Lao PDR and other pilot countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Achieving the Millennium Development
            Goals (MDG) and poverty reduction objectives of developing
            countries requires a substantially greater investment in
            capacity development. This translates into action at three
            levels: improving the skills of individuals, developing
            organizational processes and systems, and creating an
            enabling environment that can support the achievement of
            these goals. The process of planning and implementing
            strategies for strengthening capacity can seem overwhelming
            for development practitioners. Unbundling the capacity
            elements into actionable components at the institutional,
            organizational, and individual levels and linking them to
            specific results can eliminate much of the perceived
            complexity that often accompanies the planning process. One
            way to begin is by using a capacity-results matrix to work
            through the process. Such a matrix is designed to help
            prioritize results, disaggregate capacity constraints,
            determine needed capacity interventions, and agree on
            indicators to measure progress.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Applying a capacity-results framework in Lao
            PDR and other pilot countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Applying a capacity-results
            framework in Lao PDR and other pilot countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2005/12/7444037/applying-capacity-results-framework-lao-pdr-other-pilot-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Social Policy,Civil Society,Poverty Reduction Strategies,Government Diagnostic Capacity Building</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Social Development,Poverty Reduction,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Alameddine, Chirine</author>
            <author>Hart-Poliquin, Moira</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20070308142958</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Capacity development briefs ; no. 14</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Social Development,Poverty Reduction,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Capacity development;Poverty
            reduction;Capacity results framework
        </keywd>
        <owner>Office of the Regional Vice Pres (EAPVP)</owner>
        <repnb>38910</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Curriculum Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Curriculum Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>