<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                            Document of&#13;
                                         The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
                                FOR OFFICIAL USEONLY&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          ReportNo: T7692 - LB&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                               ONA&#13;
&#13;
                                       PROPOSEDGRANT&#13;
&#13;
                             INTHEAMOUNT OFUS$5MILLION&#13;
&#13;
                          FROMTHE TRUST FUNDFOR LEBANON&#13;
&#13;
                                              TO THE&#13;
&#13;
                                     LEBANESEREPUBLIC&#13;
&#13;
                                             FOR THE&#13;
&#13;
  EMERGENCY POWER SECTOR REFORM CAPACITY REINFORCEMENT PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                         February26,2007&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SustainableDevelopmentDepartment&#13;
Middle East andNorth Africa&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricted distribution and may be used by recipients only in the&#13;
performance o f their official duties. Its contents may not otherwise be disclosedwithout World&#13;
Bank authorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                          CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
&#13;
                 (Exchange Rate Effective average January, 2007)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Currency Unit = Lebanese Pound&#13;
                                 1US$ = 1,1512LBP&#13;
&#13;
                                 1 LBP = O.O00661US$&#13;
&#13;
                                 FISCAL YEAR&#13;
                            January 1   - December31&#13;
&#13;
                     ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CDR    Counsil for Development and Reconstruction&#13;
EdL    Lebanese Power Company "Electvicite` du Liban "&#13;
EMP    Environmental MonitoringPlan&#13;
ESIA   Economic and Social Impact Assessment&#13;
FM     Financial Management&#13;
GOL    Government o f Lebanon&#13;
HCP    Higher Council for Privatization&#13;
IBRD   International Bank for Reconstructionand Development&#13;
IPP    IndependentPower Producer&#13;
LNG    LiquefiedNatural Gas&#13;
MOEW   Ministryo fEnergyand Water&#13;
MOF    Ministryo fFinance&#13;
PFM    Project Financial Management&#13;
SA     Special Account&#13;
SOE    Statement o f Expenditures     .&#13;
WA     Withdrawal Application&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Vice President:     Daniela Gressani&#13;
                      Country Director:     Joseph Saba&#13;
                        Sector Director     Inger Andersen&#13;
                       Sector Manager:      Jonathan D. Walters&#13;
                    Task Team Leader:       Anna Bjerde&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                              FOROFFICIAL USEONLY&#13;
                                                               LEBANON&#13;
&#13;
            EMERGENCYPOWERSECTOR REFORMCAPACITY REINFORCEMENT&#13;
                                                               PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      A .  Background and Strategy            .....................................................................................................       1&#13;
         1.   Background.........................................................................................................................         1&#13;
        2.    Impact o f the July 2006 Hostilities .....................................................................................                  2&#13;
        3.    Government Strategy .......................................................................................................... 3&#13;
&#13;
      B Bank Response and Strategy&#13;
       .                                             ...............................................................................................      5&#13;
&#13;
      C .  Detailed Project Description             ................................................................................................      6&#13;
         1.   Project development objective and key indicators..............................................................                              6&#13;
        2.    Project components and cost...............................................................................................                  6&#13;
        3. Lessons learned and reflected inthe project design...............................................................                              8&#13;
&#13;
      D Institutional Arrangements and Project Implementation&#13;
       .                                                                                               .................................................  9&#13;
         1. Institutional and implementationarrangements.....................................................................                             9&#13;
        2. Monitoringand evaluation of outcomesh-esults...................................................................                               10&#13;
        3. Procurement arrangements...................................................................................................                   10&#13;
        4. Financial management and disbursement arrangements......................................................                                      11&#13;
        5. Safeguards............................................................................................... :............................       14&#13;
        6. Sustainability and Risks....................................................................................................... 15&#13;
&#13;
     E Economic and FiscalJustification&#13;
       .                                                     .....................................................................................       16&#13;
&#13;
     Annex 1: Results Framework and Monitoring                             ........................................................................      17&#13;
&#13;
     Annex 2: Matrix for the Implementation of Sector Reforms                                        .................................................   19&#13;
&#13;
     Annex 3: Project Preparation and Supervision                           .......................................................................      22&#13;
&#13;
     Annex 4: Statement of Loans and Credits                      ................................................................................       23&#13;
&#13;
     Annex 5: Country at a Glance             ...................................................................................................        24&#13;
&#13;
     Annex 6: Map (IBRD No          .33433)...............................................................................................               26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This document has a restricted distribution and may be used by recipients only in the performance o f&#13;
their official duties. Its contents may not be otherwise disclosed without World Bank authorization.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A. BACKGROUNDAND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
 1. Background&#13;
&#13;
Lebanon's electricity sector suffers from years o f overall poor governance, weak institutional,&#13;
management and technical capacity, and a serious lack of investment in operation and&#13;
maintenance as well as new infrastructure. This has ledto poor quality o f service, low consumer&#13;
confidence in public service provision, high cost o f electricity and inadequate cost-recovery.&#13;
The main consequences are a considerable dependence of the sector on budgetary subsidies&#13;
estimated by the Ministry o f Finance to be close to US$1 billion in 2006 and high additional&#13;
costs born by users, particularly industries, to compensate for the unreliability o f power supply.&#13;
This situationis expected to further deteriorate unless drastic actions are taken soon.&#13;
&#13;
The problems date back to the end o f the 1975-1990 civil war, when Electricit6 du Liban (EdL)&#13;
struggled, without success, to resume reliable and affordable electricity services throughout&#13;
Lebanon. The main outstanding issues can be summarized as follows:&#13;
&#13;
     The cost o f electricity generation i s high because o f lack of access to natural gas for power&#13;
     generation.    Out o f Lebanon's four main generation plants, two plants were originally&#13;
     designed and built to operate on natural gas but instead run on very expensive gas oil. The&#13;
     two other main plants (Jiyeh and Zouk) have long passed their refurbishing time and have&#13;
     high generation cost and use imported fuel oil which is subject to high international oil&#13;
     prices;&#13;
     The system operation is inefficient. Plant efficiency is below normal levels due to poor&#13;
     maintenance, poor control o f fuel stocks and consumption, and an ad hoc dispatch to meet&#13;
     demand;&#13;
     The reliability o f supply is poor. The transmission network is fraught with problems. The&#13;
     main 220kV backbone grid i s not yet fully completed, nor i s the long-planned national load&#13;
     control center inplace. Major investments are also requiredinthe medium- and low-voltage&#13;
     transmission and distribution systems as well as in metering to reduce transmission and&#13;
     distribution losses. But EdL's worsening deficiency inmanagerial and technical capacity, as&#13;
     well as poor planning and execution o f funding have long delayed implementation o f&#13;
     investmentprograms;&#13;
     Metering, billing and collection are highly inefficient. Technical losses are estimated at&#13;
     about 15%, while another 17.8% loss i s explained by illegal connections. In reality, out o f&#13;
     the 67% o f the power produced that EdL manages to bill for, about 90% on average i s&#13;
     eventually collected annually;&#13;
     EdL's management systems are outdated and ineffective. Accounting and financial reporting&#13;
     systems are not functioning adequately and do not allow the annual closing o f EdL's account&#13;
     or their auditing.   The consumer management system i s not reliable while the human&#13;
     resources management system i s also ineffective.&#13;
&#13;
The serious technical deficiencies in the sector are closely related to the poor governance o f the&#13;
sector and the lack o f implementation o f much needed reforms o f EdL. Indeed, a major problem&#13;
i s the legal status o f EdL as a non-commercial "Etablissement Public", which puts EdL's staff&#13;
under the status of civil servants, with an inadequate pay scale to retain competent managers and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
technical staff and career management rules incompatible with the operation o f a utility. EdL's&#13;
staff i s about 57 years old on average and EdL i s currently losing around 150 staff per year to&#13;
retirement out o f about 2,300 current employees. This is further aggravated by the lack o f a&#13;
sector strategy and o f a long term investment plan to orient investment decisions based on&#13;
economic and technical criteria and to ensure that investment decisions are made in a timely&#13;
manner. Finally, the vicious circle o f lack o f financing due to the socio-political difficulty to&#13;
charge cost reflective tariffs, leading to lack o f investment and poor service, which in turn&#13;
encourages power thefts and poor payment discipline, results in a widening financial gap. This&#13;
gap i s very vulnerable to changes in international oil prices as Lebanon imports all o f its energy&#13;
needs.&#13;
&#13;
Right before the hostilities broke out the situation with EdL had reached a critical point,&#13;
including a complete dearth o f human resources to manage operations and address financial and&#13;
administrative problems, a surge in sector deficits which had to be met through treasury&#13;
advances for fuel payments and debt service (from about US$275 million in 2003 to a total&#13;
burdeno f about US$570 million in 2005, and up to US$1billion in 2006; the latest figure was&#13;
heavily impacts by the high oil prices in 2006), and an all time low confidence in the sector by&#13;
the electricity consumers who due to lack o f electricity availability and frequent power cuts&#13;
equip themselves with costly back-up generators. This situation was further aggravated by the&#13;
adverse impact of the recent high prices o f crude oil, on which Lebanon relies heavily for its&#13;
power generation. The high pricing policy, along with the unreliable supply i s a major problem&#13;
for the industrial development in Lebanon, and thus a barrier to the country's overall economic&#13;
growth. Furthermore, low income consumers who cannot afford runningtheir own generator are&#13;
fully exposed to the effect o fun-reliablepower supply.&#13;
&#13;
The negative cumulative effect o f the inefficient situation had become impossible to ignore and&#13;
on July 6, 2006 the Council o f Ministers approved a reform program aimed at addressing the&#13;
most critical problems and achieving the quickest improvements possible. However, on July 13,&#13;
the hostilities broke out and, once again an electricity sector reform program was put to the side&#13;
as more urgentpriorities took over.&#13;
&#13;
2. Impact of the July 2006 Hostilities&#13;
&#13;
The hostilities lasted for 33 days. On August 14, 2006, a UN-brokered ceasefire brought an end&#13;
to the intense hostilities. The hostilities resulted in serious human and physical infrastructure&#13;
losses in Lebanon. The direct damage has been estimated by the World Bank at about US$2.4&#13;
billion with a further $700-$800 million o f indirect damage. The cost o f the hostilities as well as&#13;
the social impact on the lives and livelihoods o f the families affected also dealt a severe blow to&#13;
Lebanon's long-term prospects for recovery. Economy-wide losses o f revenue from foregone&#13;
output are estimated at US$2.3 billion in 2006 alone and the projected growth in real GDP o f 6&#13;
percent in 2006 has contracted by nearly the same magnitude. Jobs have been lost, government&#13;
revenues have dropped while at the same time government expenditures have increased by&#13;
approximately US$690 million`.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1Lebanon: Economic and Social Impact Assessment; The World Bank; January 20,2007&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Although the hostilities caused limited direct physical harm to the overall electricity&#13;
infrastructure (the physical damage has been estimated at US$84 million), the indirect impact i s&#13;
substantial.&#13;
&#13;
The latter includes:&#13;
    (i)     The loss o f revenue (primarily due to a drop in supply capacity, interruptions in&#13;
            collections innumerous areas, and the destruction o f some service perimeters); and&#13;
    (ii)    The increased cost o f generation for EdL (primarily due to damage to the production&#13;
            fuel supply chain, particularly storage facilities).&#13;
&#13;
In turn, these indirect effects have severely aggravated the short term needs for government&#13;
subsidiesto the power sector.&#13;
&#13;
Moreover, the unexpected and substantial increase in public expenditures needed for the&#13;
country's reconstruction efforts in other sector which suffered more extensive damage put a&#13;
tremendous burden on the government's finances and make government subsidies to the power&#13;
sector even more un-sustainable than before the hostilities. And last, Lebanon will be under&#13;
increasing pressure from donors as a condition for their support to show its concrete commitment&#13;
to urgently address the severe performance problems, inefficiencies and poor governance o f the&#13;
power sector. It i s against this grim public finance context that swift action on the reform o f the&#13;
power sector no longer i s a choice but a must.&#13;
&#13;
3. Government Strategy&#13;
&#13;
In2002, an Electricity Law (Law 462) was passedwhich lays out the restructuring o f EdL. The&#13;
Law calls for the creation o f a regulatory authority, unbundling o f all or parts o f the sector,&#13;
incorporation o f the new entities under commercial law, and, ultimately, privatization o f up to&#13;
40% o f the shares. Since the Law was enacted, several attempts have been made to advance its&#13;
implementationbut there has beenno change to the structure or status o f EdL as o f yet.&#13;
&#13;
The July 2006 reform package includes immediate reforms and initiatives for improving sector&#13;
performance. That reform program has as ultimate objective to turn the sector around through&#13;
private sector participation, in accordance with Law 462. While there is recognition that full&#13;
privatization would be difficult intoday's environment o f significant dependence o f the sector on&#13;
large subsidies and o f high political risk, several steps have been proposed to commence the&#13;
turnaround o f the sector, including restructuring and incorporation under commercial law and&#13;
outsourcingto the private sector o f key functions. The key objectives o f the government's power&#13;
sector reform are to:&#13;
&#13;
    (i)     Reduce the government subsidiesto the sector;&#13;
    (ii)    Ensure continuous supply o f quality electricity and restore consumer confidence in&#13;
            the sector;&#13;
    (iii)   Make the sector commercially viable through lowering the cost o f electricity&#13;
            production, develop a priority investment program, including completion o f priority&#13;
            projects such as introduction o f natural gas and feasibility studies for generation&#13;
            capacity;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    (iv)   Improve governance and management by establishing systems and processes to'&#13;
           enable the generation o f reports with reliable information (financial and technical);&#13;
           and&#13;
    (v)    Develop a comprehensive privatization strategy which is commensurate with the risks&#13;
           inLebanon.&#13;
More specifically, the reform package endorsed by the GOLprovides for:&#13;
&#13;
Better governance&#13;
&#13;
0   The constitution o f a multi-ministry high level committee, entrusted with developing&#13;
    solutions to the problems o f the electricity sector and addressing the need for a qualified and&#13;
    accountable Board o f EdL, as well as with examining some contracts for the provision o f&#13;
    fuel;&#13;
    The appointment o f new membersto the Board o f EdLwith the responsibility o f supervising&#13;
    the EdL's financial and administrative performance;&#13;
&#13;
Cost reduction&#13;
    The contracting o f an international consultant to supervise the operation and maintenance&#13;
    contracts for the Zahrani and Baddawi power plants;&#13;
    The contracting o f an international consultant to assess the validity o f retaining the Zouk and&#13;
    Jiyehpower plants untilmore efficient substituteplants are constructed;&#13;
&#13;
0   The extension o f the natural gas pipeline from the Baddawi area to the Zahrani area, and its&#13;
    phased implementation;&#13;
&#13;
Improved quality of sewice&#13;
&#13;
0   The contracting an international consultant to invite private investments in new power plants&#13;
    inthe Baddawi, Zahrani and other geographical areas through Independent Power Producers;&#13;
    and,&#13;
&#13;
0   The signing o f a contract with consultants C.R.A. International to complete the re-&#13;
    engineering of the distribution segment in order to improve billing, metering and cost&#13;
    recovery o f EdL.&#13;
&#13;
The reform program i s attached ina matrix format inAnnex 2.&#13;
&#13;
The urgency o f the Government's reforms, including the reform measures relating to the power&#13;
sector, has been confirmed and validated at the January 25, 2007, Paris I11Conference, during&#13;
which the international community was presented with the Government's comprehensive and&#13;
ambitious reform program and asked to provide its financial support.             The substantial aid&#13;
pledgedto Lebanon (over US$ 7.6 billion) and the repeated emphasis put on acting on the power&#13;
sector were testimonies o f the collective recognition o f the priority need to address the power&#13;
sector situation as part o f the country's sustainable reconstruction and economic recovery&#13;
program. The proposedproject will lay the necessary institutional foundation for the recovery o f&#13;
the power sector and to meet the Government stated priorities listed above.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
B. BANK RESPONSEAND STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
Bank Response. On September 20, 2006, the Bank's Board o f Governors approved a transfer o f&#13;
US$70 million from IBRD surplus to a Trust Fund for Lebanon (TFL) (Resolution 580) to&#13;
support the Government's reconstruction efforts. Bank support centers on priority areas where&#13;
the Bank has a distinct comparative advantage, namely the rehabilitation o f damaged&#13;
infrastructure, support to groups affected by the hostilities andjump-starting economic activities.&#13;
&#13;
The Bank's short-term emergency response to the post-hostilities needs centered on undertaking&#13;
an economic and social impact assessment (ESIA) which outlines key reform elements necessary&#13;
for transitioning from short-term reconstructionto sustainable growth.&#13;
&#13;
Bank Strategy. The ESIA includes a comprehensive chapter on the electricity sector. In this&#13;
chapter, the Bank provides recommendations for the power sector in the short- and medium-&#13;
term. The key strategic points are highlighted below:&#13;
&#13;
    Major efforts are needed to improve governance. Areas where improvement i s particularly&#13;
    critical are billing and collection, management o f the fuel chain and investment decision&#13;
    making;&#13;
    Improved commercial operation o f EdL through incorporation will contribute to both&#13;
    reducing the fiscal burden on Government through improved productivity and management&#13;
    and improving service delivery through better planning, more focus on operation and&#13;
    maintenance (O&amp;M) o f facilities and the possibility to hire competent and skilled staff at&#13;
    market salaries.&#13;
    The sector investment needs are very significant, but can only be economic and efficient if&#13;
    two conditions are in place: (i) management and skills at EdL; and (ii)proper least&#13;
                                     better                                          a&#13;
    cost expansion plan i s undertaken, along with an assessment o f the transmission and&#13;
    distribution investment needs.    This needs to be accompanied by a comprehensive fuel&#13;
    sourcing strategy.&#13;
    Lessons from the reconstruction after the civil war have shown that long-term environmental&#13;
    impacts from hasty reconstruction can offset benefits if proper mitigating measures are not&#13;
    implementedina timely manner. Hence the sector reform and reconstruction process should&#13;
    be consistent with a proper environmental protection strategy.&#13;
&#13;
The recommendations o f the World Bank are fully consistent and supportive o f the&#13;
Government's reform program inthe sector.&#13;
&#13;
Rationalefor Bank involvement. The proposed project i s a key pillar o f the Bank's assistance&#13;
to Lebanon following the hostilities. The project will assist in addressing the performance&#13;
problems o f the sector which inturn will, over the mediumterm, reduce the fiscal burdeno f the&#13;
sector and thus free up government resources for other priority uses. This i s particularly acute&#13;
given the contraction o f the economy as well as the increased expenditure to rebuild housing,&#13;
basic infrastructure andprovide assistance to those most affected by the hostilities.&#13;
&#13;
The Bank and Lebanon have a long-standingrelationship inthe energy sector, both ininvestment&#13;
support and sector reform. There have been several projects, but with mixed results on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
policy and reform front. Since the end o f the hostilities last summer, the Bank has been working&#13;
closely with the government at all levels and across several ministries to lay out the reform&#13;
program for the sector, which has also served as the basis on which Lebanon has sought&#13;
substantial donor support. Most o f the emphasis has been placed on the short-term measures that&#13;
will initiate the reform process and establish sound foundations for sustainable sector recovery&#13;
over the longer term.&#13;
&#13;
The rationale for Bank involvement is therefore the extensive experience that the Bank brings in&#13;
terms o f implementing sector reform in difficult settings, which help lay sound foundations for&#13;
sustainable growth over the medium to longer term. The proposed grant project may followed&#13;
by IBRD support, which in turn would help provide the policy environment under which&#13;
significant other donors' funds can contribute to meet the significant investment and institutional&#13;
needs inthe sector.&#13;
&#13;
C. DETAILED PROJECTDESCRIPTION&#13;
&#13;
1. Projectdevelopmentobjectiveandkeyindicators&#13;
&#13;
The objective o f the proposed project is to accelerate the implementation o f reforms and&#13;
restructuring o f EdL by enhancing the capacity o f MOEW, EdL and the multi-ministryhigher&#13;
level committee&#13;
&#13;
2. Projectcomponents&#13;
&#13;
The proposed project will finance the provision o f advisory services which will complement the&#13;
service contracts, technical assistance and investment support currently provided by other&#13;
donors. The components are as follows:&#13;
&#13;
Component 1: Provide Support to Strengthen the Capacity of the Ministry of Energy and&#13;
Water (MOE W) to Implement Power Sector Policy Reform.&#13;
&#13;
The objectives o f the assistanceproposedunder this component are to provide policy advice to&#13;
M O E W instrategic areas, complete key on-going projects, and assist inthe establishment o fthe&#13;
regulatory agency. The duration o f this component i s expected to last for 2 years.&#13;
&#13;
The services covered under this component include:&#13;
&#13;
(i) Policy advice on key sector strategic issues&#13;
&#13;
    Support inthe preparation o f a national energy strategy integrating the power sector least cost&#13;
    plan, the tariff study, and the fuel sourcing strategy;&#13;
    Support MOEW to formulate and implement a fuel sourcing strategy for Lebanon.&#13;
&#13;
(ii) Complete on-goingprojects&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
0   Review proposals for immediate supply o f Liquefied Natural Gas (LNG) to the Zahrani&#13;
    power plant and provide support to negotiate the contract;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
0    Supervise the contract aimed to reduce the financial gap indistribution;&#13;
0    Evaluate the proposal to attract IPPs and provide support to the M O E W to finalize the&#13;
     contract ifdetermined to be the desired approach.&#13;
&#13;
(iii) Establishment of the Renulatow Anencv&#13;
&#13;
     Reviewprevious studies prepared for the creation o fthe Energy Regulatory Agency;&#13;
     Assist inthe recruitment o f key staff and the allocation o fbudget to the Agency.&#13;
&#13;
Support to the M O E W will also include a short-term component that will support the immediate&#13;
hiringo f a strategic advisor to the MOEW giventhe particular lack o f capacity inthe Ministryat&#13;
present. The advisor has already beenhired on apart-time basis.&#13;
&#13;
A Master Plan for the electricity sector, financed separately by AFD, will also be undertaken.&#13;
The Master Planwill include a detailed least cost expansionplananalysis for the sector.&#13;
&#13;
Component 2: Provide Support to the Government of Lebanonfor the Restructuring of EdL.&#13;
&#13;
The objective o f this component is to assist the Government in the restructurhg o f EdL,&#13;
including the incorporation under commercial law o f the proposed structure o f generation,&#13;
transmission and distribution under a holding company. The assistance i s expected to last for.18&#13;
months, with several intermediate milestones, including issuance o f necessary decrees within 3-6&#13;
months, allocation o f main assets within 6-9 months and renewal o f key staff within 12-18&#13;
months. The key services envisaged under this component include:&#13;
&#13;
     Based on previous advisory services obtained, advising on the Government's proposed&#13;
     structure o fthe new EdL and restructuring strategy;&#13;
     Providing support for the incorporationo f the companies to be created;&#13;
     Designing for each company a detailed organization chart, governance scheme, set o f job&#13;
     descriptions and staff mapping, internal procedures and helping prepare their initial business&#13;
     plans; and&#13;
0    Developing an asset register and proposing a level o f capitalization o f the new companies&#13;
     and a shareholding structure.&#13;
&#13;
Component 3: Provide Support to EdL to Improve the Operational and Financial&#13;
Performance and the Implementation of its Restructuring.&#13;
&#13;
The objectives o f the assistance proposed under this component are to (i) EdL improve its&#13;
                                                                               help&#13;
performance with a focus on technical andprocurement, commercial and financial aspects during&#13;
the interim period between the beginning o f the project and the moment the restructuring is&#13;
implemented, and (ii) in the restructuring o f EdL. This assistance i s expected to last for&#13;
                        assist&#13;
eighteen months, or earlier inthe case EdL i s incorporated and restructured sooner. The services&#13;
covered under this component will address:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
fi) Generation Efficiencv and Procurement&#13;
0    Develop a plan to improve the efficiency for each power plant and support actions to&#13;
     implement proposed improvements; and&#13;
     Reorganize the procurement function inEdL.&#13;
&#13;
(ii) Transmission and Distribution(T&amp;D) reliability and efficiencv and commercial issues&#13;
&#13;
0    Identify priority actions to improve reliability and reduce T&amp;D losses and non-technical&#13;
     losses and help implement the proposed measures;&#13;
0    Assist inthe finalization o f any ongoing project, including substations in Saida and Baalbek,&#13;
     the dispatch center, the 220 kV network, etc.; and&#13;
0    Assist introuble shooting technical issues throughout the entity.&#13;
&#13;
fiii) Financial issues and accountinR&#13;
&#13;
0    Assist inthe development of asset registers and inventory control;&#13;
0    Ensure the preparation of auditable financial statements for overdue years;&#13;
0    Undertake the preparation o f detailed financial forecasting for EdL; and&#13;
0    Assist the General Manager inday to day financial matters.&#13;
&#13;
(iv) Restructuring of EdL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
0    Provide assistance to the advisory consultants responsible for the restructuring assignments&#13;
     on a needs basis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Expenditure by category       Amount in (US$)             Disbursement&#13;
&#13;
            Consultancy Services                 5.0                       100%&#13;
&#13;
            Total Grant Amount                   5.0                       100%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Table B: Disbursement Schedule (US$million) per Fiscal Year&#13;
&#13;
                                               2007         2008           2009        Total&#13;
     Total of Project Disbursements             1.6           3.0          0.4          5.0&#13;
&#13;
      Disbursement Rate                         32%          60%           8%          100%&#13;
&#13;
3. Lessonslearnedand reflectedin the projectdesign&#13;
&#13;
The Bank's past experience o f the implementation o f sector reform projects in Lebanon shows&#13;
mixed results.    Reforms have been slow to be designed and endorsed, partially due to the&#13;
political fragmentation o f the country and interference in the day to day operations o f EdL.&#13;
However, the momentum for reform i s high in Lebanon at the moment, given the heavy burden&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the sector places on the government budget and the need for the government to fund other&#13;
priority reconstruction efforts. Therefore, the sector reform plan agreed among the key decision-&#13;
makers i s worth supporting. The most important first ingredient i s to ensure sufficient capacity&#13;
to implementwhat has been endorsed and work out the details o fhow to restructure EdL&#13;
&#13;
The Bank's experience in implementing projects in post-conflict countries has highlighted the&#13;
importance o f a synergy-focused, flexible and very concrete project design to allow for&#13;
adaptation to changing circumstances in a context o f wide participation o f the donor community.&#13;
In line with this, the project design has been kept concrete, supporting the implementation of&#13;
measures that already emerged from earlier work in the sector. Laying the ground for sector&#13;
reform will also lead to increased opportunities for donors to provide further financing support to&#13;
this longer-term initiative and the associated investmentneeds.&#13;
&#13;
Over the years, the Bank has also captured global lessons on power sector reform. The main&#13;
lessons learned that are relevant for Lebanon are:&#13;
&#13;
     Incash short sectors, it is vital to have strong, centralizedcash management inplace before&#13;
     unbundling to ensure money will flow back to fuel procurement and O&amp;M, otherwise&#13;
     subsidies may increase;&#13;
     Unbundling should be done carefully and the number o f unbundled entities should be as&#13;
     limitedas possible;&#13;
     Learn how to reform as the process gets underway - be ready to make adjustments&#13;
     midstream;&#13;
     Ensurethere is sufficient in-house capacityto design and manage the reformprocess.&#13;
&#13;
D. INSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTSAND PROJECTIMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
1. Institutionalandimplementationarrangements&#13;
&#13;
The project will be implemented over a period o f two years, using existing Government&#13;
structures where possible. The institutional arid implementation arrangements will be as follows:&#13;
&#13;
The three assignments will be overseen by an inter-ministry Higher Level Committee (HLC)&#13;
under the chairmanship o f the Prime Minister and comprising the Ministers o f Energy and&#13;
Finance, the Council for Development and Reconstruction (CDR), the Higher Council for&#13;
Privatization (HCP) and EdL. While the implementingagency will be the CDR which will also&#13;
sign the contracts, the beneficiaries o f the grant are MOEW, EdL and the HCP, acting as an&#13;
administrator o f the H L C for the restructuring o f EdL. A Project Agreement will be enteredinto&#13;
between the CDR and the World Bank.              The selection and evaluation committee for the&#13;
consulting assignments will be headed by the CDR and comprise representatives from the H L C&#13;
(Le., the Prime Minister's Office, CDR, HCP, MOEW, MOF and EdL). The consultants will&#13;
report directly to the beneficiaries and to the H L C as needed. The beneficiaries will coordinate&#13;
with the CDR for payment processing purposes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2. Monitoringand evaluationof outcomes/results&#13;
&#13;
The CDR will provide quarterly progress reports that monitor the progress o f the technical&#13;
assistance financed under the project. Inaddition, these progress reports will serve as a basis for&#13;
optimizing the coordination efforts between the three components o f the project. These reports&#13;
will be submittedto the World Bank, the MOEW, the CDR andthe HCP.&#13;
&#13;
Given the high level o f complexity and sensitivity o f the issues addressed under this project,&#13;
strong supervision efforts, including frequent field visits, will be needed, particularly at key&#13;
junctures o f the restructuring o fEdL.&#13;
&#13;
3. Procurementarrangements&#13;
&#13;
The Grant is intendedto fund three (3) contracts for consultant services to be provided by firms,&#13;
all to be recruited in compliance with the Bank Guidelines. It i s estimated that those contracts&#13;
will cost US$8 million equivalent of which the Grant will finance US$5 million.                The&#13;
procurement methods for the consulting firms and the level o f Bank review are established inthe&#13;
project's procurement plan designed by CDR during appraisal and to be updated on a quarterly&#13;
basis or when needed. All updates will be submittedfor Bank's approval.&#13;
&#13;
The grant will be implementedby CDR which has extensive experience inhandlingprocurement&#13;
following Bank Guidelines. Substantial lessons have been learned over the years in expediting&#13;
administrative procedures, and the inherent risk i s therefore foreseen to be average with respect&#13;
to procurement processing. The Planning and Programming Division will implement the project&#13;
and the Director o f this Division will take the role o f Project Coordinator for this project. H e&#13;
will be assisted by a team o f engineers with previous World Bank project experience and the&#13;
Selection and Evaluation Committee duringthe consultant selection and evaluation phases. The&#13;
Division will be responsible for monitoring and managing ongoing contracts.&#13;
&#13;
Each o f the three beneficiaries o f the program (MOEW, EdL, and the Higher Level Committee)&#13;
will assign staff for managing the project. This staff will follow up on procurement processing:&#13;
(i)validate TORS,(ii)participate inthe selection ofthe respective consultant and contract&#13;
negotiation, and (iii) monitor the consultant and manage the contracts. Payments from CDR will&#13;
be issued upon submission o f the request from the pertinentbeneficiary attaching an approval o f&#13;
the consultant's invoice. A copy o fthe submittedreports shall be filed inCDR.&#13;
&#13;
The Planning and Programming Division will be responsible for maintaining accurate&#13;
procurement records, including all actions related to Bank-financed procurement. This includes&#13;
advertisement, all submitted expressions o f interest and proposals, minutes o f public openings,&#13;
evaluation process, contract administration, deliverables and reports, invoices and payment&#13;
copies. The procurement files and updated procurement plans will be maintained for review by&#13;
the Bank's supervisionmissions. The beneficiaries will maintain complete filing with respect to&#13;
contract administration: contract copy, deliverables and reports, invoices copy, payment copy,&#13;
etc.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4. Financialmanagementanddisbursementarrangements&#13;
&#13;
The Planning and Programming Division in CDR will be required to maintain the Grant's&#13;
records and accounts, and prepare financial statements in a format acceptable to the Bank,&#13;
adequate to reflect the operations, resources and expenditures related to the Grant. All Financial&#13;
Management (FM) related matters will follow the arrangements in place for World Bank&#13;
financed projects implementedby CDR.&#13;
&#13;
The project's FM arrangements are considered adequate for the project and will include: (i)&#13;
engaging a Finance Officer with relevant academic degree and sufficient work experience to&#13;
follow up on the project's accounts and generate the requiredreports, (ii)              applying government&#13;
controls and procedures as well as technical approval from the beneficiary entities and fiduciary&#13;
approval for all payments, (iii)     purchasing the license to install the ring fenced accounting&#13;
system inplace for all World Bank financed projects in CDR to follow up and separately report&#13;
on the project, (iv) engaging a focal point in each o f the beneficiary entities to facilitate&#13;
coordination with CDR, (v) issuing quarterly financial reports and (vi) yearly auditing by an&#13;
independentauditor acceptable to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
Risk Analysis and mitigating measures. A risk assessment was carried out for this project and is&#13;
included in the project files. Below i s a summary o f the risks identified and the mitigating&#13;
measures addressing these risks:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     Risk&#13;
 Risk           Risk&#13;
                rating               Incorporated Risk MitigatingMeasures (MM)                      rating&#13;
                                                                                                   gter MM&#13;
 Inherent Rbk (IR)&#13;
 Country Level  Significant According to Lebanon's CFAA, the overall risk assessment o f the       loderate&#13;
                            .&#13;
                            Project FinancialManagement system i s significant.&#13;
                            Mitigating measures:&#13;
                                The grant will follow the same FM system inplace for other WB&#13;
                            .   projects in CDR (ring fenced accounting and reporting system&#13;
                                already inplace)&#13;
                                The project will be monitored on a quarterly basis through the&#13;
                                revision o f interimfinancial statements and supervised twice a&#13;
                                year. An external independent auditor will audit the grant&#13;
                                accounts.&#13;
 Entityand      Significant The flow o f information between the beneficiary entities and CDR      Moderate&#13;
 project Level              might not be timely and efficient.&#13;
                            Mitigating measures:&#13;
                                The project will assign a focal point ineach o f the beneficiary&#13;
                            .   entities who will follow up on the project and coordinate with the&#13;
                                finance officer.&#13;
                                The finance officer will be requested to performquarterly visits&#13;
                                to the beneficiary units to reconcile the payments made and in&#13;
                                process and follow up o n the project's commitments.&#13;
 Overall I R    Moderate                                                                           Moderate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Budgeting      Moderate    The grant will prepare a yearly budget and cash forecast that i s      o w&#13;
                            monitored on a auarterlv basis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                             CDR will purchase the license o f the existing ring fenced accounting Low&#13;
 Accounting         L o w    system and install it for the project. The system i s currently fully&#13;
                             operational and i s performing adequately.&#13;
                             Amounts available inthe special account (SA) may not be sufficient   Cow&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Funds Flow       Moderate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                ,&#13;
 Financial                   The accounting system will generate interim financial statements, SA L o w&#13;
 Reporting           L o w   reconciliations and commitment reports.&#13;
                             CDR will engage an external independent auditor to audit the grant's L o w&#13;
 Auditing            L o w   accounts and special account and to submit a yearly audit report&#13;
                             together with a management letter.&#13;
  Overall CR      Moderate                                                                         Low&#13;
&#13;
Implementing entity and staffing. The FM system inplace at CDR i s based on principles and&#13;
procedures defined by the legal framework and operational decrees applicable to CDR. The&#13;
control environment inCDR was assessedand found to be acceptable.&#13;
&#13;
CDR will engage a Finance Officer with relevant academic and work experience to follow up on&#13;
the project's accounts (this could be on a part-time basis given the limited scope o f the project).&#13;
The new finance officer will be trained by the finance officers working on other World Bank&#13;
financed projects and will be part o f the project management arrangements at CDR. The finance&#13;
officer's role i s to follow up on the Grant activities, post data inthe system, prepare and monitor&#13;
the yearly budgets, prepare financial reports and coordinate with the project unit and the&#13;
implementing entities on all FMand disbursementrelated matters.&#13;
&#13;
In order to ensure proper flow of information and to facilitate the coordination with the&#13;
beneficiary entities, the project will assign a focal point in each entity whose role i s to follow up&#13;
on the part o f the project implemented by the entity and to coordinate with CDR. The Finance&#13;
Officer will also be requested to perform quarterly visits to the beneficiary entities in order to&#13;
reconcile payments requests sent with those paid to follow up on the amounts remaining on&#13;
signedcontracts.&#13;
&#13;
Accounting. The projects' accounting system utilized in CDR is a ring fenced system with&#13;
integrated procurement and financial management modules. The accounting system i s governed&#13;
by a detailed chart o f accounts broken down by category, component and contract. The system&#13;
has been operating adequately under a number o f projects and its outputs have been tested and&#13;
found to be satisfactory. The same system will be amended to reflect this project's activities but&#13;
there will be no change inthe system's main features and modules.&#13;
&#13;
The project will follow the cash basis o f accounting and the project's accounts will be&#13;
maintained using the double-entry bookkeeping principles and commitments will be monitored&#13;
and tracked usingthe contracts screen. `Supportingdocuments will be kept by CDR.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Budgeting.    The project's finance officer will prepare an annual budget based on the&#13;
procurement plan. This budget will be generated from the accounting module and will be&#13;
monitoredon a regular basis.&#13;
&#13;
Financial Reporting. The project will be required to generate quarterly un-audited financial&#13;
reports and submit them to the World Bank as part o f the project's progress report or separately.&#13;
These reports are made up of:&#13;
&#13;
    1. Financial reports: to include a statement o f sources and uses o f funds, quarterly cash&#13;
        forecast, an expenditure report comparing actual and planned expenditures by activity&#13;
        and implementing entity inaddition to a special account reconciliation statement.&#13;
    2. Contracts listing: To include a listing o f all contracts showing amounts committed and&#13;
        disbursedunder each.&#13;
&#13;
These reports will be system generated and should be remitted to the World Bank within one&#13;
month from the end o f the quarter starting from the quarter where the first grant disbursement&#13;
took place. The proposed format o f the reports will be agreed duringnegotiations.&#13;
&#13;
Auditing. CDR has pervious experience with the audit requirements o f the World Bank as they&#13;
currently implement most of World Bank financed projects inLebanon. Ingeneral, the audits o f&#13;
World Bank financed projects didnot identify any major accountability issues, however, over the&#13;
last few years CDR has been systematically late in submitting these reports. As such, the&#13;
external auditor's TOR should be preparedand submitted for the Bank's no objection, at least 10&#13;
months prior to the end of the project's fiscal year. Audit costs will not be financed bythe Grant.&#13;
&#13;
The Project's financial statements will be audited by an independent auditor acceptable to the&#13;
World Bank. The external audit report will encompass all project activities and will be in&#13;
accordance with internationally accepted auditing standards. The annual audit report o f the&#13;
project's accounts will include an opinion on the project's financial statements and the special&#13;
account transactions. The project's auditor will also be required to give an opinion on whether&#13;
expenditures reimbursed on the basis o f Statements o f Expenditures (SOEs) are eligible for&#13;
World Bank financing and are reflected on the project's financial statements.&#13;
&#13;
The following audit reports will be due under this project:&#13;
             IAudit Report                                     IDue Date&#13;
              1) Project Specific Financial Statements          Annually by June 30&#13;
              2) Special Opinions (ifspecifically required)&#13;
                  0   SOE                                       Annuallv bv June 30&#13;
                      Special Account                          1Annually by June 30&#13;
&#13;
In addition to the audit reports, the auditor will prepare a management letter identifying any&#13;
observations, comments and deficiencies, in the system and controls that the external&#13;
independent auditor consider pertinent and will provide recommendations                  for their&#13;
improvements.      One combined management letter for all World Bank financed projects&#13;
implementedby CDR is acceptable.&#13;
&#13;
The proceeds o f the grant will be disbursed in accordance with the World Bank's disbursements&#13;
guidelines as outlined in the Disbursement Handbook. Transaction based disbursement will be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
used under this project. Accordingly, requests for payments from the grant account will be&#13;
initiated through the use o f withdrawal applications (WAS) either for Direct Payments,&#13;
Reimbursements, Replenishments to the Special Account (SA), or Issuance o f Special&#13;
Commitments. All WASwill include appropriate supporting documentation including detailed&#13;
SOEs for reimbursements and replenishments to the SA.&#13;
&#13;
Authorized signatories, names and corresponding specimens o f their signatures will be submitted&#13;
to the World Bank prior to the receipt o f the first replenishment application.&#13;
&#13;
Retroactiveflnancing: Payments made to the grant recipient out o f its own resources before the&#13;
date o f a grant agreement are normally not eligible for financing under the grant, except that&#13;
withdrawals, in an aggregate amount not exceeding the equivalent o f US$ 1,000,000 million,&#13;
may be made on account o f payments made for expenditures before that date but on or after&#13;
January 19, 2007.      Payments must be for expenditures that are eligible under the Grant&#13;
Agreement. Procedures for procurement and the use o f consultants, and processing and&#13;
clearances are subject to the World Bank's Procurement and Consultants Guidelines.&#13;
Documentation requirements for expenditures claimed under retroactive financing are the same&#13;
as those for disbursement against payments made after the Grant Agreement i s signed.&#13;
&#13;
Statement of Expenditures (SOE):           During implementation SOEs will be used for all&#13;
expenditures relating to consulting services under consultant firms contracts costing less than&#13;
US$100,000 equivalent each and under individual consultant contracts costing less than&#13;
US$50,000 equivalent each. The supporting documentation will be maintained at CDR and will&#13;
be made available for review by World Bank supervisionmissions uponrequest. Documentation&#13;
relating to SOEs would be retained for up to one year from the date the World Bank receives the&#13;
audit report for the fiscal year in which the last withdrawal application from the grant account&#13;
was made.&#13;
&#13;
Special Account: To facilitate project implementation and make timely payments, CDR will&#13;
open a US$ SA at the Central Bank o f Lebanon. The authorized allocation will be US$750,000&#13;
with an initial deposit o f US$500,000. The SA will be managed and administered by the CDR&#13;
who will also be responsible for submitting the withdrawal applications with appropriate&#13;
supporting documentation for expenditures incurred. Deposits into andpayments from the SA to&#13;
pay consultants and others will be made inaccordance with the provisions o f the grant agreement&#13;
and the disbursement letter. Replenishments o f the SA would follow World Bank's procedures.&#13;
The minimumvalue o f applications is 20% o f the amount advances to the designated account o f&#13;
this project.&#13;
&#13;
5. Safeguards&#13;
&#13;
The project will finance only consultant and technical assistance services.               Adverse&#13;
environmental and social impacts during implementation o f the technical assistance activities are&#13;
therefore very limited. The project has hence been classified as Category C, consistent with the&#13;
World Bank Operational Policy 4.01. However, potential indirect social and environmental&#13;
impacts o f the reforms supported by the project cannot be ignored and attention to such concerns&#13;
will be carefully incorporated in the scope o f the relevant strategic advisory services supported&#13;
by the project. Inparticular, the issue o f fuel oil storage will be closely examined inthe context&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
o f the fuel sourcing strategy, to avoid future dramatic environmental damage o f the scale o f the&#13;
oil spill from the Jiyeh power plant's tanks, upon their destruction during the recent hostilities.&#13;
Similarly, close attention in the scope o f the advisory services to the Ministryo f Energywill be&#13;
given to identifying and minimizing the adverse impacts o f energy policies on the various&#13;
stakeholders, with a particular concern for the most vulnerable stakeholders, such as the poor,&#13;
when it comes to advising on an energy strategy, review o f tariff structures, and the overall&#13;
restructuring o f the sector.&#13;
&#13;
  Safeguard Policies Triggered by the Project                           Yes              No&#13;
  Environmental Assessment (OP/BP/GP 4.01)                               [I             [ J&#13;
  Natural Habitats (OP/BP 4.04)                                          [I             [ J&#13;
  Pest Management (OP 4.09)                                              [I             [ J 111&#13;
  Cultural Property (OPN 11.03,beingrevisedas OP 4.11)                   [I             [J1&#13;
  Involuntary Resettlement (OP/BP 4.12)                                  [I             [ J 1&#13;
  IndigenousPeoples (OD 4.20, being revisedas OP 4.10)                   [I             C J 1&#13;
  Forests (OP/BP 4.36)                                                   [I             [ J 1&#13;
  Safety o fDams (OP/BP 4.37)                                            [I             [ J 1&#13;
  Projects inDisputedAreas (OP/BP/GP 7.60)                               [I             [ J 1&#13;
  Projects on International Waterways (OP/BP/GP 7.50)                    [I             [ J 1&#13;
&#13;
6. Sustainability and Risks&#13;
&#13;
SustainabiZity. The design of the reforms has essentially been completed and a legal framework&#13;
for the restructuring o f the sector exists. The focus therefore needs to be on implementation&#13;
which is where progress has beenlacking inthe past. The combination o fthe current momentum&#13;
for reforms inLebanon and the capacity that will be brought through the proposedproject should&#13;
ensure sustainability o f the project.&#13;
&#13;
Risks&#13;
&#13;
(i) Delays in implementation: Based onpast project experience inLebanon, the proposed project&#13;
could face implementation delays resulting from lack o f capacity This risk will be mitigated by&#13;
the early establishment o f the Selection and Evaluation Committee and the increased capacity in&#13;
financial management expertise in the CDR. Moreover, frequent communication between the&#13;
Bank and the implementing agency, including the Higher Level Committee and the direct&#13;
beneficiaries o f the assistance services, as well as regular Bank supervision missions will ensure&#13;
support i s available when needed. Delay in implementation may also stem from difficulty to&#13;
reach a political consensus at key decision junctures during the implementation o f the power&#13;
sector strategy, EdL restructuring and internal reorganization.       This risk is partly mitigated&#13;
through close cooperation and sector dialogue with MOEW and other stake-holders in Lebanon.&#13;
The project is also based on the Electricity Law, which was widely accepted by all parties and&#13;
constitutes the platform for sector reforms. There is, however, a remaining risk of political&#13;
interference ina fluid political environment, which cannot be mitigated inthe local context.&#13;
&#13;
(ii)Inadequate$financing: About 35% ofthe estimated project total cost is expected to be&#13;
financed by the GOL.        The complementary financing from the GOL i s a testament o f its&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
commitment to the reform program. But it also represents a risk incase the Government finds it&#13;
difficult to provide on time the funds needed, as faced with too many other calls on public&#13;
finance for reconstruction, or should no other donor be able to fill the funding gap. To prevent&#13;
any major setback inthe implementationof the technical assistance program proposed under the&#13;
project due to failure o f obtaining full financing, the detailed design o f the program will be built&#13;
insuch a way to clearly delineate activities and time frames for which financing is firm from the&#13;
ones that remain conditional to a confirmation o f the availability o f complementary financing.&#13;
Either way, clear priority will be given to the implementation o f the restructuring o f EdL, the&#13;
major bottleneck to sector improvement. Also, the Bank has consulted with other donors,&#13;
including AFD and EIBwho are bothkeen to support the sector.&#13;
&#13;
(iii) Political and security risks: The current volatile political and security context in Lebanon&#13;
represents a non-negligible risk to the adequate implementation o f the planned reforrn and&#13;
investment programs inthe sector. This may have an impact on the lack o f interest by firms to&#13;
bid on work in Lebanon, resulting in higher bid prices. Mitigation measures are the upfront&#13;
indication that the consultant assignments are Bank financed with direct payment to service&#13;
providers; and the limitedcommercial risk for the consultants resultingfrom the advisory nature&#13;
o ftheir assignment.&#13;
&#13;
E. ECONOMIC AND FISCAL JUSTIFICATION&#13;
&#13;
Economic impact. With the support o f the technical assistance provided under the proposed&#13;
project, improvement in sector investment planning should reduce sector investment needs and&#13;
the long-term cost o f electricity. Improvement inEdL management and governance should also&#13;
generate economic gains through a lower consumption o f production factors for power supply.&#13;
The expected improvement in reliability will also have a positive economic impact by reducing&#13;
the utilization o f non-economical individual power generators, and through the reduction of&#13;
economic production lost due to power supply un-reliability.           The economic impact o f the&#13;
reduction o f power thefts i s difficult to evaluate, as the direct impact o f the reduction on welfare&#13;
i s clearly negative, but the indirect impact o f the reduction o f subsidies may be socially&#13;
beneficial, depending upon the utilization bythe Government o fthe savings on reduced subsidies&#13;
to EdL.&#13;
&#13;
Fiscal impact. The fiscal benefits o f the reforms can be measured in terms o f reduced need for&#13;
Government subsidies. As part o f the Economic and Social Impact Assessment preparedby the&#13;
World Bank, some scenarios were analyzed to assess the impact o f some measures, which&#13;
included reduction in losses, better fuel management, and, eventually, a tariff increase in 2009.&#13;
These scenarios also included expected efficiency gains from commercialization and private&#13;
sector participation in the sector. All these scenarios indicated that government subsidies could&#13;
be reduced over time with the understanding that these subsidieswould take several years to be&#13;
fully eliminated. One scenario presenteda case where government subsidies to the power sector&#13;
could eventually be phased out by the year 2012. This scenario assumed an annual reduction in&#13;
technical and commercial losses, an oil price drop from the current level (US$50-60/barrel) to&#13;
US$35/barrel by 2015, supply o f natural gas to key power plants (Zahrani and Bedawwi) at&#13;
favorable prices, and a one-time tariff increase o f 25%. Inother words, the subsidieswill require&#13;
several measures to be implemented simultaneously, and will take several years to be eliminated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                              Annex 1: ResultsFrameworkandMonitoring&#13;
                                                 LEBANON:&#13;
      EMERGENCY POWERSECTOR CAPACITY REINFORCEMENT PROJECT&#13;
                                            ResultsFramework&#13;
&#13;
               PDO                     ProjectOutcomeIndicators                Use of ProjectOutcome&#13;
                                                                                       Information&#13;
&#13;
Accelerate the implementation o f     Cost reductionprojects start being    To track progress o fprojected&#13;
reforms and restructuring o f EdL by  implemented.                          project outcomes and identify&#13;
enhancing critically needed capacity.                                       corrective measures as needed.&#13;
                                      EdLis restructured and is better&#13;
                                      managed and comprises a more&#13;
                                      skilledstaffbase resulting in&#13;
                                      efficiency andproductivity gains.&#13;
&#13;
                                      Capacity i s injectedinEdL so that&#13;
                                      cost reduction projects get&#13;
                                      implemented and reliability o f&#13;
                                      supply better supplied.&#13;
   IntermediateOutcomes                   IntermediateOutcome                     Use of Intermediate&#13;
                                                   Indicators                    OutcomeMonitoring&#13;
&#13;
1. Reinforcementof the capacity                                             To track implementation progress&#13;
inthe MinistryofEnergy and                                                  and, incase o f delays, be able to&#13;
Water (MOEW)                                                                take corrective action.&#13;
&#13;
1.1. Provision o f policy advice in Fuel source strategy formulated and&#13;
     strategic areas                  approved&#13;
&#13;
                                      National energy strategy integrating&#13;
                                      the power sector least cost plan, the&#13;
                                      tariff study, and the fuel sourcing&#13;
                                      strategy prepared&#13;
&#13;
1.2. Completion o f key on-going      Fuel supply contract for the Zahrani&#13;
     sector projects                  plant reviewed and negotiated&#13;
&#13;
                                      Reduction o f the financial gap in&#13;
                                      distribution&#13;
&#13;
                                      Proposed IPPs evaluated and, if&#13;
                                      viable, contracted&#13;
&#13;
1.3. Establishment        o f     the Key staff recruited and budget&#13;
     regulatory agency.               allocated to the new Agency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2. Reformprocess, and in&#13;
particular the restructuringof&#13;
EdL, conducted bothinthe short&#13;
and the longer term.&#13;
&#13;
2.1. Detailed restructuring plan     Government approval o f the plan&#13;
     adopted &amp; Initial&#13;
     implementation started&#13;
&#13;
2.2. Decrees providing for EdL's     Cabinet approval o fthe Decrees&#13;
     incorporation&#13;
&#13;
2.3. Roadmap for restructured        Detailedorganization chart,&#13;
     entities developed              governance scheme, job descriptions&#13;
                                     and staff mapping, internal&#13;
                                     procedures and initial business plan&#13;
                                     for created entities designed;&#13;
&#13;
2.4. Assets and capitalization       Asset register completed and level o f&#13;
     allocation for newly-created    capitalization o f the new companies&#13;
     entities                        and shareholding structure proposed&#13;
&#13;
2.5. Key staffing inplace innew      Key financial, procurement,&#13;
     entities                        technical and commercial positions&#13;
                                     filled at EdL&#13;
&#13;
3. Reinforcementof the capacity&#13;
of the Electric utility(EdL)&#13;
&#13;
3.1.   Improvement    o f generation Efficiency improvement plan&#13;
efficiency and procurement           developed for eachpower plant &amp;&#13;
                                     implementation initiated&#13;
                                     EDLProcurement functions&#13;
                                     reorganized&#13;
&#13;
3.2. Increase o f T&amp;D reliability,   Identifypriority actions to improve&#13;
efficiency, and commercial aspects   reliability and reduce T&amp;D losses&#13;
                                     and non-technical losses;&#13;
&#13;
                                     Finalization o f key ongoing project,&#13;
                                     including Saida and Baalbek&#13;
                                     substations, national dispatch center,&#13;
                                     and the 220 kV network:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.3.    Strengthening     o f  EdL's Asset register and inventory control&#13;
&#13;
financial and accounting capacity    finalized;&#13;
                                     Auditable financial statements for&#13;
                                     overdue years produced;&#13;
                                     Detailed EdL financial forecasting&#13;
                                     produced.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        I .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   .&#13;
D&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        . .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              0&#13;
              N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
D           e    e       e&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  e&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
D      e            e&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    e            e&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                       Annex 3: ProjectPreparationandSupervision&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            Planned                       Actual&#13;
InitialPID to PIC                      January 8,2007          January 29,2007&#13;
Initial ISDS to PIC                    January 8,2007          January 29,2007&#13;
Appraisal                              January 15,2007         January 15,2007&#13;
Negotiations                           February 15,2007        Completed by February 26,2007&#13;
RVP approval                           February 27,2007&#13;
Planneddate of effectiveness           March 31,2007&#13;
Planned date o fmid-term review        November 30,2008&#13;
Planned closing date                   June 30,2009&#13;
&#13;
Key institutionsresponsible for preparation o fthe project:&#13;
&#13;
1. CDR&#13;
2. Ministry of Energy and Water&#13;
3. HCP&#13;
4. EdL&#13;
5. Ministry ofFinance&#13;
&#13;
Bank staff and consultants who workedon the project included:&#13;
&#13;
Name                                                Title                     Unit&#13;
Anna Bjerde                     Lead Energy Specialist                      M N S S D&#13;
DianaMasri                      Financial Management Specialist             MNACS&#13;
Lina Fares                      Procurement Specialist                      MNACS&#13;
Michael Hamaide                 Operations Officer                          MNSSD&#13;
Masaki Takahashi                 Senior Power Engineer                      EWDEN&#13;
Khalid Boukantar                Program Assistant                           MNSSD&#13;
Annemarie Mtonyi Mecca          Consultant                                  LEGMS&#13;
Annande Ribeiro Araujo          Consultant                                  M N S S D&#13;
Ananda Covindassamv             Consultant                                  M N S S D&#13;
&#13;
Bank funds expendedto date on project preparation:&#13;
    1. Bank resources: $50,000&#13;
    2. Trust funds: $0&#13;
    3. Total: $50,000&#13;
&#13;
EstimatedApproval and Supervision costs:&#13;
    1. Remainingcosts to approval: $35,000&#13;
    2. Estimated annual supervision cost: $80,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                           Annex 4: Statementof LoansandCredits&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            Differencebetween&#13;
                                                                                                                            expected and actual&#13;
                                                                  Original Amount in US$ Millions                             disbursements&#13;
&#13;
Project ID    FY    Purpose                                    IBRD       IDA        SF        GEF     Cancel.   Undisb.   Orig.     Frm. Rev'd&#13;
PO50529      2003   LB-CULTURAL HERITAGE AND                     31.50      0.00      0.00      0.00     0.00     29.91     19.36         5.45&#13;
                    URBANDEV.&#13;
PO34038      2002   LB-URBANTRANSPORT                            65.00      0.00      0.00      0.00     0.00     49.61     43.76        28.91&#13;
                    DEVELOPMENT PROJECT&#13;
PO74042      2002   LB-BA'ALBECK WATER AND                       43.53      0.00      0.00      0.00     0.00     32.18     30.90        -1.30&#13;
                    WASTEWATER&#13;
PO71113      2001   LB CommunityDevelopmentProject&#13;
                       -                                         20.00      0.00      0.00      0.00     0.00     13.60     12.60        13.32&#13;
PO45174      2000   LB-EDUCATION DEVELOPMENT                     56.57      0.00      0.00      0.00    11.99     22.94     34.93        -0.16&#13;
                    PROJECT&#13;
PO50544      2000   LB-FIRST MUNICIPAL                           80.00      0.00      0.00      0.00     0.00     14.52     14.52         4.89&#13;
                    INFRASTRUCTURE&#13;
P103875      2007   LB-FIRST MUNICIPAL                           00.00      0.00     30.00      0.00     0.00     30.00     30.00         0.00&#13;
                    INFRASTRUCTURE - ADDITIONAL&#13;
                    FUNDING GRANT&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Total:  316.50       0.00     30.00      0.00    11.99    192.76    186.07        51.11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 LEBANON&#13;
                                                         STATEMENT OF IFC's&#13;
                                                      Heldand DisbursedPortfolio&#13;
                                                        InMillions ofUSDollars&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Committed                                    Disbursed&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 IFC                                         IFC&#13;
        F Y Approval   Company                      Loan        Equity      Quasi     Partic.   Loan       Equity      Quasi      Partic.&#13;
&#13;
        1996           Byblos Bank                  0.15          0.00       0.00       0.00       0.15       0.00      0.00       0.00&#13;
        1998           Idarat SHV                   0.64          0.00       0.00       0.00       0.64       0.00      0.00       0.00&#13;
        1999           Byblos Bank                  9.78          0.00       0.00       0.00       9.78       0.00      0.00       0.00&#13;
                       GTFP BLF                     5.08          0.00       0.00       0.00       5.08       0.00      0.00       0.00&#13;
                       GTFP Bank Beirut             1.12          0.00       0.00       0.00       1.12       0.00      0.00       0.00&#13;
        2005           SIS Adma                     8.00          0.00       0.00       0.00       6.00       0.00      0.00       0.00&#13;
&#13;
                                  Total portfolio:   24.77        0.00       0.00       0.00      24.77       0.00      0.00       0.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               Approvals PendingCommitment&#13;
&#13;
                        F Y Approval   Company                             Loan         Equity      Quasi       Partic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Total pending commitment:      0.00        0.00         0.00        0.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                  Annex 5: Countryat a Glance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               M . East    Upper-&#13;
POVERTY and SOCIAL                                             &amp; North    mlddle-&#13;
                                                      Lebanon   Africa    income       Development diamond*&#13;
&#13;
2004&#13;
Population,mid-year (millions)                             4.6      294        576&#13;
GNIpercapita (Atlas method, US$j                         4,980     2,000     4,770                Life expectancy&#13;
&#13;
GNI (Atlas method, US$ billionsj                          22.7      589      2,748                       -&#13;
Average annual growth, 1998-04&#13;
&#13;
Population (%)                                              13        18        0.8&#13;
Laborforce (%j                                             2.7       -13       -0.9    GNI                             Gross&#13;
                                                                                       per                             primary&#13;
M o s t recent estimate (latest year available, 1998-04)                               capita                       enrollment&#13;
Poverty(% of population belownationalpo vertylinej&#13;
Urbanpopulation (%of totalpopulafionj                       88        56        72&#13;
Life expectancyat birth (yearsj                             71        68        69&#13;
Infantmortality (per lOOOlivebidhsj                         27        45        24&#13;
Child malnutrition (%ofchildrenunder5j                                                     Access to improvedwatersource&#13;
Access to an improved water source (%ofpopulationj         0 0        88        93&#13;
Literacy (%ofpopulation age 15+j                                      69        91&#13;
Gross primaryenrollment (%of school-age population)        0 3       0 0       0 6       -Lebanon&#13;
  Male                                                     0 5       0 4       0 8       ___ Upperwniddle-incomegroup&#13;
  Female                                                   0 2        94       0 6&#13;
&#13;
KEY ECONOMIC RATIOS and LONG-TERM TRENDS&#13;
&#13;
                                                1984     1994     2003      2004&#13;
&#13;
GDP (US$ billions)                                          9.1      19.9      21.8&#13;
Gross capital formationlGDP                          ..   32.4      20.3       21.2&#13;
Exports of goods and sewicesiGDP                     ..    8.3       TT.3      21.3                    Trade&#13;
&#13;
Gross domestic savingsiGDP                           ..   -25.1      0.3        1.2&#13;
Gross nationalsavingslGDP                                   0.1      5.8        8.3&#13;
&#13;
Current account balanceiGDP                          ..   -30.1    -20.3     -8.9&#13;
Interest paynentslGDP                                      0.3       6.4        5.7&#13;
Total debtiGDP                                       ..   23.3      93.5      98.0&#13;
Total debt serviceiexports                           ..    5.3      66.1      70.7&#13;
Present value of debtlGOP                                           98.5&#13;
Present value of debtiexports                                      397.9                           Indebtedness&#13;
                                   1984-94 1994-04       2003     2004 2004-08&#13;
(averageannualgrowthj&#13;
GDP                                     8.5       2.9      4.9       6.3                 -Lebanon&#13;
&#13;
GDP percapita                           6.4        1.4     3.6       5.0                  __Upper-middle-incomegroup&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         lsg4&#13;
(%of GDPj                                                                              Growth of capital and GDP (Oh)&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture                                         ..     a 0       7.8&#13;
Industry                                            .,    27.1      20.1      20.8     2o&#13;
 Manufacturing                                      ..     7.7      2 7&#13;
Services                                            ..    60.9      72.1      72.3      0&#13;
                                                                                   - -&#13;
Householdfinal consumptionexpenditure               ..    10.5      83.4      82.2&#13;
Generalgov't final consumptionexpenditure           ..                                -20&#13;
                                                           14.5     6.3        6.7&#13;
Imports of goods and services                       ..    65.8      37.3      41.4             -GCF           -GDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            1984-94 1994-04&#13;
(averageannualgrowth)                                                                Growth o f exports and imports (Oh)&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture                                                 2.1      4.9&#13;
Industry                                                   -to       4.9&#13;
 Manufacturing                                             -to       4.9&#13;
Services                                                   2.6       0.1&#13;
&#13;
Householdfinal consumptionexpenditure                      2.2        t o&#13;
Generalgov't final consumptionexpenditure                  2.2      -4.2&#13;
Gross capital formation                                   -2.3     24.7&#13;
Imports of goods and sewices                      6.7     -0.3       2.7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
             1984    1994         2004       inflation (%f                    1&#13;
                        i g           st)&#13;
                        6 0           2 Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       w o          23 0&#13;
                       -I19          -5 9&#13;
                     -20 0            -9 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
T R A D E&#13;
             1986   1994          2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             ? 375&#13;
                an&#13;
              404&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             2984   IS94          2004      Currant account balanca to GDP (%)&#13;
&#13;
                       756         4 $46&#13;
                     5.880         Y  os&#13;
                   -5 734         -4 31':&#13;
&#13;
                       32'         t 052&#13;
                     2 'bb         12086&#13;
&#13;
                    -2 742        -4 "QY&#13;
&#13;
                     4 603         2 9?3&#13;
                      i P 6 i       2236     2'5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   1t355&#13;
               8 5  zcuo 1       I,%5 7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    lS54          2004&#13;
&#13;
                     2 Qi         2 t 3 N&#13;
                        64           38I&#13;
                          0             0&#13;
&#13;
                        8 5        4 b 5&#13;
                          8           48&#13;
                          0             0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        $6&#13;
                        -0             -7&#13;
                      39%         2 884&#13;
                        73&#13;
                          0                                    F 6.3WF&#13;
&#13;
                        77              c&#13;
                        27            45&#13;
                          4           36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                     IBRD 33433&#13;
&#13;
                                           3530'E                                                     3600'E                                                          3630'E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          To&#13;
                                                                                                                 To                   To                 Hims&#13;
                                                                                                            Al Hamidiyah         Tall Kalakh&#13;
                                                                                                                               Kabir&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           LEBANON                                                                                                             Qoubauyat&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     Halba&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                           3530'N&#13;
                                                                                                                      Funaydiq                                                           To&#13;
                                                                            Tripoli                          Abou Moussa                                                            Al Qusayr&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             Zhgarta                                           Hermel&#13;
                                                                                                  N O R T H&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Chekka                           L E B A N O N&#13;
                                                                                                Sib'il&#13;
                                                                                                Sib'il                                                                     Qaa&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Amioun                           Ihdin&#13;
                                                                      Jaoz                                    Bcharri                        .&#13;
                                                                                                                                           s     Orontes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           Douma                 Qurnat                                n&#13;
                                                                                                 as Sawda'&#13;
                                                                                                    Sawda'                          t     Al Labwah&#13;
                                                                                                 (3,088 m)              Aynata&#13;
           Mediterranean                                                                                                                                       y                M t n s .&#13;
                                                                                                                               M                          e&#13;
                                                                                                                                                        l&#13;
                      Sea                                                 Al Aqurah                                                               l                                          To&#13;
                                                       Jbeil                                                              n                     a&#13;
                                                                                                                        o                    V&#13;
                                                                        Ibrahim         Afqa                          n                a&#13;
                                                                                                                                  a                      A n t i - L e b a n o n           An Nabk&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   a&#13;
3400'N                                           Jounie                                                        b              k   Baalbeck&#13;
                                                                                                                            e                                                              3400'N&#13;
                                                                                                             e           B&#13;
                                                               M O U N T                                 L&#13;
                                  B E I R U T                L E B A N O N                              B E K A A&#13;
                                  BEIRUT              Antilyas&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                Rayak&#13;
&#13;
                                      Baabda               Hammana                               Zahleh&#13;
                                                                                                                            To&#13;
                                                                                                                        Az Zabadani&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Damour                                          Litani&#13;
                                                     Beit&#13;
                                                     ed Dine&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Jieh                                                                 To&#13;
                                                                            Joub Jannine                    Ad Dimas&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Saida            Awwali&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   Qaraaoun&#13;
                                             Jezzine&#13;
                  El Zahrani&#13;
3430'N                                                                           Rachaiya                                                                                                 3430'N&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Hasbani                                                  0          10           20               30 Kilometers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Nabatiyeh                                                                               0                   10                        20 Miles&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Maryjayoun&#13;
&#13;
                                        N A B A T I Y E H&#13;
            Tyre            Litani&#13;
                      S O U T H                                                                                                        LEBANON&#13;
                                                               To&#13;
                                                             Baniyas&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   L E B A N O N                      To&#13;
                                                      To                                                                           SELECTED CITIES AND TOWNS&#13;
                                                     Qiryat&#13;
                            Tibnine        Hula     Shemona                                                                        GOVERNORATE (MOHAFAZAT) CAPITALS&#13;
&#13;
 Naqoura                                                                                                                           NATIONAL CAPITAL&#13;
                            Bent Jbail                                         This map was produced by&#13;
                                                                               the Map Design Unit of The&#13;
                               Rmaich           To                             World Bank. The boundaries,                         RIVERS&#13;
                                               Gadot                           colors, denominations and&#13;
                                                                               any other information shown                         MAIN ROADS&#13;
       To                                                                      on this map do not imply, on&#13;
    Nahariyya                                                                  the part of The World Bank                          RAILROADS&#13;
                                                                               Group, any judgment on the&#13;
3300' N                                                                       legal status    of any territory,&#13;
                                                                               or any endorsement or                               GOVERNORATE (MOHAFAZAT) BOUNDARIES&#13;
                                                                               a c c e p t a n c e  o f s u c h&#13;
                                                                               boundaries.                                         INTERNATIONAL BOUNDARIES&#13;
&#13;
                                         3530'E                                                    3600'E&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   NOVEMBER 2004&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="7518022">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2007/02/7518022/lebanon-emergency-power-sector-reform-capacity-reinforcement-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2007/02/7518022/lebanon-emergency-power-sector-reform-capacity-reinforcement-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2007/02/7518022/lebanon-emergency-power-sector-reform-capacity-reinforcement-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2007-04-11T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2007/04/05/000020439_20070405103952/Rendered/INDEX/T7692.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2007/04/05/000020439_20070405103952/Rendered/PDF/T7692.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2007-02-26T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2007-04-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Buff cover</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309937</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Lebanon - Emergency Power Sector Reform
            Capacity Reinforcement Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objective of the Lebanon Emergency
            Power Sector Reform Capacity Reinforcement Project is to
            accelerate the implementation of reforms and restructuring
            of Lebanese Power Company (EdL) by enhancing the capacity in
            the Ministry of Energy and Water (MEOW), the Electricity
            utility (EdL) and a multi-Ministry Higher Level Committee
            (HLC) overseeing the reform process and in particular the
            restructuring of EdL, both in the short and the longer term.
            The project has three main components, with first being to
            support of the strengthening of MOEW to implement power
            sector policy reforms. This would include giving policy
            advice on key sector strategy issues, completing on going
            projects, and an establishment of a regulatory agency. The
            second project component is to provide support to the
            government of Lebanon for the restructuring of the EdL. The
            third component is to provide support to EdL to improve the
            operational and financial performance and the implementation
            of its restructuring. This would include developing a plan
            for procurement and efficiency, transmission and
            distribution reliability, help on financial issues and
            accounting, and the actual advisory of consultants for the restructuring.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Lebanon - Emergency Power Sector Reform
            Capacity Reinforcement Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Lebanon - Emergency Power Sector
            Reform Capacity Reinforcement Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2007/02/7518022/lebanon-emergency-power-sector-reform-capacity-reinforcement-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>LB-Emergency Power Sector Reform Capacity
            Reinforcement -- P104774</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Corporate Law,Infrastructure Economics,Energy Production and Transportation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Environment,Law and Development,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Energy</teratopic>
        <count>Lebanon</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe, Middle East and North Africa!$!107234</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Middle East!$!80463</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000020439_20070405103952</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Power</subsc>
        <admreg>Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Environment,Law and Development,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Energy</historic_topic>
        <prdln>Special Financing</prdln>
        <sectr>Energy and mining</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accountability, Accounting, administrative
            procedures, approach, asset register, auditing, audits,
            availability, capitalization, collective, commercial law,
            comparative advantage, contract negotiation, cost recovery,
            crude oil, debt, decision making, deficits, Deposits,
            distribution losses, economic growth, EIB, electricity,
            electricity consumers, electricity generation, electricity
            infrastructure, Electricity Law, electricity sector,
            electricity sector reform, electricity services, energy
            needs, energy policies, energy strategy, Environmental,
            environmental impacts, environmental protection, Exchange
            Rate, Financial Management, Financial Performance, financial
            reports, financial statements, fuel, fuel chain, fuel
            supply, generation capacity, generators, government budget,
            government expenditures, government subsidies, holding
            company, housing, imports, income, incorporated,
            incorporation, Independent Power Producers, Indigenous
            Peoples, inventory, investment program, legal framework,
            limited, LNG, maintenance contracts, managers, Middle East,
            Natural Gas, natural gas pipeline, North Africa, oil,
            outsourcing, Plant efficiency, policy environment,
            post-conflict, POWER, Power Company, power generation, power
            plant, power plants, Power Producer, Power Producers, POWER
            SECTOR, POWER SECTOR REFORM, private sector participation,
            Privatization, productivity, public expenditures, public
            finance, public service provision, regulatory agency,
            regulatory authority, reorganization, resources management,
            retirement, service contracts, service providers,
            stakeholders, stocks, supply chain, Sustainable Development,
            sustainable growth, tariff structures, technical assistance, voltage
        </keywd>
        <owner>Sustainable Development (MNSSD)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Emergency Recovery Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe, Middle East and North Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Middle East</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF058084-EMERGENCY POWER SECTOR REFORM
            CAPACITY REINFORCEMENT PROJECT</trustfund>
        <repnb>T7692</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>MM</ml:concept><ml:concept>EMMP</ml:concept><ml:concept>EMP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business and Commercial Laws and Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Green Growth and Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Maternal Mortality and Morbidity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Management and Mitigation Plans</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Law and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Green Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Corporate Law</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Lebanon</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>