<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP-738&#13;
Issues in the Appraisal of Energy Projects&#13;
for Oil-Importing Developing Countries&#13;
Sudhir Anand&#13;
Barry Nalebuff     FILE  COPY&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 738&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 738&#13;
Issues in the Appraisal of Energy Projects&#13;
for Oil-Importing Developing Countries&#13;
Sudhir Anand&#13;
Barry Nalebuff&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1985&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, NW.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing July 1985&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'lena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Sudhir Anand is a fellow and tutor at St. Catherine's College, Oxford University,&#13;
and university lecturer in quantitative economic analysis. Barry Nalebuff is a junior&#13;
fellow of the Society of Fellows of Harvard University. Both are consultants to the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Anand, Sudhir, 1946-&#13;
Issues in the appraisal of energy projects&#13;
for oil-importing developing countries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 738)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Energy development--Developing countries--Cost&#13;
effectiveness. I. Nalebuff, Barry, 1958-&#13;
II. Title. III. Series.&#13;
HD9502.D442A53   1985    333.79'15'091724            85-13619&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0563-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
This paper develops a theoretical framework to evaluate&#13;
the benefits and costs of energy projects in oil-importing&#13;
developing countries (OIDCs). The framework is used to address&#13;
various questions: How should the problems of energy dependency&#13;
and vulnerability be reflected in a project appraisal? Are there&#13;
externalities not captured in the market price of the resource?&#13;
Should royalty values be included in cost-benefit calculations?&#13;
Why do the real prices of exhaustible resources rise over time?&#13;
Should several energy development projects be done simultaneously?&#13;
What are the true costs of stockpiling oil? Is there a need for&#13;
an international institution to act as coordinator directing a&#13;
strategy for information gathering and project diversification&#13;
across countries?&#13;
We are particularly grateful to Harinder Kohli for motivating&#13;
this work and for providing continuous support and encouragement. We&#13;
appreciate the comments and suggestions on earlier drafts from Panos&#13;
Cavoulacos, Kemal Dervis, William Hogan, Harinder Kohli, Deepak Lal,&#13;
Alan Manning, Ricardo Martin, James Mirrlees, John Page, D.C. Rao,&#13;
Paul Seabright, Edilberto Segura, Robert Stobaugh, Yannis Stournaras, and&#13;
Michael Webb. Tony Tenorio expertly guided this paper both in and out of&#13;
the word processor maze, and we are very grateful to him.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ISSUES IN THE APPRAISAL OF ENERGY PROJECTS&#13;
FOR OIL-IMPORTING DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
1.  INTRODUCTION ...................       1...... ....ee.....          1&#13;
2.  COST-BENEFIT ANALYSIS .... oo ..... o. oo... o..o...oo...o......o   5&#13;
2.1  Evaluating Conflicting Probability Estimates ... 0.......      5&#13;
2.2  The Costs of Uncertainty         ..............................  10&#13;
2.3  Valuation of Project Output Under Uncertainty ....*....   11&#13;
2.4  Income Distribution Considerations ....................       20&#13;
2.5  Correcting for Uncertainty Through the Discount Rate ..    21&#13;
2.6  Project Appraisal in Relation to the Status Quo........    23&#13;
3.  HOTELLING'S RULE AND THE PRICE PATH OF OIL ....... . .........    26&#13;
3.1  Perfect Competition, Costless Extraction, and a&#13;
Constant Discount Rate    .......... * * * * a ......*....   27&#13;
3.,2  Extraction Costs o..oo........ooo......o...o.....o...a.....oo..oo..o...    31&#13;
3.3  Imperfect Competition . . . . . . . . . ..... . . ... . . . . . ... . . ..0 0......  33&#13;
3.4  The Discount Rate in Developing Countries        .............   35&#13;
3.5  The Cost Arising from Uncertain Reserves ..............      36&#13;
3.6  The Effects of New Energy Supplies ....................      39&#13;
4.  COORDINATING STRATEGIES ....      ................................    42&#13;
4.1  Information Externalities in Exploration       ..............  42&#13;
4.2  Diversification and Multi-Project Analysis    ............   44&#13;
4.3  Risk Pooling and Multi-Project Analysis ...............      48&#13;
5.  THE COSTS OF IMPORTING OIL .................................       51&#13;
5.1  The Costs of Stockpiling         ..............................  55&#13;
5.2  Inventories and Flexibility in Production    .............   56&#13;
5.3  Financing Energy Development in OIDCs        .................  59&#13;
6.  CONCLUSIONS    ................ . * . . . . . . . . . ......................... .    63&#13;
7.  REFERENCES ......        ..........................................  66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ISSUES IN THE APPRAISAL OF ENERGY PROJECTS&#13;
FOR OIL-IMPORTING DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
1. INTRODUCTION&#13;
The theory behind cost-benefit analysis is relatively well&#13;
developed [see Little and Mirrlees (1968), (1974); Dasgupta, Marglin and&#13;
Sen (1972); Squire and van der Tak (1975); Ray (1984); Mason and Merton&#13;
(1984)], but its application to real world problems is not always easy.&#13;
This paper considers the application of cost-benefit analysis to energy&#13;
problems in oil-importing developing countries (OIDCs).&#13;
The results are divided into four parts: Section 2 focuses on&#13;
presenting a methodology for handling uncertainty; Section 3 studies the&#13;
implications of exhaustibility; Section 4 examines the externalities&#13;
associated with exploration; Section 5 applies these tools in an analysis&#13;
of the costs associated with importing oil.&#13;
We begin in Section 2 with a discussion of the theoretical issues&#13;
involved in the appraisal of energy projects in OIDCs. Cost-benefit&#13;
analysis is not straightforward in the presence of uncertainty. There may&#13;
be several conflicting estimates of a project's chance of success. The&#13;
range of possible outcomes can affect both the total risk borne in the&#13;
economy and the income distribution. Uncertain future returns have to be&#13;
appropriately discounted to the present. Projects which deplete&#13;
exhaustible resources are irreversible and therefore the cost-benefit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
analysis must take into account the value of current reserves. These&#13;
issues are all addressed in the general framework of the expected welfare&#13;
maximization model.&#13;
In Section 3 we present Hotelling's rule as the starting point&#13;
for forming expectations about the price path of oil and other exhaustible&#13;
energy resources. All project appraisals for programs ranging from new&#13;
energy development to conservation or stockpiling are strongly influenced&#13;
by the expected future price of energy, and oil in particular. Here,&#13;
exhaustibility plays an important role. Energy prices today and in the&#13;
future depend on estimates of total world hydrocarbon reserves, their&#13;
extraction costs, and the predicted availability of backstop technologies.&#13;
To a large extent, oil serves as a proxy for energy. Unexpected dis-&#13;
coveries lead to jumps in energy price. In addition to the price and&#13;
quantity risks associated with uncertain reserves, there is an inefficiency&#13;
in the intertemporal allocation of oil; depletion takes place more slowly&#13;
in order to maintain flexibility in the event of worse-case scenarios. The&#13;
gains from developing new energy supplies (and conservation) include lower&#13;
prices, reduced vulnerability, and greater competition in the world mar-&#13;
ket. Countries will also respond differently to the expected price path of&#13;
oil. Oil-importing developing countries frequently have above average&#13;
discount rates due to below average creditworthiness and constraints&#13;
arising from imperfect capital markets or restrictions on foreign invest-&#13;
ment; from their perspective, the high price of oil today relative to the&#13;
future should lead them to deplete their own resources at a faster rate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section 4 widens the scope of cost-benefit analysis to capture&#13;
the externalities involved when research strategies for exploration are&#13;
coordinated. The uncertainty concerning the total size of oil and gas&#13;
reserves hurts all oil-importing countries. Because information can easily&#13;
be shared once obtained, the gains to information gathering extend beyond a&#13;
country's border; projects that reduce the uncertainty associated with&#13;
reserve levels must be evaluated from an international perspective. The&#13;
advantage of better information is that countries can choose their actions&#13;
more appropriately. There may also be economies of scale for gathering&#13;
information; a little knowledge may be useless but it is still costly to&#13;
acquire.  Related is the question of economies of scope:  to develop&#13;
renewable energy resources, how many competing directions of research&#13;
should be financed? Since only the best solutions will be implemented,&#13;
this reduces the advantages to diversification. With regard to diversi-&#13;
fication, there is an important distinction between risk-sharing and risk-&#13;
pooling: sharing involves spreading risk among a larger number of indivi-&#13;
duals, while pooling involves accepting a larger number of less than&#13;
perfectly correlated projects. Pooling together independent projects&#13;
increases both the total expected return and the total variance. When the&#13;
risks are already spread as thinly as possible, there is no safety in the&#13;
law of large numbers.&#13;
Section 5 examines the options for an oil-importing developing&#13;
country to reduce both its vulnerability and dependence on imported oil.&#13;
Stockpiles can be an effective and inexpensive tool to lower a country's&#13;
vulnerability to short-run supply disruptions. Other strategies many&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
developing countries could use to reduce their dependence on foreign oil in&#13;
the long-run include (i) increasing conservation, (ii) promoting renewable&#13;
energy projects and, in the medium-run, (iii) depleting their stocks of&#13;
exhaustible energy resources. Because of capital constraints and the&#13;
difficulties associated with financing private contracts, there may be too&#13;
little energy development taking place in oil-importing developing&#13;
countries. The evidence presented by Blitzer et.al. (1984) is quite&#13;
striking. While 70% of 1980 worldwide exploratory wells were drilled in&#13;
the United States compared with about 3% for the entire group of&#13;
oil-importing developing countries, the success rates were almost equal at&#13;
30%. In terms of cost effectiveness during the 1970s, the developing&#13;
countries were four times better: 1.6 barrels of hydrocarbon reserves were&#13;
generated per dollar of investment in developing countries compared with&#13;
0.4 barrels of reserves in the United States.&#13;
Section 6 brings together the theory and applications in a brief&#13;
conclusion that summarizes the results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
2. COST-BENEFIT ANALYSIS&#13;
The first and most obvious problem in evaluating a project is the&#13;
fact that nothing is certain. To handle this difficulty, economists have&#13;
developed the use of statistical expectation. The relevant index is the&#13;
Expected Present Value (EPV) of the stream of returns emanating from a&#13;
project. This index considers the monetary value as a proxy for the&#13;
utility value of a project.   If in period t the probability of an output&#13;
worth Z is pt(Z), and rt is the appropriate rate of discount between&#13;
periods 1 and t, then&#13;
EPV =     f [ | Zpt(Z)dZ ]/(1 + rt)t*              (1)&#13;
t&#13;
The expected present value index is only the first step in&#13;
project appraisal. The following subsections elaborate this criterion from&#13;
the viewpoints of: estimating the probabilities p(Z); modifying the&#13;
criterion to reflect the costs of uncertainty; taking into account income&#13;
distribution effects; choosing an appropriate discount rate for the&#13;
project; accounting for the status quo, and examining project timing.&#13;
2.1 Evaluating Conflicting Probability Estimates&#13;
Probabilities are only estimates, and in practice they may be no&#13;
better than rough guesses. Thus, there may be several conflicting esti-&#13;
mates of the likelihood of any outcome; e.g., when flipping a weighted&#13;
coin, the probability of heads may be uncertain. This is contrasted in&#13;
section 2.2 with the different type of uncertainty caused by the possibil-&#13;
ity of multiple outcomes; for example, in a coin toss, the outcome,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
either heads or tails, is uncertain. This subsection focuses on the&#13;
problem of how to evaluate EPV when the range of possible outcomes is known&#13;
(e.g., heads or tails) but the probability of each event is uncertain.&#13;
Consider the following two situations. In case A, there are two&#13;
estimates: both show that the probability of a I million rupee return is&#13;
0.25.  In situation B, there is uncertainty in the estimates.  Estimate 1&#13;
shows the probability of a 1 million rupee return to be 0.10; estimate 2&#13;
shows the probability to be 0.40. In the second case there are conflicting&#13;
estimates of the chance of success, one believing it to be only 10% while&#13;
the other more optimistically expecting a 40% chance of success. The&#13;
probabilities are shown in the table below.&#13;
Case    A         B&#13;
Estimate 1        0.25       0.1&#13;
Estimate 2        0.25       0.4&#13;
Average        0.25       0.25&#13;
Since both estimates agree in Case A, it is straightforward that&#13;
the expected present value should be calculated using a 0.25 probability of&#13;
a 1 million rupee return. For Case B, assume that the two conflicting&#13;
estimates are equally precise. [Technically, this means that there is an&#13;
equal variance associated with each of the two estimates.] Both estimates&#13;
are then given equal weight and the expected chance of a 1 million rupee&#13;
return in Case B is&#13;
p(1,000,000) = (0.5 x 0.1) + (0.5 x 0.4) = 0.25,&#13;
which is the same as in Case A. The expected return, the variance, and all&#13;
other moments are equal in the two situations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The project in situation B should not be penalized because there&#13;
are conflicting estimates about its actual chance of success. There is no&#13;
risk aversion to uncertainty about the estimated probability of success.&#13;
Given a weighted average of the "best guesses" (the relative weights being&#13;
determined by the relative precisions of the estimates), there is no dis-&#13;
advantage from not knowing the exact probability of success. Indeed, there&#13;
can even be a benefit arising from uncertainty in the estimated probability&#13;
of success.&#13;
The benefit from uncertainty becomes clearer in the context of&#13;
sequential decision-making [Rothschild (1971)]. When the probability of&#13;
success is known with certainty, there is no more information that can be&#13;
found out. For example, the probability of heads when flipping an unbiased&#13;
coin is known to be 1/2. With this information, the only remaining&#13;
decision is whether or not to take the gamble. Alternatively, when the&#13;
probability of success is unknown, there is the additional possibility of&#13;
gaining further information. Of course, gathering this information may be&#13;
expensive and thus it is not necessarily worthwhile.&#13;
Faced with the two conflicting estimates in Case B of 0.1 and&#13;
0.4, there is a potential advantage to obtaining further estimates if the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
information costs are not too large. The new estimates can push the chance&#13;
of success up or down and this may affect the desirability of continuing&#13;
the project. This situation is depicted in the decision chart in&#13;
Figure 2.1. More information can also be gathered in Case A; however, the&#13;
impact and hence the value of the new information is expected to be&#13;
smaller.&#13;
The value of the additional information depends on the extent to&#13;
which the estimates diverge. When the probability is known (as in the case&#13;
of the unbiased coin) there is no value to obtaining additional estimates.&#13;
To the extent that the conflicting estimates are farther apart, there is&#13;
more uncertainty to be resolved.l/ There is greater confidence that 0.25&#13;
is the actual chance of success in Case A since both estimates agree; in&#13;
Case B at least one, and perhaps both, of the estimated probabilities must&#13;
be wrong.&#13;
1/ While the value of additional information may be high, the existence of&#13;
conflicting probability estimates does not in itself imply anything&#13;
about the costs of additional information. As always, benefits must be&#13;
compared with costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
~~N cet Risks&#13;
obtain additional&#13;
estimates&#13;
Figure 2.1: Decision Chart with Uncertain Probabilities of Success&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
This point may be summarized by noting that once an action is&#13;
taken, all that matters is the expected probability of success. There is&#13;
no reason to be risk averse due to divergent probability estimates; but,&#13;
divergent estimates suggest that there may be a value to obtaining further&#13;
information. When the cost of additional information is small, there can&#13;
be a potential gain from this flexibility.&#13;
2.2 The Costs of Uncertainty&#13;
A cost from uncertainty can arise when a project has several&#13;
possible outcomes. Individuals are averse to fluctuations in their&#13;
income. A project that generates returns Z with probability p(Z) has an&#13;
expected payment of&#13;
Z= f Zp(Z)dZ.                             (2)&#13;
The cost from bad outcomes is greater than the benefits from correspond-&#13;
ingly good outcomes. Decision-makers prefer a sure thing to any pure&#13;
gamble with the same expected outcome. And, except in the hypothetical&#13;
case of complete contingent claims markets, it is not possible to purchase&#13;
complete insurance and eliminate the effects of uncertainty [Arrow and Lind&#13;
(1970)].&#13;
Risk aversion becomes important when the range of the possible&#13;
income levels for individuals is more than trivially affected by the&#13;
outcome of the project. For Bangladesh, with its population of about&#13;
100 million, even a large project having returns between $50 million and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
$150 million results in an income variation per person of at most a&#13;
dollar. This may turn out to be a small risk relative to even a low per&#13;
capita national income of $100.&#13;
There are two factors that complicate this straightforward&#13;
example of a risk-sharing argument. Project outcomes are correlated with&#13;
the state of the economy; because there are real costs to the risks&#13;
associated with fluctuations in the economy, adding incremental risk will&#13;
be important. Secondly, project risks may not be spread evenly across the&#13;
population; appraisals must include consideration of the differential&#13;
effects of a project on different groups of people. These points are taken&#13;
up in the next two subsections.&#13;
2.3 Valuation of Project Output Under Uncertainty&#13;
This subsection demonstrates the importance of taking into&#13;
account the correlation between fluctuations in per capita income and&#13;
project output when calculating the costs of uncertainty.&#13;
Let Y     =  national income per person;&#13;
Z     =  net project output per person;&#13;
V(Y) = social valuation of representative person's&#13;
income, where V'(Y)&gt;0 and V"(Y)&lt;0.&#13;
A project Z should be done if it raises expected social welfare, i.e.,&#13;
E[V(Y+Z)]&gt;E[V(Y)], where E[ ] denotes the expectation operator.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Define the certainty equivalent z of a project as that income&#13;
which the government would consider equally satisfactory as a project Z&#13;
whose net output is random. In other words, z is defined through the&#13;
equation:&#13;
EIV(Y+Z)1 = E[V(Y+z)I.                         (3)&#13;
Letting Y=E[Y] and Z=E[Z], we can expand the left-hand and right-hand sides&#13;
of equation (3) around (Y+Z). The Taylor series expansions to second order&#13;
of the left-hand and right-hand sides, respectively, are:&#13;
E[V(Y+Z)I = V(Y+Z) + V'(Y+Z)E[Y-T+Z--] + (1/2)V"(Y+Z)E[(Y-Y)+(Z-Z)12  (4)&#13;
E[V(Y+z)] = V(Y+Z) + V'(Y+Z)E[Y-Y4+z-ZI + (1/2)V"(Y+Z)E[(Y-Y)+(z-Z)]2  (5)&#13;
Equating the right-hand sides of equations (4) and (5) yields&#13;
(1/2)V"(Y+Z)[Var(Y) + Var(Z) + 2Cov(Y,Z)]&#13;
= (z-Z)V'(Y+Z) + (1/2)V"(Y+Z)[Var(Y) + (z-Z)2].         (6)&#13;
Hence,&#13;
z= Z + (1/2) V (Y+Z)  [Var(Z) + 2Cov(Y,Z) - (z-Z)21&#13;
V' (Y+Z)&#13;
= Z - (1/2) R(Y+Z) [Var(Z) + 2Cov(Y,Z)I                 (7)&#13;
where R(y) =  YV(y) is the relative risk aversion (or elasticity of&#13;
V'(y)&#13;
marginal valuation of income) at income level y, and (z-Z)2 is assumed&#13;
(n+z)&#13;
negligible compared with (z-Z).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
The costs of uncertainty can be broken up into two terms: the&#13;
variance effect and the covariance effect. We look at these two terms&#13;
sequentially in order to gauge their relative importance. As will be seen&#13;
below, the cost due to the variance term will typically be significantly&#13;
smaller than the benefit associated with the (negative) covariance term for&#13;
energy projects in OIDCs.&#13;
Both terms are equally affected by the choice of the relative&#13;
risk aversion parameter, denoted by R. Stern (1977) reviews the literature&#13;
on alternative estimates of the elasticity of social marginal valuation of&#13;
income, and suggests values between 1.5 and 2.5 as reasonable and broadly&#13;
acceptable. We assume a constant value of R=2 in the relevant range&#13;
around (Y+Z), which implies the specification for the valuation function&#13;
of V(y) - a - by-1.&#13;
First we focus on the variance term. If national income per&#13;
person is itself certain (i.e., Y is not a random variable), then&#13;
Cov(Y,Z) = 0. In this case, equation (7) reduces to:&#13;
z     - (1/2) R Var(Z)                           (8)&#13;
Consider a large government project in which over the range of&#13;
possible outcomes per capita income can vary by 1%. For the example of&#13;
Bangladesh, this would be a project with an outcome that is uncertain over&#13;
a $100 million range. Even for countries with smaller populations such as&#13;
Mali, Upper Volta, or Botswana where energy projects of $150 million would&#13;
not be unrealistic, the uncertainty associated with the project outcome&#13;
will almost always be less than 5% of per capita income.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Starting with a per capita income of $100, an example of a&#13;
project with a 1% range is:&#13;
( $0.5 with probability 1/2 )&#13;
Z =  (                               )                                      (9)&#13;
( $1.5 with probability 1/2 )&#13;
The project has an expected per capita return Z = 1 and a variance&#13;
Var(Z) = 0.25. The risk premium or proportion by which the expected money&#13;
value of the project has to be deflated because of the uncertain return is:&#13;
(Z-z)  (1/2)(R)Var(Z)&#13;
%         Z~~(Y+Z)&#13;
(1/2)(2)0.25 = 0.0025.                     (10)&#13;
101&#13;
Thus, the risk premium is just under one-quarter of one percent. In this&#13;
case the expected monetary value of the project has to be adjusted&#13;
downwards by a miniscule amount which, for practical purposes, may be&#13;
ignored.&#13;
When a per capita income of $100 is subject to a 5% risk, the&#13;
risk premium is twenty-five times bigger; here the downward adjustment&#13;
would be around 6%. Although this is now relevant, we see below that it&#13;
may still be only one-eighth as large as a realistic effect due to the&#13;
corresponding covariance.&#13;
Economists are concerned with the value of the energy project&#13;
conditional on the state of the economy and of the world. Knowing the&#13;
correlation between the economy and the project is important both for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
determining the value to the economy of money from the project and for&#13;
determining the amount of money the project is likely to generate. A small&#13;
variation of the earlier examples shows how the correlation between&#13;
national income and the project's return can have a much more significant&#13;
effect on the certainty equivalent monetary value of the project.&#13;
The first example demonstrated that the risk adjustments asso-&#13;
ciated with even large projects are relatively small (with the qualifica-&#13;
tion that income distribution effects must also be considered). But to&#13;
determine the monetary value of a project, it is essential to realize that&#13;
the price of the output, especially in the case of energy, will in general&#13;
be related to the state of the economy. The welfare value of the project&#13;
will also depend on the state of the economy. We are not worried about&#13;
causality, whether the project affects the economy or the state of the&#13;
economy affects the project. Here, we are emphasizing that the swings in&#13;
the economy may be correlated with the output of the project and this&#13;
should be taken into account. For energy projects in oil-importing&#13;
developing countries it is very likely that the marginal welfare value of&#13;
the project's output, ZV'(Y), and national income per person in the economy&#13;
as a whole, Y, are negatively correlated since they are oppositely affected&#13;
by variations in the world price of oil. An oil embargo will make the&#13;
development of internal energy sources (including energy conservation)&#13;
particularly attractive both because the economy will be depressed due to&#13;
the embargo and because of the skyrocketing price of the remaining&#13;
available oil; the marginal welfare value of income will be high when the&#13;
project output is high. That is, for an economy dependent on oil imports,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
oil will usually be expensive when the economy is depressed and vice&#13;
versa. These effects would be further amplified by changes in the shadow&#13;
price of foreign exchange, which are also likely to be negatively&#13;
correlated with the economy.2/&#13;
We can now make illustrative estimates of the extent to which the&#13;
expected monetary value of output may have to be adjusted to take account&#13;
of fluctuations in the marginal value of income. Consider the earlier&#13;
example of a 1% variation again, but now suppose that when the output of&#13;
the project is $0.5, national income per head is $110, and when the output&#13;
of the project is $1.5, national income per head is $90. Again suppose&#13;
that the two events occur with probability 1/2. We continue to assume that&#13;
the elasticity of marginal valuation of income is two in this range, i.e.,&#13;
V'(y) = y-2. In this case, there is a negative covariance between Y and Z,&#13;
given by&#13;
Cov(Y,Z) = E[(Y-Y)(Z-Z)]                                  (11)&#13;
= -5.&#13;
The certainty equivalent monetary value for this project, z, is greater&#13;
than its expected monetary value, Z, and the proportional upward adjustment&#13;
can be obtained from equation (7) straightforwardly as&#13;
2/ A project appraisal has to consider all the general equilibrium&#13;
effects of changes in the economy. It is necessary to estimate&#13;
changes both in the price of energy and in the prices of all other&#13;
commodities (i.e. foreign exchange, interest rates, transportation,&#13;
etc.). To calculate the EPV, the expectation of the shadow value of&#13;
output has to be taken across all states of nature corresponding to oil&#13;
price (or supply) shocks. Strictly speaking, this requires working out&#13;
all the shadow prices in each state of nature contingent on assumptions&#13;
about government policy; this is not an easy task.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
(Z~Z= -(1/2)(R) [2o(,)&#13;
Z               (Y+Z-)Z&#13;
= (1/2)(2)10 = 0.099.                        (12)&#13;
101&#13;
This ignores the (downwards) adjustment for Var(Z) which was shown to be&#13;
negligible (0.0025). The negative correlation between Y and Z therefore&#13;
calls for an upward adjustment in Z of 9.9%. For R = 4 the increase is&#13;
twice as large, almost 20% of the expected monetary value of the project.&#13;
Such upward adjustments imply corresponding upward changes to the expected&#13;
present value of the entire stream of returns from the project.&#13;
When the project outcome ranges over 5% of per capita income&#13;
(e.g., Z = -$1.5 when income is $110 and Z = $3.5 when income is $90) then&#13;
the covariance correction is five times larger at almost 50%. It is now&#13;
important to include the 6% reduction due to the variance term, which still&#13;
leaves a net upward correction of approximately 44%.&#13;
Our conclusion from this analysis is that it may be necessary to&#13;
make significant adjustments to account for uncertainty. When calculating&#13;
an example of the size of the effects associated with the uncertainty in&#13;
the price and availability of oil imports, oil dependency can lead to a&#13;
negative correlation between the output of an energy project and national&#13;
income per head which is forty times more important than the variance in&#13;
income from the project for the average individual. This ratio of 40 to 1&#13;
does not depend on the magnitude of the relative risk aversion, as changes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
in R proportionally affect both terms. However, the ratio does depend on&#13;
the size of the project relative to national income; doubling the size of&#13;
the project (or considering a country with half the per capita income) also&#13;
doubles the relative importance of the variance effect. Even in the&#13;
largest projects (5% case), though, the covariance term is still eight&#13;
times larger and of the opposite sign.&#13;
A negative correlation between the return on asset i and the&#13;
portfolio as a whole is beneficial because it reduces the variance of the&#13;
total return.3/ Two important examples of energy projects negatively&#13;
correlated with the economy--conservation for the long-term and stockpiling&#13;
for the short-term--are considered in sections 3.6 and 5.1, respectively.&#13;
The beneficial effects of this negative correlation are analogous&#13;
to those associated with asset pricing in the literature on modern fin-&#13;
ance. Let ri and rm denote the random rates of return on stock i and on a&#13;
portfolio of all stocks in the market, respectively. Under the assumptions&#13;
of the capital asset pricing model (CAPM), the expected risk-adjusted rate&#13;
of return on stock i, ri, in an efficient market satisfies the equation&#13;
r.  rp +  im[ rm r[                                             (13)&#13;
where r is the risk-free interest rate,&#13;
3/ If the negative correlation is sufficiently large, people would be&#13;
willing to hold an asset which loses money on average. House insurance&#13;
is such an asset; the expected return to the owner is negative&#13;
(otherwise insurance companies would be unprofitable) but the payoff&#13;
occurs precisely when the marginal utility of income is very high.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Cov(ri, rm)                                               (14)&#13;
Sim =   Var(rm)&#13;
is a measure of risk, and rm is the expected rate of return on the market&#13;
portfolio [Sharpe (1964)]. In countries with well-developed capital&#13;
markets, ri is the appropriate risk-adjusted discount factor to use in&#13;
evaluating a project's returns. This approach has the advantage that it is&#13;
not necessary to estimate risk aversion coefficients needed in equation&#13;
(7); the cost of risk is determined by the required return on the market&#13;
portfolio. In developing countries, it may be easier to estimate risk&#13;
aversion parameters and thus calculate certainty equivalents directly&#13;
through equation (7) than to estimate the return on the market portfolio&#13;
(even if it exists). Two other difficulties that prevent straightforward&#13;
application of CAPM and the corresponding ri are presented in section 2.5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
2.4 Income Distribution Considerations&#13;
Project risks are not borne equally across the population.&#13;
+ ithough the earlier analysis with the representative individual assumes&#13;
that the government can and will spread risks evenly over the entire popu-&#13;
lation, in practice it may turn out that certain groups bear a dispro-&#13;
portionate share of variations in the price of energy. Government policy&#13;
could in principle correct the distributional consequences of oil price&#13;
changes, but this cannot be taken for granted. On balance, and without&#13;
strong evidence to the contrary, it is safer to assume that government&#13;
policy will remain unchanged. Project choice must take into account sub-&#13;
optimal policies of government, whatever the reason for their existence.&#13;
However, identifying government policies is not always straightforward.&#13;
For example, when oil import costs rise the government's financial position&#13;
is affected. If its policy is to maintain a balanced budget then the&#13;
government may be forced to raise taxes; if its policy is to maintain tax&#13;
rates then the government may be forced towards a budget deficit. In&#13;
advance, it is difficult to know whether government policy is to maintain&#13;
tax rates or a balanced budget.&#13;
If government policy fails to spread risk evenly then the use of&#13;
a representative individual can underestimate the costs associated with&#13;
energy price fluctuations, and the appraisal of domestic energy projects&#13;
should take such distributional implications into account.4/&#13;
4/ The analyses in this paper consider the sum of a project's effects&#13;
across a population and are thus cast in the framework of utilitarian-&#13;
ism. Other ethical considerations may affect the results of cost-&#13;
benefit analysis [Schulze and Kneese (1981)]. When evaluating the&#13;
effects of risk, a Rawlsian criterion would focus on the utility of the&#13;
worst-off individual while a refusal to make interpersonal comparisons&#13;
of utility would require the project to improve everyone's expected&#13;
welfare (Pareto criterion).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
2,5 Correcting for Uncertainty Through the Discount Rate&#13;
When evaluating an investment with an uncertain payoff over time,&#13;
it is sometimes possible to compensate for the riskiness by adjusting the&#13;
required rate of return or the discount rate in calculating EPV. For&#13;
riskier investments it is then argued that the adjustment is made by&#13;
raising the discount rate. In general, neither proposition is&#13;
straightforward except under very special conditions [Lind (1982)].&#13;
The correct measure of project risk is, of course, covariance&#13;
with the economy.  In the CAPM model, using a project's covariance with the&#13;
market to arrive at the risk-adjusted rate of return works but only on the&#13;
margin; that is, it is only worth spending an additional dollar to expand&#13;
the project if that generates an increase of more than (l+r)* What CAPM&#13;
misses and what is important when evaluating large energy projects are the&#13;
intramarginal returns.&#13;
Large positive gains do not offset equivalently large losses due&#13;
to the concavity of the social valuation function. Consider a typical&#13;
investment project which becomes profitable after a set-up period in which&#13;
there are losses. Initially, when the expected return in a period is&#13;
negative marginal valuation increases, so the direction of the appropriate&#13;
adjustment in the discount rate applied to the expected return is to lower&#13;
the rate. Later, when the expected returns are positive, diminishing&#13;
marginal valuation requires a higher discount rate. It follows that no&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
single correction in the discount rate can be made to reflect risk&#13;
correctly at every point in time if the expected return is positive in some&#13;
periods and negative in others. Even if there is some risk-adjusted rate r&#13;
which equates the present value of expected returns (Zt) discounted at r to&#13;
the present value of the certainty equivalent of these returns (Zt)&#13;
discounted at the risk-free rate r, there will be no guarantee that r &gt; r.&#13;
There is also another, quite separate, point concerning the&#13;
discount rate if it is known that the project risk will be resolved in the&#13;
course of the project's life [Wilson (1982)]. Assume that the values of&#13;
the uncertain return in each period are, in fact, correctly captured by&#13;
discounting the expected returns by a risk-adjusted rate, r, which is&#13;
greater than the risk-free rate, r.  It is only correct to use the rate r&#13;
to discount the expected returns until the uncertainty has been resolved.&#13;
A return twenty years in the future that is uncertain today but will become&#13;
known in five years should only be discounted for five years of risk. This&#13;
can be seen by adapting our earlier example.&#13;
Suppose the project Z at the end of each period yields a return&#13;
of $0.5 with probability 1/2 and $1.5 with probability 1/2. After the&#13;
first period, the uncertainty becomes resolved one way or the other&#13;
forever. Thus at the end of the first and all subsequent periods, the&#13;
returns are either ($0.5, $0.5, $0.5,...) with probability 1/2 or ($1.5,&#13;
$1.5, $1.5,...) with probability 1/2. For example, the project might be an&#13;
oil-drilling project whose returns depend on the size of the reserves which&#13;
become known only at the end of period 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
For this project at the beginning of period 1, the expected&#13;
present value of all future returns discounted at the rate r, EPV(r), is&#13;
given by:&#13;
-11                                                  (15)&#13;
EFV (r)=I        -t=-&#13;
t=1 (1+r)      r&#13;
On the other hand, the present value of the project at the end of period 1&#13;
will be either (0.5)(l+r)/r with probability 1/2 or (1.5)(1+r)/r with&#13;
probability 1/2. Because this return is risky, it has to be discounted&#13;
back to the beginning of the first period by the rate r. Hence, the&#13;
correct measure of expected present value is:&#13;
EPV(r,r) =             l+r                                      (16)&#13;
r(l+r)    r+rr&#13;
This yields a higher present value because&#13;
1+r      +      1&#13;
EPV(r,r)    l-+r   &gt;  +r  &gt; 1 = EPV(r)&#13;
r+rr    r+rr   r&#13;
since r &gt; r.  Using a higher discount rate to value uncertain future&#13;
returns underestimates their value if the uncertainty is diminished or&#13;
resolved at some intermediate point in the life of the project.&#13;
2.6 Project Appraisal in Relation to the Status Quo&#13;
Cost-benefit analyses often neglect the costs associated with&#13;
depleting a finite reserve of an exhaustible resource. The price of oil in&#13;
the ground is called its royalty value. This royalty value should be&#13;
subtracted from the market (i.e. well-head) price of oil in a project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
appraisal. The reason is that oil extracted now cannot be extracted&#13;
later: the total supply is fixed. This opportunity cost is a real cost.&#13;
In particular, instead of extracting the oil it may be possible to sell it&#13;
in its current form by auctioning the drilling and extraction rights. That&#13;
is why it is important to emphasize that costs and benefits should be&#13;
measured relative to the status quo. Currently the oil is in the ground.&#13;
When developing exhaustible resources, the appropriate measure of benefit&#13;
is the value added, the difference between the price of oil and the royalty&#13;
value of deposits.&#13;
The royalty value of an oil reserve is based on the market price&#13;
of oil in the ground. Market prices are determined by the valuation of the&#13;
last (or marginal) unit sold. A problem arises in countries whose reserves&#13;
are not traded. Domestic conditions may prevent many LDCs from trading&#13;
their coal, gas and oil reserves internationally. One starting point for&#13;
valuing oil reserves that are not traded is the price paid for the&#13;
currently operating fields in Prudhoe Bay. The auction price divided by&#13;
total expected reserves leads to a price per barrel in the ground off&#13;
Alaska. Adjustments have to be made in order to estimate the price per&#13;
barrel in the ground of a developing country. More uncertainty about&#13;
reserve levels and higher costs of extraction or transportation to points&#13;
of sale will lead to a lower royalty value.5/ Such differences in costs&#13;
5/ With uncertain reserves, the royalty value is also related to marginal&#13;
exploration costs [Devarajan and Fisher (1982)].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
must also be discounted because they are spread over time. In the absence&#13;
of complete markets, countries can at least begin to place bounds on the&#13;
value of their reserves by comparing their relative profitability with that&#13;
of reserves traded in the market, such as off Alaska.&#13;
Project appraisals which include in the benefits the value of&#13;
extracted oil but neglect estimated royalty costs can easily have internal&#13;
rates of return of several hundred percent. Even so, using this method of&#13;
accounting, alternative projects can have even higher rates of return. For&#13;
example, a country that sells its oil reserves in the ground to a foreign&#13;
oil company receives a large positive payment and apparently incurs no&#13;
costs. This leads to a practically infinite internal rate of return. This&#13;
example helps illustrate both the weakness of using the internal rate of&#13;
return criterion and the mistakes that may be made if the royalty cost of&#13;
depleting the resource is left out of the calculation.&#13;
It is also important to consider the timing of energy projects.&#13;
Since oil reserves are exhaustible, complete extraction today precludes&#13;
extraction tomorrow; that is, alternative programs for oil extraction are&#13;
mutually exclusive. Even with renewable energy projects, timing decisions&#13;
require comparisons of mutually exclusive options; the decision to proceed&#13;
with a synthetic fuels program today precludes postponing the project for&#13;
one year. Thus, even when the expected discounted value of one project&#13;
option is positive, it may not be the optimal alternative. Project&#13;
appraisal should choose the program with the highest (positive) expected&#13;
value among all of the mutually exclusive options.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
3. HOTELLING'S RULE AND THE PRICE PATH OF OIL&#13;
Oil is an exhaustible resource; a barrel extracted today results&#13;
in one barrel less for extraction tomorrow. When the timing of oil extrac-&#13;
tion and sales is chosen to maximize discounted profits, this leads to an&#13;
expected price path due to Hotelling (1931). This section demonstrates the&#13;
technique for calculating an optimal extraction rule in a general model.&#13;
The solution is specialized first in a subsection focusing on a stylized&#13;
example of perfect competition, and then in subsections looking at extrac-&#13;
tion costs and imperfect competition.&#13;
Hotelling's rule is the solution to the following dynamic&#13;
optimization problem. Consider an entrepreneur who owns S barrels of oil&#13;
reserves. If he sells at a rate of qt barrels at time t, he expects to&#13;
receive revenue at the rate of R(qt); in the case of perfect competition,&#13;
R(qt) will be equal to expected price Pt times quantity qt. His costs of&#13;
extraction, C(qt,4t,t), depend on the time t at which the extraction&#13;
occurs, and on both the extraction rate (qt) and the change in the&#13;
extraction rate (4t); extracting a larger quantity is costlier as is the&#13;
attempt to speed up the extraction rate.6/ The entrepreneur is&#13;
constrained to sell no more than his total reserves, S.&#13;
6/ The problem can be further complicated by permitting extraction costs&#13;
to depend on the size of remaining reserves and by permitting storage&#13;
(instead of sales) after extraction.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Formally, the problem can be expressed as 7/&#13;
-rt t&#13;
Max IO fo [R(qt) - C(qt. 4t,t)]e t]dt,                           (17)&#13;
subject to           foq dt S S,                                 (18)&#13;
and            q   o.                                    (19)&#13;
Letting subscripts denote partial derivatives with respect to the relevant&#13;
argument, the Euler condition for an optimal path can be written as:&#13;
-rt                          rt                   (0&#13;
[R1t(t) - C (q ,q ,t)]e       - _ 1   - d[C (q, qtt)e  t]/dt                (20)&#13;
with strict equality whenever the extraction rate is positive, and where X&#13;
is chosen to ensure that the solution satisfies the exhaustion constraint&#13;
(18). Although it may appear that this is difficult to interpret, in the&#13;
special cases considered below the solution is surprisingly intuitive.&#13;
3.1 Perfect Competition, Costless Extraction, and a Constant Discount Rate&#13;
The simplest and most idealized case involves entrepreneurs&#13;
acting under perfect competition with costless extraction and a constant&#13;
discount rate, r. The optimality condition (20) reduces to&#13;
-rt                       -rt,(1&#13;
q &gt;o and p e    =A;or qoandpte              A(&#13;
where Pt is the market price. Thus oil is extracted and sold only in the&#13;
7/ We use rt to represent the continuous time analogue of the average&#13;
discount rate between o and t, i.e.,&#13;
rt ' [JO  r(s)ds]/t&#13;
whr   ra0&#13;
where r(s) is the instantaneous rate of discount at time s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
period(s) in which its present discounted value is highest. The Lagrange&#13;
multiplier is the maximum discounted price, A = max [ptert.&#13;
Hotelling applied this example in an equilibrium model to deter-&#13;
mine an expected price path of oil. Let all oil reserves be held by entre-&#13;
preneurs acting in a competitive market. No single seller believes that he&#13;
can affect the price of oil. Thus, all entrepreneurs will sell their oil&#13;
in the period (periods) which has (have) the maximum discounted price&#13;
pte-rt. Unless the present discounted price for every period is the same,&#13;
the market will not be in equilibrium. For example, if the price of oil is&#13;
expected to rise more quickly than the nominal interest rate, then all&#13;
suppliers will hold on to their oil anticipating higher profits. This&#13;
raises the price of oil today relative to its price in the future and&#13;
restores equilibrium. If the price of oil is expected to rise slower than&#13;
the interest rate, suppliers will try to sell more oil today and invest&#13;
their profits to receive the nominal interest rate.  This flooding of the&#13;
market leads to a lowering of the price today relative to the future and&#13;
restores the equilibrium path. Hence under the assumption of perfect&#13;
competition, costless extraction, and a constant discount rate, the price&#13;
must rise at the nominal interest rate.&#13;
The rising price path will be constrained if there is a backstop&#13;
technology which can provide an unlimited supply of energy at a constant&#13;
price. In this case, the oil price path must also be at the right level to&#13;
ensure that the stock of exhaustible resources will be exhausted just at&#13;
the time when the backstop technology is expected to become competitive.&#13;
If entrepreneurs thought that an alternative supply would arrive before&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
their stocks are exhausted, they would increase their oil supply now in&#13;
order to prevent being stuck with excess oil in the future. This brings&#13;
the market back into equilibrium as it results in a lower price and higher&#13;
demand in each period.&#13;
Because of the boundary condition that leads to exhaustion, the&#13;
price of oil today is very sensitive to changes in long-run interest&#13;
rates. A higher interest rate results in a price path of oil with a faster&#13;
rise in prices over time. If today's price remains constant then all&#13;
future consumption will be reduced. To ensure exhaustion, the equilibrium&#13;
price today must fall to compensate for its swifter rise. Higher interest&#13;
rates shift consumption from the future to the present. Similarly, because&#13;
of the boundary condition, if new reserves are found or an increase in&#13;
conservation takes place, the whole equilibrium price path must be lowered&#13;
to stimulate the additional demand needed to ensure exhaustion; thus,&#13;
today's price must fall.&#13;
The recent dramatic rises and falls in the price of oil have&#13;
caused many to doubt the validity of Hotelling's implied steady rise in the&#13;
price of oil. However, even under these very stylized assumptions, Hotell-&#13;
ing's rule only requires that the price of oil is expected to rise at the&#13;
interest rate. The price path of oil will be changed by the presence of&#13;
extraction costs, by variations in the interest rate, by new discoveries&#13;
that affect expected world oil reserves, by new technologies for the use of&#13;
oil substitutes (coal, synthetic fuels) or for interfuel substitution, and&#13;
by changes in consumption patterns (due for example to faster than&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
anticipated conservation efforts). The volatility of nominal interest&#13;
rates and fluctuations in the world's proven reserves are reflected in the&#13;
high variance of oil prices around their expected (or average) growth&#13;
path.&#13;
Over the time scale for which an oil futures market exists&#13;
(approximately one year ahead), oil can be sold on the spot market and&#13;
purchased in the futures market if its price is expected to rise slower&#13;
than the rate of interest. Clearly this argument only works if one has oil&#13;
to sell today. But, the presence of reserves shows that somebody must be&#13;
saving rather than selling oil today in order to sell it next year. Those&#13;
holding reserves have the power to bring the market into equilibrium.&#13;
Although the possibility for arbitrage exists, several potential&#13;
factors can interfere with the stylized Hotelling solution:&#13;
(1) Extraction is not costless. As illustrated in equation (17),&#13;
costs depend both on the rate of extraction and on changes in the&#13;
speed of extraction;&#13;
(2) Oil for the future is held by a monopolist who in the interest of&#13;
profit maximization chooses not to sell today;&#13;
(3) Oil for the future is held by a cartel with conflicting objec-&#13;
tives different from profit maximization;8!/&#13;
8/ For example, current revenue requirements may lead some members of the&#13;
cartel to overproduce, thus disrupting production quota agreements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
(4) oil for the future is held by both a cartel and a competitive&#13;
fringe, and either (i) the competitive fringe chooses to save&#13;
rather than sell its oil for strategic reasons [Nichols and&#13;
Zeckhauser (1977), Crawford and Sobel (1982)]; or (ii) the&#13;
competitive fringe tries to sell oil as fast as it can but is&#13;
constrained by a physical limit to the rate of extraction.&#13;
These first two issues are discussed in the subsections that&#13;
follow. In the short run, the market may be out of equilibrium because&#13;
most oil is located far away from where it is consumed; transportation is&#13;
slow and expensive; there are lags in production; demand is volatile; and&#13;
expectations may turn out to be wrong. When prices are thought to be too&#13;
high, competitive producers who try rapidly to increase their extraction&#13;
rate often must pay much higher marginal costs and may even sacrifice some&#13;
of their recoverable reserves (due to technological inefficiencies involved&#13;
in excessively rapid extraction).&#13;
3.2 Extraction Costs&#13;
Even in a perfectly competitive market with a constant discount&#13;
rate, extraction costs can fundamentally alter the expected price path of&#13;
oil. With constant unit extraction costs, C(qt,4t,t) = cqt, the Euler&#13;
conditions lead to an equilibrium in which&#13;
(pt-c)ert= A .                                                 (22)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Price net of unit extraction costs rises at the discount rate; this implies&#13;
that price rises slower than the discount rate. When unit extraction costs&#13;
are constant with respect to output but fall over time with technical&#13;
progress, the corresponding equilibrium is&#13;
-r t&#13;
(p-ce    = Xe&#13;
Here, falling marginal costs ct further slows the rate of price apprecia-&#13;
tion. Only if marginal costs actually rise faster than the discount rate&#13;
will price appreciation be faster than the discount rate. Significantly&#13;
more complicated is the solution when extraction costs depend on changes in&#13;
the rate of extraction; if speeding up extraction is expensive, it becomes&#13;
necessary to evaluate the path of equation (20)'s final term,&#13;
d[C2(qt,4t,t)]/dt. 9/&#13;
Extraction costs may also vary across different suppliers. For&#13;
any price path, those with smaller unit extraction cost will choose to&#13;
extract first.l1/ Marginal revenue net of marginal cost appreciates&#13;
faster for suppliers with large marginal costs; high-cost suppliers have a&#13;
relatively greater benefit from postponing their extraction costs into the&#13;
9/   The solution remains tractable in the special case where the cost&#13;
function takes the linear form:&#13;
C(qt,4t,t) = clqt + c24t&#13;
Then, along an equilibrium path,&#13;
rt&#13;
P= c  + rc  + Ae&#13;
10/ Similar is the point discussed in section 3.4 that countries with&#13;
above average discount rates (typically OIDCs) will be the first to&#13;
extract their resources. Of course this effect will be mitigated if&#13;
their extraction costs are also higher.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
future. The shift over time from low to high cost extractors (or from low&#13;
to high cost techniques) will be partially offset through improvement from&#13;
technological innovations. This illustrates the importance of using&#13;
forecasts of extraction costs as an integral part of the technique for&#13;
forming price expectation.&#13;
3.3 Imperfect Competition&#13;
Compared with the competitive solution, the price path of ex-&#13;
haustible resources may be different when the oil reserves are held by a&#13;
monopolist or cartel. A monopolist will choose an intertemporal distribu-&#13;
tion of supply to maximize total discounted profit; supplies are redistri-&#13;
buted over time until the present discounted value of marginal revenue&#13;
minus marginal cost for any period is the same. Unlike the competitive&#13;
solution, the monopolist may choose not to exhaust the entire stock of&#13;
resources by the time the backstop technology is expected to become com-&#13;
petitive. Greater profits may result if the monopolist follows a higher&#13;
price path and when the competitive backstop technology constrains his&#13;
ability to raise prices further he exhausts all remaining stock at the&#13;
constant backstop price lStiglitz and Dasgupta (1980)].&#13;
There are two potential differences to the solution of Hotell-&#13;
ing's rule under a monopoly:  (i) the price path may be different to the&#13;
extent that marginal revenue is different from price; (ii) the whole price&#13;
path may be higher if the monopolist finds it optimal not to exhaust supply&#13;
by the stage at which the backstop technology becomes competitive.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
A monopolist will generally start off with a higher price.&#13;
Later, when we evaluate the capital costs of stockpiling or optimal&#13;
extraction policies (for the competitive fringe), it will be more important&#13;
to consider how the price of oil changes over time. Under a monopolist,&#13;
the rate of oil price rises can be either faster or slower than under&#13;
competition. If extraction is costless and consumers have a demand&#13;
function with constant price elasticity, then the price of oil rises at the&#13;
monopolist's discount rate [Stiglitz (1976)]; if the monopolist shares the&#13;
world discount rate, then the rate of price rise is the same as in the&#13;
competitive case.&#13;
To see this result, note that marginal revenue, MR, is given by&#13;
MR = p(l-1/e), where p is price and e is the elasticity of demand. In the&#13;
Hotelling solution with costless extraction, marginal revenue rises at the&#13;
interest rate. Thus, if elasticity e is constant, price is a fixed&#13;
multiple of marginal revenue; hence both price and marginal revenue rise at&#13;
the rate of interest.&#13;
When calculating the expected price path of oil, the solution may&#13;
differ from Hotelling's rule to the extent that oil reserves are controlled&#13;
by a monopoly and the price elasticity of demand changes over time. An&#13;
increase in the price elasticity brought about by gradually increased&#13;
substitution possibilities will imply that price rises slower than the&#13;
monopolist's discount rate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
3.4 The Discount Rate in Developing Countries&#13;
The appropriate social discount rate for developing countries may&#13;
be higher than the interest rates which prevail in the rest of the world.&#13;
The suboptimality of domestic savings [Little and Mirrlees (1968), (1974)]&#13;
and restrictions on foreign investment suggest that rates of return to&#13;
domestic projects in developing countries are likely to be higher than&#13;
those obtainable elsewhere. Thus, these countries attempt to borrow funds&#13;
from international development agencies and capital markets until they run&#13;
up against lending constraints and large risk premia. In contrast, the&#13;
discount rate for oil-exporting, capital rich countries is likely to be&#13;
lower than in the rest of the world.&#13;
There are several implications of an OIDC's discount rate being&#13;
higher than that of oil-exporting countries. First, given any path for the&#13;
world price of oil, it will pay an OIDC to deplete its own reserves at a&#13;
faster rate than the oil-exporting countries if it has the same (or lower)&#13;
extraction costs.  To the extent that its marginal extraction costs rise&#13;
with both the amount and the speed of extraction, this depletion policy&#13;
will be moderated. Such a policy does have the side effect of increasing&#13;
the OIDC's future dependence on oil imports.&#13;
A higher discount rate also raises the costs of stockpiling.&#13;
Whatever the capital gain (or loss) from changes in the world price of oil&#13;
over time, the annual opportunity cost of the capital tied up in the oil&#13;
stockpile is higher. Other opportunity costs of storing oil will also be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
higher because the capital tied up (in extraction and storage facilities --&#13;
see Section 5.1) has to be valued at the higher interest rate.&#13;
3.5 The Cost Arising from Uncertain Reserves&#13;
Unless future supplies of oil are known with certainty, it is&#13;
impossible to allocate oil consumption efficiently over time [Gilbert&#13;
(1976)]. If an unexpected bonus of oil is found, then too little consump-&#13;
tion will have occurred; if a well runs dry unexpectedly soon, then too&#13;
much consumption will have occurred. A cost to uncertainty arises because&#13;
we assume the loss from a shortage is greater than the benefit from an&#13;
equivalent surplus. If it is increasingly difficult to find replacements&#13;
for oil as shortages become more severe then prices must rise more steeply&#13;
in the event of a shortage than they fall when there is a surplus.&#13;
Resolving the uncertainty over oil reserves sooner on average increases&#13;
today's consumption and lowers the price.&#13;
It is important to emphasize that oil reserves are uncertain,&#13;
although expectations will be held on the basis of available information.&#13;
Resolving the uncertainty will not result in oil stocks being equal to the&#13;
expected reserves;ll/ oil stocks may be higher or lower than the average&#13;
of all possibilities. The benefit of resolving the uncertainty is that we&#13;
know the actual stocks sooner and can thus plan better.&#13;
11/ Devarajan and Fisher (1982) contrast the extraction costs of uncertain&#13;
versus certain reserves. They point out the economies of scale that&#13;
arise when extracting large reserves. Thus, expected extraction costs&#13;
of a random reserve are lower than for a certain reserve equal to the&#13;
expected size of the random reserve.  But, resolving the uncertainty&#13;
sooner does not help since it does not take us to the mean value.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Consider a two-period model in which the total quantity of oil is&#13;
either 0.5 or 1.5 (each with chance 1/2). Extraction is costless. At the&#13;
time when first-period consumption is decided, total supply is uncertain.&#13;
Before the second period, the remaining supply becomes known. In a&#13;
competitive market, second-period prices will lead to the resource just&#13;
being exhausted. To capture the increasing difficulty of finding&#13;
substitutes for oil, the demand function must be assumed convex in price.&#13;
For example, let demand as a function of price be&#13;
q(p)  =  I/p.                                                   (23)&#13;
If consumption in the first period is q1, then the first-period price is:&#13;
P1  =  I/ql.                                                    (24)&#13;
Second-period consumption q2 will either be (0.5-q1) or (1.5-ql).&#13;
Second-period prices p2(q2) may be written as a function of the total&#13;
stock Z and first-period consumption q1 as follows:&#13;
P2(q2)  =  1/q2  =  1/(Z-q1),  since Z  =  ql+q2-               (25)&#13;
Hotelling's rule can be used to determine the equilibrium. The&#13;
expected discounted second-period price must equal the first-period price.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
Thus, if r is the risk-free interest rate, this implies&#13;
Pi  =  [(1/2)p2(1.5-ql) + (1/2)p2(0.5-ql)]/(1+r).               (26)&#13;
Hence first-period consumption q1 is given as the solution to the equation:&#13;
2/ql  =  [1/(1.5-ql) + 1/(0.5-ql)]/(1+r).                       (27)&#13;
In the two-period model, it is reasonable to think of the periods as each&#13;
being ten years.  Then if r  =  100%, this gives&#13;
ql  =  0.39,  P1  =  2.5;&#13;
p2(0.5-ql) = 9.1, P2(0.5-qj) = 0.9; hence EIp2] = 5.0.&#13;
If the stock Z were known with certainty at the beginning of the first&#13;
period, the outcome would be either&#13;
for  Z  =  0.5       Pi  =  3, P2  =  6; q1  =  0.33, q2  =  0.17&#13;
or&#13;
for  Z  =  1.5  :  P1  =  1, P2  =  2; ql  =  1.0, q2  =  0.5.&#13;
The average price and consumption levels are:&#13;
E[pl]  =  2, E[p2]  =  4;&#13;
and   E[q1]  =  0.67,  E[q2    =  0.33.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
In this example, the cost of uncertainty in the first period results in a&#13;
25X higher price compared with the average of the paths when the reserves&#13;
are known.&#13;
The inefficiency in intertemporal allocation arises because of&#13;
the need to maintain flexibility in facing the uncertain second-period&#13;
supply; this inefficiency is relative to the optimal depletion path in a&#13;
world with no uncertainty. Caution in the first period reduces the costs&#13;
of adjusting to a worse than expected outcome in the second period. When&#13;
the elasticity of demand is lower, the cost of adjusting to a shortage is&#13;
greater and more flexibility is needed; first-period consumption must be&#13;
reduced even further which leads to greater inefficiency and higher prices.&#13;
This subsection illustrates an important externality associated&#13;
with oil exploration projects: the evaluation of such projects should&#13;
include the benefit of reducing the misallocation arising from uncertainty&#13;
about the size of global reserves.&#13;
3.6 The Effects of New Energy Supplies&#13;
In evaluating the benefits from the technologies of producing&#13;
energy, it is important to make a distinction between the production of&#13;
energy from exhaustible and from renewable resources. The development of&#13;
known exhaustible resources in a world of certainty should not affect the&#13;
world price because everyone knows that they will be extracted sooner or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
later.12/ The development of renewable energy resources (e.g., solar,&#13;
hydro and nuclear), however, does have an effect on prices as it increases&#13;
the world's total supply of energy.13/ This may also be accomplished more&#13;
gradually through energy conservation [for estimates of its potential, see&#13;
World Bank (1982)]. By using the available oil or coal more efficiently,&#13;
the same outputs can be produced with less oil or coal; when conservation&#13;
results in a 25% greater efficiency this is equivalent to an effective&#13;
increase of 25% in the entire stock of reserves.&#13;
Conservation leading to an increase in equivalent oil reserves&#13;
held by the competitive market fringe results in a lower oil price today.&#13;
Reducing energy import needs decreases dependency and hence vulnerability&#13;
to oil-price shocks; it is also likely to create greater competition in&#13;
world oil markets. Conservation leads to a gain in efficiency, and the&#13;
development of renewable resources leads to an increase in supply. This&#13;
should benefit all oil-importing countries.14/ These benefits must be&#13;
weighed against the costs of conservation.&#13;
12/ Other oil-exporting nations can cut back current production knowing&#13;
that their supply will be more in demand later when other countries'&#13;
exhaustible resources run out. This assumes that they can still meet&#13;
their current revenue requirements by borrowing against their now&#13;
larger future incomes; some of the effects of borrowing constraints&#13;
are discussed below.&#13;
13/ Similarly, a new technology that improves the cost-effectiveness of&#13;
alternative exhaustible resources (e.g., gas or coal) creates&#13;
additional supplies of energy.&#13;
14/ The development of both renewable and non-renewable energy resources&#13;
shifts revenues away from oil-exporters, but in the case of non-&#13;
renewable resources these revenues are simply postponed until the&#13;
future.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
No developing country acting alone can achieve all these&#13;
effects. As in the case of information gathering (see Section 4.1), the&#13;
World Bank can have an important function as a coordinator. It has the&#13;
advantage of being able to consider the welfare of developing nations as a&#13;
whole and thus it can help internalize the externalities generated by the&#13;
actions of its individual members. The Bank can take into account and&#13;
forecast the effect on the world price of oil of developing countries&#13;
reducing their demand through conservation or producing a greater share of&#13;
their own energy needs.&#13;
Related to this issue is the question of the timing for&#13;
importing countries to extract their limited stocks of exhaustible&#13;
resources [see Crawford and Sobel (1982) and Gilbert et. al. (1978)]. The&#13;
cartelization of the current market is moderated by the fact that many&#13;
countries at present have sizeable reserves, i.e. there is a large&#13;
potential competitive fringe. Without these reserves, there would be a&#13;
much greater potential for cartelization in the future. But, this issue&#13;
arises only if developing countries increase their production of depletable&#13;
resources. Conserving energy and developing renewable energy resources&#13;
have no such negative externality: the world's energy supply is&#13;
increased.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
4. COORDINATING STRATEGIES&#13;
The advantage to coordinating strategies for information gather-&#13;
ing and developing alternative energy sources has resulted in oil-importing&#13;
countries forming the International Energy Agency.15/ This is only a&#13;
first step in the right direction. Countries (or multinational oil&#13;
companies) acting alone collect too little information and wastefully&#13;
duplicate or excessively diversify their research strategies. This section&#13;
discusses externalities associated with exploration and research&#13;
diversification.&#13;
4.1 Information Externalities in Exploration&#13;
The first step in developing energy resources is the gathering of&#13;
information. There are important reasons why this should be done by a&#13;
central authority rather than the free market (if it exists). Information&#13;
is perhaps one of the only true public goods. It can be shared by an&#13;
unlimited number of people and across countries. Thus everyone has an&#13;
incentive to wait for others to gather the information rather than to pay&#13;
the costs and duplicate efforts. There is an inefficiency when more than&#13;
one group pays the costs to find out the same information. While there can&#13;
be private advantages when information is withheld, the sum of the benefits&#13;
is generally not reduced when the information is shared. Duplicating&#13;
15/  Similarly, participants in the International Energy Plan hope to&#13;
minimize the costs of a supply interruption by formalizing sharing&#13;
rules in advance. However, the sharing rules are poorly designed and&#13;
may be expected to break down in the event of a major disruption&#13;
[Hogan (1981)].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
efforts to gather information frequently occurs in zero-sum games, such as&#13;
futures markets, where each trader tries to take advantage of another.&#13;
Competitive information gathering affects the distribution of income but&#13;
not the size of the pie.&#13;
The consumers of oil at present all pay a risk premium because&#13;
the world's total supply of oil (and its substitutes) is not known&#13;
precisely. As demonstrated earlier, uncertainty leads to an inefficient&#13;
intertemporal allocation of resources. No one country can eliminate this&#13;
uncertainty by investing in exploratory drilling. Yet each country that&#13;
investigates its level of reserves contributes to a reduction of the total&#13;
uncertainty. The IEA and the World Bank are in a position to coordinate&#13;
the actions of their member countries and thus help them take advantage of&#13;
these externalities.&#13;
Apart from the contribution made to a reduction of the total&#13;
uncertainty, information gathering provides advantages and disadvantages to&#13;
individual oil-exporting countries. More information about the level of a&#13;
country's reserves decreases the risk of unanticipated future price varia-&#13;
bility for its own oil [Gilbert et. al. (1978)]. However, each individual&#13;
oil-exporting country will prefer greater uncertainty about others'&#13;
reserves since its oil will then command a higher risk premium.&#13;
Oil-importing developing countries will benefit from a reduction&#13;
in the uncertainty about the world's supply of oil. Although they would&#13;
not necessarily be willing to pay for exploration on their own, they would&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
be much more receptive to a quid-pro-quo policy, agreeing to find out about&#13;
their own resources provided others found out about theirs. [This is&#13;
equivalent to a scheme in which everyone shares in each other's expenses.]&#13;
Even though the information that is discovered may not be put to immediate&#13;
use, the change in the world's belief about the level of reserves will&#13;
reduce the risk premium associated with the current price of oil.&#13;
4.2 Diversification and Multi-Project Analysis *&#13;
The discussion has focused on oil but the issue is clearly one of&#13;
energy generally. A country considering research and development strate-&#13;
gies should examine the various approaches to producing both oil and its&#13;
substitutes. For example, hydroelectric power and shale oil may prove&#13;
equal to oil in their importance for many South American countries. How&#13;
much should research be diversified, the eggs spread among more than a&#13;
single basket?&#13;
This subsection demonstrates the reasons why a project's cost-&#13;
benefit analysis cannot be done in isolation of the alternatives. When&#13;
there are several projects, all of which have goals that are substitutes&#13;
for one another, it is important that they be evaluated simultaneously.&#13;
Independent project evaluation can lead to excessive diversification; too&#13;
many projects could be accepted.&#13;
* This self-contained subsection may require familiarity with the&#13;
mathematics of convex functions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
Diversification is generally motivated by uncertainty. Research&#13;
and exploration are inherently risky propositions. Several R&amp;D projects&#13;
may be run at once to increase the chance of finding at least one success.&#13;
If the success of a research and development project could be predicted in&#13;
advance, then there would be no advantage to funding more than a single&#13;
project to solve a particular problem. Even when there is uncertainty,&#13;
diversification may not be advantageous; it may be optimal to fund only a&#13;
single project.&#13;
There are two important special features of research projects&#13;
that motivate specialization rather than diversification in the presence of&#13;
uncertainty. First, there may be economies of scale in producing informa-&#13;
tion. Second, there may be diseconomies of scope; when there are several&#13;
alternative solutions, only the best one is implemented.&#13;
A little information costs more than it is worth [Radner and&#13;
Stiglitz (1975), Dasgupta (1982)]. Gathering information has a direct&#13;
economic cost. The benefits can only be calculated indirectly. Actions&#13;
are based on the information available. The information's value is then&#13;
determined by the expected return from the ensuing action. When actions&#13;
are chosen optimally (conditional on the information), a slight perturba-&#13;
tion will not change the expected return. The value of incremental&#13;
information arises from the distribution of actions becoming more appro-&#13;
priate given the outcomes. At zero information, only a single action is&#13;
taken and hence there are no gains from redistributing actions more appro-&#13;
priately. Starting from ignorance, there is initially a cost to obtaining&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
information but no benefit. Thus, research projects initially have&#13;
increasing returns to scale; when a research project is worth doing, it&#13;
should be done on a reasonably large scale.16/&#13;
An example may help illustrate this point. Imagine that the&#13;
information concerns the probability of finding oil in a given geological&#13;
structure. In the extreme case of perfect information the probability of&#13;
finding oil is either 0 or 1; drilling when undertaken will always be&#13;
successful. At the other extreme of zero information, there is still a&#13;
prior probability of finding oil. If this probability is above some crit-&#13;
ical value, then drilling for oil is expected to be profitable. Gathering&#13;
only a very small amount of information can only make a small change from&#13;
the prior probability of success. A small amount of information cannot be&#13;
sufficiently favorable to induce drilling when, based on prior beliefs,&#13;
drilling was inadvisable. Since the distribution of actions is the same,&#13;
there is no expected gain from only a marginal amount of information.&#13;
There is an analogy between fixed costs in production and the ineffective-&#13;
ness of a small amount of information: the fixed cost associated with&#13;
gathering information is the cost of obtaining the minimal amount of&#13;
information needed to have a potential effect on the decision. This is one&#13;
example of increasing returns to scale in information gathering.&#13;
If society is only interested in the single best technique for&#13;
producing energy, and its research projects do not suffer from decreasing&#13;
returns to scale, then as shown below it is indeed appropriate to put all&#13;
the money into one project [Nalebuff and Varian (1983)]. While this result&#13;
16/ This argument relates to projects starting from scratch: small&#13;
additions to ongoing projects may well be worthwhile.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
is obvious if there is no uncertainty about the returns from the&#13;
project,17/ its interest lies in the fact that it is also true when the&#13;
fruits of research are uncertain. One goes with the expected winner. This&#13;
result does not depend on the correlation between projects (positive,&#13;
negative, or zero).&#13;
To formalize this proposition, consider a government allocating&#13;
funds to various projects. Each project produces output fi(Xi,ei) where&#13;
Xi are the funds allocated to project i and ei is a random variable&#13;
determining the project's success. The government has a budget constraint&#13;
that X -=B. The random variables may have any general joint probability&#13;
density function g(el ....en).  Society only cares about the winner.  The&#13;
value of outputs (fl,---,fn) is Max (fl--,fn).  Conditional on any&#13;
realization of e=(el,...,en), the value of each research project,&#13;
fi(Xi,ei), is assumed to be convex; as argued above, there are increasing&#13;
returns to scale in gathering information. The expected return from&#13;
following research strategy X = (Xl,...,Xn) is&#13;
E[Max[f i(Xi,e d]] = f...f Max[f1(X  e 1) ...,fn(Xn en)]g(e ,...,e )de    de&#13;
For each realization of e, the valuation function Max[fi(Xi,ei)]&#13;
is the composite of two increasing and convex functions and is thus&#13;
convex. The expectation of Max [fi(Xi,ei)] is just a weighted average of&#13;
the valuation function conditional on ei; a weighted average of convex&#13;
functions is still a (weakly) convex function. Because the maximum value&#13;
17/ With no uncertainty, the best project is known and only it should be&#13;
funded.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
of a convex function occurs at a boundary, it is optimal to fund only one&#13;
project; for some i, Xi* = B and Xj = 0 for j$i.&#13;
A government does not care whether there is a second firm to&#13;
discover a new technology; only the first discoverer counts. Specializa-&#13;
tion may hasten the time and improve the quality of the discovery.&#13;
Diversification is only justified if the leading project encounters&#13;
diminishing returns to scale or if there is diminishing marginal valuation&#13;
with respect to increases in the value of the best outcome.&#13;
Initially it may seem counter-intuitive that specialization is&#13;
optimal even in an uncertain world. On reflection it becomes clear:&#13;
diversification is implied by the convexity of the constraints or the&#13;
concavity of the objective function. If these conditions are not met,&#13;
diversification is not necessarily optimal. The standard assumptions about&#13;
concavity are likely to be violated when considering the returns from&#13;
several simultaneous research projects.&#13;
4.3 Risk Pooling and Multi-Project Analysis&#13;
Outside of research and development, the total value of several&#13;
projects is generally equal to the sum of the outputs. Then, one justifi-&#13;
cation for accepting several simultaneous projects is the advantage from&#13;
risk-pooling. As discussed earlier in the context of the capital asset&#13;
pricing model (CAPM), when there are several projects which are negatively&#13;
correlated there is a reduction in risk because the sum of the outputs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
becomes more certain. Often this intuition is mistakenly extended to&#13;
include projects which have a less than perfect positive correlation, and&#13;
the claim is made that accepting several independent projects also results&#13;
in lower risk.&#13;
As the number of independent and identically distributed assets&#13;
increases, the average return converges in probability to a constant.&#13;
Thus, adding an additional asset and an additional shareholder (to an&#13;
existing portfolio of n assets held by n people) results in lower risk to&#13;
all; the additional asset increases the variance by a factor of (n+l)/n&#13;
while the additional shareholder lowers the portfolio's variance by a&#13;
factor of [n/(n+1))2.  But a government may not be able to increase its&#13;
number of shareholders beyond its existing population. Investments will&#13;
already be spread as thinly as possible. Given that the maximum risk&#13;
spreading has already taken place, a government cares about the sum of the&#13;
returns rather than the mean return. Accepting additional independently&#13;
distributed projects linearly increases both the total expected return and&#13;
the total variance. This may or may not be beneficial.&#13;
The fallacy of large numbers [Samuelson (1963)] is designed to&#13;
contrast with the law of large numbers; it shows that investing in a large&#13;
number of independent and identically distributed assets may be undesir-&#13;
able. Consider an asset with a positive expected return but with suffi-&#13;
cient variance so that an investor would choose not to hold this asset at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
any income level. The 'fallacy" shows that holding any number of indepen-&#13;
dent and identically distributed replicas of this asset is also undesir-&#13;
able. Thus, if the government of Monaco is sufficiently risk averse that&#13;
it never wants to be the house for a single bet at Monte Carlo, then it&#13;
will also refuse to play the house over a period of a day, year, or&#13;
century. The proof follows by induction. Since by assumption accepting a&#13;
single bet is never desirable, expected welfare is improved by eliminating&#13;
the final replication. Continuing to remove each remaining final replica-&#13;
tion implies that expected welfare is maximized when none of the bets is&#13;
left.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
5. THE COSTS OF IMPORTING OIL&#13;
There are two interrelated costs facing an economy which is&#13;
heavily dependent on imported oil: the danger from disruptions in supply&#13;
and a higher variance in the economy's performance due to fluctuations in&#13;
the price of oil. Our discussion starts at supply disruptions.&#13;
Developing countries have at least two important reasons why they&#13;
should be concerned about their supply of oil being cut off: embargos and&#13;
wars. The history of 1973 proves the real possibility of an embargo. Wars&#13;
have disrupted the flow of oil either by cutting off the producers (as in&#13;
Iran-Iraq) or by blockades around the consumer (as in Malawi during the&#13;
Tanzania-Uganda war or in Argentina during the Falklands/Malvinas crisis).&#13;
The costs of a disruption include threats to national security (defence),&#13;
massive inefficiencies from disturbances in production, and hardships&#13;
suffered by individuals unable to obtain or to afford fuel for cooking and&#13;
heating [Deese and Nye (1981), Plummer (1982)].&#13;
The responses to this danger include (1) reducing domestic con-&#13;
sumption through tariffs and quotas and through increased conservation;&#13;
(2) buying on the spot market; (3) investing in backstop technologies;&#13;
(4) strategic stockpiling of crude oil; and (5) carrying excess domestic&#13;
production capacity. We consider each of these options.&#13;
The market price fails to reflect all the externalities asso-&#13;
ciated with importing an additional barrel of oil. To reduce demand to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
appropriate level, it is optimal for a government to combine the use of&#13;
tariffs and quotas. If demand is restrained solely by the use of quotas,&#13;
then the oil-exporting country would raise its price until market demand is&#13;
at the quota level. The importing country could capture this price&#13;
increase by imposing a tariff on oil imports [Hogan (1982)]. Domestic&#13;
consumers would be better off when part of the price of oil is paid to&#13;
their own government rather than to sellers of oil abroad.&#13;
In the presence of uncertainty, there is an advantage to supple-&#13;
menting tariffs with quotas. A quota helps to limit a country's foreign&#13;
exchange commitment in the importation of energy. In countries where oil&#13;
imports form a very large share of export earnings, small fluctuations in&#13;
the volume of energy imports can cause large changes in the balance-of-&#13;
payments. With their capacities to borrow already stretched (and their&#13;
foreign reserves exhausted), many OIDCs face the risk of sharp rises in the&#13;
exchange rate. In such situations the concomitant costs to the non-traded&#13;
sectors of the economy can be excessive.&#13;
Ideally, countries can reduce their risk by investing in assets&#13;
that are negatively correlated with the supply, or positively correlated&#13;
with the price, of oil (e.g., purchasing shares of oil companies). Subsi-&#13;
dizing conservation has a high payoff in the event of a supply disruption.&#13;
Similarly, the development of a contingent rationing scheme creates another&#13;
negatively correlated asset; it is valuable only in the event of a supply&#13;
disruption. Ration coupons which are tradable help protect the poor&#13;
against oil-price shocks while maintaining the incentive for efficient&#13;
allocation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
To a greater or lesser extent, all countries respond to&#13;
threatened disruptions by buying on the spot market. There are two dis-&#13;
advantages to this approach: (i) the spot market accounts for a very small&#13;
percentage of the total oil traded (less than 5%), so that individual&#13;
countries may face very high prices if they all move to the spot market to&#13;
meet disruptions; (ii) oil purchased in spot markets may be at great&#13;
distance from the home country and the consequent transport costs and time&#13;
lags could entail considerable losses to the economy.&#13;
Reliance on renewable resources (such as alcohol from biomass) is&#13;
generally not economic at the present world price of oil but may become so&#13;
in the future with a long-term increase in its real price [World Bank&#13;
(1980)1. Because oil is an exhaustible resource whereas most synthetic&#13;
fuels are not, we would expect the real price of oil to rise in the&#13;
long-term but that of most synfuels to remain more or less constant. Thus,&#13;
in due course, synfuels should become competitive in relation to&#13;
exhaustible oil supplies. In any case, some development of renewable&#13;
resources at higher cost today may be warranted as a way of reducing the&#13;
uncertainty in supplies faced by oil-importing developing countries. The&#13;
extent of such development depends on the exact premium attached to&#13;
security of supplies, which varies according to a country's circumstances.&#13;
A further protection against interruptions of oil supply is for&#13;
countries to keep a strategic stockpile of oil reserves. There are several&#13;
ways in which these reserves can in principle be held. They can be kept&#13;
above ground in storage tanks, or under ground--in leached salt caverns or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
abandoned salt, hematite, limestone, granite, chalk, or coal mines, or&#13;
indeed in existing or disused oil-wells. Some new suggested systems for&#13;
crude-oil storage include rubber bags and artificially created "lagoons",&#13;
sometimes lined with impermeable synthetic plastics of polyethylene&#13;
products. Idle tankers are also obvious potential storage facilities.&#13;
The argument for public stockpiling must depend on an implicit&#13;
belief that the private market does not have sufficient incentives to&#13;
maintain an adequate stockpile [Wright and Williams (1982)]. There are&#13;
several potentially large externalities that are not captured by the&#13;
private incentives to stockpile. In the event of a shortage, private&#13;
sellers expect (with good reason) that the government will impose a price&#13;
ceiling. This cuts off part of the favorable tail of benefits. The&#13;
expected value to society of the stockpile exceeds its market price when&#13;
the government limits prices. A second factor mitigating competitive&#13;
stockpiling arises when the size of the optimal stockpile is large enough&#13;
to affect prices. Purchasing a large stockpile may force oil prices to&#13;
rise if it restricts the supply available to consumers. The higher oil&#13;
prices resulting from stockpiling creates a comparative advantage for the&#13;
oil producers to hold the stockpiles. Having a stockpile may also provide&#13;
strategic advantages not captured by the market. Hogan (1982) stresses the&#13;
advantage of a stockpile in reducing the probability of a disruption; as&#13;
the impact of an embargo is diminished, it is less likely to be deployed.&#13;
Countries that extract and refine some of their own oil also have&#13;
the option of keeping a safety reserve in the form of several untapped&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
wells that can be brought into immediate production (i.e. carrying excess&#13;
capacity). The economic theory of exhaustible resources shows that this is&#13;
essentially another form of stockpiling.&#13;
5.1 The Costs of Stockpiling&#13;
The true costs of stockpiling an exhaustible resource are likely&#13;
to be significantly lower than those associated with carrying inventories&#13;
of ordinary (renewable) goods. The reason is that exhaustible resources&#13;
such as oil are expected to reap capital gains from price rises along a&#13;
Hotelling equilibrium path.  Although there is a notional interest loss on&#13;
the capital tied up in stored oil, this is offset to the extent that the&#13;
real price of oil rises over time. With perfect competition and zero&#13;
extraction costs, the price of oil would be expected to rise at exactly the&#13;
rate of interest; in this case there is no opportunity cost to the capital&#13;
invested in the stockpile - it is simply another form of holding savings.&#13;
Authors such as Samouilidis and Berahas [1982, p. 569] underestimate the&#13;
returns to stockpiling because they attribute an interest cost to the&#13;
stockpile but do not take into account capital gains in its value.18/&#13;
The opportunity cost of capital tied up in stockpiling must be&#13;
evaluated at the country's own internal discount rate. Yet the price path&#13;
for oil is largely determined by the lower discount rates used by capital&#13;
rich, oil-exporting countries (section 3.3). Together with the effect of&#13;
18/ Of course, capital gains (or losses) can arise not only from price&#13;
changes along an equilibrium price path, but because the oil for the&#13;
stockpile may be purchased when the market is out of equilibrium.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
positive extraction costs in moderating the rate of price increase, this&#13;
suggests that capital gains in the value of the stockpile are unlikely to&#13;
offset the full opportunity cost of capital tied up in the stockpile.&#13;
There are additional costs of stockpiling. Building storage&#13;
facilities for oil can be expensive (with costs ranging from 3 dollars per&#13;
barrel in existing salt mines to 16 dollars per barrel in above-ground&#13;
tanks) and there is generally some loss from evaporation (on the order of&#13;
less than 2% per year). When extraction costs are incurred for oil&#13;
extracted from own reserves, these could have been delayed until the oil&#13;
was actually needed. The money spent on early extraction leads to an&#13;
opportunity cost that should be evaluated at the country's discount rate.&#13;
Extraction costs may also be falling over time with improvements in&#13;
technology. The lost savings in extraction costs should be attributed to&#13;
the costs of maintaining the stockpile. A developing country may not have&#13;
adequate refining capabilities. Hence, it may need to stockpile refined&#13;
instead of crude oil. The additional expense of purchasing refined oil&#13;
could also have been postponed until the oil was just ready for use.&#13;
Although refining costs do grow to keep up with inflation, real interest is&#13;
lost on the capital spent on refining.&#13;
5.2 Inventories and Flexibility in Production&#13;
Even a country which produces some of its own energy has reasons&#13;
to carry stockpiles. These inventories can be used to counter the&#13;
disruptive effects of the second major problem associated with importing&#13;
oil, viz. its price variability.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
Inventories can be used to accommodate fluctuations in supply&#13;
while reducing price variability. If inventories are not used (or run&#13;
out), the price mechanism will act as a brake; during peak periods of&#13;
demand, price will rise to choke off some of the excess demand. The&#13;
optimal stabilization results in neither a constant price nor a band-width&#13;
rule; it is the solution demonstrated by Gustafson (1958) to a dynamic&#13;
optimization problem that turns out to be similar to Hotelling's rule&#13;
[Newbury and Stiglitz (1982)1. The costs of oil supply shocks can be&#13;
reduced but not eliminated through an optimal management of strategic oil&#13;
reserves.&#13;
Note that price variation is in itself not always harmful.&#13;
Random variation in input costs is beneficial because cost functions are&#13;
concave in input prices. Firms can take extra advantage of oil when it is&#13;
a bargain and substitute away from it when it is expensive. The use of oil&#13;
inventories accentuates this advantage if stockpiles can be built up when&#13;
the purchase price is low.&#13;
Inventories illustrate one of the advantages of flexibility.&#13;
This argument has been extended to claim that the choice of energy&#13;
production techniques should be relatively more capital-intensive so as to&#13;
have greater flexibility in meeting variations in demand. By paying a&#13;
higher fixed cost, firms hope to exploit the opportunity of relatively&#13;
efficient production over a range of output levels. Yet, it may be&#13;
preferable to use inventories rather than excess capacity to meet these&#13;
types of unexpected fluctuations. Making relatively large fixed cost&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
investments takes away an even more important aspect of flexibility, the&#13;
option of shutting down [see Mason and Merton (1984)]. If the price of&#13;
imported oil becomes very low (perhaps because of a technological break-&#13;
through in offshore development) then one of the production options is to&#13;
shut down and import oil.&#13;
The fact often overlooked is that for projects with a high&#13;
marginal (i.e. variable) cost, there is a greater probability of the&#13;
economy being able to take advantage of cheaper alternatives. The choice&#13;
of a technology usually involves making trade-offs between high fixed costs&#13;
and high marginal costs. It is optimal to choose projects with a rela-&#13;
tively small fixed cost component (and correspondingly higher marginal&#13;
costs) when taking into account the often desirable option of temporarily&#13;
shutting down and relying on imports if they become cheap. For example, in&#13;
the production of ethanol from corn, the marginal input costs (corn @&#13;
$2.50/bushel) form over 85% of the total production costs on a project with&#13;
an output of 50 million gallons per year [Manassah (1981), Part A, Table I,&#13;
p. 335]. Similarly, in the production of ethanol from sugarcane in South-&#13;
east Brazil, biomass inputs made up almost 65% of the production costs&#13;
while the levelized investment cost was less than 20% of the total expend-&#13;
itures [Gray (1981), p. 298].  These types of projects have the flexibility&#13;
to be expanded or contracted depending on whether the world oil price is&#13;
high or low.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
5.3 Financing Energy Development in OIDCs&#13;
A primary concern of most developing countries is how to finance&#13;
the high cost of imported oil. Countries that are constrained in their&#13;
ability to borrow may also find it difficult to undertake the large invest-&#13;
ments needed to develop their own domestic energy sources.&#13;
The cost of importing energy has formed too significant a propor-&#13;
tion of many developing countries' exports (in 1980 it was more than 50%&#13;
for India, Brazil, etc.). The true cost of these imports is particularly&#13;
high when account is taken of their overvalued exchange rates. Large ex-&#13;
penditures on imported oil add pressure to the exchange rate and increase&#13;
the risk premia on loans to such countries (e.g. Brazil, Turkey, and&#13;
Jamaica).&#13;
A loan to pay for consumption goods such as energy is an espe-&#13;
cially risky proposition. Moreover, the risk premium with loans may be&#13;
expected to rise as the total outstanding debt grows. Countries such as&#13;
Brazil are already beginning to find themselves in situations where borrow-&#13;
ing money to buy oil has become prohibitively expensive. But at the same&#13;
time that it is negotiating crippling loans, Brazil also has a large&#13;
savings account in the form of shale oil deposits. Borrowing is one form&#13;
of dissaving. Brazil has started borrowing from its future self by dis-&#13;
saving (that is, depleting) its stocks of non-renewable resources. An&#13;
advantage of borrowing from your future self is that the risk premium is&#13;
much smaller. Countries are less likely to default on loans taken from&#13;
their own future generations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
Many developing countries are held back from taking advantage of&#13;
their ability to dissave by the fact that they do not have sufficient&#13;
capital to purchase consumption goods, and thus do not have the capital for&#13;
the investment needed to provide them with access to their savings in the&#13;
ground. Investors and banks realize that the risks associated with&#13;
developing a country's supply of exhaustible resources are far smaller than&#13;
financing a loan used to pay for current energy consumption. Thus,&#13;
developing countries often contract with multinational oil companies both&#13;
for their access to capital and for their technical expertise. There are&#13;
advantages and disadvantages to this approach [see Blitzer et. al.&#13;
(1982)].&#13;
Selling a contract for oil exploration and development can help a&#13;
small country spread the risk associated with the uncertain size of its&#13;
reserves and the uncertain cost of developing them. But, in addition to&#13;
sharing risks, the contract should provide the outside developer with&#13;
incentives to minimize costs and to explore efficiently. For example,&#13;
efficiency is promoted if a developer could pay a fixed sum in return for&#13;
the rights to all the costs and benefits; in this contract, the developer&#13;
is also accepting all of the risks.&#13;
A difficulty arises if the contract can be broken. Most multi-&#13;
national oil companies have good reason to fear that they will be national-&#13;
ized or heavily taxed if oil reserves or oil prices prove much higher than&#13;
expected. This uncertainty reduces their incentives to finance the&#13;
exploration and development costs. This effect is especially severe if oil&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
companies depend on their few large successes to cover their more frequent&#13;
small losses.&#13;
A valuable area of ongoing research examines optimal contract&#13;
design in a constrained environment; how should energy development&#13;
contracts make tradeoffs between risk-sharing and incentives if the&#13;
contract may be broken? Blitzer et. al. (1984) compare four commonly used&#13;
contract formulas: service contracts, toll or fee per barrel contracts,&#13;
production sharing contracts, and royalty contracts. They emphasize that&#13;
the contracts should attempt to spread the different risks in proportion to&#13;
each party's comparative ability to accept these risks. Consider the&#13;
production sharing contract; the developer is rewarded with a fixed&#13;
fraction of the benefits for assuming a fixed fraction of the costs. If&#13;
the fraction of benefits equals the fraction of costs then the developer&#13;
has the correct incentives for efficient exploration and production.&#13;
However, developers often do not expect to receive benefits above some&#13;
maximum level (due to taxes, nationalization, currency restrictions). In&#13;
this case, efficient incentives are provided only if the developer's&#13;
fraction of benefits is larger than his fraction of costs to compensate for&#13;
his loss of the upper tail of benefits. This uneven sharing of costs and&#13;
benefits results in the host country bearing more risk - a result of its&#13;
inability to commit itself credibly to contractual agreements.&#13;
At present several developing countries are in a position where&#13;
they could undertake development of their exhaustible resources and thereby&#13;
potentially lend themselves money. But they need financing to get&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
themselves started. In particular, since they are developing, they need&#13;
the capital now more than later. Thus, they should not be especially&#13;
worried that they will leave their future generations with less savings in&#13;
the ground. Taking advantage of their exhaustible resources will leave&#13;
their descendants with a much greater wealth, a developed country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
6. CONCLUSIONS&#13;
The central message of this paper is that investment in energy&#13;
projects in oil-importing developing countries is likely to be far more&#13;
beneficial than continued reliance on imports. Investments in domestic&#13;
energy sources reduce variability of national income, create externalities&#13;
which help reduce the world market price of energy, and lead to greater&#13;
security of supplies. In the framework of energy investments, this paper&#13;
has attempted to identify the relative benefits of the different types of&#13;
energy projects--exhaustible resources, renewable resources, stockpiles,&#13;
and conservation.&#13;
The expected present value (EPV) of a domestic energy production&#13;
or conservation program does not reflect its true social welfare benefits;&#13;
the EPV must be adjusted upwards to account for the reduced variability in&#13;
per capita income brought about by the insurance value of an energy project&#13;
(being an asset negatively correlated with national income). A further&#13;
adjustment may be required when the project's output also affects the&#13;
income distribution. The adjustment for risk should be limited to the&#13;
period for which the uncertainty remains unresolved.&#13;
The appraisal of domestic non-renewable energy projects must take&#13;
account of the same insurance benefits, but there is also a large adjust-&#13;
ment in the opposite direction. Conventional appraisals tend to ignore the&#13;
opportunity cost of depletion of the exhaustible resource. This cost can&#13;
be included by subtracting a royalty value per barrel from the market price&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
of oil; equivalently, the predicted market value of the extraction rights&#13;
can be subtracted from the EPV of the entire stream of returns. The value&#13;
added by the project when correctly computed can result in a much lower EPV&#13;
or internal rate of return for the project.&#13;
No correction for depletion is necessary for renewable energy&#13;
resources. Given a long-run increase in the expected price of exhaustible&#13;
resources under Hotelling's rule, renewable energy projects will eventually&#13;
become economic. Their production technology may also allow greater flexi-&#13;
bility in responding to the variability of world prices; low fixed costs&#13;
and high marginal costs permit the option of shutting down temporarily and&#13;
relying on imports when these are cheap. A low fixed-cost technology&#13;
becomes more attractive with a higher discount rate; owing to capital&#13;
shortages, the discount rate is indeed likely to be higher in OIDCs. Other&#13;
things equal, this will also imply a faster depletion rate of its exhaus-&#13;
tible energy resources.&#13;
The development of domestic exhaustible energy resources is a way&#13;
of borrowing from future generations without paying a risk premium.  In&#13;
situations where many OIDCs are overexposed to foreign borrowing, a reduc-&#13;
tion in the risk premium on loans can represent a considerable gain. The&#13;
reduced dependence on foreign oil imports also implies a reduction in the&#13;
variability of the balance-of-payments and hence the exchange rate.&#13;
Externalities in gathering information about the extent of&#13;
reserves imply that the full benefits of exploration are not received by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
the countries that undertake it. A coordinated strategy or scheme through&#13;
which each country shares in each other's expenses will help internalize&#13;
the benefits.&#13;
In calculating the true costs of stockpiling oil, the opportunity&#13;
cost of capital invested in the stockpile must be compared with the&#13;
expected appreciation in its value over time.&#13;
One of the responsibilities of the World Bank and development&#13;
economists is to help oil-importing developing countries deal with the&#13;
special problems created by the present high costs of energy. Energy is an&#13;
essential ingredient in development. It is important to internalize the&#13;
externalities arising from the development of energy resources across&#13;
countries. It is also necessary to specify and use appropriate project&#13;
evaluation criteria/guidelines so that the optimum development of OIDCs'&#13;
exhaustible and renewable energy resources can be implemented. Significant&#13;
adjustments from the standard approach must be made in the appraisal of&#13;
energy projects in OIDCs to reflect the special features associated with&#13;
energy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
7. REFERENCES&#13;
Arrow, Kenneth J. and Robert C. Lind (1970): "Uncertainty and the&#13;
Evaluation of Public Investment Decisions", American Economic Review,&#13;
Vol. 60 (June), pp. 364-378; reprinted in Richard Layard (ed.),&#13;
Cost-Benefit Analysis, Penguin Modern Economics Readings, Penguin&#13;
Books, England, 1972.&#13;
Blitzer, Charles R., Donald R. Lessard and James L. Paddock (1982): "Risk&#13;
Bearing and the Choice of Contract Forms for Oil Exploration and&#13;
Development", Working Paper No. MIT-EL 82-053WP, International Energy&#13;
Studies Program, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge,&#13;
September.&#13;
Blitzer, Charles R., Panos Cavoulacos, Donald R. Lessard, and James L.&#13;
Paddock (1984): "An Analysis of Financial Impediments to Oil and Gas&#13;
Exploration in Developing Countries", Working Paper No. MIT-EL 84-005,&#13;
Center for Energy Policy Research, Massachusetts Institute of&#13;
Technology, Cambridge, January.&#13;
Bohi, Douglas R. and W.D. Montgomery (1982): Oil Prices and Security:&#13;
Analytics of the Import Premium, Working Paper, Resources for the&#13;
Future, Washington, D.C.&#13;
Cecelski, Elizabeth and William Ramsay (1981): Prospects for Fuel Alcohols&#13;
from Biomass in Developing Countries, Resources for the Future,&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
Crawford, Vince and Joel Sobel (1982): "Strategic Considerations in the&#13;
Stockpiling of Oil", mimeographed, University of California at San&#13;
Diego.&#13;
Dasgupta, Partha S. (1982): "Environmental Management Under Uncertainty",&#13;
in (eds.) Smith and Krutilla (1982).&#13;
Dasgupta, Partha S., Stephen Marglin and Amartya K. Sen (1972): UNIDO&#13;
Guidelines for Project Evaluation, United Nations, New York.&#13;
Deese, David A. and Joseph S. Nye (eds.) (1981): Energy and Security,&#13;
Ballinger Publishing House, Cambridge, Massachusetts.&#13;
Devarajan, Shantayanan and Anthony C. Fisher (1982): "Measures of Natural&#13;
Resource Scarcity Under Uncertainty", in (eds.) Smith and Krutilla&#13;
(1982).&#13;
Fisher, Anthony C. (1981): Resource and Environmental Economics, Cambridge&#13;
Survey of Economic Literature, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.&#13;
Garg, Prem C. and James L. Sweeney (1978): "Optimal Growth with Depletable&#13;
Resources", Resources and Energy, pp. 43-56.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
Gilbert, Richard J. (1976): "Optimal Depletion of an Uncertain Stock",&#13;
SEER Technical Report No. 10, University of California, Berkeley.&#13;
Gilbert, Richard J. and Knut A. Mork (1982): "Efficient Pricing During&#13;
Energy Disruptions", mimeographed, University of California at Berkeley&#13;
and University of Arizona.&#13;
Gilbert, Richard J. and Joseph E. Stiglitz (1978): Effects of Risk on&#13;
Prices and Quantities of Energy Supplies, Volumes I to IV, Report&#13;
EA-700, EPRI, Palo Alto, California.&#13;
Gilbert, Richard J., David M.G. Newbery and Joseph E. Stiglitz (1978):&#13;
An Overview of the Economic Theory of Uncertainty and its Implications&#13;
for Energy Supply, EA-586-SR, EPRI, Palo Alto, California.&#13;
Gray, Dale F. (1981): "Methods for the Economic Evaluation of Petroleum&#13;
Exploration and Synthetic Fuels Production: An Application to Brazil",&#13;
Ph.D. Thesis, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge,&#13;
Massachusetts.&#13;
Gustafson, R.L. (1958):  "Carryover Levels for Grains", U.S. Department of&#13;
Agriculture, Technical Bulletin No. 1178.&#13;
Hogan, William W. (1981): "Energy and Security Policy", Energy and&#13;
Environmental Policy Center, Discussion Paper E-81-09, John F. Kennedy&#13;
School of Government, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts,&#13;
September.&#13;
Hogan, William W. (1982): "Policies for Oil Importers", Energy and&#13;
Environmental Policy Center, Discussion Paper E-82-02, John F. Kennedy&#13;
School of Government, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts,&#13;
February.&#13;
Hotelling, Harold (1931): "The Economics of Exhaustible Resources",&#13;
Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 39, pp. 137-75.&#13;
Lind, Robert C. (1982): "A Primer on the Major Issues Relating to the&#13;
Discount Rate for Evaluating National Energy Options", in Lind et.al.&#13;
(1982).&#13;
Lind, Robert C. et.al. (1982): Discounting for Time and Risk in Energy&#13;
Policy, published by Resources for the Future, Inc., Washington, D.C.,&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, Maryland.&#13;
Little, Ian M.D. and James A. Mirrlees (1968): Manual of Industrial&#13;
Project Analysis in Developing Countries, Vol. 2, Social Cost-Benefit&#13;
Analysis, Development Center, Organization for Economic Cooperation and&#13;
Development, Paris.&#13;
Little, Ian M.D. and James A. Mirrlees (1974): Project Appraisal and&#13;
Planning for Developing Countries, Basic Books, New York.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
Manassah, Jamal T. (ed.) (1981): Alternative Energy Sources, Parts A &amp; B,&#13;
Academic Press, New York.&#13;
Mason, Scott P. and Robert C. Merton (1984): "The Role of Contingent&#13;
Claims Analysis in Corporate Finance", mimeographed, Sloan School of&#13;
Management, M.I.T., Cambridge, Massachusetts, January.&#13;
Nalebuff, Barry J. and Hal Varian (1983): "Some Aspects of Risk Sharing in&#13;
Non-Classical Environments", in (ed.) Dale W. Jorgenson, Proceedings of&#13;
the Arne Lynde Symposium on Social Insurance, North Holland.&#13;
Newbery, David M.G. and Joseph E. Stiglitz (1982): "Optimal Commodity&#13;
Stock-Piling Rules", mimeographed, Princeton University, New Jersey,&#13;
February.&#13;
Nichols, Albert L. and Richard J. Zeckhauser (1977): "Stockpiling&#13;
Strategies and Cartel Prices", The Bell Journal of Economics, Vol.8,&#13;
No. 1, Spring.&#13;
Pindyck, Robert S. (1978): "The Optimal Exploration and Production of&#13;
Non-Renewable Resources", Journal of Political Economy, October,&#13;
pp. 841-861.&#13;
Plummer, James L. (1981):  "Methods for Measuring the Oil Import Reduction&#13;
Premium and the Oil Stockpile Premium", The Energy Journal, Vol. 2,&#13;
No. 1.&#13;
Plummer, James L. (ed.) (1982):  Energy Vulnerability, Ballinger Press,&#13;
Cambridge, Massachusetts, U.S.A.&#13;
Radner, Roy and Joseph E. Stiglitz (1975): "Fundamental Non-Convexities&#13;
in the Value of Information", mimeographed, Stanford University,&#13;
California.&#13;
Ray, Anandarup (1984): Cost-Benefit Analysis: Issues and Methodologies,&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press (for the World Bank), Baltimore,&#13;
Maryland.&#13;
Rothschild, Michael (1971): "A Two-Armed Bandit Theory of Market Pricing",&#13;
Working Paper No. 10, University of California, Berkeley.&#13;
Samuelson, Paul A. (1963): "Risk and Uncertainty: A Fallacy of Large&#13;
Numbers", Scientia, Vol. 6, April/May.&#13;
Samouilidis, J.E. and S.A. Berahas (1982): "A Methodological Approach to&#13;
Strategic Petroleum Reserves", Omega, Vol. 10, No. 5, pp. 565-574.&#13;
Schulze, William D. and Allen V. Keese (1981): "Risk in Benefit-Cost&#13;
Analysis", Risk Analysis, Vol. 1, No. 1, March, pp. 81-88.&#13;
Sharpe, W.F. (1964): "Capital Asset Prices: A Theory of Market&#13;
Equilibrium Under Conditions of Risk", Journal of Finance, Vol. 19,&#13;
September, pp. 425-442.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
Smith, V. Kerry and John V. Krutilla (eds.) (1982): Explorations in&#13;
Natural Resource Economices, published for Resources for the Future&#13;
Inc., The Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, Maryland.&#13;
Squire, Lyn and Herman G. van der Tak (1975): Economic Analysis of&#13;
Projects, The Johns Hopkins University Press (for the World Bank),&#13;
Baltimore, Maryland.&#13;
Stern, Nicholas H. (1977):  "Welfare Weights and the Elasticity of the&#13;
Marginal Valuation of Income", in (eds.) M. Artis and A.R. Nobay,&#13;
Current Economic Problems, Basil Blackwell, Oxford.&#13;
Stiglitz, Joseph E. (1976): "Monopoly and the Rate of Extraction of&#13;
Exhaustible Resources", American Economic Review, Vol. 66, pp. 655-61.&#13;
Stiglitz, Joseph E. and Partha S. Dasgupta (1980): "Market Structure and&#13;
Resource Depletion: A Contribution to the Theory of Intertemporal&#13;
Monopolistic Competition", Econometric Research Program Research&#13;
Memorandum No. 261, Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey, March.&#13;
Stobaugh, Robert and Daniel Yergin (eds.) (1979): Energy Future, Report of&#13;
the Energy Project at the Harvard Business School, Random House,&#13;
New York.&#13;
Wilson, Robert (1982):  "Risk Measurement of Public Projects", in Lind&#13;
et.al. (1982).&#13;
World Bank (1980): Energy in the Developing Countries, Washington, D.C.,&#13;
August.&#13;
World Bank (1980a): Alcohol Production from Biomass in the Developing&#13;
Countries, Washington, D.C., September.&#13;
World Bank (1981): "Energy Pricing in Developing Countries: A Review of&#13;
the Literature", by DeAnne Julius and Meta Systems (Consultants),&#13;
Energy Department Paper No. 1, World Bank, Washington, D.C., September.&#13;
World Bank (1982): Potential for Industrial Energy Conservation in&#13;
Developing Countries, by Edilberto Segura and staff of the Industry&#13;
Department, Washington, D.C., October.&#13;
Wright, Brian D. and Jeffrey C. Williams (1982): "The Roles of Public and&#13;
Private Storage in Managing Oil Import Disruptions", mimeographed, Yale&#13;
University and Brandeis University, March.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Wdforld  BankL                            LC 83-22655. ISBN 0-8018-3222-5. Stock    Electricity Pricing: Theory and&#13;
Uv@iId  Bank                           No. IH 3222, $22.50.                     Case Studies&#13;
YUb&amp;2a0lo                                                                          Mohan Munasinghe and Jeremy J.&#13;
Of Rdjtod                                 The Economics of Power                   Warford&#13;
System  Reliability and                  Describes the underlying theory and&#13;
Interest                                 Planning: Theory and Case                 practical application of power-pricing&#13;
Studies                       ~~~~~~~~policies that maximize the net eco-&#13;
Studies                                  nomic benefits to society of electricity&#13;
Decentralized Renewable                   Mohan Munasinghe                          consumption. The methodology pro-&#13;
Energy Development in China:              A completely integrated treatment of      vides an explicit framework for analyz-&#13;
The State of the Art           ~~~system reliability. Indicates that appli-  ing system costs and setting tariffs,&#13;
The State of the Art                      cation of the reliability optimization    and it allows the tariff to be revised on&#13;
Robert P. Taylor                          methodology could help realize con-       a continual basis. Case studies of elec-&#13;
Describes China's achievements in the     siderable savings in the electric power   tricity pricing exercises in Indonesia,&#13;
development of biogas, small-scale hy-    sector, which is especially important     Pakistan, the Philippines, Sri Lanka,&#13;
droelectric plants, and other decentral-  for developing countries with limited     and Thailand describe the application&#13;
ized renewable energy systems. Dis-       foreign exchange reserves.                of the methodology to real systems.&#13;
cusses the Chinese approach to            The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1980.  The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1982.&#13;
decentralized energy development          344 pages (including tables, maps, index).  399 pages (including appendixes, index).&#13;
during the 1970s, and the advantages      LC 79-2182. ISBN 0-8018-2276-9, hard-     LC 8147613. ISBN -8018-2703-5, Stock&#13;
and disadvantages of the Chnese           cover; ISBN 0-8018-2277-7, paperback.     No. JH 2703, $29.50 hardcover.&#13;
methods.                                  Stock Nos. JH 2276, $27.50 hardcover; IH&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 535. 1983. 47     2277, $12.50 paperback.&#13;
pages.                                                                                  NEW&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0127-6. Stock No. WP 0535.    The Effect of Discount Rate&#13;
$3.                                       and Substitute Technology on              Energy Efficiency and Fuel&#13;
Depletion of Exhaustible                 Substitution in the Cement&#13;
NVEW                                  Resources                                 Industry with Emphasis on&#13;
Yeganeh Hossein Farzin                    Developing Countries&#13;
Developing Electric Power:                Staff Working Paper No. 516. 1982. 51     Mogens H. Fog and Kishore L.&#13;
Thirty Years of World Bank                pages (including references).             Nadkarni&#13;
Experience                                ISBN 0-8213-0004-0. Stock No. WP 0516.    Presents concepts, measures, and is-&#13;
Hugh CoUier          $3.                                     ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~sues relevant to achieving improve-&#13;
Hugh Collier                              $3.                                       ments in energy efficiency in both the&#13;
Drawing on the experience of the                .      .       .     sasindustrialized and developing coun-&#13;
World Bank in lending for the devel-      Electrcity Economics: Essays              tries. Identifies possible constraints to&#13;
opment of electric power in some          and Case Studies                          energy efficiency programs. Indicates&#13;
thirty countries, this book assesses the  Ralph Turvey and Dennis                   measures that can be taken at the gov-&#13;
results of these lending operations and   Anderson                                  emient, industry, and plant levels to&#13;
analyzes the reasons for their success    Argues the merits of relating the price   conserve energy. Indudes five an-&#13;
or failure. It describes the Bank's ob-   of electricity to the marginal or incre-  nexes.&#13;
jectves and methods and explains          mental cost of supply and deals with      Technical Paper No. 17. 1983. 94 pages.&#13;
how and why they have evolved since       interactions between pricing and in-      ISBN 0-8213-0270-1. Stock No. BK 0270.&#13;
the Bank began to lend for power de-      vestment decisions, income distribu-      $3&#13;
velopment in the early 1950s.            tion, and distortions in the pricing sys-&#13;
The issues addressed are those that       tem of the economy.&#13;
arise with the growth of the electric     The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1977;  Essesg  Opin  eeopngn Counties&#13;
power industry in developing coun-        2nd printing, 1981. 382 pages (including  Issues in  Developing Countdres&#13;
tries: investment planning and project   tables, maps, index).                      Daffel G. Fallen-Bailey and Trevor&#13;
appraisal, the expansion of the system,                                             A. Byer&#13;
pricing policies, and the problems of     LC 76-9031. ISBN 0-8018-18664, hard-A  Be&#13;
organization that affect power supply    cover; ISBN 0-8018-1867-2, paperback.      Staff Working Paper No. 350. 1979. 113&#13;
agencies and the sector as a whole.       Stock Nos. JH 1866, $30 hardcover; JH     pages.&#13;
This first systematic account of the      1867, $12.95 paperback.                   Stock No. WP 0350. $5.&#13;
Bank's lending policies and operations    French: L'economie de l'electricite: essais et&#13;
concentrates on a specific sector-elec-   etudes de cas. Economica, 1979. ISBN 2-&#13;
tric power-and deals with actual          7178-0165-0, Stock No. IB 0551, $12.95.       NEW&#13;
cases, not abstractions or general prim-  Spanish: Electricidad y economia: ensayos  TeEeg    rniini&#13;
ciples.                                   y estudios de casos. Editorial Tecnos,    The Energy Transition in&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1984.  1979. ISBN 84-309-0822-6, Stock No. IB   Developing Countries&#13;
200 pages.                                0535, $12.95.                             Details why the World Bank intends to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
commit one fourth of its loan funds to&#13;
support energy projects through 1987.&#13;
This valuable analysis updates Energy     Renewable Energy Resources&#13;
in the Developing Countries (1980), the&#13;
last comprehensive Bank report on the    Alcohol Production from                  market size during the 1980s. Con-&#13;
subject. Since then the Bank has pro-    Biomass in the Developing                cludes that there is a significant poten-&#13;
vided needed energy assistance in de-     Countries                               tial for additional methanol capacity in&#13;
veloping countries by expanding and                                               developing countries that possess low-&#13;
diversifying its energy activities. The   Explains the techniques for manufac-    cost gas resources, yet, in most cases,&#13;
insight gained from projects the Bank    turing ethyl alcohol from biomass raw    do not have an adequate supply of oil.&#13;
has financed form the basis for the       materials; analyzes the economics of    Complements the report, Alcohol Pro-&#13;
penetrating analysis in this new re-      and prospects for production and gov-   duction from Biomass in the Developing&#13;
port.                                    ermnent policies needed to accommo-      Countries (September 1980).&#13;
1983. 138 pages.                         date conflicting needs of various sec-   1982. 81 pages.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0225-6. Stock No. BK 0225.   tors of the economy in promoting         ISBN 0-8213-0018-0. Stock No. BK 0018.&#13;
$6.                                       World Bank can play in assisting de-&#13;
Global Energy Prospects                   veloping countries in designing na-MoizngR ewbeE ry&#13;
Global Jonergy Chospes Ational alcohol programs. (One of three                    Mobilizing Renewable Energy&#13;
Bourn Jong Choe, Adrian                   publications dealing with renewable     Technology in Developing&#13;
Lambertini, and Peter K. Pollak           energy resources in developing coun-    Countries: Strengthening Local&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 489. 1981. 71     tries. See Mobilizing Renewable Energy  Capabilities and Research&#13;
pages.                                    Technology in Developing Countries:&#13;
Stock No. WP 0489. $3.                    Strengthening Local Capabilities and Re-  Focuses on the research required to&#13;
search and Renewable Energy Resources in  develop renewable energy resources in&#13;
the Developing Countries.)              the developing countres and on the&#13;
1980 78page (icludng 2 anex ig- need to strengthen the developing&#13;
e1980. 78 pages (including 12 annex fig-  countires' own technological capabili-&#13;
u tok res).  BK 9172 (English), BK 9173   ties for using renewable energy.&#13;
Stock Nos. BK 9172 (English), BK 9173   1981. 56 pages.&#13;
(French), BK 9174 (Portuguese), BK 9175&#13;
(Spanish). $5.                          Stock No. BK 9431. $5.&#13;
Emerging Energy and Chemical             Renewable Energy Resources&#13;
India: The Energy Sector                 Applications of Methanol:                in the Developing Countries&#13;
P.D. Henderson                           Opportunities for Developing             Examines the contributions that re-&#13;
Summary review of the sector, provid-     Countries                               supphles in developing countries and&#13;
ing technical, historical, and statistical  Methanol, or methyl alcohol, is among  discusses the role of the World Bank&#13;
background information.                   the major basic chemical raw materials  in renewable energy development over&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1975. 210 pages  produced today. This report reviews     the next five years.&#13;
(including map, 2 appendixes, index),     the major chemical and, particularly,&#13;
fuel applications of methanol as a basis  1980. 40 pages (including annex).&#13;
ISBN 0-19-560653-1, Stock No. OX          for projecting the minimal methanol      Stock No. BK 9176. $5.&#13;
560653, $12.95 hardcover.&#13;
NEW&#13;
NEW&#13;
A Model of World Energy&#13;
Markets and OPEC Pricing                  The Transfer of Petrochemical            The authors outlines the nature of the&#13;
Boum-Jong Choe                            Technology to Latin America:             market for petrochemical technology,&#13;
Uses seven industrial and developing      An Empirical Study of                    identifies the main technology supplier&#13;
country groups, three energy using        Participants, Policies, and              engineering contractors), and describes&#13;
sectors, and one energy transformation    Processes                                the structure of the petrochemical in-&#13;
sector (thermal power generation) to&#13;
analyze world energy and petroleum        Mariluz Cortes and Peter Bocock          dustry in Latin America. Provides a&#13;
markets. Econometric simulation                              ~~~~~~~primer on the broad issues, concludes&#13;
markets. Econometric simulation           This book deais with the transfer of     with a critical, data-based discussion of&#13;
model used under a wide range of as-      technology from industrial to indus-    the main factors that appear to deter-&#13;
sumptions about economic growth and       trializing countries. It draws on exist-  mine the different types of arrange-&#13;
OPEC pricing through the early 1990s.    ing literature in English and Spanish     ments used.&#13;
suggests that past and expected future    (much of which is not readily available&#13;
prices will provide incentive to substi-  (mucheo  hihi nonpcait) randoilyavilablre-  Supported by detailed tables and ap-&#13;
tute away from energy and petroleum.      search to present a comprehensive pic-   pendixes, covering 280 individual&#13;
Coal will play a key role as a substi-    sueac tof perensentdea whcmperehesiempi-  transfers over a 40-year period.&#13;
tute fuel for the next 20 years.          cal technology has been transferred for  The Johns Hopkins University Press. June&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 633. 1984. 186    virtually all installations in operation,  1984. 200 pages.&#13;
pages.                                    under construction, or being planned     LC 83-049365 ISBN 0-8018-3259-4. Stock&#13;
Stock No. WP 0633. $5.                   in Latin America up to the mid-1970s.     No. JH 3259, $25, hardcover.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of this form.)        P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                                Name&#13;
Firm                                                 Title&#13;
Address                                              Firm&#13;
City              State_    Postal Code              Address&#13;
Country             Telephone (     1                City             State_      Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                              Country              Telephone(&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my W Check C International Money Order El Unesco Coupons O International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my a VISA O MasterCard O American Express F Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number            Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
D Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Internal&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                       Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price    Total Amount s&#13;
All prices subject to change.  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
Total copies      Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each)   S_&#13;
Total  S_&#13;
BRO0053                                                           Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World Bank Publications&#13;
ARGENTINA                           GERMANY, FEDERAL REFUBUC              KUWAIT                               SRI LANKA AND THE MALDrvES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL                    OF                                  MEMRB                                Lake House Bookshop&#13;
Galena Guemes                        UNO- Vedag                           PO. Box 5465                         P 0 Box 244&#13;
Ronda 165, 4th Floor-Ofc. 45Y465     D-5300 Bonn 1                        Kuwait                               103, Sir Chittampaiam A. Gardiner&#13;
1333 Buenos Aires                   Snirockstrasse 3                      MALAYStA                               Ma'vbwatha&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW                GREECE                                Universitv of Malava Cooperatve      Sn La  ka&#13;
GUINEA. FIJI, SOLOMON              MEMRB                                  Bookshop, Limited                   n  r&#13;
ISLANDS, AND VANUATU              24. Ippodamou Street                  P 0. Box I127, alan Pantai Baru      SWEDEN&#13;
Info-Line                           Athens-11635                          Kuala Lunmpur                        For single titles&#13;
o ve. GPO                            HONG KOnG0 L    ACtd                 ME ICO                               ABCE Fntzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel&#13;
Sydney, NSW 2001           Asia 20030 Ltd.                       LNFOTECRgenggts12Bo165&#13;
Stdney, NSW 201l                    6 Fl- 146 Prince Edward Road. W,      San Lorermo 153-1i. Col. del Valle   S-103 27 Stockholms&#13;
Australia                            Kowloon                                Deleg. Benito Juarez               For sbsuriepn ordes:&#13;
BAHRAIN                              Hong Kong                            03100 Mexico Citv                    Werergren-Waiams AB&#13;
MEURB 22103                          INDIA                                MOROCCO                               Box 30J04&#13;
Manama Town 317                      LBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd.    MEMRB                                S-104 25 Stockholm&#13;
Post Box 7015                        2 Rue Moliere Racine                 SWrrTZRLAND&#13;
BANGLADESH                           New Delhi 110t02                     CasabLanca                           Librairie Pavot&#13;
Micro Industnes Development          10 Firt Main Road                    THE NErHERLANDS                      6 Rue Grenus&#13;
Asststance Socxety                 Gandhi Nagar                          Medical Books Europe, BV (MBE)       Case postal 381&#13;
Dhaka.                               Bangalore 560009                     Noorderwal 38.                        CH 1211 Geneva 11&#13;
BELGIUM                              Apeetav Chambers, PO. box 76         7241 BL Lochem                       TANZANIA&#13;
Publications des Nahions Unises      3 Wallace Stheet                     NIGERIA                              Ofr   mest  rs&#13;
Av. du Roi 202                       Bornbav U00D1                         University Press Linited             P. 0. Box 5299&#13;
106 Brussels                        &amp;1B, Chowr  hee La                    Three Crowns Building Jencho         Dar es Salasm&#13;
BRAZIL                               Calcutta 700016                      Private Mail Bag 395                  THAILND&#13;
Publcacoes Tecrucas Internadonais    71188, I(CA), Swarup Nagr               dan                                Central Departme0t Store&#13;
Ltda.                              Kampu 20800                           NORWAY                               306 Susom Road&#13;
Rua Peixoto Gomnide, 209                                                  Tanumt Karl Johan, A. S.              Bangkok&#13;
01409 Sao Paulo, SP                  Sivaganga Road                        P 0  Box 1177                        TRINIDAD &amp; TOBAGO&#13;
Nungamnbakkam                        Seonum                                Svstemahcs Studies Unit&#13;
CANADA                               Madras 60034                          Oslo 1                               SS Fastern Main Road&#13;
Le Diffuseur                        INDONESIA                              PAKISTAN                             Carepe&#13;
C.P. 85, I01 Ampere St               Pt Indira Limited                     Mirza Book Agency                    Trinidad, West Indies&#13;
Boucherville. Quebec J48 E6        Jl Samn Ratulangi 37                  65, Shahrah-e-Quaid-e-Azam            TUNISIA&#13;
CHILE                               Jakarta Pusat                          P.O. Box No. 729                     Societe Tunisienne de Diffusion&#13;
Editorial Renacimiento               PO Box 181                            Lahore 3                             5 Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Mialoreo  3                          IRELAND                               PANAMA                               Tunis&#13;
Santiago                             TDC Publishes                         Edicones Librena Cultural            TURKEY&#13;
COSTA RICA                           12 North Frederick Stet                 Panamena, S.A.                     Haset Kitapevi A.S.&#13;
Libreria Trelos                      Dublin I                              Av. 7. Espana 16                     469, Istikla Caddesi&#13;
Cale 11-13                           ITALY                                 Panama Zone I                        Bevoglu-Istanbul&#13;
SAn Fernandez GueaLicosa Commiasionara Sansoni SPA                         PERU                                 UGANDA&#13;
Via Laraamnora 45                     Editorial Desarrollo SA              L'ganda Bookshop&#13;
CYPRUS                               50121 Florence                        Apartado 3824                        Attn:Mr Martn-Luther Galiwango&#13;
.MZMRB                                                                      m&#13;
P0  3ox 2098                         JAPAN                                                                      P 0. Box 7145&#13;
Nicosia                              Eastern Book Service (EBS)            PHIIUPPINES                          Kampala&#13;
37-3, Hongo 3-Chome, Bunkvo-ku        National Book Store                  LNrrED ARAB EMIRATES&#13;
DENMARK                                113                                 701 Rizal Avenue                     MEMRS&#13;
SamhundsLitteratsr                   Tokvo                                 Metro Manila                         P. 0  Box 6097&#13;
Rosenoerns Alle 11                   JORDAN                                PORTUGAL                             Shaxlab&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V                  )MEMRb                               Livr   Portugal                      LNTED KINGDOM AND&#13;
EGYPT, ARAB REPUBUC OF               P 0 Box 3143                          Rua Do Canno 70-74                     NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
Al Ahram                            !abal                                  120 Lisbon                          Microirifo Lid.&#13;
GalStreet                            Amman                                 SAUDI ARABIA                         P 0  Box 3&#13;
Cairo                                KEN'tA                               Jarir Book Store                      Alton, Hampshire GU 34 2PG&#13;
FINLAND                              Atnca Book Service jE.A.) Ltd.        P 0. Box 3196                        United Kingdom&#13;
Akateeminen Kujakauppa               P 0  Box 45245                        Riyadh 11471                         VENEZUELA&#13;
PS. BOX 128                          Nairobi                               SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA             Lbrena del Este&#13;
ieisFLi10                            KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                    niornation Publications Pnvate, Ltd.   Aptdo. 60.337&#13;
relsinki 10                     Pan Korea Book Corporahon             02-06 Lst Fl., Pei-Fu Indu3thial Bldg.,    Caracas 1060-A&#13;
FRANCE                               P 0  Box 101. Kwangwtamun             24 New Industial Road                WEST        SAMOA&#13;
World Bank Publicatons               Seoul                                 Singapore                            Weslev Bookshop&#13;
66 Avenue d'Iena                                                           SPAIN                                Api&#13;
73116 Parns                                                                Mundi-Prensa Libros, S.A.&#13;
Castello 37&#13;
28001 Madrid&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                           European Office                Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                    66, avenue d'lena              Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.         75116 Paris, France            1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234              Telephone: (1) 723-54.21       Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK             Telex: 842-620628              Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                              Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN             ISBN 0-8213-0563-8&#13;
&lt; &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="887897">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/07/887897/issues-appraisal-energy-projects-oil-importing-developing-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/07/887897/issues-appraisal-energy-projects-oil-importing-developing-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/07/887897/issues-appraisal-energy-projects-oil-importing-developing-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/02/15/000178830_9810190343212/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/02/15/000178830_9810190343212/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-02-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1985-07-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Issues in the appraisal of energy projects
            for oil-importing developing countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper develops a theoretical
            framework to evaluate the benefits and costs of energy
            projects in oil-importing developing countries. The
            framework is used to address various questions: How should
            the problems of energy dependency and vulnerability be
            reflected in a project appraisal? Are there externalities
            not captured in the market price of the resource? Should
            royalty values be included in cost-benefit calculations? Why
            do the real prices of exhaustible resources rise over time?
            Should several energy development projects be done
            simultaneously? What are the true costs of stockpiling oil?
            Is there a need for an international institution to act as
            coordinator directing a strategy for information gathering
            and project diversification across countries?
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Issues in the appraisal of energy projects
            for oil-importing developing countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Issues in the appraisal of energy
            projects for oil-importing developing countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1985/07/887897/issues-appraisal-energy-projects-oil-importing-developing-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Energy and Environment,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Energy</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Anand, Sudhir</author>
            <author>Nalebuff, Barry</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_9810190343212</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Oil &amp; Gas Exploration &amp; Development</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 738</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Energy</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Oil &amp; Gas</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0563-8</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Petroleum importing developing countries;
            Cost-benefit analysis; Energy; Projects; Petroleum prices;
            Bank rates; Bank rates; Import finance
            arbitrage,asset pricing,BENEFIT
            ANALYSIS,capital constraints,capital
            markets,coal,commodities,conservation,consumption
            patterns,contingent claims,Cost effectiveness,Cost-benefit
            analyses,development projects,Discount Rate,discount
            rates,discounted value,economic analysis,economies of
            scale,economies of scope,economists,elasticity,energy
            conservation,Energy prices,energy
            resources,equilibrium,Expected Present Value,expected
            return,expected returns,expected
            value,externalities,fuels,gas,gas reserves,Imperfect
            Competition,imports,Income,Income Distribution,income
            levels,inefficiency,insurance,insurance companies,interest
            rate,interest rates,Inventories,LDCs,marginal
            utility,marginal value,Market prices,national income,nominal
            interest rate,nominal interest rates,oil,oil company,oil
            prices,oil reserve,oil reserves,opportunity
            cost,optimization,per capita income,Present Value,price
            changes,price fluctuations,profit maximization,proven
            reserves,renewable energy resources,risk averse,risk
            aversion,risk premium,Sales,shadow prices,social
            welfare,spread,stocks,substitutes,substitution,suppliers,tax
            rates,underestimates,utility value,Valuation,value
            added,value of output,volatility,world oil
        </keywd>
        <owner>Development Economics and Chief Economist</owner>
        <repnb>SWP738</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cartels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Horizontal Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Fixing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development Commercialization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Innovation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Volatility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anticartel Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Renewable Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research, Development and Innovation (RDI)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>