<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP-659&#13;
The Benefits and Costs of Official Export Credit Programs&#13;
of Industrialized Countries&#13;
An Analysis&#13;
Heywood Fleisig         j  . I \ (A&#13;
FILE C|  OI t' `        Catharine Hill&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 659&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 659&#13;
The Benefits and Costs of Official Export Credit Programs&#13;
of Industrialized Countries&#13;
An Analysis&#13;
Heywood Fleisig&#13;
Catharine Hill&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright ( 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 Hi Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing October 1984&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present&#13;
the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been&#13;
prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and&#13;
the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and should&#13;
not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to any individual&#13;
acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared solely for the convenience&#13;
of the readers; the denominations used and the boundaries shown do not imply, on&#13;
the part of the World Bank and its affiliates, any judgment on the legal status of any&#13;
territory or any endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in the&#13;
Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each is&#13;
available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The World&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the European&#13;
Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'1ena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Heywood Fleisig is a senior economist in, and Catharine Hill a consultant to, the&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department of the World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Fleisig, Heywood W.&#13;
The benefits and costs of official export credit&#13;
programs of industrialized countries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 659)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Export credit. I. Hill, Catharine, 1954-&#13;
II. Series.&#13;
HG3753.F57  1984           382'.63          84-13211&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0387-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
This paper analyzes the benefits and costs of official direct&#13;
export credit and subsidy programs.   It estimates that the subsidy in&#13;
the direct loan and subsidy programs of seven major lending industrial&#13;
countries ranged from $1.5 billion to $3.5 billion in 1980.   Of this&#13;
amount, developing countries received between $500 million and $2.4&#13;
billion allowing for export price changes.  The paper analyzes several&#13;
problems in estimating the subsidy. In particular, it shows how market&#13;
factors determine the subsidy's effect on export prices and volumes and,&#13;
thereby, the ultimate division of the subsidy between borrowers and&#13;
lenders.   Finally,  the paper assesses the world social benefits and&#13;
costs that result from the subsidy and ensuing changes in export prices&#13;
and volumes.&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
We are grateful to J. Michael Finger, Ben Crain and David Dod&#13;
for numerous helpful comments, encouragement and support during this&#13;
project. Nicholas Hope, Jeffrey Katz and Thomas Klein of the World Bank,&#13;
and Bevan Stein of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and&#13;
Development, provided comments and invaluable guidance during the&#13;
analysis of the data. Mark Connell provided excellent research&#13;
assistance. Any errors of fact or logic remain our responsibility, as do&#13;
the views expressed in this paper, which are not necessarily those of the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
We prepared this paper for the National Bureau of Economic&#13;
Research Conference, "The Structure and Evolution of U.S. Trade Policy,"&#13;
held in Cambridge, Massachusetts in December 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EXTRACTO&#13;
En este trabajo se analizan los costos y beneficios de los programas ofi-&#13;
ciales de cr6dito directo y de subsidio a la exportaci6n. Se estima que en pro-&#13;
gramas de prestamos directos y subvenciones de siete importantes paises presta-&#13;
mistas el subsidio fluctu6 entre US$1.500 millones y US$3.500 millones en 1980.&#13;
De esta suma, los paises en desarrollo recibieron entre US$500 millones y&#13;
US$2.400 millones, tomando en cuenta las variaciones de los precios de exporta-&#13;
cion. En este trabajo se examinan diversos problemas que presenta la estimaci6n&#13;
del subsidio. En particular, se indica la forma en que los factores del mercado&#13;
determinan el efecto del subsidio en los precios y volumenes de exportaci6n y, a&#13;
traves de este, c6mo se divide finalmente el subsidio entre prestatarios y pres-&#13;
tamistas. Por ultimo, en este trabajo se analiza la asignaci6n de los costos y&#13;
beneficios sociales mundiales resultantes del subsidio y de las variaciones con-&#13;
siguientes de los precios y volXumenes de exportaci6n.&#13;
Ce document analyse les coufts et avantages des programmes offi-&#13;
ciels d'octroi de credit et de subventions directs a l'exportation. Les&#13;
auteurs estiment que l1'lement de subvention des programmes d'octroi de&#13;
prets et de subventions directs de sept grands pays preteurs se situait&#13;
entre 1,5 et 3,5 milliards de dollars en 1980. Les pays en d6veloppement&#13;
en ont recu entre 500 millions et 2,4 milliards de dollars, compte tenu&#13;
des variations des prix a l'exportation. Ce document analyse plusieurs&#13;
des probl&amp;mes que souleve l'estimation de l'element de subvention.  I1&#13;
montre en particulier comment les facteurs du marche determinent l'effet&#13;
de l'element de subvention sur le prix et le volume des exportations et,&#13;
partant, comment il se r6partit en fin de compte entre emprunteurs et&#13;
preteurs. Enfin, les auteurs examinent le calcul des cofits et avantages&#13;
sociaux mondiaux qui resultent de t1l1ment de subvention et des varia-&#13;
tions qu'il engendre dans le prix et le volume des exportations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.   Introduction and Summary       ........        ............ .        1&#13;
II.  Measuring the Subsidy on Official Export Credit Programs.            4&#13;
Methods of Calculating the Subsidy on&#13;
Official Export Credits .........................           4&#13;
Empirical Findings .....                                        8&#13;
III. Benefits and Costs of Export Credit Subsidy Programs .....          13&#13;
The Distribution of the Subsidy between Borrowers&#13;
and Exporters: Price Increases by Exporters&#13;
Recapture Part of the Subsidy ...................          13&#13;
Nonsubsidized Citizens Pay the Subsidy When&#13;
There is no Market Failure ......................          14&#13;
Other Benefits and Costs to Borrowing Countries .....          16&#13;
Other Benefits and Costs to Lending Countries .......          18&#13;
Appendices&#13;
A.   International Controls of Officially Supported&#13;
Export Credits ......................................          29&#13;
B.   Efficiency Losses and Income Redistribution Arising&#13;
from Export Credit Subsidization ....................          35&#13;
C.   The Macroeconomics of the Size and Distribution&#13;
of the Cost of Export Credit Subsidies ..............          44&#13;
D.   Estimating the Annual Costs of Export&#13;
Credit Subsidies ....................................          48&#13;
E.  Glossary ..........        ......................................     52&#13;
F.   Data on Official Export Credits ..........................          56&#13;
1. Organization for Economic Cooperation&#13;
and Development ....................................          56&#13;
2.  World Bank ...........................................          57&#13;
3.  Berne Union ..........................................          57&#13;
4.  Export-Import Bank of the United States ..............          59&#13;
Footnotes             ...............................................    60&#13;
Bibliography  .       ...............................................    66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION AND SUMMARY&#13;
Governments support export credits in, broadly, two ways: through&#13;
direct loan and subsidy programs, on the one hand, and insurance and&#13;
guarantee programs on the other. This paper considers the first set of&#13;
programs. Under direct loan programs, government institutions extend&#13;
export credits directly, often in association with private financing.&#13;
Under subsidy programs, governments operate indirectly on export credits by&#13;
extending preferential refinancing and interest subsidies to private&#13;
lenders. In the United States, Canada, and Japan, official export&#13;
institutions lend directly to both domestic exporters and foreign importers&#13;
at fixed subsidized rates. In Germany, France, the United Kingdom, and&#13;
Italy, official institutions combine direct lending, refinancing of private&#13;
export credits at preferential rates, and interest rate subsidies to&#13;
achieve similar results.&#13;
The subsidy in officially-supported export credits arises in&#13;
several ways: loans are made at fixed rates to borrowers who would&#13;
normally qualify only for variable-rate loans, at maturities generally&#13;
longer than available in the private market for comparable loans to such&#13;
borrowers, and at lower rates than these borrowers would otherwise pay.&#13;
Industrial countries have often attempted to limit the subsidy on&#13;
official export credits. In April 1978, the major industrial exporters&#13;
agreed in the Arrangement on Guidelines for Officially Supported Export&#13;
Credit to specify minimum interest rates, minimum down-payments, and&#13;
maximum periods of repayment. The Arrangement specifies the minimum&#13;
interest rates irrespective of currency denomination, despite the effect of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
different national rates of inflation producing different nominal interest&#13;
rates in lending countries. Therefore, the Arrangement actually allows&#13;
credit subsidization to vary over time and across countries. Since market&#13;
rates have increased relative to the Arrangement's fixed minimum interest&#13;
rates, the Arrangement-s permitted subsidies have risen. For similar&#13;
reasons, countries with high market interest rates have been able to offer&#13;
larger subsidies than countries with low market rates.&#13;
Attempts to reform the Arrangement to better reflect market&#13;
interest rates in member countries and to reduce levels of subsidization&#13;
have typically not succeeded. Arrangement signatories have increased&#13;
minimum interest rates several times by small amounts, but subsidies in&#13;
1982 continued at high levels and still varied considerably from currency&#13;
to currency. Negotiations to limit export credit subsidies, therefore,&#13;
continue.&#13;
This paper analyzes the costs and benefits of the direct loan and&#13;
subsidy programs. It estimates that the subsidy in the direct loan and&#13;
subsidy programs ranged from $1.5 billion to $3.5 billion in 1980.1 Of&#13;
this amount, the paper estimates that, after export price changes,&#13;
developing countries received between $500 million and $2.4 billion.&#13;
After discussing issues in estimating the subsidy, the paper sets&#13;
forth the market factors that determine the subsidy's effect on export&#13;
prices and volumes and, thereby, the ultimate division of the subsidy&#13;
between borrowers and lenders. It finds that borrowers receive between 50&#13;
and 100 percent of the subsidy, depending on the supply, demand, and market&#13;
structure of thes export industries receiving subsidized credit. In&#13;
situations without external costs or benefits it finds, in both competitive&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
and most common monopolistic export markets, that borrowers cannot lose&#13;
from accepting export credit subsidies and that lenders cannot gain from&#13;
giving them.&#13;
The paper then raises a variety of issues relevant in assessing&#13;
the social costs and benefits to borrowers and lenders resulting from the&#13;
subsidy and ensuing changes in export prices and volumes:&#13;
o    Some developing countries may lose from subsidized export&#13;
credit if their own export industries must compete&#13;
against subsidized credit;&#13;
o    Some developing countries might be forced away from the&#13;
best currency composition of their debt portfolios if&#13;
export credit programs limit their choice of currency&#13;
denominations;&#13;
o    Some lending countries might achieve offsetting gains in&#13;
employment, to the extent that subsidized exports&#13;
persistently come out of otherwise unemployed resources;&#13;
o    The redistribution of income toward low-income countries&#13;
and away from high-income countries makes it more&#13;
difficult to measure the welfare loss associated with the&#13;
efficiency loss.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
II. MEASURING THE SUBSIDY ON OFFICIAL EXPORT CREDIT PROGRAMS&#13;
Outstanding direct and subsidized export credits of the major&#13;
lending countr:Les (Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the United&#13;
Kingdom and the United States) amounted to nearly $55 billion at the end of&#13;
1978. These lenders offered substantial subsidies, charging interest rates&#13;
between 7 and 8 per cent, at the same time that private lenders charged&#13;
rates between 5 and 15 per cent.&#13;
This section estimates that the subsidy paid by official export&#13;
credit granting institutions ranged between $1.5 billion and $3.5 billion&#13;
in 1980. The subsidy equals the difference between the rate charged by the&#13;
lender and the rate the borrower would have paid had the borrower gone to&#13;
the private market. Depending on supply, demand, and market structure in&#13;
the subsidized export sector, exporters in lending countries recapture&#13;
between 50 and 100 percent of the subsidy. Of the amount transferred to&#13;
borrowers, about 70 percent of the subsidy went to developing countries, 25&#13;
percent to centrally planned economies, and the balance to developed coun-&#13;
tries.&#13;
Methods of Calculating the Subsidy on Official Export Credits&#13;
Calculating the subsidy on official export credits requires first&#13;
making a judgment about the private rate that the borrower would have&#13;
paid. This rate will always exceed the government borrowing rate, but&#13;
beyond that will depend on the characteristics of both the borrower and the&#13;
loan. The subsidy element may be calculated as an annual interest&#13;
differential or as the present value of future interest differentials over&#13;
the life of the loan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
The Private Interest Rate Must Exceed the Government Borrowing Rate&#13;
The subsidy a borrower receives equals the difference between the&#13;
official export credit institution-s rate and the rate charged in the&#13;
private market for the same type of loan and borrower. Some estimates&#13;
compute the subsidy by comparing the government borrowing rate with the&#13;
official export credit rate. Such computations underestimate the subsidy,&#13;
however, because importers will always pay a higher interest rate on their&#13;
loans, given currency denomination and maturity, than will the government&#13;
of the country issuing the currency because:&#13;
o    Privately-granted export credit is tailored to the&#13;
individual transaction--a retail transaction--with a low&#13;
volume and a high overhead. In contrast, government debt&#13;
is marketed in large volumes, and in standardized units&#13;
and maturities.&#13;
o    Privately-granted export credit, because of this&#13;
individual tailoring, is harder to resell; by contrast,&#13;
liquid markets exist at most maturities for government&#13;
debt.&#13;
o    Only the government of the currency-issuing country can&#13;
absolutely guarantee the payment of bonds denominated in&#13;
its own currency because only that government can legally&#13;
create that currency at will. Since no private or&#13;
foreign government borrower can make the same guarantee&#13;
about his debt, lenders will always require additional&#13;
compensation for this added risk.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
The market interest rate measures the cost to society of granting export&#13;
credit when its productive resources are fully employed (see Appendixes B&#13;
and C). The government interest rate, at full employment, will always fall&#13;
short of the private market rate for the same maturities, for the reasons&#13;
discussed above. At full employment, the subsidy is the difference between&#13;
the export credit agency's rate and the market rate. The difference&#13;
between the export credit agency's rate and the government interest rate&#13;
provides only some peripheral information relating to the budgeted cost --&#13;
not the social cost -- of the export-credit granting agency.&#13;
Estimating the Subsidy Using the Private Interest Rate&#13;
That the Importer Would Have Paid&#13;
Borrowers can pay interest on their loans at interest rates fixed&#13;
over the life of the loan, or at interest rates that float above the&#13;
wholesale bank rate.  Typically, good credit risks can borrow at either&#13;
rate, while riskier borrowers must take floating rate loans.&#13;
This paper computes the subsidy under both of these assumptions&#13;
about the riskiness of the borrower. It estimates the subsidy for&#13;
borrowers who would otherwise have financed their imports with a floating&#13;
rate loan by multiplying the outstanding portfolio of officially supported&#13;
export credits by the interest rate differential between the lending&#13;
country-s short-term market rate and the average interest rate actually&#13;
received on the portfolio.2&#13;
The paper estimates the subsidy for borrowers who otherwise would&#13;
have borrowed at fixed rates by multiplying the loans granted in each year&#13;
by the difference between the bond rate at which they could have borrowed&#13;
and the interest rate charged on the direct export credit. It derives the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
total subsidy on the loan portfolio by adding the subsidies on all loans&#13;
still outstanding. (Appendix D discusses the estimation of fixed and&#13;
floating rate subsidies.)&#13;
These methods produce an ex post measure of the subsidy that&#13;
represents the savings in debt service in any given year under different&#13;
assumptions about the alternative borrowing possibilities available to the&#13;
borrowing country. The two measures of the subsidy may differ from ex ante&#13;
expectations of the subsidy. In the fixed-rate calculation, the savings in&#13;
interest payments in future years are set at the time the loan is committed&#13;
and, if the borrower does not refinance, the expected and actual future&#13;
interest subsidy are equal. In the floating rate case, the subsidy in any&#13;
year will change with movements in the short-term interest rate. The&#13;
expected subsidy and the actual subsidy will, therefore, only be equal if&#13;
borrowers realize their expectations of movements in the floating rate.&#13;
An Alternative Method for Calculating the Subsidy&#13;
The subsidy may also be expressed as the discounted present value&#13;
of the fixed-rate subsidy on loans authorized in any one year. The subsidy&#13;
would equal the difference between the face value of the subsidized loan&#13;
and the present value of the repayment stream computed at the market rate&#13;
of interest.3 Computing the present discounted value of the subsidy&#13;
permits representing and analyzing the interest subsidy in a price-&#13;
equivalent form: borrowers should be indifferent between receiving the&#13;
interest subsidy and a decrease in the price of the good equal to the&#13;
present discounted value of the interest subsidy. However, official&#13;
institutions lend only a portion of the purchase price of an export; since&#13;
that portion differs both between countries and within countries among&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
different goods and, since some important countries do not report these&#13;
data, computing the price-equivalent subsidy still does not permit&#13;
comparing its size to export prices or unit values.&#13;
The present value of the subsidy, moreover, is difficult to&#13;
compute because its calculation requires information on people's beliefs&#13;
about the future course of interest rates (for a floating-rate loan) or&#13;
about their refinancing plans (for a fixed-rate loan). By contrast, the&#13;
method presented in the previous section avoids this problem by calculating&#13;
the interest subsidy for one year on all loans outstanding in that year.&#13;
Empirical Findings&#13;
Subject to some important qualification discussed below, the paper&#13;
finds that the subsidy ranged between $1.5 billion and $3.5 billion in 1980&#13;
for borrowers whose financing alternatives were, respectively, fixed and&#13;
floating rate loans.&#13;
Computing the subsidy requires knowing the maturity structure of&#13;
the portfolio of outstanding loans, the year in which each loan was made,&#13;
and the interest rate charged on each loan. Extremely severe data&#13;
limitations required strong simplifying assumptions. (Appendix D discusses&#13;
these issues). Problems exist both in comparing the diverse national&#13;
institutional arrangements and in penetrating the secrecy that lending&#13;
countries maintain about the volume of lending and the degree of&#13;
subsidization reflected in loan terms.&#13;
Subject to these data limitations, the paper estimates that the&#13;
total subsidy amounted to about $1.5 billion in 1980 if the borrower's&#13;
alternative was, in actuality, a fixed-rate loan (see Table 1). A negative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
Table 1:  ESTIMATE OF THE SUBSIDY WHEN BORROWERS&#13;
ALTERNATIVE IS A FIXED-RATE LOAN ($ Million)ab&#13;
1976     1977      1978      1979       1980&#13;
Canada                         14.6      13.7     24.6    (27.3)c    (46.9)&#13;
France                          n.a.      n.a.   420.5   (464.8)    (552.4)&#13;
Germany                        23.9       6.3    (-5.4)  (-16.2)    (-17.5)&#13;
Italy                          53.3      74.0     94.2   (110.9)    (128.8)&#13;
Japan                          36.7      31.7     21.2      15.4       (55.6)&#13;
United Kingdom                289.7    358.7    423.9   (499.9)    (543.1)&#13;
United States                 108.3      81.6     57.5      85.2       213.5&#13;
Total                         526.5    566.0  1,036.5  1,187.3    1,522.8&#13;
a.  The estimates are based on data obtained from the Export-Import Bank of&#13;
the United States.  For a detailed discussion of the data, see Appendix&#13;
F.&#13;
b. For a detailed description of the estimating procedure, see Appendix D.&#13;
c. The numbers in parentheses were calculated assuming outstanding loans&#13;
remained constant over the previous year. This was done when data were&#13;
not available for recent years. Since most programs have been growing,&#13;
this should provide a lower bound on the estimate of the subsidy.&#13;
entry in this table implies that a borrower took an official loan at a rate&#13;
in excess of the market bond rate. Since a sensible borrower would not&#13;
willingly do that, negative entries rather indicate that the typical&#13;
recipient of official export credits, contrary to assumption, could not&#13;
borrow at the fixed bond rate assumed and that the estimate of $1.5 billion&#13;
is too low.&#13;
If the typical recipient of official export credit would have&#13;
borrowed at floating rates in the absence of official lending, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
estimated subsidy rises to about $3.5 billion in 1980 (see Table 2).&#13;
Negative subsidies, as shown in the table, can arise either where borrowers&#13;
are unable or unwilling to refinance their fixed-rate official loans at&#13;
lower floating rates. Borrowers might be unable to refinance at the&#13;
spreads assumed in Table 2 (50 basis points over the three month interbank&#13;
rate in the country where the loan is made). In that case, Table 2&#13;
underestimates the subsidy.4 On the other hand, borrowers might be&#13;
Table 2: ESTIMATE OF THE SUBSIDY WHEN BORROWERS ALTERNATIVE&#13;
IS A FLOATING-RATE LOAN ($ Million) a,b&#13;
1976     1977      1978      1979        1980&#13;
Canada                        -14.8    -23.6      91.0   (151.2)c   (288.4)&#13;
France                          n.a.      n.a.   152.5   (336.4)    (725.1)&#13;
Germany                       -76.2    -44.4  (-113.1)  (-40.3)        (39.5)&#13;
Italy                         169.5    134.4      81.4    (92.8)    (222.0)&#13;
Japan                          95.4    -35.2   -253.7   -107.9        (471.5)&#13;
United Kingdom                243.0      37.4    118.4   (533.0)    (855.9)&#13;
United States                 -86.4    -44.6    189.8    546.3         992.2&#13;
Total                         330.5     24.0    266.3  1,511.5    3,524.6&#13;
a.  The estimates are based on data obtained from the Export-Import Bank&#13;
of the United States. For a discussion of the data, see Appendix F.&#13;
b. For a detailed description of the estimating procedure, see Appendix&#13;
D.&#13;
c. The numbers in parentheses were calculated assuming outstanding loans&#13;
remained constant over the previous year. This was done when data&#13;
were not available for recent years. Since most programs have been&#13;
growing, this should provide a lower bound on the estimate of the&#13;
subsidy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
unwilling to refinance longer-term fixed rate commitments at lower,&#13;
floating short-term rates if they foresaw a pattern of short-term rates&#13;
over the life of the longer-term loan that would make it unprofitable for&#13;
them to refinance; it is difficult to imagine an operational test of this&#13;
explanation.&#13;
Lacking direct information on the regional distribution of the&#13;
subsidy by type of borrower, the paper estimates it by assuming that&#13;
lenders subsidize all borrowers by approximately the same amount. Then the&#13;
distribution of the loans by type of borrower would be the same as the&#13;
distribution of the subsidy by type of borrower. Table 3 shows the&#13;
distribution of loans by type of borrower: about 69 percent of the loans&#13;
went to developing countries, about 24 percent to Eastern Europe and China,&#13;
and the remainder to other developed countries.5&#13;
The entire subsidy is not transferred to foreign borrowers, how-&#13;
ever, because domestic exporters in the lending country can raise prices&#13;
and recapture part of the subsidy's benefits. The next section discusses&#13;
why recapture probably ranges between zero and one-half in most typical&#13;
markets. Applying these recapture rates to the estimated range of total&#13;
subsidy granted by the export credit -- $1.5 to $3.5 billion -- yields an&#13;
estimate of subsidy actually transferred to $.75 to $3.5 billion.&#13;
Assuming that the transferred subsidy is distributed by type of&#13;
borrower in the same proportion as the pattern of lending implies that&#13;
developing countries would have received about 70 percent of the total&#13;
subsidy, or $.5 to $2.4 billion. Because the Arrangement permits lower&#13;
interest rates and longer maturities for low income countries, 70 percent&#13;
is a conservative estimate of the proportion of the subsidy going to&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Table 3: GEOGRAPHIC DISTRIBUTION OF SUBSIDIZED EXPORT CREDITS&#13;
1978            1979&#13;
Lender           Borrower                              (percentage)   (percentage)&#13;
France           Developed Countries                         19                5&#13;
Eastern Europe and China                    18              33&#13;
Less Developed Countries                    63              62&#13;
Total                                100              100&#13;
Germany          Developed Countries                          7               5&#13;
Eastern Europe and China                    28              26&#13;
Less Developed Countries                    66              69&#13;
Total                                100              100&#13;
Italy a          Developed Countries                          -&#13;
Eastern Europe b                            52              30&#13;
Less Developed Countries                    48              70&#13;
Total                                100              100&#13;
Japan            Developed Countries                          4               2&#13;
Eastern Europe and China                    26              43&#13;
Less Developed Countries                    70              55&#13;
Total                                100              100&#13;
United Kingdom  Developed Countries                          13              15&#13;
Eastern Europe and China                    34              19&#13;
Less Developed Countries                    53              66&#13;
Total                                  100             100&#13;
United States   Developed Countries                          16              11&#13;
Eastern Europe and China                     1               2&#13;
Less Developed Countries                    83              87&#13;
Total                                100              100&#13;
Total            Developed Countries                         12               7&#13;
Eastern Europe and China                    22              24&#13;
Less Developed Countries                    66              69&#13;
Total                                100              100&#13;
a.   The figures for Italy only include credits with a repayment term over&#13;
five years.&#13;
b.   Figures for Italy do not include loans to China.&#13;
Source: Trends in Export Credits Among Major Competitors. Export-Import&#13;
Bank of the United States. Policy Analysis Staff. Washington, D.C.,&#13;
March 6, 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
III. THE BENEFITS AND COSTS OF EXPORT CREDIT SUBSIDY PROGRAMS&#13;
In both competitive and most common monopolistic export markets,&#13;
recipients of subsidized export credits cannot lose while, symmetrically,&#13;
providers of subsidized export credits cannot gain, so long as there are no&#13;
external costs or benefits. This section first considers how the market&#13;
reaction of export prices and volumes to the subsidy determines the final&#13;
distribution of the subsidy between lending-country exporters, lending-&#13;
country citizens who provide the subsidy, and the borrowing-country&#13;
importers. It then considers a variety of external costs and benefits that&#13;
affect the social costs and benefits arising from various redistributive&#13;
and efficiency aspects of the program.&#13;
The Distribution of the Subsidy between Borrowers and Exporters:&#13;
Price Increases by Exporters Recapture Part of the Subsidy&#13;
The distribution of the subsidy will depend on supply, demand, and&#13;
market organization in the markets receiving subsidized export credit (see&#13;
Appendix B). In a competitive market, when officially supported export&#13;
credits increase demand for a good whose supply is totally inelastic,&#13;
subsidized buyers bid up the price above its previous level. Since the&#13;
quantity sold remains constant, by assumption, buyers can only be satisfied&#13;
when the price has risen by enough to extinguish the extra demand created&#13;
by the subsidy. The export price must rise then by the full amount of the&#13;
subsidy. The domestic exporting industry, therefore, recaptures the entire&#13;
subsidy through higher prices and the borrowing country gains nothing. If&#13;
the price of the export is fixed on world markets, whatever the supply&#13;
conditions, the entire subsidy is also transferred to the domestic&#13;
exporting industry. The existence of many perfect substitutes for the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
subsidizing country's exports means that only a slight price advantage&#13;
suffices to capture much of the market. Subsidy recipients will bid up the&#13;
price of the subsidizing country's exports by nearly the full amount of the&#13;
subsidy and still willingly buy the same or greater amounts than before.&#13;
If supply is less than totally inelastic and the price of the&#13;
export is not given on world markets, however, some of the subsidy must be&#13;
transferred to the borrowing country to induce them to purchase more. When&#13;
supply curves are infinitely elastic over the range of the subsidy, all of&#13;
the subsidy is transferred to the borrowing country importers.&#13;
If the exporter in the lending country is a monopolist, some of&#13;
the subsidy must be transferred to the borrowing-country importer. The&#13;
monopolist always operates in the elastic portion of his demand curve, and&#13;
can always increase profits by expanding sales volume when his demand curve&#13;
shifts out.&#13;
Given available information on supply, demand, and market&#13;
organization in the markets receiving subsidized export credit, this paper&#13;
estimates that borrowers receive between 50 and 100 percent of the subsidy&#13;
(see Appendix B). In competitive markets, existing estimates of&#13;
elasticities of supply and demand (Stern 1976) suggest that almost all of&#13;
the subsidy is transferred to the borrower. If the exporters in lending&#13;
countries are monopolists, this paper estimates that boirowers get half of&#13;
the subsidy,6 though this finding rests on assumed values for the second&#13;
derivatives of demand and marginal cost functions.&#13;
Nonsubsidized Citizens Pay the Subsidy When There Is No Market Failure&#13;
If official export credit lending does not solve a market failure&#13;
within the lending country, and markets are competitive, then overall&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
efficiency or output cannot rise. If the subsidy eliminates no market&#13;
failure but, at the same time, makes borrowing country importers and&#13;
lending country exporters better off, then it must make other citizens of&#13;
lending countries worse off. If borrowing-country importers receive any of&#13;
the subsidy, as is likely, the lending country as a whole must lose.&#13;
Depending on whether the price or volume of exports rises, nonsubsidized&#13;
citizens in lending countries bear the cost in different ways.&#13;
In a fully-employed economy, real net exports can rise only by&#13;
reducing real domestic investment, consumption, or government expenditure&#13;
(see Appendix C for further discussion). If the rise in net exports forces&#13;
a decline in domestic investment projects, the lending country citizens&#13;
lose the market rate of interest on the foregone investment,7 while the&#13;
lending country government receives the lower, subsidized interest rate on&#13;
the same quantity of exports. The loss to the lending country government&#13;
and its nonsubsidized citizens amounts to the difference between the market&#13;
rate and the lower subsidized rate. These losses may, however, be partly&#13;
offset by terms-of-trade gains that increase exporters profits when the&#13;
subsidized loan increases demand. As discussed above, however, the lending&#13;
country typically will not recover part of this subsidy; that part will be&#13;
transferred to the borrowing-country and lost through the inefficient use&#13;
of resources.&#13;
When the economy is fully employed, but where an increase in&#13;
imports offsets the rise in exports so that net exports remain unchanged,&#13;
the net cost to the subsidizing country is the same as before. Purchasers&#13;
of imported goods pay the higher world market interest rate to finance&#13;
their additional imports, while their government receives the lower,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
subsidized interest rate on the additional exports it financed. As before,&#13;
gains to exporters partly offset this loss, but the rest of the subsidy is&#13;
retained by borrowing country importers or absorbed by the higher cost of&#13;
less efficient production.&#13;
Other Benefits and Costs to Borrowing Countries&#13;
While borrowing countries generally gain from the subsidy on&#13;
export credits even after prices adjust, other costs, difficult to quan-&#13;
tify, may offset the gain. Restrictions on the currency denomination of&#13;
the export credit may distort the currency denomination of the borrowing&#13;
country's debt and, thereby, offset part of the gain from the subsidy to&#13;
the borrowing country. The subsidy calculation may also overstate the gain&#13;
to borrowing countries if they compete in third markets against exports&#13;
from industrialized countries that receive subsidized credit.&#13;
Currency Choice Limitations May Produce a Suboptimal Debt Portfolio&#13;
Just as a country will choose a portfolio of international reserve&#13;
currencies that, by various accounts, produces some optimal risk-return&#13;
combination in the light of that country-s future consumption and&#13;
investment plans, so a country will desire a portfolio of international&#13;
debt denominated in different currencies that achieves the same end.&#13;
If the borrowing-country's acceptance of the export credit leads&#13;
to denominating additional debt at market rates in a currency that moves&#13;
the borrowing country away from its optimal debt portfolio, then the above&#13;
estimate of the interest subsidy overestimates the gain to the borrower.&#13;
The gain to the borrower cannot be negative, however, since the subsidy&#13;
expands the choices available to the borrower, and the borrower need not&#13;
accept the subsidized credit to purchase the export.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
The seriousness of this problem depends on several impondera-&#13;
bles. First, export-credit granting agencies do denominate loans in&#13;
currencies other than their domestic currencies, though they offer less&#13;
choice than do international banks. Second, the individual firm has some&#13;
opportunity to rearrange the currency denomination of its other assets and&#13;
liabilities, so it need not restrict its entire portfolio by the initial&#13;
choice of export-credit instrument. Finally, the entire country has even&#13;
more freedom to rearrange its assets and liabilities to compensate for any&#13;
deviations from an optimal debt structure that the currency composition of&#13;
the subsidized export credit might produce.&#13;
Terms of Trade Effects in Third Markets May Offset the Gain to&#13;
Developing Countries of Official Export Credit Subsidies&#13;
The gain to borrowing countries from subsidized export credit may&#13;
be offset if the borrowing countries also export goods to third markets&#13;
which compete with exports from industrial countries that receive&#13;
subsidies. When a developing country's exports compete with goods which&#13;
receive subsidies from industrial countries, its terms of trade&#13;
deteriorate. The fact that many developing countries have instituted&#13;
official export credit programs to match industrial country subsidies&#13;
suggests that these countries do export goods competitive with subsidized&#13;
industrial country exports. In particular, some evidence exists that&#13;
developing countries have become increasingly competitive at producing&#13;
customized capital goods.&#13;
When developing countries compete against industrial country&#13;
exports to other developing countries that receive subsidized credit, the&#13;
distribution of the subsidy among individual developing countries changes,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
but the estimat:e of the transfer to all developing countries does not.&#13;
Subsidies granted or price reductions on developing country exports to&#13;
industrial countries could, however, reduce the estimates of the transfer&#13;
presented here. Developing country exports competing against industrial&#13;
countries exports that receive most subsidized export credits (SITC&#13;
category 7), however, amounted to only $14 billion in 1980, while&#13;
industrial country export credits go primarily to developing countries.&#13;
Given this, terms of trade for developing country exports would have to&#13;
deteriorate far beyond those ever experienced to reverse the estimates of&#13;
the flows given above. At most, even assuming that all developing country&#13;
exports of such goods to industrial countries compete against goods&#13;
receiving subsidized credits, the subsidy estimate would be reduced by&#13;
about 25 percent.8&#13;
Other Benefits and Costs to Lending Countries&#13;
The exporter generally recaptures only part of the export credit&#13;
subsidy through higher prices. Whether the lending country as a whole&#13;
gains from the subsidy, therefore, depends on whether the official export&#13;
credit solves a market failure within the lending country. A variety of&#13;
externalities on which export credit subsidies could act have been advanced&#13;
by proponents of officially supported credits. Even where these arguments&#13;
have merit, however, in few cases are export credit subsidies the best&#13;
means of achieving a given goal.&#13;
The Effects of Officially Supported Export Credits on Employment&#13;
Export subsidies can increase employment in export industries.&#13;
However, when the economy is already at full employment, employment in the&#13;
subsidized export industry rises at the expense of employment elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Since total employment cannot increase beyond full employment, and the&#13;
resulting resource shift may temporarily aggravate inflation, employment&#13;
gains in export industries provide no net social gain for the subsidizing&#13;
country.&#13;
In the face of general unemployment, an export subsidy can&#13;
increase total employment. However, so can monetary and fiscal policies.&#13;
Moreover, as general tools to regulate the economy, monetary and fiscal&#13;
policies may be superior to export subsidies. The export credit subsidy&#13;
normally increases the production of exports relative to other domestically&#13;
produced goods, increasing the relative cost of the export goods to&#13;
domestic consumers. Unless considerations other than a general increase in&#13;
employment prompt the use of subsidies, other policies--such as monetary&#13;
and fiscal policies--could increase employment and output without these&#13;
side-effects on relative prices and sectoral outputs. No reason exists,&#13;
moreover, to believe that an export subsidy will provide a stronger or less&#13;
inflationary stimulus to employment than other forms of budgetary spending&#13;
or tax reductions.&#13;
In addition, if export credits do not vary over the business&#13;
cycle, their beneficial effects in reducing unemployment in recessions will&#13;
bear a cost later when they contribute to overheating the economy during&#13;
booms. Since export credits are often committed far in advance of actual&#13;
transactions and are usually extended over periods that are longer than any&#13;
one stage of the cycle, and since future cycles cannot be perfectly fore-&#13;
seen, great difficulties beset the use of export credits for stabilization&#13;
purposes. 9 These rigidities enhance the desirability of alternative&#13;
policies to deal with unemployment and inflation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Export subsidies could be used to support employment in chroni-&#13;
cally depressed industries or regions. The subsidy could serve as an&#13;
alternative to unemployment payments if it were clear that, in the absence&#13;
of the subsidy, the unemployed labor in a particular industry or region&#13;
would not be employed elsewhere. However, pursuing such a policy for a&#13;
long time would result in increasing losses to the country by extending the&#13;
period of time during which resources were used inefficiently.&#13;
Official Export Credits and Capital Market Imperfections&#13;
Sometimes the absence of private market credit may indicate a&#13;
market imperfection that prevents the gains from trade from being fully&#13;
realized. In such a case, the government can correct the market deficiency&#13;
by providing credit, making society's use of resources more efficient.10&#13;
The absence of private market loans, however, does not prove that&#13;
the market is imperfect. Some less-developed countries, for example,&#13;
cannot float bonds in the bond market. Many reasons exist for this, all&#13;
relating to the absence of the kind of creditworthiness and volume of&#13;
credit demand that makes floating a bond issue worthwhile. Likewise, many&#13;
corporations cannot raise funds by selling bonds. Instead, they and&#13;
smaller partnerships and individuals must ordinarily finance their business&#13;
loans by borrowing from a retail bank at higher rates of interest than bond&#13;
issuers pay.&#13;
Most less developed countries raise funds by borrowing from banks&#13;
in the Eurodollar market or in national banking markets. Their loans&#13;
typically have interest rates that float at a predetermined number of basis&#13;
points (hundredths of a percentage point) over a benchmark interest rate&#13;
such as the prime rate or the London Interbank Offer Rate (LIBOR). When an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
official export credit institution lends to such a borrower at, for&#13;
example, a rate comparable to a lower corporate bond rate, it grants that&#13;
country a subsidy equal to the difference between the retail rate it would&#13;
have been charged because of the greater risk, and the rate charged by the&#13;
official institution.&#13;
When a bank refuses credit to a foreign borrower at market rates&#13;
because of the condition of the country or of the borrower within the&#13;
country, then the risk attached to the loan exceeds that represented by the&#13;
retail rates that banks typically charge these countries. The subsidy&#13;
granted by the official institution is greater than the difference between&#13;
the rate it charges and the market rate because it is taking a risk larger&#13;
than the one reflected in the market rate.&#13;
When the private sector responds to risky loans by charging higher&#13;
rates or by refusing to make them at all, this does not, as noted, neces-&#13;
sarily mean that a market imperfection exists. When such imperfections are&#13;
absent, official loans at below-market rates cannot raise total income or&#13;
increase efficiency. Without solving a market imperfection, such practices&#13;
can only redistribute income away from non-subsidized citizens and toward&#13;
domestic exporters or citizens of a borrowing country.&#13;
Matching Foreign Subsidized Credit Programs&#13;
If a foreign government permanently subsidizes an export product,&#13;
the policy that would yield the largest income for another country's&#13;
citizens as a group would permit the foreign producer to supply the good.&#13;
In this way, the country that does not match the foreign subsidy can earn&#13;
larger quantities of foreign exchange and import more goods by reallocating&#13;
domestic resources from the production of the foreign-subsidized good to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
the next-most-productive sector. The receipts from the sales of these&#13;
next-best exports will be only marginally lower, and the subsidy to&#13;
foreigners will no longer be necessary. Although neither workers nor&#13;
equipment can be reallocated without costs, reallocation involves a one-&#13;
time cost whereas matching subsidies involve a permanent stream of costs.&#13;
For that reason, the reallocation of resources may be cheaper when the&#13;
foreign subsidy program is expected to last a long time.&#13;
If it is known, however, that the foreign country's subsidy is&#13;
only temporary, then the lending country may gain by competing with a&#13;
matching subsidy. Whether a country will benefit from matching subsidies&#13;
depends on whether the costs of competing in the short run are outweighed&#13;
by the benefits of not having to shift productive resources first out of&#13;
and then back into the affected export sector.&#13;
Any one lending country might use subsidized export credits to&#13;
bring pressure on other countries that refuse to curb their own subsidized&#13;
lending through an international agreement. Whether this would produce a&#13;
benefit for any one country would depend on the cost to the country of&#13;
continued subsidization of exports by other countries.&#13;
Common views of fairness may also dictate matching foreign&#13;
subsidies. When one government subsidizes export credits, it injures the&#13;
producers in other countries who are competing directly with those&#13;
subsidized products in both the foreign and domestic markets. Because&#13;
neither workers nor equipment can be reallocated without cost, citizens in&#13;
the non-subsidizing country as a whole may temporarily lose income and&#13;
wealth. The workers and capital owners in the industry will typically bear&#13;
these costs, but ,costs will be spread to other citizens through programs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
such as unemployment insurance. These risks are quite similar to those&#13;
borne by other groups of industrialists and workers who face weather&#13;
changes, technical changes in foreign countries, demand changes, input&#13;
price changes, and changes in local governments subsidies and tax&#13;
exemptions. Nonetheless, when one government makes a conscious decision&#13;
aimed largely and necessarily at damaging exporters in other countries, the&#13;
fellow citizens of damaged exporters may believe this commercial misfortune&#13;
is more inequitable than the others described above. In this case, a&#13;
country may be willing to sacrifice some efficiency to attain an outcome it&#13;
sees as more equitable. The total costs of the subsidy must be weighed&#13;
against the equity considerations.&#13;
The Effect of Officially Supported Export Credits on the Exchange Rate&#13;
Increased exports can produce exchange rate appreciation. Where&#13;
small interest rate subsidies produce a large increase in the total value&#13;
of exports, an export credit subsidy program may result in exchange rate&#13;
appreciation. However, where comparatively large interest rate subsidies&#13;
fail to produce a much larger increase in exports, any appreciation may be&#13;
quickly reversed.&#13;
After the merchandise sale, however, the receipt of interest&#13;
payments on the subsidized loan will fall short of the payments on foreign&#13;
loans made by citizens who were originally crowded out of the national&#13;
capital market. This net drain on interest payments will reduce the&#13;
current account. Therefore, after the initial, temporary rise in export&#13;
receipts, the subsidized loan may produce a current account deficit and&#13;
exchange rate depreciation that counteracts the initial trade surplus and&#13;
exchange rate appreciation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Even when subsidized loans produce exchange-rate appreciation,&#13;
such appreciation is not always desirable. Whether appreciation benefits a&#13;
country will depend on general economic conditions and on the objectives of&#13;
economic policy. If the economy as a whole is near full employment,&#13;
inflationary pressures are high, and export industries and import-competing&#13;
domestic industries are in good condition, a subsidized export-credit&#13;
program may help reduce inflation by producing exchange rate appreciation&#13;
over and above that warranted by monetary conditions. The gain to the&#13;
exporter obtaining the susidized loan, however, will be offset by other&#13;
losses from exchange-rate appreciation. Exchange-rate appreciation raises&#13;
export prices in foreign markets, reducing sales of nonsubsidized&#13;
exports. At the same time, it lowers foreign prices and increases the&#13;
pressure on import-competing industries.&#13;
The Benefits of an Increase in Exports&#13;
A rise in exports can reflect a socially desirable increase in&#13;
productivity or in savings, but subsidizing exports does not force this&#13;
relation to operate in reverse. For example, exports may increase because&#13;
productivity rises in the export industries. If the exchange rate does not&#13;
change, exporters will either supply more exports at the old price,&#13;
undersell their competitors, or deliver a higher quality product at the&#13;
same price. The rise in productivity would be a clear benefit to the&#13;
country, with more output resulting from a given quantity of inputs.&#13;
However, the rise in exports would only reflect these gains; it would not&#13;
produce them.&#13;
Similarly, higher saving rates can increase net exports, but&#13;
subsidizing exports need not raise total national saving. A rise in saving&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
will reduce the consumption of imported goods and free up more domestic&#13;
goods to be exported, thus increasing the current account surplus. Such an&#13;
increase in the current account surplus means citizens are accumulating&#13;
capital in foreign countries. Accumulation of foreign assets passes on a&#13;
larger total capital stock to future generations of citizens. Although the&#13;
future generation's consumption gain is partly offset by the current&#13;
generation-s loss, so long as both generations fully undertake this shift,&#13;
no external cost warrants using public policy to undo the savings decision.&#13;
In economies at full employment, however, a subsidized rise in&#13;
exports can occur only at the expense of some domestic activity--consump-&#13;
tion, investment, or government expenditure--or when offset by a corre-&#13;
sponding rise in imports. If imports rise to provide the goods absorbed by&#13;
the increase in exports, then the subsidy has produced no rise in net&#13;
exports. If the subsidy does increase net exports at the expense of&#13;
domestic consumption or government spending, then the subsidy may ulti-&#13;
mately raise the total of domestic and foreign investment. However, the&#13;
domestic expenditure most likely to fall as a consequence of subsidy-&#13;
induced rises in borrowing rates is domestic investment. In this case,&#13;
there will be no net increase in capital passed on to future generations,&#13;
although future generations will get more capital located in foreign&#13;
countries. Citizens as a group will gain no obvious advantage from such a&#13;
shift.&#13;
A Foreign Policy or National Security Role for Official Export Credits&#13;
Official export credits are sometimes justified as a way of&#13;
protecting industries that are important for national defense, and as a way&#13;
of transferring resources to foreign countries that need economic aid. It&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
is doubtful, however, that export credit subsidies are an efficient way of&#13;
achieving either of these ends.&#13;
If a country wished to preserve an industrial activity within its&#13;
borders on national security grounds, it could achieve that by subsidizing&#13;
the exports of that industry.11 Secondary national defense benefits may&#13;
also accrue from having a larger pool of skilled workers in a given&#13;
industry. It must be shown, however, that an export credit subsidy is a&#13;
relatively inexpensive way to achieve this end. For example, if&#13;
maintaining a core of trained technicians and a manufacturing capacity in&#13;
naval nuclear generating units is an important national defense objective,&#13;
then a standing annual order for such devices might be cheaper than&#13;
subsidizing the export of entire nuclear power plants, which include mostly&#13;
goods and services that are unrelated to defense preparedness.&#13;
Official export credits may also serve a foreign aid function.&#13;
This does not, however, appear to have been their primary purpose. In the&#13;
United States, for example, official export credits have been more&#13;
concentrated in Europe than is foreign aid, and do not bear much relation&#13;
to the pattern of foreign aid disbursement in areas outside Europe (see&#13;
Table 4). If official export credits are distributed differently from&#13;
other foreign assistance, it is unclear how to evaluate them as effective&#13;
foreign aid instruments. It might be that an addition to foreign aid would&#13;
be voted by lending-countries  governments in exactly the way it is spent&#13;
by official export credit institutions; but, on the other hand, it might&#13;
not be. Official export credits are also an inefficient form of foreign&#13;
aid since they .are tied to the export of particular goods. As discussed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
above, part of the subsidy is absorbed in the inefficient use of resources,&#13;
lost to both domestic citizens and foreigners alike.&#13;
On occasion, the granting of export credits might also be valuable&#13;
as a foreign policy device if it enabled a government to take quicker&#13;
action. This was the case in the United States in the past, when the&#13;
Eximbank was set up to finance trade with the Soviet Union in the 1930s and&#13;
later used to assist in European recovery after World War II.&#13;
Other Externalities&#13;
A variety of other purposes for subsidized export credits could be&#13;
advanced. In all cases, however, not only does the existence of an&#13;
externality justifying government involvement need to be proved, but the&#13;
use of export credit subsidies rather than other policies must be shown to&#13;
be optimal. For example, subsidized export credits might be part of a&#13;
successful industrial policy program. The case for adopting an industrial&#13;
policy would first have to be made, however, and only then could the&#13;
relative efficacy of subsidized export credit relative to other policies be&#13;
evaluated. The different economic performances of intensive users of&#13;
official export credit -- the United Kingdom and Japan, for example --&#13;
suggest caution in adopting easy generalities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4. DISTRIBUTION OF U.S. ECONOMIC ASSISTANCE AND EXIMBANK LOANS, BY REGION, FISCAL YEARS 1962-1979&#13;
(percentages of annual totals)&#13;
1962-1976                    1977                        1978                        1979&#13;
Economic     Eximbank      Economic      Eximbank      Economic      Eximbank      Economic      Eximbank&#13;
Assistance      Loans      Assistance      Loans       Assistance      Loans       Assistance       Loans&#13;
Near East and&#13;
South Asia            38.2          11.4          63.5           2.8          59.5           2.3          63.8           8.9&#13;
Latin America         19.4          22.0           9.3          21.1           8.9          32.9          11.1          15.0&#13;
East Asia             28.7          20.6           9.0          33.2           8.7          38.8           8.7          40.1    1&#13;
Africa                10.3           5.6          11.1          19.8          13.9          19.1          14.8          16.2&#13;
Europe                 2.1          32.6           4.1          21.5           9.0           5.9           1.5          18.7&#13;
Canada                 0.0           1.8           0.0           0.1           0.0           0.8           0.0           0.3&#13;
Oceania                1.3           6.0           3.0           1.4           0.1           0.3           0.2           0.8&#13;
Total a          100.0         100.0        100.0         100.0         100.0         100.0         100.0          100.0&#13;
Source:  Agency for International Development, U.S. Overseas Loans and Grants and Assistance from International&#13;
Organizations, Obligations and Loan Authorizations, July 1, 1945-September 30, 1979, Washington, D.C.&#13;
a. Columns may not add to totals because of rounding.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
APPENDIX A&#13;
INTERNATIONAL CONTROLS OF OFFICIALLY SUPPORTED EXPORT CREDITS&#13;
Countries have attempted to control subsidized export credit&#13;
terms since the 1930s. The Berne Union (the International Union of&#13;
Credit and Investment Insurers) was formed in 1934 to provide a forum&#13;
for the discussion and exchange of information among member export&#13;
credit insurance agencies, now numbering 35 member agencies from 27&#13;
countries. Over the years, the Berne Union has made non-binding&#13;
recommendations on the regulation of export credit policies. For&#13;
example, in 1953, the member nations agreed to limit maturities to five&#13;
years on export credit for heavy capital goods, and to three years on&#13;
all other export credit. Beginning in the late 1960s, members increas-&#13;
ingly disregarded these guidelines.&#13;
In 1963, the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Develop-&#13;
ment (OECD) Trade Committee established a Group on Export Credits and&#13;
Credit Guarantees. The Export Credit Group, as it is known, organized&#13;
an information exchange system in 1972, which provided for prior&#13;
consultation on credit of longer than five years. At the same time, the&#13;
OECD reached agreement on credit terms for ships and aircraft.&#13;
Negotiations continued for a more comprehensive agreement on&#13;
export credits. On October 27, 1974 the Export Credit Group concluded&#13;
an informal agreement which has come to be known as the "Gentlemen's&#13;
Agreement." It stipulated a minimum interest rate of 7-1/2 percent on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
credits of over five years, and a maximum repayment period of three&#13;
years on credits granted to wealthy nations.&#13;
Jurisdictional confusion slowed the negotiations in 1975, when&#13;
both the European Commission and the individual governments claimed the&#13;
right to negotiate on commercial policy for European Community (EC)&#13;
members. Because the European Court of Justice awarded this authority&#13;
to the European Commission, the export credit agreement concluded on&#13;
July 1, 1976 was enacted as a series of unilateral declarations by the&#13;
nations involved in its negotiation, rather than as a formal agree-&#13;
ment. These nations--Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the United&#13;
Kingdom and the United States--agreed to a matrix of minimum interest&#13;
rates and maximum repayment terms for officially-supported credit of two&#13;
years or more for three different income categories of recipient&#13;
nations. This 1976 agreement, known as the "Consensus," was accepted by&#13;
13 additional OECD members during the succeeding year.&#13;
Table 5: INITIAL CONSENSUS MINIMUM INTEREST RATES&#13;
Repayment Term&#13;
Category of Country:                   2-5 years           over 5 years&#13;
Per Capita Income&#13;
Relatively Poor:&#13;
Under $1,000                         7.25                   7.50&#13;
Intermediate:&#13;
$1,000 - $3,000                      7.25                  7.75&#13;
Relatively Rich:&#13;
Above $3,000                         7.75                   8.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
The dispute with the European Commission was resolved by 1977,&#13;
and on April 1, 1978 the "Arrangement on Guidelines for Officially&#13;
Supported Export Credit" was concluded, superseding the Consensus. The&#13;
members of the European Economic Community participated as a single&#13;
unit. The Arrangement reiterated the conditions specified in the&#13;
Consensus, and continued as a voluntary set of guidelines.&#13;
Because the Arrangement specifies the same minimum interest&#13;
rates for credit denominated in all currencies, it permits actual credit&#13;
subsidization to vary both over time and across countries. As market&#13;
rates increased over time, the fixed minimum interest rates permitted a&#13;
greater subsidy. The same fixed minimum rates permitted countries with&#13;
high market interest rates to offer larger subsidies than could coun-&#13;
tries with low market rates.&#13;
At the request of participants in the OECD Arrangement,&#13;
Mr. Axel Wallen, former Chairman of the OECD Export Credits Group,&#13;
examined alternatives to the existing Arrangement. This study&#13;
(Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1980) discussed&#13;
two alternatives to the fixed matrix: a "Uniform Moving Matrix" and a&#13;
"Differentiated Rate System." The Uniform Moving Matrix would link&#13;
Arrangement minimum rates to a basket of market interest rates of&#13;
participant countries. The minimum interest rate would be identical for&#13;
all currencies but the level would be tied to some average of market&#13;
rates. If market interest rates increased, therefore, the minimum rate&#13;
on officially supported export credits would also increase, preventing&#13;
the subsidy on officially supported export credits from automatically&#13;
increasing. As with the existing Arrangement, however, subsidization&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
rates would vary considerably from currency to currency, depending on&#13;
the individual currency's market interest rates relative to the&#13;
Arrangement minima.&#13;
The Differentiated Rate System would specify different minimum&#13;
interest rates for each currency. Rather than equalize nominal interest&#13;
rates, this system would attempt to equalize interest rate&#13;
subsidization. If minimum interest rates were defined to equal&#13;
comparable market rates for each currency, subsidies would be&#13;
eliminated. Alternatively, minimum rates could be specified so as to&#13;
allow for an agreed absolute or proportional rate of subsidization.&#13;
Despite a great deal of pressure, principally from the United&#13;
States, little progress has been made in reforming the Arrangement&#13;
according to either of the alternatives suggested in the Wallen&#13;
Report. In the summer of 1980 at the Venice Summit, the United States&#13;
supported the Differentiated Rate System, but was unable to reach agree-&#13;
ment with the European Community. Instead, Arrangement signatories&#13;
modestly increased the minimum interest rates, and stated their inten-&#13;
tion to pursue a better solution.&#13;
Additional increases in the Arrangement minimum interest rates&#13;
were negotiated in November 1981 and July 1982. The next round of&#13;
negotiations is scheduled for May 1983, but because of the recent easing&#13;
of interest rates, a further increase in the Arrangement rates appears&#13;
unlikely.&#13;
The principle features of the present Arrangement are:&#13;
Cash payment:  A minimum 15 per cent cash payment is required on all&#13;
contracts, no part of which may be provided by the donor agency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Interest rates: Recipient countries are divided into three categories--&#13;
category 1 contains those with per capita GNP over U.S.$4,000; category&#13;
2 contains those with per capita GNP under $4,000 but not eligible for&#13;
IDA assistance; and category 3 contains those eligible for IDA&#13;
assistance. Minimum interest rates vary according to the category of&#13;
country and term of the loan (Table 6).&#13;
Maturity terms: Category 3 countries must repay loans within 10 years;&#13;
all others must repay within 8 1/2 years.&#13;
Table 6: CURRENT ARRANGEMENT MINIMUM INTEREST RATES&#13;
(as of January 1, 1983)&#13;
Repayment Term&#13;
Category of Country             2-5 years     5-10 years       5-8 1/2 years&#13;
Category 3                        10.00           10.00          -&#13;
(relatively poor)&#13;
Category 2a                       10.85               -        11.35&#13;
(intermediate)&#13;
Category 1                        12.15               -        12.40&#13;
(relatively rich)&#13;
a. Countries which recently graduated to Category 2 (e.g. Algeria,&#13;
Colombia, Malaysia, Nigeria) are eligible for export credit at 11.35&#13;
percent with repayment terms up to 10 years, rather than 8 1/2.&#13;
Exceptions: The Arrangement exempts agricultural commodities, military&#13;
equipment, commercial jet aircraft, and nuclear power plants. Partial&#13;
exceptions allow extended repayment terms for satellite ground stations,&#13;
conventional power plants and cryogenic (liquified natural gas) tankers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
Local-cost support: The Arrangement pertains to financing the foreign-&#13;
exchange cost of export goods from the lending country, not to local&#13;
costs incurred in installing equipment in the borrowing country. The&#13;
Arrangement prohibits local-cost financing in relatively rich countries,&#13;
but permits local-cost insurance and guarantees.&#13;
Mixed Credit: Export credits generally involve less than a 5 per cent&#13;
grant element. All credits with a grant element below 15 per cent&#13;
require prior notification of other Arrangement signatories. Credits&#13;
involving a 15 to 25 per cent grant element require prompt notification,&#13;
while those with more than a 25 per cent grant element are considered&#13;
Official Development Assistance and are exempted from notification&#13;
requirements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
APPENDIX B&#13;
EFFICIENCY LOSSES AND INCOME REDISTRIBUTION ARISING&#13;
FROM EXPORT CREDIT SUBSIDIZATION&#13;
For both competitive and most common monopolistic export&#13;
markets, where external gains and losses are absent, a lending country&#13;
cannot make itself better off by providing export credits at subsidized&#13;
rates; nor can a borrowing country make itself worse off by accepting&#13;
them.12 Under typical supply, demand, and cost conditions, subsidizing&#13;
export credit produces a combination of some loss in efficiency together&#13;
with redistribution of income away from citizens providing the subsidy&#13;
and toward domestic exporters and foreign importers. These effects&#13;
become extreme at the limit: a lending country offering exports in&#13;
perfectly price-inelastic supply or facing perfectly price-elastic&#13;
excess demand will transfer nothing to the borrowing country; on the&#13;
other hand, a lending country offering exports in perfectly price-&#13;
elastic supply will transfer nothing to its home exporters from the&#13;
subsidy program.&#13;
This analysis examines equilibrium reached in the market for&#13;
the export good as prices and quantities adjust to a change in the&#13;
export credit subsidy. We have not used a more general equilibrium&#13;
framework for two reasons. First, the smallness of these programs&#13;
relative to the economies providing the loans would make the computation&#13;
of the effects econometrically non-operational. Second, proper expan-&#13;
sion to more general effects would require a major escalation in&#13;
complexity, since analyzing export credits perforce requires dropping&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
the assumption that trade is balanced and introducing instead a frame-&#13;
work that optimizes over time.&#13;
The subsidy, s, is the present value of the interest rate&#13;
subsidy expressed per unit of quantity demanded. The demand curve is&#13;
entirely a foreign demand curve, so only the export market is shown. In&#13;
equilibrium, the demand price and supply price will differ by the amount&#13;
of the subsidy, so&#13;
(1)      PS(QS) . PD(QD) + s&#13;
In a competitive market, the social gain to the lending&#13;
country, GL, from subsidizing the export credit equals the producers'&#13;
surplus less the cost of the subsidy. For inverse supply curves whose&#13;
integral is defined over the closed interval [O,Q*], social gain, GL,&#13;
will be&#13;
(2)      GL - PsQ* - ofQ* PS(Q)dQ - sQ*&#13;
Totally differentiating expression (2), the change in the gain&#13;
with respect to the subsidy will be&#13;
dGL    QdPS   s*                dPSs*&#13;
(3)      d8    Q d8         ~ ds    Q* -   Q* (S    1) _ 8dQ*&#13;
(3)    ds       ds     ds               ds           ds&#13;
The social gain to the borrowing country, GB, equals the&#13;
consumers  surplus plus the subsidy.  For inverse demand curves whose&#13;
integral is defined over the closed interval [O,Q ], the social gain,&#13;
GB, will be&#13;
*&#13;
(4)       GB - 0fP PD(Q)dQ    S PQ+s&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Totally differentiating expression (4), the change in gain to&#13;
the borrowing country with respect to the subsidy will be&#13;
(5)       dGB -      dPs   1)&#13;
Endogenous Price, Upward-Sloping Supply Curve,&#13;
Downward-Sloping Demand Curve&#13;
Where prices are endogenous, the changes in the quantities of&#13;
exports supplied equal those demanded in equilibrium, so that dQS - dQD&#13;
- dQ*. The change in the equilibrium quantity of exports (Q*) with&#13;
respect to the subsidy (s) can be derived from (1) and will be&#13;
(6)      ds    1P$   6PD&#13;
aQ aQD&#13;
ds    s  ~D&#13;
Given that QS(Ps) - QD(PD) and PS - PD + 8, the change in the&#13;
equilibrium supply price will fall between zero and one:&#13;
aQD&#13;
(7)      dP          bPD                 dPS    1&#13;
ds     6Q5   =QD                ds     1&#13;
aS     aD&#13;
Evaluating (3) by expressions (6) and (7) indicates that the&#13;
lending country cannot gain from the credit subsidy  (ddGL 40)&#13;
while similarly evaluating (5) indicates that the borrowing country&#13;
cannot lose from the credit subsidy (dGB &gt;0)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
Endogenous Price, Horizontal Supply Curve&#13;
If the supply curve is horizontal (PS(QS) = k), substitution of&#13;
-    0  in (6) implies&#13;
FJQs&#13;
dQ*      I1     &gt;&#13;
aQD&#13;
while, by assumption,&#13;
dP5&#13;
(9)       ds s&#13;
Evaluating expression (3) with the values shown in (8) and (9)&#13;
indicates that the lender must lose (dGL &lt;0) , while similarly&#13;
evaluating expression (5) indicates that the borrower must gain the&#13;
entire subsidy (dGB = Q ds).&#13;
Endogenous Price, Vertical Supply Curve&#13;
Since  dQS   dQD  when the price is endogenous, a vertical&#13;
supply curve implies that  dQS = dQD m dQ* = 0.  Totally differentiating&#13;
the inverse demand curve shown in (1), given that dPD = 0 because dQD =&#13;
0, indicates that&#13;
dPl&#13;
(10)      ds    1&#13;
Evaluating expression (3) given dQ =0 and dPs=ds indicates that&#13;
the lending country on net loses nothing  (dGL - 0);  rather, inelastic&#13;
supply forces the transfer of the subsidy from domestic taxpayers to&#13;
domestic producers of the subsidized export product. Similarly&#13;
evaluating expression (5) with those values indicates that the borrowing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
country gains nothing (dGB - 0) , but rather returns the entire subsidy&#13;
to the lending country by paying a higher price for the product.&#13;
Exogenous Price, or Horizontal Demand Curve&#13;
If a country is a relatively small supplier in the&#13;
international market, it can take the world market price as given. In&#13;
this case, P.    PW+ s,  for a constant Pw   Recalling that domestic&#13;
purchasers are not eligible for the loan subsidy,&#13;
dPs&#13;
(11)      dP5 w &#13;
while&#13;
(12)     dQ*      1     &gt;0&#13;
ds      p&#13;
aQS&#13;
Substituting the values of expressions (11) and (12) into&#13;
expression (3), the subsidizing country must lose because of the&#13;
inefficiency resulting from the increase in production  (dGL &lt;0)&#13;
Substitution in (5), however, indicates that the borrowing country does&#13;
not gain because the export price rises by the amount necessary to&#13;
absorb the subsidy   dGB - 0).&#13;
Monopolist Exporter&#13;
If a country's export market is monopolistic, the monopolist&#13;
will set the market price at a level that maximizes profit. The&#13;
monopolist's total cost curve is assumed to be C - C(Q). In the&#13;
presence of a subsidy, the price charged by the monopolist will be&#13;
(13)     PM ' PD(Q) + s&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Assuming the monopolist sells only in the export market, monopolist&#13;
profits will be&#13;
(14)               - = QP     C(Q) = QPD(Q) + SQ - C(Q)&#13;
If the monopolist maximizes profits,&#13;
(15)       bit    QbD P&#13;
(15)  aQ  '   aQD+ PD + S _C 0Q=&#13;
The second order condition will be&#13;
2          a2           P     2&#13;
(16)      a         Q    D   + 2   D _ a C  &lt; 0&#13;
aQ2        aQ2          Q      Q&#13;
The change in the quantity of exports (Q*) with respect to the subsidy&#13;
(s) can be derived by totally differentiating (15) and will be&#13;
*&#13;
(17)      dQ-   2                   &gt; 0&#13;
ds    a2        a       2&#13;
8  D     PD _b2C&#13;
Q-+ 2D    &#13;
aQ2    6QD   oQ2&#13;
This is greater than zero by the second order condition, expression&#13;
(16).  From (13) and (17)&#13;
bPD&#13;
(18)      dPM  -_                        +1&#13;
ds   -    2 &#13;
a PD     'PD   a2C&#13;
aQr      aQ    anQ&#13;
or, by the second order condition and  'PD &lt; O&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41-&#13;
a2PD   aPD   a2C&#13;
dP      Q 2              2&#13;
(19)      ds       82               2     1&#13;
Q    2D + 2 &#13;
aq 2     aQ    6Q&#13;
Note that  dPM  is not necessarily positive.  If the numerator in (19)&#13;
ds                dPM&#13;
is greater than zero, then    M  will be negative.&#13;
Assuming that the monopolist sells only in the foreign market,&#13;
the social gain to the lending country, GL, will equal the producer's&#13;
surplus less the cost of the subsidy. For monopolist cost curves whose&#13;
integral is defined over the closed interval [0, Q*], social gain will&#13;
be&#13;
(20)      GLM   PMQ* -       N MC(Q)dQ - sQ*,     ac - MC(Q)&#13;
Totally differentiating expression (20), the change in the gain&#13;
with respect to the subsidy will be&#13;
(21)      ds       Q* d   + PM  9 MC(Q)d  _ Q  -a&#13;
(21)    ds         de     M ds         ds           ds&#13;
*dPmMCQ                            d&#13;
Q  (ds- 1) + (PM          CQ)d&#13;
ds-           M               da&#13;
Q   dM    1)  + (PD   MC(Q))d&#13;
Using (15), (17) and (18) and noting the second order condition,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
dGLM                               &lt;0&#13;
(22)      ds        2                2&#13;
Q  2D +2bD   b C&#13;
aQ2      aQ    aQ&#13;
Therefore, the lending country loses from the credit subsidy  ( dGL &lt; 0).&#13;
The expression for the gain to the borrower facing a monopolis-&#13;
tic exporter is the same as in the competitive case (expression (4)).&#13;
Evaluating the change in the gain to the borrowing country, expression&#13;
(5), with expression (19), indicates that the borrowing country gains&#13;
from the credit subsidy (dGB &gt; 0).&#13;
Empirical Estimates of the Distribution of the Subsidy between&#13;
Borrowers and Exporters&#13;
In the competitive case, expression (5) shows the gain to the&#13;
borrower resulting from the subsidy. Representing the gain in relation&#13;
to the total subsidy yields&#13;
dGB       dPs&#13;
(23)      Qds   1   ds&#13;
Substituting for dps from expression (7) yields&#13;
ds&#13;
aQS&#13;
(24)      Qds -Q  _ 3QD&#13;
ap s    pD&#13;
aS   aD&#13;
Using  QS= QD and assuming that  PS= PD before the subsidy is&#13;
introduced,  dGB can be written as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
(25)      QdsB                 ,    &gt; 0 and   &lt; 0&#13;
where  e and I are the elasticities of supply and demand for exports&#13;
respectively.&#13;
Using previously estimated supply and demand elasticities&#13;
(Stern 1976),  dBranges approximately between three-quarters and one&#13;
and, therefore, most of the subsidy is transferred to the borrower.&#13;
In the monopolist case, the gain to the borrower as a result of&#13;
the subsidy as a proportion of the total subsidy is&#13;
(26)      dGB   1 _ dP&#13;
Qds       ds&#13;
dPm&#13;
Substituting for  d8  from expression (19) yields&#13;
Q    D  +   D   a&#13;
dGB      Q 2   +  Q    aQ2&#13;
(27)      dGB _ l-   aQ         apD a &#13;
27  Qds       2              2&#13;
(2D +2aD   a2C&#13;
aQ 6Q    aQ    6Q2&#13;
Evaluation of the sign or the magnitude of this expression is impossible&#13;
without estimates of the second derivatives of the demand and cost&#13;
curves. If we assume the demand and marginal cost curves are linear, as&#13;
the intermediate case between the convex and concave alternatives, then&#13;
dGB   1/2 and the borrower receives half of the subsidy.&#13;
Qds&#13;
Therefore, admittedly in the presence of some potentially large&#13;
gaps, present knowledge about competitive and monopolistic market struc-&#13;
ture of industries receiving subsidized export credits suggests that&#13;
borrowers receive between half and all of the subsidy on official export&#13;
credits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
APPENDIX C&#13;
THE MACROECONOMICS OF THE SIZE AND DISTRIBUTION&#13;
OF THE COST OF EXPORT CREDIT SUBSIDIES&#13;
Appendix B analyzed the distribution of costs and benefits of&#13;
the export subsidy program in a microeconomic framework. Since, at full&#13;
employment, domestic exporters and foreign importers must gain from&#13;
subsidized credit, while total domestic output cannot rise, the sub-&#13;
sidizing taxpayers must lose from the program. This appendix shows this&#13;
outcome in terms of the GNP accounts; the results are similar.&#13;
Case 1: Export Subsidies That Result in Additional Export Volumes at&#13;
Full Employment&#13;
Suppose that when the export subsidy increases foreign demand&#13;
for exports, the export price remains unchanged but the volume of&#13;
exports rises. Rearranging the national income identity produces:&#13;
(1)      Y -  C  -  I  -  G  +  M  =  X&#13;
If the economy is at full employment, so that Y is at its&#13;
maximum (Y - Y), the rise in exports cannot occur out of additional&#13;
production; instead, consumption, investment, or government expenditure&#13;
must fall, or imports must rise.&#13;
If the rise in exports is achieved by increasing imports, no&#13;
change occurs initially in the trade balance. The lending country gains&#13;
an asset--the export credit that bears interest at the lower, subsidized&#13;
rate; at the same time, lending country citizens incur an identical&#13;
liability to finance additional imports, but they pay interest at the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
unsubsidized world interest rate. The lending country net debt position&#13;
does not change, but the lending country loses the difference between&#13;
the subsidized and the unsubsidized interest rates. Exporters sell a&#13;
larger volume of their products, but total lending country national&#13;
output remains unchanged. Foreign importers pay the lower, subsidized&#13;
interest rate to the lending country, while lending country importers&#13;
pay the higher market interest rate and a larger total interest bill to&#13;
foreigners.&#13;
Suppose now that imports remain unchanged, so that exports and&#13;
the trade balance increase by reducing domestic investment. At the&#13;
margin, domestic investment earns the domestic, unsubsidized rate of&#13;
interest. By giving up the domestic investment project, lending country&#13;
investors lose the unsubsidized rate of interest on the foregone&#13;
domestic investment project now devoted to exports; in exchange, the&#13;
lending country receives the lower, subsidized rate of interest on the&#13;
rise in exports. If consumers require the same marginal return on a&#13;
unit of consumption that they require on a unit of investment, then a&#13;
rise in exports at the expense of domestic consumption produces the same&#13;
net loss for society. If the government requires the same marginal&#13;
return on government expenditure that its private citizens receive on&#13;
private investment, then a rise in exports at the expense of government&#13;
expenditure produces the same net loss for society.&#13;
Case 2: Export Credit Subsidies That Increase Export Values and Unit&#13;
Values but Leave Export Volumes Unchanged&#13;
If the volume of exports does not change, export promotion&#13;
incurs no real cost to the economy as a whole. The preceding discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
rests on the assumption that there is such a real cost, and that it is&#13;
borne by investors, consumers or the government. This section estab-&#13;
lishes that, even in the absence of such a real cost, the loss to the&#13;
nonsubsidized sector will exactly equal the gain to the subsidized&#13;
sector.&#13;
With constant real exports, resulting from a vertical export&#13;
supply curve, the export price (PX) will rise by the change in the&#13;
present value of the interest subsidy per unit of sales (Appendix B,&#13;
expression 10):&#13;
(2)      dPx  =  ds&#13;
Asstume, for simplicity, that there are two types of goods--&#13;
those produced for home consumption, H, and those produced for export,&#13;
X. The geometrically-weighted GNP deflator would then be&#13;
(3)      p    =  p ap (1-a)&#13;
H X&#13;
Assume now that the central bank pursues credit policies that&#13;
prevent the GNP deflator from rising despite the credit subsidy's&#13;
initial upward impact on export prices, so that the rate of change of&#13;
the GNP deflator is&#13;
(4)      py  =  aPH + (l-a)Px  -  0&#13;
The real value of exporters output measured in terms of GNP is&#13;
(5)       1        X&#13;
y&#13;
The change in that value as a result of the subsidy is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
dV      XdPx      Xds&#13;
(6)            =     K -    Xds&#13;
py      py&#13;
The real value of products produced for home consumption&#13;
measured in terms of GNP is&#13;
HPH&#13;
(7)       2  = P&#13;
y&#13;
and this will fall by the same amount as the rise in the real value of&#13;
exports&#13;
(8)      dV2      -Xds&#13;
py&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
APPENDIX D&#13;
ESTIMATING THE ANNUAL COSTS OF EXPORT CREDIT SUBSIDIES&#13;
The annual value of the subsidy can only be calculated when the&#13;
rate that would have been charged in the market to each borrower is&#13;
known. However, each borrower has different characteristics, so the&#13;
total subsidy can only be roughly estimated.&#13;
This appendix discusses the procedure that this paper uses to&#13;
estimate the subsidy on official export finance for one year, 1980,&#13;
using the Export-Import Bank of the United States as an example.&#13;
Equivalent calculations were done for the remaining six countries&#13;
discussed in the text.&#13;
Fixed-Rate Estimate of the Value of the Subsidy: Assume That Eximbank&#13;
Borrowers Could Have Sold Aaa Corporate Bonds&#13;
Only the best of Eximbank's borrowers could have borrowed at&#13;
the U.S. Aaa corporate bond rate. Assuming that all borrowers from&#13;
Eximbank could have obtained loans at the Aaa corporate bank rate&#13;
results in the fixed-rate estimate of the value of the subsidy. Given&#13;
detailed information on the loans in the outstanding portfolio, the&#13;
fixed-rate subsidy can be calculated as&#13;
1980       AA&#13;
(1)      tiT   At(rt  - rt)&#13;
At   =    Authorizations made in t still outstanding in 1980&#13;
rAA=    Corporate Aaa bond rate in t&#13;
rt    =    Average interest rate on loans authorized in t&#13;
T    -    Year during which oldest outstanding loans were&#13;
authorized.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
Table 7 shows the amount of direct loans authorized and the&#13;
weighted average interest rate charged. The Aaa corporate bond is also&#13;
shown, as is the amount saved annually by Eximbank borrowers--the&#13;
subsidy. The total subsidy on Eximabank's loan portfolio in any year is&#13;
the sum of the subsidies on the debt still outstanding from earlier&#13;
years.&#13;
Table 7: ESTIMATION OF THE EXIMBANK LOAN SUBSIDIES&#13;
Weighted           New&#13;
Average         Direct Loan                            Estimated&#13;
Interest       Authorizations          Aaa              Subsidy&#13;
Rate on          (millions          Corporate          (millions&#13;
Direct Loans       of dollars)        Bond Yield        of dollars)&#13;
1971               6.00             2,300                7.39               32.0&#13;
1972               6.00             2,200                7.21               26.6&#13;
1973               6.00             2,900                7.44              41.8&#13;
1974               6.38             4,300                8.57               94.2&#13;
1975               7.90             2,300                8.83              21.4&#13;
-1976               8.42            2,100                8.43                0.2&#13;
1977               8.50               800                8.02              -3.8&#13;
1978               8.38             2,900                8.73               10.2&#13;
1979               8.28             4,300                9.63               58.1&#13;
1980               8.44             3,600               11.94             126.0&#13;
Sources: Weighted-average interest rates were supplied by Eximbank staff.&#13;
The Aaa corporate bond yield was taken from the Federal Reserve&#13;
Board, Annual Statistical Digest and Federal Reserve Bulletin,&#13;
various issues.&#13;
If the data on the percent of past authorizations still&#13;
outstanding are not available, these estimates assume that all loans&#13;
authorized in a given year have a maturity equal to the average and that&#13;
t/T percent (where T - average maturity and t ranges from 1 to T) of&#13;
loans authorized (T + 1 - t) years in the past are still outstanding.&#13;
For example, 1/9th of loans authorized 9 years ago would still be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
outstanding, given T = 9. These estimates weight the resulting subsidy&#13;
so that the weighted average of loan authorizations made in the past&#13;
equals the total outstanding export credits. Using this procedure for&#13;
Eximbank yields a fixed-rate estimate of the subsidy equal to $213.5&#13;
million for 1980.&#13;
If the data on past authorizations are not available, these&#13;
estimates assume that authorizations have remained constant over time.&#13;
Since authorizations have generally been increasing for the countries&#13;
considered, this assumption will yield a lower bound for the fixed-rate&#13;
estimate. For example, using this procedure for Eximbank yields an&#13;
estimate of the subsidy of $171.2 million for 1980.&#13;
Floating-Rate Estimate of the Value of the Subsidy:&#13;
Assume That Borrowers Would Have Borrowed at Rates&#13;
Floating with the Eurocurrency Rate&#13;
The floating-rate comparison is appropriate in cases where the&#13;
borrowers are not creditworthy enough to secure fixed-interest loans by&#13;
selling bonds. Instead, they borrow at rates that follow the Eurocur-&#13;
rency rates. In 1980, on a portfolio of $13.8 billion, Eximbank earned&#13;
a return of 7.31 percent. Comparable floating rate on Eurodollar loans&#13;
for that year bore an average rate of 14.5 percent, so the subsidy was&#13;
7.19 percent on $13.8 billion, or $992 million. The floating-rate&#13;
subsidy in 1980 is calculated as&#13;
-   rE     r&#13;
(2)   A1980 (r1980- r1980)&#13;
A1980   =  Total outstanding official export credits in 1980&#13;
1980   =  Eurocurrency loan rate in 1980&#13;
r1980   =  Average interest rate on total outstanding official&#13;
export credits in 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
Computing the subsidy requires knowing the weighted average&#13;
interest rate on the entire portfolio. Sometimes the lending agency&#13;
supplies that information, but in other cases the lending agency sup-&#13;
plies only the average interest rate for each year's authorizations. In&#13;
the latter case, computing the average interest rate on the entire port-&#13;
folio requires knowing the volume of each year's authorizations still&#13;
outstanding. Where the lending agency also does not supply that infor-&#13;
mation, we estimate the authorizations still outstanding, by year, as we&#13;
did for the fixed-rate estimate of the subsidy (see above).&#13;
Other Problems in Estimating the Value of the Subsidy&#13;
In calculating the value of the subsidy on official export&#13;
credits, this estimate assumes that borrowers faced, as an alternative,&#13;
the market rate on loans denominated in the same currency as the&#13;
subsidized export credit. Recently, countries have begun providing&#13;
officially-supported export credits in foreign currencies. In such&#13;
cases, the subsidy for any one country is the difference between the&#13;
subsidized rate and the market rates for loans in the currencies in&#13;
which the subsidized export credits are made. This procedure was used&#13;
for the calculation of the subsidy for Canada, where a large proportion&#13;
of loans are denominated in U.S. dollars. Although several other&#13;
countries have started to provide official export credits in foreign&#13;
currencies, inadequate data prevented our taking this into account in&#13;
the subsidy calculations. The error introduced is probably small,&#13;
however, both because foreign currency authorizations have only become&#13;
important in the last few years and because authorizations are not&#13;
immediately reflected in outstanding loans.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
APPENDIX E&#13;
GLOSSARY&#13;
Bond Insurance - A recently available type of insurance offered&#13;
by some agencies. Importers of capital goods and projects often require&#13;
exporters to give bonds to ensure compliance with contracts, or in cases&#13;
of non-compliance, to ensure reimbursement of advance payments. Private&#13;
bond issuers can purchase insurance to cover the risks incurred.&#13;
Buyer Credits - Credits extended directly by a bank or other&#13;
financial institution in the supplier's country to the foreign buyer or&#13;
to a bank in the buyer's country. (The terms "supplier" and "exporter"&#13;
and the terms "buyer" and "importer" are interchangeable.)&#13;
Commercial Risk - The risk of non-payment arising from default&#13;
by, as well as the insolvency of, an importer in his home currency (as&#13;
compared to risk arising from an inability to convert local currency&#13;
into the currency in which the debt is denominated).&#13;
Down Payments - Buyers receiving export credit support are&#13;
obliged to make payments prior to shipment.   Currently they amount to&#13;
about 15 per cent of the contract value, to be paid either at the time&#13;
of contract signing or during the course of manufacture.&#13;
Commitment - A contract or agreement representing a firm&#13;
obligation to provide funds. The term "authorization" is used&#13;
interchangeably with commitment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
Disbursement - The actual international transfer of funds. In&#13;
practice, the disbursement of funds can occur a number of years after&#13;
the funds are committed and can occur in several installments.&#13;
Exchange Risk Insurance - Insurance covering exporters against&#13;
losses which may be incurred when the contract payment is denominated in&#13;
a foreign currency and that currency depreciates relative to the&#13;
domestic currency.&#13;
Export Credits - Loans directly tied to exports and ranging in&#13;
maturity from under 90 days to extended terms of 10 years and more.&#13;
Short-term credits (often termed "trade credits") are generally&#13;
interpreted as those under 180 days and receive little or no support&#13;
from governments, with the important exception of insurance protection&#13;
against political and commercial risks. Medium-term credits have a&#13;
maturity of up to five years, while long-term credits refer to&#13;
maturities of over five years.&#13;
Forfaiting - The purchase (discounting) of buyer notes from an&#13;
exporter, with the assumption of the credit risk on the notes by the&#13;
purchasing institution.&#13;
Grace Periods - Export credits do not have explicit grace&#13;
periods, since the term of the credit is calculated from the delivery of&#13;
the goods or from the date of project completion. In general, buyers&#13;
must make the first principal payment within six months, and subsequent&#13;
payments in equal semi-annual installments.&#13;
Grant Element - A measure of the subsidy component ("conces-&#13;
sionality") of a loan. It is defined as the difference between the face&#13;
value of the loan and the present value of the stream of repayments on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
that loan (discounted at the market rate), expressed as a percentage of&#13;
the face value. Thus, a loan made at market rates has a zero grant&#13;
element, while a grant - a loan made at zero percent interest with an&#13;
infinite maturity -- has a 100 percent grant element.&#13;
Guarantee - A type of insurance offered to financial institu-&#13;
tions that issue export credits covering both political and commercial&#13;
risks of non-payment by the buyer.&#13;
Inflation Risk Insurance - Insurance covering exporters against&#13;
domestic cost increases on capital goods and projects occurring during a&#13;
lengthy production period.&#13;
Insurance - Insurance is offered to exporters who lend to&#13;
importers directly and covers both political and commercial risks of&#13;
non-payment by the buyer. The term is often used interchangeably with&#13;
guarantees.&#13;
Local Cost Support - Support for costs associated with an&#13;
export transaction incurred in the currency of the importer. Export&#13;
credit support is normally limited to the foreign exchange costs&#13;
involved. However, export credit agencies sometimes provide insurance&#13;
and financing for up to 15 percent of the local or on-site costs&#13;
associated with the export contract.&#13;
Mixed Credits - The combination of government foreign aid funds&#13;
with official export credits to produce concessional financing packages&#13;
having a grant element between official export credits and official&#13;
development assistance (ODA).&#13;
Official Development Assistance (ODA) - The OECD defines ODA as&#13;
funds provided for the promotion of economic development in recipient&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
countries that contain at least a 25 percent grant element. ODA is&#13;
theoretically distinct from official export credits, which are provided&#13;
for the purchase of exports from the donor country and carry a grant&#13;
element of generally less than 5 percent. The increased use of mixed&#13;
credit financing has blurred the distinction between ODA and export&#13;
credits.&#13;
Official Export Credits - Credits extended directly by some&#13;
governments either to their own exporters or to foreign buyers, often in&#13;
association with private financing, to support export transactions&#13;
requiring long maturities and large amounts of credit. Both in purpose&#13;
and in the nature of the terms provided, official export credits are&#13;
generally equivalent to private buyer credits supported with preferen-&#13;
tial refinancing and interest subsidies by governments.&#13;
Political Risk - The risk of borrower country government&#13;
actions which prevent, or delay, the repayment of export credits. Such&#13;
actions presuppose that the importer has deposited on time the amounts&#13;
due in local currency. Many export credit insurance agencies also&#13;
include under political risk such events as war, revolution, or other&#13;
military-civil disturbances which prevent or delay contractual&#13;
payments. Some also include physical disasters such as cyclones, floods&#13;
or earthquakes.&#13;
Sovereign Risk - See political risk.&#13;
Supplier Credits - Export credits extended by a supplier&#13;
(exporter) to a foreign buyer (importer) for, typically, maturities of&#13;
up to five years. Supplier credits normally finance the bulk of manu-&#13;
factured exports outside of capital goods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
APPENDIX F&#13;
DATA ON OFFICIAL EXPORT CREDITS&#13;
(1) Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development&#13;
The Development Assistance Committee (DAC) of the OECD collects&#13;
information on transfers of long-term financial resources from DAC&#13;
member countries to developing countries. DAC reports data for&#13;
officially-supported export credits comprising directly-extended&#13;
official export credits and officially insured or guaranteed private&#13;
export credits. Guaranteed private export credits, in turn, include&#13;
financial credits and supplier credits. Supplier credits are private&#13;
export credits extended by an exporter. Financial credits refer to&#13;
credits by a bank or other financial institution extended to a foreign&#13;
buyer. Included under guaranteed private export credits are credits on&#13;
which an export creditor receives official support, including&#13;
discounting of an export credit at preferential terms by an official&#13;
agency or provision of a subsidy to an export creditor to reduce the&#13;
interest rate charged by him to the borrower.&#13;
Data reporting procedures raise problems in calculating the&#13;
subsidy. When official support for export credits takes forms other&#13;
than direct credits (e.g. - the United Kingdom's interest make-up scheme&#13;
or France's rediscounting facilities), program activities show up in&#13;
data for guaranteed private export credits. As a result, while OECD&#13;
data permit deriving figures on total officially supported export&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
credits, they do not permit isolating those programs equivalent to the&#13;
direct loan program of the U.S. Eximbank.&#13;
The OECD Trade Committee's Group on Exports Credits and Credit&#13;
Guarantees also collects data on officially-supported export credits.&#13;
These data do not, however, differentiate among types of systems used to&#13;
support export credits and, therefore, do not permit breaking out the&#13;
equivalent of direct loan programs only.&#13;
(2) World Bank&#13;
Under the Debtor Reporting System (DRS), the World Bank&#13;
collects information on the external debt of developing economies that&#13;
have received either IBRD loans or IDA credits. Countries report&#13;
changes in their long-term external public and publicly-guaranteed debt&#13;
to the DRS. For the World Debt Tables, several other sources supplement&#13;
these data, including the OECD's Creditor Reporting System (CRS) and the&#13;
World Bank's Capital Markets System (CMS). Available data on private&#13;
debt without public guarantees are also included. The data are broken&#13;
down by official and private creditors. Officially-extended buyer&#13;
export credits can be identified for the United States, Germany, Japan&#13;
and Canada. As with the OECD data, however, credits receiving support&#13;
through refinancing at preferential rates or interest rate make-up&#13;
schemes are included in private-source loans and cannot be distinguished&#13;
from other private credits.&#13;
(3) Berne Union&#13;
The Berne Union (The International Union of Credit and&#13;
Investment Insurers) collects data on export credit insurance and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
guarantees issued 35 export credit and insurance agencies from 27&#13;
countries.&#13;
Berne Union data cover commitments and offers. Commitments are&#13;
export credits for which insurance or guarantees have been issued by&#13;
Berne Union member agencies. They are reported on an outstanding basis,&#13;
net of repayments, and include undisbursed amounts. Commitments are&#13;
broken into short-term credits and payments due on an annual basis.&#13;
Offers, reported separately, are potential export credits which have not&#13;
yet reached the contract stage and for which insurance and guarantees&#13;
have not been issued. The Berne Union presents data organized by&#13;
recipient country, and by Berne Union member agency, updated on a&#13;
quarterly basis.&#13;
Commitments include supplier credits extended directly by the&#13;
exporter (which are said to be "insured") and buyer credits or financial&#13;
credits extended by private banks (which are said to be "guaranteed").&#13;
Commitments also include export credits extended directly by two member&#13;
agencies, the U.S. Eximbank and Canada's EDC. Berne Union data also&#13;
indirectly include official export credit support supplied by the&#13;
remaining five countries discussed in the paper (Germany, France, Italy,&#13;
Japan and the United Kingdom), since each country requires insurance or&#13;
guarantees for official support. The Berne Union data as reported&#13;
cannot, however, be used as reported to calculate the subsidy element on&#13;
direct official export credits; although they include such credits, they&#13;
are aggregated with other export credits for which insurance and&#13;
guarantees have been issued by Berne Union member agencies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
(4) Export-Import Bank of the United States&#13;
The Export-Import Bank of the United States submits a semi-&#13;
annual report to Congress on competition in the provision of officially&#13;
supported export credit and financing ("Report to the U.S. Congress on&#13;
Export Credit Competition and the Export-Import Bank of the United&#13;
States"). Until recently, data on official export credit financing&#13;
programs were reported for the seven countries considered in this&#13;
paper. Financing programs include both direct credits, such as those&#13;
extended by the U.S. Eximbank and Canada's EDC, and refinancing&#13;
facilities and interest rate subsidy programs (programs comparable to&#13;
direct export credits).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
FOOTNOTES&#13;
1   Governments also subsidize exports through loan insurance and&#13;
guarantee programs, when they sell insurance and guarantees at prices&#13;
below their true market value. When a government guarantees or insures&#13;
a loan made to finance an export, it creates a financial instrument&#13;
against which the lending institution, either a bank or an exporter, can&#13;
borrow at rates close to the government borrowing rate. The potential&#13;
profit on a guaranteed or insured loan to the lender equals the rate at&#13;
which the importer could have borrowed in the private market without&#13;
insurance or a guarantee, and the rate at which the lender can borrow&#13;
against the guaranteed loan, minus any insurance or guarantee fees.&#13;
All of the countries considered have institutions that extend export&#13;
credit insurance or guarantees. Through these institutions the&#13;
government assumes a large proportion of the credit risk on loans to&#13;
foreign buyers. Although the subsidy element on an insured or&#13;
guaranteed loan is generally smaller than on a directly supported export&#13;
credit, there are about three times more insured or guaranteed export&#13;
credits outstanding than direct loans. Therefore, the total subsidy on&#13;
such programs may still be substantial.&#13;
2   We assume that the borrower alternatively could borrow at the market&#13;
rate in the same currency as the subsidized export credit. Following&#13;
sections discuss problems with this assumption in greater detail.&#13;
3   J. H. Boyd (Boyd 1982) defines subsidy in this way, while R. E.&#13;
Feinberg (Feinberg 1982) discusses three estimates of this concept of&#13;
the subsidy. Boyd estimated the present value of the interest subsidy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
on loans authorized by the Eximbank for each year between 1976 and&#13;
1980. He took into consideration variations in the repayment schedules&#13;
of Eximbank loans over time and attempted to calculate the appropriate&#13;
discount rate. Rather than deriving the discount rate directly from the&#13;
rates charged in the private market for comparable loans, Boyd estimated&#13;
what the marginal cost of Eximbank's capital would have been had&#13;
Eximbank been a private financial intermediary; Boyd used this rate as a&#13;
proxy for the appropriate private market discount rate.&#13;
Feinberg reviews three estimates of the interest subsidy implicit in&#13;
the Eximbank's authorizations in a given year: Those of the U.S. Office&#13;
of Management and Budget, the Joint Economic Committee of the U.S.&#13;
Congress, and J. Hovarth (Hovarth 1975). All three estimates were based&#13;
on the present discounted value technique. They differ in their&#13;
consideration of such things as average maturity and grace periods of&#13;
loans. In all three cases, estimates employ a single discount rate to&#13;
represent the equivalent rate on private market loans.&#13;
4 A 50-basis points spread probably underestimates the cost of export&#13;
credit, particularly to developing countries. If the spread is&#13;
increased to 200 basis points, the estimate of the subsidy increases&#13;
from $3.5 billion to $4.5 bilion and most of the entries in the table&#13;
turn positive.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
Table 8 : ESTIMATE OF THE SUBSIDY WHEN BORROWERS ALTERNATIVE&#13;
IS A FLOATING-RATE LOAN ($Million)&#13;
200 Basis Points&#13;
1976      1977       1978       1979       1980&#13;
Canada                     7.1        5.3      164.9     207.9      344.6&#13;
France                     n.a.       n.a.    359.5      564.8      955.2&#13;
Germany                  -41.0      -24.4     -72.3         4.5       84.7&#13;
Italy                    197.4      164.7     116.5      129.3      257.4&#13;
Japan                    200.7       96.9     -75.9        57.2     630.4&#13;
United Kingdom           325.1      132.5     234.5      669.9   1,002.8&#13;
United States             76.0      128.2      362.3      723.3   1,199.2&#13;
Total                 765.3      503.2   1,089.5   2,356.9   4,474.3&#13;
We might calculate the subsidy more accurately by using&#13;
available data on the actual risk premia that borrowers receiving&#13;
officially subsidized export credit pay in the private market. If most&#13;
borrowers pay a higher spread than we have assumed, or if some borrowers&#13;
receiving subsidized export credits are not creditworthy enough to&#13;
borrow in the private market, then we have underestimated the actual&#13;
subsidy.&#13;
5   Currently, we do not have data on the geographic distribution of&#13;
direct and subsidized loan programs. We assumed, therefore, that such&#13;
programs were distributed geographically in the same pattern as the sum&#13;
of direct and subsidized loan programs and guarantee programs. In&#13;
addition, no information was available on the geographic distribution of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
Canadian official export credits. We assumed, therefore, that it&#13;
equaled the average of the other lending countries.&#13;
6   We thank Robert Lawrence for suggesting this extension to us.&#13;
7   If private citizens and the government choose additional consumption&#13;
and investment expenditures so that the returns on those expenditures&#13;
equaled those on additional investment projects, the cost of the&#13;
additional exports to society would be the same whether investment,&#13;
consumption or government expenditure is displaced.&#13;
8   We thank Helen Hughes for bringing this point to our attention and&#13;
Ernst Lutz for providing the trade data.&#13;
9   In the United States, the evidence suggests that export credits have&#13;
not been used countercyclically. Instead, direct loan authorizations&#13;
have been high when unemployment has been low.&#13;
10 The original impetus for the formation of the Eximbank arose in such&#13;
a situation. The Eximbank was set up during President Franklin D.&#13;
Roosevelt's administration to finance trade with the Soviet Union. The&#13;
administration viewed opening diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union&#13;
as an important political objective. At the same time, it wished to&#13;
alleviate the constricting effects that the 1931 Hawley-Smoot Tariff had&#13;
on trade and to promote exports as a means of increasing domestic&#13;
employment. Since the economy was in a depression, these were all&#13;
important policy objectives. The Soviet Union, unlike many other&#13;
countries, was agreeable to increasing imports at that point.&#13;
At the same time, the private market was unlikely to finance trade&#13;
with the Soviets. The lack of diplomatic recognition had slowed the&#13;
development of commercial ties, and unofficial State Department policy,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
together with the Johnson Debt Default Act, operated to block loans to&#13;
countries that had defaulted on war debts. Unlike the present&#13;
situation, there was much evidence then to support the view that the&#13;
private market would not have lent sufficiently to secure the side-&#13;
effects that were considered desirable on political and economic&#13;
grounds.&#13;
Similarly, after World War II, when the U.S. government viewed the&#13;
level of private lending to Europe as insufficient to prevent economic&#13;
difficulties and consequent political disorder that could have seriously&#13;
compromised the NATO alliance, the Eximbank was one of the institutions&#13;
used to channel government loans to Europe.&#13;
11 Aircraft producers receive one of the largest shares of official&#13;
export lending. Military considerations do not generally govern such&#13;
loans, though. Subsidized loans are made for civilian aircraft that are&#13;
generally not used by the military. In the United States, for example,&#13;
most military airframes are made by other companies, and when the&#13;
government finance sales of those planes, it does so with loans from&#13;
other programs. Indeed, Appendix II, Section 5 of the Export-Import&#13;
Bank Act of 1945, as amended through November 10, 1978, states that the&#13;
"Bank shall not: extend loans, guarantees, or insurance under this Act in&#13;
connection with the sale of defense articles or defense services."&#13;
12 In several special cases paying an export subsidy, as compared to&#13;
levying a tariff or doing nothing, may increase domestic welfare. When&#13;
domestic product markets are imperfectly competitive, and producers sell&#13;
in both the home and foreign markets, an export subsidy rather than a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
tariff may increase domestic welfare. For example, if a domestic mono-&#13;
polist has a decreasing marginal cost curve, an export subsidy will lead&#13;
to increased output and lower average costs. If the monopolist can dis-&#13;
criminate between the domestic and foreign markets, the falling marginal&#13;
cost of total output will lead the monopolist to reduce prices in the&#13;
domestic market and increase the welfare of domestic consumers. The&#13;
optimal export subsidy will balance the cost of the subsidy against the&#13;
increased consumer surplus. Even if the monopolist cannot discriminate&#13;
between the two markets, an export subsidy may increase welfare under&#13;
certain elasticities of demand in the home and foreign markets (Auquier&#13;
and Caves 1979).&#13;
These results do raise the possibility that policymakers, in struc-&#13;
turing an export credit subsidy program, could identify industries with&#13;
increasing returns, or base subsidies on different home and foreign&#13;
demand conditions.&#13;
However, two serious problems greatly weaken this case for export&#13;
subsidization: first, the argument artificially restricts policymakers'&#13;
choices, thereby neglecting the even superior welfare outcome that the&#13;
subsidizing government could achieve by simply regulating the home&#13;
monopolist's home market price; and second, the rise in the monopolist's&#13;
real output that contributes to the rise in home welfare must, under&#13;
full employment, incur costs that reduce other output whose loss is not&#13;
accounted for in the calculation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
BIBLIOGRAPHY&#13;
Auquier, A.A. and R.E. Caves, 1979. Monopolistic export industries,&#13;
trade taxes, and optimal competition policy. The Economic&#13;
Journal. 89: 559-581.&#13;
Bank for International Settlements. 1969. Export credit insurance and&#13;
export credit. Volume 1: Country studies. Basle: Bank for&#13;
International Settlements.&#13;
Basevi, G. 1970. Domestic demand and ability to export. Journal of&#13;
Political Economy. 78: 330-7.&#13;
Boyd, J. H. 1982. Eximbank lending: A federal program that costs too&#13;
much. Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis Quarterly Review (Winter&#13;
1982).&#13;
Cizauskas, Alber C. 1980. The changing nature of export credit finance&#13;
and its implications for the developing countries. World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 409. Washington, D.C.: The World Bank.&#13;
Export-Import Bank of the United States. Various years. Report to the&#13;
U.S. Congress on export credit competition and the Export-Import&#13;
Bank of the United States. Washington, D.C.: Export-Import Bank of&#13;
the United States.&#13;
. 1981. Trends in export credits among major competitors.&#13;
Policy Analysis Staff Report. Mimeographed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
_   Various years.  Annual report of the Export-Import Bank of the&#13;
United States. Washington, D.C.: Export-Import Bank of the United&#13;
States.&#13;
Feinberg, R. E. 1982. Subsidizing success, the Export-Import Bank in&#13;
the U.S. economy. Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press.&#13;
Fry, Richard. Various years. Export Finance Service. The Banker&#13;
Research Unit Annual Report. London: The Banker Research Unit.&#13;
______. 1979. Competition in Export Credit Terms. The Banker&#13;
(August) 65-71.&#13;
Hovarth, J. 1975. Are Eximbank credits subsidized: toward an&#13;
empirical analysis. In Marer, Paul, ed. U.S. financing of East-West&#13;
Trade. Indiana University.&#13;
Midland Bank. 1980. Export credit facilities: An international&#13;
comparison. Midland Bank Review (Autumn): 20-29.&#13;
Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development. 1982. The&#13;
export credit financing systems in OECD member countries.  Paris:&#13;
Director of Information, OECD.&#13;
_   Various years.  OECD Financial Statistics.  Tome I - Tables.&#13;
Paris: OECD.&#13;
_  1980.  Arrangement on guidelines for officially supported&#13;
export credits - interest rate study. Report by Axel Wallen to the&#13;
OECD Trade Directorate. Paris: OECD.&#13;
Stern, Robert M., Francis, Jonathan, and Schumacher, Bruce. 1976.&#13;
Price elasticities in international trade. London: The Macmillan&#13;
Press Ltd.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
United States. Congress. House of Representatives. Subcommitee on&#13;
International Trade, Investment and Monetary Policy of the Committee&#13;
on Banking Finance and Urban Affairs. 1981. The benefits and costs&#13;
of the Export-Import Bank loan subsidy program. 97 Cong., First&#13;
session, March 5, 12, 17, 18; and April 28, 1981.&#13;
U.S. Federal Reserve System. 1982. Federal Reserve Bulletin 68 (1):&#13;
A68. Washington, D.C.: Publications Services of the Federal&#13;
Reserve System.&#13;
___.  19130.  Annual Statistical Digest, 1974-1978.  Washington,&#13;
D.C.: Publications Services of the Federal Reserve System, p. 248.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank                                 The Developing Countries and    Export Promotion Policies&#13;
International Shipping                    Barend A. de Vries&#13;
FUbft atiolM                               Harald Hansen                             Staff Working Paper No. 313. 1979. 80&#13;
of Related                                 Staff Working Paper No. 502. 1981. 151    pages    W&#13;
pages (including 12 annexes, 38 tables,   Stock No. WP 0313. S3&#13;
Interest                                   bibliography).&#13;
Stock No. WP 0502. $5.&#13;
NEW&#13;
Exports of Capital Goods and&#13;
NEW                                   Related Services from the&#13;
Republic of Korea&#13;
Economics and the Politics of             Larry E. Westphal, Yung W. Rhee,&#13;
Protection: Some Case Studies             Linsu Kim, Alice Amsden&#13;
Adjustment to External Shocks              of Industries                             Examines Korea's spectacular export&#13;
in Developing Economies                   Vincent Cable                              growth-from $50 million of goods in&#13;
Bela Balassa                               Looks at factors which effect an indus-   1962 to $25 billion in 1982. Five kinds&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 472. 1981. 31      try's attitude toward protection by       of project-related exports are character-&#13;
pages (including appendix).                analyzing four of Great Britain's indus-  ized (overseas construction, plant ex-&#13;
Stock No. WP 0472. $3.                    tries: footwear, knutwear, cutlery, and    ports, direc investments, consulting&#13;
consumer electronics. Case studies ex-    services, licensing and technical agree-&#13;
Adjustmnent Policies and            -      amine import competition from devel-      ments). Discusses the role of these ex-&#13;
Adjustment Policiesg ounris ad  djutmntd,-ports in Korea's strategy for develop-&#13;
Problems in Developed Countries            tions exercised within each industry.     ment. Shows how these strategies&#13;
Martin Wolf                                Study includes some explanations for      conform to the country's dynamic&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 349. 1979. 236     protectionist behavior among indus-       comparative advantage by enlarging its&#13;
pages (including references).             tries and a discussion of the politics of  idustnal base.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0349. $10.                   uecisionmaking in regard to trade pol-     Staff Working Paper No. 629. 2983. 80&#13;
icY.                                      pages.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 569. 1983. 80     ISBN 0-8213-0310-4.Stock No. WP 0629.&#13;
Britain's Pattern-of                      pages.                                     $3.&#13;
Specialization in Manufactured            ISBN 08213-0199-3.Stock No. WP 0569.       On Exports and Economic&#13;
Goods with Developing                     $3.                                        Growth&#13;
Countries and Trade Protection                                                       Gershon Feder&#13;
Vincent Cable and Ivonia Rebelo            Effects of Non-Tarff Barers               Staff Working Paper No. 508. 1982. 24&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 425. 1980. 61      to Trade on Prices,                       pages (including appendix, references).&#13;
pages (including 3 appendixa).             Employment, and Imports: The              Stock No. WP 0508. $3.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0425. $3.                     Case of the Swedish Textile&#13;
and Clothing Industry                     India's Exports&#13;
Carl Hamilton                             Martin Wolf&#13;
NEW                                    Staff Working Paper No. 429. 1980. 63     Despite improved performance, the&#13;
pages (including appendix, bibliography).  growth of India's exports continues to&#13;
Bureaucracies and the Political            Stock No. WP 0429. $3.                    lag behind need, potential, and the&#13;
achievements of several of its competi-&#13;
Economy of Protection:                                                               tors. 1his study examines India's over-&#13;
Reflections of a Continental               Energy, International Trade,              all export performance in the 1960s&#13;
European                                   and Economic Growth                       and 1970s, with emphasis on the cen-&#13;
Patrick Messerlin                          Alan S. Manne and Sehun Kim               tral role of incentives. The mapor prob-&#13;
Analyzes three factors that influence      Staff Working Paper No. 474. 1981. 30     lems and policies are discussed, as&#13;
the "bureaus" (bureaucrats) in their       pages (including 2 appendixes, references).  wel as current strategic options.&#13;
decisions affecting protectionism in       Stock No. WP 0474 S3                      Oxford University Press. 1982. 224 pages&#13;
France.                                                                              (including index).&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 568. 1983. 64                                                LC 82-6309. ISBN 0-19-520211-2. Stock&#13;
paged.                                                           .No. OX 520211, $22.50 hardcover. (A&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-198-5. Stock No. WP 0568.      European Community                        specially priced edition is available in India&#13;
S3.                                        Protection against                        from Oxford University Press branches.)&#13;
Manufactured Imports from&#13;
Capital-Importing Oil                      Developing Countries: A Case              Industrial Country Policy and&#13;
Exporters: Adjustment Issues               Study in the Political Economy            Adjustment to Imports from&#13;
and Policy Choices                         of Protection                             Developing Countries&#13;
Alan H. Gelb                               E. Verreydt and J. Waelbroeck             J. M. Finger&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 475. 2981. 38      Staff Working Paper No. 432. 1980. 25     Staff Working Paper No. 470. 1981. 22&#13;
pages (including 9 tables).                pages.                                    pages (including references).&#13;
;tock No. WP 0475. $3.                    Stock No. WP 0432. $3.                     Stock No. WP 0470. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Italian Commercial Policies in             in the EEC markets but have less effect       NEW&#13;
the 1970s                                  in keeping out non-EEC imports.                       -&#13;
Enzo R. Grill                              Staff Working Paper No. 567. 1983. 48     Real Wages and Exchange&#13;
Staff Working Paper No&amp;. 428. 1980. 47     pages.                                    Rates in the Philippines, 1956-&#13;
pages.                                     ISBN 0-8213-0197-7. Stock No. WP 0567     78: An Application of the&#13;
Stock No. WP 0428. $3.                                                               Stolper-Samuelson-Rybczynski&#13;
Output and Employment                     Model of Trade&#13;
Changes in a "Trade Sensitive"            Deepak Lal&#13;
NEW                                   Sector Adjustment in the U.S.              Explains the movements of real wages&#13;
Footwear Industry                         in the Philippines in termns of a simple&#13;
Korea's Competitive Edge:                  John H. Mutti and Malcolm D.              regression model. Examines the coun-&#13;
try's postwar economic performance&#13;
Managing Entry into World                  Bale                                      and draws some tentative conclusions&#13;
Markets                                    Staff Working Paper No. 430. 1980. 21     for economic policy.&#13;
Yung Whee Rhee, Bruce Ross-                pages (including footnotes, references).  Staff Working Paper No. 604. 1983. 60&#13;
~rson, and GalTy PursellStock No. WP 0430. $3.&#13;
Larson, and Garry Pursefl                                      ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~pages.&#13;
How did Korea manage to expand its         Pattems of Barriers to Trade in           ISBN 0-8213-0213-2. Stock No. WP 06(4.&#13;
exports from less than $100 million a      Sweden: A Study in the                    $3.&#13;
year in the early 1960s to more thanSwdnASty,ith&#13;
$20 billion a vear in the early 1980s?     Theory of Protection                      Shadow Prices for Trade&#13;
To find out about the underpinnings        Lars Lundberg                             Strategy and Investment&#13;
of Korea's competitive edge, the au-       Staff Working Paper No. 494, 1981. 35     Planning in Egypt&#13;
thors asked more than 100 major Ko-        pages (including 3 appendixes).           John Page, Jr.&#13;
rean exporters what had been impor-        Stock No. WP 0494. $3.                              g&#13;
tant for them in institutional support,                                               Sff Working Paper No. 521. 1982. 212&#13;
in technological development, and in       The Political Economy of                  pages.&#13;
marketing overseas. The findings           Protection in Belgium                      ISBN 0-8213-0009-1. Stock No. WP 0521.&#13;
show that there is a strong interaction    P.K.M. TharaSn                             $10.&#13;
between exporting and the effective-       Staff Workan&#13;
ness of a country's economic institu-      Staff Working Paper No. 431, 1980. 22      Structural Change in Trade in&#13;
tions, both public and private. Without    pages (including statistical appendix, refer-  Manufactured Goods between&#13;
effective institutions, a country may      ences).                                    Industrial and Developing&#13;
not be able to implement effective pol-     OC N.          .                          Countries&#13;
icies for export promotion. Conversely,&#13;
successful exporting appears to give       The Political Market for                   Bela Balassa&#13;
economic institutions more vitality and    Protection in Industrial                   Staff Working Paper No. 396. 1980. 46&#13;
effectiveness. The findings also show      Countries: Empirical Evidence              pages.&#13;
how Korea's selectivity-in the acqui-      Kym Anderson and Robert E.                 Stock No. WP 0396. $3.&#13;
sition of technology and in the mnarket-   Baldwin&#13;
ing of products overseas-has been an       Staff Working Paper Nlo. 492. 1981. 28         NEW_&#13;
important part of Korea's success in       pages (including references).&#13;
the world marketplace.                     Stock No. WP 0492. $3.                    TCme  tructure of Intem     etional&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press. June                                              Competitiveness in the Federal&#13;
1984. About 204 pages.                     On Protectionism  in the                   Republic of Germany: An&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-3266-7. $19.95.                Netherlands                                Appraisal&#13;
K.A. Koekkoek, J. Kol, and L.B.M.         Frank D. Weiss&#13;
On the Political Economy of                Mennes                                    Probes the comparative trade advan-&#13;
Protection in Germany                      Staff Working Paper No. 493. 1981. 70     tage of the Federal Republic of Ger-&#13;
H. H. Glismann and F. D. Weiss             pages (including 3 annexes, references).  many in the 1980s with surprising con-&#13;
Staff  orkin Pape No. 47. 190. 30Stock No. WP 0493. $3.                    clusiorns: developing countries uire&#13;
Staff WN'orking Paper No. 427. 1980. 30    Stock No. WP 0493 $3.competitive with the Federai Republic&#13;
pages (including bbliography).                                                        of Germrany in a far wider range of&#13;
Stock No. WP 0427. $3.                         NEW                                   products than had been previously&#13;
Public Assistanlce to Inldustries         thought. Suggests probable trends, es-&#13;
Public Asistaite to Inusth'es  pecially towz,rdI developing countries.&#13;
NEW                                    and Trade Policy in France                Concludes that the faster income in&#13;
Bemard Bobe                               developing countries gnrws, the faster&#13;
The Political Economy of                   Describes the institutional structure     these countries will become competi-&#13;
Protection in Italy: Some                  through which trade police is deter-       tive in an even wider wange of goods.&#13;
Empirical Evidence                         mined. Focuses on the evolution of         innovation, though a key factor, can&#13;
Enzo Grilli and Mauro La Noce              France's international commerce in the    not determine comparative aevantage,&#13;
1970s and assesses probable trends for    because innovations spread rapidly&#13;
This analysis is based on a model that     the future.                               through the wold economy.&#13;
specifies the demand side of the mar-                                                      -&#13;
ket. Examines 35 industrial subsectors     Staff Working Paper No. 570. 1933. 64     Staf 'Working Paper No. 571. 1983. 84&#13;
in terms of EEC tariff protection and      pages.                                    pages.&#13;
Italy s domestic subsidy assistance.       ISBN 0-8213-0200-0. Stock No. WP 0570.    ISBN 0.8213-0201-9. Stock No. W' P 0571.&#13;
Finds that tarnffs protect Italian exports  $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Structure of Protection in            Trade and Employment                     Why the Emperor's New&#13;
Developing Countries                      Policies for Industrial                  Clothes Are Not Made in&#13;
Bela Balassa and others                   Development                              Colombia: A Case Study in&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1971,  Keith Marsden                           Latin American and East Asian&#13;
394 pages (induding 5 appendixes, index).  In the last decade, the developing      Manufactured Exports&#13;
LC 77-147366. ISBN 0-8018-1257-7, Stock   countries have proved that they can      David Morawetz&#13;
No. JH 1257. $25 hardcover.               compete internationally in exporting     Focuses on the exports of a particular&#13;
manufactured goods, as well as pri-      commodity (clothing) from a particular&#13;
mary products and services. This pa-     Latin American country (Colombia) in&#13;
per examines three sets of issues: (a)   an attempt to understand why Latin&#13;
Testing for Direction of                  whether good export performance is        America has been so much less suc-&#13;
Exports: India's Exports of               attributable to special characteristics of  cessful at exporting manufactured&#13;
Manufactures in the 1970s                 the most successful countries or          goods to date than East Asia. It is the&#13;
Ashok KhJ'~anna                           whether their success can be readily     first study to go into great detail in ex-&#13;
Ashok Khanna                  ~~~~~replicated in other countries; (i')   amining the price~, and esoecially the&#13;
Tests the hypothesis that the exports     whether the penetration of the mar-       nonprice, deterninants 0 export suc-&#13;
of a developing country with an ad-       kets of industrial countries has          cess.                   epr&#13;
vanced manufacturing sector will differ   reached, or will soon reach, a limit;     Oxford University Press, 1981. 208 pages&#13;
among destinations: the capital inten-    and (c) whether trade in manufactures     (including appendiPes, bibliography).&#13;
sity of exports will be greater to the    among the developing countries can&#13;
more labor abundant destinations, and     expand further. Concludes with a dis-     LC 81-9547, ISBN 0-19-520283-X, Stock&#13;
the labor intensity of export will be     cussion of the contribution of small      No. OX 520283, $22 hardcover.&#13;
greater to the more capital abundant      enterprises to the creation of employ-    Worker Adjustment to&#13;
destinations. India's exports of manu-    ment and the alleviation of poverty.      Liberalized Trade: Costs and&#13;
factures for 1973 and 1978 are used for   1982. 70 pages (including annex).         Assistance Policies&#13;
the analysis.                             ISBN 0-8213-0017-2. Stock No. BK 0017.    Graham Glenday, Glenn P.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 538. 1983. 41 ge.                                           Jenkins, and John C. Evans&#13;
lSBN 0-8213. 132-2 Stock No. WP 0538.                                               Staff Working Paper No. 426. 1980. 87&#13;
$3.                                       Trade in Non-Factor Services:             pages (including 2 appendixes, bibliog-&#13;
Past Trends and Current Issues           raphy().&#13;
Andre Sapir and Ernst Lutz               Stock No. WP 0426. $3.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 410. 1980. 140   World Trade and Output of&#13;
The Tokyo Round: Results and              pages (including 4 annexes).              Manufactures: Structural&#13;
Implications for Developing               Stock No. WP 0410. $5.                    Trends and Developing&#13;
Countries                                                                           Countries' Exports&#13;
Ria Kemper                                Trade in Services: Economic               Donald B. Keesing&#13;
Staff Wlorking Paper No. 372. 1980. 38    Determinants and                          Staff Working Paper No. 316. 1979.&#13;
pages (including annex).                  Develo pment-Related Issues               74 pages (including statistical annex).&#13;
Stock No. WP 072. $3.         AndreSapir and Ernst Lutz                Stock No. WP 0316. $3.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 480. 1981. 38    Trends in International Trade&#13;
pages (including appendix, references).  in Manufactured Goods and&#13;
Trade Adjustment Policies and             Stock No. WP 0480. $3.                    Structural Change in the&#13;
Income Distribution in Three                                                        Industrial Countries&#13;
Income Distribution in Three                                                       Bela Balassa with the assistance of&#13;
Archetype Developing                      Trade Policy for Developing               Kenneth Meyers&#13;
Economies                                 Countries                                 Exanines recent trends in trade in&#13;
Jaime de Melo and Sherman                 Donald B. Keesing                         manufactured goods between the in-&#13;
Robinson                                  World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 353,   dustrial and the developing countries.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 442. '980. 91     August 1979, vii + 264 pages (including   Analyzes (a) the implications of these&#13;
pages (including appendixes, references).  references)                             trends for structural change in the in-&#13;
Stock No. WP 0442. $3.                    Stock No p P@353 S10                      dustrial countries and (b) changes over&#13;
Stock No. WP-0353. $10.                  time in the current dollar value and&#13;
the commodity composition of trade in&#13;
-                        Trade Policy Issues for the               manufactured goods. Recommends&#13;
Trade among Developing                    Developing Countries in the               tepoatic a c geadeiamed at promoting n&#13;
Countries: Theory, Policy                 1980s                                     change&#13;
Issues, and Principal Trends              Isaiah Frank                              Staff Working PanrNe.. 611. 1983. 44&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 479. 7981. 116    World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 478.  pages.&#13;
pages (including 2 appendixes, references).  August 1981. 52 pages.                 ISBN 0-8213-0251-5.Stock No. WP 0611.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0479. $5.                    Stock No. WP-0478. S3.                   $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of this form.)        P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                               Name&#13;
Firm                                                Title&#13;
Address                                             Firm&#13;
City              State_      Postal Code           Address&#13;
Country            T'elephone (    I                City             State_      Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                             Country      _      Thlephone (     )&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my O1 Check OI International Money Order O Unesco Coupons O International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my El VISA El MasterCard [lAmerican Express L Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                    Signature&#13;
O Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Intenal&#13;
Stock Number  Authorl Title                                     Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price   Total Amount $&#13;
All prices subject to change. Prices may vary by country. Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
'Ibtal copies     Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 eachl  $S -&#13;
'Ibtal  $&#13;
IBRD053                                                          Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World                   INDONESIA                                Attn: Mr. J.M. Hernandez&#13;
Pt. Indira Limited                      Castello 37&#13;
Bank Publications                       Attn: Mr. Bambang Wahyudi                Madrid&#13;
JI, Dr. Sam Ratulangi No. 37            SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                           Lake House Bookshop&#13;
ARGENTINA                               IRELAND                                  Attn: Mr. Victor Walatara&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL,                     TDC Publishers                           41 Wad Ramanayake Mawatha&#13;
Attn: Ms. Monica Bustos                 Attn: Mr. James Booth                    Colombo 2&#13;
Florida 165 4 piso                     12 North Frederick Street                SWEDEN&#13;
GaBena Guemes                           Dublin 1                                 ABCE Fritzes Kungi, Hovbokhandel&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                       JAPAN                                   Attn: Mr. Eide Segerback&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW GUINEA,    Eastem Book Servce                              Regening t  12, Box 16356&#13;
Attn: Mr. Terumasa Hirano                       san&#13;
FIJI, SOLOMON ISLANDS,                  Atn   r  euaaHrn                         -0  7Stockholmr&#13;
WESTERN SAMOA, AND                      37-3, Hongo 3-Chome, Bunkyo-ku 113      SWITZERLAND&#13;
VANUATU                                 Tokyo                                   Librainie Payot&#13;
The Australian Financial Review         Tokyo                                     brairie Payrt&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)             KENYA                                    Attn: Mr. Henri de Perrot&#13;
Attn: Mr. David Jamieson                Africa Book Services (E.A.) Ltd.        6, rue Grenus&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                    Attn: Mr. M.B. Dar                      1211 Geneva&#13;
Broadway                                P.O. Box 45245                          TANZANIA&#13;
Sydney, NSW 20001                       Nairobi                                 Oxford University Press&#13;
BELGIUM             KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                     ~~~~~~~Attn: Mr. Anthony Theobold&#13;
Publications des Nationrs Unies         Pan Korea Book Corporation               Dar es Saiaam&#13;
Attn: Mr. Jean de Lannoy                Attn: Mr. Yoon-Sun Km&#13;
av. du Roi 202                      P.O. Box 101, Kwanghwamun                THAILAND&#13;
Brssels                                 Seoul                                   Central Deartment Store, Head Office&#13;
1060 Brssl                              NALAYSIA                                Attn: Mrs. Ratana&#13;
LANADA                                  University of Malaya Cooperative        BAtn gkok   tad&#13;
Lttn Mifuers Suan emteBookshop Ltd.Bago&#13;
AttnC  Mrs. Suzanne Ver5ette            Attn: Mr. Mohammed Fahim Htj            Thailand Management Association&#13;
C.P.85, ouchrvile J4 5E6Yacob                                         Attn: Mrs. Sunan&#13;
Quebec                                  P.O. Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru        308 Silom Road&#13;
COSTA RICA                              Kuala Lumpur                            Bangkok&#13;
Librenia Trejos                         MEXICO                                  UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
Attn: Mr. -ugo Charntberlaiil           LNFOTEC                                 NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
Canle 11-13, Av. Fernandez Guell        Attn: Mr. Jorge Cepeda                  Microinfo Ltd.&#13;
.,an Jose                               San Lorenzo 153-1i, Col. del Valle,     Attn: Mr. Roy Selwyn&#13;
DENMARK                                 Deleg. Benito Juarez                    Newman Lane, PO. Box 3&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur                      03100 Mexico, D.F.                      Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Attn: Mr. Wilfried Roloff               NETHERLANDS                             England&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 11                      MBE BV                                  UNITED STATES&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V.                   Attn: Mr. Gerhard van Bussell           The World Bank Book Store&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                 Noorderwal 38,                          600 19th Street, N.W.&#13;
Al Aihradn                              7241 BL Lochem                          Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
Attr: Nlr. Sayed El-Gabri               NORWAY                                  (Postal address: P.O. Box 37525&#13;
Al Galaa Ste.et                         Johan Grundt Tanum A.S.                 Washington, D.C. 20013, U.S.A.,&#13;
Cairo                                   Attn: Ms. Randi Mikkelborg              Baker and Taylor Company&#13;
FINLAND                                 P.O. Box 1177 Sentrum                   501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
Akateeminen Kir3akauppa                 Oslo 1                                  Momence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
'ttn: N'r. Kan Litmanen                 PANAMA                                  380 Edison Way&#13;
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100                  Ediciones Libreria Cultural Panamena    Reno, Nevada, 89564&#13;
Helsinki 'n)                            Attn: Mr. Luis Fernandez Fraguela R.    50 Kirbv Avenue&#13;
FRANCE                                  Av. 7, Espana 16                        Somerville, Nev. Jersev, 08876&#13;
World Barik Publications                Panama Zone 1                           Commerce, Georgia .30599&#13;
66, avenue d'6lra                       PHILIPPINES&#13;
75116 Paris                             National Book Store                     Bemarn  Associates&#13;
970- Gore alerHihway&#13;
C ERMANY, Federal Republic of           Attn: Mrs. Socorro C. Ramos             Lanham, Maryland, 20761&#13;
U"NO-Verlag                             701 Rizal Avenue&#13;
gAttn: Mr. ,oachim Kr-ause              Manila                                  Biackweil North America, Inc.&#13;
Simiocksrrasse 23                       SAUDI ARABIA                            1001 Fries Mill Road&#13;
D-533) Bonn 1                           Jarir Book Store                        Blackwood, New Jersey 08012&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                        Attn: Mr. Akram Al-Agil                 Sidney Kramer Books&#13;
Asia 2'.)00 Ltd.                        P.O. Box 3196                           1722 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Attn: Ms. Gretchen Wearing Srrmith      Riyadh                                  Washlington, D.C. 20006&#13;
6 r'. 146 Prince Edward Road            SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                United Nations Bookshop&#13;
Kowloon                                 Information Publications Private, Ltd.  United Nations llaza&#13;
INDIA                                   Attn: Ms. Janet David                  N!ev York, N.Y. 10017&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd.       02-06 1st Floor, Pei-Fu Industrial      VENEZUELA&#13;
At.r: Nlr. D.P. 'Veer                     Buildingreria del Este&#13;
5 Ansaii Road, Post Box 7015            24 New Industrial Road                  Linb Mei. Juan Pet cas&#13;
New D)el3 i 110QU2                      Singapore                               Avda Francisco de Miranda, no. 52&#13;
(B.ar,ch offices in 50ombay, Bangaiore,  SPAIN                                  Edificio Galipan, Aptdo. 60.337&#13;
Kanpu-. Caicutta.. and Madras)          Mundi-Prensa Libros, S.A.               Caracas 106-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                                 European Office                      Tokyo Office                         U&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                          66, avenue d'lna                    Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.                75116 Paris, France                 1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234                     Telephone: (1) 723-54.21            Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK                    Telex: 842-620628                   Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                                          Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN        253N  0-8213-0387-2&#13;
-e~~~~ W&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="887899">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/10/887899/benefit-costs-official-export-credit-programs
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/10/887899/benefit-costs-official-export-credit-programs</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/10/887899/benefit-costs-official-export-credit-programs</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/02/15/000178830_98101903423321/Rendered/INDEX/multi_page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/02/15/000178830_98101903423321/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-05-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The benefit and costs of official export
            credit programs
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper discusses direct loan and
            subsidy programs, one way in which governments support
            export credits, and analyzes the costs and benefits of these
            programs. It also sets forth the market factors that
            determine the subsidy's effect on export prices and
            volumes and, thereby, the ultimate division of the subsidy
            between borrowers and lenders. A variety of issues relevant
            in assessing the social costs and benefits to borrowers and
            lenders are raised: (i) some developing countries may lose
            from subsidized export credit if their own export industries
            must compete; (ii) some developing countries might be forced
            away from the best currency composition of their debt
            portfolios if export credit programs limit their choice of
            currency denominations; (iii) some lending countries might
            achieve offsetting gains in employment, to the extent that
            subsidized exports persistently come out of otherwise
            unemployed resources; and (iv) the resdistribution of income
            toward low-income countries and away from high-income
            countries makes it more difficult to measure the welfare
            loss associated with the efficiency loss.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The benefit and costs of official export
            credit programs
        </docna>
        <display_title>The benefit and costs of official
            export credit programs</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/10/887899/benefit-costs-official-export-credit-programs</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Economic Adjustment and Lending,Strategic Debt Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Fleisig, Heywood</author>
            <author>Hill, Catherine</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903423321</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 659</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0387-2</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Cost-benefit analysis; Export credits;
            Export prices; Export subsidies; Export volume; Loans
            affiliates,alternative
            policies,benchmark,benchmark interest rate,bond
            market,bonds,borrower,Borrowing,Borrowing Countries,capital
            goods,centrally planned economies,commitments,competitive
            markets,Competitors,consumers,cost functions,credit
            demand,credit programs,credit risks,Credit
            Subsidies,debt,debt service,demand curve,discounted present
            value,discounted value,Economic Analysis,economic
            conditions,Economic Cooperation,Economic
            Research,elasticities,Exchange Rate,export
            credit,exports,external costs,externalities,face
            value,fiscal policies,foreign exchange,full
            employment,imports,Income,inflation,insurance,interest
            differentials,interest payments,interest rate,interest
            rates,international banks,international
            debt,lender,lenders,Less Developed Countries,loan,local
            governments,Macroeconomics,marginal cost,market
            factors,maturities,maturity,net exports,nominal interest
            rates,portfolio,present value,price changes,Price
            Increases,prime rate,producers,productive
            resources,productivity,purchase
            price,refinance,repayment,savings,social
            costs,Subsidization,subventions,supply curves,tax
            exemptions,Terms of Trade,total costs,underestimates,unemployment,wealth
        </keywd>
        <owner>Development Economics and Chief Economist</owner>
        <repnb>SWP659</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competitiveness and Competition Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Microeconomic and Market Reforms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competition Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>