<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>318&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           privatesector     P U B L I C        P O L I C Y    F O R               T H E&#13;
&#13;
   NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         NOTE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             2008&#13;
                                                                                                                             Reform Teams&#13;
&#13;
                 FEBRUARY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                Alberto Criscuolo and        How the Most Successful Reformers Organized Themselves&#13;
                                                                                                Vincent Palmade&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             What do Botswana, Cape Verde, Malaysia, Mauritius, and Taiwan&#13;
                         PRESIDENCY                                                             Alberto Criscuolo&#13;
                                                                                                                             (China) have in common? They belong to an exclusive group of&#13;
                                                                                                (acriscuolo@worldbank.org)&#13;
                                   VICE                                                         is a private sector          economies that grew out of poverty in less than 30 years. They also&#13;
                                                                                                development specialist with  initially relied on a small, dedicated team of experts to get the job&#13;
                                                                                                FIAS, the multi-donor&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                investment climate advisory  done. These teams brought to bear world-class skills along with&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                service of the World Bank    direct access to the top level of government and a large development&#13;
                                       DEVELOPMENT&#13;
                                                                                                Group. Vincent Palmade&#13;
                                                                                                                             budget. That combination of skills, access, and resources gave them&#13;
                                                                                                (vpalmade@worldbank.org)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                is lead private sector       the clout to steer an ambitious reform agenda through vested&#13;
                                                  SECTOR&#13;
                                                                                                development specialist in&#13;
                                                                                                                             interests and layers of government.&#13;
                                                                                                the Africa Region of the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                World Bank.&#13;
                                                        PRIVATE                                                              Only a small number of developing economies       22 university graduates and 12 kilometers of&#13;
                                                                                                                             have managed to grow out of poverty in one        paved roads. Mauritius had an economy that&#13;
                                                               AND                              This Note draws&#13;
                                                                                                                             generation, sustaining GDP per capita growth at   depended almost exclusively on sugar and was&#13;
                                                                                                especially on the&#13;
                                                                                                                             rates averaging more than 4 percent a year.1&#13;
                                                                                                preliminary findings of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                Alberto Criscuolo,           Achieving this economic performance required&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                Figure Out of poverty in less than 30 years&#13;
                                                                  FINANCIAL                     Starting Weak, Growing       deep microeconomic reforms spanning many&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                             1                                                 Compound annual growth&#13;
                                                                                                Strong: Institutions to      policy areas and industries.                                                                     in GNI per capita (percent)&#13;
                                                                                                Drive High Growth               How did these reformers organize them-                                              0        2       4        6         8     10      12&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                (Washington, D.C.:           selves at the beginning of their development                        Least developed&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                        countries (1973­2006)&#13;
                                                                                                World Bank,                  journey? A recent study examined that question&#13;
                                                                           GROUP                                                                                                                       Cape Verde&#13;
                                                                                                forthcoming).                by focusing on five cases--Botswana, Cape                              (1988­2006)&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                          Mauritius&#13;
                                                                                                                             Verde,    Malaysia,  Mauritius,   and   Taiwan                         (1982­2006)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                BANK                                         (China)--chosen because of their varied cul-                                 Malaysia&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                    (1972­2006)&#13;
                                                                                                                             tural and administrative heritages (ranging&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                         Botswana&#13;
                                                                                                                             from strong autocratic governments to weak                             (1962­2006)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             multiparty   coalitions).   These    economies                         Taiwan, China&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                    (1962­2006)&#13;
                                                                                    WORLD                                    achieved remarkable performance despite dire&#13;
                                                                                                                             starting conditions (figure 1). Botswana was the         Note: Gross national income (GNI) per capita is calculated using the World Bank Atlas&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      method. "Least developed countries" is a United Nations classification.&#13;
                                                                                         THE                                 poorest country in the world in 1966, with only          Source: World Bank 2007.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
R E F O R M T E A M S H O W T H E M O S T  S U C C E S S F U L  R E F O R M E R S O R G A N I Z E D T H E M S E L V E S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       prone to violence in the decade before inde-                                            Economic Development Board, Chile on its&#13;
                                       pendence in 1968. Cape Verde had virtually no                                           "Chicago boys," the Republic of Korea on its&#13;
                                       private sector and among the world's worst                                              Economic Planning Board, and Japan on its&#13;
                                       human development indicators in 1975.                                                   Ministry of Trade and Industry. More recent&#13;
                                                                                                                               examples include the Executive Office in Dubai&#13;
                                       Dedicated reform teams at the top                                                       and the Ministry of Reform in Georgia, which was&#13;
                                       Remarkably, the study found that all these                                              ranked the top reformer in Doing Business 2007&#13;
                                       economies initially relied on a small, dedicated                                        and among the top 10 in Doing Business 2008&#13;
                                       reform team that was connected to the top of                                            (World Bank and IFC 2006, 2007). According to&#13;
2&#13;
                                       government and in charge of formulating and                                             Simeon Djankov, lead author of the Doing Business&#13;
                                       updating the reform strategy, building consen-                                          reports, "The Ministry of Reform . . . has a small&#13;
                                       sus, coordinating and mobilizing resources for                                          cabinet--20 people or so--all former bankers,&#13;
                                       implementing the strategy, and, crucially, nur-                                         consultants, and lawyers. If I had to identify one&#13;
                                       turing the reformist political leadership over                                          organizational feature of Georgia's success (9.4&#13;
                                       time (figure 2).2                                                                       percent GDP growth in 2006), this would be it."3&#13;
                                            Malaysia's team was its Economic Planning&#13;
                                       Unit, which reported directly to the prime min-                                         The six key functions of reform teams&#13;
                                       ister. The unit started in the early 1960s with 15                                      Reform teams were embedded in the policy&#13;
                                       staff, half of whom were expatriates. Cape Verde                                        process and at the same time relieved of daily&#13;
                                       relied on three returnee advisers around the                                            administrative matters and one step removed&#13;
                                       prime minister (who was also the minister of                                            from the political frontline. That was the best&#13;
                                       planning and development assistance) in 1975.                                           way to leverage scarce technocratic expertise,&#13;
                                       Botswana also had an Economic Planning Unit,                                            maximize impact on policy formulation, and&#13;
                                       which started in 1965 with two economists and                                           perform the six key functions of these teams.&#13;
                                       soon became the core of the powerful Ministry&#13;
                                       of Finance and Development Planning. Taiwan                                             Designing development strategies&#13;
                                       (China) had the Council for U.S. Aid (created in                                        The reform teams were charged with designing&#13;
                                       1948), which reported directly to the president                                         comprehensive yet focused strategies, often in&#13;
                                       and combined some of the economy's best engi-                                           preparation for or soon after independence.4&#13;
                                       neering minds with top-notch U.S. economists.                                           Focus was essential, since the teams lacked the&#13;
                                            Other star performers followed a similar                                           capacity to fix all problems at once.&#13;
                                       approach--with                    Singapore             relying        on       its        Following initial attempts at import substitu-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Figure   How smart governments got started&#13;
                                        2&#13;
                                                                         Coordination&#13;
                                                     Donors                                        Small, dedicated             Access&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Head of state&#13;
                                                                                                  world-class team&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     Engaged but&#13;
                                                                     arm's length                                Advocacy and&#13;
                                                                                                               funds to support&#13;
                                                                                                                    reforms&#13;
                                                         Private&#13;
                                                         sector&#13;
                                                                                                                                             Line ministries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                Source: Authors.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
tion leading to mixed growth outcomes, all the       Grooming political leaders&#13;
reform teams settled on export-driven strategies     A sound development strategy is worth little if&#13;
focusing on the industries with the strongest        not backed by outstanding political leadership&#13;
export potential: mining and food processing in      able to make tough decisions and discipline&#13;
Botswana; tourism and fishing in Cape Verde;         often reluctant administrations. The five reform&#13;
apparel, sugar, and tourism in Mauritius; and        teams benefited from plenty of outstanding&#13;
light manufacturing and then information and         political leadership. For example, Botswana's&#13;
communication technology in Malaysia and             first president laid the groundwork for sound&#13;
Taiwan (China).                                      mining policies when he gave up the mining&#13;
                                                                                                         3&#13;
   The reform teams identified key constraints       rights of his own tribe (through the historic&#13;
and success factors by industry, such as ensuring    Mines and Mineral Act of 1967) to the benefit&#13;
good governance in mining and developing best-       of the national government.&#13;
practice export processing zones for light man-          At the same time the continual and almost&#13;
ufacturing and information and communication         symbiotic engagement of reform teams with top&#13;
technology. They also adapted the strategies to      political figures helped groom several genera-&#13;
changing conditions (such as rising labor costs)     tions of political leaders. The second chairman&#13;
and terminated bad experiments (Taiwan,              of the Council for U.S. Aid, C. Y. Yen, later&#13;
China, is one of the few economies ever to aban-     became president of Taiwan (China) (Wade&#13;
don an ailing automotive assembly industry).         1990). Pedro Pires, the team leader in Cape&#13;
   Finally, the development strategies always        Verde in 1975, is now the president of the coun-&#13;
included a fundamental "social contract" with        try. Botswana's second president, Quett Masire,&#13;
citizens on better health, education, and infra-     had been in charge of the Economic Planning&#13;
structure. That not only ensured social cohesion     Unit for 14 years, and its third, Festus Mogae,&#13;
but also aided the competitiveness of industries.    had been head of the Ministry of Finance and&#13;
                                                     Development Planning for 5 years.&#13;
Leading the dialogue with the private sector&#13;
Economic policymaking required the reform            Leading critical policy negotiations&#13;
teams to lead an intense but arm's-length rela-      The reform teams brought unique skills and&#13;
tionship with the private sector. The team in        expertise to bear in key negotiations. These&#13;
Mauritius, for example, strategically engaged the    included negotiations with foreign companies&#13;
sugar industry in pursuing access to international   on mining concessions in Botswana and with&#13;
markets on favorable terms. And Botswana's ini-      large U.S. electronics companies on the acqui-&#13;
tially relied on the entrepreneurial class of cattle sition   of  technology     licenses in  Taiwan&#13;
ranchers (the "beefocracy") to advocate for an       (China)--and negotiations on access to the&#13;
export-oriented, private sector­led strategy of      European market and on more flexible labor&#13;
modernization.                                       rules   for  exporting    companies,   both   in&#13;
   This approach required the reform teams to        Mauritius.&#13;
mix top-notch knowledge of industries with rig-&#13;
orous economics--a mix leading to creative and       Mobilizing and allocating resources&#13;
sometimes explosive tensions. One example:           The teams played a key part in mobilizing&#13;
the legendary "showdowns" in Taiwan (China)          resources for implementing strategies, particu-&#13;
between the Economic Research Unit and the           larly by coordinating donor support. In Taiwan&#13;
Sectoral Planning Department of the Council          (China) the Council for U.S. Aid managed U.S.&#13;
for Economic Planning and Development (for-          aid flows. Malaysia's Economic Planning Unit&#13;
merly the Council for U.S. Aid; Wade 1990).          was in charge of the development budget, which&#13;
   In all cases the autonomy and apolitical nature   amounted to a third of the national budget.&#13;
of the teams enabled them to engage with the         Cape Verde's Ministry of Planning was in charge&#13;
business community while avoiding the risks of       of mobilizing donor support. One trick it used&#13;
capture by dominant interest groups--what Peter      was to set up competition between donors by&#13;
Evans (1995) would call "embedded autonomy."         assigning each an island. Similarly, Botswana's&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
R E F O R M T E A M S H O W T H E M O S T S U C C E S S F U L R E F O R M E R S O R G A N I Z E D T H E M S E L V E S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ministry of Finance and Development Planning                              India. Reform teams are not the answer to all&#13;
put donors in charge of the performance of dif-                           problems. But they can be a good start.&#13;
ferent industries--for example, Canada for min-&#13;
ing and the United Kingdom for agriculture.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 viewpoint&#13;
Compelling the administration to act                                      Notes&#13;
These central, dedicated reform teams were in                                  1. According to World Bank operational classifica-&#13;
&#13;
an ideal position to monitor progress and sug-                            tions and staff calculations, fewer than 15 economies grad-&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 is an open forum to&#13;
gest corrective actions to the national leader-                           uated from low-income to middle-income status between&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 encourage dissemination of&#13;
ship. Indeed, their unique combination of                                 1965 and 2006.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 public policy innovations for&#13;
monitoring capacity and access to the top (the                                 2. The reform teams also led deliberate efforts to cre-&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 private sector­led and&#13;
stick) and financial and technical resources                              ate capable public institutions for effectively managing&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 market-based solutions for&#13;
(the carrot) enabled them to compel the                                   economic policies.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 development. The views&#13;
administration to act. They also experimented                                  3. Email message to authors, April 19, 2007.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 published are those of the&#13;
with different organizational drivers, such as                                 4. These strategies were, for Taiwan (China), the                 authors and should not be&#13;
expatriates    embedded         in    line        positions               Nineteen Points Program of Economic and Financial                      attributed to the World&#13;
(Botswana), cross-departmental task forces                                Reform of 1960 (Haggard and Zheng 2006); for Mauritius,                Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
(Taiwan, China), staff exchanges (Mauritius),                             the Meade Report of 1961; for Botswana, the Transitional               organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
&#13;
and tight-knit networks of policy officials (Cape                         Plan for Development of 1965; for Malaysia, the New                    the conclusions represent&#13;
&#13;
Verde). Implementing agencies had little                                  Economic Policy of 1971; and for Cape Verde, the                       official policy of the World&#13;
&#13;
choice but to come to specific agreements with                            Emergency Recovery Plan of 1975.                                       Bank or of its Executive&#13;
&#13;
the reform teams on implementation targets,                                                                                                      Directors or the countries&#13;
&#13;
budgets, and responsibilities.                                            References                                                             they represent.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               Evans, Peter. 1995. Embedded Autonomy: States and&#13;
Conclusion                                                                Industrial Transformation. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton                  To order additional copies&#13;
&#13;
Dedicated, multiskilled, change management                                University Press.                                                      contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
&#13;
teams are common in the private sector.                                        Haggard, Stephan, and Yu Zheng. 2006. "Institutional              managing editor,&#13;
&#13;
Companies rely on them to effect radical                                                                                                         Room F 4K-206,&#13;
                                                                          Innovation and Private Investment in Taiwan." World&#13;
&#13;
change, such as launching a new product or                                                                                                       The World Bank,&#13;
                                                                          Bank Group, FIAS, Washington, D.C.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
turning    around    a    loss-making          operation.                      Kikeri, Sunita, Thomas Kenyon, and Vincent Palmade.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
Governments typically use them in times of cri-                           2006. "Reforming the Investment Climate: Lessons for&#13;
&#13;
sis, such as during a war or after an earthquake.                         Practitioners." Policy Research Working Paper 3986.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Telephone:&#13;
Most low-income countries are in a war against                            World Bank, Washington, D.C.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 001 202 458 7281&#13;
poverty--and need radical change in the way                                    Wade, Robert. 1990. Governing the Market: Economic&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Fax:&#13;
their government operates. Yet they rarely rely                           Theory and the Role of Government in East Asian&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 001 202 522 3480&#13;
on such teams. Instead, governments' limited                              Industrialization. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Email:&#13;
technical and financial resources typically are                           Press.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
scattered thinly, with no strategic focus and lit-                             World Bank. 2007. World Development Indicators 2007.&#13;
&#13;
tle coordination. In the absence of strong gov-                           Washington, D.C.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Produced by Grammarians,&#13;
ernment leadership, donor support typically                                    World       Bank      and       IFC    (International  Finance    Inc.&#13;
follows the same patterns.                                                Corporation). 2006. Doing Business 2007: How to Reform.&#13;
&#13;
    Understanding how reform teams operate,                               Washington, D.C.                                                       Printed on recycled paper&#13;
what drives them to perform when others have                                   ------.       2007.     Doing        Business 2008:  Comparing&#13;
&#13;
failed, and how donors can work with them is                              Regulation in 178 Economies. Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
critical. Yet these questions have been largely&#13;
overlooked in the development discourse. This&#13;
Note is a first step toward tackling such ques-&#13;
tions, including whether the model would apply&#13;
to such large economies as Brazil, China, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            T h i s N o t e i s a v a i l a b l e o n l i n e :&#13;
                                                                                        h t t p : / / r r u . w o r l d b a n k . o r g / P u b l i c P o l i c y J o u r n a l&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="9065004">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2008/02/9065004/reform-teams
        </url>
        <availablein>French,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="000333038_20080619005737" node_id="9065004"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2008/02/9065004/reform-teams</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2008/02/9065004/reform-teams</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2008/03/10/000333037_20080310061206/Rendered/INDEX/428100VP0Refor180Box327331B1PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2008/03/10/000333037_20080310061206/Rendered/PDF/428100VP0Refor180Box327331B1PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2008-02-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2008-03-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Reform teams
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This note is about reform teams.They
            belong to an exclusive group of economies that grew out of
            poverty in less than 30 years. They also initially relied on
            a small, dedicated team of experts to get the job done.
            These teams brought to bear world-class skills along with
            direct access to the top level of government and a large
            development budget. That combination of skills, access, and
            resources gave them the clout to steer an ambitious reform
            agenda through vested interests and layers of government.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Reform teams
        </docna>
        <display_title>Reform teams</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2008/02/9065004/reform-teams</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>m,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,E-Business,ICT Policy and Strategies,Enterprise Development &amp; Reform</subtopic>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Information and Communication Technologies,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Criscuolo , Alberto ; Palmade , Vincent</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20080310061206</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 318</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Information and Communication Technologies,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            business community, calculations, change
            management, communication technology, competitiveness,
            Economic Development, Email message, favorable terms,
            financial resources, good governance, Implementing agencies,
            income, Innovation, innovations, investment climate,
            lawyers, leadership, licenses, low-income, manufacturing,
            minister, networks, policy formulation, political leaders,
            political leadership, Private Investment, PRIVATE SECTOR,
            PRIVATE SECTOR DEVELOPMENT, reforms, responsibilities,
            targets, technical resources, Telephone, violence, worth
        </keywd>
        <owner>AFT:  Finance &amp; Priv Sect Dev FO (AFTFP)</owner>
        <repnb>42810</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Les equipes de reformes des pays
            emergeants les plus performants
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment and Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Conflict, Crisis and Fragility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Cohesion and Violence Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>EPZ</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Zones</ml:concept><ml:concept>Export Processing Zones</ml:concept><ml:concept>SEZ</ml:concept><ml:concept>Special Economic Zones</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Cohesion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Poles and Economic Zones</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>