<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                     43169&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Evaluation of the Environmentally&#13;
and Socially Sustainable&#13;
Development Network's Staff&#13;
Learning Program in FY05 and&#13;
FY06&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Dawn Roberts&#13;
Izlem Yenice&#13;
Sara Kruse&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Evaluation of the&#13;
Environmentally and&#13;
Socially Sustainable&#13;
Development Network's&#13;
Staff Learning Program&#13;
in FY05 and FY06&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Dawn Roberts&#13;
&#13;
Izlem Yenice&#13;
&#13;
Sara Kruse&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WBI Evaluation Studies&#13;
No. EG07-127&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank Institute&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
April 2007&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                Acknowledgments&#13;
&#13;
        The World Bank Institute Evaluation Group (WBIEG) prepared this report under&#13;
the direction of Richard Tobin, who served as task team leader for the evaluation. Dawn&#13;
Roberts is the principal author.&#13;
&#13;
        The team gratefully acknowledges the thoughtful reflections and explanations&#13;
provided by members of the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development&#13;
network's knowledge-sharing and learning team and sector managers in focus groups and&#13;
interviews. In addition, Najma Siddiqi and Jan Weetjens provided valuable comments to&#13;
strengthen the report. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed in WBI&#13;
Evaluation Studies are entirely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the&#13;
views of the World Bank Group, including WBI.&#13;
&#13;
        WBI Evaluation Studies are available at http://www.worldbank.org/wbi/evaluation&#13;
&#13;
Suggested citation: Roberts, Dawn, Izlem Yenice, and Sara Kruse. 2007. Evaluation of&#13;
the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network's Staff Learning&#13;
Program in FY05 and FY06. Report No. EG07-127. Washington, DC: World Bank&#13;
Institute.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Vice President, World Bank Institute                         Frannie Léautier&#13;
Acting Chief Learning Officer                                Ana-Maria Arriagada&#13;
Manager, Institute Evaluation Group                          Richard Tobin&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             ii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                 Contents&#13;
&#13;
EXECUTIVE SUMMARY ......................................................................................................vii&#13;
&#13;
1.   INTRODUCTION....................................................................................................... 1&#13;
&#13;
2.   STAFF LEARNING PROVIDED BY ESSD ................................................................. 4&#13;
&#13;
  Integration of Knowledge Sharing and Learning into ESSD's Business ..................... 4&#13;
&#13;
  The Scope and Scale of ESSD's Learning Program..................................................... 7&#13;
&#13;
3.   PARTICIPATION IN ESSD'S LEARNING PROGRAM .............................................. 10&#13;
&#13;
  Patterns of Participation.............................................................................................. 10&#13;
&#13;
     Overview of participants mapped to ESSD .......................................................... 10&#13;
&#13;
     Numbers of events attended by ESSD staff.......................................................... 12&#13;
&#13;
     Participation by staff outside of ESSD ................................................................. 13&#13;
&#13;
  Factors Influencing Participation................................................................................ 13&#13;
&#13;
     Perspectives of participants................................................................................... 13&#13;
&#13;
     Perspectives of managers...................................................................................... 15&#13;
&#13;
4.   QUALITY AND EFFECTIVENESS OF ESSD'S LEARNING PROGRAM..................... 16&#13;
&#13;
  Overall Quality............................................................................................................ 16&#13;
&#13;
  Relevance.................................................................................................................... 18&#13;
&#13;
  Areas of Effectiveness ................................................................................................ 19&#13;
&#13;
  Satisfaction with Learning Design and Delivery........................................................ 21&#13;
&#13;
  Use of Skills and knowledge Acquired in Learning Events ....................................... 22&#13;
&#13;
  Suggestions for Future Learning from ESSD Staff .................................................... 24&#13;
&#13;
5.   CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS ............................................................ 26&#13;
&#13;
  Suggested Actions for the KSL Team ........................................................................ 26&#13;
&#13;
     Knowledge and learning results framework ......................................................... 26&#13;
&#13;
     Data management.................................................................................................. 27&#13;
&#13;
     Accountability and continuous improvement....................................................... 28&#13;
&#13;
  Suggested Actions for the CLO and the KLB ............................................................ 28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          iii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
     Improvements to centralized systems................................................................... 28&#13;
&#13;
     Fostering a community of practice ....................................................................... 29&#13;
&#13;
APPENDIXES&#13;
&#13;
  Appendix A: Methodology ......................................................................................... 31&#13;
&#13;
  Appendix B: Responses of Participants to Survey .................................................... 34&#13;
&#13;
  Appendix C: Suggestions from Participants for Making ESSD/SDN Learning&#13;
              Programs More Effective ...................................................................... 37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              iv&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
AFR    Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
ARD    Agriculture and rural development&#13;
&#13;
CGIAR  Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research&#13;
&#13;
CLO    Chief Learning Officer&#13;
&#13;
CO     Country office&#13;
&#13;
EAP    East Asia and Pacific Region&#13;
&#13;
ECA    Europe and Central Asia Region&#13;
&#13;
ESSD   Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development network&#13;
&#13;
HR     Human Resources&#13;
&#13;
INF    Infrastructure network&#13;
&#13;
KLB    Knowledge and Learning Board&#13;
&#13;
KSL    Knowledge sharing and learning&#13;
&#13;
LCR    Latin America and Caribbean Region&#13;
&#13;
LMS    Learning Management System&#13;
&#13;
MNA    Middle East and North Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
SAR    South Asia Region&#13;
&#13;
SDN    Sustainable Development network&#13;
&#13;
SLC    Strategic learning center&#13;
&#13;
VPU    Vice presidential unit&#13;
&#13;
WBIEG  World Bank Institute Evaluation Group&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             v&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
vi&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
&#13;
        At the request of the Knowledge and Learning Board (KLB), the World Bank&#13;
Institute Evaluation Group (WBIEG) evaluated the staff learning program provided by&#13;
the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development (ESSD) network in FY05&#13;
and FY06. The study focused on helping the network understand its accomplishments&#13;
vis-à-vis staff learning, address weaknesses, and improve the relevance, effectiveness,&#13;
and impact of ESSD's learning program in the future. WBIEG collected and analyzed&#13;
data from members of ESSD's learning team, network staff, sector managers, Bank data&#13;
systems, and assessments of quality by participants in ESSD learning events.&#13;
&#13;
                           STAFF LEARNING PROVIDED BY ESSD&#13;
&#13;
        Integration of knowledge sharing and learning into ESSD's business. The&#13;
composition of ESSD's knowledge-sharing and learning (KSL) team fosters&#13;
collaboration across the network's departments and units, and the team works cohesively&#13;
to identify and address strategic priorities. Major centralized initiatives to guide, support,&#13;
and monitor the network's KSL program in FY05 and FY06 included assessments of&#13;
knowledge and learning needs and preferences and ongoing tracer studies of selected&#13;
programs. The team also demonstrated a commitment to transparency, developing and&#13;
maintaining a KSL site on the intranet. Despite such effort, focus groups and interviews&#13;
with regional managers revealed limited awareness of the network's learning program.&#13;
&#13;
        The scope and scale of ESSD's learning program. The Bank's learning&#13;
management system (LMS) indicated that ESSD was the main sponsor for 142 learning&#13;
events in FY05 and 155 events in FY06. However, these data provided limited&#13;
information on the overall learning program and did not include some important learning&#13;
initiatives such as peer exchanges, KSL product grants, and a mentoring program. The&#13;
network championed the synergy of learning and knowledge-sharing activities and&#13;
products for staff, and the program in FY05 included a coordinated series of offerings to&#13;
develop the capacity of staff designing and organizing KSL initiatives. A portfolio of&#13;
KSL products and online resources supplemented ESSD-related learning events in both&#13;
years.&#13;
&#13;
                     PARTICIPATION IN ESSD'S LEARNING PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
        Patterns of participation. At least 75 percent of ESSD staff attended one ESSD-&#13;
related learning event in FY05, and at least 60 percent did so in FY06. This decrease can&#13;
be explained in part by the fact that ESSD week was offered in FY05 but not in FY06.&#13;
The profile of ESSD participants underscored that the learning program must develop&#13;
locally appropriate technical expertise for a staff based largely at headquarters but also&#13;
located in many country offices, effectively serve senior staff, and cater to many people&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              vii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
who were new to the Bank. Overall, staff mapped to the network participated in an&#13;
average of 2.2 ESSD learning events in FY05 and 1.7 events in FY06. Staff based at&#13;
headquarters, new to the Bank, or in ESSD's vice presidential unit (VPU) tended to&#13;
participate in the most events each year.&#13;
&#13;
        Factors influencing participation. ESSD staff expected the learning program to&#13;
serve a variety of functions, and a majority of participants indicated that the following&#13;
goals were important or very important for motivating them to attend learning events:&#13;
becoming aware of new ideas and emerging issues in their sector (94 percent); enhancing&#13;
job performance in current position (93 percent); networking or sharing information (89&#13;
percent); developing core sector skills and knowledge (84 percent); and developing&#13;
advanced, specialized sectoral knowledge (76 percent). The relative importance of these&#13;
factors did not differ significantly between staff at headquarters and those in country&#13;
offices, but several participants did express concern about the accessibility of the&#13;
program for staff outside of Washington. In focus groups and interviews, managers&#13;
reflected that the many demands of Bank operations often made it difficult for staff to&#13;
attend learning events.&#13;
&#13;
             QUALITY AND EFFECTIVENESS OF ESSD'S LEARNING PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
        Overall Quality. Insufficient information was available on the objectives of the&#13;
learning program, the planned activities, and the events actually delivered to support an&#13;
independent analysis of how well the program was aligned with the strategic priorities of&#13;
ESSD's business plan. This evaluation therefore explored the program's quality and&#13;
effectiveness by examining perceptions among ESSD-mapped staff and managers. Nearly&#13;
two-thirds (65 percent) of ESSD-mapped participants in ESSD learning events indicated&#13;
that the overall quality of the learning program was very good (17 percent) or good (48&#13;
percent). At the same time, however, a question asking survey respondents to describe&#13;
concrete experiences with the learning program revealed that many of these participants&#13;
did not know which events were offered as part of ESSD's KSL program. Average&#13;
ratings from participants' assessments of the quality of individual events improved&#13;
notably from FY05 to FY06, suggesting that the efforts to develop KSL capacity in FY05&#13;
were successful.&#13;
&#13;
        Relevance.Seventy percent of ESSD participants found the relevance of the&#13;
learning choices to be very good (23 percent) or good (47 percent). Ratings were more&#13;
positive among respondents in the ESSD VPU, but this dynamic could be explained by&#13;
the focused emphasis during this period on developing the capacity of staff who design&#13;
KSL initiatives.&#13;
&#13;
        Areas of Effectiveness. Ratings of the program's effectiveness were significantly&#13;
higher for raising awareness of new issues (69 percent very good or good) and providing&#13;
opportunities for networking (64 percent very good or good) than for developing core&#13;
sector skills and knowledge (56 percent very good or good) or developing advanced,&#13;
specialized sector knowledge (48 percent very good or good). These results indicate that&#13;
the program was most effective in those areas that were deemed to be most important by&#13;
participants. Identifying steps to increase program effectiveness will require the&#13;
establishment of clear objectives for the learning program and communicating relevant&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             viii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
events and products to managers and staff so that they know of opportunities to address&#13;
their demands.&#13;
&#13;
        Satisfaction with learning design and delivery. Two-thirds of participants (67&#13;
percent) provided positive ratings (very good or good) for the organization of learning&#13;
events, and 75 percent provided positive ratings for the quality of instructors or speakers.&#13;
Again, respondents in the ESSD VPU provided higher ratings on average. These ratings&#13;
signal the need for improvements since many participants (one quarter to one third) were&#13;
not satisfied with design or delivery features. These generalizations about the program&#13;
across two years may be of limited use given the indication by participants' assessments&#13;
that quality increased notably from FY05 to FY06 and evidence that respondents could&#13;
not necessarily differentiate between ESSD's staff learning program and those offered by&#13;
other VPUs.&#13;
&#13;
        Use of skills and knowledge acquired in learning events. Two-thirds of ESSD&#13;
participants (66 percent) reported using the skills and knowledge they gained in ESSD&#13;
learning events frequently or very frequently. Participants were most likely to apply what&#13;
they learned when the skills and knowledge were relevant to their current job&#13;
responsibilities.&#13;
&#13;
        Suggestions for future learning from ESSD staff. Participants expressed a strong&#13;
interest in attending learning events that would clarify the new organizational structure&#13;
and work programs resulting from the consolidation of ESSD and the Infrastructure&#13;
network into the Sustainable Development network (SDN). To improve the effectiveness&#13;
of ESSD-related learning in the future, respondents emphasized the need to increase the&#13;
involvement of country office (CO) staff in the learning program (both as providers and&#13;
participants) and to improve the relevance of offerings.&#13;
&#13;
                          CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
&#13;
Suggested Actions for the KSL Team&#13;
&#13;
        ESSD established centralized structures and processes to shape its overall learning&#13;
program, and the findings of this evaluation did not signal the need for major changes to&#13;
the current model. Recommended actions, in the order they should occur, include:&#13;
&#13;
        Knowledge and learning results framework. The lack of clear objectives for the&#13;
        learning program, detailed information on how planned activities supported&#13;
        learning objectives, and data on the delivery and content of learning events&#13;
        prevented a systematic analysis of how well the program's offerings supported the&#13;
        strategic priorities of ESSD's business plan. The KSL team should establish&#13;
        measurable objectives for its learning program with associated indicators to gauge&#13;
        how well the program is addressing the network's business needs.&#13;
&#13;
        Data management. Participants and ESSD learning events and sector managers&#13;
        all provided evidence that staff did not have enough timely information to choose&#13;
        and schedule appropriate learning offerings. To improve the quality and use of the&#13;
        LMS, standard guidelines should be established for entering learning activity data&#13;
        and a quality assurance process created to support improved data management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             ix&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       Accountability and continuous improvement. ESSD had various structures and&#13;
       strategies in place to incorporate evaluation findings into the planning, design,&#13;
       and delivery of learning activities. Nevertheless, findings from this study&#13;
       underscored the need for systematic monitoring and dissemination to support&#13;
       program improvements. The network's KSL team should clarify responsibilities&#13;
       and establish a cycle for incorporating formative guidance into its learning plan,&#13;
       sharing best practices among learning providers, and monitoring areas of potential&#13;
       weaknesses.&#13;
&#13;
Suggested Actions for the CLO and the KLB&#13;
&#13;
       Steps to ensure that staff engage in effective ESSD-related professional and&#13;
technical learning include:&#13;
&#13;
       Improvements to centralized systems. The CLO and KLB have actively supported&#13;
       the development of the LMS and the toolkit and template for creating learning&#13;
       plans. The experiences for ESSD's learning program suggest that the CLO's&#13;
       office should continue refining processes, definitions, and systems that support&#13;
       VPUs in developing and delivering staff learning. Findings from this evaluation&#13;
       can inform improvements to the learning plan toolkit and action steps for the&#13;
       LMS.&#13;
&#13;
       Fostering a community of practice. Just as ESSD's KSL team fosters efficiency&#13;
       and synergy in learning across the network's units, so should the KLB promote&#13;
       and facilitate collaboration and information sharing to support the new results&#13;
       agenda. A simple electronic learning community could supplement KLB&#13;
       meetings by sharing knowledge, tools, lessons learned, and other resources across&#13;
       VPUs. Such a platform would strengthen the centralized functions embodied by&#13;
       the KLB and allow VPUs to access and adapt each others' products or strategies&#13;
       to support the Bank's decentralized business.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             x&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                               1.        INTRODUCTION&#13;
&#13;
1.1     Effective staff learning is of critical importance to the World Bank to ensure that&#13;
personnel have the best mix of skills, behaviors, experience, and technical expertise for&#13;
achieving the Bank's business objectives. The Chief Learning Officer (CLO) and the&#13;
Knowledge and Learning Board (KLB) work together to guide and oversee the overall&#13;
staff learning program. Based on annual learning plans approved by the CLO, the six&#13;
regions, 11 strategic learning centers (SLCs), and other VPUs provide learning activities&#13;
that increase staff effectiveness within specific lines of business. The CLO manages a&#13;
substantial investment in staff learning each year--$76.8 million in FY06--and works&#13;
with the KLB to select certain programs to be evaluated by the World Bank Institute&#13;
Evaluation Group (WBIEG). At the request of the KLB, WBIEG evaluated the overall&#13;
learning program provided by the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable&#13;
Development (ESSD) network in FY05 and FY06.&#13;
&#13;
1.2     ESSD has shepherded the Bank's efforts to assist clients in achieving poverty&#13;
reduction through sustainable development. An integrated approach to growth based on&#13;
social and environmental responsibility is necessary for developing countries to&#13;
overcome risks and vulnerabilities, and ESSD fosters this integration through a set of&#13;
interrelated sector strategies on agriculture and rural development, forests, water&#13;
resources, the environment, and social development. The network also advanced the&#13;
sustainable development agenda through global partnerships such as with the Global&#13;
Environment Facility and the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research&#13;
(CGIAR) and through cross-sectoral work to strengthen the links with the water and&#13;
sanitation, transportation, urban, energy, and rural development sectors.1&#13;
&#13;
1.3     The broad reaching work of ESSD has required the synchronization of knowledge&#13;
sharing, learning, and strategic staffing, and the network's learning plans in FY05 and&#13;
FY06 focused on ensuring that staff had access to relevant knowledge-sharing and&#13;
learning programs to support ESSD's strategic priorities. This evaluation focused on the&#13;
overall ESSD learning program to help the network understand its accomplishments vis-&#13;
à-vis staff learning and to improve the program's future relevance, effectiveness, and&#13;
impact. The goal of the study was to provide the KLB and the network with information&#13;
to guide strategic decisions about staff learning programs.&#13;
&#13;
1.4     Nine evaluation questions guided this study in exploring the composition of the&#13;
overall learning program, staff participation, and the quality and effectiveness of ESSD&#13;
learning opportunities for staff:&#13;
&#13;
        Staff learning provided by ESSD&#13;
&#13;
1The Bank formally integrated environmental and infrastructure projects at the end of FY06 with the&#13;
consolidation of ESSD and the Infrastructure network into the Sustainable Development network.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                o What was the rationale and process the network used to shape the&#13;
                    agenda and to ensure the achievement of strategic and business&#13;
                    objectives?&#13;
&#13;
                o What was the scope and scale of the network's learning program?&#13;
&#13;
        Staff participation in ESSD's learning program&#13;
&#13;
                o To what extent did the network staff participate in ESSD learning?&#13;
                o What factors influenced participation?&#13;
                o To what extent did learning activities reach the target audience?&#13;
                o To what extent did staff who were not part of the target audience&#13;
                    participate in the network's learning program?&#13;
&#13;
        Quality and effectiveness of ESSD's learning program&#13;
&#13;
                o To what degree was the network learning program relevant to the&#13;
                    needs of Bank staff?&#13;
&#13;
                o Did the network provide a high quality learning program, especially&#13;
                    from staff and managers' perspectives?&#13;
&#13;
                o How can the learning program be improved?&#13;
&#13;
1.5     The evaluation also provided preliminary information (self-reported data from&#13;
staff) on the extent to which participants of ESSD's learning activities used the skills and&#13;
knowledge they acquired.&#13;
&#13;
1.6     The WBIEG team used a mixed-method approach, collecting qualitative and&#13;
quantitative data from Bank data systems, ESSD staff, and sector managers. Data-&#13;
collection strategies included:&#13;
&#13;
        A focus group discussion with the ESSD knowledge-sharing and learning (KSL)&#13;
        team to explore the processes used by team members to develop learning plans&#13;
        and design learning events. This session was held in March 2006 and focused&#13;
        primarily on the FY05 learning program.&#13;
&#13;
        Focus groups and interviews with managers of ESSD staff to explore the skills&#13;
        and knowledge needed to conduct the network's business, the processes used for&#13;
        assessing staff learning needs, and the perceived quality and effectiveness of the&#13;
        overall learning program. These sessions occurred from March to May 2006 and&#13;
        also focused primarily on the FY05 learning program.&#13;
&#13;
        A survey of participants in ESSD learning events to explore perceptions about the&#13;
        quality and effectiveness of the learning program and the motivations for&#13;
        participating. The focus groups and interviews with the learning team and&#13;
        network managers informed the development of the survey instrument, and its&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      questions then focused on ESSD's overall learning program for both FY05 and&#13;
      FY06.&#13;
&#13;
1.7   The team also reviewed and analyzed existing data, including participants'&#13;
assessments of quality for ESSD learning activities, data related to learning events, and&#13;
demographic variables. The methodology for this evaluation is in appendix A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
           2.      STAFF LEARNING PROVIDED BY ESSD&#13;
&#13;
2.1      Since FY04, knowledge sharing has been increasingly embedded in ESSD's staff&#13;
learning program. Specialists in professional and technical areas, learning, and&#13;
information management collaborate to provide learning programs and knowledge&#13;
products that support staff in conducting the network's business. The network's KSL&#13;
team developed and implemented processes to support a comprehensive program for&#13;
addressing the learning and knowledge needs of staff in FY05 and FY06. Unfortunately,&#13;
this overall program was not yet accurately reflected in the Bank's learning management&#13;
system (LMS) or well understood by regional managers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   INTEGRATION OF KNOWLEDGE SHARING AND LEARNING INTO ESSD'S BUSINESS&#13;
&#13;
2.2     For FY05 and FY06, ESSD had formal structures to address staff learning and&#13;
knowledge needs. These included a KSL oversight committee chaired by the network's&#13;
Knowledge and Learning Coordinator and a KSL cross-departmental team to develop and&#13;
implement an overall program of knowledge-sharing and learning initiatives (events and&#13;
products) each year. By design, the composition of the team fostered collaboration&#13;
within ESSD. Team members represented the three main families of social development,&#13;
environment, and agriculture and rural development (ARD), the Quality Assurance and&#13;
Compliance Unit responsible for safeguards, CGIAR, resource management, human&#13;
resources, communications team (including external affairs), and ESSD information&#13;
technology and advisory services.&#13;
&#13;
2.3     KSL team members supported the Bank's decentralized business by working in&#13;
their respective units to assess learning needs and identify priorities in line with business&#13;
objectives. They also worked cohesively as a team, meeting regularly and sharing&#13;
processes and practices to address the network's agreed-upon learning priorities. Major&#13;
centralized initiatives to guide, support, and monitor the overall KSL program in FY05&#13;
and FY06 included assessments of knowledge and learning needs and preferences and&#13;
tracer studies of some programs to track effectiveness. Common practices used by KSL&#13;
team members to develop and implement the KSL program are described in box 2.1. The&#13;
examples provided are not intended to present a comprehensive list of practices and tools&#13;
across the three departments but do illustrate how different units use joint or parallel&#13;
processes to design and deliver ESSD's learning program.&#13;
&#13;
2.4     ESSD's KSL team demonstrated a commitment to transparency, developing and&#13;
maintaining a central KSL page on the intranet for staff and also posting relevant KSL&#13;
information on the intranet sites of individual ESSD departments. Through these online&#13;
resources, network staff had access to knowledge products, descriptions of learning&#13;
events, evaluation data, quarterly reports to the KLB, and contact lists for KSL team&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
members. In addition, the team actively publicized planned events through systematic e-&#13;
mail announcements.&#13;
&#13;
Box 2.1. Examples of processes, standards, and tools used by ESSD's KSL team&#13;
&#13;
Identifying learning priorities based on staff needs and network business objectives&#13;
&#13;
    Formal assessments of learning needs,                   Interviews and focus groups with country office&#13;
    including a survey on knowledge and learning            teams and country managers and directors&#13;
    preferences in ARD, a survey to assess&#13;
    demand for social development orientation, and          Participation in project reviews by Quality&#13;
&#13;
    broad KSL needs assessment survey of                    Assurance Group to note areas of weakness or&#13;
&#13;
    network staff                                           recurring themes&#13;
&#13;
    Interviews and focus groups with regional and           Review of work program agreements (WPAs) to&#13;
&#13;
    anchor managers                                         link learning with business needs (in ARD, the&#13;
                                                            leader for each WPA is the anchor person for a&#13;
                                                            thematic group)&#13;
&#13;
Translating priorities into network KSL plan, programs, and products&#13;
&#13;
    Review of needs and priorities of each                  Establishment of publications group and&#13;
    department to establish crosscutting themes or          common standards to bring together experience&#13;
    principles of strategic importance on which to          of all units&#13;
    focus overall learning program (usually occurs&#13;
    through two or three half-day meetings of the           Use of team approach to ensure quality of&#13;
&#13;
    KSL team)                                               programs and products, including clarification of&#13;
                                                            demand, checking alignment with corporate&#13;
    Input to and review of KSL plan by sector               priorities, and cross-checking pedagogy with&#13;
    boards                                                  KSL specialists from department, anchor, and&#13;
                                                            learning support group&#13;
&#13;
Measuring the quality and effectiveness of KSL activities and products&#13;
&#13;
    One person responsible for monitoring and               Informal solicitation of comments from anchor&#13;
    evaluation function, including participants'            and regional managers familiar with events or&#13;
    assessments of quality of individual events             products&#13;
&#13;
    Customized evaluations for major network                Tracer studies of the peer exchange, ACS&#13;
    learning events                                         group training, and the innovations and product&#13;
                                                            grants programs&#13;
    Review of qualitative comments submitted in&#13;
    participant questionnaires                              Feedback forms with publications such as&#13;
                                                            Environment Matters support continuous&#13;
                                                            improvement&#13;
&#13;
Sources: Focus group with ESSD KSL team in March 2006 and quarterly reports submitted to the KLB&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.5      Despite the efforts of the KSL team to develop a transparent learning program&#13;
closely linked with network business needs, focus groups and interviews with regional&#13;
managers revealed a lack of awareness about ESSD's learning program. In general,&#13;
these managers equated the learning program with ESSD week and were not consistently&#13;
familiar with other offerings. They also did not necessarily know how to learn about the&#13;
ESSD learning program or whom to contact if they wanted to offer input. These findings&#13;
indicated that the KSL team's internal processes for strategic planning and program&#13;
development should include a comprehensive communications strategy to connect better&#13;
with its network audiences.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2.6     The perspectives of regional managers provided important insights into the&#13;
challenges facing ESSD's KSL team. Managers had minimal knowledge about the&#13;
program but also seemed to be largely satisfied: several echoed the sentiment that ESSD&#13;
week in FY05 was of "phenomenal quality." When asked to reflect on the larger ESSD&#13;
learning program, managers generally noted that network learning was a relatively low&#13;
priority. Common themes voiced by managers are presented in box 2.2.&#13;
&#13;
Box 2.2. Comments from managers illustrating dominant themes&#13;
&#13;
  Lack of awareness about ESSD's KSL team and learning plan&#13;
&#13;
      o   "I think there is a communication breakdown. I have no idea who is the learning coordinator in&#13;
          [sector] and I am on the sector board. "&#13;
&#13;
      o   "It's not my top priority to understand what learning is offered. Most of the courses are&#13;
          irrelevant to staff in the field and the bulk of my staff are in the field, so I don't pay any&#13;
          attention, and I don't try to understand what is in the ESSD learning plan."&#13;
&#13;
  Limited responsibility of managers to connect staff with ESSD learning opportunities&#13;
&#13;
      o   "Bank staff are voracious learners, intellectually curious: they find their own learning&#13;
          opportunities as they need them...As a manager, my role is to prevent operational gaffes, so I&#13;
          tend to focus on teamwork and behavioral issues. I never think to say of course you should&#13;
          stay updated in your field."&#13;
&#13;
      o   "An ESSD professional has to have technical expertise and is working as a professional and&#13;
          is inclined to update skills. That responsibility [to find the learning opportunities] does not fall&#13;
          on the manager."&#13;
&#13;
  Few incentives for staff to develop specialized technical expertise&#13;
&#13;
      o   "The incentive framework here, what a TTL [task team leader] needs to be promoted, requires&#13;
          an integrator rather than a specialist. A TTL needs to know many areas, the politics of one's&#13;
          own unit, and good negotiation skills. No project is just one discipline. A pure technical&#13;
          specialist has fewer promotional opportunities."&#13;
&#13;
      o   "Staff don't necessarily want technical courses. You need a strong technical background to&#13;
          be hired, but then you need to have broad knowledge to understand the general strategy for&#13;
          your country. For narrow technical expertise, we can bring in a consultant."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Focus groups and interviews with regional sector managers and directors, March to May, 2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.7      The limited understanding about ESSD's program among managers was not&#13;
surprising given that the learning program focused on crosscutting themes and offered&#13;
content across all Bank operations. The program championed issues for sustainable&#13;
development rather than targeting a static group of clients (described more in chapter 3),&#13;
and the activities could not always be easily distinguished from those of other staff&#13;
learning providers in the Bank. The need for more effective dissemination about ESSD&#13;
learning activities was therefore part of a broader challenge wherein ESSD's KSL team&#13;
did not yet benefit effectively from the Bank's larger staff learning infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
2.8     ESSD has championed the synergy of learning and knowledge-sharing activities&#13;
and products for staff since FY04, sometimes at the forefront or even outside of the&#13;
Bank's larger staff learning infrastructure. The Bank's Learning Board was not&#13;
reconstituted into the KLB until FY06. The structure of the LMS in FY06 supported the&#13;
recording of individual learning events but not the important contextual information&#13;
showing how events connect into coherent programs. Bank-wide definitions for KSL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
events remained elusive for ESSD's KSL team, causing the network to code activities&#13;
and products within three tentative categories: knowledge generation, knowledge sharing&#13;
and learning, and information management.&#13;
&#13;
2.9                  The challenges associated with Bank-wide definitions and structures provide&#13;
important context for this evaluation in FY06 and are explored throughout this report. A&#13;
key issue described in the next section is that no central information source accurately&#13;
reflected ESSD's offerings and products, so managers and staff who did not know who&#13;
offered learning focused on specific crosscutting themes would have difficulty&#13;
identifying opportunities available through ESSD's learning program.&#13;
&#13;
                            THE SCOPE AND SCALE OF ESSD'S LEARNING PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
2.10                 To provide staff with the skills and knowledge needed to achieve network&#13;
business objectives, ESSD's KSL team offered a multilayered program in FY05 and&#13;
FY06, with a core of learning courses and events recorded in the LMS. These were&#13;
supplemented by nonformal, short-format sessions and a portfolio of KSL products. The&#13;
learning program for FY05 focused in particular on building the capacity of ESSD's KSL&#13;
staff, so that they, in turn, could develop effective KSL events and products for their&#13;
constituencies in the future.&#13;
&#13;
                       Figure 2.1: ESSD learning events or programs in FY05 and FY06&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     100&#13;
                                                 84&#13;
&#13;
       st             80&#13;
&#13;
         en                   61                      62&#13;
           evforeb    60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      40&#13;
                  muN     27&#13;
                                      22 23&#13;
                      20&#13;
                                                            4   2       3    5      2    0     0    2&#13;
                      0&#13;
                         Brown bag   Courses   Workshops    Sector    Study tours Team-based Conferences&#13;
                          lunches                           weeks                   action&#13;
                                                                                   learning&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         2005 (142 events) 2006 (155 events)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Source: Learning Management System, September 2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.11                 The KLB tracks the numbers and types of learning events via the LMS and&#13;
provided data on the events offered by ESSD as the main sponsor in FY05 and FY06.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2The LMS became the Bank's data system for staff learning in FY06 and continued to evolve during the&#13;
course of this evaluation. Although the KLB encourages collaboration across VPUs in delivering learning&#13;
programs, the LMS did not yet have the capability to report cosponsored events as of December 2006.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
As the official record of the program's core offerings, these data are shown in figure 2.1.&#13;
In contrast, quarterly reports from the ESSD KSL team posted on ESSD's intranet and&#13;
reflections from managers and staff indicated that these data provided an inaccurate&#13;
profile. For example, ESSD's quarterly report to the KLB for the first quarter of FY06&#13;
stated that "ESSD has delivered 27 knowledge-sharing and learning events including&#13;
training courses, seminars, workshops, fieldtrips, and BBLs with a total of 716&#13;
participants." In contrast, the LMS reported that ESSD had delivered eight events&#13;
during the first quarter of FY06 (four brown bag lunches, three workshops, and one&#13;
study tour) with a total of 171 participants.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.12    The LMS was a new and evolving data system in FY06, and LMS data were of&#13;
limited use in this study. The underreporting of events indicated that course providers&#13;
(or designated responsible parties) were not consistently entering data on learning&#13;
activities. The LMS administrator noted that data on event duration were unreliable for&#13;
FY06. The counts of events alone did not provide a meaningful profile: for example,&#13;
ESSD week and social development days were all collectively entered as one event&#13;
(sector week), whereas a social development video shown three times in one day was&#13;
counted as three separate learning events (brown bag lunches). Finally, the focus of the&#13;
LMS on recording formal learning activities meant that a number of innovative&#13;
knowledge-sharing and learning opportunities provided by ESSD were not reflected by&#13;
LMS data.&#13;
&#13;
2.13    Examples of KSL programs and products not recorded in the LMS either by&#13;
design or by omission are shown in box 2.3. These initiatives were important&#13;
components of the learning program in FY05 and FY06, in many cases providing&#13;
opportunities and online resources to staff in country offices.&#13;
&#13;
2.14    Overall, ESSD provided a diverse learning program in FY05 and FY06 with a&#13;
complex mix of learning events and KSL products. Individual programs and products&#13;
often focused on crosscutting themes. The participation of network staff in ESSD&#13;
learning events and the role of various factors in influencing attendance are explored in&#13;
chapter 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3ESSD's knowledge and learning coordinator provided this data on learning events in the quarterly report&#13;
in response to a question asking for a summary of the learning plan status and significant achievements&#13;
during the quarter. Subsequent quarterly reports did not include the same question and focused instead on&#13;
achievements during the past 12 months.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Box 2.3. ESSD KSL programs and products that did not appear in the Learning&#13;
                              Catalogue (FY05) or the LMS (FY06)&#13;
&#13;
 o Peer exchanges. Program for country office staff to learn from peers across regions and/or family&#13;
       groups through visiting another country office, undertaking a field or site study, joining a mission, or&#13;
       participating in operational or analytical work.&#13;
&#13;
 o Group mentoring. Mentors and mentees work across headquarters and country office locations&#13;
       for a mutual learning program based on distance learning methods, including self-paced and&#13;
       instructor-led e-learning, videoconferences, and performance support tools.&#13;
&#13;
 o Hub training and study tours. These programs were organized to make core training courses&#13;
       accessible to country office staff and to provide exposure to development projects. An example of&#13;
       a hub training event not recorded in LMS is "Approaches to integrated rural development," held in&#13;
       December 2005 in Morocco and Tunisia.&#13;
&#13;
 o Grants. Awards through three programs (KSL innovation grants, product grants, and electronic&#13;
       and blended-learning grants) supported various knowledge and learning initiatives, including the&#13;
       development of e-learning modules and performance support multimedia tools.&#13;
&#13;
 o Online courses and performance support tools. Selection includes face-to-face and e-learning&#13;
       prototypes for 11 courses and modules, including an online course for community driven&#13;
       development, tools for the SDV orientation, and a CD-ROM on social accountability.&#13;
&#13;
 o KSL resource pack. A step-by-step guide and a set of quick reference tools for designing and&#13;
       organizing high quality KSL products and processes.&#13;
&#13;
 o CD-ROM. Highlights and materials from the KSL capacity enhancement series, in a format&#13;
       conducive to self-paced learning.&#13;
&#13;
 o GEMS for sustainable development. Four video interviews that can be used as stand-alone&#13;
       learning inputs or in combination with other sessions and programs to stimulate dialogue, provide&#13;
       information, discuss experiences, or present ESSD's vision of KSL. The interviews are&#13;
       supplemented with earlier presentations and interviews from the KSL open house, ESSD week, and&#13;
       development marketplace FY05.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Sources: Quarterly reports submitted to the KLB and ESSD's KSL intranet&#13;
&#13;
 Note: The LMS is not designed at this point to list knowledge products or to advertise grants. The selection of&#13;
 offerings presented here illustrates the degree to which the LMS did not yet reflect ESSD's comprehensive learning&#13;
 program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 3.         PARTICIPATION IN ESSD'S LEARNING PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
3.1       The business of sustainable development is crosscutting, and ESSD's learning&#13;
program served staff throughout the Bank in FY05 and FY06. This evaluation explored&#13;
the patterns of participation in the program and the factors that influenced whether staff&#13;
attended ESSD learning events.4 Overall, staff mapped to ESSD demanded learning to&#13;
address a broad range of goals--from becoming aware of new ideas and emerging issues&#13;
in their sectors to developing advanced, specialized technical expertise. In both years,&#13;
participation in ESSD learning was highest among staff who were based at headquarters,&#13;
in the ESSD VPU, or new to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                   PATTERNS OF PARTICIPATION&#13;
&#13;
3.2       ESSD's learning program in FY05 served at least 3,406 nonunique participants,&#13;
with 1,604 (47 percent) of these mapped to ESSD.5 The program in FY06 reached at&#13;
least 3,812 nonunique participants, with 1,245 (33 percent) of these mapped to ESSD.&#13;
This overview of participation provides insight into the reach of the program, targeting&#13;
audiences throughout the Bank to advocate for sector-related issues and delivering&#13;
training on safeguards across all Bank operations.&#13;
&#13;
Overview of participants mapped to ESSD&#13;
&#13;
3.3       As part of the network's anchor, the KSL team focused specifically on providing&#13;
ESSD staff with the skills and knowledge they needed to conduct the Bank's business.&#13;
Human resource (HR) data indicated that there were 744 staff mapped to ESSD at the end&#13;
of FY05, and 75 percent (561) had attended at least one learning event. In June 2006,&#13;
there were 731 staff mapped to ESSD, and 60 percent (438) had attended at least one&#13;
ESSD learning event during FY06.6&#13;
&#13;
3.4       These rates of participation in at least one ESSD learning event showed a notable&#13;
decrease from FY05 to FY06. This change could be explained in part by the fact that&#13;
ESSD week, which attracts many network staff, was not offered in FY06. ARD did offer&#13;
&#13;
4 Data on participation in ESSD events in FY05 and FY06 were extracted from the LMS and supplemented&#13;
with lists provided by ESSD's knowledge and learning coordinator. Because not all events appear in the&#13;
LMS (as discussed in chapter 2) and not all events that do appear have participants listed, the numbers&#13;
presented throughout this chapter should be considered minimum levels.&#13;
5 Information on participants was available for 128 events in FY05 and 142 events in FY06. The numbers&#13;
reported reflect the simple cumulative total of participants in all events, so individuals are counted multiple&#13;
times if they attended multiple events. The number of unique individuals who attended ESSD learning&#13;
events in FY05 was 1,444. The number of unique individuals attending ESSD learning events in FY06 was&#13;
1,723.&#13;
6 These rates were calculated using PeopleSoft data through June 30, 2005 for FY05 and through June 20,&#13;
2006 for FY06.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rural days in FY06, but these had substantially lower attendance than ESSD week. In&#13;
addition, the overall program included many KSL tools and products in FY06 (discussed&#13;
in chapter 2) that were not recorded in the LMS.&#13;
&#13;
3.5        The general profile of ESSD staff who participated in at least one learning event&#13;
in FY05 or FY06 and the characteristics of all network staff are shown in table 3.1.&#13;
Individual learning events serve categories of staff, but over time, the program should&#13;
address the ESSD-related learning needs of all or most network staff. The profile of all&#13;
network staff therefore highlights some important implications for the learning program.&#13;
In keeping with the Bank's emphasis on agriculture and rural development, ARD staff&#13;
comprise the largest sector.7 The programs, events, and products offered must develop&#13;
locally appropriate technical expertise for a staff that is concentrated largely at&#13;
headquarters but also located in many country offices. Key stakeholders include many&#13;
senior staff with extensive experience in Bank operations but also a large number of staff&#13;
who are new to the Bank.&#13;
                  Table 3.1. Profiles of ESSD participants and all ESSD staff&#13;
&#13;
                                                 ESSD staff who participated in ESSD  All ESSD staff (June 2006,&#13;
                                                   learning in FY05 or FY06 (n=660)             n=731)&#13;
&#13;
Location&#13;
World Bank headquarters                                  481                  73%       508            69%&#13;
Country office                                           179                  27%       223            31%&#13;
&#13;
Sector&#13;
ARD                                                      290                  44%       308            42%&#13;
Environment                                              225                  34%       255            35%&#13;
Social development                                       144                  22%       167            23%&#13;
Primary VPUa&#13;
ESSD                                                     117                  18%       116            16%&#13;
Africa region                                            122                  18%       130            18%&#13;
Europe and Central Asia (ECA) region                      67                  10%        78            11%&#13;
South Asia (SAR) region                                   74                  11%        89            12%&#13;
East Asia and Pacific (EAP) region                        90                  14%       112            15%&#13;
Latin America and Caribbean (LCR) region                  83                  13%        87            12%&#13;
Middle East and North Africa (MNA) region                 41                   6%        41             6%&#13;
Global Environment Facility                               19                   3%        21             3%&#13;
World Bank Institute                                      14                   2%        14             2%&#13;
Development economics and chief&#13;
economist                                                 10                   2%        15             2%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Length of time in Bank&#13;
New Bank employee (hired in 2003 or later)               158                  24%       178            24%&#13;
&#13;
Grade Level                                               24                   4%        26             4%&#13;
GE&#13;
GF-GG                                                    480                  73%       520            71%&#13;
GH and above                                             156                  24%       185            25%&#13;
&#13;
Source: HR data extracted from PeopleSoft, June 2005 and June 2006.&#13;
aThis list includes the most common VPUs. Other VPUs throughout the Bank have staff mapped to ESSD, but none of&#13;
these has more than five staff in the pool of ESSD participants for FY05 and FY06.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7As noted in the World Bank Annual Report 2006, agriculture is a vital part of the Bank's work, reflected&#13;
by the $1.8 billion in Bank lending in FY06 and the selection of agriculture as the focus of the upcoming&#13;
2008 World Development Report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3.6     Overall, the characteristics of ESSD staff who participated in at least one ESSD&#13;
learning event were similar to those of all network staff in FY06.&#13;
&#13;
Numbers of events attended by ESSD staff&#13;
&#13;
3.7     ESSD-mapped staff participated in an average of 2.2 ESSD learning events in&#13;
FY05 and 1.7 events in FY06. The number of events attended varied significantly&#13;
depending on participants' locations, VPUs, sectors, grade levels, and length of time in&#13;
the Bank: 8&#13;
&#13;
        Location. In both years, headquarters staff participated in more ESSD learning&#13;
        events on average than country office staff.&#13;
&#13;
        VPU / region. In both years, staff in the ESSD VPU tended to participate in more&#13;
        ESSD learning events than those affiliated with any region or other VPU.&#13;
&#13;
        Sector. ARD staff attended fewer events in FY05 on average than those in&#13;
        environment or social development. In FY06, participation did not differ&#13;
        significantly by sector.&#13;
&#13;
        Grade level. In FY05, junior staff tended to participate in more ESSD learning&#13;
        events on average than senior staff. Those at the GE level participated in more&#13;
        events than those at the GF-GG levels, and all of these staff (GE-GG) participated&#13;
        in more events than those at the GH level or above. In FY06, the rates of&#13;
        participation did not vary significantly by grade level.&#13;
&#13;
        Length of time in the Bank. In both years, new staff who had joined the Bank in&#13;
        2003 or later participated in more activities on average than those who had&#13;
        worked at the Bank for four years or more.&#13;
&#13;
3.8     The decrease in the average number of events attended from FY05 to FY06 could&#13;
be consistent with the objectives of ESSD's learning plan given that the agenda in FY06&#13;
emphasized greater on-the-job support and guidance through KSL products such as&#13;
performance support tools. However, the lower participation rates among regional&#13;
staff--especially those based in country offices--suggests a need for the program to&#13;
increase accessibility for these audiences.&#13;
&#13;
3.9     Overall, these findings are consistent with the program description presented in&#13;
chapter 2. The strategic redesign of staff learning and knowledge sharing entailed&#13;
building the capacity of staff at headquarters who design and organize KSL initiatives, so&#13;
that the anchor could better address the needs of the network. The disappearance of&#13;
differences in participation by sector and grade level in FY06 could indicate that the&#13;
program had become more unified in addressing staff learning needs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8Throughout the report, differences in means or percentages are reported only if they are significant at the&#13;
p&lt;0.05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Participation by staff outside of ESSD&#13;
&#13;
3.10    The crosscutting nature of sustainable development obliges the KSL program to&#13;
target issues rather than predefined audiences. ARD must educate those focused on&#13;
human health about such issues as avian flu. Rural days included a session on agriculture&#13;
and the World Trade Organization, with meaningful policy discussions warranting the&#13;
involvement of trade specialists in the Bank's poverty reduction and economic&#13;
management network as well as staff from the International Finance Corporation and the&#13;
Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency. These examples highlight the context of&#13;
ESSD's learning program, which serves many Bank personnel who are not mapped to the&#13;
network. In FY06, 1,285 non-ESSD staff attended at least one ESSD learning event.9&#13;
Examining the general characteristics of this group for FY06 provides a more complete&#13;
understanding of the program's audiences:&#13;
&#13;
        Forty-four percent were not regular Bank staff (with no grade levels assigned).&#13;
        These included consultants, temporary staff, and junior professionals.&#13;
&#13;
        Eighty-nine percent were based at headquarters.&#13;
&#13;
        Sixty-two percent had been employed by the Bank for five or fewer years.&#13;
&#13;
        Of the 725 with grade levels assigned, about half (54 percent) were GF or GG,&#13;
        and 23 percent were ACS staff (GA-GD) participating in professional and&#13;
        technical training. Fourteen percent were senior level staff (GH and above), and&#13;
        the remaining 9 percent were at the GE level.&#13;
&#13;
3.11    Overall, the profile of participants outside of the network portrayed a far-reaching&#13;
learning program offered by ESSD that served mainly headquarters-based Bank staff at&#13;
all levels and across all VPUs. These numbers underscore the importance of effective&#13;
communication strategies to reach appropriate audiences for specific initiatives.&#13;
&#13;
                            FACTORS INFLUENCING PARTICIPATION&#13;
&#13;
3.12    The top priority of ESSD's KSL program in FY05 and FY05 was to support&#13;
network staff in conducting the Bank's business. This evaluation focused on ESSD staff&#13;
as the primary consumers of ESSD's learning program and explored the reasons why&#13;
they participate in ESSD learning events.&#13;
&#13;
Perspectives of participants&#13;
&#13;
3.13    A survey of ESSD staff who had participated in ESSD's learning events in FY05&#13;
or FY06 asked respondents to rate the importance of six goals for motivating them to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9Fewer data were available regarding non-ESSD participants in FY05, so this section focuses on FY06.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
participate. The extent to which each goal was rated as important or very important is&#13;
shown in figure 3.1.10&#13;
&#13;
3.14    Five of the six goals listed were identified as important or very important by a&#13;
majority of respondents, indicating strong demand among staff for learning in these areas.&#13;
Overall, respondents assigned greater importance to enhancing their current job&#13;
performance and becoming aware of new ideas than to all other goals. Preparing for a&#13;
promotion or new position was significantly less important than all other factors.&#13;
&#13;
                Figure 3.1. Importance of goals in motivating participants&#13;
                                     to attend ESSD learning events&#13;
&#13;
              Enhancing job&#13;
          performance in current                       55                                 39              94&#13;
             position (n=196)&#13;
&#13;
         Becoming aware of new&#13;
           ideas and emerging                             63                                30           93&#13;
         issues in sector (n=196)&#13;
&#13;
         Networking and sharing                                                                        89&#13;
           information (n=193)               31                                58&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Developing / refreshing&#13;
           core sector skills and               36                             48                  84&#13;
            knowledge (n=191)&#13;
&#13;
           Developing advanced,&#13;
            specialized sector                  35                           41               76&#13;
            knowledge (n=191)&#13;
&#13;
         Preparing for promotion&#13;
         or new position (n=191)       17               23           40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  0              20             40             60            80            100&#13;
                                                             Percentage of respondents&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Very Important   Important&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Source: Survey of ESSD participants: "Indicate the importance of the following goals for motivating you to&#13;
                participate in learning activities provided by ESSD."&#13;
&#13;
        Note: Ratings for this item were based on a 5-point scale: not important at all, unimportant, neutral, important,&#13;
                and very important.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.15    In a few cases, the relative importance of individual goals varied significantly&#13;
among staff depending on their grade levels, sector, VPUs, and length of time in the&#13;
Bank. These differences reflected variations in the demands for staff learning, but ratings&#13;
by staff based in country offices did not differ from those of staff based at headquarters&#13;
for any of the goals listed. The following findings could be useful to KSL team members&#13;
in assessing how best to meet the needs of their constituencies:&#13;
&#13;
        VPU.11 Respondents affiliated with AFR or ECA tended to assign higher&#13;
        importance to networking and sharing information than their colleagues in EAP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10The survey questionnaire with frequencies of responses is in appendix B. Survey results presented&#13;
throughout this report reflect the percentages of those respondents who expressed an opinion.&#13;
11Analyses of VPU subgroups throughout this report focus on the regions and the ESSD VPU.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        EAP staff generally placed more importance on becoming aware of new ideas&#13;
        than those in MNA.&#13;
&#13;
        Sector. ARD staff and those in the environment sector tended to assign higher&#13;
        importance to enhancing their performance in their current positions than did staff&#13;
        in social development.&#13;
&#13;
        Grade level. Staff at the GF-GG levels assigned higher importance on average to&#13;
        preparing for a promotion or new position than those at the GH level or above.&#13;
&#13;
        Length of time in the Bank. Relatively new staff (four to eight years at Bank)&#13;
        assigned higher importance to developing advanced, specialized sector knowledge&#13;
        than new staff (zero to three years) and more seasoned employees (nine years or&#13;
        more).&#13;
&#13;
3.16    These variations offer greater understanding of the factors that motivated staff to&#13;
participate in ESSD's learning program and the types of content or programming that&#13;
they demanded to have their learning needs met. The extent to which ESSD's learning&#13;
program delivered quality programming for FY05 and FY06 in the areas considered to be&#13;
important is examined in chapter 4.&#13;
&#13;
Perspectives of managers&#13;
&#13;
3.17    Nineteen sector managers and directors reflected during interviews and focus&#13;
groups on their roles in motivating staff to participate in learning events. These&#13;
discussions explored how managers assessed staff learning needs and linked their staff&#13;
with appropriate opportunities. The most dominant theme centered on the lack of time&#13;
for training given the many demands of Bank operations. Another common theme was&#13;
that managers did not have the time or expertise to direct staff to appropriate learning&#13;
opportunities, both because the overall performance evaluation process was too&#13;
perfunctory and because they were not sure how to find more specialized learning&#13;
tailored to individual staff. Comments illustrating these themes are in box 3.1.&#13;
&#13;
 Box. 3.1. Comments from managers on what affects staff participation in learning&#13;
&#13;
   o   "Our staff get hardly any training, but that is not necessarily because it is not offered. It is because&#13;
       they do not have time. I think we have used 19 percent of our training budget this fiscal year."&#13;
&#13;
   o   "We do a terrible job [assessing staff learning needs]. For the OPE process, we have three pieces&#13;
       of paper...and we do the results assessment only because we don't like having to focus on three&#13;
       different IT systems. We just tell staff to put down on the main form what [learning events] they&#13;
       would like to take, and we discuss it, and then the next year we review what happened and say `oh&#13;
       dear' and put down the same things again."&#13;
&#13;
   o   "There is a trade-off between the sort of generic learning and networking of ESSD week and&#13;
       having much more tailored training to the specific technical needs of individual staff. There is not&#13;
       the money to do both in one year. That's for sure. It is easier to come to ESSD week because it is&#13;
       there, but if we were better managers, maybe we would put more effort into helping our staff do&#13;
       more tailored training, but we don't have the time or the knowledge to do that."&#13;
&#13;
   o   "As managers, we are told to take learning more seriously, but in the end we are judged on the&#13;
       delivery of projects. Deliverables will always have a higher priority than training."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       4.      QUALITYAND EFFECTIVENESS OF ESSD'S&#13;
                             LEARNING PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
4.1     This evaluation explored the quality and effectiveness of the network's learning&#13;
program in FY05 and FY06 by examining perceptions among ESSD-mapped staff and&#13;
managers in combination with participants' assessments of individual learning events.&#13;
Major stakeholders were satisfied with the program's overall quality but also&#13;
demonstrated an uncertainty about which learning events ESSD offered. Participants&#13;
indicated on average that the program was most effective in providing opportunities for&#13;
networking and raising awareness of emerging issues. Respondents in the ESSD VPU&#13;
were generally more satisfied with the program's quality and relevance than regional&#13;
staff.&#13;
&#13;
                                    OVERALL QUALITY&#13;
&#13;
4.2     ESSD's learning plans for FY05 and FY06 emphasized that the objectives of the&#13;
learning program were to support the strategic priorities of the ESSD business plan. For&#13;
FY05, the learning plan included some measurable objectives such as "increase the&#13;
number and improve the quality of cross-sector learning programs." The FY06 learning&#13;
plan listed priority areas to support rather than measurable objectives and then presented&#13;
"a brief profile of knowledge-sharing and learning activities to be offered by ESSD&#13;
during FY06." The limited information available on the objectives of the learning&#13;
program, the planned activities, and the events actually delivered across both years&#13;
prevented an assessment of how well the program was aligned with the strategic priorities&#13;
of the ESSD business plan as intended.&#13;
&#13;
4.3     Given these limitations, focus group discussions with managers and members of&#13;
ESSD's KSL team framed the context through which to examine the program's quality.&#13;
The survey of participants then systematically explored the experiences of staff&#13;
(including managers) with the learning program in FY05 and FY06. Survey respondents&#13;
provided a summary rating of the program's overall quality, and nearly two-thirds (65&#13;
percent) rated the program as very good (17 percent) or good (48 percent) (figure 4.1).&#13;
These ratings varied little among subgroups: the only notable difference was that&#13;
respondents whose primary VPU was ESSD provided higher ratings on average than&#13;
those from EAP or ECA.&#13;
&#13;
4.4     An important consideration in reviewing the ratings of program participants is&#13;
that respondents did not necessarily know which learning events had been offered as part&#13;
of ESSD's KSL program. To explain better the overall assessments of quality, the survey&#13;
questionnaire prompted respondents to describe one positive experience and one negative&#13;
experience that they had had with ESSD's program in FY05 or FY06. Despite these&#13;
instructions, comments from many staff reflected an understanding of staff learning as a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
monolithic entity in the Bank, with descriptions focusing on team leadership, regional&#13;
programs, voicemail training, Introductions to Bank Operations, and a range of other&#13;
non-ESSD learning events. This lack of differentiation among learning programs is an&#13;
important finding of this evaluation, with implications for the ratings on quality and&#13;
effectiveness discussed throughout this chapter.&#13;
&#13;
    Figure 4.1. Ratings by participants for the overall quality of the ESSD Learning&#13;
                                       Program in FY05 and FY06&#13;
&#13;
                                       Percentage of respondents (n=187)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            100&#13;
&#13;
             80&#13;
&#13;
             60                           48&#13;
&#13;
             40                                            29&#13;
&#13;
             20           17&#13;
                                                                               5              1&#13;
               0&#13;
                     Very good          Good               Fair               Poor         Very poor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Source: Survey of ESSD participants: "Rate the overall quality of the ESSD learning&#13;
        program based on your experiences with ESSD-related learning activities in FY05 and FY06."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.5     Among those survey respondents who did provide specific comments on ESSD-&#13;
related learning experiences, the positive examples cited tended to focus on the&#13;
networking and knowledge-sharing opportunities provided by sector fora (25&#13;
respondents) or on the direct relevance of the training to respondents' jobs in Bank&#13;
operations (18 respondents). Negative examples highlighted ways that offerings did not&#13;
meet participants' expectations due to a lack of relevance, the inappropriate level of&#13;
content, or poor organization.&#13;
&#13;
4.6     ESSD routinely receives feedback on the quality of individual staff learning&#13;
activities through assessments by participants at the end of events. By design, these&#13;
assessments focus on what is offered in the learning program rather than what is missing,&#13;
so they should not be used to gauge the program's overall quality. Nonetheless,&#13;
participants' satisfaction with learning events provides insights into ways that the&#13;
program is changing or areas that merit attention.&#13;
&#13;
4.7     WBIEG conducted participant assessments for a sample of ESSD learning&#13;
activities in FY05 and FY06, and the results are shown in table 4.1. These ratings reflect&#13;
a notable improvement from FY05 to FY06 in many areas; for example, 79 percent of&#13;
participants provided positive ratings for the overall quality of the training in FY05&#13;
compared with 91 percent in FY06.12 Given the heavy emphasis of ESSD's KSL&#13;
&#13;
12These ratings were based on a 5-point scale, where 1 was very low and 5 was very high. The Bank&#13;
benchmark for quality is 80 percent of respondents provide a rating of 4 or 5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
program on developing tools and building the capacity of its KSL staff in FY05, the&#13;
increase in positive assessments by participants in FY06 for various aspects related to&#13;
design and delivery is not surprising and provides evidence of the success of these&#13;
efforts.&#13;
&#13;
    Table 4.1. Participants' assessments of quality for ESSD learning activities&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          Percentage of respondents&#13;
           Question on participant assessment questionnaire             providing ratings of 4 or 5 on 5-&#13;
                                                                                  point scale&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           FY05                 FY06&#13;
                                                                         (30 events)         (39 events)&#13;
&#13;
    To what extent did the training fulfill your learning needs?             75                   84&#13;
&#13;
    To what extent did the training achieve its announced objectives?        77                   85&#13;
&#13;
    How would you rate the training content or subject matter?               79                   89&#13;
&#13;
    How would you rate the order in which the content was presented?         76                   87&#13;
&#13;
    How would you rate the materials used during the training?               72                   84&#13;
&#13;
    How would you rate the overall quality of the training?                  79                   91&#13;
&#13;
    How would you rate the overall usefulness of the training?               78                   89&#13;
&#13;
    How would you rate the relevance of this training to the Bank's          85                   87&#13;
    mission?&#13;
&#13;
    My knowledge/skills increased as a result of this training.              84                   91&#13;
&#13;
    The knowledge/skills gained through this training are directly           77                   85&#13;
    applicable to my job.&#13;
&#13;
   Source: WBIEG data from participants' assessment of quality&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.8     Participants' assessments of quality indicated that many ESSD staff valued their&#13;
ESSD-related learning experiences in FY05 and FY06, but the ratings cannot be used to&#13;
measure how well the entire ESSD learning program addressed staff learning needs. The&#13;
survey of participants explored many of the areas included in participants' assessments&#13;
but focused on reactions to and perceptions of the overall learning program rather than to&#13;
specific offerings. The following sections therefore focus on aspects related to quality:&#13;
the program's relevance, areas of effectiveness, learning design and delivery features, and&#13;
the extent to which participants applied the skills and knowledge they acquired in their&#13;
work.&#13;
&#13;
                                                      RELEVANCE&#13;
&#13;
4.9     Participants in ESSD's learning events were asked to reflect on their experience&#13;
with learning activities provided by ESSD and rate the relevance of the offerings in FY05&#13;
and FY06.13 Seventy percent of respondents rated the relevance as very good (23&#13;
percent) or good (47 percent). Twenty-three percent indicated that the relevance was fair.&#13;
Seven percent of respondents characterized the relevance of the learning choices offered&#13;
as poor (6 percent) or very poor (1 percent).&#13;
&#13;
4.10    These ratings for the program's overall relevance depended on the primary VPU&#13;
of respondents. Respondents in the ESSD VPU found offerings to be more relevant on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
13Responses to this item were based on a 5-point scale: very poor, poor, fair, good, and very good.&#13;
Respondents could also indicate that they had no opinion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
average than those in EAP, LCR, MNA, and SAR. No other variable appeared to&#13;
influence ratings for relevance, including whether respondents were based in country&#13;
offices, their sectors, or their length of time with the Bank. Although the lower&#13;
satisfaction among regional staff provides an indicator of possible program weaknesses,&#13;
this evaluation focused on a time period when the emphasis was on building the capacity&#13;
of staff to design and deliver KSL initiatives. These efforts could well have resulted in&#13;
lower satisfaction for a limited period until this expanded capacity could have an impact.&#13;
The findings regarding regional staff in this context therefore underscored the importance&#13;
of monitoring this dynamic carefully.&#13;
&#13;
                                       AREAS OF EFFECTIVENESS&#13;
&#13;
4.11    The survey of participants explored how well ESSD's learning program achieved&#13;
four key objectives for learning among ESSD staff in FY05 and FY06 (figure 4.2).&#13;
Ratings on the program's effectiveness were significantly higher for providing&#13;
opportunities for networking and raising awareness of new ideas than for developing core&#13;
sector skills and knowledge or for developing advanced, specialized sector knowledge.14&#13;
These results indicate that the program was most effective in those areas that were&#13;
deemed to be most important by participants (see figure 3.1).&#13;
&#13;
  Figure 4.2. Ratings on the effectiveness of the overall ESSD learning program in&#13;
                                                FY05 and FY06&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Providing opportunities&#13;
          for networking and&#13;
          knowledge sharing           23                       41                          29          6&#13;
&#13;
                (n=186)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Raising awareness of&#13;
       new ideas and emerging        20                         49                          22        8&#13;
       issues in sector (n=184)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Developing core sector&#13;
        skills and/or knowledge    13                    43                             36            7 1&#13;
                (n=181)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Developing advanced,&#13;
           specialized sector     10                  38                          39                12   2&#13;
          knowledge (n=176)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               0%            20%           40%            60%              80%          100%&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Percentage of Respondents&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Very good  Good    Fair   Poor     Very poor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Source: Survey of ESSD participants: "Rate the following aspects of the overall ESSD learning program based&#13;
                 on your experiences participating in ESSD-related learning activities in FY05 and FY06:"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14As noted earlier, some managers and staff demonstrated a limited understanding of which events were&#13;
included in ESSD's learning program, so respondents may have focused narrowly on sector weeks in&#13;
providing ratings for effectiveness.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.12      As described in chapter 3, ESSD staff demanded learning events in all four of&#13;
these areas, with a majority of respondents (at least 76 percent) indicating that each one&#13;
was an important or very important goal that motivated them to participate in learning&#13;
activities. The effectiveness ratings presented above can be used to explore how well the&#13;
program addressed the demand for learning in each area. Those respondents who&#13;
indicated that an area was important or very important but did not provide positive ratings&#13;
(good or very good) for the program's effectiveness appeared not to have their learning&#13;
needs fully addressed in FY05 and FY06.&#13;
&#13;
4.13      As shown in table 4.2, these participants who did not have their learning needs&#13;
met reflect a sizeable share of all respondents in each area--ranging from 26 percent to&#13;
39 percent. Noting the relative sizes of these groups and identifying whether&#13;
demographic variables appeared to influence effectiveness ratings provides useful&#13;
guidance for planning program improvements.&#13;
&#13;
 Table 4.2. Subgroups' satisfaction with the program's effectiveness&#13;
&#13;
       Area of effectiveness            Respondents whose demand                   Differences by subgroupb&#13;
                                       for learning was not satisfieda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Providing opportunities for                 57           31%                 Staff in ESSD and EAP tended to be&#13;
  networking and knowledge                                                     more satisfied than AFR staff&#13;
  sharing (n=186)                                                              Those at the GH grade level or&#13;
                                                                               above tended to be more satisfied&#13;
                                                                               than those at the GF or GG levels.&#13;
&#13;
  Raising awareness of new                    48           26%                 Staff in ESSD tended to be more&#13;
  ideas and emerging issues                                                    satisfied than those in ECA&#13;
  in sector (n=184)&#13;
&#13;
  Developing core sector                      61           34%                 No differences among subgroups&#13;
  skills and/or knowledge&#13;
  (n=181)&#13;
&#13;
  Developing advanced,                        67           39%                 Those at the GH grade level or&#13;
  specialized sector                                                           above tended to be more satisfied&#13;
  knowledge (n=176)                                                            than those at the GF or GG levels.&#13;
&#13;
 Source: Survey of ESSD participants&#13;
 aRespondents were included here if they rated the area as important or very important and then rated the program's&#13;
 effectiveness in that area as fair, poor, or very poor.&#13;
 bSubgroups in this analysis included location, sector, VPU, grade level, and years in the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.14      Overall, ESSD's learning program appeared to have been most effective in&#13;
satisfying the demand for raising awareness of new ideas and least effective in addressing&#13;
the need for developing advanced, specialized sector knowledge. An analysis of&#13;
responses by subgroup revealed a fairly consistent program across the network. The few&#13;
differences indicated that staff in the ESSD VPU or at a senior level (GH or above)&#13;
tended to be more satisfied with the program's effectiveness in some areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.15    While some managers questioned the priority of advanced, specialized technical&#13;
learning (discussed in chapter 2), input from staff indicated a strong demand for this type&#13;
of learning that was not addressed sufficiently by ESSD's program. The findings on&#13;
effectiveness based on participants' perceptions highlighted important challenges to the&#13;
program. An incremental process to improve the program's effectiveness should include&#13;
clear objectives for the learning program (presented in the learning plan) and then&#13;
disseminating these objectives and planned activities to relevant managers and staff so&#13;
that they know of opportunities that could address their demands. Once these basic&#13;
strategies have been implemented, monitoring staff satisfaction would likely provide&#13;
more specific guidance on content or resources needed to increase the program's&#13;
effectiveness.&#13;
&#13;
                  SATISFACTION WITH LEARNING DESIGN AND DELIVERY&#13;
&#13;
4.16    Aside from feedback on content, participants of ESSD learning events provided&#13;
ratings for the organization of events and the quality of speakers in the overall learning&#13;
program in FY05 and FY06. Two-thirds of respondents (67 percent) characterized the&#13;
organization of learning events (e.g., design and logistics) as very good (22 percent) or&#13;
good (45 percent), and 30 percent rated this as fair. For the quality of instructors or&#13;
speakers, 75 percent provided a rating of very good (26 percent) or good (49 percent),&#13;
and 22 percent rated this as fair. These ratings signal the need for improvements since&#13;
many participants (one quarter to one third) did not provide positive ratings for design or&#13;
delivery features. Nonetheless, these generalizations about the program across two years&#13;
may be of limited use given the indication by participants' assessments that quality&#13;
increased notably from FY05 to FY06 and evidence that many respondents did not&#13;
differentiate between ESSD's staff learning program and those offered by other VPUs.&#13;
&#13;
4.17    An important function of any staff learning program is to provide information on&#13;
planned activities to potential participants. Communication strategies must be tailored to&#13;
attract the appropriate target audiences and implemented far enough in advance so that&#13;
staff can fit learning into their schedules. The survey of participants explored this&#13;
function of the learning program, and 55 percent of respondents indicated that the&#13;
timeliness of information about upcoming learning offerings was very good (17 percent)&#13;
or good (38 percent). Thirty-four percent indicated that the timeliness of information was&#13;
fair.&#13;
&#13;
4.18    ESSD's strategies for disseminating information on upcoming offerings seem&#13;
especially important given that managers in focus groups and survey respondents in their&#13;
comments both demonstrated limited awareness about the scope of the program beyond&#13;
ESSD week. Respondents indicated how they learned about upcoming events by rating&#13;
the effectiveness of various communication methods used by the ESSD learning team.&#13;
As shown in figure 4.3, most respondents (94 percent) found e-mail announcements to be&#13;
very effective or effective while less than one third (31 percent) provided these positive&#13;
ratings for the learning management system or for ESSD's intranet KSL web page.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 Figure 4.3. Effectiveness of means to inform staff about upcoming learning events&#13;
&#13;
         E-mail announcements                       60&#13;
                 (n=191)                                                                  34         5 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Communication with        16&#13;
               peers (n=186)                                46                         22       10     6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Managers (n=186)       13             33                    22            11       20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Posters or fliers (n=180)  9            31                      29                 19      11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Learning management&#13;
              system (n=176)        9         22                   35                   20         15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Network web page&#13;
                    (n=179)         7         24                   32                  19         18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Newsletters (n=178) 2           25                    38                       21      13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  0%          20%           40%            60%              80%        100%&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Percentage of respondents&#13;
&#13;
               Very effective      Effective    Moderately effective       Slightly effective   Not effective&#13;
&#13;
      Source: Survey of ESSD participants: "How effective are the following means for helping you acquire timely&#13;
               information about ESSD learning events?"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.19    The relative effectiveness of various means to inform staff about upcoming events&#13;
has important implications for ESSD's learning program. Highly effective means such as&#13;
e-mail announcements and communication with peers generally require staff to be&#13;
reactive in addressing their learning needs. Staff learn of an interesting upcoming event&#13;
and decide whether to attend. The LMS was developed to serve in part as a central&#13;
information source for learning within the Bank, but the ratings from participants indicate&#13;
that the LMS is not yet effective for those staff who wish to be more proactive and select&#13;
a logical combination of events to attend over the next year or two.&#13;
&#13;
            USE OF SKILLS AND KNOWLEDGE ACQUIRED IN LEARNING EVENTS&#13;
&#13;
4.20    The survey of participants provided some information about how much&#13;
respondents used the skills and knowledge they acquired in ESSD learning events in&#13;
FY05 and FY06. While these findings are based only on self-reported data by&#13;
participants, they do present a glimpse into the possible impact of ESSD's learning&#13;
program over time.&#13;
&#13;
4.21    Two-thirds of ESSD participants (66 percent) used the skills and knowledge they&#13;
gained in ESSD learning events frequently or very frequently. This finding was based on&#13;
two separate questions, one focused on the use of knowledge and concepts and the&#13;
second focused on the use of skills and techniques.15 Thirty-four percent of respondents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
15For both questions, responses were based on a 5-point scale: never, rarely, occasionally, frequently, and&#13;
very frequently. The frequencies of responses to the individual questions are in appendix B.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
indicated that they had used the knowledge and concepts or skills and techniques only&#13;
occasionally or even less.&#13;
&#13;
4.22    Again, an analysis of demographic variables showed that the program had fairly&#13;
consistent results across all network staff, with only a few differences among subgroups:&#13;
&#13;
        Location. Staff based in country offices tended to use the skills and techniques&#13;
        they acquired more frequently than those in headquarters. Location appeared to&#13;
        have no influence on the frequency of use for knowledge and concepts.&#13;
&#13;
        VPU. Staff affiliated with AFR and LCR tended to use the skills and techniques&#13;
        they gained more frequently than staff in MNA.&#13;
&#13;
        Length of time with the Bank. Relatively new staff (four to eight years in the&#13;
        Bank) tended to use the skills and techniques they gained more frequently than&#13;
        new staff (zero to three years).&#13;
&#13;
4.23    To develop an understanding of why participants did or did not use the skills and&#13;
knowledge that they had acquired, the survey asked respondents to rate the importance of&#13;
various factors for influencing this use. As presented in figure 4.4, responses showed that&#13;
direct relevance to current job responsibilities and having time available to apply skills&#13;
and knowledge were relatively more important whereas the presence of an incentive&#13;
system or peer support was generally less important.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 4.4. Factors that influenced whether participants used skills and knowledge&#13;
&#13;
          Direct relevance to&#13;
        current job responsibility            39                                49                      88&#13;
                 (n=193)&#13;
&#13;
         Available time to apply                                                         70&#13;
                  (n=189)                  29                          41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       My unit's resources (staff&#13;
            and $) (n=183)                 29                       34              63&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Managerial support                                              54&#13;
                   (n=185)             18                 36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Peer support (n=181)       12              34                  46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Incentive system for staff                                 37&#13;
          in my unit (n=177)         11          26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  0            20             40             60                80           100&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Percentage of Respondents&#13;
&#13;
                                                            Very Important    Important&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Source: Survey of ESSD participants: "Rate the importance of the following factors for influencing whether or not&#13;
             you use the skills and knowledge you acquired in ESSD learning events."&#13;
     Note:  Responses were based on a 5-point scale: very important, important, neutral, unimportant, and not&#13;
             important at all.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.24     The factors identified as most important here (direct relevance and available time)&#13;
underscore the potential of on-the-job learning and learning from peers in teamwork.&#13;
ESSD's learning program has no control over participants' work schedules, but the&#13;
importance (and often shortage) of available time for applying new skills and knowledge&#13;
should be considered in designing learning events. Well-designed learning events are of&#13;
little value if target audiences are unable or unwilling to attend these events.&#13;
&#13;
                     SUGGESTIONS FOR FUTURE LEARNING FROM ESSD STAFF&#13;
&#13;
4.25     ESSD's KSL team conducted surveys of network staff in FY05 and FY06 to&#13;
collect data on staff learning needs and preferences. The survey of ESSD participants&#13;
supplemented those findings by soliciting priorities for future learning, suggestions for&#13;
learning offerings given the creation of the sustainable development network (SDN), and&#13;
other comments to guide program improvements.&#13;
&#13;
4.26     To gauge priorities for future learning among ESSD participants, the&#13;
questionnaire prompted respondents to rank four areas of learning. Figure 4.5 shows how&#13;
frequently each area was selected as the highest or second highest priority, confirming&#13;
that staff place diverse demands on the program that range from raising awareness of new&#13;
issues to developing specialized, technical knowledge.&#13;
&#13;
             Figure 4.5. Top priorities for learning among ESSD participants&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Emerging 'hot topic'                                                                       62&#13;
          issues (n=165)                       38                                 24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Advanced, specialized&#13;
        sector knowledge                   31                                 31                   62&#13;
            (n=162)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Core sector skills /&#13;
        knowledge (n=170)            18                         30                  48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  General operations skills&#13;
     / knowledge (n=177)             18                   21              39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             0                  20                      40                   60                   80&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Percentage of Respondents&#13;
&#13;
                                                          Top choice       Second choice&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Survey of ESSD participants: "Please rank (1-4) the following areas, according to your own learning interest and&#13;
         priorities."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.27      When asked to suggest new learning opportunities for FY07 or FY08, respondents&#13;
most frequently listed topics related to helping them understand the integration of ESSD&#13;
and INF.16 This collection of entries from at least 50 respondents focused on the vision,&#13;
goals, and work programs of the new SDN, clarification on the new organizational&#13;
structure, how the INF and ESSD teams will work together, and what the key INF issues&#13;
are related to individual ESSD sectors. Beyond the emphasis on the transition to the&#13;
SDN, comments frequently suggested learning topics that were not network-specific such&#13;
as improving skills for writing or for monitoring and evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
4.28      Finally, participants had the opportunity to offer other suggestions for improving&#13;
the effectiveness of the learning program in the future. Two dominant themes emerged&#13;
from the comments offered by 64 respondents:&#13;
&#13;
          Involve CO staff more in the learning program. Twenty-one respondents&#13;
          suggested increasing the opportunities available for CO staff by offering more&#13;
          study tours, strategically selecting country office locations to hold face-to-face&#13;
          learning events, and offering more distance learning events. Many of these&#13;
          participants also noted the need for regional and CO staff to be involved in&#13;
          designing and delivering learning events.&#13;
&#13;
          Improve the relevance of offerings for participants. Sixteen comments provided&#13;
          advice on how to increase the relevance of learning events, usually through&#13;
          including concrete examples from Bank operations. Five of these participants&#13;
          also noted that relevance could be improved simply by providing a better&#13;
          description of the target audience so that staff would know which events were&#13;
          appropriate according to their levels and interests.&#13;
&#13;
4.29      Suggestions from participants provided some guidance on how better to address&#13;
staff demand for learning, particularly when considered in combination with the closed-&#13;
ended survey ratings, the available data on learning activities, and the insights provided&#13;
by managers and learning coordinators (appendix C). Conclusions and recommendations&#13;
for ESSD's learning program based on all data sources are presented in the next chapter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16Respondents were prompted to list up to three suggestions for orientation sessions and three suggestions&#13;
for training courses; however, similar types of responses appeared in both categories.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       5.      CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
&#13;
5.1     ESSD has increasingly integrated staff learning and knowledge sharing since&#13;
FY04 and developed KSL structures, processes, and capacity to support a next generation&#13;
learning program. These initiatives yielded a comprehensive program with coordinated&#13;
series of learning events supplemented by KSL products and resources. Despite these&#13;
efforts, the program was not adequately supported by the existing staff learning&#13;
infrastructure at the Bank in FY05 and FY06 and was not well understood by network&#13;
managers and staff. The findings and recommendations of this evaluation, summarized&#13;
below, identify some steps that the KSL team, the CLO, and the KLB can implement to&#13;
optimize learning provided by the new Sustainable Development network.&#13;
&#13;
                        SUGGESTED ACTIONS FOR THE KSL TEAM&#13;
&#13;
5.2     To increase the synergy and efficiency of staff learning across all network units,&#13;
ESSD established centralized structures and processes to shape the overall learning&#13;
program. The result for FY05 and FY06 was a consistent program, with few differences&#13;
in quality, relevance, or effectiveness across sectors. Furthermore, the initiative to&#13;
develop capacity among KSL staff in FY05 appeared to have contributed to a notable&#13;
improvement in participants' assessments of quality in FY06. The findings of this&#13;
evaluation did not signal the need for major changes to the current model but instead&#13;
indicated areas for improvement within it. Recommended actions for the KSL team are&#13;
presented below in the order in which they should occur.&#13;
&#13;
Knowledge and learning results framework&#13;
&#13;
5.3     ESSD's KSL team held strategic planning meetings each year to set priorities for&#13;
the overall program, but this evaluation did not produce evidence that the program was&#13;
aligned with business objectives or effectively addressing staff demands for learning.&#13;
The lack of clear objectives for the learning program, detailed information on how&#13;
planned activities support learning objectives, or data on the delivery and content of&#13;
learning activities prevented a systematic assessment of how well the program's offerings&#13;
supported the strategic priorities of ESSD's business plan.&#13;
&#13;
5.4     The KSL team should establish measurable objectives for its learning program&#13;
with associated indicators to gauge how well the program is addressing network business&#13;
needs. The learning plan template and toolkit provided by the CLO's office has fostered&#13;
some improvements for FY07, but the translation from the network's strategic priorities&#13;
to specific learning objectives can be strengthened. In what ways should the skills and&#13;
knowledge of staff be developed to achieve the network's priorities? Among which&#13;
groups or levels of staff? How will SDN assess the degree to which learning objectives&#13;
have been achieved? The KSL team must refine its learning plan in collaboration with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             26&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the CLO's office (discussed below) to create a useful tool for designing and delivering&#13;
the learning program and assessing its success vis-à-vis strategic priorities.&#13;
&#13;
Data management&#13;
&#13;
5.5     Input from sector managers and program participants suggested that many of the&#13;
program's stakeholders did not have an accurate understanding of what learning events&#13;
and products ESSD offered. A majority of participants did not find the LMS to be an&#13;
effective resource for finding information about planned learning activities in FY06,&#13;
either because staff did not know how to use the system appropriately or because&#13;
providers did not enter consistent and desirable details about upcoming events.&#13;
&#13;
5.6     To improve the quality and use of the LMS, the KSL team should establish&#13;
standard guidelines for entering learning activity data and a quality assurance process to&#13;
support improved data management. The LMS is still a relatively new data system at the&#13;
Bank, and learning teams must provide feedback and support to ensure that this is a&#13;
useful tool to facilitate and track staff learning. Recommendations for continuing to&#13;
refine the data quality and use of the LMS include:&#13;
&#13;
        Establish clear guidelines for all providers of staff learning for what types of&#13;
        events or programs should be recorded in the LMS. The focus on combining&#13;
        learning and knowledge sharing and delivering coherent programs rather than&#13;
        isolated events may have resulted in confusion about which activities should&#13;
        appear in the LMS. The KSL team should create standards for recording events&#13;
        to promote consistency across the network's learning program.&#13;
&#13;
        Organize and present details about learning events so that staff can easily choose&#13;
        and schedule activities most appropriate for them. At minimum, the system&#13;
        should identify events by theme or issue, list the date(s) or estimated period when&#13;
        the events will occur, indicate the general format or event type, stipulate the level&#13;
        of expertise required by participants, and describe the expected scope or depth of&#13;
        the content. Specification of expected outcomes would also be desirable.&#13;
&#13;
        Clarify accountability for data quality and institute a quality assurance process.&#13;
        The LMS can be a reliable tool to facilitate and track staff learning only if&#13;
        learning coordinators or course providers enter consistent data on learning&#13;
        activities and participation. Appropriate use of the system is in everyone's best&#13;
        interest, both to link staff with optimal learning programs and to provide the&#13;
        learning team with data on learning provision and participation over time. The&#13;
        KSL team should therefore clarify who is responsible for entering data on&#13;
        learning events and establish a system for checking data quality (at least for a&#13;
        sample) and following up as needed.&#13;
&#13;
        Test usability of system and provide feedback to the LMS administrator. The new&#13;
        system is intended to serve learning needs, and the KSL team should ensure that&#13;
        the system is a useful tool for the network. Key steps could include actively&#13;
        testing the system to monitor functions and improvements or soliciting feedback&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        on usability from a sample of staff. Constructive input from users is necessary to&#13;
        guide the CLO's office in refining the LMS to be an optimal data system.&#13;
&#13;
5.7     Efforts to improve the quality of data in the LMS should be supplemented with a&#13;
clear communications strategy to educate staff and managers better about their network's&#13;
learning program and how the LMS can identify opportunities to address staff learning&#13;
needs.&#13;
&#13;
Accountability and continuous improvement&#13;
&#13;
5.8     ESSD already had various structures and strategies in place to incorporate&#13;
evaluation findings into the planning, design, and delivery of learning activities. The&#13;
KSL team had a specialist responsible for participant assessments of most network&#13;
learning activities. The team had also conducted regular needs assessments and selected&#13;
certain programs for tracer studies. Despite this promising existing infrastructure for&#13;
evaluating and informing program activities, this study did identify some areas where&#13;
ongoing monitoring is needed. For example, program satisfaction was notably higher for&#13;
staff based in the anchor compared with those in the regions.&#13;
&#13;
5.9     In keeping with its knowledge and learning results framework, the KSL team&#13;
should clarify responsibilities and establish a cycle for incorporating improvements into&#13;
its learning plan and monitoring program improvements. This evaluation provided a&#13;
one-time snapshot of subgroups' satisfaction with the program and suggestions for&#13;
improvements. How will the team ensure that this information informs program&#13;
improvements over time? The differences in ratings between regional staff and anchor&#13;
staff noted above could well be explained by the emphasis on developing KSL capacity&#13;
during this time period. The differences might be a temporary result of the reinvention of&#13;
the learning program or they could signal a more significant problem, so the participation&#13;
and satisfaction of regional staff should be monitored systematically in light of these&#13;
findings. Similarly, the KSL team should have a system for disseminating and applying&#13;
best practices for learning providers, such as the guidance from participants that learning&#13;
events should include concrete examples from Bank operations.&#13;
&#13;
                    SUGGESTED ACTIONS FOR THE CLO AND THE KLB&#13;
&#13;
5.10    The CLO and the KLB should also take steps to ensure that Bank and network&#13;
staff engage in effective professional and technical learning opportunities. Areas for&#13;
improvement highlighted by evaluation findings suggest a need to refine the LMS and&#13;
educate users and to foster a learning community that collaborates and shares promising&#13;
practices.&#13;
&#13;
Improvements to centralized systems&#13;
&#13;
5.11    The CLO's office should continue refining processes and systems that support&#13;
VPUs in developing and delivering learning programs, notably the LMS and the tools&#13;
and guidance for developing learning plans. ESSD's learning plans for FY05 and FY06&#13;
did not identify measurable objectives or indicators for assessing how learning offerings&#13;
addressed strategic priorities, and this may be an area in which the CLO can take the lead&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
and encourage attention to results rather than just activities and outputs. The CLO should&#13;
continue to provide a learning plan toolkit and develop specific examples to support SDN&#13;
(and all SLCs) in creating a useful tool. As part of its regular review of learning plans,&#13;
the CLO's office should require clear evidence that proposed activities are aligned to&#13;
networks' strategic priorities. In addition, the KLB must continue to prioritize action&#13;
steps related to the LMS. These include working with VPUs to address system&#13;
weaknesses (as discussed above), clarify definitions for event types, improve data&#13;
integrity, and continue to educate the Bank community on using the LMS.&#13;
&#13;
Fostering a community of practice&#13;
&#13;
5.12    The KLB should promote and facilitate collaboration and information sharing to&#13;
support the new results agenda for staff learning. By its existence, the KLB signals the&#13;
value of centralizing some learning functions. This body can capitalize on opportunities&#13;
for greater efficiency by establishing systems for sharing knowledge and tools across&#13;
VPUs. A platform is needed to supplement KLB meetings by providing resources such&#13;
as:&#13;
&#13;
        promising examples for designing the new results framework, such as excerpts&#13;
        from learning plans;&#13;
&#13;
        successful models of on-the-job training or descriptions and/or evaluation&#13;
        findings from innovative learning programs;&#13;
&#13;
        discussion threads on experiences with and improvements to the LMS (or other&#13;
        relevant processes and systems);&#13;
&#13;
        tools or processes proven by some VPU(s) to be useful in assessing learning&#13;
        needs;&#13;
&#13;
        reports on VPUs' learning efforts or major initiatives (such as the comprehensive&#13;
        staff learning needs assessment conducted by ESSD); and&#13;
&#13;
        apparent gaps in the learning opportunities provided to VPU staff that could&#13;
        signal areas for cross-VPU collaboration.&#13;
&#13;
A simple electronic learning community could provide an enabling environment both for&#13;
strengthening the centralized learning functions entrusted to the KLB and for adapting&#13;
tools and processes where helpful for supporting the Bank's decentralized business and&#13;
staff.&#13;
&#13;
5.13    ESSD's learning program in FY05 and FY06 challenged the boundaries of staff&#13;
learning at the Bank. Clarifying the program's objectives and strengthening the&#13;
connections between the network's program and the centralized functions embodied by&#13;
the KLB will increase the program's visibility and definition for all staff and provide data&#13;
for systematically monitoring and improving network-related learning and knowledge&#13;
sharing over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           APPENDIX A: METHODOLOGY&#13;
&#13;
         This evaluation focused on the overall ESSD learning program in FY05 and FY06&#13;
to help the network understand its accomplishments vis-à-vis staff learning and improve&#13;
the relevance, effectiveness, and impact of the ESSD learning program. The goal of the&#13;
evaluation was to provide the KLB and the network with information to guide strategic&#13;
decisions about staff learning programs. The WBIEG team used a mixed-method&#13;
approach and relied on three types of data: existing data on ESSD learning activities and&#13;
Bank staff, focus group and interview data from sector managers and members of the&#13;
ESSD learning team, and survey responses from participants of the ESSD learning&#13;
program.&#13;
&#13;
                                          DATA COLLECTION&#13;
&#13;
         Existing data. Human Resources (HR) provided lists of ESSD-mapped staff as of&#13;
June 2005 and June 2006. These lists provided demographic variables and were matched&#13;
with lists of ESSD participants collected through Business Warehouse (BW) in FY05 and&#13;
through LMS in FY06. The team compiled the pool of ESSD participants for FY05 and&#13;
FY06 by including staff who had participated in at least one event in either year. Overall,&#13;
the existing data provided an overview of the events offered, allowed the team to explore&#13;
patterns of participation among ESSD staff and staff outside the network, and supported&#13;
analysis on the potential role of demographic variables for participation and satisfaction.&#13;
&#13;
         Focus group and interview data. All members of the ESSD learning team were&#13;
invited to a focus group discussion in March 2006, and eight members attended. This&#13;
session explored the processes used by the learning team to develop the learning plan and&#13;
design learning events and examined perceptions about the quality and effectiveness of&#13;
the program in FY05. Three focus groups were also held for sector managers, with a total&#13;
of eleven managers participating. Eight managers who had not attended any focus groups&#13;
participated in individual interviews. The selection of focus groups and interviews&#13;
ensured that managers from all sectors and regions provided reflections on what skills&#13;
and knowledge their staff need, how learning needs are assessed, and the quality and&#13;
effectiveness of the overall learning program.&#13;
&#13;
         Survey data. The study included a web-based surveys of ESSD-mapped&#13;
participants in ESSD events. The participant survey explored perceptions about the&#13;
quality and effectiveness of the learning program, motivations for participating, and&#13;
suggestions for future improvements. The pool of ESSD participants (described under&#13;
existing data) totaled 660 staff. Of these, the team randomly selected 400 and contacted&#13;
these individuals via email to direct them to the survey (August to October 2006). A total&#13;
of 200 staff responded to the survey for a response rate of 51 percent.17 The profile of&#13;
respondents is similar to that of the overall population of ESSD participants as shown in&#13;
table 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
17Four of the randomly selected staff left the Bank after the team launched the survey, so this response rate&#13;
is based on a denominator of 396.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
              Table 1. Survey respondents compared to overall pool of participants&#13;
&#13;
                                           Survey respondents           All ESSD participants&#13;
                                                (n=200)                       (n=660)&#13;
&#13;
Location&#13;
World Bank headquarters                    134           67%            481             73%&#13;
                                            66           33%            179&#13;
Country office                                                                          27%&#13;
&#13;
Sector&#13;
ARD                                         89           45%            290             44%&#13;
Environment                                 59           30%            225             34%&#13;
Social development                          52           26%            144             22%&#13;
&#13;
VPU / region&#13;
ESSD                                        34           17%            117             18%&#13;
Africa region                               32           16%            122             18%&#13;
Europe and central Asia region              15            8%             67             10%&#13;
South Asia region                           26           13%             74             11%&#13;
East Asia and Pacific region                29           15%             90             14%&#13;
Latin America and Caribbean region          27           14%             83             13%&#13;
                                            13            7%             41             6%&#13;
Middle East and North Africa region&#13;
&#13;
Length of time in Bank&#13;
New Bank employee (hired in 2003 or         58           29%            158             24%&#13;
later)&#13;
&#13;
Grade Level&#13;
GE                                           8            4%             24             4%&#13;
GF-GG                                      156           78%            480             73%&#13;
GH+                                         36           18%            156             24%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          ANALYSIS&#13;
&#13;
         The team relied on basic descriptive statistics for this study, mainly frequencies,&#13;
cross tabulations, t tests, and correlations. Quantitative data available from HR, BW, and&#13;
LMS allowed the team to explore the characteristics of ESSD staff and ESSD learning&#13;
activities. The data collected through web surveys were merged with the demographic&#13;
variables of participants to explore the potential influence of subgroup categories on&#13;
participation or satisfaction. The analysis focused on differences based on location&#13;
(headquarters versus country office), grade level, sector, VPU, and length of time at the&#13;
Bank. Differences in means and percentages were reported only if they were significant&#13;
at the p&lt;0.05 level. Qualitative data collected through interviews, focus groups, and&#13;
open-ended survey questions were sorted according to major themes and used to&#13;
understand or explain better the results of the quantitative analysis.&#13;
&#13;
                                         LIMITATIONS&#13;
&#13;
         In some cases, the evaluation team encountered inconsistencies in participant lists&#13;
or activity data (especially between BW and the learning catalog) and worked to resolve&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              32&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
these before merging datasets. Some ESSD events that do not appear in LMS and all&#13;
ESSD-cosponsored events have not been included in this study. Finally, because this&#13;
study was conducted during FY06, the interviews and focus groups focus mainly on&#13;
FY05.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         33&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                       APPENDIX B: RESPONSES OF PARTICIPANTS TO SURVEY&#13;
&#13;
1. Indicate the importance of the following&#13;
goals for motivating you to participate in     Not important at all  Unimportant     Neutral    Important  Very important  Response Average&#13;
learning activities provided by ESSD:&#13;
&#13;
Becoming aware of new ideas and emerging&#13;
issues in your sector                               1% (1)            2% (3)         5% (9)     30% (59)     63% (124)              4.54&#13;
&#13;
Enhancing your job performance in your&#13;
current position                                    1% (1)            1% (2)         5% (10)    39% (76)     55% (107)              4.46&#13;
&#13;
Preparing you for a promotion or new position       5% (10)          18% (34)       37% (70)    23% (44)     17% (33)               3.29&#13;
&#13;
Networking and sharing information                  1% (1)            2% (3)         9% (18)    58% (112)    31% (59)               4.17&#13;
Developing or refreshing core sector skills&#13;
and/or knowledge                                    1% (1)            3% (5)        13% (24)    48% (92)     36% (69)               4.17&#13;
&#13;
Developing advanced, specialized sector&#13;
knowledge                                           0% (0)            7% (13)       17% (32)    41% (79)     35% (67)               4.05&#13;
&#13;
Other (please specify below)                      13% (2)             6% (1)         6% (1)     19% (3)      56% (9)                   4&#13;
&#13;
2. Rate the following aspects of the overall&#13;
ESSD learning program based on your&#13;
experiences with ESSD-related learning         Very poor                Poor          Fair        Good     Very good       Response Average&#13;
&#13;
activities in FY05 and FY06:&#13;
&#13;
Relevance of the learning choices offered           1% (1)            6% (11)       23% (44)    47% (89)     23% (43)               3.86&#13;
Timeliness of information about upcoming&#13;
learning offerings                                  3% (5)            8% (15)       34% (63)    38% (69)     17% (31)               3.58&#13;
&#13;
Organization of learning events (e.g., design&#13;
and logistics)                                      1% (1)            4% (7)        30% (55)    45% (83)     22% (40)               3.83&#13;
&#13;
Quality of instructors or speakers                  1% (2)            2% (4)        22% (40)    49% (90)     26% (48)               3.97&#13;
Effectiveness of the overall learning program&#13;
in raising awareness of new ideas and               2% (3)            8% (14)       22% (41)    49% (90)     20% (36)               3.77&#13;
emerging issues in your sector&#13;
Effectiveness of the overall learning program&#13;
in providing opportunities for networking and       1% (2)            6% (11)       29% (54)    41% (77)     23% (42)               3.78&#13;
knowledge sharing&#13;
Effectiveness of the overall learning program&#13;
in developing core sector skills and/or             1% (1)            8% (14)       36% (66)    43% (77)     13% (23)               3.59&#13;
knowledge&#13;
Effectiveness of the overall learning program&#13;
in developing advanced, specialized sector          2% (3)           12% (21)       39% (68)    38% (66)     10% (18)               3.43&#13;
knowledge&#13;
Overall quality of the ESSD learning program        1% (1)            5% (10)       29% (55)    48% (90)     17% (31)               3.75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                34&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4. Thinking about the set of skills and&#13;
knowledge you acquired in ESSD learning&#13;
events in FY05 and FY06, indicate how             Never              Rarely          Occasionally        Frequently   Very frequently Response Average&#13;
often you USE these skills and knowledge&#13;
in your work:&#13;
&#13;
Knowledge and concepts                          1% (1)              4% (7)            37% (66)           45% (79)      14% (24)               3.67&#13;
&#13;
Skills and techniques                           1% (2)              7% (12)           42% (73)           41% (72)       9% (16)                3.5&#13;
&#13;
5. Rate the importance of the following&#13;
factors in influencing whether or not you&#13;
use the skills and knowledge you acquired  Not important at all   Unimportant           Neutral          Important    Very important  Response Average&#13;
&#13;
in ESSD learning events:&#13;
&#13;
Direct relevance to your current job&#13;
responsibility                                  0%  (0)             2% (4)            10% (19)           49% (95)      39% (75)               4.25&#13;
&#13;
Manager support                                 4%  (7)             8% (14)           35% (64)           36% (66)      18% (34)               3.57&#13;
&#13;
Peer support                                    3%  (5)             7% (13)           44% (80)           34% (62)      12% (21)               3.45&#13;
&#13;
Incentive system for staff in my unit           6%  (10)           16% (29)           41% (73)           26% (46)      11% (19)                3.2&#13;
&#13;
Available time to apply                         2%  (4)             7% (13)           21% (39)           41% (78)      29% (55)               3.88&#13;
&#13;
My unit's resources (staff and $)               3%  (6)             4% (8)            30% (54)           34% (62)      29% (53)               3.81&#13;
&#13;
Other (please specify below)                    0%  (0)             8% (1)            15% (2)            23% (3)       54% (7)                4.23&#13;
&#13;
6. How effective are the following means&#13;
for helping you acquire timely information Not effective        Slightly effective Moderately effective   Effective    Very effective Response Average&#13;
about ESSD learning events?&#13;
&#13;
Learning Management System(LMS)               15%   (26)           20% (35)           35% (61)           22% (38)       9% (16)                2.9&#13;
&#13;
Network web page                              18%   (32)           19% (34)           32% (57)           24% (43)       7% (13)               2.84&#13;
&#13;
Communication with peers                        6%  (12)           10% (18)           22% (40)           46% (86)      16% (30)               3.56&#13;
&#13;
Managers                                      20%   (38)           11% (20)           22% (41)          33%) (62)      13% (25)               3.09&#13;
&#13;
Posters or fliers                             11%   (20)           19% (35)           29% (52)           31% (56)       9% (17)               3.08&#13;
&#13;
Newsletters                                   13%   (24)           21% (38)           38% (67)           25% (45)       2% (4)                2.81&#13;
&#13;
E-mail announcements                            1%  (1)             1% (2)             5% (10)           34% (64)      60% (114)              4.51&#13;
&#13;
Other (please specify below)                    0%  (0)             0% (0)             0% (0)            25% (1)       75% (3)                4.75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                35&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7. Please rank (1-4) the following areas,&#13;
according to your own learning interest         1           2            3           4       Response Total&#13;
and priorities (1=high, 4=low):&#13;
&#13;
Emerging `hot topic' issues                  38% (63)    24% (39)     21% (34)    18% (29)       165&#13;
&#13;
Advanced, specialized sector knowledge       31% (51)    31% (51)     20% (33)    17% (27)       162&#13;
&#13;
Core sector skills/knowledge                 18% (30)    30% (51)     36% (62)    16% (27)       170&#13;
&#13;
General operations skills/knowledge          18% (31)    21% (38)     22% (39)    39% (69)       177&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  36&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX C: SUGGESTIONS FROM PARTICIPANTS FOR MAKING&#13;
        ESSD/SDN LEARNING PROGRAMS MORE EFFECTIVE&#13;
&#13;
1. Disseminate to Country Office Staff written materials produced for presentations/&#13;
discussions organized by the Bank in Washington elsewhere. 2. Organize more study&#13;
tours. 3. Assign a budget for acquisition of books/learning materials for each staff.&#13;
&#13;
No more to add to the previous fruitful arrangement.&#13;
&#13;
1. More sessions with implementing agencies which would highlight implementation&#13;
issues and provide a reality check and sounding board for our ideas and procedures. 2.&#13;
Greater effort to reach out to field based staff who cannot attend, e.g., videoconferences,&#13;
sending them course material, e-learning, etc. 3. An opportunity for staff (sp. field based)&#13;
to discuss training needs, career paths and core skill requirements with HR, e.g., have a&#13;
counseling booth during SD week. 4. Face to face interaction with the evaluation group&#13;
for quick and ready feedback.&#13;
&#13;
1. Organize more in-depth clinics (most trainings that I have attended tend to be quite&#13;
superficial) 2. Facilitate region-region knowledge exchange (engage more the region staff&#13;
rather than only the anchor staff).&#13;
&#13;
a. WBI could make it a point to send a mix of participants from its various programs to&#13;
the same training events to allow for more cross fertilization; this means ESSD needs to&#13;
invite not only WBIEN but the other programs to send it participants as well.&#13;
&#13;
Any institution needs to continuously adapt itself to its environment. The training allows&#13;
staff with a deep in-house knowledge to glean from what is going on in the outside world&#13;
and bring that to bear on the work we do for poverty alleviation. Keep up the great work&#13;
with relevant training for the reality we are in.&#13;
&#13;
Apart from SDN specific learning, it would be useful to have updates on general&#13;
operation training or tailor made training e.g., Financial Management for SDN Team, etc.&#13;
&#13;
As project TTLs are traveling a lot, please organize several sessions of the same module&#13;
during the year. Once quarterly for instance or at least twice a year.&#13;
&#13;
Better way to announce the planned programs. More programs related to environment and&#13;
development.&#13;
&#13;
Budget, timeliness and course content.&#13;
&#13;
Bundling all ESSD learning programs into one is not an effective way of obtaining&#13;
feedback on learning programs. The learning programs offered by the three departments&#13;
are quite different, and our objective in attending them varies according to their sectoral&#13;
relevance to us.&#13;
&#13;
Choose topics and speakers very carefully. Some not operational or out of dates.&#13;
&#13;
Courses should not be compressed into e.g., 1 day for a 3-5 day course during the ESSD&#13;
/SDN Week as this leaves participants poorly equipped. More comprehensive training&#13;
programs should be on offer for field staff while more budgets should be made available.&#13;
&#13;
Cross-support opportunities within the region and outside the region ­ On-the-job training&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             37&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- participation in multisectoral teams - Mentoring - Participation opportunities for field&#13;
staff in ARD Hub Trainings, study tours, etc. - Facilitate field staff participation in&#13;
learning programs (budget, language, location, etc.).&#13;
&#13;
Decentralization.&#13;
&#13;
Don't know enough about how effective are the learning events but it seems like we need&#13;
to find a way to reach in the significant numbers of field staff - both international and&#13;
nationally recruited. It is not apparent to me that we are now reaching them.&#13;
&#13;
Don't crowd too much onto the agenda. Leave lots of time for discussion. Manage&#13;
panelists/ trainers so that they deliver what they are supposed to deliver in timely fashion.&#13;
&#13;
ESSD/SDN becomes a very big department, the courses should be divided into several&#13;
levels i.e.: 1. courses suited to all staff 2. Courses suited only to certain specialist 3.&#13;
courses suited only certain to level of staff.&#13;
&#13;
Find a way to make it available to overseas staff. Decrease work load so time can be&#13;
allocated to training without feeling that deadlines will be missed.&#13;
&#13;
Have Unit orientation sessions that includes the various sectors together and then training&#13;
sessions to suit technical needs for say Social Development, Rural, etc. Solicit thematic&#13;
presentations from the field so that those with best practices can show case them.&#13;
&#13;
I think the current learning sessions/training function well.&#13;
&#13;
I will invite INF staff to join our Environmental Economics Thematic Group. Some of us&#13;
from ENV will also join an informal economists' group organized by INF staff.&#13;
&#13;
I would recommend an evaluation and monitoring system to assess the degree of&#13;
improvement of operational skills of staff as related to learning events.&#13;
&#13;
Use true real life examples and bank formats e.g. when you teach procurement do it as if&#13;
you were preparing a procurement annex not as a half day example.&#13;
&#13;
I think that two areas that should benefit greatly from the network integration --and thus&#13;
should be the focus on new learning programs--are water resources management, and&#13;
brown environmental issues; the latter should now be fully mainstreamed into&#13;
infrastructure program.&#13;
&#13;
It is important that courses that improve the linkages between the merged networks are&#13;
planned to enhance impact at the client level. The involvement of the client governments&#13;
in these programs is also important.&#13;
&#13;
It is important to organize more regional learning events.&#13;
&#13;
It would be useful if the ESSD/SDN programs focused more on providing practical,&#13;
operationally relevant knowledge by "practitioners" on SD work being carried out by the&#13;
Bank. Less focus on theory and more on how staff are actually implementing SD&#13;
programs - this would be especially useful in facilitating cross-regional learning.&#13;
&#13;
Keep up the good work. Thanks.&#13;
&#13;
Magically find a way to help people find time in their work/travel schedules to take part&#13;
in training and learning courses. I usually am on the road when something interesting is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               38&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
scheduled, or just don't have time relative to my work load.&#13;
&#13;
Make online courses. Announce in advance. Offer courses in country offices. Offer&#13;
multisectoral study tours with competitive financing of limited set of participants.&#13;
&#13;
More email announcements (not only through TGs but through managers etc) clean up&#13;
learning system so it is apparent which course are actually on offer and which are&#13;
placeholders.&#13;
&#13;
More focus on project implementation is needed.&#13;
&#13;
More learning programs for handling new operations/challenges under the new&#13;
Sustainable Development Department in each region.&#13;
&#13;
More time should be given to the training courses. Trainers with consistent experience&#13;
should be identified and hired for the circumstance.&#13;
&#13;
More training on hot topics and issues associated with sustainable development and the&#13;
suggested way to deal with them should be provided some time should be set for&#13;
individual Q and A face to face between lecturer and participant after lectures.&#13;
&#13;
More training targeting field staff (e.g., e-learning, DLN, regional events etc.).&#13;
&#13;
Need to make these more demand driven, with the majority of input coming from&#13;
operational staff in the regions.&#13;
&#13;
Not ESSD-specific, but I find the 'new' LMS very cumbersome and user-unfriendly&#13;
compared to its previous incarnation. In general, it is hard to know about upcoming ESSD&#13;
training opportunities, unless an email is sent round. I often assume that, aside from&#13;
ESSD week, nothing is going on, unless I see an email announcement saying otherwise.&#13;
&#13;
Please raise more resources to promote mentoring and cross fertilization training&#13;
program, from south to south and /or north to south experience.&#13;
&#13;
Please stop using power point to hammer home the Bank's policies - it isn't about the&#13;
Bank, it is about the borrowers - and to help them we need skills in risk management that&#13;
our Bank policies don't mention - bring outside experts in parallel fields such as safety,&#13;
land, contract or labor law and insurance - where liability and risk are managed in other&#13;
ways than just command and control.&#13;
&#13;
Prepare the training courses having both audiences (INF and ESSD) in mind.&#13;
&#13;
Provide adequate time for training, if necessary by staging core skills/knowledge courses&#13;
by levels.&#13;
&#13;
Providing regular training and orientations for field staff (country offices).&#13;
&#13;
Reference to concrete project experiences in modernizing irrigation systems.&#13;
&#13;
Round table discussions -- bring in a world class speaker from time to time.&#13;
&#13;
Sector Managers should be asked to prepare and deliver training courses. There should be&#13;
quizzes at the end of training and follow-up survey to validate whether the training&#13;
courses are achieving any serious business purpose.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             39&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Secure enough time for training courses Sequence the courses from basic for those who&#13;
not use the topic but need to know about it and those who are involved in the&#13;
implementation.&#13;
&#13;
Send list of participants to all participants ahead to facilitate networking!&#13;
&#13;
Significantly increase opportunities for field-based staff to participate in and/or benefit&#13;
from learning opportunities. Strong HQ bias at present. Not much e-learning and few&#13;
seminars available for field staff to watch. Encourage field-based CSCs to have bigger&#13;
role in promoting learning.&#13;
&#13;
Strengthen the experiential learning element.&#13;
&#13;
Task Teams should present their projects rather than selected individual speakers to focus&#13;
on real life experiences.&#13;
&#13;
The courses offered are in DC and field staff are frequently not allowed to travel there and&#13;
attend them given lack of funding. It would be good to allow field staff to come to DC at&#13;
least once a year, or in general see their managers at least once a year. Another suggestion&#13;
is to allow field staff to attend courses in ILO, Turin as nearer to staff location and of&#13;
good quality. The best learning opportunity is actually work in other countries in similar&#13;
projects with good teams.&#13;
&#13;
The training programs now should focus more on team building and how to work together&#13;
towards sustainable development - how to remove silos. The challenge is to demonstrate&#13;
the effectiveness of SDN.&#13;
&#13;
There should be fewer courses offered at one time but better prepared and introducing&#13;
new aspects/ approaches the Bank envisages in its programs for the future. Along with&#13;
addressing the basic skills required by all Bank staff , some trainings can reflect the&#13;
diverse regions the Bank works in, and on issues that are emerging or progressing, e.g.,&#13;
how Bank is helping in the developing countries in new emerging issues around many&#13;
facets of poverty and how these should be addressed. Also reflect on the types of diverse&#13;
skills that Bank staff need. Even if these skills are not provided but at least an awareness&#13;
of what is required and staff be encouraged to move in that direction. This will also help&#13;
ESSD to provide future trainings in those areas identified.&#13;
&#13;
Training should be in the field not in Washington.&#13;
&#13;
Trainings should be organized both in HQ and field offices as opposed to the current&#13;
regional HUB training arrangement so that participants could have opportunities to do&#13;
field visits for first hand seeing things on the ground in a different working environment.&#13;
Seeing makes believing, I think.&#13;
&#13;
With the very wide scope of the Network, care is needed so that people won't get too&#13;
many learning announcements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              40&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="9321771">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2007/04/9321771/evaluation-environmentally-socially-sustainable-development-networks-staff-learning-program-fy05-fy06
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2007/04/9321771/evaluation-environmentally-socially-sustainable-development-networks-staff-learning-program-fy05-fy06</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2007/04/9321771/evaluation-environmentally-socially-sustainable-development-networks-staff-learning-program-fy05-fy06</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2008/04/02/000333037_20080402033838/Rendered/INDEX/431690WBWP0NO010Program0in0FY050and.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2008/04/02/000333037_20080402033838/Rendered/PDF/431690WBWP0NO010Program0in0FY050and.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2007-04-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2008-04-02T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Evaluation of the environmentally and
            socially sustainable development network's staff
            learning program in FY05 and FY06
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Effective staff learning is of critical
            importance to the World Bank to ensure that personnel have
            the best mix of skills, behaviors, experience, and technical
            expertise for achieving the Bank's business objectives.
            At the request of the Knowledge and Learning Board (KLB),
            the World Bank Institute Evaluation Group (WBIEG) evaluated
            the staff learning program provided by the Environmentally
            and Socially Sustainable Developments (ESSDs) network in
            FY05 and FY06. The study focused on helping the network
            understand its accomplishments vis-a vis staff learning,
            address weaknesses, and improve the relevance,
            effectiveness, and impact of ESSDs learning program in the future.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Evaluation of the environmentally and
            socially sustainable development network's staff
            learning program in FY05 and FY06
        </docna>
        <display_title>Evaluation of the environmentally
            and socially sustainable development network's staff
            learning program in FY05 and FY06</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2007/04/9321771/evaluation-environmentally-socially-sustainable-development-networks-staff-learning-program-fy05-fy06</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Teaching and Learning,Primary Education,Educational Sciences,Education for Development (superceded),Education For All</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Roberts, Dawn</author>
            <author>Yenice, Izlem</author>
            <author>Kruse, Sara</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20080402033838</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>WBI Evaluation Studies; -- No. EG07-127</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to knowledge, achievement,
            achievements, action learning, attention, behaviors, best
            practices, boundaries, collaboration, community of practice,
            continuous improvement, DATA COLLECTION, discussion,
            discussions, distance learning, focus groups, formal
            learning, grade levels, Human Resources, idea, ideas,
            individual learning, information management, information
            technology, innovation, innovations, innovative learning,
            insights, instructor, instructors, Integration, job
            training, Knowledge Sharing, leadership, learners, Learning,
            learning activities, learning centers, Learning Design,
            learning experiences, learning initiatives, learning
            methods, learning modules, learning needs, learning
            objectives, learning opportunities, Learning Programs,
            mentoring, Mentors, Middle East, mutual learning, needs
            assessment, North Africa, Online courses, organizational
            structure, Pacific Region, participation rates, pedagogy,
            peer support, quality assurance, quality learning,
            sanitation, social development, Study tours, technical
            training, Thinking, training courses, use of knowledge,
            variety, vision
        </keywd>
        <owner>Evaluation Group (WBIEG)</owner>
        <repnb>43169</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Observatory</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>PeopleSoft</ml:concept><ml:concept>SAP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tracer Study</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>ERP Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>