<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                               43168&#13;
&#13;
Nonformal Staff Learning in&#13;
the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
Heidi S. Zia&#13;
Antonieta Romero-Follette&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Nonformal Staff Learning&#13;
in the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
Heidi S. Zia&#13;
Antonieta Romero-Follette&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WBI Evaluation Studies&#13;
EG07-130&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank Institute&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
June 2007&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                Acknowledgments&#13;
&#13;
       The World Bank Institute Evaluation Group (WBIEG) prepared this report&#13;
under the direction of Richard Tobin. Heidi Zia is the principal author.&#13;
&#13;
       The authors thank Donald MacDonald who reviewed the study at several stages&#13;
and offered suggestions for its improvement. Most notably, Don graciously agreed to&#13;
formulate a definition of nonformal learning on behalf of the Office of the Chief&#13;
Learning Officer and applied the definition to the Learning and Management System for&#13;
proper recording of all nonformal learning in the World Bank Group.&#13;
&#13;
       The authors also thank Humberto S. Díaz for his assistance in formatting and&#13;
graphics.&#13;
&#13;
       WBIEG evaluates learning by staff of the World Bank and activities of the&#13;
World Bank Institute (WBI). The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed in&#13;
WBI Evaluation Studies are entirely those of the authors and do not necessarily&#13;
represent the views of the World Bank Group, including WBI.&#13;
&#13;
       WBI Evaluation Studies are available at http://www.worldbank.org/wbi/evaluation&#13;
&#13;
Suggested citation: Zia, Heidi S., and Antonieta Romero-Follette. 2007. Nonformal&#13;
Staff Learning in the World Bank. Report No. EG07-130. Washington, DC: World&#13;
Bank Institute.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Vice President, World Bank Institute                         Frannie Léautier&#13;
Acting Chief Learning Officer                                Ana-Maria Arriagada&#13;
Manager, Institute Evaluation Group                          Richard Tobin&#13;
Task Team Leader                                             Heidi S. Zia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           ii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                               Contents&#13;
&#13;
ACRONYMS AND ABBREVIATIONS .................................................................................... iv&#13;
&#13;
1. OBJECTIVE ....................................................................................................................1&#13;
&#13;
2. DATA COLLECTION.......................................................................................................2&#13;
&#13;
3. DEFINITION AND SCOPE OF NONFORMAL LEARNING..................................................2&#13;
&#13;
         Share of nonformal activities in total learning budget.......................................6&#13;
         Share of nonformal learning in total number of events.....................................8&#13;
&#13;
4. EVALUATION OF NONFORMAL LEARNING .................................................................11&#13;
&#13;
    References.................................................................................................................14&#13;
&#13;
    Appendix 1 Scoping nonformal learning in the Bank, FY04-06.............................15&#13;
&#13;
    Appendix 2 Mapping of formal and nonformal learning.........................................17&#13;
&#13;
    Appendix 3 Number of formal and nonformal learning events, FY04-06 ..............18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        iii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
           Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
ACS        Administrative and Client Support Group&#13;
AFR        Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
DEC        Development Economics&#13;
EAP/SAR    East Asia and Pacific/South Asia&#13;
ECA        Europe and Central Asia&#13;
ESSD       Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network&#13;
EXT        External Affairs, Communications &amp; United Nations Affairs&#13;
FSE/PSD    Financial Sector and Private Sector Development Network&#13;
GSD        General Services Department&#13;
HD         Human Development Network&#13;
HR         Human Resources&#13;
IEG        Independent Evaluation Group&#13;
IFC        International Finance Corporation&#13;
INF        Infrastructure Network&#13;
ISG        Information Support Group&#13;
LCR        Latin America and Caribbean&#13;
LEG        Legal&#13;
MIGA       Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
MNA        Middle East and North Africa&#13;
OED        Operations Evaluation Department&#13;
OPC        Operations Policy and Country Services&#13;
PREM       Poverty Reduction and Economic Management Network&#13;
SEC        Corporate Secretariat&#13;
SFR        Strategy, Finance and Risk Management&#13;
SLC        Strategic Learning Centers&#13;
WBI        World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               iv&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                1.       OBJECTIVE&#13;
&#13;
       This study addresses the concern that the World Bank Institute Evaluation&#13;
Group's (WBIEG) approach to evaluation of staff learning does not fairly or well&#13;
characterize the Bank's training nor its overall quality because assessments of staff&#13;
learning typically focus on formal learning activities included in the Bank's Learning&#13;
Management System (LMS). This concern is especially acute among parts of the Bank&#13;
in which nonformal learning constitutes a large and major portion of the training&#13;
provided.&#13;
&#13;
       Addressing this concern requires agreement on a definition of nonformal&#13;
learning, an estimate of its size relative to formal learning, and reliable information&#13;
about nonformal learning within the Bank. To address these issues, this report:&#13;
&#13;
       1.   Provides a platform for dialogue among KLB members on the definition,&#13;
            scope, and role of nonformal learning in the Bank;&#13;
&#13;
       2.   Provides a working definition of nonformal learning, supplemented by a&#13;
            literature review and a proposed definition from the office of the Chief&#13;
            Learning Officer (CLO);&#13;
&#13;
       3.   Characterizes FY04-06 learning events as either formal or nonformal;&#13;
&#13;
       4.   Identifies the relative amount and cost of formal and nonformal staff&#13;
            learning for three fiscal years (FY04-06) for the Bank's major providers of&#13;
            staff learning; and&#13;
&#13;
       5.   Identifies the extent to which nonformal learning events are or are not&#13;
            included in the LMS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                           2.        DATA COLLECTION&#13;
&#13;
        This study is based on data on learning activities from the Bank's business&#13;
warehouse (BW), which feeds into the LMS (i.e., the BW/LMS), and interviews with&#13;
members of the KLB (see appendix 1 for the interview protocol).1&#13;
&#13;
        The LMS does not currently categorize staff learning as either formal or&#13;
nonformal. To address this situation, WBIEG downloaded activity-level data by vice-&#13;
presidential units (VPUs) and strategic learning centers (SLCs) and categorized staff&#13;
learning activities as either formal or nonformal. Since the BW data provide only the&#13;
count of activities in each of the VPUs and SLCs, and not their costs, representatives of&#13;
all VPUs and SLC were interviewed to verify data in the BW and to obtain information&#13;
on each unit's expenditures for formal and nonformal learning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       3.     DEFINITION AND SCOPE OF NONFORMAL&#13;
                                         LEARNING&#13;
&#13;
        WBIEG started with a definition of nonformal learning included in one of its&#13;
prior reports. According to Prom-Jackson and her coauthors (2002), "Nonformal&#13;
learning events, as distinguished from formal training for knowledge acquisition, are&#13;
organized in the Bank as brown bag lunch (BBL) sessions, clinics, workshops, and&#13;
work sessions for `learning groups' or for a `community of learning practice' engaged&#13;
in learning, sharing and using learning for further reflections, for solutions or new&#13;
perspectives."&#13;
&#13;
        WBIEG modified this definition by categorizing workshops as formal instead of&#13;
nonformal learning. WBIEG also asked the Office of the Chief Learning Officer (CLO)&#13;
to provide definitions. This office proposed the following:&#13;
&#13;
           Nonformal learning represents structured and/or unstructured&#13;
           learning activities where participants have varying levels of&#13;
           inputs and controls over the objectives and agenda as the activity&#13;
           is being delivered.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1When learning events are created, they are recorded both in the Business Warehouse and the LMS.&#13;
WBIEG used data from the former, whose software has data quality-control functions not found in the&#13;
LMS. For example, BW identifies and eliminates duplicate records.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
           Formal learning represents structured learning activities where&#13;
           objectives and agenda are for the most part, predetermined by the&#13;
           deliverer/supplier.&#13;
&#13;
        Based on a series of consultations with the CLO's office, WBIEG developed a&#13;
definition of formal and nonformal learning that categorizes World Bank Group staff&#13;
learning into formal and nonformal (see table 1). The CLO's office uses this&#13;
categorization to map staff learning activities to the LMS.2&#13;
&#13;
                Table 1. Categorization of nonformal and formal&#13;
                learning events&#13;
&#13;
                           Nonformal                             Formal&#13;
&#13;
                ART/workout                         Course&#13;
&#13;
                Brown bag lunch                     Sector week&#13;
                Coaching/mentoring                  Workshop&#13;
&#13;
                Team-based action learning          Distance learning course&#13;
                Retreat                             Language learning&#13;
&#13;
                Study tour                          Online course or module&#13;
&#13;
                Performance support tool            Conference&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Among those interviewed, nearly 60 percent agreed with this categorization, yet&#13;
pointed to a number of limitations:&#13;
&#13;
        · Conferences may contain nonformal components. One interviewee said that&#13;
            conferences "are not fully formal learning" and another commented that&#13;
            they could also be categorized as nonformal learning because "they are not&#13;
            designed to impart specific skills."&#13;
&#13;
        · Sector weeks, like conferences, also contain nonformal components. Two&#13;
            interviewees commented that sector weeks are mainly used as networking&#13;
            versus learning venues. One interviewee said that sector weeks "center on&#13;
            relationship building with some formal components."&#13;
&#13;
        · Categorizing retreats is problematic. Some KLB members believe that&#13;
            retreats are not learning activities but rather "resemble business meetings or&#13;
            organizational support activities because they are not always designed with&#13;
            a learning objective in mind and are indeed funded by management budget&#13;
            and not the learning budget."&#13;
&#13;
            In contrast, two people indicated that retreats are learning activities and&#13;
            "should get the same formal treatment as workshops and conferences,&#13;
            particularly in regions with highly decentralized staff resources where&#13;
            managers use retreats as joint learning venues for Washington-based and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2See appendix 2 for KLB's mapping of "on-the-job" and external training to the LMS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
            field staff. One member also added that retreats are a result of a formal&#13;
            learning plan.&#13;
&#13;
       · Study tours may be formal learning events. Three KLB representatives,&#13;
            while agreeing "in principle" with the proposed categorization, indicated a&#13;
            need to revisit the grouping of study tours. They said that study tours could&#13;
            be categorized as formal learning because they have a precise learning&#13;
            objective, are structured, are carefully planned, and include all aspects of a&#13;
            typical course.&#13;
&#13;
       · BBLs may have a formal component. Several KLB members noted that&#13;
            BBLs could be characterized as formal learning as they are the means for&#13;
            addressing learning demands, and "despite their nonformal setting, the&#13;
            learning that takes place is in BBLs is formal." An example of BBLs with&#13;
            formal aspects is the annual "Ramadan BBL Series" organized by MNA.&#13;
            These series require the same level of planning and preparation as formal&#13;
            courses.&#13;
&#13;
       · Performance support tools should be considered formal if they are part of a&#13;
            course. Examples of performance supports that are "not stand-alone&#13;
            products" are EXT support tools for courses on behavioral change.3&#13;
&#13;
       The KLB members who did not agree with the proposed categorization of&#13;
formal and nonformal learning raised several concerns:&#13;
&#13;
       1. The proposed list of nonformal activities is not exhaustive. The views of&#13;
           several KLB members are largely captured by one member who said that&#13;
           "nonformal learning includes peer-to-peer learning, working by doing,&#13;
           learning from mistakes, learning over a conversation during lunch, and&#13;
           hallway conversations." Other interviewees added that "there is a lot of&#13;
           team learning and mentoring on substantive operational issues that are not&#13;
           captured [in the proposed categorization]"; that "extensive on-the-job&#13;
           training and experiential learning should be counted as nonformal learning"&#13;
           and that "nonformal mentoring, advisory groups (hotlines) and nonformal&#13;
           networks are also a part of nonformal learning."&#13;
&#13;
       2. Nonformal learning is part of program delivery. One interviewee claimed&#13;
           that "nonformal learning takes place when you have a project or a strategy&#13;
           that you are sharing with others  this is part of program delivery and should&#13;
           not come from the learning budget."&#13;
&#13;
       3. The separation of nonformal and formal learning is artificial. Two KLB&#13;
           members noted that integrating formal and nonformal learning is part of a&#13;
           broader (and necessary) integration of learning and knowledge sharing.&#13;
           Another member noted that "by categorizing learning into formal and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3EXT also considers developmental assignments and short-term staff exchanges as nonformal learning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
               nonformal we are trying to draw a line that is arbitrary, as it can go either&#13;
               way."&#13;
&#13;
         In addition to KLB contributions to characterizing and defining nonformal&#13;
learning, the authors conducted a literature search on formal definitions of nonformal&#13;
learning (box 1).&#13;
&#13;
   Box 1. Definitions of nonformal learning&#13;
&#13;
                Throughout the literature on adult learning, nonformal learning is often defined in the&#13;
     context of -- and in contrast to -- formal learning. It is defined by the lack of "formal"&#13;
     attributes in the learning process. In contrast to formal learning, which is universally known to&#13;
     involve such attributes as a dedicated time and space, a set curriculum, transfer of knowledge&#13;
     from instructor to student and sometimes a certificate of knowledge acquired, nonformal&#13;
     learning is broadly defined as a cumulative learning process, unrelated to any particular&#13;
     setting whereby the individual gains knowledge (Tissot 2000), either intentionally or&#13;
     unintentionally (Eraut 2000) and it is not necessarily certified. Examples of definitions that&#13;
     define nonformal learning in the context of formal learning include:&#13;
&#13;
              "Education for which none of the learners is enrolled or registered" (OECD&#13;
              1977).&#13;
&#13;
              "Any organized, systematic educational activity carried on outside the&#13;
              framework of the formal system, to provide selected types of learning to&#13;
              particular subgroups in the population" (Coombs and Ahmed 1974).&#13;
&#13;
              "Learning which takes place in the work context, relates to an individual's&#13;
              performance of their job and/or their employability, and which is not&#13;
              formally organized into a program or curriculum by the employer. It may be&#13;
              recognized by the different parties involved, and may or may not be&#13;
              specifically encouraged" (Dale and Bell 1999).4&#13;
&#13;
                A problem in defining nonformal learning as learning that lacks formal attributes is&#13;
     that it leaves a broad and vague residual from all that is counted as formal learning ­ that is&#13;
     also too broad and vague for analytical purposes. In addition, the content of "formal" is likely&#13;
     defined differently in different settings (in some settings, formal learning is by definition one&#13;
     that leads to a certification). Definitions of nonformal learning that are independent of&#13;
     definitions for formal learning include:&#13;
&#13;
              "Nonformal learning consists of learning embedded in planned activities&#13;
              that are not explicitly designated as learning, but which contain an&#13;
              important learning element" (Tissot 2000).&#13;
&#13;
              "Nonformal learning is not provided by an education or training institution,&#13;
              and as a rule it does not entail certification upon completion of the study.&#13;
              Nevertheless, nonformal learning is structured, in terms of learning&#13;
              objectives, learning time or learning support. Nonformal learning is&#13;
              intentional from the learner's point of view" (The European Commission&#13;
              2001).&#13;
&#13;
              "Boundaries between formal, informal and nonformal learning can only be&#13;
              meaningful drawn in relation to particular contexts, and for particular&#13;
              purposes" (Colley et al. 2002).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4In this view, the nonconventional learning setting and the absence of curriculum are central.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Share of nonformal activities in total learning budget&#13;
&#13;
        The BW's cost data cover only part of the learning events and the coverage of&#13;
nonformal events is particularly problematic, so WBIEG relied on learning&#13;
coordinators' estimates of the nonformal share of their learning budgets. Interviews&#13;
revealed that nonformal learning represented over one-quarter (27 percent) of budgets&#13;
for staff learning. Nonetheless, the share of the budget allocated to nonformal activities&#13;
varied significantly across units  from 60 percent in ISN to 5 percent in ACS, OPC,&#13;
PREM, and WBI respectively (see figure 1 and table 2).&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1. Share of nonformal activities in learning budgets by unit, FY04-06*&#13;
&#13;
  70%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  60%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  50%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  40%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  30%&#13;
                                                                                                            27&#13;
                                                                                                            percent =&#13;
&#13;
  20%                                                                                                       nonformal&#13;
                                                                                                            learning&#13;
                                                                                                            share of&#13;
                                                                                                            budget&#13;
  10%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    0%   NSI                                           A&#13;
                IEG&#13;
                     HDN  LEG  LCR ESD AFR         SFR     IFC&#13;
                                                        MN     ECA INF      SEC ISG&#13;
                                                                       HRS1          GSD WBI      OPC CSA&#13;
                                                                                             PREM&#13;
                                           EAP/SAR&#13;
&#13;
      * Weighted by units. Excludes PSD, DEC and EXT for which data was not reported.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2. Estimated share of nonformal learning in learning budgets, FY04-06&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Average annual&#13;
                                                        nonformal learning&#13;
                              Share of nonformal              budget,           Total average learning&#13;
       SLC/VPU                 budget, FY04-06               USD '000             budget, USD '000&#13;
A. Regions&#13;
          AFR                         35%                          3,313                   9,467&#13;
       EAP/SAR                        33%                          2,819                   8,543&#13;
          ECA                         25%                          1,667                   6,667&#13;
          LCR                         40%                          2,187                   5,467&#13;
         MNA                          25%                           670                    2,680&#13;
B. SLC&#13;
         ACSa                          5%                           18                      367&#13;
         ESSD                         40%                           683                    1,708&#13;
         HDN                          50%                          1,150                   2,300&#13;
          INF                         20%                           373                    1,867&#13;
          ISG                         10%                           40                      400&#13;
         HRSb                         20%                          2,405                   12,027&#13;
          ISN                         60%                           360                     600&#13;
          OPC                          5%                           150                    2,990&#13;
        PREM                           5%                           132                    2,633&#13;
          PSDc                         ...                          ...                     395&#13;
C. Other KLB members&#13;
         DECc                          ...                          ...                     250&#13;
         EXTc                          ...                          ...                     513&#13;
          IEG                         50%                           325                     650&#13;
          WBI                          5%                           17                      340&#13;
          SFR                         30%                           149                     497&#13;
D. Observers&#13;
          GSD                         10%                           120                    1,200&#13;
          IFC                         25%                          2,617                   10,467&#13;
         SECa                         10%                           33                      330&#13;
          LEG                         40%                           287                     717&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Overall shared&#13;
    (unweighted)                      26%&#13;
    Overall Shared&#13;
     (weightede)                      27%&#13;
  Total budget USD&#13;
          '000                                                     19,515                  73,073&#13;
&#13;
Source: Bank's Business Warehouse.&#13;
a The estimated share of nonformal learning for ACS and SEC0 is based on data from FY06.&#13;
b The estimated share represents the sum of budgets for management and CET.&#13;
c Did not provide an estimated share of budget for nonformal learning.&#13;
d Excludes units for which data were not available.&#13;
e Weighted by units' learning budgets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    All learning coordinators reported that nonformal learning activities are financed&#13;
from the learning budget, but the estimates of expenditures on nonformal learning do&#13;
not reflect staff time expended on attending, organizing, or leading the activities.&#13;
Proper costing of nonformal training should include such costs. Consequently, if costs&#13;
for staff time were included, the percentages of budget resources devoted to nonformal&#13;
activities would increase.&#13;
&#13;
Share of nonformal learning in total number of events&#13;
&#13;
        The BW/LMS constitutes the only comprehensive, Bank-wide source of data on&#13;
staff learning activities. To gauge the accuracy of its data and to determine the extent to&#13;
which the BW/LMS includes (or excludes) nonformal learning events, WBIEG&#13;
compared the shares of nonformal learning indicated in the BW/LMS to estimates&#13;
received from those interviewed (figure 2).&#13;
&#13;
    Figure 2. Shares in number of nonformal learning events, FY04-06&#13;
 90%&#13;
&#13;
 80%&#13;
              Group 1                           Group 2                                                    Group 3&#13;
 70%&#13;
&#13;
 60%&#13;
&#13;
 50%&#13;
&#13;
 40%&#13;
&#13;
 30%&#13;
&#13;
 20%&#13;
&#13;
 10%&#13;
&#13;
  0%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             -7&#13;
         CS-1A  OPC-2 PRM-3    ISG-1 LCR-2 IFC-3   HRS-4           EXT-6 FR-7A          WBI-1 INF-2 ECA-3  LEG-4&#13;
                                                                               ESSD-8                            HDN-5 OED-6           DEC-8 MNA-9&#13;
&#13;
                                                         EAP/SAR-5&#13;
                            According to KLB Members                          According to WB/LMS data                         FSE/PSD&#13;
&#13;
Source: Authors' calculations based on interviews with KLB members.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        At the level of individual VPU/SLCs, WBIEG found many differences between&#13;
data in the BW/LMS and learning coordinators' estimates. Indeed, data from the two&#13;
sources matched infrequently (group 1 in figure 2). In most of the remaining cases,&#13;
there was a difference of at least 10 percentage points between the estimates from those&#13;
interviewed and the data in the BW/LMS. In four cases (LCR, MNA, ISG, and DEC),&#13;
the differences exceeded 30 percent (table 3). There is no benchmark for what&#13;
constitutes an acceptable difference, but the differences are nonetheless noteworthy and&#13;
emphasize the desirability of agreement among VPUs and SLCs about which learning&#13;
events are formal and which are nonformal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3. Average number and shares of learning events in FY04-06&#13;
&#13;
                       Annual average number of            Percentage share of         Annual average share&#13;
                       nonformal and formal events         nonformal and formal        in number of events in&#13;
                       in FY04-06                          events in FY04-06           FY04-06&#13;
                       (BW/LMS data)                       (BW/LMS data)               (Interview data)&#13;
&#13;
SLC/VPU                   NF         F        Total           NF             F             NF              F&#13;
a. Regions&#13;
AFR                       19.3     26.3        45.6          42%            58%            50%            50%&#13;
EAP/SAR                   13.3     62.3        75.7          18%            82%            33%            67%&#13;
ECA                       38.7     49.0        87.7          44%            56%            25%            75%&#13;
LCR                       29.3     57.7        87.0          34%            66%            70%            30%&#13;
MNA                       10.3       2.7       13.0          79%            21%            30%            60%&#13;
Unweighted Total                                             43%            57%            42%            56%&#13;
Weighted Total          111.0     198.0      309.0           36%            64%            61%            59%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
b. SLCs&#13;
ACS                        2.0     49.0        51.0             4%          96%              5%           95%&#13;
ESSD                    113.7      88.0      201.7           56%            44%            60%            40%&#13;
HDN                     141.7      61.0      202.7           70%            30%            50%            50%&#13;
HRS                       23.7    297.0      320.7              7%          93%            25%            75%&#13;
INF                       65.0     49.0      114.0           57%            43%            42%            58%&#13;
ISG                     250.7     805.3      1056.0          24%            76%            66%            34%&#13;
OPC                        5.0     85.7        90.7             6%          94%              5%           95%&#13;
PREM                      86.3     65.7      152.0           57%            43%            55%            45%&#13;
FSE/PSD                   12.0     12.7        24.7          49%            51%            10%            90%&#13;
Unweighted Total                                             37%            63%            35%            65%&#13;
Weighted Total          700.0     1,513.3    2,213.3         32%            68%            52%            48%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
c. Other KLB members&#13;
DEC                        9.5     14.0        23.5          40%            60%              0%          100%&#13;
EXT                        2.5     38.0        40.5             6%          94%            20%            80%&#13;
IEG                        7.0       5.7       12.7          55%            45%            30%            70%&#13;
SFRV   a                    ...      ...         ...            ...            ...         30%            70%&#13;
WBI                        9.0     41.0        50.0          18%            82%              5%           95%&#13;
Unweighted Total                                             30%            70%            17%            83%&#13;
Weighted Total            28.0     98.7      126.7           22%            78%            11%            89%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
d. Observers&#13;
GSDa                        ...      ...         ...            ...            ...         70%            30%&#13;
IFC                        2.0       5.0        7.0          29%            71%            50%            50%&#13;
LEG                       27.0     18.7        45.7          59%            41%            40%            60%&#13;
SECa                        ...      ...         ...            ...            ...         10%            90%&#13;
Unweighted Total                                             44%            56%            43%            58%&#13;
Weighted Total            29.0     23.7        52.7          55%            45%            41%            59%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
e. Other                  41.0    196.3      237.3           17%            83%                ...          ...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall Unweighted                                              34%            66%             34%          65%&#13;
Overall Weighted  b       909.0   2,030.0    2,939.0            31%            69%             51%          49%&#13;
Overall Unweighted&#13;
 w/out ISG                                                      35%            65%             33%          66%&#13;
Overall Weighted&#13;
w/out ISG                 658.0   1,224.7    1,883.0            35%            65%             43%          57%&#13;
Source: BW/LMS data and interview data.&#13;
Notes: ... Data not reported.&#13;
         a SFR, GSD, and SEC learning activity counts were not included in the BW/LMS at the time of the study.&#13;
         b Weighted by the number of events in the BW/LMS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        Contrary to expectations for a pattern of underreporting of nonformal learning&#13;
activities by the BW/LMS, WBIEG found that in 9 of the 20 units data in the BW/LMS&#13;
were higher than those reported by the KLB representatives (group 3 in figure 2).&#13;
&#13;
        Such differences suggest the need for:&#13;
&#13;
    (a)     Both the BW/LMS and learning coordinators' estimates to be taken with a&#13;
            degree of caution and at best as estimates for the actual extent of nonformal&#13;
            learning; and&#13;
&#13;
    (b)     The Office of CLO and KLB members to become advocates for a systematic&#13;
            reporting of learning deliverables in the BW/LMS database. To do so, they&#13;
            may consider establishing monitoring systems coupled with incentive&#13;
            schemes within their respective VPU/SLCs to ensure accurate,&#13;
            comprehensive, and timely entry of training activities in the LMS.&#13;
&#13;
        Discrepancies between BW/LMS database and KLB reporting of nonformal&#13;
learning shares within individual VPU/SLCs are reflected on the overall average shares&#13;
of nonformal events in the Bank. On average, the estimated weighted share of&#13;
nonformal learning reported by KLB members was 20 percentage points higher than&#13;
indicated in the BW/LMS database (table 3).5 Adjusting for the size of learning&#13;
offerings by VPU/SLCs, nonformal learning represents about 31 percent of all staff&#13;
learning according to BW/LMS but as much as 51 percent according to the KLB&#13;
members.6&#13;
&#13;
        In addition to differences between data sources, WBIEG also found a variation&#13;
in nonformal learning shares across individual VPU/SLCs. Eight KLB representatives&#13;
reported that one-half or more of their learning events were nonformal: LCR and GSD&#13;
(70 percent), ISG (66 percent), ESSD (60 percent), PREM (55 percent), AFR, HDN,&#13;
and IFC (50 percent respectively). In contrast, six reported that only 10 percent or fewer&#13;
of their activities were nonformal: FSE/PSD and SEC (10 percent), WBI, OPC, and&#13;
ACS (5 percent each), and DEC (0 percent) (figure 2). Additional data on the&#13;
distribution of formal and nonformal learning events by provider are in appendix 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5The unweighted averages of shares of nonformal learning from both sources are similar.&#13;
6The 20 percent gap decreases to 8 percent when ISG, the largest provider of learning activities, is&#13;
excluded.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       4.         EVALUATION OF NONFORMAL LEARNING&#13;
&#13;
          A decision to evaluate nonformal learning will depend on at least four factors:&#13;
(i) the definition of nonformal learning; (ii) the size and scope of nonformal learning;&#13;
(iii) the KLB's opinion of the usefulness of an assessment; and, (iv) the likely costs,&#13;
which depend largely on the methodology used.7&#13;
&#13;
          Considering that nonformal training, as defined in this report, captures over one-&#13;
quarter of the learning budget, an assessment of effectiveness and impact may be&#13;
warranted. A majority of respondents agreed.&#13;
&#13;
          Proponents of evaluating nonformal learning indicated that an evaluation of such&#13;
learning could be useful because it would:&#13;
&#13;
          1.     Promote an institutionally accepted distinction between formal and&#13;
                 nonformal learning;&#13;
&#13;
          2.     Encourage the development of adequate measures of and benchmarks for&#13;
                 effectiveness for nonformal events;&#13;
&#13;
          3.     Create a much needed instrument for measuring the impact of nonformal&#13;
                 learning events; and,&#13;
&#13;
          4.     Assess the usefulness of the largest component of nonformal learning&#13;
                 events in the Bank  i.e., brown bag lunches.&#13;
&#13;
          Proponents of an evaluation indicated that a decision to conduct such an&#13;
evaluation should depend on: (i) the degree to which the evaluation would impose on&#13;
the participants; (ii) whether the KLB would provide resources to learning providers for&#13;
evaluation of their nonformal offerings; and, (iii) a clearly defined and well-articulated&#13;
objective and purpose for the evaluation to "avoid evaluating for the sake of evaluating"&#13;
and imposing another evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
          The KLB members who did not support an investment in evaluating nonformal&#13;
learning provided the following reasons:&#13;
&#13;
          1.     "An evaluation of nonformal learning will not add any value because&#13;
                 nonformal learning is a demand-driven type of activity which will happen&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7 The definition of nonformal learning will affect the feasibility of an evaluation. For example, if&#13;
nonformal learning is defined largely as peer-to-peer learning and hallway conversations, then it is&#13;
infeasible to evaluate it in any meaningful way. The amount of nonformal learning is also a concern. If&#13;
there is little such learning, an evaluation might not be desirable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
               regardless of any evaluation...and there is no value added associated with&#13;
               such an evaluation."&#13;
&#13;
          2.   "Nonformal learning is too vague a notion and marginal to our unit...There&#13;
               is little value in quantifying nonformal learning, and if a lot of nonformal&#13;
               learning takes place, then why don't we formalize it?"&#13;
&#13;
          3.   One interviewee said that "anything one puts resources into is worth&#13;
               evaluating, but a Bank-wide evaluation of nonformal learning is useless.&#13;
               WBIEG must distinguish between different types of nonformal learning and&#13;
               develop specific instruments to be used by the SLCs and VPUs themselves,&#13;
               for measuring the effectiveness of their various types of nonformal events."&#13;
&#13;
          4.   WBIEG should evaluate nonformal training "only if we could evaluate the&#13;
               gains of on-the-job training experiences  particularly with respect to&#13;
               impact of decentralization [field assignments]. The compelling contribution&#13;
               to learning is on-the-job learning versus BBLs, which are awareness raising,&#13;
               networking, etc."&#13;
&#13;
          5.   Because of the many ways that staff members learn, assessing the impact of&#13;
               nonformal learning would depend on anecdotal evidence.&#13;
&#13;
          6.   "It will be very hard to evaluate [nonformal training] because the learning&#13;
               goals of [nonformal training activities] are not articulated."&#13;
&#13;
          Should the KLB decide to proceed with an evaluation of nonformal learning, at&#13;
least three approaches deserve consideration. First, WBIEG can develop instruments for&#13;
measuring various types of nonformal learning and distribute them to VPUs and SLCs&#13;
to conduct self evaluations. With this option, WBIEG would design a customized&#13;
instrument for various kinds of nonformal learning. The instrument would be&#13;
standardized to accommodate all professional and technical nonformal learning events&#13;
throughout the World Bank Group. Each unit would be responsible for conducting self-&#13;
evaluations using these instruments and reporting results to the KLB.&#13;
&#13;
          Second, WBIEG could add nonformal learning events to its population of&#13;
current activity-level evaluations. These assessments seek participants' opinions about&#13;
such topics as quality, usefulness, and relevance. To date, one criterion for eligibility&#13;
for such assessments is that activities are registered as formal events in the learning&#13;
catalogue at least two weeks before the activity begins. This criterion could be&#13;
amended or discarded, and WBIEG's sample of events to assess could be drawn from&#13;
the entire population of learning events, both formal and nonformal.8 WBIEG does not&#13;
recommend this option because of the diverse nature of nonformal learning events and&#13;
the unsuitability of the evaluation instrument for certain kinds of nonformal events,&#13;
such as coaching and BBLs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8This option requires that WBIEG specify the duration of nonformal learning activities that would be&#13;
eligible for evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        Third, WBIEG could conduct a Bank-wide survey to assess staff views on the&#13;
usefulness, effectiveness, and impact of nonformal learning relative to formal learning.&#13;
Such a survey would have a "public benefit component," in that it would be useful not&#13;
only to KLB members but also provide recommendations for task managers to improve&#13;
the effectiveness and usefulness of various types of nonformal training offerings.&#13;
&#13;
        A decision to proceed with an evaluation of nonformal learning must consider&#13;
the two challenges inherent in such an endeavor, namely data constraints on nonformal&#13;
learning activities and on costs.&#13;
&#13;
        Data constraints on nonformal learning activities are a reflection of the nature of&#13;
nonformal learning versus possible inadequacies in the LMS. Certain types of&#13;
nonformal learning, such as use of performance support tools, learning that occurs&#13;
during videoconferences with colleagues around the world, and other on-the-job&#13;
trainings (such as peer learning, coaching/mentoring, and developmental assignments)&#13;
cannot  on a practical level  be captured in any systematic and useful way.9&#13;
&#13;
        Obtaining cost data on nonformal learning is as equally challenging as is&#13;
quantifying on-the-job learning sessions. Task managers typically do not report the cost&#13;
of their nonformal learning activities in the LMS, and cost data do not include staff time&#13;
for preparation of and attendance at events such as BBLs.&#13;
&#13;
        WBIEG also recommends that the reliability of the BW/LMS be increased. Any&#13;
evaluation of learning programs, including nonformal learning, would benefit from a&#13;
robust, all-inclusive, and reliable dataset of learning events in the Bank. To improve the&#13;
reliability of BW/LMS, WBIEG recommends that KLB provide and promote the use of&#13;
a common, Bank-wide definition of nonformal learning and then advocate for a&#13;
systematic reporting of learning deliverables in the BW/LMS database. To do so,&#13;
members of the Board may wish to consider establishing monitoring systems coupled&#13;
with incentive schemes within their respective VPU/SLCs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9Some nonformal learning events (such as individualized training in software use and short-term staff&#13;
exchanges for special projects) will never be entered into the BW/LMS  not because they cannot be&#13;
captured and accounted for, but because it is too time consuming and costly to do so.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                    REFERENCES&#13;
&#13;
Colley, Helen, Phil Hodkinson, and Janice Malcolm. 2002. Nonformal Learning:&#13;
        Mapping the Conceptual Terrain: A Consultation Report. Leeds: University of&#13;
        Leeds Lifelong Learning Institute. Available at http://www.infed.org/archives/e-&#13;
        texts/colley_nonformal_learning.htm.&#13;
&#13;
Coombs, P. H., and M. Ahmed. 1974. Attacking Rural Poverty. How Nonformal&#13;
        Education Can Help. Baltimore: John Hopkins University Press.&#13;
&#13;
Dale, M., and J. Bell. 1999. Informal Learning in the Workplace. DfEE Research&#13;
        Report 134. London: Department for Education and Employment.&#13;
&#13;
Eraut, M. 2000. "Informal learning, implicit learning and tacit knowledge in&#13;
        professional work" in F. Coffield, The Necessity of Nonformal Learning. Bristol:&#13;
        The Policy Press.&#13;
&#13;
European Commission. 2001. Making a European Area of Lifelong Learning a Reality.&#13;
        Brussels: European Commission. Available at&#13;
        http://europa.eu.int/comm/education/policies/lll/life/communication/com_en.pdf&#13;
&#13;
Jeffs, T., and M. Smith. 1990. Using Informal Education. Buckingham: Open&#13;
        University Press.&#13;
&#13;
Livingstone, D.W. 2001. Adults' Informal Learning: Definitions, Findings, Gaps and&#13;
        Future Research. NALL Working Paper No. 21. Toronto: Ontario Institute for&#13;
        Studies in Education. Available at&#13;
        http://www.oise.utoronto.ca/depts/sese/csew/nall/res/21adultsifnormallearning.htm&#13;
&#13;
Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development. 1977. Learning&#13;
        Opportunities for Adults Vol IV: Participation in Adult Education. Paris: OECD.&#13;
&#13;
Prom-Jackson, Sukai, M. Palmisano, W. Jackson, R. Novojilov, and T. Melon. 2002.&#13;
        An Evaluation of Nonformal Learning in Professional Technical Networks,&#13;
        2000-2001. Report No. EG-03-61. Washington, DC" World Bank Institute.&#13;
&#13;
Tissot, P. 2000. Glossary on identification, assessment and recognition of qualifications&#13;
        and competences and transparency and transferability of qualifications. In&#13;
        Bjornavold, J. Making Learning Visible: Identification, Assessment and&#13;
        Recognition of Non-formal Learning in Europe. Luxembourg: Office for&#13;
        Official Publications of the European Communities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                    APPENDIX 1&#13;
&#13;
   SCOPING NONFORMAL LEARNING IN THE BANK, FY04-06&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interviewee:&#13;
&#13;
  VPU/SLC:&#13;
&#13;
       Date:&#13;
&#13;
1. Do you agree with the following categorization of nonformal (vs.&#13;
   formal learning)?&#13;
&#13;
          Formal and nonformal types of events (LMS)&#13;
&#13;
          Nonformal Learning                    Formal Learning&#13;
&#13;
          ART/workout                           Course&#13;
&#13;
          Brown bag lunch                       Sector week&#13;
&#13;
          Coaching/mentoring                    Workshop&#13;
&#13;
          Team-based action learning            Distance learning course&#13;
&#13;
          Retreat                               Language learning&#13;
&#13;
          Study tour                            Online course or module&#13;
&#13;
          Performance support tool              Conference&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  YES                                        NO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Comments:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2. Based on the definition above, what percentage of your activities&#13;
   (number of activities) were:&#13;
&#13;
                     Nonformal _____________&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Formal _________________&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3. What was your learning budget in:&#13;
&#13;
                       FY 2004      $&#13;
&#13;
                       FY 2005      $&#13;
&#13;
                       FY 2006      $&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4. What is your best estimate for the SHARE of your budget spent on&#13;
   nonformal learning in:&#13;
&#13;
                       FY 2004      %&#13;
&#13;
                       FY 2005      %&#13;
&#13;
                       FY 2006      %&#13;
&#13;
5. What is the primary source of funding of:&#13;
    Nonformal learning activities?_________________________________&#13;
    Formal learning activities?&#13;
   ____________________________________&#13;
Comments:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6. Do you see a need for an evaluation of nonformal learning in the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  YES                               NO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
If yes, what are the key evaluation questions that the study should pose?&#13;
____________________________________________________________&#13;
____________________________________________________________&#13;
____________________________________________________________&#13;
____________________________________________________________&#13;
____________________________________________________________&#13;
_____&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   APPENDIX 2&#13;
&#13;
          MAPPING OF FORMAL AND NONFORMAL LEARNING&#13;
&#13;
      Category                       Type              Formal/Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
Face-to-face      ART/workout                    Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Brown bag lunch                Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Coaching/mentoring             Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Conference                     Formal&#13;
&#13;
                  Course                         Formal&#13;
&#13;
                  Language learning              Formal&#13;
&#13;
                  Retreat                        Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Sector week                    Formal&#13;
&#13;
                  Study tour                     Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Team-based action learning     Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Workshop                       Formal&#13;
&#13;
Online            Distance learning course       Formal&#13;
&#13;
                  Online course or module        Formal&#13;
&#13;
                  Performance support tool       Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
On-the-job        Peer learning                  Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Coaching/mentoring             Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Developmental assignment       Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
                  Other on-the-job learning      Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
External          External                       Formal&#13;
&#13;
Videoconference   Videoconference                Nonformal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                              APPENDIX 3&#13;
&#13;
   NUMBER OF FORMAL AND NONFORMAL LEARNING EVENTS,&#13;
                                                 FY04-06&#13;
&#13;
                         2004                                 2005                  2006&#13;
SLC/VPU         NF         F    Total                 NF        F    Total    NF      F    Total&#13;
&#13;
a. Regions&#13;
AFR             27        30      57                   22      29     51       9     20     29&#13;
EAP/SAR         21        36      57                   13      108    121      6     43     49&#13;
ECA             72        43     115                   34      37     71      10     67     77&#13;
LCR             57        64     121                   29      65     94       2     44     46&#13;
MNA              1         3       4                   5        2      7      25      3     28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total           178      176     354                  103      241    344     52    177     229&#13;
&#13;
b. SLCs&#13;
ACSa             3        56      59                   1       47     48             44     44&#13;
ESSD            151      105     256                  124      68     192     66     91     157&#13;
HDN             177       65     242                  143      46     189     105    72     177&#13;
HRSb            20       371     391                   28      315    343     23    205     228&#13;
INF             88        38     126                   73      52     125     34     57     91&#13;
ISG             175      937     1,112                295      661    956     282   818    1100&#13;
OPC              5        90      95                   1       55     56       9    112     121&#13;
PRM             115       73     188                  104      68     172     40     56     96&#13;
PSD             26        10      36                   7       10     17       3     18     21&#13;
&#13;
without ISG     585      808     1,393                481      661   1,142    280   655     935&#13;
Total           760      2,553   2505                 776     1,322  2,098    842   2128   2970&#13;
&#13;
c. Other KLB members&#13;
DEC             18        18      36                   1        7      8             17     17&#13;
EXT              2        35      37                   3       44     47      ...    35     35&#13;
OED              9         4      13                   5       12     17       ..     1      1&#13;
SFR              2        ...      2                   ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    ...&#13;
WBI             12        39      51                   13      57     70       2     27     29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total           43        96     139                   22      120    142      2     80     82&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
d. Observers&#13;
GSDDR           ...        3       3                            1      1      ...    14     14&#13;
IFC              2         1       3                   ...     ...    ...     ...     9      9&#13;
LEG             22        17      39                   31       6     37      28     33     61&#13;
SEC             ...       ...     ...                  ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    ...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total           24        21      45                   31       7     38      28     56     84&#13;
&#13;
e. Other        59       182     241                   48      208    256     16    199     215&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall        1,064     3,028   3,284               980      1,898  2,878    940   2,640  3,580&#13;
W/out ISG       889      1,283   2,172               685      1,237  1,922    378   1,167  1,545&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Bank's Learning Management System and Business Warehouse.&#13;
aACS is HRAC in LMS.&#13;
bHRS is the aggregate of HRSLO &amp; HRSDL.&#13;
...= Not reported.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="9321768">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2007/06/9321768/nonformal-staff-learning-world-bank
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2007/06/9321768/nonformal-staff-learning-world-bank</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2007/06/9321768/nonformal-staff-learning-world-bank</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2008/04/02/000333037_20080402032846/Rendered/INDEX/431680WBWP0NO01ng0in0the0World0Bank.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2008/04/02/000333037_20080402032846/Rendered/PDF/431680WBWP0NO01ng0in0the0World0Bank.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2007-06-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2008-04-02T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Nonformal staff learning in the World Bank
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This study addresses the concern that
            the World Bank Institute Evaluation Group's (WBIEG)
            approach to evaluation of staff learning does not fairly or
            well characterize the Bank's training nor its overall
            quality because assessments of staff learning typically
            focus on formal learning activities included in the
            Bank's Learning Management System (LMS). This concern
            is especially acute among parts of the Bank in which
            nonformal learning constitutes a large and major portion of
            the training provided. Addressing this concern requires
            agreement on a definition of nonformal learning, an estimate
            of its size relative to formal learning, and reliable
            information about nonformal learning within the Bank.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Nonformal staff learning in the World Bank
        </docna>
        <display_title>Nonformal staff learning in the
            World Bank</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2007/06/9321768/nonformal-staff-learning-world-bank</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Teaching and Learning,Education For All,Education for Development (superceded),Educational Sciences,Primary Education</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Zia, Heidi S</author>
            <author>Follette, Antonieta Romero</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20080402032846</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>WBI Evaluation Studies; -- No. EG07-130</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            action learning, Adult Education, adult
            learning, Adults, Boundaries, categorization, Communities,
            curriculum, DATA COLLECTION, decentralization, Distance
            learning, experiential learning, formal courses, formal
            learning, formal training, Human Development, Human
            Resources, Informal Education, Informal Learning,
            instructor, integration, job training, knowledge
            acquisition, knowledge sharing, leading, learners, Learning,
            learning activities, Learning Centers, learning demands,
            learning goals, learning objectives, Learning Opportunities,
            learning process, learning programs, learning time, Lifelong
            Learning, mentoring, Middle East, Nonformal Education,
            nonformal training, North Africa, Open University,
            peer-to-peer learning, recognition, Study tours, Sub-Saharan
            Africa, systematic educational activity, tacit knowledge,
            team learning, training activities, Workplace
        </keywd>
        <owner>Evaluation Group (WBIEG)</owner>
        <repnb>43168</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuous Vocational Training (CVT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Technical Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical Vocational Education and Training Policies and Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical and Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Education and Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adult Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adult Education, Literacy, and Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuing Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>