<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The S a n i t a t i o n B u s i n e s s  46080&#13;
100              MILLION&#13;
                  CUSTOMERS&#13;
AWAIT            YOU!&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                 The Sanitation Business&#13;
&#13;
100 MILLION CUSTOMERS AWAIT YOU!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             FIRST EDITION&#13;
                                      April 2008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             100 Million Customers Await You! i&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                    That's right! There really are 100 million potential customers waiting for you. Data show that&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    45% of Indonesian people do not have access to sanitation services. That's more than 100&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    million people. The government can't necessarily deal with this by it self. Like it or not, people&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    are waiting for your participation in providing sanitation services. As a business venture, of&#13;
   CUSTOMERS                                                                        course.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         YOU!                                                       If we rely on the government to improve and develop sanitation facilities, it's going to be a&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    long wait. Government efforts are limited by financial constraints. Existing facilities cannot&#13;
            MILLION          AIT                                                    be properly maintained. And some facilities in disrepair and abandoned because they are&#13;
&#13;
                   100          WA                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  CONTENTS&#13;
                                                                                    unusable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
FIRST EDITION 2008                                                                  Now is the time for the private sector to get involved in sanitation. Perhaps the sanitation&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    sector hasn't seemed to be a very attractive prospect. Low status, small profits. But on the                                                              That's Right! They're Waiting for You                           1&#13;
                                                                                    contrary this business is actually just as good as any other business. This business is profitable,&#13;
&#13;
Published by:                                                                       it benefits lots of ordinary people, and it helps create jobs. Your business could even give                                                              01. Public WCs                                                  6&#13;
                                                                                    sanitation an improved image in your area.&#13;
&#13;
The National Development Planning Agency,                                                                                                                                                                                                     02. Septic Tanks                                                8&#13;
Ministry of Home Affairs, Ministry of Health,                                       It should be noted that the idea that sanitation is only for the poor is incorrect. Your customers&#13;
&#13;
Ministry of Public Works, Ministry of Industry,                                     will be from the middle to upper classes too. They need sanitation services as well. Like&#13;
&#13;
Ministry of Finance, and                                                FOREWORD    garbage transportation and emptying out septic tanks, for instance.                                                                                       03. Emptying Septic Tanks                                      10&#13;
Ministry of the Environment,&#13;
                                                                                    This book looks at a wide variety of initiatives that could be managed by the private sector.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              04. Sewerage Systems                                           12&#13;
WorkingwithWaterandSanitationProgram-EastAsiaandthe                                 And at the back of the book, there's a checklist of reasons why you should get involved in the&#13;
&#13;
Pacific(WSP-EAP),WorldBankthroughtheIndonesiaSanitation                             sanitation business. After all, the purpose of this book is to encourage you to consider entering&#13;
&#13;
Sector Development Program (ISSDP).                                                 the sanitation business.                                                                                                                                  05. Sewage Treatment                                           14&#13;
&#13;
Co-funded by:                                                                       Budi Hidayat                                                                                                  Design:                                     06. Garbage Transportation                                     16&#13;
                                                                                    Director of Settlements and Housing ­ National Development Planning Agency&#13;
&#13;
Government of the Netherlands                                                                                                                                                                     Qipra Galang Kualita, PT&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              07. Composting                                                 18&#13;
and Government of Sweden.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                  Rudy Yuwono - Laksmi Wardhani - Utari&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                  Ninghadiyati (concept and text).            08. Recycling                                                  20&#13;
                                                                                                                Content and input:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                  M Taufik Sugandi - Endang Sunandar&#13;
                                                                                                                NugrohoTriUtomo(NationalDevelopmentPlanningAgency);SanitationWorkingGroup,                                                    09. Final Disposal Site                                        22&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                  - Zarkonie (layout and graphics).&#13;
                                                                                                                comprisingmembersrepresentingtheNationalDevelopmentPlanningAgency,Ministryof&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                HomeAffairs,MinistryofHealth,MinistryofPublicWorks,MinistryofIndustry,Ministry    Hidayah Pujiwati - Echi Desvita ­ Salida    10. Energy from Waste                                          24&#13;
                                                                                                                ofFinance,andMinistryoftheEnvironment;andmembersoftheISSDPconsultantteam(J.       Arianti (editorial support).&#13;
                                                                                                                Sinarko Wibowo, Hony Irawan, and others).&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              Don't Worry, You're Not Alone                                  26&#13;
                                                                                                                Photos:                                                                           Translated from Bahasa Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                ISSDP, WASPOLA, WSP-EAP, Winarko Hadi, Heri Wibowo.&#13;
                                                                                               ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
  ii                   Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                       100 Million Customers Await You!   iii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                      THAT'S RIGHT!            In cities, there are actually millions of toilets that are not connected to septic&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               tanks or sewerage systems. More than 50% of garbage is not collected either.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               A big problem? Yes, but it is also a big opportunity for you. And now is the time&#13;
&#13;
                                                      THEY'RE WAITING FORYou   for you to start a sanitation business. Don't delay, make your move. There are&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               lots of opportunities for you to venture into. It's profitable and it's sustainable.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               And prospects in this business will only get brighter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
iv Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                     100 Million Customers Await You! 1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           THE OPPORTUNITIES KEEP                                                                                                                                                                    Collection&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               Qipra&#13;
          noitcelloC                                                                                                                                                                                                       ON GROWING                                                                                                                                                                                               Photo:&#13;
                                                                                                                       ToachievetheMillenniumDevelopmentGoals(MDGs),especiallyforincreasedpublicaccesstoimproved&#13;
&#13;
                    arpiQ                                                                                               sanitationfacilities,weneedtoinvestRp5trillion(US$530million) peryear.Itwouldbetoomuchto&#13;
&#13;
                         :otohP                                                                                                                                                                                              Opportunities for private enterprise in the sanitation sector have never been accurately&#13;
                                                                                                                        expectthegovernmenttodothatalone.Itwouldbeevenmoreunrealistictoexpectcommunity-based&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             calculated. But there's no doubt that the opportunities are great. Overall, 45% of Indonesians,&#13;
                                                                                                         business       initiativestofillthegap.Thisisanopportunityfortheprivatesectortomakeuptheinvestmentshortfall.&#13;
                                                                        in 1989,John Peter startedup his&#13;
                                               of Rp          (US$430)                                                                                                                                                       in urban and rural areas, do not have access to proper toilets. Even more do not have access&#13;
         With                   an investment       4 million                                             dealers.&#13;
                                                                      plasticfrom wastepickers to plastics&#13;
                                                   selling      scrap                                           to&#13;
         trading                  in waste plastic,         back&#13;
                                                                           into        he has been sellingdirect                                                                                                             to garbage services. So, it would be no exaggeration to say that the sanitation business in&#13;
                                                    that  turnsscrapplastic    pellets,&#13;
                                                                                                               sell      Yourentry--andthatofotherentrepreneurs--intothesanitationsectorhasbeenlongawaited.We&#13;
         Since                  getting an extruder&#13;
                                                                         costs            a kiloand the pellets&#13;
                                                  rocketed.  Scrapplastic      onlyRp 400&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             Indonesia has 100 million potential customers.&#13;
            factories.               His revenues                                               regularlyturns over&#13;
                                                                                                                         believethatyoucanbringabreathoffreshairtothesector.Aswellasbringinginvestment,youcan&#13;
                                                   a kilo.Thanks to thisinnovation,his business&#13;
                 for Rp           8,000 (US$0.85)&#13;
                                                                a month.                                                  bringmoreeffectiveandefficienttechnologicalapproaches.Sanitationfacilitieswillbebuilttocomfort,&#13;
                    more         than Rp 1 billion(US$110,000)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               The sanitation business, especially the recycling business, is expanding&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             The potential of the sanitation business keeps on growing with increased                                        with people's growing awareness of the environment. More and more&#13;
                                                                                                                  healthandenvironmentalqualitystandards.Yourcompetitionwithotherprivatecompanieswillcreateaclimate&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             factories are required to maximize their use of recycled materials in&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             public demand for better sanitation services. In the past, people were happy&#13;
                                                                                                                  conducivetothedevelopmentofbettersanitationservices.Thatcompetitionwillalsostimulateinnovation,                                                                                                                            the manufacture of their products.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             if their city had a final disposal site. Even an open site was better than&#13;
                                                                                                                  encouraging you and other businesses to offer innovative services.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             nothing. But today, people want their final disposal sites to be sanitary&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             landfills. This is a golden opportunity for the private sector. Better quality&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             services are a competitive advantage for private companies.&#13;
                                                                                                                  Thesanitationbusinesscangiveyoulargeprofits.Justtakealookatothercompaniesinvolvedinthisbusiness.&#13;
    The sanitation business is proven profitable, even though the&#13;
&#13;
    management is still generally done in the conventional ways. With                                                 OneisJohnPeterSimanungkalitinBandung(seephoto).WithstartingcapitalofjustRp4million(US$&#13;
    more efficient technologies and a more professional approach to                                                                                                                                                          Opportunities in the sanitation business come not only from government,&#13;
                                                                                                                       430)in1989,hisgarbagebusinessnowturnsovermorethanRp1billion(approximatelyUS$110,000)a&#13;
    management, the sanitation business could yield even greater profits.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             but from the private sector too. In the property sector, building managers&#13;
                                                                                                                                 month.Therearesuccessstoriesinhouseholdwastecollection,too.Aswellasbeingprofitable,                                                                                                                                        Privatesectorparticipationinthesanitationindustryshould&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             usually contract out management of their toilets. Opportunities in the&#13;
                                                                                                                                          thesanitationbusinessissustainable.Peoplewillalwaysthrowawayrubbish,urinate                                                                                                                                       openupnewjobopportunities,includingforlesseducatedand&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             sanitation business come from the public as well, for example, the business                                                    unskilled workers.&#13;
                                                                                                                                               and defecate.&#13;
Photo: Qipra Collection                                                                                                                                                                                                      of emptying out household septic tanks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               Echi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   Photo:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    2   Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     100 Million Customers Await You!       3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                   EMPTYING OUT SEPTIC TANKS&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                        RECYCLING&#13;
                                                                                                                                  COMPOSTING&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             GARBAGE COLLECTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  SEWAGE TREATMENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                PUBLIC WCs                 SEWERAGE SYSTEM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                 FINAL DISPOSAL SITE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  GARBAGE TRANSPORTATION&#13;
       he sanitation   business  can be  defined as services&#13;
 T     or production operations associated with improving&#13;
       sanitation   conditions.  The business   is generally&#13;
                                                   domestic&#13;
 divided  into the   garbage   business   and the&#13;
                                                      shown&#13;
 wastewater   business.   Any or  all ofthe activities&#13;
                                             business. There&#13;
 in thepicture   could  be your  sanitation&#13;
                                               be a planning&#13;
 are lots  of options   available.  You could&#13;
&#13;
                               facility         contractor. Or&#13;
 consultant  or a sanitation           building&#13;
                                                        If you&#13;
  a producer  or supplier   of sanitation   equipment.&#13;
                                                be an operator&#13;
  want to get even   more  involved,  you could&#13;
                                                    just as an&#13;
  or manager    of a sanitation   facility.Or even&#13;
&#13;
  investor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                         100 Million Customers Await You! 5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  The Figures&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  There's no doubt the business of public WCs in busy places is&#13;
                                                                                              kIsmail                                                                                                 skaeppoT                                                                                                                    financially tempting. They get more users a day than public latrines&#13;
                                                                                         Taufi                                                                                                                :otohP                                                                                                              in residential areas. And the users can afford to pay more. Rp 1,000&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   Photo:                                                                                                                                                                      events,such as  exhibitions and concerts.  One mobile&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                     Mobile           toilets are       in demand  for outdoor                                                                    (US$ 0.11) to go to the toilet and Rp 2,000 (US$ 0.22) for a bath are&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               1 million(US$108)   a day. To  purchase  a mobileunit&#13;
                                                                              One company operating              in the businessof public WCs in shopping centers in Bandung is PT                   toilet, with         six stalls,       leases for up to Rp&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                  Masadenta.                                                                            (US$5,500) a unit. There  are alreadyseveral              reasonable charges. If the public WC offers hot water, you can charge&#13;
                                                                              Some of the toilets                                                                                                                                                          Rp 50 million&#13;
                                                                                                           the company operates are in Kings ShoppingCenter and PlazaParahyangan. They                outright         is quite        expensive,at around&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                       contract                                                                 mobile toilets.&#13;
                                                                              the WCs from the             building owners. PT Masadenta   has been in businessfor more than 20                       local Indonesian                 manufacturers producing&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                years, and has                                                                                                                                    up to Rp 3,500 (US$ 0.40). Your operating expenses could be less&#13;
                                                                              more than 600              employees.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  than Rp 5 million (US$ 540) a month. A public toilet with 10 to 20&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   To make your business more profitable, try to make sure that your public latrines&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  stalls could bring in Rp 1 million (US$ 108) a day. The cost of the&#13;
                                                                             There is a need for public WCs. Especially in busy public places like train stations, airports, shopping centers      are in an area where factory workers live in rented houses. And you should offer&#13;
                   PUBLIC                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         lease with the building owner varies from place to place. Some are&#13;
                                                                             and the like. When nature calls, visitors to these places need public toilets. Workers in these places need           something extra, hot water, for instance, or a larger MCK (bathing, washing and&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  Rp 30 million (US$ 3,260) a year.&#13;
                                                                             them too. People who live in houses that don't have toilets need public WCs as well. And in Indonesia, there          toilet facility), which makes it easier for mothers to bathe their children. Another&#13;
&#13;
                    WCs                                                      are still numerous houses without toilets.                                                                            opportunity you could look into is leasing mobile toilets (see picture).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             There is a variety of opportunities for you in the public WC business. One is managing public toilets under&#13;
&#13;
  Public WCs are also often called toilets. Or if we want to be              contract. Another is leasing the facilities from the owner. You cover the operating costs, and in return you&#13;
&#13;
  sophisticated, they are called restrooms. In residential areas, if they    get to keep the tariffs collected from users.&#13;
&#13;
  areusedforbathingandwashing,theyarecalled"Mandi-Cuci-Kakus"&#13;
&#13;
  (Bathing, Washing-Toilet) or popularly referred to as "MCK". You           Not all property owners have public WCs that are ready for you to lease. Some property owners just rent out&#13;
&#13;
  might never have imagined that the WC business can be very                 unutilized plots of land. With an agreement in place, you are then free to build and operate public toilets on&#13;
&#13;
  profitable. A discrete location (but well-sign posted) has proven to       this land. After a few years of operation as agreed the management of the toilets reverts to the land owners.&#13;
&#13;
  be more successful.                                                        This kind of cooperation is called Build-Operate-Transfer or BOT.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                            onyT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                Photo:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Thereareopportunitiestoexploreinbuildingandoperatingpubliclatrinesinresidentialareastoo.Butrevenues&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                         Location        &amp; Innovation! To make sure thatlots of people&#13;
                                                                             might be lower than that of public WCs.                                                                                                                                                                    visit yourtoilets,choose&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                        or a train                                                                              a busy location&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          station.You need                                                                     like a busterminal&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            to be innovative too. For example,   you may  choose&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                        modern                                                                                  to go for&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        conveniences,                                                                     a luxury&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      like automatic                                                              design with all&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    flushing and disinfecting.&#13;
6 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         100 Million Customers Await You! 7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            Another way of taking advantage of the opportunities in this business is to&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            get into the manufacturing of septic tanks (see photo). There is huge demand&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            for factory-made septic tanks nowadays. They are not only easy and quick to&#13;
                                                                                    International&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            install, but these products also scarcely ever leak. They also come in a variety&#13;
                                                                             .Induro                                                                                                                                                                                                                              Hadi&#13;
                                                                            PT                                                                                                                              of sizes. There are small ones for houses and larger ones for businesses or&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Photo:                                                                                                                                buildings. There are all sorts of innovations that could enhance your product                  Winarko&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  PT. Induro International                        is Southeast Asia's                                                                       performance and effectiveness. For example, integrating bio-filters into the&#13;
                                                                                                                                     top manufacturerof fiberglass reinforced plastics (FRP). Originally                                                                                             Photo:&#13;
                                                                  set up in 1974                         as PT Induro Fiberglass, the company changed   its name to PT  Induro International  to get a      septic tanks so that organic matter settles quickly, or incorporating chlorification&#13;
                                                                  foothold in the                        international market. The company has more than 30 years   of experience in the manufacture                                                                                              Nowadays,               in shops  selling sanitationequipment,  you'll findfactory-produced&#13;
                                                                  of products from                         FRP, including processing                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           septic tanks.&#13;
                                                                                                                                     tanks, vessels,scrubbers, fume                                         so that seepage outflow is bacteria-free.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                      stacks, chemical  pipes, fittings                                                                                           They are              usually blue and  made of  fiberglass.At the top  there's a dark-colored&#13;
                                                                  &amp; ducting, public                        transport components,                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 lid. At first&#13;
                                                                                                                                   automotive components,  septic tanks, doors  and toilets. PT Induro      There are strategies to ensure the loyalty of your customers. When you have           glance, it            looks likea water collection tank. Theseproducts  are an alternative&#13;
                                                                  International made                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        to conventional,&#13;
                                                                                                             its debut on the  Southeast Asian market in 1996. The company won      ISO 9001 and ISO                                                                                             brick-built             septic tanks. They vary in size.&#13;
 2                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       The smallest is 1,000&#13;
                                                                  9001:2000 certification                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       liters and costs close&#13;
                                                                                                                     in 1999 and 2000,                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 to Rp&#13;
                                                                                                                                         and is now moving                                                  finished building or installing a septic tank in someone's house, get him or         3 million               (US$326).&#13;
                   SEPTIC                                                                                                                                     into marketing    consumer products.                                                                                                                                   There's   a 3,000-liter   model   too, at   Rp 6 million    (US$352).&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            her to sign up for after sales maintenance services. For a monthly fee, your&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 Although there are national standards, most septic tanks are still not designed or built                   inspectors will make regular check-ups. As well as ensuring that the septic tank&#13;
                    TANKS                                                                        to proper standards. If the government enforced compliance to the standards almost all                     is not leaking, they will check its performance. Customers will also have their&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 septic tanks in Indonesia would likely have to be reconstructed. This means enormous                       septic tanks cleaned out regularly, at no extra charge.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 market potential for those in the septic tank business. Just imagine, in Jakarta and&#13;
 Most middle-upper class homes and buildings in urban areas&#13;
                                                                                                 surrounding areas alone there are more than 1 million septic tanks. That doesn't even&#13;
 in Indonesia have septic tanks. Unfortunately most of these&#13;
                                                                                                 include new houses and buildings that are under construction. They need septic tanks,&#13;
 septic tanks are not properly designed, built or maintained.&#13;
                                                                                                 too. They have no choice--Jakarta does not have adequate sewerage systems to&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            Materials and technology innovations have&#13;
 If the standards for proper septic tanks are enforced, demand&#13;
                                                                                                 accommodate the need.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            made mass-produced septic tanks more&#13;
 for properly built septic tanks will significantly increase.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            effective and practical. The spherical shape&#13;
 Nowadays there are lots of factory-produced septic tanks&#13;
                                                                                                 There are lots of ways you can take advantage of these opportunities in the septic tank&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            allows for better mixing of sewage.&#13;
 on the market. Technological innovations are making them&#13;
                                                                                                 business. You could offer septic tank construction services. Of course your services would&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            Polyethylene plastic construction makes for&#13;
 even more effective.&#13;
                                                                                                 have to differ from those offered by an ordinary builder. At the very least you should have&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            lighter, more robust septic tanks.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 consultants ready to help customers choose the right type and size of septic tank. You&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 also need to give a guarantee on the septic tanks that you build. Most importantly, you&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           Photo: Internet&#13;
8 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                must guarantee that they function effectively and meet national standards.                                                                                                                                                                                                         100 Million Customers Await You! 9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  The Figures&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      If you want it simpler, provide sewage trucks for local governments to lease. In some cities,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      private companies simply rent out sewage suction trucks to the governments. Financial constraints&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      means that governments cannot afford to buy new trucks. Leasing suction trucks is quite&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      expensive, at around Rp 3.5 million­10 million (US$ 380 - 1,080) a month, per truck, depending                 In the septic tank emptying business, all your revenues come from&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      on the type and number of trucks leased. The larger the capacity, the higher the rental fee.                   the people whose septic tanks you clean out. The tariff varies between&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      Jawa Tengah provincial government spends more than Rp 400 million (US$ 43,500) for a year's                    Rp 200,000-400,000 (US$ 22­44) per clean out, depending on the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     volume of the septic tank and the distance from the house to the&#13;
                                                                                Echi                                                                                                  lease on three medium-sized suction trucks.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     sewage treatment unit. There are plenty of openings in this business.&#13;
                                                                          Photo:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      There are still plenty of opportunities in the septic tank emptying business, but you should                   If in one month, one truck pumps out 80 septic tanks, you pocket&#13;
                                                                      Yustarman's decision    to open a septic tank emptying  business turned   out to be a good  one. His growing&#13;
                                                                      business generates    a monthly profit                                                                                                                                                                                         around Rp 30 million on each truck you operate. On top of the cost&#13;
                                                                                                             of Rp 8 million (US$870), from   the Rp 120,000- 130,000 (US$ 13-14)     differentiate your services. Offer septic tank cleaning services as a part of a septic tank&#13;
                                                                      payments from     his customers. Almost the same   as his initial investmentof just Rp 10 million(US$1090).     maintenance package. The service you offer is total septic tank inspection and maintenance.                    of leasing or loan repayments on the truck, you will have to pay your&#13;
                                                                      He used this money    to buy a pump, compressor and   vacuum. Yustaram    doesn't have hisown vehicles--he&#13;
                                                                      works together    with another company. But has managed                                                                                                                                                                        workers' wages, fuel costs and fees. Another cost is for disposal of&#13;
                                                                                                                                 to open two branches,  in Kalibata, SouthJakarta,    That way, you can ensure that septic tanks are functioning properly. You record the customer's&#13;
                                                                      and Rawamangung,      East Jakarta. Headoffice is in Tomang  in West Jakarta.He has 20 employees   who help                                                                                                                    the sewage at the sewage treatment plant, which around Rp 15,000-&#13;
  3                                                                   run the day-to-day                                                                                              details, including the number of people living in the house and the specifications of the septic&#13;
                                                                                          business of serving customers.&#13;
                    Emptying                                                                                                                                                          tank. Every time you clean it out, you make a note of the date. Many companies in other                        20,000 (US$ 1.60 ­ 2.20) per truck.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      countries offer this kind of service. One is Indah Water Consortium Sdn Bhd in Malaysia.&#13;
                                                                      Septic tank emptying services are in demand. How could they not be? Almost 65% of homes in urban&#13;
                    SEPTIC TANKS                                                                                                                                                      Especially for houses and buildings located outside its sewerage system. With this kind of&#13;
                                                                      areas use septic tanks. And once every 1-3 years, the sewage in the septic tank has to be cleaned out.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      service, you'll have loyal customers.&#13;
                                                                      Here is a great opportunity for you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  There are lots of septic tanks in Indonesia, and they need to       You could get into the business as a provider of septic tank emptying services. For that, you need&#13;
&#13;
  be cleaned out regularly. This is creates a huge business                                                                                                                           Integrated services, such as those offered by Indah Water, attract monthly customer&#13;
                                                                      sewage trucks and people willing to go out to people's houses to pump out their septic tanks when&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      fees. They are around RM 6.00 a month for a simple house--about Rp 200,000 (US$ 22)&#13;
  opportunity. Many provide this service, but there are still lots    they are full. Your job is simply to pump the sewage from the septic tank and dispose of it at the              a year. Commercial buildings pay RM 25.00 a month, or around Rp 800,000 (US$ 87) a&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      year. For this fee, septic tanks are checked once a month, and septic tanks are cleaned&#13;
  of openings. And if you want to be more competitive, offer          nearest sewage treatment plant. That's it. In one day, one of your trucks could clean out up to four            out once every two years. There is a surcharge for houses and buildings that produce&#13;
  an integrated service.                                              household septic tanks.                                                                                         more than a set volume of sewage. These figures are obviously much more attractive&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      than the figures for conventional septic tank cleaning. This company uses very hi-tech&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      sewage trucks. The volume pumped out can be measured accurately, and only sewage&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      As well as making sure there is no competition in your target area, there are several other things that         that has settled in the bottom of the septic tank is pumped out. In Indonesia, the entire&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      contents of the tank are pumped out.&#13;
                                                                      you need to think about before getting into this business. Firstly, the distance to the sewage treatment&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      plant from your target areas. The closer the sewage treatment plant, the more customers you can                                                                                                              tenretnI:otohP&#13;
                                                                      potentially serve. Secondly, do you need to work with the local sanitation department? If so, there may&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      be local fees you need to pay.&#13;
10 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           100 Million Customers Await You! 11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      The Figures&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         Former governor of Jakarta, Sutiyoso, has said that potential earnings&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         from development of a sewerage system in Jakarta could be more&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   Collection                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            than Rp 1.5 trillion (US$ 160 million) a year. Sources of income are&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              Qipra&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         not limited to users. Sale of raw water (effluent from sewage&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Photo:                                                                                                                 noitcelloC                                                                                                                                treatment plants) could bring in Rp 250 billion (US$271 million)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    A sewerage system              is a domestic wastewater treatment system,                                                            arpiQ&#13;
                                                                                                                                              which is made upof a wastewatercollection                                                                                                                                                  annually. Sale of organic fertilizer (dried sludge from sewage treatment&#13;
                                                                    pipe network and             a treatment plant.In industrializedcountries, sewerage systems are thenorm, and septic&#13;
                                                                    tanks are almost                                                                                                                          :otohP&#13;
                                                                                                 unknown. This                                                                                                                                                                                                                           plants) could raise Rp 350 billion a year. Sales of biogas could make&#13;
                                                                                                               helps prevent pollutionof groundwater.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            systems.  They include Jakarta, Bandung, Cirebon,                    Solo,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             Only a few                 cities inIndonesia  have sewerage                                                                                Rp 55 billion a year (US$5.9 million). Customer fees alone would&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        and Denpasar.  And even these have limitedcoverage.                   In 2004,&#13;
                                                                    Thedevelopmentofaseweragesystemrequiresverylargeinvestment.Especiallyseweragesystemsonacityscale.As                      Surakarta,                 Yogyakarta, Medan,  Tangerang,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   its sewerage                  stage willbe completedin 2008,                   and    generate Rp 875 billion (US$ 95 million) annually.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             Denpasar                  municipality began building              system. The first&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             of 51,000&#13;
                                                                    anexample,constructionofaseweragesystemfor10,000homesinDenpasarcostmorethanRp5trillion(US$530million).                                                                                       of a sewage           plant witha capacity&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             should cover                 10,000 homes.  This system will consist            treatment&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  of pipeline.&#13;
                                                                    So,aslongasseptictanksareallowed,seweragesystemswon'tbepopular.Limitsonseptictanksareclearlyneeded                        m3/day                  and a totalof 130 kilometers&#13;
&#13;
  4                                                                 for the sewerage system business to grow.&#13;
                    SEWERAGE                                                                                                                                                               If you have the expertise you can become a sewerage system operation contractor in a particular&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                           area. The actual system will be developed by a developer or by the local government, you then&#13;
                    SYSTEMS                                         Fancygettinginvolved?Thereareseveralpathwaysintotheseweragesystembusiness.Ifyouhaveplentyofcapital,you&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                           simply operate it for the term of contract. It is usually for a period of 15-20 years. You are&#13;
                                                                    couldinvestinandoperateaseweragesysteminaparticulararea.Notjustanywhere,ofcourse.Entrepreneurslikeyou&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                           responsible for the smooth running and effectiveness of the system.&#13;
                                                                    shoulddevelopseweragesystemsinbusinessandcommercialareasorineliteresidentialareas.Itwouldbeevenbetter&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    ifyoubuilttheseweragesystemwhiletheareaisbeingdeveloped.Worktogetherwiththedeveloperofthearea.&#13;
  Sewerage systems are not a new way of managing domestic&#13;
                                                                    Constructionofseweragesystemsinestablishedareasismorecomplex.Justtoinstallthepipeline,youwouldhaveto                   Not all sewerage systems are built for large areas; many are built for small ones. The&#13;
  wastewater. The Dutch colonial government started building                                                                                                                               success story of Agus Gunarto's small sewerage system in Malang offers inspiration to&#13;
                                                                    diguptheroadormoveotherexistingpipesystems.Andeventhen,thelocalresidentsmightnotwanttohaveasewerage                    other entrepreneurs, as does the success of the development of sewerage systems under&#13;
  them in the early 1900s. Unfortunately, their construction&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                           the SANIMAS program.&#13;
                                                                    system.&#13;
  almost came to a standstill after that. Now sewerage&#13;
&#13;
  systems are back in demand. This rekindled interest indirectly&#13;
                                                                    Developingaseweragesystemiscostly,buttherearestrategiesthatyoucouldadopttomakethisbusinessaffordable.&#13;
  opens up opportunities for you.&#13;
                                                                    Firstly,developaseweragesystemforsmallresidentialareas,withnomorethanaround100houses.Secondly,usean&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    anaerobictreatmentsystemtominimizeuseofelectricity.Thirdly,thinkaboutdevelopingasmall-boreseweragesystem,                                                                                                                           noitcelloC&#13;
                                                                    which means you'll only be collecting and treating sewage from individual household septic tanks.                                                                                                                                             arpiQ&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       :otohP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 100 Million Customers Await You! 13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             Small-scale&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             sewage treatment plant&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    Dried sludge from a sewage&#13;
                                                                                         idaH                                                                                                                       treatment plant can be used&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             Sewage treatment plants can be built as small scale-systems using&#13;
                                                                                             okraniW                                                                                                                as fertilizer. It has a very high&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    N and P content, and it                                                                                  aerobic treatment technology. This means that sewage treatment&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    doesn't smell. In its blackish&#13;
                                                                                                    :otohP                                                                                                          dried form, it is not evident                                                                            plants don't need large plots of land. The Association of Health&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    that this fertilizer was made                                                                            and Environmental Engineers has designed a blueprint for this kind&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 treatment  plant. Everyday, this plantreceives waste from  6-8&#13;
                                                                                        Padang              municipality has a well-run  sewage                                                                     from human excreta.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                           have&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   anaerobic pools and  sun-drying  of sludge.Other cities                                                                                                                   of sewage treatment plant. The system consists of an aerobic&#13;
                                                                                        sewage              trucks. This  simple system  relies on&#13;
                                                                                                                                                       many of them are   now not working  as well as the one in&#13;
                                                                                        sewage              treatment   plants likethis. Unfortunately,                                                                                                                                                                      digester, an anaerobic digester and a sludge drying bed. It requires&#13;
                                                                                        Padang.                                                                                                                     However, sewage sludge&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             a plot of just 80 m2. With a capacity of 2.5m3/day, this system can&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    treatmentplantsdon'tnecessarily&#13;
                                                                          Sewagesludgetreatmentplantsareanimportantpartofdomesticwastewatermanagementinitiativesespeciallyforcities                                                                                                                                          be built at a cost of around Rp 300 million (US$ 32,600) all in. The&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    havetobebuilttoservethewhole&#13;
                                                                          inIndonesia,wheremosthomesrelyonseptictanksorotheron-sitesystems.Sadly,notallcitiesinIndonesiahavesewage                                                                                                                                           installation is made from used containers that can be moved around.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    city,orusetechnologythatrequires&#13;
                                                                          sludgetreatmentplants.Andthosethatdohavesewagetreatmentplants,manyofthemdon'tfunctionanymore.One                                                                                                                                                   Monthly operating costs are around Rp 2 million (US$ 217).&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    alargeareaorbebuiltfarawayon&#13;
                                                                          reasonforthefailureoftheanaerobictreatmentfunctionisinsufficientinflowofsewage.Mostdriversofsewagetrucks&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    theoutskirtsofthecity.Withalittle&#13;
  5                                                                       can'tbebotheredtogotoatreatmentplanttounloadthecontentsoftheirtrucks,becausemostoftheplantsareonthe&#13;
                    SEWAGE                                                                                                                                                                                          modificationofthetechnologyand&#13;
                                                                          city outskirts.                                                                                                                                                                  ardniyaR&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    adoptionofgoodbusinessstrategies,              :otohP&#13;
                    TREATMENT                                                                                                                                                                                       thesewagetreatmentplantbusiness&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    offers you fantastic opportunities.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                    Totakeadvantageofthisbusinessopportunity,youcandevelopasmall-scalemechanicalsewagesludge&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Septic tanks and other on-site systems are used so that the                                                                                                                                                       treatmentplantthatisbigenoughtoservetheneedsofasinglesub-district.Youcanalsouseodor-free,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  sewage sludge does not pollute the environment. But many                                                                                                                                                          aerobictreatmenttechnology.Thenyouwon'thavetobuilditontheoutskirtsoftown.Youroperatingcosts&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  sewage trucks, dispose of sewage sludge into rivers. Their                                                                                                                                                        wouldbehigher,butitwillbeoff-setbytheincreasednumberofsewagetrucksthatcometoyourplant.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  excuse is that the treatment plant is too far away. Or that there                                                                                                                                                 Theydon'thavedistanceasanexcuseanymore.And,withbetterserviceandimprovedperformance,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  are no sewage sludge treatment plants in the area. But don't                                                                                                                                                      itwouldbereasonableforyoutoeventuallychargehigherfees.Additionallyprocessedanddried&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  lose heart. Instead, look at this situation as an opportunity.                                                                                                                                                    sludge can be sold as fertilizer for extra revenue.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Rayindra&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          Photo:&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  Illustration: D'Zarhoney&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Sewage treatment                           plants in other  countries use aerobicsystems and mechanical   sludge-drying. The dried sludge&#13;
                                                                      is then used as                        fertilizer. Mechanical sewage treatment   plants can be builton smaller plotsof land. Which makes&#13;
                                                                      it easier to find                      a location for them.  Sewage treatment  plants don't haveto be on the outskirtsof the city anymore.&#13;
14 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                    Which means that                           more sewage trucks    can access them  easily.                                                                                                                                                                                                    100 Million Customers Await You! 15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             There are a wide variety of businesses that produce lots of garbage, for example hotels,                                                   Internet&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             industry, office building, restaurants, and shopping malls. Many of them do not have                                                 Photo:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             adequate cleaning services. They need your garbage collection services too. Another of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             your partners could be private real estate developers. They need to offer good quality                                       Internet&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         ihcE                                                                                                                garbage collection and transportation services to market their homes successfully.                                     Photo:&#13;
                                                                             :otohP                                                                                                                                                                                                                            It's not                         only trucks thattransportgarbage.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               practice                                                           In other&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                if the                                     countries,it isdone&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             If you own a large fleet of trucks but don't fancy being a garbage transportation contractor,                                                             siteis alongway  from                                    by train.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            town.                                        This&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  Several                                     is good&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           private&#13;
                                                                                                                               Madyaindo                is gainingan ever stronger  hold                                                                                                                       concept                          to transport                                      firms  haveproposed&#13;
                                                                      With the       tagline "Cleanliness Solutions",PT Ganda              Tama (GMT)                                                                                                                                                                                                        garbage  from Jakarta                                      adopting&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  city to the                                    this&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              Bantar&#13;
                                                                                                                            company                               of indoor and outdoor      you can open a garbage truck leasing business instead. Government sanitation                                      Tailworks                          Corporation                                        Gebang   dump.  One&#13;
                                                                      in the sanitation       business. Set up in 1983, this           operates  in the business                                                                                                                                                                                               Berhad from Malaysia,                                      of these&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     who                                           is&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           works&#13;
                                                                                                                        of garbage             providing  garden maintenance   services.                                                                                                                      Indonesia                          (the Indonesian                                 in partnership with&#13;
                                                                      cleaning.       This includes managing  of a fleet            trucks and                                                                                                                                                                                                                   Railway                                              PT Kereta  Api&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                            in Menteng,      departments don't have enough money to buy all the trucks they need. For example,                                                                                           Company).&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              has                                                                  Unfortunately, theJakarta&#13;
                                                                                                            H. Sofyan             Ch. Dewi,  is responsible  for sanitation                                                                                                                                        yet to                        make  a decision                                             municipal&#13;
                                                                      Today, the       company    set up by           and Aryuni                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  on thisproposal.                                       government&#13;
  6                                                                                                                      Jakarta.                  garbage  from Jakarta's Hilton Hotel,     300 of the thousand or so garbage trucks operating in Jakarta city are leased from&#13;
                                                                       Central       Jakarta, and Pasar Minggu  in South          It also collects&#13;
                    GARBAGE                                                                                             department.           also handles  the cleaning of the buildings&#13;
                                                                       and leases       its trucksto Jakarta'ssanitation             PT GMT&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             private firms. The cost of leasing trucks can run into thousands of dollars a month.&#13;
                                                                                                                       To do allits work,               employs   1,000 workers  and has&#13;
                                                                       and offices       of severalprivate companies.                     the company&#13;
                                                                                                                                            and a lift truck.&#13;
                                                                       25 dump        trucks, 4 open trucks,8 arm-rolltrucks, 3compactors,&#13;
&#13;
                    TRANSPORATION                                                                                                                                                            Several private companies do more than just transport garbage. One example&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      The term 'garbage transportation' usually refers to the transferring of garbage from a temporary                       is PT Wira Gulfindo Sarana, which owns a private transfer station in East&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      disposal site or transfer station to a final disposal site. It might seem a simple task, but the                       Jakarta. This company also has capsule trucks to transport garbage to the&#13;
  Most rubbish has to be transported to a final disposal site.&#13;
                                                                      investment and operating costs involved are actually very high. More than 60% of routine garbage                       Bantar Gebang final disposal site. Recently this place was upgraded to a&#13;
  It is taken there on various kinds of trucks. The costs involved&#13;
                                                                      budgets are spent on these operations. The trucks are very expensive. An ordinary 6 m3 capacity                        garbage treatment plant that produces compost. For each ton of garbage,&#13;
  in providing the trucks and operating costs are enormous.&#13;
                                                                      truck costs more than Rp 400 million (US$ 43,500). Arm-roll trucks cost even more and compactors                       Jakarta municipality pays almost Rp 130,000 (US$ 14).&#13;
  Not many cities are able to allocate the necessary budget.&#13;
                                                                      cost more still. The investment cost will be even higher if the garbage requires transportation by&#13;
  Your participation in the form of investing in these trucks&#13;
                                                                      train. There are lots of opportunities for you in the garbage transportation business. The most&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             You don't need to invest in trucks to get involved in the garbage transport business.&#13;
  would ease the burden of local government budgets.&#13;
                                                                      feasible is becoming a garbage transportation contractor. Your partners could be regional government                   Motorbikes fitted with wagons are becoming more and more popularly used especially&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             for transporting garbage in residential areas.&#13;
                                                                      or private companies. What you need is garbage trucks. The trucks could be the simple or more                                                                                                                     noitcelloC&#13;
                                                                      sophisticated models, depending on the need. If it is your job to transport garbage from a transfer                                                                                                                         arpiQ&#13;
                                                                      station to a final disposal site, you will need large capacity trucks. Preferably fitted with compactors,                                                                                                                        :otohP&#13;
                                                                      so you can make efficient use of fuel. If your job is to transport garbage from source, a small or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                    medium-sized truck will do.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   100 Million Customers Await You! 17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                    Youcanaddvaluetoyourcompostbyproducingitingranularform.Thetechniqueisvery                    Internet&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     ihcE                                                                                                           simpleandtheinvestmentisminimal.Itismoreeffectivethanconventionalcompostand            Photo:&#13;
                                                                         :otohP                                                                                                     canincreasericeproductivityby20%-30%.Granulesaremorepracticaltoo.Youshould         Production             of granularcompost    begins with drying ordinary   compost.  The dried  compost&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       milled and                                                                                                 is then&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              finely ground. It is turnedinto granules&#13;
                                                                                                                               that compressed                  Greater Jakarta     learn from the experience of other granular compost producers.                                                                                       by mixing  the ground    compost  with a little&#13;
                                                                   PT Wira        Gulfindo Sarana was known   as the company                    and transported&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       water and             adhesive.  This can  be done in a cement&#13;
                                                                                                                       1992, the           opened  a transferstation,charging a                                                                                                                                                         mixer. This product   is easier to sell in large&#13;
                                                                   area's garbage        to the BantarGebang  dump. In            company                                                                                                                              quantities.            One granular compost    producers exports   2,000 tons&#13;
                                                                                                                its mainbusiness             compost.  Garbage that couldnot be                                                                                                                                                                       of compost   annually   to Japan,&#13;
                                                                   tipping       fee of Rp60,000 (US$ 6.50). But                  was making                                                                                                                           the US,            Italy and Taiwan.&#13;
                                                                                                                the company,  led by BudhiSentosa  Rachmat  Kertadjaja,began to     Organicgarbagecanalsobeturnedintoliquidfertilizer.Ithasmanyadvantagesovercompost.&#13;
                                                                   processed        was ball-pressed. Over time,&#13;
  7                                                                                                                                                                           is&#13;
                                                                                                                                     marketfor thisBIOKOM    granularcompost&#13;
                                                                   concentrate        on production of granular compost. The target                                                 Ithasamoreconcentratednutrientcontent.It'seasiertoapplybysplashingorsprayingit&#13;
                                                                                                               company              busy preparingitself to"Go organic" by 2010.&#13;
                                                                   farmers        outside the Jakartaarea. The          is currently&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                    onthesoil.Itssellingpriceishigher.Liquidfertilizercanbemadebymixingwaterwithliquid&#13;
                    COMPOSTING&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                    extractoforganicmatterthathasbeenfermentedanaerobically.Ittakeslesstimetoproduce.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     It's common knowledge that organic garbage can be turned into compost. Several community                       Moderntechnologieshavebeendevelopedtomaketheprocessofmakingliquid&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     groups have been doing it for their own use and for sale. This is an effective way of reducing                 fertilizermoreefficient.Oneofthesetechnologiesisautothermalthermophilicaerobic&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     the volume of organic garbage. Unfortunately, from a commercial point of view, composting                      digestion(ATAD).Onedrawbackisthat,unlikecompost,liquidfertilizerdoesnot                                                             Liquid fertilizer has a higher economic value. It sells at Rp 30,000&#13;
  There's a guaranteed supply of raw materials--70% of                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  (US$3.3) a liter. This product is sold in 500 ml and 1000 ml bottles,&#13;
                                                                     might not be an attractive proposition. The unit selling price is low compared to the high labor               function as a soil conditioner.                                                                                                     making it easier to transport. One liter of liquid fertilizer reportedly&#13;
  urban garbage is organic. You could opt to process garbage&#13;
                                                                     and time inputs. You can only expect to get around Rp 500 (US$0.50) per kilo, so you'll only make                                                                                                                                                  has a nutrient content equal to 50 kilograms of compost.&#13;
&#13;
  to make compost or liquid fertilizer. Both have their&#13;
                                                                     a decent profit if you high volume orders. Or, you could make slight modifications to the compost&#13;
  advantages. Sales strategy is critical to giving your product&#13;
                                                                     products to make them more attractive to your customers.&#13;
  the competitive edge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     Photo: Taufi k Ismail&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        100 Million Customers Await You! 19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     There are still lots of opportunities to utilize new inorganic garbage, such as&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     the ever increasing volume of e-waste or electronic appliance waste. This&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     kind of waste is piling up by the day as we produce more and more of these&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     products and old ones become obsolete. E-waste needs to be processed&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     properly. It can't be incinerated because that would pollute the environment.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     This type of waste can be recycled into other products. China, for example,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   ihcE                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              has managed to increase its national income from recycling e-waste. Japanese&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                              Collection&#13;
                                                                       :otohP                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        investors set up special factories to collect the e-waste from the products&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                         Qipra                                                                                                       they make. The next step is to get other electronics producers involved. In&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     this way, e-waste can have a positive use and not pollute the environment.&#13;
                                                                                                                  Ancol Sayang   Lingkungan                Environment) Recycling&#13;
                                                                 In 1996,      Djiwo Siswo   Yuwono  set up the                              (Love Ancol&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   Photo:&#13;
                                                                                                                                     by making  recycled paper from used materials&#13;
                                                                 Group. With       an investment of Rp 1 million(US$ 108), he began&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  how serious           about doing  this, PT Pembangunan    Jaya,&#13;
                                                                 gathered        from his neighborhood.  Seeing                he was                                                          A variety                  of recyclingtechnologies&#13;
                                                                                                                                 invited him to work with them  in processing their                                                               are available.You needto use theseto give youa competitiveedge.&#13;
                                                                               its corporatesocial responsibility (CSR) program&#13;
                                                                 through&#13;
  8                                                                                                                                          orders not only from PT Pembangunan&#13;
                                                                 waste paper.       Today, Ancol Sayang  Lingkungan   Recycling Group gets&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              and several                      To expand its market&#13;
                                                                  Jaya, but      from PT IndonesiaPower, PT   Astra Indonesia,             other organizations.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                             wings&#13;
                                                                                                   and wedding               from recycled  paper. The  group has spread its&#13;
                                                                  the group       makes souvenirs                invitations&#13;
                    RECYCLING                                                                                          groups   in Jatiwaringin,    Tangerang    and Puwakarta.&#13;
                                                                  outside        Ancol   too, setting  up satellite&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                       It is not only plastics that can be recycled; other materials are paper,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                       metal and glass should play a part in your processing chain,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   Let's look at the journey of scrap plastic in the recycling chain. Take a 240 ml plastic mineral                    too. With good financial and technological capital, your&#13;
&#13;
  By now most everyone would have heard the term recycling.        water cup, for example. The wastepickers that collect these cups sells them for up to Rp 3,000                      processing will be more efficient. Let wastepickers and&#13;
&#13;
  But perhaps not everyone realizes that there is an enormous      a kilo. In the hands of someone who owns a shredder, these plastic cups are shredded, and then                      collectors gather the materials for recycling. Good relations&#13;
&#13;
  business potential in recycling. Nowadays, thousands of          sold for Rp 5,000 a kilo. In the hands of someone with the right equipment, the shredded plastic                    with them will guarantee you the supply of raw&#13;
&#13;
  different kinds of garbage can be recycled­plastic, paper,       is then melted down and made into plastic pellets. This is sold to plastics factories for Rp 8,000                  materials you need.&#13;
&#13;
  metal, glass and bottles. Lots of people are recycling, but      a kilo. This illustration shows that the economic value of recycling material increases more than&#13;
&#13;
  only a few are using the latest technology. There are still      100% if we use appropriate technology to process it first. This is where you come into the&#13;
&#13;
  lots of openings for you to have a successful recycling          recycling business. Not in the collection chain, but in the processing chain. This is what John&#13;
&#13;
  business.                                                        Peter, who you read about at the beginning of this booklet, did.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           Photo: Qipra Collection&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             100 Million Customers Await You! 21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   Another option is opening a private final disposal site. This would&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   be a profitable venture, but the investment cost is very high because&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   you need to secure a large plot of land, and on top of that it wouldn't&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   be easy to get started. To avoid opposition from the local inhabitants,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    Collection&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   you have to go through the environmental impact analysis procedures&#13;
                                                                               Qipra&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   required by law. You don't want a repeat of the case of the Bojong&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         Photo:                                                                                                                                                                                               ihcE&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   integrated final disposal site. To reassure the locals, apply garbage&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      The operational                management   of finaldisposal                                                                                                                                                :otohP&#13;
                                                                                                                                  sites inIndonesiais still farfrom ideal.                         disposal technologies that are more environment-friendly. Using better&#13;
                                                                      be transferred                                                                                      Their operation&#13;
                                                                                                    to the private                                                                       could&#13;
                                                                                                                  sector. Theprivatecompany  would then                                                                                                                                                                                                                            into&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          be responsible                                                                                                                                                     reusable materials.Organic  garbage    is reprocessed&#13;
                                                                      properly.                                                                                           for operating&#13;
                                                                                                The government's,                                                                      the site                                                                                                     are demolishedto reclaim&#13;
                                                                                                                  sanitation                                                                                                                                                               landfills&#13;
                                                                                                                            department,                                                            techniques means you could charge larger tipping fees, too.               Many old&#13;
                                                                                                                                         would then take on    the exclusiverole of regulators.                                                                              good quality     compost.  Inorganicgarbage is sortedas needed.&#13;
&#13;
  9FINAL                                                                                                                                                                                           Managing a final disposal site would offer various sources of additional&#13;
                                                                      Aslongasthereisgarbage,therewillbeaneedforfinaldisposalsites.Evenwithcompostingandincinerators,final&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   income. First, selling biogas (see the next section on Energy from Garbage) to&#13;
                                                                      disposalsitesarestillneededfordumpingtheresidueandashes.Uptonow,mostfinaldisposalsiteshavebeen&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   the local people, or turning&#13;
                    DISPOSAL                                          builtandareownedandoperatedbythegovernment.Butwithmountingcriticismfromlocalcommunities,many&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   it into electrical energy.&#13;
                                                                      localgovernmentshavebegunthinkingaboutinvolvingtheprivatesectorintheirmanagement.Hereisanattractive&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   Reuse all the garbage in&#13;
                                                                      business opportunity for you.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   your final disposal site,&#13;
  Ultimately, there would still be unrecyclable garbage that&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   because some of it,&#13;
  has to be disposed of. So, there will always be a need for&#13;
                                                                      Oneopportunityyoucouldconsiderismanagingfinaldisposalsitesundercontract.Insomecountries,manymunicipal&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   organic and inorganic, has&#13;
  final disposal sites. Most facilities that are good are sanitary&#13;
                                                                      governmentsworkinpartnershiptomanageandoperatetheirfinaldisposalsites.InIndonesia,thereareveryfew&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   a resale value. In some&#13;
  landfills. Many recent technological developments have&#13;
                                                                      ofthesepartnerships.OneexampleisPTPatriotBangkitBekasi,whichwonthecontracttooperatetheBantar&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   countries, old landfills&#13;
  made final disposal sites more environment-friendly.&#13;
                                                                      Gebangfinaldisposalsitebackin2004.Togetintothisbusiness,youneedtoprovidethenecessaryheavyequipment,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   are demolished and the                                                                                                                 Round baling makes more efficient use the land&#13;
                                                                      workers,andagoodenvironmentalmanagementplan.Andofcourse,you'llneedtherighttechnicalknowledge.                                                                                                                                                                       the final disposal site is on. This means your final&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                   waste is reprocessed.&#13;
                                                                      Municipalgovernmentswillpayforyourservicesbytheweightofgarbagedumpedatthefinaldisposalsite.This                                                                         Collection                                                                                  disposal site can hold more garbage. And it is&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          safer for the local environment.&#13;
                                                                      ranges from around Rp 50,000 to 100,000 (US$5.40­10.80) per ton.                                                                                                   Qipra&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   Photo:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              100 Million Customers Await You! 23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      When sounding out these opportunities in the waste energy business, you must be very&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      careful as not all activities are self-financing. A waste power generator could not survive&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    Clean Development&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      on the revenue from sales of electricity alone. You'd still need to supplement revenue&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      with tipping fees to cover operating costs. Generating biogas might be more profitable&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      for you. Especially if you capture the energy from existing final disposal sites. Several                                     Mechanism&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      private firms are exploring the potential of waste gases from final disposal sites.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      Unfortunately, most of them are just capturing and burning methane gas to get compensation                                       Climate change. The suspected causes are carbon dioxide, methane and other&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       greenhouse gases. The more of these gases are emitted, the hotter the earth&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      under the clean development mechanism (CDM) scheme. Not many genuinely want to                                                   gets. With this knowledge, in Kyoto, Japan in 1997, industrialized countries&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      turn this biogas into energy. One is the power generation plant run on biogas at Suwung                                          were asked to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions. A target was agreed&#13;
                                                                           tenretnI:otohP                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              for each industrialized country. Amazingly, they don't have to reduce their&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      final disposal site (Denpasar, Bali), which generates 2 MW of electricity. That's enough                                         own greenhouse emissions. If they want to pay for reducing greenhouse&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       gases in developing countries, they'll get credit for working to achieve their&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      to power 40,000 homes. The investment cost was US$ 20 million.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       carbon emission targets.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    sawdust  as a fuel. Ujan Solichin went ahead and developed&#13;
                                                                         The idea             came from   sawmill workers  who use&#13;
                                                                                                                                            dust at  his home in PasirAngi, Ciamas,Jawa Barat.                                                                                                                                         That is why lots of industrialized countries want to finance initiatives to&#13;
10                                                                       the idea             into making "waste  briquettes"  from sawmill&#13;
                                                                                                                                          in their production is waste. These briquettes  sell for                                                                                                                                     reduce greenhouse gas emissions in Indonesia. Including management of&#13;
                   ENERGY                                                They are              called thatbecause  the main  raw material&#13;
                                                                                                                                     the price               which costs Rp 2,300a liter. Aswell                                                                                                                                       biogas from our final disposal sites. This financing mechanism is known as&#13;
                                                                         Rp 1,600              a kilo (US$0.17). Which  is well below          of kerosene,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                  and smoke-free.  It even produces blue flames.Not surprisingly,                                                                                                                                      the clean development mechanism (CDM). You could strive to obtain this&#13;
                                                                         as being              cheap, the briquettes are odorless&#13;
                                                                                                                                     businesses.                   nine employees  who are   paid                                                                                                                                      financial assistance if you want to run a business managing gases from final&#13;
                                                                         the briquettes              are sought after by large-scale              With the  help of&#13;
                    FROM WASTE                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         disposal sites. Of course, there are procedures and bureaucracy that you have&#13;
                                                                                                                                 corporal          produce  100-200 kilograms of wastebriquettes&#13;
                                                                         Rp 15,000              (US$ 1.60) each a day, this chief        is able to&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                       demand,             is as much     as 60  tons a    week.                                                                                                                                       to go through. It's not easy, but many have tried, and succeeded.&#13;
                                                                          a day.               This is   still well  below    market              which&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Some kinds of waste have a high energy content. With the                               The energy contained in waste can be captured in a variety of ways. One way is to incinerate&#13;
&#13;
  price of oil rising all the time, energy sources that have a better                    waste that is suitable for incineration. The heat produced can then be used to generate electricity.&#13;
&#13;
  economic value are being sought and utilized more. There are                           Waste power generators use waste as fuel. Another way to process waste is to decompose the&#13;
&#13;
  several ways of capturing energy from waste. With a growing                            waste until it produces biogas. This can only be done with biodegradable organic waste. A third&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           Collection&#13;
  market, this business has a huge potential. So it's worth looking                      way is turning organic waste into waste briquettes. These burn easily, are smoke-free, and safe&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                      Qipra&#13;
  into its feasibility.                                                                  for the environment. Waste briquettes retail at a far lower price than kerosene or gas. Another&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                Photo:&#13;
                                                                                         option might be in the form of round baling.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            An example                   of an electricity generatingplant runon biogas,  near Perth,Australia.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            this installation                                                                                   Operating&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             turns landfill                                                              since 2003,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           biogas into2.1 MW  of electricity.Under theclean development&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            scheme,                   credit is                                                                          mechanism&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               given for   using methane  gas from landfills. The CDM    scheme&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            enormous                                                                                             in Indonesia&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       opportunities.                                                                        offers&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       Data show   that Indonesia'swaste potential   is vast.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            404 million                                                                                      It couldgenerate&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         m3 of                                                                                up to&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  methane     emissions   each year.  The equivalent     of 79 MW    of electricity.&#13;
&#13;
24 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  100 Million Customers Await You! 25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               To give legal certainty to you and other entrepreneurs, we have the Presidential&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               Regulation 67/2005 on Public and Private Sector Partnerships in Infrastructure&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               Development. This regulation guarantees financial risk sharing between public&#13;
DON'T WORRY                                                         POLITICAL SUPPORT&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               and private sector partners. Government will also help you to get public acceptance&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      There's no need to worry about not having political support. If it has to do with public health,         for you project and financial support without sovereign guarantees, and protect&#13;
&#13;
           YOU'RE NOT                                                 no official is going to knock it back. You'll get support. From the executive and the legislative        you against corruption, collusion and nepotism. The Ministry of Public Works,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      officials at national, provincial, district and municipal levels. In fact, recently, through programs    through Regulation of the Minister of Public Works 21/2007 concerning the                                     ihcE&#13;
                                     ALONE                            driven by the Indonesian National Development Planning Agency, government agencies are                   Policy and Strategy for Development of a National Garbage Management System                                       :otohP&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      meeting more frequently to discuss the development of the sanitation sector. Inter-agency                also calls for an increase in the role of the private sector as partners in garbage&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         You might           not be aware&#13;
                                                                      work groups have been formed at national and regional levels. They are working to coordinate                                                                                                                                                         of it, butpublic sector&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               management.                                                                                                                                                         participation in the sanitationbusiness&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         way to help                                                                                       has gone&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              the government.                                                                       a long&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                People running  garbage  transportation  businesses have reduced&#13;
                                                                      their authorities, responsibilities and roles to speed up sanitation development. The obligation                                                                                                                   to purchase           costly garbage                                                                     the need&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                trucks.  Those in the public  WC business    have eased&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         responsibility          to build                                                                the government's&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         public facilities.So it's onlyright that the government&#13;
  From what you've read in this booklet, you are now aware            to meet the Millennium Development Goal targets is spurring everyone on to work harder and             TAX BREAKS                                                                                                  sector participation                                                                     should facilitateprivate&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      with various  incentives and facilities.&#13;
&#13;
  that there all kinds of opportunities in the sanitation             work together.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               Tax breaks may apply to some activities in the sanitation sector. These include paper&#13;
  business. If you still don't feel at ease, you might like to&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               pulp production, land transportation, organic agro-industry, and production of&#13;
  know that there are things to help you on the way. Demand&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               packaging from paper, card and plastic. This is implied in Government&#13;
  aside, political support, regulations, tax breaks, and technical  REGULATIONS&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               Regulation 148/2000 on Income Tax Facilities for Capital Investment&#13;
  assistance on sanitation sector development are all&#13;
                                                                      Soonwe'regoingtohaveaWasteManagementLawthatwillgenerateacomprehensivegarbagemanagement&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               in Certain Sectors in Certain Regions.&#13;
  available. Let's hope these help persuade you to get involved&#13;
                                                                      scheme.Theparticipationofall,includingtheprivatesectorandcommunities,willbeguaranteedunderthis&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               For capitalization, you can make use of credit facilities for small and&#13;
  in the sanitation business.&#13;
                                                                      law.Optimaluseofwasteisamustforagenciesresponsibleforthecity'ssanitation.Atalowerlevel,wehave&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               medium-sized enterprises. Loans start from Rp 100 million (US$10,800)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      manylocalordinancesthatrequirecommunitiestomanagetheirowngarbageproperly,tohavepropertoilets,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               and go up to a maximum of Rp 2.5 billion (US$ 272,000). The interest&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      andtonotengageinactivitiesthatpollute.Allareoffencesforwhichyoucanbefinedorheldincustody.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               is linked to interest on Bank Indonesia Certificates. Getting a loan is&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               easy, too. You need to have been in business for a least two years. Then            noitcelloC&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               you just have to submit a loan application, a business feasibility report,                    arpiQ&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               business permits, and proof of your identity. Along with financial reports                         :otohP&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               for the past two years and your business credentials.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 Sanitation          Working  Group has  been set up&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 In Indonesia                            the Water   Supply and   Environmental             (WSES)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           representatives                    Development   Planning&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 at the national                            level. This  group comprises                     of the National&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             of the Environment,  Ministryof Finance,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 Agency,                    Ministry          of Public Works, Ministry  of Health, Ministry&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         Affairs.Representatives   of non-governmental  organizations&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 Ministry                   of Industry,          and Ministry of Home&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   programs. The same   components  make up  working&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 and the                    private sector          provideinput and   coordinate&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  groups at                            the districtand municipal   level.&#13;
&#13;
26 Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           100 Million Customers Await You! 27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="9936489">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2008/04/9936489/sanitation-business-100-million-customers-await
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2008/04/9936489/sanitation-business-100-million-customers-await</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2008/04/9936489/sanitation-business-100-million-customers-await</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2008/10/15/000333037_20081015050849/Rendered/INDEX/460800WSP0Box3101Millions1Customers.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2008/10/15/000333037_20081015050849/Rendered/PDF/460800WSP0Box3101Millions1Customers.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2008-10-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2008-04-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The sanitation business : 100 million
            customers await you!
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            That's right! There really are 100
            million potential customers waiting for readers. Data show
            that 45 percent of Indonesian people do not have access to
            sanitation services. That's more than 100 million
            people. The government can't necessarily deal with this
            by it self. Like it or not, people are waiting for readers
            participation in providing sanitation services. If the
            author relies on the government to improve and develop
            sanitation facilities, it's going to be a long wait.
            Government efforts are limited by financial constraints.
            Existing facilities cannot be properly maintained. And some
            facilities in disrepair and abandoned because they are
            unusable. Now is the time for the private sector to get
            involved in sanitation. Perhaps the sanitation sector
            hasn't seemed to be a very attractive prospect. Low
            status, small profits. But on the contrary this business is
            actually just as good as any other business. This business
            is profitable, it benefits lots of ordinary people, and it
            helps create jobs. It should be noted that the idea that
            sanitation is only for the poor is incorrect. Reader
            customers will be from the middle to upper classes too. They
            need sanitation services as well. Like garbage
            transportation and emptying out septic tanks, for instance.
            This book looks at a wide variety of initiatives that could
            be managed by the private sector.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The sanitation business : 100 million
            customers await you!
        </docna>
        <display_title>The sanitation business : 100
            million customers await you!</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2008/04/9936489/sanitation-business-100-million-customers-await</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Urban Solid Waste Management,Wastewater Treatment,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Transport Economics Policy &amp; Planning,Sanitation and Sewerage</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Transport,Water Supply and Sanitation</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20081015050849</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Indonesia Sanitation Sector Development Program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Transport,Water Supply and Sanitation</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to sanitation, aerobic digestion,
            air, airports, anaerobic treatment, bacteria, biogas,
            briquettes, bus, bus terminal, Capital Investment, carbon
            dioxide, carbon emission, city outskirts, Climate change,
            compactors, compost, Composting, disposal sites, domestic
            wastewater, drivers, efficient use, electricity, emission
            targets, emissions, environmental management, excreta,
            filters, Final Disposal, Final Disposal Site, financial
            risk, fuel, fuel costs, garbage, GARBAGE COLLECTION, garbage
            disposal, garbage trucks, gases, glass, greenhouse
            emissions, greenhouse gas, greenhouse gas emissions,
            greenhouse gases, groundwater, heat, heavy equipment, high
            energy, household waste, human excreta, incineration,
            incinerators, Income Tax, inspection, journey, landfill,
            latrines, Mechanical sewage treatment, methane, methane gas,
            nutrient content, old landfills, open trucks, organic
            matter, organic waste, pipes, plastic, plastics, pollution,
            property owners, public facilities, public health, public
            latrines, public toilet, public toilets, public transport,
            Public Works, pumps, Railway, raw water, Recycling,
            residential areas, rivers, road, rubbish, sanitary
            landfills, Sanitation, sanitation department, sanitation
            departments, sanitation development, sanitation equipment,
            sanitation facilities, Sanitation Program, sanitation
            sector, sanitation services, Scrap, scrubbers, seepage,
            septic tank, septic tank cleaning, septic tank emptying,
            septic tanks, Sewage, sewage sludge, Sewage Treatment,
            sewage treatment plant, sewage treatment plants, Sewerage,
            SEWERAGE SYSTEM, Sewerage Systems, sludge, sludge drying,
            sludge treatment, small sewerage, small-bore sewerage, tank
            cleaning, tank inspection, TAX, tipping fees, toilet,
            transportation, transportation services, urban areas, urban
            garbage, users, vehicles, Waste, waste collection, Waste
            Management, waste paper, wastewater, wastewater collection,
            wastewater management, wastewater treatment, wastewater
            treatment system, Water Supply
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>46080</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Climate Business</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Energy Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Innovation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Landfills</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Wastewater</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Methane</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Innovation, Technology and Entrepreneurship</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>