<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<wiki:nominee year="1952" span="1" winner="false" award="lead-actress" xmlns:wiki="http://marklogic.com/wikipedia">
  <!--
                            Copyright (c) 2010 MarkLogic Corporation.
                            Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
                            under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
                            or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
                            with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
                            A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
                            Free Documentation License"
                            
                            Content derived from http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudden_Fear and http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Crawford
                            Modified in May 2009 by Mark Logic Corporation under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License.
                        -->
  <wiki:name link="/wiki/Joan_Crawford">Joan Crawford</wiki:name>
  <wiki:person link="/wiki/Joan_Crawford" name="Joan Crawford">
    <wiki:oscar year="1945" span="1" winner="true" award="lead-actress" film-link="/wiki/Mildred_Pierce_(film)" film-title="Mildred Pierce"/>
    <wiki:oscar year="1947" span="1" winner="false" award="lead-actress" film-link="/wiki/Possessed_(1947_film)" film-title="Possessed"/>
    <wiki:oscar year="1952" span="1" winner="false" award="lead-actress" film-link="/wiki/Sudden_Fear" film-title="Sudden Fear"/>
    <wiki:image link="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/cc/JoanCrawfordByYousufKarsh.jpg/220px-JoanCrawfordByYousufKarsh.jpg"/>
    <wiki:birth>
      <wiki:date>1905-03-23</wiki:date>
      <wiki:place>
	<wiki:primary link="/wiki/San_Antonio,_Texas">San Antonio, Texas</wiki:primary>
	<wiki:secondary link=""/>
      <enrich><woeid xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng">12590021</woeid><placeTypeName code="9" xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng">County</placeTypeName><name xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng">Bexar</name><country code="US" type="Country" xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng">United States</country><admin1 code="US-TX" type="State" xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng">Texas</admin1><admin2 code="" type="County" xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng">Bexar</admin2><admin3 xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng"/><locality1 xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng"/><locality2 xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng"/><postal xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng"/><centroid xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng"><latitude>29.437559</latitude><longitude>-98.461708</longitude></centroid><boundingBox xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng"><southWest><latitude>29.114491</latitude><longitude>-98.806419</longitude></southWest><northEast><latitude>29.760620</latitude><longitude>-98.117012</longitude></northEast></boundingBox><areaRank xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng">8</areaRank><popRank xmlns="http://where.yahooapis.com/v1/schema.rng">0</popRank></enrich></wiki:place>
    </wiki:birth>
    <wiki:death>
      <wiki:date>May 10, 1977</wiki:date>
      <wiki:place>
	<wiki:primary link="/wiki/New_York_City,_New_York">New York City, New York</wiki:primary>
	<wiki:secondary link=""/>
      </wiki:place>
    </wiki:death>
    <wiki:description>
      <wiki:abstract>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><b>Joan Crawford</b> (March 23, 1905 – May 10, 1977), born <b>Lucille Fay LeSueur</b>, was an American actress in film, television and theatre. Starting as a dancer in traveling theatrical companies before debuting on <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadway_theatre" title="Broadway theatre">Broadway</a>, Crawford was signed to a motion picture contract by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer" title="Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer">Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer</a> in 1925. Initially frustrated by the size and quality of her parts, Crawford began a campaign of self-publicity and became nationally known as a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flapper" title="Flapper">flapper</a> by the end of the 1920s. In the 1930s, Crawford's fame rivaled MGM colleagues <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norma_Shearer" title="Norma Shearer">Norma Shearer</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greta_Garbo" title="Greta Garbo">Greta Garbo</a>. Crawford often played hardworking young women who find romance and financial success. These "rags-to-riches" stories were well-received by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Depression" title="Great Depression">Depression</a>-era audiences and were popular with women. Crawford became one of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood,_Los_Angeles,_California" title="Hollywood, Los Angeles, California">Hollywood's</a> most prominent movie stars and one of the highest paid women in the United States, but her films began losing money and by the end of the 1930s she was labeled "box office poison".</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After an absence of nearly two years from the screen, Crawford staged a comeback by starring in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mildred_Pierce_(film)" title="Mildred Pierce (film)">Mildred Pierce</a></i> (1945), for which she won the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Actress" title="Academy Award for Best Actress">Academy Award for Best Actress</a>. In 1955, she became involved with the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PepsiCo" title="PepsiCo">Pepsi-Cola Company</a> through her marriage to company Chairman <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfred_Steele" title="Alfred Steele">Alfred Steele</a>. After his death in 1959, Crawford was elected to fill his vacancy on the board of directors but was forcibly retired in 1973. She continued acting in film and television regularly through the 1960s, when her performances became fewer; after the release of the British horror film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trog" title="Trog">Trog</a></i> in 1970, Crawford retired from the screen. Following a public appearance in 1974, after which unflattering photographs were published, Crawford withdrew from public life and became more and more reclusive until her death in 1977.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford married four times. Her first three marriages ended in divorce; the last ended with the death of husband Al Steele. She adopted five children, one of whom was reclaimed by his birth mother. Crawford's relationships with her two older children, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christina_Crawford" title="Christina Crawford">Christina</a> and Christopher, were acrimonious. Crawford disinherited the two and, after Crawford's death, Christina wrote a "tell-all" memoir, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mommie_Dearest" title="Mommie Dearest">Mommie Dearest</a></i>, in which she alleged a lifelong pattern of physical and emotional abuse perpetrated by Crawford.</p>
	<h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Early_life">Early life</span></h2>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford was born <b>Lucille Fay LeSueur</b> in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Antonio,_Texas" title="San Antonio, Texas">San Antonio, Texas</a>, the third child of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tennessee" title="Tennessee">Tennessee</a>-born Thomas E. LeSueur (1868–1938), a laundry laborer of French Huguenot and English ancestry, and Anna Bell Johnson (1884–1958), who was of Swedish and Irish descent. Her older siblings were Daisy LeSueur, who died very young, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hal_LeSueur" title="Hal LeSueur">Hal LeSueur</a>. Thomas LeSueur abandoned the family a few months before Crawford's birth. He reappeared in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abilene,_Texas" title="Abilene, Texas">Abilene</a>, Texas, in 1930 as a 62-year-old construction laborer on the George R. Davis House, built in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prairie_School" title="Prairie School">Prairie School</a> architecture.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford's mother subsequently married Henry J. Cassin. The family lived in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawton,_Oklahoma" title="Lawton, Oklahoma">Lawton, Oklahoma</a>, where Cassin ran a movie theater. Crawford was unaware that Cassin was not her birth father until her brother Hal told her. The 1910 federal census for <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comanche_County,_Oklahoma" title="Comanche County, Oklahoma">Comanche County, Oklahoma</a>, enumerated on April 20, showed Henry and Anna living at 910 "D" Street in Lawton. Crawford was listed as five years old, thus showing 1905 as her likely year of birth. However, the state of Texas did not require the filing of birth certificates until 1908, allowing Crawford to claim she was born in 1908.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford preferred the nickname "Billie" as a child and she loved watching <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaudeville" title="Vaudeville">vaudeville</a> acts perform on the stage of her stepfather's theater. Her ambition was to be a dancer. However, in an attempt to escape piano lessons to run and play with friends, she leapt from the front porch of her home and cut her foot deeply on a broken milk bottle. Crawford had three operations and was unable to attend elementary school for a year and a half. She eventually fully recovered and returned to dancing.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Around 1916, Crawford's family moved to <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kansas_City,_Missouri" title="Kansas City, Missouri">Kansas City, Missouri</a>. Cassin was first listed in the City Directory in 1917, living at 403 East Ninth Street. While still in elementary school, Crawford was placed in St. Agnes Academy, a Catholic school in Kansas City. Later, after her mother and stepfather broke up, she stayed on at St. Agnes as a work student. She then went to Rockingham Academy as a work student. While attending Rockingham she began dating and had her first serious relationship, with a trumpet player named Ray Sterling. It was Sterling who inspired her to begin challenging herself academically, and in 1922, Crawford registered at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephens_College" title="Stephens College">Stephens College</a> in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia,_Missouri" title="Columbia, Missouri">Columbia, Missouri</a>. She gave her year of birth as 1906. Crawford attended Stephens for less than a year, as she recognized that she was not academically prepared for college.</p>
	<h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Career">Career</span></h2>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under the name Lucille LeSueur, Crawford began dancing in the choruses of traveling revues and was spotted dancing in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detroit" title="Detroit">Detroit</a> by producer <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_J._Shubert" title="Jacob J. Shubert">Jacob J. Shubert</a>. Shubert put her in the chorus line for his 1924 show <i>Innocent Eyes</i> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winter_Garden_Theatre" title="Winter Garden Theatre">Winter Garden Theatre</a> on <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadway_(theatre)" title="Broadway (theatre)">Broadway</a> in New York City. While appearing in <i>Innocent Eyes</i> Crawford met a saxophone player named James Welton. The two were allegedly married in 1924 and the couple lived together for several months, although this supposed marriage was never mentioned in later life by Crawford. She wanted additional work and approached <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loews_Theaters" title="Loews Theaters">Loews Theaters</a> publicist <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nils_Granlund" title="Nils Granlund">Nils Granlund</a>. Granlund secured a position for her with producer Harry Richmond's act and arranged for her to do a screen test which he sent to producer <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry_Rapf" title="Harry Rapf">Harry Rapf</a> in Hollywood. Stories have persisted that Crawford further supplemented her income by appearing in one or more <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pornographic_film" title="Pornographic film">stag</a>, or soft-core pornographic, films, although this has been disputed. Rapf notified Granlund on December 24, 1924 that <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer" title="Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer">Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer</a> had offered Crawford a contract at $75 a week. Granlund immediately wired LeSueur – who had returned to her mother's home in Kansas City – with the news; she borrowed $400 (which she never paid back) for travel expenses. The night after Christmas she left Kansas City and arrived in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Culver_City,_California" title="Culver City, California">Culver City, California</a>.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As Lucille LeSueur, her first film was <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pretty_Ladies" title="Pretty Ladies">Pretty Ladies</a></i> in 1925, which starred <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZaSu_Pitts" title="ZaSu Pitts">ZaSu Pitts</a>. Also in 1925 she appeared in a small role in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Only_Thing" title="The Only Thing">The Only Thing</a></i> and in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Clothes" title="Old Clothes">Old Clothes</a></i> opposite <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jackie_Coogan" title="Jackie Coogan">Jackie Coogan</a>. MGM publicity head <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pete_Smith_(film_producer)" title="Pete Smith (film producer)">Pete Smith</a> recognized her ability but felt that her name sounded fake; it also, he told studio head <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_B._Mayer" title="Louis B. Mayer">Louis B. Mayer</a>, sounded like "Le Sewer". Smith organized a contest in conjunction with the fan magazine <i>Movie Weekly</i> to allow readers to select her new name. Initially the name "Joan Arden" was selected but, when another actress was found to have prior claim to that name, the alternate name "Crawford" became the choice. Crawford initially wanted her new first name to be pronounced "Jo-anne". She hated the name Crawford, saying it sounded like "crawfish". Her friend, actor <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Haines" title="William Haines">William Haines</a>, quipped, "They might have called you 'Cranberry' and served you every Thanksgiving with the turkey!" Crawford continued to dislike the name throughout her life but, she said, "liked the security that went with it".</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Growing increasingly frustrated over the size and quality of the parts she was given, Crawford embarked on a campaign of self-promotion. As MGM screenwriter <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederica_Sagor_Maas" title="Frederica Sagor Maas">Frederica Sagor Maas</a> recalled, "No one decided to make Joan Crawford a star. Joan Crawford became a star because Joan Crawford decided to become a star." She began attending dances in the afternoons and evenings at hotels around Hollywood, where she often won dance competitions with her performances of the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charleston_(dance)" title="Charleston (dance)">Charleston</a> and the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Bottom_(dance)" title="Black Bottom (dance)">Black Bottom</a>. Her strategy worked, and MGM cast her in the film where she first made an impression on audiences, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund_Goulding" title="Edmund Goulding">Edmund Goulding</a>'s <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sally,_Irene_and_Mary" title="Sally, Irene and Mary">Sally, Irene and Mary</a></i> (1925). She played Irene, a struggling chorus girl. In the same year, Crawford worked on <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_of_the_Night" title="Lady of the Night">Lady of the Night</a></i>, starring <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norma_Shearer" title="Norma Shearer">Norma Shearer</a>. Crawford was made up and used as a double for Shearer and her face is briefly seen. Crawford coveted the roles that Shearer played but knew that Shearer's husband, producer <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irving_Thalberg" title="Irving Thalberg">Irving Thalberg</a>, guaranteed Shearer first choice of roles in any MGM property. "How can I compete with Norma?" Crawford was quoted as saying. "She sleeps with the boss."</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The following year, Crawford was named one of the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WAMPAS_Baby_Stars" title="WAMPAS Baby Stars">WAMPAS Baby Stars</a>, along with <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Astor" title="Mary Astor">Mary Astor</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Brian" title="Mary Brian">Mary Brian</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolores_Costello" title="Dolores Costello">Dolores Costello</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolores_del_R%C3%ADo" title="Dolores del Río">Dolores del Río</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janet_Gaynor" title="Janet Gaynor">Janet Gaynor</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fay_Wray" title="Fay Wray">Fay Wray</a>. For the next two years, Crawford appeared in increasingly important films. In 1926, she made <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris_(1926_film)" title="Paris (1926 film)">Paris</a></i>, where she was able to show her sex appeal. She became the romantic interest for some of MGM's leading male stars, among them <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ram%C3%B3n_Novarro" title="Ramón Novarro">Ramón Novarro</a>, William Haines, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gilbert_(actor)" title="John Gilbert (actor)">John Gilbert</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_McCoy" title="Tim McCoy">Tim McCoy</a>. Crawford appeared in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Unknown_(1927_film)" title="The Unknown (1927 film)">The Unknown</a></i> (1927), starring <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lon_Chaney,_Sr." title="Lon Chaney, Sr.">Lon Chaney, Sr.</a> who played a carnival knife thrower with no arms. Crawford played his skimpily clad young carnival assistant whom he hopes to marry. She stated that she learned more about acting from watching Chaney work than from anything else in her career. "It was then", she said, "I became aware for the first time of the difference between standing in front of a camera, and acting."</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 1928, Crawford starred opposite Ramón Novarro in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Across_to_Singapore" title="Across to Singapore">Across to Singapore</a></i>, but it was her role as Diana Medford in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Our_Dancing_Daughters" title="Our Dancing Daughters">Our Dancing Daughters</a></i> (1928) that catapulted her to stardom. The role established her as a symbol of modern 1920s-style femininity that rivaled the image of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clara_Bow" title="Clara Bow">Clara Bow</a>, the original IT girl, and who was at that time Hollywood's foremost <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flapper" title="Flapper">flapper</a>. A stream of hits followed <i>Our Dancing Daughters</i>, including two more flapper-themed movies, in which Crawford embodied for her legion of fans (many of whom were women) an idealized vision of the free-spirited, all-American girl. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/F._Scott_Fitzgerald" title="F. Scott Fitzgerald">F. Scott Fitzgerald</a> wrote of her:</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On June 3, 1929, Crawford married <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Fairbanks,_Jr." title="Douglas Fairbanks, Jr.">Douglas Fairbanks, Jr.</a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Malachy%27s_Roman_Catholic_Church" title="Saint Malachy's Roman Catholic Church">Saint Malachy's Roman Catholic Church</a> in New York City. Fairbanks was the son of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Fairbanks" title="Douglas Fairbanks">Douglas Fairbanks</a> and the stepson of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Pickford" title="Mary Pickford">Mary Pickford</a>, who were considered Hollywood royalty. Fairbanks Sr. and Pickford were opposed to the marriage and did not invite the couple to their home, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pickfair" title="Pickfair">Pickfair</a>, for eight months after the marriage. The relationship between Crawford and Fairbanks, Sr. eventually warmed; she called him "Uncle Doug" and he called her "Billie". Following that first invitation, Crawford and Fairbanks, Jr. became more frequent guests, which was hard on Crawford. While the Fairbanks men played golf together, Crawford was left with Pickford or left alone.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To rid herself of her <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southwestern_United_States" title="Southwestern United States">Southwestern</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accent_(linguistics)" title="Accent (linguistics)">accent</a>, Crawford tirelessly practiced diction and elocution. She said:</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Her first <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sound_film" title="Sound film">talkie</a> was <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Untamed_(1929_film)" title="Untamed (1929 film)">Untamed</a></i> (1929), opposite <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Montgomery_(actor)" title="Robert Montgomery (actor)">Robert Montgomery</a>, which was a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Box_office" title="Box office">box office</a> success. Crawford made an effective transition to sound movies. One critic wrote, "Miss Crawford sings appealingly and dances thrillingly as usual; her voice is alluring and her dramatic efforts in the difficult role she portrays are at all times convincing."</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the early sound film, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Our_Blushing_Brides" title="Our Blushing Brides">Our Blushing Brides</a></i> (1930), another financial success, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer" title="Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer">MGM</a> began to develop a more sophisticated image of Crawford, rather than continuing to promote her <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flapper" title="Flapper">flapper</a> girl persona of the silent era. In 1931, she starred opposite <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clark_Gable" title="Clark Gable">Clark Gable</a> in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Possessed_(1931_film)" title="Possessed (1931 film)">Possessed</a></i>. They began an affair during the production, resulting in an ultimatum from studio chief <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_B._Mayer" title="Louis B. Mayer">Louis B. Mayer</a> to Gable that the affair end. Gable complied, although for many years their affair resumed sporadically and secretly. Upon release, <i>Possessed</i> was an enormous hit.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The studio then cast her in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Hotel_(film)" title="Grand Hotel (film)">Grand Hotel</a></i>, which starred the most famous actors of the 1930s and was MGM's most prestigious movie of 1932. Crawford later achieved continued success with <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letty_Lynton" title="Letty Lynton">Letty Lynton</a></i> (1932). Soon after its release, a plagiarism suit forced MGM to withdraw it. It has never been shown on television or made available on home video, and is therefore considered the "lost" Crawford film. The film is mostly remembered because of the "Letty Lynton dress", designed by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_(costume_designer)" title="Adrian (costume designer)">Adrian</a>: a white cotton organdy gown with large ruffled sleeves, puffed at the shoulder. It was with this gown that Crawford's broad shoulders began to be accentuated by costume. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macy%27s" title="Macy's">Macy's</a> copied the dress in 1932, and it sold over 500,000 replicas nationwide.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In May 1933, Crawford divorced Fairbanks. Crawford cited "grievous mental cruelty"; "a jealous and suspicious attitude" toward her friends and "loud arguments about the most trivial subjects" lasting "far into the night".</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following <i>Possessed</i>, Crawford starred opposite Gable in the hit <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dancing_Lady" title="Dancing Lady">Dancing Lady</a></i> (1933), in which she received top billing. Crawford's next movies, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sadie_McKee" title="Sadie McKee">Sadie McKee</a></i>, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chained_(1934_film)" title="Chained (1934 film)">Chained</a></i> and <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forsaking_All_Others" title="Forsaking All Others">Forsaking All Others</a></i> (all 1934), were among the top money makers of the mid-1930s.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 1935, Crawford married her second husband, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franchot_Tone" title="Franchot Tone">Franchot Tone</a>, a stage actor from New York who planned to use his film salary to finance his theatre group. Tone and Crawford appeared together in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Today_We_Live" title="Today We Live">Today We Live</a></i> (1933) and were immediately drawn to each other, although Crawford was hesitant about entering into another romance so soon after her split from Fairbanks. The couple built a small theatre at Crawford's Brentwood home and put on productions of classic plays for select groups of friends. Before and during their marriage, Crawford worked to promote Tone's Hollywood career but Tone was ultimately not interested in being a movie star and Crawford eventually wearied of the effort. Tone began drinking and physically abusing Crawford and she filed for divorce, which was granted in 1939. Crawford and Tone eventually reconciled their friendship and Tone even proposed in 1964 that they remarry. When Tone died in 1968, Crawford arranged for him to be cremated and his ashes scattered at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muskoka_Lakes" title="Muskoka Lakes">Muskoka Lakes</a>, Canada.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The <i>Motion Picture Herald</i> placed Crawford on its list of the top-ten moneymaking stars from 1932, the first year of the poll, through 1936 and <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Life_(magazine)" title="Life (magazine)">Life</a></i> magazine proclaimed her "First Queen of the Movies" in 1937. Later in 1937 she dropped out of the top ten for the first time, and in 1938 the <i>Independent Film Journal</i> named her and several other stars as "box office poison" based on their supposed lack of popular appeal. However, Crawford made a small comeback with her role as home-wrecker Crystal Allen in director <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Cukor" title="George Cukor">George Cukor's</a> comedy <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Women_(1939_film)" title="The Women (1939 film)">The Women</a></i> in 1939. She also broke from formula by taking the unglamorous role of Julie in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strange_Cargo_(1940_film)" title="Strange Cargo (1940 film)">Strange Cargo</a></i> (1940), her eighth and final film with Clark Gable. Crawford then starred as a facially disfigured blackmailer in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Woman%27s_Face" title="A Woman's Face">A Woman's Face</a></i> (1941). While the film was only a moderate box office success, her performance was hailed by many critics.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford adopted her first child, a daughter, in 1940. Because she was single, California law prevented her from adopting within the state so she arranged the adoption through an agency in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_Vegas_metropolitan_area" title="Las Vegas metropolitan area">Las Vegas</a>. The child was temporarily called Joan until Crawford changed her name to <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christina_Crawford" title="Christina Crawford">Christina</a>. She married actor <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phillip_Terry" title="Phillip Terry">Phillip Terry</a> on July 21, 1942 after a six-month courtship. Together the couple adopted a son whom they named Christopher, but his birth mother reclaimed the child. They adopted another boy, whom they named Phillip Terry, Jr. After the marriage ended in 1946, Crawford changed the child's name to Christopher Crawford.</p>
      </wiki:abstract>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For $500,000 for three movies, Crawford signed with <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warner_Bros." title="Warner Bros.">Warner Bros.</a> and was placed on the payroll on July 1, 1943. She made a cameo with many other stars in the G.I. morale-booster <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood_Canteen_(1944_film)" title="Hollywood Canteen (1944 film)">Hollywood Canteen</a></i> (1944). Crawford said one of the main reasons she signed with Warner Bros. was because she wanted to play the character "Mattie" in a proposed 1944 film version of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edith_Wharton" title="Edith Wharton">Edith Wharton</a>'s novel <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethan_Frome" title="Ethan Frome">Ethan Frome</a></i> (1911). However, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bette_Davis" title="Bette Davis">Bette Davis</a> wanted to play Mattie and reportedly told <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Warner" title="Jack Warner">Jack Warner</a>, "Joan's far too old, and besides, she can't act."</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford wanted to play the title role in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mildred_Pierce_(film)" title="Mildred Pierce (film)">Mildred Pierce</a></i> (1945), but Davis was the studio's first choice. However, Davis did not want to play the mother of a seventeen year old daughter and she turned the role down. Director <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Curtiz" title="Michael Curtiz">Michael Curtiz</a> did not want Crawford and told Jack Warner, "She comes over here with her high-hat airs and her goddamn shoulder pads...why should I waste my time directing a has-been?" Curtiz demanded Crawford prove her suitability by taking a screen test. After the test, Curtiz agreed to Crawford's casting. Crawford starred opposite <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Carson" title="Jack Carson">Jack Carson</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zachary_Scott" title="Zachary Scott">Zachary Scott</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eve_Arden" title="Eve Arden">Eve Arden</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ann_Blyth" title="Ann Blyth">Ann Blyth</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butterfly_McQueen" title="Butterfly McQueen">Butterfly McQueen</a>. <i>Mildred Pierce</i> was a commercial success. It epitomized the lush visual style and the hard-boiled <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_noir" title="Film noir">film noir</a> sensibility that defined Warner Bros. movies of the later 1940s. Crawford earned the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award" title="Academy Award">Academy Award</a> for <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Actress" title="Academy Award for Best Actress">Best Actress in a Leading Role</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 1945 to 1952, Crawford reigned as a top star and respected actress, appearing in such roles as Helen Wright in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humoresque_(film)" title="Humoresque (film)">Humoresque</a></i> (1946), Louise Howell Graham in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Possessed_(1947_film)" title="Possessed (1947 film)">Possessed</a></i> (1947, for which she was nominated for a second Oscar for Best Actress) and the title role in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daisy_Kenyon" title="Daisy Kenyon">Daisy Kenyon</a></i> (also 1947). She did a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/It%27s_a_Great_Feeling#Reception_and_Joan_Crawford.27s_cameo" title="It's a Great Feeling">critically well received sendup of her screen image</a> in a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cameo_appearance" title="Cameo appearance">cameo</a> in the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doris_Day" title="Doris Day">Doris Day</a>-<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Carson" title="Jack Carson">Jack Carson</a> musical, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/It%27s_a_Great_Feeling" title="It's a Great Feeling">It's a Great Feeling</a></i> (1949). Crawford's other movie roles of the era include Lane Bellamy in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flamingo_Road_(1949_film)" title="Flamingo Road (1949 film)">Flamingo Road</a></i> (1949), a dual role in the film noir <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Damned_Don%27t_Cry" title="The Damned Don't Cry">The Damned Don't Cry</a></i> (1950) and her performance in the title role of <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harriet_Craig" title="Harriet Craig">Harriet Craig</a></i> (1950) at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia_Pictures" title="Columbia Pictures">Columbia Pictures</a>. After filming <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/This_Woman_Is_Dangerous" title="This Woman Is Dangerous">This Woman Is Dangerous</a></i> (1952), Crawford asked to be released from her Warner Bros. contract. As she had done before, Crawford triumphed as Myra Hudson in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudden_Fear" title="Sudden Fear">Sudden Fear</a></i> (1952) at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RKO" title="RKO">RKO</a>, which was the movie that introduced her co-star, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Palance" title="Jack Palance">Jack Palance</a>, to the screen and earned Crawford a third and final Oscar nomination for Best Actress.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford adopted two more children in 1947, twins whom she named Cindy and Cathy.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford worked in the radio series <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Screen_Guild_Theater" title="The Screen Guild Theater">The Screen Guild Theater</a></i> on January 8, 1939; <i>Good News</i>; <i>Baby</i>, broadcast March 2, 1940 on <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arch_Oboler" title="Arch Oboler">Arch Oboler</a>'s <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lights_Out_(radio_show)" title="Lights Out (radio show)">Lights Out</a></i>; <i>The Word</i> on <i>Everyman's Theater</i> (1941); <i>Chained</i> on the <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lux_Radio_Theater" title="Lux Radio Theater">Lux Radio Theater</a></i> Suspense, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Corwin" title="Norman Corwin">Norman Corwin</a>'s <i>Document A/777</i> (1948). She appeared in episodes of anthology TV shows in the 1950s and, in 1959, made a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pilot_episode" title="Pilot episode">pilot</a> for her series, <i>The Joan Crawford Show</i>, but the show was never picked up by a network.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford married her final husband, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfred_Steele" title="Alfred Steele">Alfred Steele</a>, at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flamingo_Las_Vegas" title="Flamingo Las Vegas">Flamingo Hotel</a> in Las Vegas on May 10, 1955. Crawford and Steele met at a party in 1950 when Steele was an executive with <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Coca-Cola_Company" title="The Coca-Cola Company">Coca-Cola</a>. They renewed their acquaintance at a New Year's Eve party in 1954. Steele by that time had become the president of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PepsiCo" title="PepsiCo">Pepsi Cola</a>. Crawford traveled extensively on behalf of Pepsi following the marriage. She estimated that she traveled over 100,000 miles for the company. Steele died of a heart attack in April 1959. Crawford was initially advised that her services were no longer required. After she told the story to <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louella_Parsons" title="Louella Parsons">Louella Parsons</a>, Pepsi reversed its position and Crawford was elected to fill the vacant seat on the board of directors. Crawford, left near-penniless following Steele's death, accepted a supporting role in the film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Best_of_Everything_(1959_film)" title="The Best of Everything (1959 film)">The Best of Everything</a></i> (1959). It was her first non-starring role in her later career.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford received the sixth annual "Pally Award", which was in the shape of a bronze Pepsi bottle. It was awarded to the employee making the most significant contribution to company sales. In 1973, Crawford was forcibly retired from the company at the behest of company executive <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_M._Kendall" title="Donald M. Kendall">Don Kendall</a>, whom Crawford had referred to for years as "Fang."</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After her triumph in RKO's <i>Sudden Fear</i>, Crawford appeared in films ranging from the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camp_(style)" title="Camp (style)">camp</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_(genre)" title="Western (genre)">western</a> film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johnny_Guitar" title="Johnny Guitar">Johnny Guitar</a></i> (1954) to the drama <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autumn_Leaves_(film)" title="Autumn Leaves (film)">Autumn Leaves</a></i> (1956), opposite a young <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cliff_Robertson" title="Cliff Robertson">Cliff Robertson</a>. By the early 1960s, however, Crawford's status in motion pictures had diminished.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford starred as Blanche Hudson, a physically disabled woman and former <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A-list" title="A-list">A-list</a> movie star in conflict with her psychotic sister in the highly successful thriller <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What_Ever_Happened_to_Baby_Jane%3F_(film)" title="What Ever Happened to Baby Jane? (film)">What Ever Happened To Baby Jane?</a></i> (1962). Despite the actresses' earlier tensions, Crawford suggested <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bette_Davis" title="Bette Davis">Bette Davis</a> for the role of Jane. The two stars maintained publicly that there was no feud between them. However, Crawford accused Davis of kicking her during the filming of a scene in which Jane attacks Blanche, and reportedly retaliated by wearing weights under her clothes in a scene in which Davis had to carry her. The director, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Aldrich" title="Robert Aldrich">Robert Aldrich</a>, explained that Davis and Crawford were each aware of how important the film was to their respective careers and commented, "It's proper to say that they really detested each other, but they behaved absolutely perfectly." After filming was completed, their public comments against each other allowed the tension to develop into a lifelong feud. The film became a huge success, recouping its costs in 11 days of nationwide release and temporarily reviving Crawford's career. Davis was nominated for an Academy Award for her performance as Jane Hudson. Crawford secretly contacted all the other Oscar nominees to tell them if they were unable to attend the ceremony, she would be happy to accept the Oscar on their behalf. Both Davis and Crawford were backstage when the absent <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Bancroft" title="Anne Bancroft">Anne Bancroft</a> was announced as the winner and Crawford accepted the award on her behalf. Davis claimed for the rest of her life that Crawford campaigned against her, a charge Crawford denied. That same year, Crawford starred as Lucy Harbin in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Castle" title="William Castle">William Castle</a>'s horror mystery <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strait-Jacket" title="Strait-Jacket">Strait-Jacket</a></i> (1964).</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Director <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Aldrich" title="Robert Aldrich">Robert Aldrich</a> cast Crawford and Davis in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hush..._Hush,_Sweet_Charlotte" title="Hush... Hush, Sweet Charlotte">Hush... Hush, Sweet Charlotte</a></i> (1964). After a campaign of intimidation by Davis while the film was on location in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louisiana" title="Louisiana">Louisiana</a>, Crawford returned to Hollywood and entered a hospital. After a prolonged absence in which Crawford was accused of feigning illness, Aldrich was forced to replace her with <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivia_de_Havilland" title="Olivia de Havilland">Olivia de Havilland</a>. Crawford was devastated. "I heard the news of my replacement over the radio, lying in my hospital bed", Crawford said. "I wept for 39 hours." Crawford nursed grudges against Davis and Aldrich for the rest of her life, saying of Aldrich, "He is a man who loves evil, horrendous, vile things." (to which Aldrich replied, "If the shoe fits, wear it, and I am very fond of Miss Crawford.")</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Upon her release from the hospital Crawford played the role of Amy Nelson in <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I_Saw_What_You_Did" title="I Saw What You Did">I Saw What You Did</a></i> (1965), another William Castle vehicle. She starred as Monica Rivers in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herman_Cohen" title="Herman Cohen">Herman Cohen</a>'s horror thriller film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berserk!" title="Berserk!">Berserk!</a></i> (1967). After the film's release, Crawford guest-starred as herself on <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Lucy_Show" title="The Lucy Show">The Lucy Show</a></i>. The episode, "Lucy and the Lost Star", first aired on February 26, 1968. Crawford struggled during rehearsals and drank heavily on-set, leading series star <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucille_Ball" title="Lucille Ball">Lucille Ball</a> to suggest replacing her with <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_Swanson" title="Gloria Swanson">Gloria Swanson</a>. Crawford was letter-perfect the day of the show and received two standing ovations from the studio audience.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In October 1968, Crawford's 29-year-old daughter, Christina (who was then acting in New York on the soap opera <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Secret_Storm" title="The Secret Storm">The Secret Storm</a></i>), needed immediate medical attention for a ruptured ovarian tumor. Until Christina was well enough to return, Crawford offered to play her role, to which producer <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_Monty" title="Gloria Monty">Gloria Monty</a> readily agreed. Although Crawford did well in rehearsal, she lost her composure while taping and the director and producer were left to struggle to piece together the necessary footage.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford's appearance in the 1969 TV film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Night_Gallery" title="Night Gallery">Night Gallery</a></i> (which served as pilot to the series that followed), marked one of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Spielberg" title="Steven Spielberg">Steven Spielberg</a>'s earliest directing jobs. She starred on the big screen one final time, playing Dr. Brockton in Herman Cohen's science fiction horror film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trog" title="Trog">Trog</a></i> (1970), rounding out a career spanning 45 years and over 80 motion pictures. Crawford made four more TV appearances, as Stephanie White in an episode of <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Virginian_(TV_series)" title="The Virginian (TV series)">The Virginian</a></i> (1970), entitled "The Nightmare"; as a board member in an episode of <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Name_of_the_Game_(TV_series)" title="The Name of the Game (TV series)">The Name of the Game</a></i> (1971), entitled "Los Angeles"; as Allison Hayes in the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Television_movie" title="Television movie">made-for-TV movie</a> <i>Beyond the Water's Edge</i> (1972); and as Joan Fairchild (her final performance) on an episode of the television series, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sixth_Sense_(TV_series)" title="The Sixth Sense (TV series)">The Sixth Sense</a></i>, entitled, "Dear Joan: We're Going To Scare You To Death" (1972). Joan also starred as Della in TV series titled the same. In this nighttime soap opera she played a reclusive millionaire who lives alone with her daughter and is only ever seen at night. Its sort of a replaying of her role in "straightjacket". There are 2 episodes (2 halves of a pilot episode) of this show available online at youtube. It is unknown whether the show was ever picked up.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Final_years_and_death">Final years and death</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 1970, Crawford was presented with the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Globe_Cecil_B._DeMille_Award" title="Golden Globe Cecil B. DeMille Award">Cecil B. DeMille Award</a> by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Wayne" title="John Wayne">John Wayne</a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Globe_Award" title="Golden Globe Award">Golden Globes</a>, which was telecast from the Coconut Grove at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambassador_Hotel_(Los_Angeles)" title="Ambassador Hotel (Los Angeles)">The Ambassador Hotel</a> in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Angeles,_California" title="Los Angeles, California">Los Angeles</a>. She also spoke at her alma mater, Stephens College, from which she never graduated.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford published her autobiography, <i>A Portrait of Joan</i> – written with Jane Kesner Ardmore – in 1962 through <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doubleday_(publisher)" title="Doubleday (publisher)">Doubleday</a>. Crawford's next book, <i>My Way of Life</i>, was published in 1971 by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_and_Schuster" title="Simon and Schuster">Simon and Schuster</a>. Those expecting a racy tell-all were disappointed, although Crawford's meticulous ways were revealed in her advice on grooming, wardrobe, exercise, and even food storage.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In September 1973, Crawford moved from apartment 22-G to the smaller apartment 22-H in the Imperial House. Her last public appearance was September 23, 1974, at a party honoring her old friend <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosalind_Russell" title="Rosalind Russell">Rosalind Russell</a> at New York's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow_Room" title="Rainbow Room">Rainbow Room</a>. Russell was suffering from <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breast_cancer" title="Breast cancer">breast cancer</a> at the time and died two years later in 1976. When Crawford saw the unflattering photos of both stars that appeared in the papers the next day, she said, "If that's how I look, then they won't see me anymore." Crawford canceled all public appearances, began declining interviews and left her apartment less and less. Her dental-related issues, including surgery which left her in need of round the clock nursing care, also plagued her from 1972 until the middle of 1975. While on antibiotics for this problem in October 1974, Crawford's drinking caused her to black out, slip and strike her face. This incident scared her enough to give up drinking and smoking, although in public she insisted it was due to her return to Christian Science. The whole incident is recorded in a series of letters sent to her insurance company held at the Lincoln Center Library for the Performing Arts, as well as being documented by her friend, Carl Johnnes, in his book.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On May 8, 1977, Crawford gave away her beloved <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shih_Tzu" title="Shih Tzu">Shih Tzu</a> "Princess Lotus Blossom", which she was too weak to care for properly. Crawford died two days later at her New York apartment from a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myocardial_infarction" title="Myocardial infarction">heart attack</a>, while also ill with <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pancreatic_cancer" title="Pancreatic cancer">pancreatic cancer</a>. A funeral was held at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campbell_Funeral_Home" title="Campbell Funeral Home">Campbell Funeral Home</a>, New York, on May 13, 1977. All four of her adopted children attended, as did her niece, Joan Crawford LeSueur (aka Joan Lowe), who was the daughter of her late brother, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hal_LeSueur" title="Hal LeSueur">Hal LeSueur</a> (who had died in 1963). In her will, which was signed October 28, 1976, Crawford bequeathed to her two youngest children, Cindy and Cathy, $77,500 each from her $2,000,000 estate. She explicitly disinherited the two eldest, Christina and Christopher, writing "It is my intention to make no provision herein for my son Christopher or my daughter Christina for reasons which are well known to them."</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A memorial service was held for Crawford at All Souls' Unitarian Church on Lexington Avenue in New York on May 16, 1977, and was attended by, among others, her old Hollywood friend <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myrna_Loy" title="Myrna Loy">Myrna Loy</a>. Another memorial service, organized by George Cukor, was held on June 24 in the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Goldwyn_Theater" title="Samuel Goldwyn Theater">Samuel Goldwyn Theater</a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_of_Motion_Picture_Arts_and_Sciences" title="Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences">Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences</a> in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beverly_Hills,_California" title="Beverly Hills, California">Beverly Hills, California</a>. Crawford was <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cremated" title="Cremated">cremated</a> and her ashes placed in a crypt with her last husband, Alfred Steele, in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferncliff_Cemetery" title="Ferncliff Cemetery">Ferncliff Cemetery</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hartsdale,_New_York" title="Hartsdale, New York">Hartsdale, New York</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crawford's hand and footprints are immortalized in the forecourt of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grauman%27s_Chinese_Theater" title="Grauman's Chinese Theater">Grauman's Chinese Theater</a> on <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood_Boulevard" title="Hollywood Boulevard">Hollywood Boulevard</a> in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood,_Los_Angeles,_California" title="Hollywood, Los Angeles, California">Hollywood</a>. She also has a star on the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood_Walk_of_Fame" title="Hollywood Walk of Fame">Hollywood Walk of Fame</a> at 1750 Vine Street. In 1999, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Playboy" title="Playboy">Playboy</a></i> listed Crawford as one of the "100 Sexiest Women of the 20th century", ranking her #84.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Mommie_Dearest"><i>Mommie Dearest</i></span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In November 1978, a year and a half after Crawford's death, Christina published <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mommie_Dearest" title="Mommie Dearest">Mommie Dearest</a></i>, which contained allegations that Crawford was emotionally and physically <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Child_abuse" title="Child abuse">abusive</a> to Christina and her brother Christopher. Many of Crawford's friends and co-workers, including <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Johnson" title="Van Johnson">Van Johnson</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ann_Blyth" title="Ann Blyth">Ann Blyth</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marlene_Dietrich" title="Marlene Dietrich">Marlene Dietrich</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myrna_Loy" title="Myrna Loy">Myrna Loy</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cesar_Romero" title="Cesar Romero">Cesar Romero</a>, and Crawford's other daughters, Cathy and Cindy, denounced the book, categorically denying any abuse. But others, including <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helen_Hayes" title="Helen Hayes">Helen Hayes</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bette_Davis" title="Bette Davis">Bette Davis</a> supported Christina's version, with Davis saying that Christina could not have made it up (Davis, while still alive, would, ironically, later become the target of her own daughter <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B._D._Hyman" title="B. D. Hyman">B. D. Hyman</a>'s tell-all in 1985, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My_Mother%27s_Keeper" title="My Mother's Keeper">My Mother's Keeper</a></i>). <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mommie_Dearest" title="Mommie Dearest">Mommie Dearest</a></i> became a bestseller and was made into the 1981 film of the same name, starring <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faye_Dunaway" title="Faye Dunaway">Faye Dunaway</a> as Joan Crawford.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Filmography">Filmography</span></h2>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Notes">Notes</span></h2>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="References">References</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li>Bret, David (2006). <i>Joan Crawford: Hollywood Martyr</i>. Robson. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/1861059310">ISBN 1861059310</a>.</li>
	<li>Considine, Shaun (1989). <i>Bette and Joan: The Divine Feud</i>. New York, E. P. Dutton, a division of Penguin Books. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/052524770X">ISBN 052524770X</a>.</li>
	<li>Granlund, Nils T. (1957). <i>Blondes, Brunettes, and Bullets</i>. New York, David McKay Company.</li>
	<li>Hoefling, Larry J. (2008). <i>Nils Thor Granlund: The Swedish Showman Who Invented American Entertainment</i>. Inlandia Press. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/098223130X">ISBN 098223130X</a>.</li>
	<li>LaSalle, Mick (2000). <i>Complicated Women: Sex and Power in Pre-Code Hollywood</i>. New York, Thomas Dunne Books, an imprint of St. Martin's Press. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0312252072">ISBN 0312252072</a>.</li>
	<li>Leese, Elizabeth (1991). <i>Costume Design in the Movies</i>. Dover Books. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/048626548X">ISBN 048626548X</a>.</li>
	<li>Newquist, Roy, with introduction by John Springer (1980). <i>Conversations with Joan Crawford</i>. New Jersey, Citadel Press, a division of Lyle Stuart, Inc. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0806507209">ISBN 0806507209</a>.</li>
	<li>Skal, David J. (1993). <i>The Monster Show: A Cultural History of Horror</i>. Penguin Books. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0140240020">ISBN 0140240020</a>.</li>
	<li>Thomas, Bob (1978). <i>Joan Crawford: A Biography</i>. New York, Bantam Books. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0553129422">ISBN 0553129422</a>.</li>
      </ul>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Further_reading">Further reading</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><i>Just Joan: A Joan Crawford Appreciation</i> by Donna Marie Nowak. Albany, BearManor Media 2010. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/9781593935429">ISBN 978-1-59393-542-9</a>.</li>
      </ul>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="External_links">External links</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><a href="http://joancrawfordbest.com" rel="nofollow">The Best of Everything: A Joan Crawford Encyclopedia</a></li>
      </ul>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001076/" rel="nofollow">Joan Crawford</a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Movie_Database" title="Internet Movie Database">Internet Movie Database</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ibdb.com/person.asp?ID=88115" rel="nofollow">Joan Crawford</a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Broadway_Database" title="Internet Broadway Database">Internet Broadway Database</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=242" rel="nofollow">Joan Crawford</a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Find_a_Grave" title="Find a Grave">Find a Grave</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://tcmdb.com/participant/participant.jsp?participantId=40864" rel="nofollow">Joan Crawford</a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turner_Classic_Movies" title="Turner Classic Movies">TCM Movie Database</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2008/03/crawford200803" rel="nofollow">Excerpt of 2008 biography from <i>Vanity Fair</i></a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.dmoz.org/Arts/People/C/Crawford,_Joan/" rel="nofollow">Joan Crawford</a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Directory_Project" title="Open Directory Project">Open Directory Project</a></li>
      </ul>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><span id="interwiki-de-fa"></span> <span id="interwiki-fi-fa"></span> <span id="interwiki-nl-fa"></span></p>
    </wiki:description>
  </wiki:person>
  <wiki:film-title link="/wiki/Sudden_Fear">Sudden Fear</wiki:film-title>
  <wiki:film link="/wiki/Sudden_Fear" title="Sudden Fear">
    <wiki:oscar-ref year="1952" span="1" winner="false" award="lead-actress" person-link="/wiki/Joan_Crawford" person-name="Joan Crawford"/>
    <wiki:oscar-ref year="1952" span="1" winner="false" award="supporting-actor" person-link="/wiki/Jack_Palance" person-name="Jack Palance"/>
    <wiki:producer link="/w/index.php?title=Joseph_Kaufman&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1">Joseph Kaufman</wiki:producer>
    <wiki:producer link="/wiki/Joan_Crawford">Joan Crawford</wiki:producer>
    <wiki:director link="/wiki/David_Miller_(director)">David Miller</wiki:director>
    <wiki:writer link="/wiki/Lenore_J._Coffee">Lenore J. Coffee</wiki:writer>
    <wiki:writer link="/w/index.php?title=Edna_Sherry&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1">Edna Sherry</wiki:writer>
    <wiki:distributor link="/wiki/RKO_Radio_Pictures">RKO Radio Pictures</wiki:distributor>
    <wiki:starring link="/wiki/Jack_Palance">Jack Palance</wiki:starring>
    <wiki:starring link="/wiki/Gloria_Grahame">Gloria Grahame</wiki:starring>
    <wiki:description>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i><b>Sudden Fear</b></i> is a 1952 <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RKO_Radio_Pictures" title="RKO Radio Pictures">RKO Radio Pictures</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feature_film" title="Feature film">feature film</a> starring <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Crawford" title="Joan Crawford">Joan Crawford</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Palance" title="Jack Palance">Jack Palance</a> in a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_noir" title="Film noir">noir-ish</a> tale about a successful woman who marries a murderous man. The screenplay by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lenore_J._Coffee" title="Lenore J. Coffee">Lenore J. Coffee</a> and Robert Smith was based upon the novel by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Edna_Sherry&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" title="Edna Sherry (page does not exist)">Edna Sherry</a>. <i>Sudden Fear</i> was directed by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Miller_(director)" title="David Miller (director)">David Miller</a> and produced by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Joseph_Kaufman&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" title="Joseph Kaufman (page does not exist)">Joseph Kaufman</a>. The film was nominated for several <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award" title="Academy Award">Academy Awards</a> and has been released to DVD.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Plot_and_cast">Plot and cast</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Myra Hudson (Crawford) is a successful Broadway playwright who rejects Lester Blaine (Palance) as the lead in her new play. Later, she meets Lester on a train bound for San Francisco, is swept off her feet, and, after a brief courtship, marries him. When Lester learns Myra is writing her will and plans to leave the bulk of her fortune to a foundation, he plots her murder in cahoots with Irene Neves (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_Grahame" title="Gloria Grahame">Gloria Grahame</a>), an old girlfriend hiding in the wings. Myra discovers their plans and concocts a diabolical scheme to kill Lester and place the blame on Irene, but cannot bring herself to go through with it. Lester learns of Myra's intention and accidentally kills Irene and himself in an attempt on Myra's life. Myra hears the two pronounced dead and breathes a sigh of relief. Others in the cast include <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruce_Bennett" title="Bruce Bennett">Bruce Bennett</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia_Huston" title="Virginia Huston">Virginia Huston</a>, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Connors" title="Mike Connors">Mike Connors</a> (performing as Touch Connors).</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Production_notes">Production notes</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marlon_Brando" title="Marlon Brando">Marlon Brando</a> was originally offered the role of Lester Blaine. The film was shot in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco,_California" title="San Francisco, California">San Francisco, California</a>. Costumes were designed by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheila_O%27Brien" title="Sheila O'Brien">Sheila O'Brien</a> and earned an Academy Award nomination.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Reception">Reception</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A. H. Weiler in the <i>New York Times</i> commented, "Joan Crawford should be credited with a truly professional performance", and Otis L. Guernsey, Jr. in the <i>New York Herald Tribune</i> wrote, "The scenario...is designed to allow Miss Crawford a wide range of quivering reactions to vicious events, as she passes through the stage of starry-eyed love, terrible disillusionment, fear, hatred, and finally hysteria. With her wide eyes and forceful bearing, she is the woman for the job."<small></small> In 1984, writer Spencer Selby noted, "Undoubtedly one of the most stylish and refined woman-in-distress noirs."</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Awards">Awards</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i>Sudden Fear</i> was nominated for <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Awards" title="Academy Awards">Academy Awards</a> for:- <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Actress" title="Academy Award for Best Actress">Best Actress in a Leading Role</a>: Joan Crawford, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Supporting_Actor" title="Academy Award for Best Supporting Actor">Best Actor in a Supporting Role</a>: Jack Palance, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Cinematography" title="Academy Award for Best Cinematography">Best Cinematography, Black-and-White</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Costume_Design" title="Academy Award for Costume Design">Best Costume Design, Black-and-White</a>.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="References">References</span></h2>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="External_links">External links</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><a href="http://tcmdb.com/title/title.jsp?stid=91824" rel="nofollow"><i>Sudden Fear</i></a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turner_Classic_Movies" title="Turner Classic Movies">TCM Movie Database</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0045205/" rel="nofollow"><i>Sudden Fear</i></a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Movie_Database" title="Internet Movie Database">Internet Movie Database</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.allmovie.com/work/112177" rel="nofollow"><i>Sudden Fear</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allmovie" title="Allmovie">Allmovie</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/sudden_fear" rel="nofollow"><i>Sudden Fear</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotten_Tomatoes" title="Rotten Tomatoes">Rotten Tomatoes</a></li>
      </ul>
    </wiki:description>
  </wiki:film>
</wiki:nominee>