<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<wiki:nominee year="2006" span="1" winner="true" award="best-picture" xmlns:wiki="http://marklogic.com/wikipedia">
  <!--
                            Copyright (c) 2010 MarkLogic Corporation.
                            Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
                            under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
                            or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
                            with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
                            A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
                            Free Documentation License"
                            
                            Content derived from http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Departed
                            Modified in May 2009 by Mark Logic Corporation under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License.
                        -->
  <wiki:film-title link="/wiki/The_Departed">The Departed</wiki:film-title>
  <wiki:film link="/wiki/The_Departed" title="The Departed">
    <wiki:oscar-ref year="2006" span="1" winner="true" award="best-director" person-link="/wiki/Martin_Scorsese" person-name="Martin Scorsese"/>
    <wiki:oscar-ref year="2006" span="1" winner="false" award="supporting-actor" person-link="/wiki/Mark_Wahlberg" person-name="Mark Wahlberg"/>
    <wiki:oscar year="2006" span="1" winner="true" award="best-picture"/>
    <wiki:director link="/wiki/Martin_Scorsese">Martin Scorsese</wiki:director>
    <wiki:distributor link="/wiki/Warner_Bros.">Warner Bros.</wiki:distributor>
    <wiki:description>
      <wiki:abstract>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i><b>The Departed</b></i> is a 2006 American <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crime_film" title="Crime film">crime film</a>, a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Remake" title="Remake">remake</a> of the 2002 <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong_Kong_cinema" title="Hong Kong cinema">Hong Kong</a> film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infernal_Affairs" title="Infernal Affairs">Infernal Affairs</a></i>. The film was directed by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Scorsese" title="Martin Scorsese">Martin Scorsese</a>, written by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Monahan" title="William Monahan">William Monahan</a>, and stars <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_DiCaprio" title="Leonardo DiCaprio">Leonardo DiCaprio</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Damon" title="Matt Damon">Matt Damon</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Nicholson" title="Jack Nicholson">Jack Nicholson</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Wahlberg" title="Mark Wahlberg">Mark Wahlberg</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Sheen" title="Martin Sheen">Martin Sheen</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Winstone" title="Ray Winstone">Ray Winstone</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vera_Farmiga" title="Vera Farmiga">Vera Farmiga</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alec_Baldwin" title="Alec Baldwin">Alec Baldwin</a>. It won four <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Awards" title="Academy Awards">Academy Awards</a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/79th_Academy_Awards" title="79th Academy Awards">79th Academy Awards</a>, including <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Picture" title="Academy Award for Best Picture">Best Picture</a>, and an <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Director" title="Academy Award for Best Director">Academy Award for Best Director</a> win for Scorsese.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This film takes place in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston" title="Boston">Boston</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts" title="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</a>, where <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_Mob" title="Irish Mob">Irish Mob</a> boss Francis "Frank" Costello (Nicholson) plants Colin Sullivan (Damon) as an <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mole_(espionage)" title="Mole (espionage)">informant</a> within the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts_State_Police" title="Massachusetts State Police">Massachusetts State Police</a>. Simultaneously, the police assign undercover cop Billy Costigan (DiCaprio) to infiltrate Costello's crew. When both sides realize the situation, each man attempts to discover the other's true identity before their cover is blown.</p>
	<h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Plot">Plot</span></h2>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At a young age, Colin Sullivan (Damon) is introduced to <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organized_crime" title="Organized crime">organized crime</a> through Irish mobster Frank Costello (Nicholson) in the Irish neighborhood of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Boston" title="South Boston">Southie</a> in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston" title="Boston">Boston</a>. Costello trains him to become his mole inside the Massachusetts State Police. Sullivan is accepted into the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_Investigations_Unit" title="Special Investigations Unit">Special Investigations Unit</a> (SIU), which focuses on organized crime. Before he graduates from the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Police_academy" title="Police academy">police academy</a>, Billy Costigan (DiCaprio) is asked by Captain Queenan (Sheen) and Staff Sergeant Dignam (Wahlberg) to become an undercover agent, as his childhood and family ties to organized crime make him a perfect infiltrator. He drops out of the academy and does time in prison on a fake assault charge to increase his credibility.</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As both infiltrate their respective organizations, Sullivan begins a romance with psychiatrist Madolyn Madden (Farmiga). Costigan sees her for his probation and also develops a relationship with her. Shortly after, Costigan makes love to her before she moves in with Sullivan. After Costello barely escapes a sting operation, both moles become aware of the other's existence (though not his identity). Sullivan is told to find the "rat" and asks Costello for his crew's information to determine who is the informer within Costello's crew. Costigan follows Costello into a movie theater where Costello gives Sullivan an envelope with the details. Costigan then chases Sullivan through Boston's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinatown,_Boston" title="Chinatown, Boston">Chinatown</a>, during which Sullivan pulls out a pocket knife and stabs an innocent bystander in the stomach. When it is over, both men still do not know each other's identity. Sullivan then has Queenan tailed as he meets Costigan in an abandoned building. Sullivan sends Costello's men in and Queenan distracts them to let Costigan escape. He is thrown from the roof and dies at the feet of Costigan, who is covered in some of Queenan's blood. When the mobsters escape, Costigan pretends he has come to rejoin them. The trailing state troopers open fire on Costello's crew, which causes casualties on both sides. Later, at one of Costello's safe houses, Delahunt (one of Costello's enforcers) tells Costigan "I gave you the wrong address--but you went to the right one" but then asks him if he knows why he didn't say anything about before dying. When Costello's henchman, Fitzgibbons, known as "Fitzy," (O'Hara) does an unsuccessful job of hiding Delahunt's corpse, it's revealed that Delahunt was also an undercover cop with the Boston PD. Costello says, "They're saying he's a cop so I won't look for the cop."</p>
	<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Now under scrutiny, Sullivan is attacked by a suspicious Dignam because of Queenan's death. Captain George Ellerby (Baldwin) places Dignam on leave. Using Queenan's bloody phone, Sullivan reaches Costigan, who refuses to abort his mission. Sullivan learns of Costello's role as an informant for the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Bureau_of_Investigation" title="Federal Bureau of Investigation">FBI</a> from Queenan's diary, causing him to worry about his dual identity being revealed. With Costigan's help, Costello is tracked to a cocaine drop-off, where he and his crew become trapped in a gunfight with police, resulting in most of the mobsters being killed. As Costello attempts an escape he is confronted by Sullivan. Costello admits he is an occasional FBI mole and tries to shoot, but Sullivan fires first fatally hitting him, then when Costello tries to shoot him again Sullivan shoots him multiple times, killing him. With Costello dead, Sullivan is applauded the next day by everyone on the force. In good faith, Costigan comes to him for restoration of his true identity, but notices an envelope containing details of Costello's men on Sullivan's desk and flees. Knowing he has been found out, Sullivan erases all records of Costigan from the police computer system.</p>
      </wiki:abstract>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At Costigan's funeral, Sullivan and Madolyn stand at the grave. She is clearly distraught. Sullivan attempts to discuss the future of her child, but she ignores him. Later, Sullivan enters his apartment with groceries, and to his surprise finds Dignam waiting for him, wearing hospital footies and surgical gloves to leave no trace of his presence and aiming a silenced pistol straight at him. Aware of Sullivan's treachery, Dignam shoots him in the temple. As Sullivan collapses dead, Dignam calmly exits Sullivan's apartment. A rat crawls along the apartment balcony, with the view of the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts_State_House" title="Massachusetts State House">Massachusetts State House</a> in the background.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Cast">Cast</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_DiCaprio" title="Leonardo DiCaprio">Leonardo DiCaprio</a> as William "Billy" Costigan, a state trooper working undercover in Costello's mob.</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Damon" title="Matt Damon">Matt Damon</a> as Staff Sergeant Colin Sullivan, Costello's informant in the Special Investigations Unit</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Nicholson" title="Jack Nicholson">Jack Nicholson</a> as Frank Costello, sadistic boss of the Boston Irish mob</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Wahlberg" title="Mark Wahlberg">Mark Wahlberg</a> as Staff Sergeant Sean Dignam, second in command of the undercover unit</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Sheen" title="Martin Sheen">Martin Sheen</a> as Captain Oliver Charles Queenan, commander of the undercover unit</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vera_Farmiga" title="Vera Farmiga">Vera Farmiga</a> as Dr. Madolyn Madden, occupational psychiatrist and girlfriend to both Billy and Colin</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Winstone" title="Ray Winstone">Ray Winstone</a> as Arnold French, Costello's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consigliere" title="Consigliere">consigliere</a></li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alec_Baldwin" title="Alec Baldwin">Alec Baldwin</a> as Captain George Ellerby, commander of the SIU</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Anderson" title="Anthony Anderson">Anthony Anderson</a> as Trooper Brown, member of the SIU and Billy's classmate at the MSP Academy</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Badge_Dale" title="James Badge Dale">James Badge Dale</a> as Trooper Barrigan, member of the SIU and Colin's classmate at the academy</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_O%27Hara" title="David O'Hara">David O'Hara</a> as "Fitzy" Fitzgibbons, one of Costello's enforcers</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Rolston" title="Mark Rolston">Mark Rolston</a> as Timothy Delahunt, one of Costello's enforcers</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin_Corrigan" title="Kevin Corrigan">Kevin Corrigan</a> as Sean, Billy's cousin</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Wahlberg" title="Robert Wahlberg">Robert Wahlberg</a> as FBI Special Agent Frank Lazio, FBI liaison to the SIU</li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Joseph_Riccobene&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" title="Joseph Riccobene (page does not exist)">Joseph Riccobene</a> as Kneecapped Bankrobber</li>
      </ul>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Themes">Themes</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Film critic <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanley_Kauffmann" title="Stanley Kauffmann">Stanley Kauffmann</a> describes a major theme of <i>The Departed</i> as one of the oldest in drama—the concept of <i>identity</i>—and how it "affects one's actions, emotions, self-assurance, and even dreams."</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The father-son relationship is a motif throughout the film. Costello acts as a father figure to both Colin and Billy while Queenan acts as Costello's foil in the role of father-figure presenting both sides of the Irish-American father archetype. Colin refers to Costello as 'Dad' whenever he calls him to inform him of police activities.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Boston_setting">Boston setting</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Born to an <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_American" title="Irish American">Irish American</a> family in the Boston neighborhood of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dorchester,_Massachusetts" title="Dorchester, Massachusetts">Dorchester, Massachusetts</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Monahan" title="William Monahan">William Monahan</a> (who adapted the screenplay from <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infernal_Affairs" title="Infernal Affairs">Infernal Affairs</a></i>) incorporates the culture and history of Boston heavily into the film. The first images are news clips from the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desegregation_busing_in_the_United_States#Boston.2C_Massachusetts" title="Desegregation busing in the United States">busing riots</a> of the 1970s, over which Costello muses about the city's troubled racial history. Several times, Dignam refers to Billy as "lace curtain," a term used primarily in the Boston metropolitan area by working-class Irish-Americans to disparage upper-middle class Irish-Americans who have "strayed from their roots" in their attempt to better themselves.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority of the characters have the non-<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhotic_and_non-rhotic_accents" title="Rhotic and non-rhotic accents">rhotic</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston_accent" title="Boston accent">Boston accent</a>. The <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts_State_House" title="Massachusetts State House">Massachusetts State House</a> is featured in the film as a symbol of Colin Sullivan's ambition. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston_Red_Sox" title="Boston Red Sox">Boston Red Sox</a> apparel is seen and worn, including the appearance of a now-out-of-print <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curse_of_the_Bambino" title="Curse of the Bambino">"Reverse The Curse"</a> bumper sticker on the wall at SIU headquarters. (Incidentally, when asked to wear a Red Sox cap during filming, Nicholson refused citing his loyalties to the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Yankees" title="New York Yankees">New York Yankees</a>, the Red Sox chief rivals.) In a bar scene, the logo of the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harpoon_Brewery" title="Harpoon Brewery">Harpoon Brewery</a>, which has locations in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston" title="Boston">Boston</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windsor,_Vermont" title="Windsor, Vermont">Windsor, Vermont</a>, is seen. Costello and his gang drive over the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zakim_Bunker_Hill_Bridge" title="Zakim Bunker Hill Bridge">Zakim Bunker Hill Bridge</a> in one scene. The building off which Queenan is thrown (and where Billy and Colin later meet) is in the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Point,_Boston" title="Fort Point, Boston">Fort Point</a> section of South Boston with the downtown skyline as backdrop (the fictitious "344 Wash" is actually an alley between Farnsworth Street and Thomson Place). <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hancock" title="John Hancock">John Hancock</a> employees are referenced by Costello, who makes an obscure but, according to urban legend, accurate reference to "the Fens"--a section of the Fenway—as a popular spot for gay cruising. Boston's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinatown" title="Chinatown">Chinatown</a> is portrayed in a crucial scene which is somewhat inaccurate, as the neighborhood is no longer home to pornographic movie theaters (Boston's red light district, the Combat Zone became defunct in the mid-1990s, but was very close to Chinatown). Characters are shown working in the striking, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brutalist" title="Brutalist">Brutalist</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Government_Service_Center_(Boston)" title="Government Service Center (Boston)">Government Service Center</a> downtown. The film includes the song "I'm Shipping Up To Boston" by the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dropkick_Murphys" title="Dropkick Murphys">Dropkick Murphys</a>, an Irish-American <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punk_rock" title="Punk rock">punk rock</a> band formed in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quincy,_Massachusetts" title="Quincy, Massachusetts">Quincy, Massachusetts</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other references include state locations such as <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Route_128_(Massachusetts)" title="Route 128 (Massachusetts)">Route 128</a>, regions such as the North Shore, there is a shot of the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Park_Street_Station" title="Park Street Station">Park Street</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Station_(Boston)" title="South Station (Boston)">South Station</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MBTA_Red_Line" title="MBTA Red Line">MBTA Red Line</a> stops, local cities such as <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worcester,_Massachusetts" title="Worcester, Massachusetts">Worcester</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brockton,_Massachusetts" title="Brockton, Massachusetts">Brockton</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloucester,_Massachusetts" title="Gloucester, Massachusetts">Gloucester</a>, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somerville,_Massachusetts" title="Somerville, Massachusetts">Somerville</a> while having turf wars with crew from nearby <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Providence,_Rhode_Island" title="Providence, Rhode Island">Providence</a>, a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cameo_appearance" title="Cameo appearance">cameo</a> by the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynn,_Massachusetts" title="Lynn, Massachusetts">Lynn</a> police, mention of the Dedham Mall (located in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dedham,_Massachusetts" title="Dedham, Massachusetts">Dedham</a> just southwest of Boston), and state slang like "Staties," a local nickname for <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts_State_Police" title="Massachusetts State Police">Massachusetts State Police</a> troopers. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deerfield_Academy" title="Deerfield Academy">Deerfield Academy</a>, a boarding school in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deerfield,_Massachusetts" title="Deerfield, Massachusetts">Deerfield, Massachusetts</a>, is referenced when Dignam points out that Billy was expelled from the school after assaulting the gym teacher (though in reality Deerfield, like most <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent_Schools" title="Independent Schools">Independent Schools</a>, has no gym class). Additionally, the label on Billy's prescription bottle shows a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beverly,_Massachusetts" title="Beverly, Massachusetts">Beverly</a> Street address in Boston. The <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Massachusetts_Boston" title="University of Massachusetts Boston">University of Massachusetts Boston</a> is referenced in several scenes.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frank Costello was largely based on <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_J._Bulger" title="James J. Bulger">James "Whitey" Bulger</a>, an Irish-American <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mobster" title="Mobster">mobster</a> in Boston who was secretly an <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FBI" title="FBI">FBI</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Informant" title="Informant">informant</a> for over three decades. The revelation that the FBI had long protected Bulger and his gang from prosecution caused a major scandal in Boston law enforcement. Bulger was believed to have been seen coming out of a theater showing the film in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Diego" title="San Diego">San Diego</a> in November 2006. Matt Damon's character is based on <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Connolly_(FBI)" title="John Connolly (FBI)">John Connolly</a>, the FBI agent who tipped off Bulger for years, allowing him to evade arrest. Bulger went into hiding and is still presumed to be at large, occupying a spot on the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FBI_Ten_Most_Wanted_Fugitives" title="FBI Ten Most Wanted Fugitives">FBI Ten Most Wanted Fugitives</a> list; Connolly is imprisoned for his role in Bulger's criminal activities. Billy's undercover role as a former State trooper who joins the Irish mob parallels the story of Richard Marinick, a former State trooper who later joined Whitey Bulger's crime syndicate. Billy lives in Somerville, where Bulger's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winter_Hill_Gang" title="Winter Hill Gang">Winter Hill Gang</a> began. Thomas Duffy, the film's technical advisor, is a former MSP major who was assigned to investigate the Irish mob upon making detective.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Reception">Reception</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i>The Departed</i> was highly anticipated when it was released on October 6, 2006 to overwhelmingly positive reviews. The film is one of the highest-rated wide release films of 2006 on <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotten_Tomatoes" title="Rotten Tomatoes">Rotten Tomatoes</a> at 93%.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entertainment_Weekly" title="Entertainment Weekly">Entertainment Weekly</a></i> put it on its end-of-the-decade, "best-of" list, saying, "If they're lucky, directors make one classic film in their career. Martin Scorsese has one per decade (Taxi Driver in the '70s, Raging Bull in the '80s, GoodFellas in the '90s). His 2006 Irish Mafia masterpiece kept the streak alive."</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Online critic <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Berardinelli" title="James Berardinelli">James Berardinelli</a> awarded the film four stars out of four, praising it as "an American epic tragedy." He went on to compare the film favorably to the onslaught of banality offered by American studios in recent years. "The movies have been in the doldrums lately. <i>The Departed</i> is a much needed tonic," he wrote. He went on to claim that the film deserves to be ranked alongside Scorsese's past successes, including <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taxi_Driver" title="Taxi Driver">Taxi Driver</a></i>, <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raging_Bull" title="Raging Bull">Raging Bull</a></i> and <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodfellas" title="Goodfellas">Goodfellas</a></i>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a largely negative review, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanley_Kauffmann" title="Stanley Kauffmann">Stanley Kauffmann</a> wrote "Is Scorsese desperate? This screenplay has the scent of it...I can't remember another Scorsese moment as shockingly banal as the finishing touch here."</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Lau" title="Andrew Lau">Andrew Lau</a>, the co-director of <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infernal_Affairs" title="Infernal Affairs">Infernal Affairs</a></i>, who was interviewed by Hong Kong newspaper <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_Daily" title="Apple Daily">Apple Daily</a></i>, said, "Of course I think the version I made is better, but the Hollywood version is pretty good too. [Scorsese] made the Hollywood version more attuned to American culture." <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andy_Lau" title="Andy Lau">Andy Lau</a>, one of the main actors in <i>Infernal Affairs</i>, when asked how the movie compares to the original, said, "<i>The Departed</i> was too long and it felt as if Hollywood had combined all three <i>Infernal Affairs</i> movies together." Lau pointed out that the remake featured some of the "golden quotes" of the original but did have much more swearing. He ultimately rated <i>The Departed</i> 8/10 and said that the Hollywood remake is worth a view, though "the effect of combining the two female characters in the [later film] into one isn't as good as in the original," according to Lau's spokeswoman Alice Tam.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The film appeared on many critics' top ten lists of the best films of 2006.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carrie Rickey of <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Philadelphia_Inquirer" title="The Philadelphia Inquirer">The Philadelphia Inquirer</a></i>, Joe Morgenstern of <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wall_Street_Journal" title="The Wall Street Journal">The Wall Street Journal</a></i>, Ruthe Stein of the <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco_Chronicle" title="San Francisco Chronicle">San Francisco Chronicle</a></i>, and Steven Rea of <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Philadelphia_Inquirer" title="The Philadelphia Inquirer">The Philadelphia Inquirer</a></i> named it one of the top ten best films of 2006. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Roeper" title="Richard Roeper">Richard Roeper</a> of the <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_Sun-Times" title="Chicago Sun-Times">Chicago Sun-Times</a></i> named it the best film of 2000s</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Awards_and_nominations">Awards and nominations</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The film won four <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Awards" title="Academy Awards">Academy Awards</a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/79th_Academy_Awards" title="79th Academy Awards">79th Academy Awards</a> for <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Picture" title="Academy Award for Best Picture">Best Picture</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Director" title="Academy Award for Best Director">Best Director</a> (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Scorsese" title="Martin Scorsese">Martin Scorsese</a>), <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Film_Editing" title="Academy Award for Best Film Editing">Best Film Editing</a> (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thelma_Schoonmaker" title="Thelma Schoonmaker">Thelma Schoonmaker</a>), and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Writing_(Adapted_Screenplay)" title="Academy Award for Best Writing (Adapted Screenplay)">Best Adapted Screenplay</a> (William Monahan). <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Wahlberg" title="Mark Wahlberg">Mark Wahlberg</a> was nominated for the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_Supporting_Actor" title="Best Supporting Actor">Best Supporting Actor</a> award for his performance. The film marked the first time Scorsese won an Oscar; many felt that he deserved it years earlier for prior efforts. Some have even gone further, calling it a Lifetime Achievement Award for a lesser film. Scorsese himself stated that he won because: "This is the first movie I've done with a plot."</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Soundtrack_music">Soundtrack music</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There were two albums released for <i>The Departed</i>, one presenting the original score composed for the movie by Howard Shore, and the other featuring earlier recordings, mostly <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pop/rock" title="Pop/rock">pop/rock</a> songs, which were used on the soundtrack.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The film opens with "<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gimme_Shelter" title="Gimme Shelter">Gimme Shelter</a>" by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rolling_Stones" title="The Rolling Stones">The Rolling Stones</a> and prominently plays "<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I%27m_Shipping_Up_to_Boston" title="I'm Shipping Up to Boston">I'm Shipping Up to Boston</a>" by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dropkick_Murphys" title="Dropkick Murphys">Dropkick Murphys</a> with lyrics written by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woody_Guthrie" title="Woody Guthrie">Woody Guthrie</a>, which gained the band some popularity. The film features the live cover of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd" title="Pink Floyd">Pink Floyd</a>'s "<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comfortably_Numb" title="Comfortably Numb">Comfortably Numb</a>" by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Waters" title="Roger Waters">Roger Waters</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Morrison" title="Van Morrison">Van Morrison</a>, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rick_Danko" title="Rick Danko">Rick Danko</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levon_Helm" title="Levon Helm">Levon Helm</a>, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garth_Hudson" title="Garth Hudson">Garth Hudson</a> of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Band" title="The Band">The Band</a> from the 1990 Berlin Wall Concert.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although "Gimme Shelter" is featured twice in the film, the song does not appear on the album soundtrack. Also heard in the movie but not featured on the soundtrack is "<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thief%27s_Theme" title="Thief's Theme">Thief's Theme</a>" by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nas" title="Nas">Nas</a>, "<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Well_Well_Well_(John_Lennon_song)" title="Well Well Well (John Lennon song)">Well Well Well</a>" by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Lennon" title="John Lennon">John Lennon</a>, "Bang Bang" by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Cuba" title="Joe Cuba">Joe Cuba</a>, and the Act II Sextet from <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donizetti" title="Donizetti">Donizetti</a>'s <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucia_di_Lammermoor" title="Lucia di Lammermoor">Lucia di Lammermoor</a></i> (Which is also Costello's ringtone in the film).</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The movie closes with a cover of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don_Gibson" title="Don Gibson">Don Gibson</a>'s "<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sweet_Dreams_(Don_Gibson_song)" title="Sweet Dreams (Don Gibson song)">Sweet Dreams</a>," by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy_Buchanan" title="Roy Buchanan">Roy Buchanan</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><b>Track Listing</b></p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The film score for <i>The Departed</i> was written by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howard_Shore" title="Howard Shore">Howard Shore</a> and performed by guitarists <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharon_Isbin" title="Sharon Isbin">Sharon Isbin</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G._E._Smith" title="G. E. Smith">G. E. Smith</a>, Larry Saltzman and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc_Ribot" title="Marc Ribot">Marc Ribot</a>. The score was recorded in Shore's own studio in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_State" title="New York State">New York State</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><b>Track Listing</b></p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="DVD_releases">DVD releases</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i>The Departed</i> was released by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warner_Brothers" title="Warner Brothers">Warner Brothers</a> on DVD on February 13, 2007 in Region 1 format and on February 19, 2007 in Region 2 format, and was released on March 14, 2007 in Region 4 format. The film is available in a single-disc full screen (1:33:1), single-disc widescreen (2:40:1) edition, and 2-disc special edition. The second disc of this film predominately contains features that concerned the crimes that influenced Scorsese with deleted scenes being the only feature that are actually film related. The <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Region_1" title="Region 1">Region 1</a> version has three available audio tracks: English, Spanish, and French (all of which are in Dolby Digital 5.1), and three subtitle tracks (English, Spanish, French). The film was released on <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_DVD" title="HD DVD">HD DVD</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blu-ray" title="Blu-ray">Blu-ray</a> at the same time as the standard-definition DVD. The 2-Disc Special Edition was packaged in a Limited Edition <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Steelbook&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" title="Steelbook (page does not exist)">Steelbook</a>. It marked the first time that an Oscar winning Best Picture was released to the home video market in DVD format only, as VHS was totally phased out by the start of 2006.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Potential_sequel">Potential sequel</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In February 2007, Mark Wahlberg had an interview with <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empire_(magazine)" title="Empire (magazine)">Empire</a></i> about <i>The Departed 2</i>. Although the film has not been <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green-light" title="Green-light">greenlit</a>, Wahlberg stated that there might be a sequel focusing on his character, Dignam, with <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_De_Niro" title="Robert De Niro">Robert De Niro</a> potentially playing a corrupted senator. He also stated that <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Monahan" title="William Monahan">William Monahan</a> is busy penning the script. However, the film was said to be on hold, due to producer <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brad_Grey" title="Brad Grey">Brad Grey</a>'s involvement, as he's now the head of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paramount_Pictures" title="Paramount Pictures">Paramount Pictures</a> and the film is a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warner_Bros." title="Warner Bros.">Warner Bros.</a> project.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In June 2010, Wahlberg and Monahan still expressed interest in a sequel, which is said to be projected for a 2012 release date.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Homages">Homages</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Throughout the film, Scorsese used Xs to mark characters for death; examples include shots of Billy walking through the airport while talking to Sgt. Dignam (Mark Wahlberg), Queenan falling to his death, and Colin returning to his apartment at the end of the movie. This is an homage to <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howard_Hawks" title="Howard Hawks">Howard Hawks</a>' classic 1932 film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scarface_(1932_film)" title="Scarface (1932 film)">Scarface</a></i>.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="See_also">See also</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_American_films_of_2006" title="List of American films of 2006">List of American films of 2006</a></li>
	<li><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_of_Damnation" title="City of Damnation">City of Damnation</a></li>
      </ul>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Notes">Notes</span></h2>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Further_reading">Further reading</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><span class="citation news">Brad Balfour (2006). <a href="http://www.popentertainment.com/scorsese.htm" rel="nofollow">"MARTIN SCORSESE, LEONARDO DiCAPRIO, MATT DAMON, VERA FARMIGA AND WILLIAM MONAHAN (records two 40-minute press conference sessions)"</a>. <i>PopEntertainment.com</i><span class="printonly">. <a href="http://www.popentertainment.com/scorsese.htm" rel="nofollow">http://www.popentertainment.com/scorsese.htm</a></span><span class="reference-accessdate">. Retrieved 2007-09-10</span>.</span><span class="Z3988" title="ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;rft.genre=article&amp;rft.atitle=MARTIN+SCORSESE%2C+LEONARDO+DiCAPRIO%2C+MATT+DAMON%2C+VERA+FARMIGA+AND+WILLIAM+MONAHAN+%28records+two+40-minute+press+conference+sessions%29&amp;rft.jtitle=PopEntertainment.com&amp;rft.aulast=Brad+Balfour&amp;rft.au=Brad+Balfour&amp;rft.date=2006&amp;rft_id=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.popentertainment.com%2Fscorsese.htm&amp;rfr_id=info:sid/en.wikipedia.org:The_Departed"><span style="display: none;"> </span></span></li>
      </ul>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="External_links">External links</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><span class="official website"><a href="http://thedeparted.warnerbros.com" rel="nofollow">Official website</a></span></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0407887/" rel="nofollow"><i>The Departed</i></a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Movie_Database" title="Internet Movie Database">Internet Movie Database</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.allmovie.com/work/310756" rel="nofollow"><i>The Departed</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allmovie" title="Allmovie">Allmovie</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/departed/" rel="nofollow"><i>The Departed</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotten_Tomatoes" title="Rotten Tomatoes">Rotten Tomatoes</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.metacritic.com/film/titles/departed" rel="nofollow"><i>The Departed</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metacritic" title="Metacritic">Metacritic</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=departed.htm" rel="nofollow"><i>The Departed</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Box_Office_Mojo" title="Box Office Mojo">Box Office Mojo</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.imsdb.com/scripts/Departed,-The.html" rel="nofollow">The script</a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Internet_Movie_Script_Database&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" title="Internet Movie Script Database (page does not exist)">imsdb</a></li>
      </ul>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><span id="interwiki-vi-fa"></span></p>
    </wiki:description>
  </wiki:film>
</wiki:nominee>