<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<wiki:nominee year="1980" span="1" winner="false" award="best-picture" xmlns:wiki="http://marklogic.com/wikipedia">
  <!--
                            Copyright (c) 2010 MarkLogic Corporation.
                            Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
                            under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
                            or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
                            with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
                            A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
                            Free Documentation License"
                            
                            Content derived from http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Elephant_Man_(film)
                            Modified in May 2009 by Mark Logic Corporation under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License.
                        -->
  <wiki:film-title link="/wiki/The_Elephant_Man_(film)">The Elephant Man</wiki:film-title>
  <wiki:film link="/wiki/The_Elephant_Man_(film)" title="The Elephant Man">
    <wiki:oscar-ref year="1980" span="1" winner="false" award="lead-actor" person-link="/wiki/John_Hurt" person-name="John Hurt"/>
    <wiki:oscar-ref year="1980" span="1" winner="false" award="best-director" person-link="/wiki/David_Lynch" person-name="David Lynch"/>
    <wiki:oscar year="1980" span="1" winner="false" award="best-picture"/>
    <wiki:producer link="/wiki/Stuart_Cornfeld">Stuart Cornfeld</wiki:producer>
    <wiki:producer link="/wiki/Mel_Brooks">Mel Brooks</wiki:producer>
    <wiki:director link="/wiki/David_Lynch">David Lynch</wiki:director>
    <wiki:distributor link="/wiki/Paramount_Pictures">Paramount Pictures</wiki:distributor>
    <wiki:distributor link="/wiki/EMI_Films">EMI Films</wiki:distributor>
    <wiki:starring link="/wiki/Anthony_Hopkins">Anthony Hopkins</wiki:starring>
    <wiki:starring link="/wiki/John_Hurt">John Hurt</wiki:starring>
    <wiki:starring link="/wiki/Anne_Bancroft">Anne Bancroft</wiki:starring>
    <wiki:starring link="/wiki/John_Gielgud">John Gielgud</wiki:starring>
    <wiki:starring link="/wiki/Wendy_Hiller">Wendy Hiller</wiki:starring>
    <wiki:description>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i><b>The Elephant Man</b></i> is a 1980 American <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drama_film" title="Drama film">drama film</a> based on the true story of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Merrick" title="Joseph Merrick">Joseph Merrick</a> (called John Merrick in the film), a severely <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deformity" title="Deformity">deformed</a> man in 19th century <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London" title="London">London</a>. The film was directed by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Lynch" title="David Lynch">David Lynch</a> and stars <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hurt" title="John Hurt">John Hurt</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Hopkins" title="Anthony Hopkins">Anthony Hopkins</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Bancroft" title="Anne Bancroft">Anne Bancroft</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gielgud" title="John Gielgud">John Gielgud</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wendy_Hiller" title="Wendy Hiller">Wendy Hiller</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Elphick" title="Michael Elphick">Michael Elphick</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hannah_Gordon" title="Hannah Gordon">Hannah Gordon</a>, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freddie_Jones" title="Freddie Jones">Freddie Jones</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The screenplay was adapted by Lynch, Christopher De Vore, and Eric Bergren from the books <i>The Elephant Man and Other Reminiscences</i> (1923) by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Frederick_Treves,_1st_Baronet" title="Sir Frederick Treves, 1st Baronet">Sir Frederick Treves</a> and <i>The Elephant Man: A Study in Human Dignity</i> by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashley_Montagu" title="Ashley Montagu">Ashley Montagu</a>. It was shot in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black-and-white" title="Black-and-white">black-and-white</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i>The Elephant Man</i> was recognized as a critical and commercial success, and received eight <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award" title="Academy Award">Academy Award</a> nominations, including <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Picture" title="Academy Award for Best Picture">Best Picture</a> in 1981.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Plot">Plot</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Frederick_Treves,_1st_Baronet" title="Sir Frederick Treves, 1st Baronet">Frederick Treves</a> (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Hopkins" title="Anthony Hopkins">Anthony Hopkins</a>), a surgeon at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_London_Hospital" title="Royal London Hospital">London Hospital</a>, discovers <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Merrick" title="Joseph Merrick">John Merrick</a> (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hurt" title="John Hurt">John Hurt</a>) in a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victorian_era" title="Victorian era">Victorian</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freak_show" title="Freak show">freak show</a> in London's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_End" title="East End">East End</a>, where he is managed by the brutish Bytes (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freddie_Jones" title="Freddie Jones">Freddie Jones</a>). Merrick is so deformed that he must wear a hood and cape when in public. Bytes further claims that his "exhibit" is an <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mental_retardation" title="Mental retardation">imbecile</a>. Treves is professionally intrigued by Merrick's condition and pays Bytes to bring him to the London Hospital so that he can examine him. He then presents a lecture to his colleagues on Merrick's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disability" title="Disability">disability</a>, dispassionately displaying him as a prize physiological curiosity. Treves draws attention to the oversized deformities of Merrick's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_skull" title="Human skull">skull</a>; it is his most obvious disability and (as he was so informed by Bytes) also the most life-threatening, as he is compelled to sleep sitting with his head resting upon his knees, as the weight of his skull would <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asphyxiation" title="Asphyxiation">asphyxiate</a> him if he were to ever lie down. On Merrick's return, Bytes beats him so severely that a sympathetic apprentice (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dexter_Fletcher" title="Dexter Fletcher">Dexter Fletcher</a>) alerts Treves, who attempts to take him back to the hospital. Bytes confronts Treves, accusing him of likewise exploiting Merrick for his own ends, which leads the surgeon to resolve to do what he can to help the unfortunate man.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ward nurses are horrified by Merrick's appearance, so Treves places him in a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quarantine" title="Quarantine">quarantine</a> room under the watchful care of the formidable matron, Mrs. Mothershead (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wendy_Hiller" title="Wendy Hiller">Wendy Hiller</a>). Mr. Carr Gomm (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gielgud" title="John Gielgud">John Gielgud</a>), the hospital's Governor, questions Treves about his mysterious patient and reminds him that the hospital is not designed as a residence for "incurables". Treves attempts to coach Merrick (who has thus far remained <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muteness" title="Muteness">mute</a>) to recite a few polite phrases, such as: "Hello. My name is John Merrick. I am very pleased to meet you." However, during an interview with Gomm, the bewildered and distressed Merrick breaks down. Gomm leaves, telling Treves that, while it was a good attempt, the man is an obvious imbecile. He orders Treves to remove him. As Gomm walks away, Treves hears Merrick recite the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psalm_23" title="Psalm 23">23rd Psalm</a> in an hitherto unheard strong and confident voice. He calls back his superior, who, in shock at this unexpected show of Merrick's intellect and conviction, allows him to remain.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is soon revealed that Merrick is sophisticated and articulate, with refined intellectual and spiritual leanings. He demonstrates a level of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literacy" title="Literacy">literacy</a> unusual even in able-bodied men of his class and background. His playing dumb was a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defense_mechanism" title="Defense mechanism">defense mechanism</a> to avoid beatings from Bytes. Gomm arranges a suite of rooms for Merrick to reside in at the hospital. Merrick settles into his new home and, with the encouragement of Treves and Nurse Nora (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lesley_Dunlop" title="Lesley Dunlop">Lesley Dunlop</a>), passes his days reading, drawing and making a model of a church visible through his window. One day, Treves brings him to take <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afternoon_tea" title="Afternoon tea">afternoon tea</a> at home together with his wife, Ann (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hannah_Gordon" title="Hannah Gordon">Hannah Gordon</a>). Merrick, overwhelmed by the familial love he perceives in the domesticity about him, reveals to them his most treasured possession, a picture of his mother, and expresses his wish that she would love him if she could only see what "lovely friends" he now has. Later, Merrick begins to receive society visitors in his rooms, including the celebrated actress <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madge_Kendal" title="Madge Kendal">Madge Kendal</a> (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Bancroft" title="Anne Bancroft">Anne Bancroft</a>). He becomes a popular object of curiosity and charity to high society. As these connections and visits increase, Mrs. Mothershead (who has charge of Merrick's daily care) complains to Treves that he is still being treated as a freak show attraction, albeit in a more upper class, celebrated style. For Treves' part, this observation (and his role in this situation) deeply trouble him, and he begins to question whether or not he has done the right thing.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Threatened dissent from a member of the Hospital Board at this decision is dramatically overturned when the hospital's Royal Patron—<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandra_of_Denmark" title="Alexandra of Denmark">HRH The Princess of Wales</a>—pays a surprise visit to the decisive board meeting with a message from <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Victoria" title="Queen Victoria">Queen Victoria</a>. Her Majesty desires that Merrick receive permanent care at the hospital and the necessary funds have been arranged. It transpires that Carr Gomm has been a source of information to an intrigued Royal Family and the outcome a reflection of his personal wishes. A <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Night_porter" title="Night porter">night porter</a> (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Elphick" title="Michael Elphick">Michael Elphick</a>) exploits Merrick by charging late-night local pub drinkers for a "viewing". Through this, Bytes gets to his former "property" and eventually abducts him to continental <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europe" title="Europe">Europe</a>, where he is once again put on show and subjected to Bytes' cruelty and neglect. Merrick escapes with the help of his fellow freak show attractions, and makes it back to London. However, he is harassed by a group of boys at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liverpool_Street_station" title="Liverpool Street station">Liverpool Street station</a>, and accidentally knocks down a young girl. He is chased, unmasked, and cornered by an angry mob, at which point he cries out:</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the shocked mob backs away, he collapses from illness and exhaustion. Treves, consumed with guilt over Merrick's plight, takes action against the night porter with the help of Mrs. Mothershead. When the police return Merrick to the hospital, he is reinstated to his rooms. He recovers a little but it is soon clear he is dying from <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronic_obstructive_pulmonary_disease" title="Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease">chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</a>. As a treat, Mrs. Kendal arranges an evening at the musical theatre, where Merrick is accompanied by his beloved friends: Treves, Mrs Mothershead, Nurse Nora, and HRH The Princess Of Wales. Resplendent in white tie, he rises in the Royal Box to an ovation, having had the performance dedicated to him from Mrs Kendal. That night, back at the hospital, Merrick thanks Treves for all he has done and finishes his model of the nearby church. Imitating one of his sketches on the wall—a sleeping child—he removes the pillows that have allowed him to sleep in an upright position, lies down on his bed and dies, consoled by a vision of his mother, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Jane_Merrick" title="Mary Jane Merrick">Mary Jane Merrick</a>, quoting <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfred_Lord_Tennyson" title="Alfred Lord Tennyson">Alfred Lord Tennyson</a>'s <i>"Nothing will Die"</i>.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Historical_accuracy">Historical accuracy</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The film is based on historical events, but makes numerous changes to recorded fact. For example, the incidents in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgium" title="Belgium">Belgium</a> and at the railway station took place before Merrick was admitted to Treves' hospital, not afterward, and Merrick traveled to Belgium of his own accord, because freak shows had been made illegal in Britain. There is also no evidence that Merrick was <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physical_abuse" title="Physical abuse">abused</a> while working at the British freak show; in fact, Merrick had saved up a great deal of money from the wages he had earned while working there and considered the freak show coordinator a close friend. Likewise, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treves" title="Treves">Treves</a> did not "rescue" Merrick from a <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sadomasochism" title="Sadomasochism">sadistic</a> carnival proprietor: Merrick freely approached the doctor with a written note requesting his care. The film's chief antagonist, Bytes, is based on Merrick's three owners <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Norman" title="Tom Norman">Tom Norman</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Sam_Roper&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" title="Sam Roper (page does not exist)">Sam Roper</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Joe_Ferarri&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" title="Joe Ferarri (page does not exist)">Joe Ferarri</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the constrictive <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deformity" title="Deformity">deformity</a> of his mouth, Merrick was never able to speak as clearly as in the film, and Treves often had to act as his interpreter for visitors. Those who knew him well, such as hospital staff and friends, grew accustomed to his impeded speech but it remained indistinct and worsened as his condition deteriorated.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Production">Production</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The film was produced by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mel_Brooks" title="Mel Brooks">Mel Brooks</a>, who had been impressed by Lynch's earlier film <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eraserhead" title="Eraserhead">Eraserhead</a></i> at a private screening. Brooks made sure that his name was not used in the marketing and promotion of the film because he did not want fans to expect that the film would be a comedy. It was Lynch's second feature film, and his first studio film.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hurt's makeup was made from casts of Merrick's body, which had been preserved in the private museum of the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_London_Hospital" title="Royal London Hospital">Royal London Hospital</a>. Lynch originally attempted to do the make-up himself, but the results were not filmable. The final make-up was devised by Christopher Tucker. It was so convincing that the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_of_Motion_Picture_Arts_and_Sciences" title="Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences">Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences</a> — which had earlier refused to give a special award to Tucker's work on <i>The Elephant Man</i> and received a barrage of complaints — was prompted to create a new category for Best Make-up for the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Awards" title="Academy Awards">Oscars</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to writing and directing the film, Lynch provided the musical direction and sound design. During its depiction of the final moments of Merrick's life, the film uses "<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adagio_for_Strings" title="Adagio for Strings">Adagio for Strings</a>" by <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Barber" title="Samuel Barber">Samuel Barber</a>.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Actor <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Treves_(actor)" title="Frederick Treves (actor)">Frederick Treves</a>, great-nephew of the surgeon, appears in the opening sequences as an Alderman trying to close down the freak show.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Reception">Reception</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i>The Elephant Man</i> received an enthusiastic critical response, with a 91% "fresh" rating on review aggregator <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotten_Tomatoes" title="Rotten Tomatoes">Rotten Tomatoes</a>. <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vincent_Canby" title="Vincent Canby">Vincent Canby</a> wrote: "Mr. Hurt is truly remarkable. It can't be easy to act under such a heavy mask... the physical production is beautiful, especially Freddie Francis's black-and-white photography. Conversely, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Ebert" title="Roger Ebert">Roger Ebert</a> awarded the film 2/4 stars, writing: "I kept asking myself what the film was really trying to say about the human condition as reflected by John Merrick, and I kept drawing blanks."</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In her book <i>The Spectacle of Deformity: Freak Shows and Modern British Culture</i>, Nadja Durbach said that the film was "much more mawkish and moralizing than one would expect from the leading postmodern surrealist filmmaker", and that it was "unashamedly sentimental". She blamed this sentimentality on Lynch's reliance on Frederick Treves' memoirs as source material.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Home_media">Home media</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the many releases of the film on both VHS and DVD, <i>The Elephant Man</i> saw an exclusive <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blu-ray" title="Blu-ray">Blu-ray</a> treatment on the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blu-ray_Disc_Region_Code" title="Blu-ray Disc Region Code">European market</a> as part of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimum_Releasing" title="Optimum Releasing">Optimum's</a> <i>StudioCanal Collection</i>. Special features included several interviews with John Hurt and David Lynch as well as an extensive documentary on the life of Joseph Merrick entitled <i>The Real Elephant Man</i>.</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="Awards_and_media_listings">Awards and media listings</span></h2>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><i>The Elephant Man</i> was nominated for <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Awards" title="Academy Awards">Academy Awards</a> for <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Picture" title="Academy Award for Best Picture">Best Picture</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Actor" title="Academy Award for Best Actor">Actor in a Leading Role</a> (John Hurt), <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Best_Art_Direction" title="Academy Award for Best Art Direction">Art Direction-Set Decoration</a> (<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuart_Craig" title="Stuart Craig">Stuart Craig</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Cartwright" title="Robert Cartwright">Robert Cartwright</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Scaife" title="Hugh Scaife">Hugh Scaife</a>), <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Costume_Design" title="Academy Award for Costume Design">Costume Design</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Directing" title="Academy Award for Directing">Director</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Film_Editing" title="Academy Award for Film Editing">Film Editing</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Original_Music_Score" title="Academy Award for Original Music Score">Music: Original Score</a>, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_Award_for_Writing_Adapted_Screenplay" title="Academy Award for Writing Adapted Screenplay">Writing: Screenplay Based on Material from Another Medium</a>. However, the film did not win any.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It won the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BAFTA_Award_for_Best_Film" title="BAFTA Award for Best Film">BAFTA Award for Best Film</a>, as well as other <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Academy_of_Film_and_Television_Arts" title="British Academy of Film and Television Arts">BAFTA Awards</a> for Best Film, Best Actor (John Hurt) and Best Production Design, and was nominated for four others: Direction, Screenplay, Cinematography, and Editing.</p>
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It was listed by <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entertainment_Weekly" title="Entertainment Weekly">Entertainment Weekly</a>'</i>s film's "Saddest Moments". In 2006, the film was listed in a televised <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australia" title="Australia">Australian</a> series <i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/20_to_1" title="20 to 1">20 to 1</a></i> countdown celebrating "Great Movie One-Liners"; the line featured was the iconic "I am not an animal! I am a human being! I am... a man!"</p>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="See_also">See also</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><i><a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Elephant_Man_(play)" title="The Elephant Man (play)">The Elephant Man</a></i> (play)</li>
      </ul>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="References">References</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><span class="citation" id="Durbach">Durbach, Nadja (2009), "Monstrosity, Masculinity, and Medicine: Reexamining 'the Elephant Man'", <i>The Spectacle of Deformity: Freak Shows and Modern British Culture</i>, Berkeley: <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California_Press" title="University of California Press">University of California Press</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number" title="International Standard Book Number">ISBN</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0520257685" title="Special:BookSources/0520257685">0520257685</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Online_Computer_Library_Center" title="Online Computer Library Center">OCLC</a> <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/314839375" rel="nofollow">314839375</a></span><span class="Z3988" title="ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;rft.genre=bookitem&amp;rft.btitle=Monstrosity%2C+Masculinity%2C+and+Medicine%3A+Reexamining+%27the+Elephant+Man%27&amp;rft.atitle=The+Spectacle+of+Deformity%3A+Freak+Shows+and+Modern+British+Culture&amp;rft.aulast=Durbach&amp;rft.aufirst=Nadja&amp;rft.au=Durbach%2C%26%2332%3BNadja&amp;rft.date=2009&amp;rft.place=Berkeley&amp;rft.pub=%5B%5BUniversity+of+California+Press%5D%5D&amp;rft_id=info:oclcnum/314839375&amp;rft.isbn=0520257685&amp;rfr_id=info:sid/en.wikipedia.org:The_Elephant_Man_(film)"><span style="display: none;"> </span></span></li>
      </ul>
      <h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <span class="mw-headline" id="External_links">External links</span></h2>
      <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<li><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0080678/" rel="nofollow"><i>The Elephant Man</i></a> at the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Movie_Database" title="Internet Movie Database">Internet Movie Database</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.allmovie.com/work/15593" rel="nofollow"><i>The Elephant Man</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allmovie" title="Allmovie">Allmovie</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=elephantman.htm" rel="nofollow"><i>The Elephant Man</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Box_Office_Mojo" title="Box Office Mojo">Box Office Mojo</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/1006527-elephant_man/" rel="nofollow"><i>The Elephant Man</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotten_Tomatoes" title="Rotten Tomatoes">Rotten Tomatoes</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.metacritic.com/film/titles/elephant-man" rel="nofollow"><i>The Elephant Man</i></a> at <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metacritic" title="Metacritic">Metacritic</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.timeout.com/film/features/show-feature/5443/david-lynch-interview.html" rel="nofollow">Time Out magazine</a> interviews David Lynch about the film</li>
	<li><a href="http://josephcareymerrick.com/" rel="nofollow">Joseph Merrick tribute website</a></li>
      </ul>
    </wiki:description>
  </wiki:film>
</wiki:nominee>