<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><sem:triples xmlns:sem="http://marklogic.com/semantics"><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="ja">ソマリア</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="pl">Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="zh">索马里</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="pt">Somália</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="nl">Somalië</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="de">Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="ar">الصومال</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="es">Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="it">Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="ru">Шаблон:Государство/ВикиданныеСомали́ (сомал. Soomaaliya, араб. الصومال‎‎ ас-Сумаль), официальное наименование — Федеративная Республика Сомали́ — восточноафриканское государство, фактически распавшееся в результате гражданской войны и деятельности сепаратистов на несколько частей. Член ООН с 20 сентября 1960 года.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="ja">ソマリア連邦共和国Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliyaجمهورية الصومال الفدرالية&lt;/dd&gt;国の標語：なし国歌：祖国を賛美せよ2012年7月31日までの国歌は目覚めよ、ソマリアソマリアの位置&lt;/dd&gt;データには原則としてソマリランドを含む。注1 : 現在公式に認められた政府および憲法が存在しないため、公用語および首都はバーレ政権以前からもの。注2 : ソマリア北部は、1960年6月26日にイギリスから独立し、ソマリア南部は、1960年7月1日にイタリアから独立し、同時に両者は合併してソマリア共和国となった。&lt;/dl&gt;ソマリア連邦共和国（ソマリアれんぽうきょうわこく）、通称ソマリアは、東アフリカのアフリカの角と呼ばれる地域を領域とする国家。ジブチ、エチオピア、ケニアと国境を接し、インド洋とアデン湾に面する。1991年勃発の内戦により国土は分断され、事実上の無政府状態が続き、エチオピアの軍事支援を受けた暫定政権が首都を制圧したものの、依然として内戦状態が続いている。現在の国土は暫定政権の南部と、1998年7月に自治宣言したプントランド（首都ガローウェ、暫定政権との連邦制に肯定的）の北東部、91年に独立宣言した旧英領のソマリランド共和国（首都ハルゲイサ、国際的に未承認、東部に分離の動き）の北部に大きく3分割されている。</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">Somalia (/sɵˈmɑːliə/ so-MAH-lee-ə; Somali: Soomaaliya; Arabic: الصومال‎ aṣ-Ṣūmāl), officially the Federal Republic of Somalia (Somali: Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya, Arabic:  جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية‎ Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fiderāliyya), is a country located in the Horn of Africa. It is bordered by Ethiopia to the west, Djibouti to the northwest, the Gulf of Aden to the north, the Indian Ocean to the east, and Kenya to the southwest.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="zh">索马里联邦共和国 （索馬里語：Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya；阿拉伯语： جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية‎；Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fiderāliyya），簡稱索馬利亞（索馬里語：Soomaaliya；阿拉伯语：الصومال‎；aṣ-Ṣūmāl；英语发音：/sɵˈmɑːliə/；so-MAH-lee-ə），是一個东非國家，位於索马里半岛上，东濱印度洋，北临亚丁湾，与埃塞俄比亚、肯尼亚、吉布提相邻。索馬里目前處於內戰狀態，戰前首都為摩加迪沙（Mogadishu）。位於索國西北部的索馬利蘭與傾向於統合的中部邦特蘭以及伊斯蘭法庭聯盟均為實質獨立。索馬里的地理位置，居於地中海與印度洋的亞丁灣之南，是各國貨輪出入蘇伊士運河的必經海路。2004年的《内罗毕全面协定》签署后，索马里成立过渡政府，2012年8月23日索马里结束为期8年的过渡期，8月29日选出联邦议会议长，9月10日全国选民普选产生新总统，9月17日总统内阁人选经联邦议会批准成立，9月21日索马里变为联邦州县自治管理，同时恢复实行联邦宪政。</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="it">La Somalia /soˈmalja/ (somalo: Soomaaliya; in arabo: الصومال, al-Sūmāl), ufficialmente Repubblica Federale di Somalia (somalo: Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya; in arabo: جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية, Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fideraaliya), è uno Stato dell'Africa Orientale situato nel corno d'Africa.Confina con Gibuti a nord, con l'Etiopia a ovest e con il Kenya a sudovest; si affaccia a nord sul Golfo di Aden e a est sull'oceano Indiano.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="pl">Nieprawidłowe parametry: { |_region:{{#property:P300}}}Somalia (som. Soomaaliya; arab. الصومال, As-Sumal, Aş-Şūmāl), Federalna Republika Somalii – państwo w północno-wschodniej części Afryki położone na Półwyspie Somalijskim (zwanym „Rogiem Afryki”). Przylega do Oceanu Indyjskiego i Zatoki Adeńskiej.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="nl">Somalië (Somalisch: Soomaaliya; Arabisch: الصومال, As-Soemal), officieel de Federale Republiek Somalië (Somalisch: Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya, Arabisch:جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fideraaliya), is een land in de Hoorn van Afrika dat grenst aan Djibouti, Ethiopië en Kenia. De hoofdstad van Somalië is Mogadishu. Het Somalisch en Arabisch zijn de officiële talen van Somalië.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="pt">Somália (em somali: Soomaaliya; em árabe: الصومال, transl. aṣ-Ṣūmāl), oficialmente República Federal da Somália (em somali: Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya; em árabe: جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية, transl. Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fiderāliyya) e anteriormente conhecida como República Somaliana e como República Democrática da Somália, é um país localizado no Corno de África.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="es">Somalia o Somalía (somalí: Soomaaliya; árabe: الصومال, As-Sūmāl), formalmente conocida como República Federal de Somalia, es un país ubicado en el llamado Cuerno de África, al este del continente africano. Al oeste y noroeste limita con Etiopía y Yibuti, al sur con Kenia, al norte con el golfo de Adén, y al este con el océano Índico. Tras una larga guerra civil, el país se dividió en pequeños estados y facciones independientes, sin un poder que lo gobierne en su totalidad.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#comment</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="de">Somalia (Somali Soomaaliya; arabisch ‏الصومال‎, DMG aṣ-Ṣūmāl) oder Bundesrepublik Somalia bezeichnet einen föderalen Staat im äußersten Osten Afrikas am Horn von Afrika. Der Name ist vom Volk der Somali abgeleitet, das  die Bevölkerungsmehrheit bildet und auch in den Nachbarländern ansässig ist.Somalia entstand aus dem Zusammenschluss der Kolonialgebiete Britisch- und Italienisch-Somaliland, die 1960 („Afrikanisches Jahr“) gemeinsam unabhängig wurden.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#seeAlso</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Al-Shabaab_(militant_group)</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#seeAlso</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Battle_of_Mogadishu_(2006)</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/name</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">(so)(ar)</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/name</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#lat</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#float">2.0333333015441894531</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#long</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#float">45.34999847412109375</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/depiction</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Flag_of_Somalia.svg</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/ns/prov#wasDerivedFrom</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somalia?oldid=645828999</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/PopulatedPlace/areaTotal</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://dbpedia.org/datatype/squareKilometre">637657.0</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/PopulatedPlace/areaTotal</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://dbpedia.org/datatype/squareKilometre">637655.0727647231</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/PopulatedPlace/populationDensity</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://dbpedia.org/datatype/inhabitantsPerSquareKilometre">16.12</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/PopulatedPlace/populationDensity</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://dbpedia.org/datatype/inhabitantsPerSquareKilometre">16.112043075976267</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="zh">索马里联邦共和国 （索馬里語：Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya；阿拉伯语： جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية‎；Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fiderāliyya），簡稱索馬利亞（索馬里語：Soomaaliya；阿拉伯语：الصومال‎；aṣ-Ṣūmāl；英语发音：/sɵˈmɑːliə/；so-MAH-lee-ə），是一個东非國家，位於索马里半岛上，东濱印度洋，北临亚丁湾，与埃塞俄比亚、肯尼亚、吉布提相邻。索馬里目前處於內戰狀態，戰前首都為摩加迪沙（Mogadishu）。位於索國西北部的索馬利蘭與傾向於統合的中部邦特蘭以及伊斯蘭法庭聯盟均為實質獨立。索馬里的地理位置，居於地中海與印度洋的亞丁灣之南，是各國貨輪出入蘇伊士運河的必經海路。2004年的《内罗毕全面协定》签署后，索马里成立过渡政府，2012年8月23日索马里结束为期8年的过渡期，8月29日选出联邦议会议长，9月10日全国选民普选产生新总统，9月17日总统内阁人选经联邦议会批准成立，9月21日索马里变为联邦州县自治管理，同时恢复实行联邦宪政。</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="ja">ソマリア連邦共和国Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliyaجمهورية الصومال الفدرالية&lt;/dd&gt;国の標語：なし国歌：祖国を賛美せよ2012年7月31日までの国歌は目覚めよ、ソマリアソマリアの位置&lt;/dd&gt;データには原則としてソマリランドを含む。注1 : 現在公式に認められた政府および憲法が存在しないため、公用語および首都はバーレ政権以前からもの。注2 : ソマリア北部は、1960年6月26日にイギリスから独立し、ソマリア南部は、1960年7月1日にイタリアから独立し、同時に両者は合併してソマリア共和国となった。&lt;/dl&gt;ソマリア連邦共和国（ソマリアれんぽうきょうわこく）、通称ソマリアは、東アフリカのアフリカの角と呼ばれる地域を領域とする国家。ジブチ、エチオピア、ケニアと国境を接し、インド洋とアデン湾に面する。1991年勃発の内戦により国土は分断され、事実上の無政府状態が続き、エチオピアの軍事支援を受けた暫定政権が首都を制圧したものの、依然として内戦状態が続いている。現在の国土は暫定政権の南部と、1998年7月に自治宣言したプントランド（首都ガローウェ、暫定政権との連邦制に肯定的）の北東部、91年に独立宣言した旧英領のソマリランド共和国（首都ハルゲイサ、国際的に未承認、東部に分離の動き）の北部に大きく3分割されている。</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="de">Somalia (Somali Soomaaliya; arabisch ‏الصومال‎, DMG aṣ-Ṣūmāl) oder Bundesrepublik Somalia bezeichnet einen föderalen Staat im äußersten Osten Afrikas am Horn von Afrika. Der Name ist vom Volk der Somali abgeleitet, das  die Bevölkerungsmehrheit bildet und auch in den Nachbarländern ansässig ist.Somalia entstand aus dem Zusammenschluss der Kolonialgebiete Britisch- und Italienisch-Somaliland, die 1960 („Afrikanisches Jahr“) gemeinsam unabhängig wurden. Das Staatsgebiet grenzt an den Indischen Ozean im Osten, den Golf von Aden im Norden, Dschibuti und Äthiopien im Westen und Kenia im Süden. Nach dem Sturz der autoritären Regierung unter Siad Barre 1991 existierte aufgrund des noch andauernden Bürgerkrieges mehr als 20 Jahre lang keine funktionierende Zentralregierung mehr. Die ab dem Jahr 2000 unter dem Schutz der internationalen Staatengemeinschaft gebildeten Übergangsregierungen blieben weitgehend erfolglos; sie vermochten zeitweise kaum die Hauptstadt unter ihrer Kontrolle zu halten. Weite Teile des Landes fielen in die Hände lokaler Clans, Kriegsherren, radikal-islamistischer Gruppen oder Piraten.Auf dem Staatsgebiet haben sich verschiedene De-facto-Regimes gebildet. Von diesen strebt jedoch nur Somaliland im Nordwesten seit 1991 nach internationaler Anerkennung als eigenständige Nation. Die übrigen, darunter Puntland, Galmudug und Azania, beanspruchten zwar Autonomie als selbstverwaltete Teilstaaten, haben die Idee des gemeinsamen somalischen Staates aber nicht aufgegeben. Mit Inkrafttreten der neuen Verfassung am 1. August 2012 sind diese autonomen Teilstaaten nun Mitglieder der neuen Bundesrepublik Somalia (zuvor Republik Somalia). Erfolge gegen die radikal-islamistischen Milizen im Jahr 2012 ermöglichten es, im September 2012 erstmals auch wieder eine gemeinsame somalische Regierung zu wählen und mit der Reorganisation staatlicher Strukturen zu beauftragen, die zunehmend von anderen Staaten und internationalen Organisationen als Vertretung Somalias anerkannt wird.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="nl">Somalië (Somalisch: Soomaaliya; Arabisch: الصومال, As-Soemal), officieel de Federale Republiek Somalië (Somalisch: Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya, Arabisch:جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fideraaliya), is een land in de Hoorn van Afrika dat grenst aan Djibouti, Ethiopië en Kenia. De hoofdstad van Somalië is Mogadishu. Het Somalisch en Arabisch zijn de officiële talen van Somalië. Met een kustlijn van 3000 kilometer heeft Somalië de langste kust van alle landen op het Afrikaanse continent. Omdat Somalië cultureel, historisch, etnisch, taalkundig en religieus zeer verbonden is met de Arabische Wereld, is het lid van de Arabische Liga. In 1960 kreeg Somalië zijn onafhankelijkheid terug en werd lid van de Verenigde Naties. Ook is Somalië lid van de Afrikaanse Unie, Arabische Liga en de Organisatie van de Islamitische Samenwerking.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="pt">Somália (em somali: Soomaaliya; em árabe: الصومال, transl. aṣ-Ṣūmāl), oficialmente República Federal da Somália (em somali: Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya; em árabe: جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية, transl. Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fiderāliyya) e anteriormente conhecida como República Somaliana e como República Democrática da Somália, é um país localizado no Corno de África. Faz fronteira com o Djibuti no noroeste, Quênia no sudoeste, o Golfo de Aden com o Iémen a norte, o Oceano Índico a leste e com a Etiópia no oeste.Na Antiguidade, a Somália foi um importante centro de comércio com o resto do mundo antigo. Seus marinheiros e mercadores eram os principais fornecedores de incenso, mirra e especiarias, os itens que foram considerados luxos valiosos para os antigos egípcios, fenícios, micênicos e babilônios com quem o povo Somali negociava. De acordo com a maioria dos estudiosos, a Somália é também o local onde o antigo Reino de Punt estava localizado. Os antigos Punties eram uma nação de pessoas que tinham relações estreitas com o Egito faraônico durante os tempos do faraó Sahure e da rainha Hatshepsut. As estruturas piramidais, templos e casas antigas de alvenaria em torno da Somália acredita-se que datam deste período. Na época clássica, várias antigas cidades-estado como Opone, Mosyllon e Malao, competiam com os sabeus, partos e axumitas pelo rico comércio indo-greco-romano que também floresceu na Somália.O nascimento do Islã no lado oposto da costa da Somália no Mar Vermelho significou que os comerciantes somalis, marinheiros e expatriados que viviam na Península Arábica gradualmente ficaram sob a influência da nova religião através dos seus parceiros comerciais convertidos muçulmanos árabes. Com a migração de famílias muçulmanas que fugiam do mundo islâmico na Somália nos primeiros séculos do Islã e da conversão pacífica da população somali por estudiosos muçulmanos somalis nos séculos seguintes, as antiga cidades-estado gradualmente se transformaram nas islâmicas Mogadíscio, Berbera, Zeila, Barawa e Merca, que faziam parte da civilização Berberi. A cidade de Mogadíscio chegou a ser conhecida como a Cidade do Islão e controlou o comércio de ouro do Leste Africano durante vários séculos. Na Idade Média, vários poderosos impérios somali dominaram o comércio regional, incluindo o Estado de Ajuuraan, que era excelência em engenharia hidráulica e construção de fortalezas, o Sultanato de Adal, cujo general, Ahmed Gurey, foi o primeiro comandante Africano na história a usar canhões de guerra no continente durante a conquista do Adal pelo Império Etíope, e da Dinastia Gobroon, cujo domínio militar forçou os governadores do Império Omani no norte da cidade de Lamu a pagar tributo ao sultão somali Ahmed Yusuf. No final do século XIX, após o fim da Conferência de Berlim, impérios europeus partiram com seus exércitos para o Corno de África. As nuvens imperiais oscilando sobre a Somália alarmaram o líder dervixe Muhammad Abdullah Hassan, que se reuniu com soldados somali de todo o Chifre da África e começou uma das mais longas guerras de resistência colonial.A Somália nunca foi formalmente colonizada. O Estado Dervixe repeliu com sucesso o Império Britânico por quatro vezes e obrigou-o a retirar-se para a região costeira. Como resultado de sua fama no Oriente Médio e na Europa, o Estado Dervixe foi reconhecido como um aliado pelo Império Otomano e o pelo Império Alemão, e manteve-se durante a Primeira Guerra Mundial como o único poder muçulmano independente continente africano. Após um quarto de século, mantendo os britânicos na baía, os dervixes foram finalmente foram derrotados em 1920, quando o Reino Unido usou pela primeira vez na África aviões que bombardearam a capital, Taleex. Como resultado deste bombardeamento, o ex-territórios dervixes foram transformadas em um protetorado da Grã-Bretanha. A Itália enfrentou situação semelhante quando sofreu a mesma oposição de sultões somalis e dos exércitos e não adquiriu o controle total de partes da Somália moderna até a era fascista, no fim de 1927. Esta ocupação durou até 1941 e foi substituído por uma administração militar britânica. O Norte da Somália continuaria a ser um protetorado e o sul da Somália tornou-se uma tutela. A União das duas regiões, em 1960, formou a República Democrática Somali.Devido aos laços de longa data com o Mundo Árabe, a Somália foi aceita em 1974 como membro da Liga Árabe. Para reforçar a sua relação com o resto do continente africano, a Somália se juntou a outras nações africanas, quando fundou a União Africana e começou a apoiar o ANC na África do Sul contra o regime do apartheid, além dos os separatistas eritreus na Etiópia durante a Guerra de Independência da Eritreia. Um país muçulmano, a Somália é um dos membros fundadores da Organização da Conferência Islâmica e é também um membro da ONU e MNA. Apesar do sofrimento constante de guerras civis e da instabilidade política, a Somália também conseguiu sustentar uma economia de livre mercado que, segundo a ONU, supera as de muitos outros países da África. A Somália é conhecida por ser um dos países mais corruptos do mundo, apenas perdendo para Afeganistão, Mianmar, Sudão e Iraque.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="ru">Шаблон:Государство/ВикиданныеСомали́ (сомал. Soomaaliya, араб. الصومال‎‎ ас-Сумаль), официальное наименование — Федеративная Республика Сомали́ — восточноафриканское государство, фактически распавшееся в результате гражданской войны и деятельности сепаратистов на несколько частей. Член ООН с 20 сентября 1960 года.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="es">Somalia o Somalía (somalí: Soomaaliya; árabe: الصومال, As-Sūmāl), formalmente conocida como República Federal de Somalia, es un país ubicado en el llamado Cuerno de África, al este del continente africano. Al oeste y noroeste limita con Etiopía y Yibuti, al sur con Kenia, al norte con el golfo de Adén, y al este con el océano Índico. Tras una larga guerra civil, el país se dividió en pequeños estados y facciones independientes, sin un poder que lo gobierne en su totalidad. En el año 2004 diferentes facciones llegaron a un acuerdo para conformar un gobierno de transición, unificando el país. Finalmente en el año 2012 se aprobó una nueva Constitución provisional que regirá para todo el país unificado. Es considerada un Estado fallido por diversos medios de comunicación. Su ciudad capital y más poblada es Mogadiscio.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="it">La Somalia /soˈmalja/ (somalo: Soomaaliya; in arabo: الصومال, al-Sūmāl), ufficialmente Repubblica Federale di Somalia (somalo: Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya; in arabo: جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية, Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fideraaliya), è uno Stato dell'Africa Orientale situato nel corno d'Africa.Confina con Gibuti a nord, con l'Etiopia a ovest e con il Kenya a sudovest; si affaccia a nord sul Golfo di Aden e a est sull'oceano Indiano. Ha la linea di costa più lunga di tutto il continente e ha un territorio prevalentemente composto da altopiani e pianure. Il clima è perlopiù arido lungo tutto l'anno, con periodici venti monsonici e piogge irregolari.Anticamente, la Somalia fu un importante centro commerciale con il resto del mondo antico e secondo molti studiosi potrebbe essere l'ubicazione più probabile del leggendario Paese di Punt. Lungo il medioevo, i flussi commerciali della regione vennero dominati da vari sultanati somali, fra cui quelli di Agiuran, Adal, Uarsangheli e Gheledi. Nel tardo XIX secolo, britannici e italiani acquisirono il controllo di parte della costa somala, portando alla creazione dei protettorati della Somalia Britannica (nord) e della Somalia Italiana (centro e sud).Il controllo sulla parte interna dei territori fu però consolidato solo lungo gli anni venti del XX secolo. Nel 1936, la Somalia Italiana fu fatta confluire nell'Africa Orientale Italiana. Amministrativamente rimase tale fino al 1941, quando passò sotto il controllo militare britannico. Dopo la Seconda guerra mondiale, il nord del Paese rimase protettorato britannico, mentre la restante parte fu affidata a una amministrazione fiduciaria italiana. Nel 1960, le due regioni furono unite nella Repubblica somala. Nel 1969, il maggiore Mohammed Siad Barre portò a termine un colpo di Stato e si insediò come presidente-dittatore, rimanendo in carica fino allo scoppio della guerra civile (26 gennaio 1991).Da allora, nonostante numerosi tentativi, nessuna autorità o fazione è riuscita a imporre il proprio controllo su tutto il Paese. La Somalia è stata governata da una pluralità di entità statali più o meno autonome, che esercitano ciascuna un diverso grado di controllo del territorio. Anche per questo motivo, la Somalia è stata considerata uno "Stato fallito" ed è uno degli Stati più poveri e violenti del mondo. In assenza di un governo centrale, l'amministrazione della giustizia è regredita a livello locale, con l'utilizzo di istituti civili, religiosi islamici oppure consuetudinari, mentre l'economia si mantiene a livelli informali, basati sull'allevamento del bestiame, sulle rimesse degli emigrati, e sulle telecomunicazioni. Il ministro degli esteri Fowsiya Haji Yusuf ha invitato i paesi occidentali ad investire nel paese, e dal 2011 sono state riaperte le ambasciate di Turchia, Gibuti, Kenya, Iran, Regno Unito, Italia e ONU. Prova del miglioramento della sicurezza in Somalia è la visita del segretario generale dell'ONU Ban Ki-moon nel dicembre del 2011. Con l'istituzione della Repubblica Federale Somala il paese sembra uscire dai 20 anni di guerra civile e instabilità che lo hanno caratterizzato.Nel settembre 2012, con l'elezione del presidente Hassan Sheikh Mohamoud e con l'instaurazione di un governo stabile, il paese sembra definitivamente uscire dalla guerra civile e ritornare alla normalità.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">Somalia (/sɵˈmɑːliə/ so-MAH-lee-ə; Somali: Soomaaliya; Arabic: الصومال‎ aṣ-Ṣūmāl), officially the Federal Republic of Somalia (Somali: Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya, Arabic:  جمهورية الصومال الفدرالية‎ Jumhūriyyat aṣ-Ṣūmāl al-Fiderāliyya), is a country located in the Horn of Africa. It is bordered by Ethiopia to the west, Djibouti to the northwest, the Gulf of Aden to the north, the Indian Ocean to the east, and Kenya to the southwest. Somalia has the longest coastline on the continent's mainland, and its terrain consists mainly of plateaus, plains and highlands. Climatically, hot conditions prevail year-round, with periodic monsoon winds and irregular rainfall.Somalia has a population of around 10 million. Around 85% of residents are ethnic Somalis, who have historically inhabited the northern part of the country. Ethnic minorities make up the remainder and are largely concentrated in the southern regions. The official languages of Somalia are Somali and Arabic, both of which belong to the Afro-Asiatic family. Most people in the country are Muslim, with the majority being Sunni.In antiquity, Somalia was an important commercial centre, and is among the most probable locations of the fabled ancient Land of Punt. During the Middle Ages, several powerful Somali empires dominated the regional trade, including the Ajuran Empire, the Adal Sultanate, the Warsangali Sultanate, and the Geledi Sultanate. In the late 19th century, through a succession of treaties with these kingdoms, the British and Italians gained control of parts of the coast and established the colonies of British Somaliland and Italian Somaliland. In the interior, Muhammad Abdullah Hassan's Dervish State successfully repelled the British Empire four times and forced it to retreat to the coastal region. The Dervishes were finally defeated in 1920 by British airpower. Italy acquired full control of the northeastern and southern parts of the area after successfully waging the so-called Campaign of the Sultanates against the ruling Majeerteen Sultanate and Sultanate of Hobyo. Italian occupation lasted until 1941, yielding to British military administration. Northern Somalia would remain a protectorate, while southern Somalia became a United Nations Trusteeship in 1949. In 1960, the two regions united to form the independent Somali Republic under a civilian government. Mohamed Siad Barre seized power in 1969 and established the Somali Democratic Republic. In 1991, Barre's government collapsed as the Somali Civil War broke out.In the absence of a central government, Somalia's residents reverted to local forms of conflict resolution. A few autonomous regions, including the Somaliland, Puntland and Galmudug administrations, emerged in the north in the ensuing process of decentralization. The early 2000s saw the creation of fledgling interim federal administrations. The Transitional National Government (TNG) was established in 2000, followed by the formation of the Transitional Federal Government (TFG) in 2004, which reestablished national institutions such as the military. In 2006, the TFG, assisted by Ethiopian troops, assumed control of most of the nation's southern conflict zones from the newly formed Islamic Courts Union (ICU). The ICU subsequently splintered into more radical groups such as Al-Shabaab, which battled the TFG and its AMISOM allies for control of the region, with the insurgents losing most of the territory that they had seized by mid-2012. In 2011–2012, a political process providing benchmarks for the establishment of permanent democratic institutions was launched. Within this administrative framework a new provisional constitution was passed in August 2012 which reformed Somalia as a federation. Following the end of the TFG's interim mandate the same month, the Federal Government of Somalia, the first permanent central government in the country since the start of the civil war, was formed. The nation has concurrently experienced a period of intense reconstruction, particularly in the capital, Mogadishu. Through the years, Somalia has maintained an informal economy, based mainly on livestock, remittances, and telecommunications.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="pl">Nieprawidłowe parametry: { |_region:{{#property:P300}}}Somalia (som. Soomaaliya; arab. الصومال, As-Sumal, Aş-Şūmāl), Federalna Republika Somalii – państwo w północno-wschodniej części Afryki położone na Półwyspie Somalijskim (zwanym „Rogiem Afryki”). Przylega do Oceanu Indyjskiego i Zatoki Adeńskiej. Na północnym zachodzie graniczy z Dżibuti,  na zachodzie z Etiopią, zaś na południowym zachodzie z Kenią.Od 1991 roku w Somalii trwa wojna domowa, obecnie kraj jest w stanie faktycznego rozpadu, a rząd kontroluje tylko niewielkie skrawki jego terytorium. W 2011 Somalia zajęła 1. miejsce (czwarty rok z rzędu) w rankingu państw o najtrudniejszych warunkach do życia. W lipcu 2011 na terenie Somalii ogłoszono stan klęski głodowej spowodowany długotrwałą suszą, plagami szarańczy, a także długoletnią wojną domową. W wyniku głodu zmarło już 12 tys. osób. Szacuje się, że w całym regionie tzw. „Rogu Afryki" (południowo-wschodnia Etiopia, Somalia, północna Kenia),  blisko 12 mln ludzi jest zagrożonych głodem.Według raportu opublikowanego przez FAO oraz amerykańską agencję rządową USAID głód, który panował w Somalii w latach 2010-2012 był skutkiem największej od 60 lat suszy w tym rejonie świata i zabił prawie 260 tysięcy ludzi, połowa ofiar to dzieci poniżej piątego roku życia. Do klęski przyczyniła się także niepewna sytuacja bezpieczeństwa i związany z nią ograniczony dostęp organizacji humanitarnych do poszkodowanych, niektóre rejony znajdowały się bowiem pod kontrolą grup związanych z Al-Kaidą.</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/areaTotal</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#decimal">637657000000.0</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/areaTotal</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#decimal">637655072764.72314453</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/capital</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Mogadishu</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/currency</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somali_shilling</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/demonym</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">SomaliSomalian</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/ethnicGroup</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somali_people</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/flag</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#string">Flag of Somalia.svg</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/foundingDate</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#date">1960-07-01</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/governmentType</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Federal_Government_of_Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/language</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somali_language</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/largestCity</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Mogadishu</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/leader</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Omar_Abdirashid_Ali_Sharmarke</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/leader</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Hassan_Sheikh_Mohamud</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/leaderTitle</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">President</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/leaderTitle</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">Prime Minister</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/longName</sem:predicate><sem:object xml:lang="en">Federal Republic of Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/officialLanguage</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somali_language</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/populationDensity</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#decimal">16.112043075976266948</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/populationDensity</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#decimal">16.120000000000000995</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/populationTotal</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#nonNegativeInteger">10428043</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/timeZone</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/East_Africa_Time</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/isPrimaryTopicOf</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#geometry</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/virtrdf#Geometry">POINT(45.349998474121 2.0333333015442)</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/thumbnail</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Flag_of_Somalia.svg?width=300</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Arabic-speaking_countries_and_territories</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Horn_African_countries</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Horn_of_Africa</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Republics</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Member_states_of_the_African_Union</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Member_states_of_the_Arab_League</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Member_states_of_the_United_Nations</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Member_states_of_the_Organisation_of_Islamic_Cooperation</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:States_and_territories_established_in_1960</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Least_developed_countries</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Somalia</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Federal_countries</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Countries_in_Africa</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/wikiPageID</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">27358</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/wikiPageRevisionID</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">645828999</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/wikiPageExternalLink</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://ssrn.com/abstract=958442</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/wikiPageExternalLink</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://www.somaligov.net/</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/wikiPageExternalLink</sem:predicate><sem:object>http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-14094503</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/aprHighC</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#decimal">32.200000000000002842</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/aprHumidity</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">77</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/aprLowC</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#decimal">25.600000000000001421</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/aprRainDays</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">5</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/aprRainMm</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">61</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/aprRecordHighC</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">36</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/aprRecordLowC</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">20</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/aprSun</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">261</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/areaKm</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">637657</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/areaMagnitude</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">100000000000</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/areaSqMi</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">246200</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/augHighC</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#decimal">28.600000000000001421</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/augHumidity</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">81</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/augLowC</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">23</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/augRainDays</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">7</sem:object></sem:triple><sem:triple><sem:subject>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Somalia</sem:subject><sem:predicate>http://dbpedia.org/property/augRainMm</sem:predicate><sem:object datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">44</sem:object></sem:triple></sem:triples>